<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn220">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 220</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><em>From Monday</em> February. 20. to <em>Monday</em>, February. 27. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em>, February 20.</head>

<p>This <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the the<!--rep in orig or typo??--> Lord Protector, from the Ministers in <em>Leicestershire</em>, had been inserted as presented, but wanting room the last week it was omitted, which take now as followeth.</p>

<p><i>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>The Humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of divers Ministers in the County of Leicester. May it please your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>,</i></p>

<p>We Ministers, and Preachers of the Gospel, in the County of <em>Leicester</em>, and the Neighbourhood thereof, whose names are <reg orig="under-written">underwritten</reg>, finding <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> unanimously sensible<pb n="1" /> of the great <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God in the late various &amp; remarkable productions of his Providence, in relation to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, cannot think it <reg orig="unexpedient">inexpedient</reg>, but very suitable with our Duty to make some express acknowledgment thereof, not so much in respect of our personal right and interests (although the securing of those from injurious hands ought not to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> unacknowledged of <reg orig="gratefull">grateful</reg> hearts) but much more for the seasonable rescue that hath been lately given to the greatest concernments of Church and State, when in manifest danger to have been misguided and swallowed up into a sad confusion; Now the glory of all, first reversed and secured to him who upholds the World by the word of his Power, who changeth times and seasons at his pleasure, and who alone hath <reg orig="Counsell">Counsel</reg> and fond Wisdom, understanding, and strength, by which Princes rule, and all the Judges of the earth; We have very apparent cause in the next place to acknowledge your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> together with your honourable Council and Assistants, under God the great and eminent instrument thereof, unto whose illustrious Conduct we impute not only many former <reg orig="publick">public</reg> mercies, but whatsoever further benefit hath been reaped (or might be hoped) by this Nation from the choice of so many godly and moderate spirited Members in the last Parliament; And as we <reg orig="unfeinedly">unfeignedly</reg> <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the God of Heaven, and honour those worthy Gentlemen, who when the concernments of Church and State so urgently required it, seasonably and unanimously <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> their Power and Trust into the hands of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, so <reg orig="doe">do</reg> we also esteem it a very large improvement of that Mercy that your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> was inclined to undertake the Protection of these shattered Nations in so dangerous and troublesome a constitution, when also spent with the tempestuous violence of contrary winds and waves, which conspired to threaten a common wrack an <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>: And now although it cannot be expected but that the Spirits of some may be disposed (upon several accounts, but especially by the practise of the <reg orig="restlesse">restless</reg> Enemies of our <reg orig="publick">public</reg> welfare) to <reg orig="mis-understanding">misunderstanding</reg> and discontent; Yet Sir we hope the great God of heaven (who is a of God order &amp; not of confusion,<pb n="2" /> and hath promised to honour those that honour him) will guide, prosper, and protect your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in defending the true Faith of Christ, and encouraging the Ministers of his Gospel, as also in your pious care and endeavours for the weal <reg orig="publick">public</reg> of these Nations, as shall declare to the World his special approbation of his noble and just intentions in these your great undertakings; further humbly assuring your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, that there shall be nothing wanting to the furtherance hereof, which the Prayers and best endeavours of <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> and many others may any way contribute: for as we are verily <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that without your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> acceptance of thus great and weighty charge, we had been suddenly plunged into a Gulf of misery, so are we likewise convinced that there can be no remove from the present establishment (as being most accommodate to our present condition) but what would be attended with very great, unavoidable, and universal danger. But fearing we may be too bold with your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> patience, we shall only beg your noble and favourable acceptance of these our humble Addresses, and that Religion and Learning may flourish, and the work of the Lord made to prosper in the hands of the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg> of Christ in these Nations under the Protection of your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> long and happy Government.</p>

<p>On <em>Saturday</em> February 11 this <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> was presented by 4 or 5 Ministers of <em>Leicestershire</em> in behalf of themselves and many others of that County and the Neighbourhood thereof, and was well accepted by his Highness, but it was not any of them that preached the next day afternoon before his Highness, as it is by some upon mistake reported.</p>

<p>There were published from his Highness the Lord Protector, two Ordinances, the one touching the assessing, levying, and collecting of the later 3 months assessment, appointed by an Act of the late Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for an Assessment at the rate of an 120000 l. by the Month, for 6 Months, from the 25 December 1653. to the 24 of June then next ensuing towards the maintenance of the Armies and Navies of this Commonwealth.</p>

<p>The other is and Ordinance of Explanation touching Treasons, as followeth.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Ordinance declaring that the offences therein mentioned, and no other shall be adjudged high Treason within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, it is among other things, ordained and established, That no Matter, Fact, Crime, or Offence whatsoever, other than such as are <reg orig="therin">therein</reg> mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken, or adjudged to be High Treason; And whereas some Doubts and Questions may arise, whether that clause in the said Ordinance doth not extend to the offences mentioned in the Instrument, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and which are thereby declared to be High Treason; For clearing thereof, and removing all scruples thereupon, His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That neither the said Ordinance, nor any clause or thing therein contained, shall extend, or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend unto all or any the Offences declared by the said Instrument to be High Treason; but that all and every the said Offences are hereby adjudged, and shall be adjudged, taken, and deemed to be High Treason; and that all and every the Offender and Offenders shall suffer the pains and penalties of High Treason, the said Ordinance, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein contained to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 25 of February, 1654. By the last Letters from <em>Perpignan</em> we hear, that the <em>Spanish</em> forces lie very still in their Quarters, not making the least attempt against any of our Garrisons since they were so ill <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg> at our last encounter with them, and therefore nothing considerable hath passed in these parts, only the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Rosa</em>, who had been sick a good while, is now dead, being a very gallant <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, and one who had got himself a great name for his Fidelity, and Valour, which he had demonstrated of late in those parts.</p>

<p>The agreement between the Marshal <em>la Ferte</em>, and the Town of <em>Beffort</em> being made, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> with his Garrison are preparing to march out, and the Besiegers to go in, which is to be performed upon the 22 of this instant <reg orig="Moneth">Month</reg>.</p>

<p>The Pr.<pb n="4" /> <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em>, who had been put out of his Lands and Church Benefits by the late Cardinal <em>de Richelieu</em> for siding with the House of <em>Austria</em>, having of late <reg orig="yeares">years</reg> altered his mind, and made his <reg orig="ful">full</reg> missions to his Majesty, is now again <reg orig="restord">restored</reg> to his former dignities and preferments <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> this last Week taken possession thereof: Those forces which are commanded by the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em>, are still hovering up and down about the County of <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, and are about five thousand, being horse for the most part: The Prince of <em>Conde</em> was lately at <em>Roscroy</em>, but now we hear he is gone to <em><reg orig="Bruxelies">Brussels</reg></em> to <reg orig="conferr">confer</reg> with the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em> concerning the next <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> Expedition.</p>

<p>The 21 instant the Prince of <em>Conty</em> was betrothed to the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Chamber; besides their Majesties, there were the most part of the Princes and chief Nobility then at Court, as also of the Ladies, the Ceremony was performed by the Archbishop of <em>Bourges</em>.</p>

<p>The 22. was the solemnity of the Espousals, which was done in the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg> by the same Archbishop; the young Bride was brought into the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Chamber by the Cardinal, she was in a suit of <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> of gold all laid with Pearls, whereof some of a very great value, and after the Church-ceremonies performed, the Cardinal feasted them all at a sumptuous Dinner: concerning her Portion it is variously reported, some making it far greater than others do.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> the 11th of February, 1654. We hear from <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>, that <em>Dom <reg orig="Hanibal">Hannibal</reg> de Gonzague</em> is come thither from <em>Vienna</em>, and hath taken possession of the place of Master of the Horse to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> from the Elector of <em>Cullen</em>, hath obtained no more, then he will send an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> to the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em>, and the Duke of Lorrain, to represent unto them the grievous oppressions of the County of <em>Liege</em>, by the late entrance of the <em>Lorrain</em> and the <em>Conde</em> Forces, and that a period may speedily be put to it.</p>

<p>From <em>Warsovia</em>. All things are here in a <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> for a Diet which is to be kept this February, others say not till next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg><pb n="5" /> : in the mean time there are particular Assemblies in each County, not only for the nominating and <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> of the Members for that Diet, but also in drawing several Heads or Articles which they are to propound at their next Session, The Prince <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, Brother to his Majesty, hath promised to be there in person, to endeavour if he may reconcile the late differences happened between many of the Nobility and the King, this being occasioned by the late peace concluded with the <em>Tartars</em> and <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em>, whom they affirm to be very <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg> to the Kingdom of <em>Poland</em>, by reason, say they, it was agreed upon after one only conference, <reg orig="ther">there</reg> being none present there for the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em>, and so being not signed by them or the <em>Tartars</em>, therefore the General <em>Kimelniskie</em> with his 40 thousand men who are to be kept in constant pay may at their pleasure vex and <reg orig="oppresse">oppress</reg> the Country of <em>Poland</em> when their pleasure is so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Maestrickt</em>: The strong opposition that the <em>Lorrain</em> Forces found at the assaulting the little Town of <em>Thuin</em> hath incensed them so far, as that ever since they have committed all manner of cruelties in the Country of <em>Liege</em> even beyond belief, whereof they have made sufficient proof in the County of <em>Kempen</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>: Our Trade being almost <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> interrupted, by reason of those differences happened between us and our <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg>, is now <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> lost by the news received here of the approach of the <em>Lorrainers</em>, there being 22 Regiments marching over the <em>Mawse</em> intending to use us as they have done at <em>Liege</em>, in case we deny them contribution Money.</p> 

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday February 21.</i></head> 

<p>We had by several Letters from <em>Scotland</em> the routing of <em><reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> Army, by Col. <em>Morgan</em>, as followeth. On Thursday last Col. <em>Morgan</em> with a party of 1200 Horse, Foot, and Dragoons <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> <em>Glencairn</em> and <em>Kenmore's</em> Army (which were given out to be 2000) at a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> which they had that day at the Head of <em>Cromar</em> 16 mile from <em>Aberdeen</em>, and (though the Enemy had that advantage) after a little dispute they were totally routed, but (being so near<pb n="6" /> the Hills) he could <reg orig="doe">do</reg> them no more execution then, and pursued 7 Miles into the Hills, their General hardly escaping with about 40 Horse: <em>Kenmore</em> had left a Garrison in <em>Kildranning</em> the Earl of <em><reg orig="Marrs">Marr's</reg></em> Castle which our men were then marching against, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> doubted not but to give a good account of it. Since this we have news also of Capt. <em>Mottiowes</em> marching out of the Garrison of <em>Dunstasnage</em>, and <em>Dunolly</em> with a party from these two Garrisons fell upon the House of <em>Archetton</em> in <em>Lorn</em> in <em><reg orig="Argillshire">Argyllshire</reg></em> and took it, with all the Men, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and Ammunition in it, he killed only three and afterwards (that it might not harbour any more of those wild Cattle that were in it) he fired it: Since which Lieutenant Colonel <em>Cottrell</em> marched out of <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> to reduce the Garrison of <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>-Dew</em> near <em>Lough Lomond</em>, and before he came near it the Enemy run away, and left word they had no orders to fight. We heard also yesterday that <em>Brokie</em> Cap. Lieut. to the late Col. <em>Wogan</em> is also dead of his wounds; and the Earl <em>Athol</em> that fires and burns <reg orig="Folkes">Folks</reg>, Corn, and Houses, threatens to shoot <em>Holland</em> the <reg orig="Chiururgion">Chirurgion</reg> to death, for not recovering <em>Wogan</em> and <em>Brokie</em>: And some of these Blades begin to cry <em>peccavi</em>, and sends to desire liberty to live peaceably, and no doubt ere long they will betray one another into hands.</p>

<p><em>Leith</em> 14 February.</p>
<p>1653</p>

<head level="3">The enclosed is a <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of <em><reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Proclamations for the bringing in of levies as followeth.</head>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased his Majesty to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> for opposing the common enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his justice hath permitted to overcome, and be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we would turn to him by unfeigned repentance. And to the end his Majesties service may be advanced<pb n="7" /> and that none of his <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> subjects may pretend ignorance; and that it may appear how willing we are that the levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires and Parishes and head Burghs by open Proclamation, that every one may make his several proportions ready to be <reg orig="deliver'd">delivered</reg> to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under our hand wheresoever the foresaid Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of honour, will move to their Duty, may be proceeded against with Fire and Sword, unworthy to be looked upon as Scotchmen, to the <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> of all false-hearted Traitors, who by their Treacheries and Rebellions against their <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> King, and his just Power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</p>

<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses has been brought forth from any <reg orig="well-affected">well affected</reg> person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said Horses has been taken, that they shall meet, and stent themselves equally, for bearing equal burden, and resound the persons from whom any horses has been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of horses now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries, forth of every thousand pound of Rent: and the proportion of foot, every third man; and what Dragoons are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one Dragoon. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes; where no Burghs are, the Provost and Bailiffs of Burghs to Proclaim this at the <reg orig="Mercat">Market</reg> Cross of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as they will answer the contrary upon their highest peril. Given under our hand the first day of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p>

<p><i>Sic subsciribitur Glencarns.</i></p>
<p><i>God save King <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> the second.</i></p><pb n="8" />

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> Feb. 16th instant, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> with a party of 1200 Horse, Foot, and <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg> hath routed <em><reg orig="Glencarnes">Glencarn's</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Kenmors">Kenmore's</reg></em> Army in <em>Scotland</em>, which were about 2000 and pursued them seven miles; their <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> hardly escaping with 40 horse to the <reg orig="mountaines">mountains</reg>, which were nigh the place of engagement: Captain <em>Mutlero</em> hath taken in the Garrison of <em>Archbetton</em> Mr. <em>Lorne</em> with all the Men, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and Ammunition, Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Cotterell">Cottrell</reg></em> hath likewise taken in the Garrison of <em>Ressedere</em>, the evening <reg orig="runing">running</reg> away upon their approach, and left word they had no orders to fight, some of the Grandees begin to run <em>pettativi</em>, and desire to live peaceably.</p>

<p>From Captain <em>Foster</em> aboard the <em><reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> Feb. 14. thus according to orders the 11th instant, I arrived to the River <em>Humber</em>, (having <reg orig="untill">until</reg> then been prevented by Northerly winds and thick weather) and gave notice thereof to the rest of the Commanders appointed to proceed with me in this Expedition, whose answer to me intimated their unfitness to sail at that present. The 12 the wind being Southerly, the <em><reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg></em> and <em>Amity</em> set sail toward the station, desiring the others speedy repair to us; towards the night the wind came to the N.N.W. we standing alongst the Dogger, fell amongst the <reg orig="Hollanders">Hollander's</reg> Dogger boats. And the 13 so soon as day appeared in the morning we discovered two sails, which we concluded to be their convoys, and bore the one of us to the one of them; and the other to the other, they about two leagues distant from us. The <em><reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg></em> sailing best, I chose the ship furthest off, fearing he might escape the other, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up each with his chase, mine proved to be a <reg orig="Swead">Swede</reg> come from <em>Newcastle</em>, which having on board prohibited goods, exceeding his allowance for provisions, as also being <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> he was the man of <reg orig="Wars">War's</reg> prize, he being on the body of their vessels, and having twice the number of men on board accustomed to sail such a ship. I have thought it my duty to bring him into <em>Humber</em>, not assuming the power to permit any one to pass of, whom I have the least just cause of <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>.<pb n="9" /> I have referred him to the Commissioners for prize Goods at <em>Hull</em>.</p>

<p>The ship the <em>Amity</em> stood with, proved to be the <reg orig="Fishers">Fisher's</reg> convoy, a Man of War of <em>Zealand</em>, a ship of 20 guns, and 70 men, and lying in his two courses, seemed (at a distance) to be no such ship; he discovering the <em>Amity</em> <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for him, they <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> very smartly for some time; the <em>Amity</em> having shot his <reg orig="Top mast">Topmast</reg> by the board, shattered the ship exceedingly, and slew and wounded most of his men. The <em><reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg></em> by reason of her chase (and for that she endeavoured by all means to escape from us) and the wind shifting was to Leeward approaching near them. The enemy <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> his ship to Captain <em>Pack</em>. The <em>Amity</em> is shattered (but one man slain) the prize totally disabled. I have judged it best to secure her for her Guns and <reg orig="Cables">Cable's</reg> sake (she hath seven new Cables) which is most considerable in her; her Hull being old.</p>

<p>From <em>Grimsby</em> 16 Feb. Cap. Pack hath taken a Dutch man of War, who fought seven <reg orig="houres">hours</reg> before he would <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, we slew seven of his men, and wounded 15. His fore Topmast was shot by the board, and the ship so torn between wind and water that she was nigh sinking, and so towed hither, her name is the Sandenburgh of Syrick-sea, one Captain <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Ariouson Blanker</em> commander, she had 20 Guns, we lost but one man, <em>viz</em>. our Cook and 4 wounded.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. The Letters from <em>Naples</em> advise us, That the Vice King having received several papers containing many grievances, of the people among others, that there was a great abuse committed by those who were Commissioners for the vitalling of the Navy, whereby many had lately died in the ships, and <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg>, by eating of ill <reg orig="bisket">biscuit</reg>, did therefore command some of the Magistrates of that City, to examine the matter, and to view the <reg orig="Store-house">Storehouse</reg>, which having done, they found it to be very bad, and caused much bad meat to be thrown into the Sea. The Drums do beat up and down the City, for the raising of those men which the Vice King intends to send into <em>Catalonia</em> and <em>Milan</em>, but as yet there is little appearance.</p><pb n="10" />

<p>From <em>Venice</em> thus: We have received Letters from <em>Constantinople</em>, which inform us how that the French <em>Ambassador</em> his Son being arrived with a packet and a Commission as a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister had had audience at the Court, and was received with as much <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> as his rank and place did permit: this doth put us in hopes that our Ambassador may at the last obtain so much as to be called from <em>Andrinopolis</em>, and be admitted to a Treaty: nevertheless, we have by way of <em>Bagusa</em>, that the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> doth follow with much eagerness the great preparations which they have begun to be ready this next Spring, and that they will hardly relate <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of their high demands, chiefly the cession of the whole Kingdom of <em>Candia</em>, which they intend to force them unto by reducing the chief City, which hath been besieged by them about two years since: the which to prevent this State, intends to have greater forces in the field, and a stronger Navy <reg orig="then">than</reg> formerly, having in the mean time sent the Commander <em>Cornaro</em>, into <em>Condia</em> with a very considerable sum of money for the payment of the Army there.</p>

<p>From <em>Milan</em>: The <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <em>de Caracene</em> our Governor is now making new Levies, to augment his Army against the next Summer, having already got together about 2000 Foot, and more are speedily to be sent hither.</p>

<p>From <em>Turin</em>: The <reg orig="Abbet">Abbot</reg> <em>Amoretti</em> who by order of the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>, was gone to confer with the <em>French</em> General, who hath his abode at <em>Pigneroll</em>, is returned hither, having composed those differences which were between them about the quartering of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>. The <em>French</em> being now in their Quarters, the Foot in the valleys about the town of <em>Pignerol</em>, and the General gone with the Horse to quarter them about the Hills.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> 23. Feb.</head>
<head level="3"><em>Paros</em> 28. <em>Feb</em>. 1654.</head>

<p>There are Letters of credence sent to <em>Monsieur de Bourdeaux Newsuille</em>, who is already in <em>London</em> to be received as Ambassador in ordinary. The Town of <em>Beffort</em> being reduced<pb n="11" /> the Earl <em>de la Suza</em>, who was Governor there, is marched with his Garrison into <em>Luanuburgh</em>, and having tarried some time at <em>Namur</em>, is gone to the Prince of <em>Condi</em>, to give him an exact <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> concerning the late <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg> of the place.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>Retz</em> doth still remain a close prisoner, but some means are used by mediators for his enlargement, by means of a marriage between the Lord <em>Mancini</em>, who is Nephew to Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, and one of the Cardinal <em>de <reg orig="Retz">Retz's</reg></em> <reg orig="Niepes">Nieces</reg>, but as yet things remain very doubtful.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Mariage">Marriage</reg> between the Duke <em>de Nemours</em>, with the Daughter to the Duke <em>de Longueville</em>, but as yet nothing set for the conformation of the <reg orig="mariage">marriage</reg>.</p>

<p>The Prince <em>Thome</em> so of <em>Savoy</em> is now wholly invested of the place of Lord of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> house, which the Prince of <em>Conde</em> enjoyed formerly. The Order formerly given for altering the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> courses of the Parliament of Roan is revoked.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>la Fertz</em> having taken in <em>Beffort</em>, hath been <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> with the Earl <em>de Harcourt</em>, and as we have it from Court, that the said Earl shall surrender <em>Brisack</em> and other places under his Government to the King, and yield to much Propositions as were made him for his <!--indempnity??--><reg orig="indempaity">indemnity</reg> upon that business.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Scots</em> as I am certainly informed, is to depart this City with his attendants in a very few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, whether for Germany or Holland, is not yet known: this being agreed upon the conclusion of a peace between us and <em>England</em>, in consequence of the peace between you &amp; the <em>Dutch</em>, which we hear is now wholly and totally finished, and that two Ambassadors are gone to take shipping for England.</p>

<p><em>Antwerp</em> the 28 of Feb. 1654. Two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since was brought hither in a Coach, the Duke of Lorrain, being guarded hither by a Troop of Horse, he was arrested the day before by the Earl de Garein, (an eminent man in the Army) by an Order sent from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em>, he is now a close prisoner in our Castle: since there hath been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> of his <reg orig="domesticks">domestics</reg><pb n="12" /> arrested and carried to prison: what is the ground or cause of his imprisonment is not yet know, but will be before many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; this take that he is charged to have tempered with France, and have <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> to betray the Prince of Conde and his Army to <!--rep in orig or typo??-->to the common enemy: and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, that in these parts either <reg orig="neare">near</reg> or remote, none <reg orig="pitties">pities</reg> him, saying, it is a just <reg orig="revvard">reward</reg> upon him for the great cruelties he hath used in many Counties and Provinces.</p>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em> 20. Feb. This day Mr. <em>Stocker</em>, sent by the Protestant Cantons of <em><reg orig="Smitzerland">Switzerland</reg></em> to mediate a Reconciliation between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and the United Provinces, who hath formerly resided long at <em>London</em>, is arrived here. The Freebooters <em>de Haen</em> hath brought in three ships taken upon the coasts of <em>Scotland</em>; two laden with coals and a Fleet laden with salted Salmon and other goods. The last Sunday arrived here an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> from <em>London</em>, with Letters from the Lord <em>Beverling</em> to the Lord States General. The Provinces of <em>Zealand, <reg orig="Utretch">Utrecht</reg>, <reg orig="Freezland">Friesland</reg></em>, and <em>Overyssel</em>; first brought into the Lord States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> their Resolution upon the Ratification of the Articles of Peace, and according to the resolution of the Lord States of <em>Holland</em>, approved of, and ratified them. The next day the same was done by the States of <em><reg orig="Gilderland">Guilderland</reg></em> and <em>Gronning</em>. Insomuch that it is generally hoped that the Treaty shall very shortly be brought to a full conclusion, and some Ambassadors go speedily for <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Rotterdam</em> Feb. 20. we are long expecting to hear, That the Lord <em>Beverning</em> hath obtained a Cessation of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> with England, which was given him in charge to demand the loss of our Merchant men. 9. lately <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <em><reg orig="Naunts">Nantes</reg></em> laden with Wines; and others daily hath caused our Admiralties to prohibit all Masters of ships to go to Sea upon the penalty of two thousand Gilders, till such time that the Lord <em>Beverling</em> be returned from <em>London</em> with the suspension of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, which he is to propose to the <em>Lord Protector</em>. In the mean time we are making all the haste we can to send over Extraordinary Ambassadors to sign the Treaty of Peace,<pb n="13" /> who we believe will be going from hence about a fortnight hence; the more haste will be made to dispatch, since we do doubt very much we shall not be able to obtain a Cessation of Arms so much desired for by all in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>.</p> 

<p>By Letters from Scilly Feb 18. thus. The 13th instant the <em>Samaritan</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, a ship of about 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with 12 Guns, and laden with wheat, together with a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Pink of Plymouth, came into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, they were both taken by Beach, one of the Brest men of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, and were redeemed on Thursday the ninth instant by the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> and the Constant Warwick; yesterday the 15 of this month, the Constant Warwick arrived here for some <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg>, and fresh water: the Captain <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that they gave chase unto Beach, but the night came too fast on them, and were hindered of an engagement, <em>Hebditch</em> one of the old <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> was taken in the Samaritan of Bristol, and is now on board the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg>: there is also a Vessel in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, called the Peeter of Dover, that came from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>, and the Master <reg orig="affirims">affirms</reg>, that there are 20 Dutch ships bound for St. Martnes, where there are 40. more, and that then they will have but three Convoys.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Letters from Germany, we hear that in the <reg orig="Dukedome">Dukedom</reg> of Lucburgh, they have been lately much annoyed by Mice, and other like <reg orig="Vermine">Vermin</reg>, the ground being almost covered with them; the Mice are of divers colours, and maketh them fear that not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of their <reg orig="Graine">Grain</reg> will undoubtedly follow, but likewise that it is a forerunner of a new war and troubles in the Country; being they are also certified, that this January last there was seen a <reg orig="Comit">Comet</reg> or blazing Star in the <reg orig="Marquisat">Marquisate</reg> of <reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg>; which they say is much like unto that which was seen in Germany, about thirty five years since, not long before their wars began.</p><pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em> &amp; <em>Saturday</em> 24. &amp; 25. Feb.</head>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em> Feb. 18. About four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, Col. <em>Daniel</em> with a party of Horse, Foot, and <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg>, together with the conjunction of another party from Dundee, in all about 1000 <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> towards <em>Dunkell</em>, where the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> most considerable quarters was, and where they had newly <reg orig="establisht">established</reg> a Garrison in the Lord <em><reg orig="Atholls">Athol's</reg></em> house near the Church. And upon <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em> approach (the Lord <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em>, and Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> having intelligence retreated to the Hills, and left <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Garrison, and some few to defend the Church) those in the Church durst not stand, <reg orig="busled">bustled</reg> to the House, whereof men attempted them together, and got under the Walls with Pickaxes, and other instruments that were in readiness, and in short time gotten to a part of the House without the loss of one man; and having slain <reg orig="onely">only</reg> three of the enemy, the rest <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> quarter and had it granted, yet notwithstanding unworthily began to resist a little, which <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> our men the more; and then the enemy <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out <reg orig="amain">again</reg>, they would accept of the <reg orig="termes">terms</reg> granted. In the House we took two Lieutenants, one <reg orig="Ensigne">Ensign</reg> with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> Colours, Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbes">Forbes'</reg></em> own quartermast. 2 <reg orig="Sarjeants">Sergeants</reg>, 2 Cornets, and 119 private rogues, together with 80 Muskets and <reg orig="Bandeleeres">Bandoleers</reg>, some Firelocks and Swords, about 16 pound of Powder, as also 25 Troop horses, and 14 or 15 case of Pistols, with much Meal, Malt, and Oates, which not having convenience to carry away, we set fire to a <reg orig="barrell">barrel</reg> of Powder, and those provisions, and blew up them and the House together. About five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> one of the late Col. <reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg> men with three of his best horses, got his Landlord to help him to water them, and run away with them to Blaire Castle, one of our Garrisons, which makes the English less trusted by <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> and the <em><reg orig="Teries">Tories</reg></em>. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> hath also removed the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Garrison at <em>Kildrummy</em>; and many of those Horsemen, he routed at his engagement with valiant <em>Glencarine</em> (the great patron or rather <reg orig="spoyler">spoiler</reg> of his Country) running to <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> near <em>Dunkell</em>, he translated them to foot. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> at his late engagement with the Enemy at <em>Cromar</em> <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> 120 and took 27 prisoners with all their Ammunition, and most of their <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and about 80 Horse, in all which we lost not one Man.</p><pb n="15" />

<p>From Upsall in Sweden Jan. 20. We have very great probability (God favouring the undertaking) to accomplish what we came hither about, and to return within, or a little time after the time <reg orig="limitted">limited</reg>, which was six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: My Lord Ambassador carries on business with a great deal of <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> and discretion, and is highly approved <reg orig="off">of</reg> by the Queen, and Grand Chancellor who <reg orig="beares">bears</reg> great power here, we were a little at a stop upon the new change of Government in England, for my Lord was forced thereby to begin again, and had a new Commission sent him from my Lord Protector, but the Queen received his new Credentials with all willingness; and now business goeth forward at least in appearance fairer <reg orig="then">than</reg> before; the Queen seeming to have a very great respect to my Lord Protector.</p>

<p>There are <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said Ambassadors now landed from Holland, and expected at London within a day or two, and that they come with full power to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Articles of peace between England and Holland, which is so more by the next.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is now published the second part of the exposition of Jude, By Mr William <reg orig="Jenkin">Jenkins</reg>, and is sold in <reg orig="Paules">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>. Jus Divinum Regiminis Ecclesiastici: Or the divine Right of Church Government, asserted and evidenced by the holy Scriptures: The third Edition corrected and augmented by sundry Ministers within the City of London. Printed for George Calvers, at the half Moon in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<p>The Tempestuous Soul Calmed by Jesus Christ, being the Extract of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Sermons Preached By A. Palmer at Burton in <reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg>, and sold by E: Brewster and G. Sawbridge at the Bible on Ludgate Hill.</p>

<p>There is newly published an excellent Book, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> the Greatness of the mystery of Godliness opened in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Sermons by <reg orig="Cathbert">Cuthbert</reg> Sidenham, late Teacher to A. Church of Christ in Newcastle: Sold by Rich: Tomlins, at the Hand and Bible at <reg orig="Pye">Pie</reg> Corner, and by William London in Newcastle,</p>

<p>The new birth, in which is brought forth the new Creature with a brief <reg orig="discription">description</reg> of Antichrist, by Rich: <reg orig="Bartlet">Bartlett</reg> <reg orig="Sarvant">Servant</reg> of Jesus Christ. Printed for L. Blaiklock at Temple <reg orig="Barre">Bar</reg>, and John Hancock in Popes Head Alley.</p>

<p>There is lately printed the Right Constitution and true Subjects of the visible Church of Christ, with its Order, ordinances, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg> and Government, written by Tho: Colliar and unworthy Servant of Christ. Likewise Protection proving subjection <unclear>for</unclear> a word of peace to be well affected. A Caveat to the contentions. A Rod for the Rebellious, both which are to be sold by Hen: Hills at the sign of Sir John Old Castle in Pie Corner.</p>

<p>Stolen out of Putney Park the twenty three of Feb. A little Nag about 13 &amp; 14 hand high, between a <unclear><!-- six characters --></unclear> and a <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear>, with a long <reg orig="main">mane</reg> blackish and <reg orig="readish">reddish</reg> with a little white lock in the said Mane, his crest something high forward, many saddle spots on the back &amp; side, a black <unclear>line</unclear> down his back and Rump, a short tail, hath all his paces, 6 or 7 years old, &amp; will lie down in the water Winter &amp; Summer after riding. If any can give the owner knowledge of him, at Mr. Maident in the old Jury, next door to Gurney Home, shall have twenty shillings for their pains.</p>

<p>There was last Saturday 24. instant, between Colbrook and Stone a <reg orig="Chesnut">Chestnut</reg> Nag, about 14 hand high, with no white at all, straight bodied, coming seven years old, with a short <reg orig="Taile">Tail</reg>, and a very thick <reg orig="Maine">Mane</reg>, high mettled. Also writings in a Cloakbag of receipts of divers sums of money of one Farmer Piat, Farmer Sadler, Farmer Brown &amp; Whosoever shall bring, or give notice of them to Mr. Jo: <reg orig="Harbert">Herbert</reg>, at the Angel in Newgate <reg orig="Merket">Market</reg> shall have 20 shillings for their <reg orig="paines">pains</reg>.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>