<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn221">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 221</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Feb. 27. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></i>, March. 6. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, February 27.</i></head>

<p>This day by Letters from <em>Dover</em> <reg orig="wee">we</reg> understood that the Lord <em>Newport</em>, and <em>Yongstall</em> Ambassadors Extraordinary from the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the untied Provinces <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> there, the day before with full power (as they say) to Conclude the Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, some heads of the Articles of the Treaty to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the people have been printed in <em>Holland</em>, and a translate Reprinted here, but are so short of the full of the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, we shall not mention them. The Ambassadors (they say) are come attended by a retinue of about 80 persons, And the Master of the Ceremonies<pb n="1" /> here is appointed to receive them at <em>Gravesend</em>, and Conduct them by water to <em>London</em>: at their landing <em>Friday</em> next, Coaches are appointed to bring them, and their attendants through the City to Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his house, in the <em>New-<reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg></em> yard <em>Westminster</em>, prepared on purpose for them.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> the 18. of <em>February</em>, 1654. We have from <em>Cullen</em>: That the Elector and the <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> are not yet agreed, that <reg orig="therupon">thereupon</reg> the Magistrates are <reg orig="under-hand">underhand</reg> making of Levy, that so in cast the differences are not composed in an amiable way, they may be in <reg orig="som">some</reg> posture of defence. The late misunderstanding between the Elector of <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em>, and the Duke of <em>Newburgh</em> doth increase daily, which makes many to <reg orig="feare">fear</reg> that it will break out into an open war, thereupon the Duke doth stand upon his Guard, having already in constant pay some Regiments of horse, and some of Foot. From <em>Liege</em> the Lorrainers continue their old trade of plundering and wasting the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, having of late plundered the <reg orig="Abby">Abbey</reg> of <em>Herkenood</em>: they have done the like at <em>Bilsen</em>, and so in many other places, even to those that had the protection of the Emperor, the King of <em>Spain</em>, and the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em>, the Earle of <em>Merode</em>, being sent out with a party, beat up the Earle of <em>Ligneuille</em> his Quarters, and had done greater execution had he had more Horse with him: another party of ours hath also lately taken a Convoy of the Enemy, where having slain 17 common <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg><pb n="2" />, and a greater number which were taken Prisoners, the Wagons and Carts with the Ammunition, and Provision which have been carried to <em>Huy</em>. The Baron of <em>Butzdarn</em>, who commanded one of their Brigades is lately deceased, which proveth to be a great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to them, and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Schmidt</em> hath likewise deserted them and many others with him. From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> thus, The Emperor continueth to be much discontented by reason of the long sitting of the Diet, who have no sooner ended one <reg orig="busines">business</reg>, but there ariseth <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> a new one, not formerly thought on; and although the Emperor would gladly be gone to <em>Vienna</em>, yet knowing that his presence is much necessary for the <reg orig="hastning">hastening</reg> of businesses, therefore will not yet leave the Assembly: From <em><!--Warsovia??-->Warsonia</em>, there hath been a strong report here about six <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, that a <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> of the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> being discontented with the General <em>Kmielmisk</em>, had killed him with a <reg orig="pistoll">pistol</reg> shot, but this thing being of so great concernment, therefore little credit given to Messengers sent to the Army, have been lost at their return in the great snow, therefore cannot tell any particulars of our Army, but that they are quartered in <em>Ukrania</em>, with the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, and that the Tartars contrary to their agreement have plundered in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places at their marching out of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em> 14. of <em>February</em>, There hath been launched three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since three new <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg>, which<pb n="3" /> with the 9. others are to be forthwith fitted to be sent to <em>Candia</em> about Easter: The new <em>Generalissimo Moccenigo</em>, is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> in them, he carrieth with him good store of Provisions, Ammunitions, and a good <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of money; there are also many Officers, who <reg orig="goe">go</reg> along with him, the great ship called the <em>Saltana</em> is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> likewise, and now that the Turks have drawn their forces at a farther distance from the <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> of <em>Candia</em>, there will be care taken that the place may be provided with all necessaries, and put in a posture of defence, in case the Turks will <reg orig="againe">again</reg> attempt to <reg orig="besiedge">besiege</reg> it the next summer, as it is probable they will: we hear from <em>Dalmatia</em> that the <em>Morlacks</em>, being allured by the good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> they had it their late in-road into <em>Bosnia</em>, are again <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> a second time, and again returned with the like <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, having brought with them great store of <reg orig="Cattell">Cattle</reg> and other rich <reg orig="bootie">booty</reg>, which they have divided among themselves, From <em>Milan</em> all our Officers are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in the <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> their Companies and Troops, that so if possible the Army may be sooner in the field this Summer ensuing, <reg orig="then">than</reg> it was last year, and by reason that our Governor seeth well he is not like to receive any Forces from the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of <em>Naples</em>, therefore he useth all means possible to have some from <em>Germany</em>, and from the <em><reg orig="Switzers">Switzer's</reg></em> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and hath lately provided all out Fortier places in case the Enemy at this Spring should make any attempt against them. From <em>Genon</em>, we hear that the D. of <em>Mantua</em> is gone from his chief <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> to <em>Casell</em>, there to give such orders as are fit for the well ordering and preserving of that place. The Duke of <em>Tursie</em> is with a part of his Galleys at <em>Porto-Mabone</em>: and there is expecting the <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> Galley which is to come from <em>Allicant</em>, and another from <em>Cartagena</em>; we hear also from <em>Cagliari</em> in <em>Sardinia</em>, that the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Doria</em> was there with his Squadron of Galleys, expecting fair weather, that so he may proceed on his intended voyage to <em>Scicila</em>: From <em>Turin</em>: The French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> and the General of the French Forces are both returned hither from <em>Pigneroll</em>, where they have been about the quartering of the French Army.<pb n="4" /> The Abbot <em>Amoresti</em> is again gone from hence, and taketh his journey for <em>Paris</em> about some <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg> which are of a great concernment.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 28.</head>

<p>From <em>Paris</em>, We hear from <em>Beffort</em>, that according to the late Capitulation made with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, to deliver up the place he did it accordingly, and marched out with his Garrison the 23 last past, they consisted of about 300 men, horse and foot, they have taken their march towards <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>. The Marshall <em>la Forte</em> having given order in the Towns and Castle as <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought necessary for its preservation is gone to <em>Dele</em>, a Castle not far from thence, where having likewise settled all things, he intends to return to Navoy in Lorraine. From Nantes, the Company adventurers for the firm Landing <em>America</em>, which is by some called <em>France Equinoxiall</em>, are making ships ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> of April, having sent one before, who carrieth great store of passengers, and some of the adventurers being gone to <em><reg orig="Gyana">Guyana</reg></em>, from whence we hear that since the late <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> committed by the <em>Salvages</em> upon some Frenchmen in the Island called <em>Mario Galand</em>; the Governor having sent about 140 persons to make new Plantations, and inhabiting of that Island, where he hath built a strong Fort for its own preservation: which these Salvages perceiving, they are come to an agreement, and live in a peaceable way. From the <em>Bassee</em>. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> having notice that some of the enemy was come as far as the <reg orig="Counterscarpe">Counterscarp</reg>, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> away some horse, did thereupon command a party to follow them: which could overtake them, but having notice by a Countryman, that about 100 of the enemy who were Firelocks were about <em>Eunrnes</em>, they rid thither, and having found them in a Trench, where they thought to lye in <reg orig="ambuscado">ambuscade</reg>, the Commander of that party charged them with so much valour, that after a hot dispute, there was 15 slain on the place, and 62 taken prisoners, among which are two chief <reg orig="Comanders">Commanders</reg>: the rest having saved themselves with great difficulty: on our side, there was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one man lost, and two wounded: The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazarini</em> is now getting possession of all such Benefices and Church livings<pb n="5" /> , as did belong formerly to the Prince of <em>Conti</em>; among others, he hath not forgot the rich Abby of <em>Glugni</em> which is of a great revenue. The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>de Retz</em> doth still remain a close prisoner, and the Duke of <em>Orleans</em> doth still <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> at his house near <em>Blois</em> being still in the same resolution as formerly, which is not come to the Court.</p>

<p><i>This day his Highness the Lord Protector with advice of his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, passed an Ordinance for reviving the Jurisdiction of the County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em>, and for holding an Assizes there to this effect.</i></p>

<p>That all Privileges and Jurisdictions belonging to the County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em> and the Inhabitants thereof, be, and are hereby Revived and Continued, as fully and amply to all intents and purposes, as the same were at any time before the tenth day of <em>October</em> last. And that all actions as well <reg orig="reall">real</reg> as <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, and all other Actions <reg orig="mixt">mixed</reg> or otherwise. Pleas, Precepts, Writs, <reg orig="Proces">Processes</reg>, Demurrers, <reg orig="Recognizances">Recognisances</reg>, Fines, Recoveries, and all other Proceedings; Matters and things, of what nature or quality soever, now depending in any Court within the said County <em>Palatine</em>, or there commenced or prosecuted since the said tenth day of <em>October</em> shall be and stand revived, continued, and of full force and effect in the Law, to all intents, constructions and purposes. And that all <reg orig="Proces">Processes</reg>, Pleas, Demurrers and Proceedings and every such Action, Actions, <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> or Plaints, which were there depending the said tenth day of <em>October</em> last, or commenced or prosecuted there at any time since, shall stand good and effectual, and be proceeded in according to the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> of the Nation, and the proceedings used within the said County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em>.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, that <em>Matthew Hales</em> one of the Justices of the Court of <em>Common-Pleas</em> at <em>Westminster</em>, &amp; <em>Hugh Wyndham</em> Sergeant at Law, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be Justices of Assizes and <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>-delivery within this said County <em>Palatine</em>, and that the said Justices or either of them, shall and may act, do and perform all matters and things, as well concerning Criminal as Common-Pleas, and all other Pleas and <reg orig="Proces">Processes</reg> whatsoever, in such manner and form as any other Justice or Justices of Assizes at <em>Lancaster</em> have usually acted, done and performed at any other time heretofore, And the Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em> hereafter named is hereby Authorised and appointed to issue forth to the said Justices, for the execution of the said premises, such Commission or Commissions as in such cases have been heretofore in the said County <em>Palatine</em>, used and accustomed. And that <em>Thomas Fell</em> Esq; be, and is hereby made and appointed Commissioner for keeping of the Seal of the said County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em>, &amp; <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have all such powers as any Chancellor or Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County <em>Palatine</em> hath formerly lawfully used and exercised concerning the same, till further Order.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em>, Feb. 21. The Earl of <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> hath drawn all the Forces he can together from <em>Weems</em> and other places, and he with the Lord Bruce were the 14 instant at <em><reg orig="Glenshir">Glenshire</reg></em>, marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Glencairn, <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg>, Kenmore, &amp;c.</em> upon their conjunction they will be between 3. and 4000. and then they intend to be revenged of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan for their late rout; but (through divine assistance) he make them amends with such another beating: yet <em><reg orig="Atholls">Athol's</reg></em> Foot are much discontented, &amp; leave him daily out of a sense of their declining, dangerous, and desperate condition by their daily losses in all parts, and complain much of the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their Horse: The English that came with <em>Wogan</em>, are much dejected at his death, and lament their leaving <em>France</em>, and being in so wretched and barbarous a place as the Highlands. We are daily sending what supply we can to Colonel <em>Morgan</em>, but cannot much <reg orig="adde">add</reg> to his strength till two Regiments come out of <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Leith</em> the same date. The Lord <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em>, The Lord <em>Bruce</em> and others have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> what Forces they can get together, and are marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Glencairn, Kenmore, <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> and then the rest upon whose conjunction they threaten to be revenged of Col. <em>Morgan</em> for the last rout, and perhaps he may make them amends with such another. Yet <reg orig="Atholls">Athol's</reg> foot are much discontented and have him daily, <reg orig="complaying">complaining</reg> much of the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their Horse, so that now they have few Foot but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="Runagadoes">Renegades</reg> from the Lowlands, They have taken off the Roof from the Garrison of <em>Weems</em>, and intend now to keep no <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, but run the same courses that <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> did, and keep their Ammunition in woods, or little villages in the Hills.</p>

<p>From Saint <reg orig="Iohnstons">Johnstone</reg> Feb. 19. 1653. I being now released, and by the providence of God come safe to this Town, have taken the first opportunity to write to you at my <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> hither, I chance to see a Printed Book, wherein the writer makes mention of our business at <em>Drummond</em>, and afterwards makes a Relation of a defeat by a party of ours, given to <em><reg orig="Atholls">Athol's</reg></em> forces at <em>Dunkell</em>, and he Comments upon it, saying it was a seasonable Mercy to <reg orig="Ballance">Balance</reg> their height upon the business<pb n="7" /> of Drummond. I bless God for any victory he <reg orig="bestowes">bestows</reg> upon us. But I desire the writer may understand that <reg orig="throw">through</reg> the goodness of God our business did <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg> <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, and the enemy did not grow high upon it, but repented that <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> work many times to my knowledge, wishing they had not seen our Forces, for their Black Swan Col. <em>Wogan</em> in whom they had such hopes, whose <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> so much <reg orig="heightned">heightened</reg> the enemy; at that time (being the first service he was upon) received a shot from my hand, of which he dyed 17. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after; and now lies interred in the Kirk of <em>Lough Key</em>, whose death with his Captain Lieut. (who was counted a man almost as gallant as himself) and Cap. <em>Kerr</em>, and the rest of the loss they received there, they <reg orig="accompted">accounted</reg> greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> both their defeats at <em>Dunkell</em>, though the last was greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> that the writer mentioned. I should have writ more large concerning our own business, and the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> discouragements upon their late defeats, but being in much pain, I shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> insert one thing more and take leave, which <reg orig="concernes">concerns</reg> a Gentleman of the South of <em>Scotland</em>, who in a vision was <reg orig="worned">warned</reg> in the name of God to go to the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> Officers of their Army, and declare to them, that for their wicked living, and <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> oppression, the Judgements of God were nigh unto them, and would shortly destroy them, the gentlemen went not; the appearance was the second time, giving him charge as before, and told him, that for his disobedience he should be struck <reg orig="Dumbe">Dumb</reg>; and if he now went not, further Judgements should fall upon him, and immediately he was <reg orig="Dumbe">Dumb</reg>: this man came the Sabbath day was seven <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before I was released to the Kirk, near the place where I was Prisoner, and declared this in writing, being then on his way to their Quarters in the North, resolving to declare it to him: this I had from the Lord of the Parish, the Minister, and many others; so with my Prayers to God for his providence to go along (as heretofore with our <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, which he hath pleased to set over us, in whom we have so great hopes, I remain,</p>

<p><i>Your ever loving friend,</i></p>
<p>G.H.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 1.</i></head>

<p>This Day a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister out of <em>Flanders</em> from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em>, had Audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em> with some of the Aldermen and Recorder, on behalf of the City, and the Magistrates of the City of <em>Westminster</em>, this Day (according to Order) attended his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and Council at <em>Whitehall</em>, upon the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of a Corporation to be granted to the City of <em>Westminster</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Chester</em>, Febr. 26. On Wednesday last, the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> took ship for Ireland, at the point of <reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg>; we hope he is well over, though there fell out very violent storms immediately after his <reg orig="imbarquing">embarking</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Upsal</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em>, January 27. Our affairs here have had a little pause; the Lord Chancellor having been indisposed in his health, but now is abroad again. The Treaty goes on, and this afternoon my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> and he have had a meeting concerning it; we cannot but believe, but we shall have a very desired issue; yet they are a little stumbled here at our detention of their ships, and at the dilatoriness of the proceedings of the Court of admiralty concerning them. There are reports here of an Extraordinary coming from France, and another from <reg orig="Rushia">Russia</reg>; this Virgin Lady is much courted in this juncture.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 2.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 7th of March 1654. The 27 last past the King and the Cardinal went a hunting to <em>Versailles</em>. The 28. the <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> of <em>Mercoeur</em> with the other <reg orig="kinred">kindred</reg> of the Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, arrived in this City, and were extraordinary well received of their Majesties at the <em><reg orig="Louure">Louvre</reg></em>. There is a strong Report that the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> will have his Father to come from <em>Rome</em> and live at Court, to that end that he hath procured him from the King the Title of Duke and Peer of <em>France</em>, and that he doth purpose to buy him, as soon as may be some Lands for him and his heirs, and Mons. <em>de <unclear>Lyoine</unclear></em> is to carry <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> to <em>Rome</em> upon that business. The 2. of this instant the King went to <em><unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear></em> to hunt wild Boar which had been brought into the Park by order of the Governor, after which he exercised<pb n="9" /> himself in shooting of birds flying, where he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> a great dexterity and experience, and having spent most part of the day upon such exercise as is fit for his quality and young years, he returned hither in the Evening on Horseback. Our late <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> at <em>Rome</em> is returned, and came to this City to give his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> an Account of his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, there is another to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> thither very shortly, who <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> about the middle of <em>April</em>, but some say not so soon: The Military affairs begin now to be taken in hand after all the mirth and <reg orig="pastim">pastime</reg> we have had this late shroving time, and I hear that the Marshal <em>Tureque</em> is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to the Army in <em>Picardy</em>, and give his orders for the speedy putting it in a warlike posture, that so we may be in the field before our Enemy, and we hear that the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em> on the other side doth all his uttermost power to be first with his Army into the Field.</p>

<p>From <em>Brussels</em> the 7th of <em>March</em>: The 27th last past the Earl <em>de Fuensaldagne</em> being gone from thence came the next day to <em>Diest</em> and the two days following, the Officers of the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> army came to meet him, what by his care and wisdom, <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the authority of the <reg orig="Archduke">Arch Duke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em>, and the good disposition in the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, he hath wrought so much upon them, as to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to obey the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em> as they did formerly, whilst the arrival of the Duke <em>Francis</em> Brother to him that is now imprisoned, and having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things as well for that particular, as for those <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affairs which concern his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and came back upon <em>Wednesday</em> last to this City. The fifth instant we heard that those of <em>French</em> forces under the command of the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> had appeared within two leagues of the City of <em>Liege</em>, and according to their motion seemed to intend to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> over the <em><unclear>Mawsri</unclear></em>, and so into the County of <unclear><em>Filsbury</em></unclear>, but care is taken to prevent them.</p>

<p>That you may understand the reasons and <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> of the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold's</em> proceedings against that famous Thief the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, who hath filled a good part of Christendom with his rapines and cruelties. I have here <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> two Translates of those two Declarations which have been sent out here by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>; the one directed to the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> of the <em>Lorain</em> Army, and the other to all men in general.</p><pb n="10" />

<p>To all high Officers, Matters de Camp. Colonels, Captains and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> bearing Arms under the Ensigns and Banners of the Lord Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, <em>Charles: Healch</em>. We give you to understand, that having this day secured for some time, the person of the said Duke of <em>Lorain, Charles</em>, in pursuance of a special order and command, which we have received from the King my Lord; for the good of the house of <em>Lorain</em> in particular, and other high and weighty considerations, relating to the welfare of the State and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> peace: His Majesties and our intention is that the whole body of his Troops do continue in the same service as they are now upon under the command of the <em>Count de Ligneville</em>, until the Lord Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> shall arrive here, (which will be in few days) to undertake the command of this Army, to the preservation of rights of the said Duke, and the house of <em>Lorain</em>, under the protection of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, Declaring that to Officers, <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, or others belonging to the said Army, shall be brought to a <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>, or questioned for any Riots, or <reg orig="misdemeanors">misdemeanours</reg> whatsoever, which they may have committed under the said Lord Duke. Hereby also strictly and <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> forbidding them to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to the service of any other neighbour, Princes, or States, either Friends or Enemies, upon pain of forfeiture of body and goods, as well as in respects to the Vassals and natural Subjects of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, as those heretofore listed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in the Musterroles of that Army; and as to other strangers, upon pain of being punished as <reg orig="desertors">deserters</reg> of their Colours. Provided notwithstanding that any formerly listed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in the service of his Majesty, and have gone from their Colours although without leave, may return again, and repair to them without danger of being questioned <reg orig="any ways">anyways</reg>, or proceeded against for the same. As to the rest we refer our self to that which the Count <em>Fuersaldagne</em> Commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Armies shall more particularly acquaint them with <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear>lation to the advantages which shall be speedily procured and effected for them.</p>

<p>Given at <em>Bruxes</em>, the 25. of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p><pb n="11" />

<p><i><em>Leopold William</em> by the grace of God <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> of <em>Austria</em>, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em>, &amp;c. Lieutenant, Governor, and Captain General of the <em>Low-Countries</em>, and <em>Burgoni</em>, &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>As no man can be ignorant what duty and respect our Cousin the Lord Duke of <em>Lorrain <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, hath been obliged to bear to the King my Lord, and all his Allies, Friends and good Subjects, since the time that he hath in these parts of his Dominions, been <reg orig="sheltred">sheltered</reg> from the violences oppressions, and usurpations that have been practised by <em>France</em> against his Person and Since: where he hath been received by his Majesty and his Lieutenant General with all friendship and good confidence, and under a special protection, not only to the espousing of all his Interests in the Solemn Assembly for Treaty of Peace, but also furnishing him with Pay, and maintenance for his Troops, and admitting him to our Resolutions and Councils of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> against the common enemy: So it's no less known to all the world how contrary the said Lord Duke hath acted, to what was due from a Prince of his birth so entertained, treated, and <reg orig="gratifyed">gratified</reg>, as is before mentioned, and so strictly bound to the Interest and Service of his Majesty, &amp; the good of his Kingdom.</p>

<p>For, besides the tears, groanings, and general exclamations of the people that bore <reg orig="publick">public</reg> testimony of the <reg orig="Thefes">Thieves</reg>, Robberies, Sacrileges, Rapes both of married women and maids, and other abominable and detestable Riots committed under the conduct of his Army, the wracks of which destructions and devastations, he himself gathered up; His Majesty and his Lieut. General have from time to time been well informed of the secret intelligences of the said Lord Duke, and of his several designs as far different from the common good, and service to which the conjunction of Forces ought to tend, and also of his inconstancies, and pretended change of judgement in Resolves of Matters of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, and the alterations and affected delays that he gave in things already debated, and that even at the very point of executing most important services, which might have been the overthrow of many and high enterprises, which in all likelihood, and according to humane reason, could not but have had a happy issue; These practises were at length grown so notorious, and to such a <reg orig="hight">height</reg>, that not only the <reg orig="Lieutenants">Lieutenant's</reg> General, Commanders of Armies, Masters de Camp, and all other Officers were <reg orig="eye-witnesses">eyewitnesses</reg><pb n="12" /> of his tricks and artifices, and could point at them, but even the meanest <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg>, and the whole people seemed astonished to see things thus pass on without any remedy provided against them. 'Tis true, the King my Lord, through his accustomed goodness and singular affection which he doth and ever will bear to the House of <em>Lorrain</em>, hath as far as possibly he could, connived at, and passed it by, in hopes that the said Duke moved with the courteous usage and benignity his Majesty hath treated him <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, might become sensible of his Interest, and in conclusion return to his duty; but on the contrary, his exorbitant proceedings arrive to such a height, that not only all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Subjects and Vassals do abhor and detest him, but also all the neighbour Princes and States were so set against him, that it was apparent that these Countries, for perfecting their misery, might have felt the effects of the vengeance which they <reg orig="design'd">designed</reg> to take of him; The King my Lord, lest he should provoke the anger of God against him and his people, could not defer any longer to stop the course of this evil, and therefore it is, upon consideration of these <reg orig="publick">public</reg> and manifest truths, that his Majesty for a speedy and effectual remedy thereunto, hath commanded us to secure the person of the said Lord Duke, in which he hath acted according to Law of Nature and Nations, which allows all <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Princes to remove from of their State and People, Oppressions and Violence, be it who it will be that opposes them and to do Justice to themselves, their people, and neighbour Potentates, States, and Friends, when all other <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> have been attempted in vain and without success, of which the ages past want not examples, in cases less fortified by circumstances, and justified than this. This proceeds not from any aversation of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> to the House of <em>Lorrain</em>, but he protests ever to protect them, and <reg orig="adhear">adhere</reg> to their Interests: In witness whereof, his Majesty hath provided that the Command of the Armies and Troops of the said Lord Duke, shall pass to, and remain <reg orig="sequestred">sequestered</reg> in the hands of the Lord Prince <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em>, his Brother, from whose natural good inclinations, and sincere intention, his Majesty is assured he shall reap the fruits, and receive the true effect of a conjunction of Forces. And until the said Duke <em>Francis</em> shall arrive, his <reg orig="Majestie's">Majesty's</reg> and Our intention is, that the Count <em>de Ligneville</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> continue in the execution of the Charge and Office of General.</p><pb n="13" /> 

<p>We therefore in the Name, and on the behalf of the King my Lord, do command all his Subjects and Vassals, and request all neighbour Princes and States to rest satisfied, and have a good opinion of this order and resolution of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg>, expecting that another time and conjuncture of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affairs may calm these motions and changes, and that God restoring <reg orig="queitnesse">quietness</reg>, by <reg orig="softning">softening</reg> the obstinate Spirit of <em>France</em> to Peace, the People may be again established in <reg orig="Tranquility">Tranquillity</reg> and a general Repose, and every one readmitted to that which is his Right. <i>Given at <reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg> the 25 of Feb. 1654.</i></p>

<p>LEOPOLD WILLIAM.</p>
<p><i>Signed by Order of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>VERREYKEN</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday March 3</i></head> 

<p>From <em>Innernesse</em> Feb. 20. The enemy are divided into divers parties to raise their assigned levies, keeping themselves on parts near to the <em><reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg></em> for their security, and from thence summon in the Country for horse and foot, whom they threaten with <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> if not accomplishing their unjust demands: <em>Glencairne</em> is to command all the forces levied in these Shires of <em>Murray</em>, and so Northward, he, with 80 Horse and 200 Foot keeps near the Hills, that upon notice of the approach of any of our Forces they may secure themselves in the inaccessible bounds; Our Horse Scouts now and then glean up some of them, having lately taken amongst others a notorious Rogue who <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> to burn divers of the <reg orig="Inhabitants">Inhabitants'</reg> house who are serviceable to the Garrison.</p>

<p><em>Leith</em> Feb. 25. <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> levies are most certainly spoiled, and the people wearied in their respects to them, despairing of help from <em>Holland</em>, and a report amongst them, that a Gentleman (their friend) in <em><reg orig="Fyff">Fife</reg></em> had lately a vision, in which he was commanded by one in form of a Man to speed to <em>Glencairn</em> and tell him, that he must decline his course which will be destructive to him, and all under him, and then vanished. The Gentleman neglected it, and then had a second vision in which he was <reg orig="sentenc'd">sentenced</reg> to be dumb for his neglect, which he now is, and certifies the same under his hand as they report; this latter prevails much on the vulgar <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg>, and the two former hath influence on all their Army, that they are much dejected and sad. <em>Athol</em> is about <em><unclear>Glenlyn</unclear></em> and hath with him about 300<pb n="14" /> Horse and Foot, he hath sent forth the fiery Crosses but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> little observed, some of his Men are gone to <em>Badgenoth</em> where <reg orig="its">it's</reg> informed <em>Glencairn</em> is. The old Laird of <em><reg orig="Glengarys">Glengary's</reg></em> at <em>Balloch</em> hath sent for and accepted of a protection from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. <reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg>, and hath engaged to keep all quiet in his Bounds for doing any prejudice to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> was there to demand his House to be demolished (as <em>Weym's</em> is) but the old Gentleman (of 80 years of age) absolutely resisted. On <em>Tuesday</em> last Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> with what Horse <em>Athol</em> could make marched <em>Tuesday</em> last towards <em>Montieth</em> or <em>Lenox</em> <reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived in design for the South. The 12 instant there was one of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniels's</reg></em> Regiment hanged at St. <em><reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg></em> for running to <em>Athol</em>, who was taken at <em>Dunkell</em> the last week and another was tied up to the Gallows, who was intercepted in his running to <em>Athol</em>. There are some others that <reg orig="ranne">ran</reg> from the same Regiment to <em>Athol</em> who were taken at <em>Dunkel</em>, but preserved by Articles: Major Gen. <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em> and Commissary General <em><reg orig="Whalleys">Whalley's</reg></em> Regiment of Horse are come up hither, and will be a very seasonable supply.</p>

<p>This <em>Friday</em> the Lords <em><unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear></em> &amp; <em>Yongistal</em> with their attendants landed at <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> where coaches provided for them, their Lordships were in one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg>, and the Master of Ceremonies with them, <unclear>driven</unclear> by 6 horses, next followed the <em>French</em> and the <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> Coaches, with above 20 more all with 6 horses, besides above forty Coaches most with <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> horse <unclear>apiece &amp;</unclear> stay <unclear>in</unclear> in<!-- rep in orig or typo?--> stately equipage <unclear>through</unclear> the City, from <em><unclear>Aldgate</unclear></em> by the <em>Royal Exchange</em>, and so to the <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> Palace yard <em>Westminster</em>, to Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em>, where they are to be entertained with <unclear>their Retinue</unclear> at the <reg orig="Seates">Seats</reg> charge for some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday March 5.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven the 28 <em>February</em>. Here are some lately come from <em>Ireland</em>, who tell us no more as for news, but that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Monague</em> there are great members of Irish ready to take shipping for <em>Flanders</em> to serve the King of <em>Spain</em>, but yet there are still <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties of <em>Tories</em>, who lie lurking in the woods and <reg orig="boggs">bogs</reg> and do much disquiet the peace of the Country, which is still in great want of people to inhabit those parts. The Lord <em>Henry</em><pb n="15" /> <em>Cromwell</em> is safe arrived in <em>Ireland</em>. From <em>Deal</em> the 2. of March two days since all the Merchants ships as were here, and in <em>Dyver</em> Road set sail, having a fair wind to go for <em>France</em>, and other parts to the Southward; also several convoys to bring them to their distinct places, there hath been likewise some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> here, but are gone all again Westward where we hear our Fleet rideth still near St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg>-point</em> by the Isle of <em>Wight</em>.</p>

<p>This afternoon the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> had audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <em>Whitehall</em>, the Room was richly hung with hangings, &amp; a rich chair of State set for the Lord Protector, and Chairs on the one side for the Ambassadors, the Entertainment was stately, and gallant, and the subject of this Audience was partly Congratulatory to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and to declare the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of their coming to make and settle a firm peace, and to rescue the old friendship which hath been for many years between the two Nations: And that to this purpose their Superiors the 7 United provinces do all of them agree and consent to the agreement of peace between us and them, which they, their Ambassadors Extraordinary, are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> fully to confirm, and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>; desiring a speedy Cessation of arms, and that all acts of hostility may cease on both sides, so that undoubtedly, some few circumstances being considered on, all will be concluded, and a Peace fully <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, as we shall be able to give you further the particulars by the next.</p>

<p>There is also and Ambassador (we hear) landed from <em>Denmark</em>, to make application to his Highness upon the success of the Dutch Treaty, his name is <em>Williamson</em>.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly published, Select Thoughts, or Choice Helps for a pious Spirit. A <reg orig="Centry">Century</reg> of Divine breathings for a Ravished Soul beholding the Excellency of her Lord Jesus; By Jos. Hall. B.N. Art of Memory, or a <reg orig="soveraign">sovereign</reg> and certain <unclear>Cure</unclear> for a weak memory, <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be apprehended by the meanest capacity, and useful for all persons, from the Gown to the Clown. Printed for Nath: Brooks at the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg>.</p>

<p>A Brief Exposition of the Prophecies of Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, Habakkuk, and Zephaniah: By Mr George Hutcheson Minister at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, Recommended unto the Reader by Mr. Edmund Calamy, ad Mr: David Dickson. Printed for Ralph Smith at the Bible in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg>.</p>

<p>Britannia Triuphalis, A brief History of the <reg orig="Warrs">Wars</reg> and other State-affairs of Great Britain, from the death of the late King, to the dissolution of the last Government. Printed for Sam: <unclear>Hayes</unclear>, and are to be sold at his shop in Dobes-head <reg orig="Ally">Alley</reg>.</p>

<p>The Life and Death of Mr. Ignatius Jurdain one of the Aldermen of the City of Exeter: By P. <reg orig="Nicolls">Nicholls</reg> Minister at Mary Arches Exon, and printed for Tho: Newberry at the 3 Golden <reg orig="Lyons">Lions</reg> in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg>.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and entered according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>