<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn222">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 222</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, March. 6. to <em>Monday</em>, March 13. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> March. 6.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dalkeith</em> Feb. 28. The last week Lieut. <em>Hellin</em>, Lieut. to Major <em><reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons having noticed that one Capt. <em>Thompson</em>, and Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Ramseys">Ramsey's</reg></em> Lieut. with 5 more of the Enemy were come down into the <em>Mearns</em>, presently mounted with 6 more of the Troop, traced them about 10 miles into the Hills, and at last took them, their horses, with their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, and one of them being an Englishman, refused to take quarter and was killed. A<pb n="1" /> party of <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> horse and foot being before <em>Down</em> Castle five miles from <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, Maj. <em>Bridges</em> went forth with a party of 60 horse, upon which the enemy fled, our men pursued, and about 4 miles from <em>Down</em> came in sight of them, but most of them got into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. We took only six prisoners and about 19 or 20 horse, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> was there, and escaped very narrowly, as did Captain <em>Hamilton</em>, whose horse was taken, but he escaped over a bog. The 10th of <em>March</em> is appointed for the enemies great Rendezvous about <em>Badgenoth</em>. <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> and Sir <em>Mongo Murray</em> came with Orders to <em>Athol</em>, when he slighted <em>Weems</em>, to prepare all the Forces he could against that time. There was a late falling out amongst them, and one <em>Graham</em> shot <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Groom through the head, and young <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> had like to have killed <em>Lorn,</em> The <reg orig="enemie">enemy</reg> have put in a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of 30 men into <em>Gaith</em> castle, about a mile from <em>Weems</em>. I have sent you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> one of Sir <em>Mungo <reg orig="Murrays">Murray's</reg></em> warrants, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> fire and sword.</p>

<p>These are to require the Gentlemen, Heritors and others concerned in the Parish of <em>Drummond</em> and <em>Buchanan</em>, that immediately after sight hereof they send to the Craig of <em>Erne</em> out of every hundred pounds of Rent half Bell Cane, one Furlet Meat, one Turf of Hay, one <reg orig="Legg">Leg</reg> of Beef, one stone Cheese, 4 Hens, or satisfaction therefore; as also to be <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> at the appointed place with your proportion of Troop Horses, every thousand pounds being one well mounted. Troop Horse with certificate: If you fail, I will pursue you<pb n="2" /> with Fire and Sword, according to the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Order.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Blaniavard in Drummond, Feb. 23. M. Murray.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Naples</em> the 7th of Febr. There is an express Order sent thorough the City that all things necessary should be in a readiness against the next day for the <reg orig="Cavalcate">Cavalcade</reg> of the Earl <em>de Castriligio</em>, who doth take upon him in a solemn manner the place of a <reg orig="Vice-king">Vice King</reg>, having taken the Oath as it is accustomed in the like case; he doth take great care in furthering of his Levies both of Horse and Foot, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the supplying of the Forces in <em>Catalonia</em>, but also to send a considerable number to <em>Milan</em>. From <em>Rome</em>, The news concerning Cardinal <em>Pamphilio</em> his being out of favour, is confirmed, but as yet the true cause thereof is not known, only that according to the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Order he doth still remain at <em>Sambuci</em>, and the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> affairs which were managed by him, are committed to the care of the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> <em>Barberini, Ghisi</em>, and <em>Sacheti</em>. From Venice thus: The Galley which was come hither from <em>Dalmatia</em>, hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> dispatched thither again, and Thirty thousand <reg orig="Duckats">Ducats</reg> for the payment of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> in those parts, and there is a strong supply of Men and Moneys, with Ammunitions to be sent speedily into that Country: this is <reg orig="hastned">hastened</reg> so much the more, by reason that by the last Letters from <em>Constantinople</em> we hear, That the Turkish Council finding the City of <em>Candia</em> well provided and guarded, and therefore are not like to prevail by taking of it, that thereupon they intend to bend their whole<pb n="3" /> strength into <em>Dalmatia</em>, or else against the Island of <em><reg orig="Corfou">Corfu</reg>, Zante</em> and <em>Cepalonia</em>. From <em>Milan</em>: All our Garrisons have been changed by putting in those that served the last Summer, and drawing out in the Field those that were there in Garrison thereby to take away all <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg>. The <em>French</em> are quartered some upon the Duke of <em>Savoy</em> his Country, and some are gone to <em>Pignerol</em>: Their General is still at <em>Turin</em>, and intends to tarry there one while till he hath some comfortable news sent from <em>France</em>, as well for having more forces added to his, as also to have moneys sent for the <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> of his Army.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Franckfort">Frankfort</reg></em> on the Main, the 27 <em>Feb</em>. 1654. By the last Post come from <em>Poland</em> we have advice, That the <em>Tartars</em> who are not marched out of the Country according to the late agreement, have made many incursions and done much harm in several Counties, chiefly in that of <em>Wolmes</em>, insomuch that many have forsaken their Habitations, but at present that storm is well over, since the Commissary General with three thousand horse hath followed them so close, that having found them in small bodies, he hath forced them to leave their robberies, and return to their own Country, although some come short thither: Yet businesses are very doubtful, and it is believed by many that the late peace made with the <em>Tartars</em> and <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> will not hold long, but that after the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> hath been again debated in the next Diet, that immediately the War will begin a new against the <em>Tartars</em> and the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> thus. The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> having declared his mind to the Diet, that he intends to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>Vienna</em> about the 20 day of <em>April</em>, and therefore the Assembly is desired that they may put a period to all affairs, and so close up all by the last day of <em>March</em>.</p> 

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>. All the Princes and States of lower <em><reg orig="Saxonie">Saxony</reg></em> have sent Commissioners hither for the carrying on of the design, long before intended, which is to make with some other Provinces a de defensive league against the invasion of the <em>Lorrainers</em>, and likewise to have an eye unto the <em>Swedes</em>, who making great preparations by Sea and Land give no little <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> in those parts.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>. The Citizens and others of that <unclear>Country</unclear> were gone for a safety to <em><reg orig="Dusseldorf">Düsseldorf</reg></em> and other places adjacent are now returned, hearing that the <em>Lorrainers</em> are gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the <em>Spaniard</em>, upon notice given of the approach of the <em>French</em>, who being come into the County of <em>Liege</em> have caused there a great alteration.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal February</em> 20. Things <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on well here: The Queen and her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Council look on <em>England</em> as much more settled under the Lord Protector than before. His Highness being one whom she much honours, and also approves of the change of the Government, she hath been in the Country, but is newly returned, and in half a day and a night (after five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> absence making speed to us) is come back through very hard Frosts in a <reg orig="Sledg">Sledge</reg> of this Country, in which she rid as long a way as contains about sixty English miles.</p>

<p>This day General <em>Deborow</em>, General <em>Monk</em>, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty, went towards <em>Chattam</em>, for dispatch of the <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> of the Navy now near ready. <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> were <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg>, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> drawn out of the Regiments, to be put on board, and a gallant Fleet will presently be at a <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>. The Dutch have also 60 new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, to add to their Fleet, which will shortly be ready. Both sides strengthen themselves as well as they can, lest there should not be a conclusion at last.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 7.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Mylor</em> in <em>Cornwall February</em> 28. Here is this day arrived Captain <em>Wall</em>, in the Castle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> from the <em>Canaries</em>, but brings no news.</p>

<p>About ten days since, Major <em><unclear>C&aelig;ly</unclear></em> had a small Barque returned to <em>St. Ives</em> thus, being one hundred leagues off, bound for <em>Bayonne</em> with Pilchards, she was taken by a Dutch Merchantman of 28 Guns, who only took 100 pieces of <em>Beef</em> from the Barque, and inquired whether we had peace in England; Answer was given that there were hopes of it; Hereupon the <reg orig="Dutch-man">Dutchman</reg> told him he would give him his ship again, and at length gave him his Ship and lading, saying, We had a new King in <em>England</em>, Whereto ours answering no, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, but you have one of more power<pb n="5" /> which ours said was a mistake, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> importuned the Dutch Captain to do so much favour as to slack sail for them that night, because a <em>Brest</em>-man of War <reg orig="hoverd">hovered</reg> about them, and <reg orig="proferd">proffered</reg> money for our English <reg orig="Vesse">Vessel</reg>. The Dutch Captain asked for the <em>Ghelt</em>. The Brest man answered it should be secured in <em>France</em>. No (said the Dutch Captain) the English-man shall have his Ship, so she came home in safety.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Mastricht">Maastricht</reg></em>, March 6. Our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> doth keep a good number of Troops in readiness to march at an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> warning, to repulse the Lorrainers and Spaniards, in case they do offer to make any attempts, or do intend to come upon any of the Territories of the States General, after they have ransacked the poor <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em>, from whence many Inhabitants are fled into this City to avoid their cruelty. They have pillaged and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> most of the Monasteries in the said <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg>, and committed such <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> abuses, that most people leave and forsake their dwellings and habitations wheresoever they come.</p>

<p>From <em>Rotterdam</em>, March 6. stilo novo; We do now hope that the business of the peace is so far advanced, that there is no farther doubt to be made but that the Treaty will be suddenly ratified by both States. All the Provinces have brought in their ratifications; and ere this we hope also that our Extraordinary <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> are arrived in <em>London</em>, and have signed the Articles formerly agreed upon.</p>

<p>The <em>Heer Stockhare</em>, Agent for the Protestant Cantons<pb n="6" /> of <em>Switzerland</em>, having been of late in <em>England</em>, and now come over hither, being sent by the said Cantons for a Mediator <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> the two Commonwealths, hath had audience of the States General, and hath made offer of his Service to adjust any Question that should yet <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> undecided <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> the two States.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of <em>France</em>, Monsieur <em>Chanut</em>, hath also had Audience of the said States, and doth very much desire that France may be also included in the Treaty. It is said here that the <em>French</em> and <em>English</em> are like to come to as good Agreement.</p>

<p>There is lately an <em>English</em> Prize brought into <em>Texel</em>, taken by a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of war, called the <em>Bee-Hive</em>, laden with piece-goods, and said to be worth 3000l. <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> are <reg orig="hastning">hastening</reg> out our Fleet with all the expedition that may be.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> the 11th of <em>March</em>, stilo novo. The Marsh. <em>de la Ferte</em> having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things at <em>Beffort</em>, is marched towards <em>Brisack</em>, with an intent to bring the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Harcourt</em> to accept of those conditions mentioned in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Declaration, which <reg orig="setleth">settleth</reg> him on those conditions as he was when he left the <reg orig="Leagure">Leaguer</reg> of <em>Villanova</em> in <em>Agenois</em>, and in a case of denial, the said Marshal is to block him up, and reduce by force of arms, having already taken some Castles which are leading on to the work; The <em>French</em> forces are still quartered in <em>Languedoc</em> and now the provisions brought into <em>Rosa</em> being <reg orig="neer">near</reg> spent; therefore care is had to relieve the place with<pb n="7" /> such necessaries as they want, <em>Don Joseph de Margeurit</em> who was left Commander in chief by the Marshal <em>de Hoquincourt</em> is using all means possible to gain some advantage upon the <em>Spanish</em> forces, who being in their Winter quarters <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> are so watchful that their enemy can gain no advantage. The Marshal <em>de la Grammont</em> passed through <em>Bourdeaux</em> without making any stay there, and so went into <em>Beyonne</em> there to settle things in a posture he being <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of that City, and places adjacent next to <em>Biscay</em>. We hear from <em>Provence</em> that they <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on still in the making ready the great Fleet, which is intended as we believe for the <em>Levant</em> but there being no moneys come from Court, the work goeth on but slowly. The Duke <em>de Guise</em>, who believeth to be Commander in chief of that expedition, being more forward in his particular than the main <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is in general, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said that at the return the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> from Court, there shall be an impost laid upon the whole Province, for the payment of five hundred thousand Livers for the furthering and advancing of that work.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxemburg</reg></em> We hear, that the Garrison lately come out of <em>Beffort</em> was arrived there in a reasonable good condition, considering the <reg orig="tediousnesse">tediousness</reg> of the march and the time of the year, these forces being <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with others are marched toward <em>Namun</em>.</p>

<p><em>Antwerp</em> the 14 of <em>March</em> 1654: The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> doth still remain in our Castle as a close prisoner, the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> doth use him with all the civil respects as may be, and as becometh a Prince, his Brother Duke <em>Francis</em> (as I hear) will be here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to command the Army: there is an Express sent to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and another in <em>Spain</em> to give notice of all what hath passed in that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, there hath not been discovered as yet any considerable sums of money in his possession, the great <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is those Jewels found about his Daughter amounting to a good round sum, he keepeth daily a very good Table having great store of men to wait on him.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> March 8.</head> 

<p>An Ordinance is preparing for the Trial and approbation of Ministers; and thirty Commissioners (Ministers and others) will be appointed to put them in execution; but the power extends only to the trying of such Ministers as have been admitted within these six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> last past, or that shall be admitted hereafter.</p>

<p>As concerning the Dutch Peace, the Articles of the late Treaty are <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>, and six Members of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> are appointed Commissioners to meet with the Dutch Ambassadors; whereupon its supposed Subscriptions <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be made on either side, in order to a firm Peace and Amity.</p>

<p>No <reg orig="newes">news</reg> from Sea, save that our Fleet ride near Saint <em><reg orig="Ellins">Helens</reg> Point</em>, in gallant Equipage, and more ships are putting forth with speed. On the other side the Dutch are preparing to put out to Sea; but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> written that their great Fleet will not be ready till May.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em>, March 12. Since the surrender of <em>Beffort</em>, the Court hath again assailed Count Harcourt with new Temptations for a surrender of what he hold in <em>Alsatia</em>, and the Marshal <em>de la Ferte Senaterre</em> hath instructions sent him for that purpose; but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> apprehended he will never trust the Court, not the Charms of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg>.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em>, and his new Princess the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece, have spent their <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hitherto in Balls and Feasting among the great ones, at which Solemnities both the King and Cardinal have made all possible expressions of mirth and contentment. The Lady is one of much beauty, and considering her <reg orig="husbands">husband's</reg> stature, may soon look over his shoulder, in such an active Court as this is. The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> keeps servants of his own about him, that as Policy and Interest made this <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> match, so Policy may keep it, till personal and state <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> do chance to break it; for <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought and said already, there is not much affection, nor confidence on either side. The Populary talk of a prodigious sum appointed for the <reg orig="Ladies">Lady's</reg> Portion, and they have most<pb n="9" /> reason to talk (though they seldom hit right) because it goes out of their Purses, whatever it be. It is not liked, that so many Persons interested in the City, should be visiting of <em>Conti</em>, where it is not known what his and his brother <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> interest may yet effect, notwithstanding the late Marriage, seeing it were no new thing in <em>Paris</em>, if the highest <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> of malice should break out at, or after a wedding.</p>

<p>His brother the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, is preparing to make work at Spring. That little cloud upon the Frontiers may chance to gather now that the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, his great Rival and Competitor in the Spanish Interest, is said in Limbo: for <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was the great impediment to the Prince's <reg orig="designes">designs</reg>, having (as he is charged) been tempering with <em>France</em>, to the prejudice of the affairs both of <em>Spain</em> and <em>Conde</em>, but being removed, and his Army disposed into the hands of his younger brother, <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em>, a person not so debauched nor odious, but more firm at the devotion of the Spaniards, it is supposed they may be able to go on the more current in their <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> upon this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>. And in <em>Flanders</em> they are very forward in their Preparations already; which being observed here, orders are issued out by Marshal <em>Turain</em>, his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> General, for putting the Army with all speed into a convenient posture to prevent them.</p>

<p>The young King here <reg orig="followes">follows</reg> his pleasure; he and the Cardinal have lately been a hunting the wild Bore at St. Germans. His Majesty shall not want delights to put State business out if his head. His eminence is sending for his Father, the old Mazarini, to follow the Sisters, Daughters, and Nieces into this Kingdom. By matches, or one way or other, they are like all to be of the blood.</p>

<p>These things are <reg orig="stomackt">stomached</reg> still by the Duke of Orleans, who keeps close still at Blois, and will not be <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg> by<pb n="10" /> any means to <reg orig="intrust">entrust</reg> his Brother at Court. The Cardinal de Retz is still kept a prisoner, to the great discontent of the Clergy, and there he is like to be kept; for Mazarin <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> well enough that this man made a Cardinal, <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> to out brave and supplant him, and the end drive him out of the Nation.</p>

<p>The inclination of Holland and the rest of the Provinces, to make a firm peace with England, hath filled this Court with the same affections. And the next thing that will be done to smooth the way, will be to <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> rid of <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and his Zetinue, who (they say) are already providing to be gone; but whether, none <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>, unless it to be Germany.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em> the 16. <em>Feb</em>. 1654. By a ship that came lately from <em>Candia</em>, we hear that <em>Vssaim</em> Bashaw, who is <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Turkish Army in that Island, intending to <reg orig="besidge">besiege</reg> a new, that City had brought all his Forces <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the place intending <reg orig="intrench">entrench</reg> and <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> themselves close to the walls, but that our Forces within had made such a <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> tally upon those infidels, that they had not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> made them to forsake their new works, but likewise made them retreat in a disorderly way, but not without some considerable <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> on our part: here are now four ships under sail, which carry men, moneys, and the like warlike necessaries for the relief of <em>Candia</em>; and there are more ships which will be ready for the same purpose in a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, our Levies likewise go on gallantly not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> those in <em>Germany</em>, but also those in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts of <em>Italy</em>, divers persons who had been<pb n="11" /> exiled from this City, have made their peace with considerable sums of money among whom is the Earl <em>Porcellago</em> of <em>Breseis</em>, who upon his agreement is to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> and maintain for one <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> 1200 men in <em>Candia</em>, and moreover to serve in person during the wars, From <em>Genoa</em> the 18 <em>ditto</em> upon <em>Wednesday</em> last here <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> Letters from Alicant and other places in <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> which imply no further, save that the Duke <em>de Tarsie </em>was <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> with four Galleys at <em>Porto Mobone</em>, and was expecting two more which being arrived he intends to come for these parts: and by that <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> it is thought some <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> will be brought to serve in the State of <em>Milan</em>. The aforesaid <em>Wednesday</em> some Commissioners sent from the City of <em>Messina</em> in <em><reg orig="Sicilia">Sicily</reg></em>, to the Spanish Court having remained some few <reg orig="daies">days</reg> here, are gone on in their journey for <em>Madrid</em>. There is likewise this week come into this Port a Galley of the Duke of <em>Florence</em> having in her besides other rich goods three hundred Balls of Silk unwrought: <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hear from <em>Rome</em> that the Duke <em>de Terra nova</em> being come to <em>Naples</em> is expected there daily to execute the plate of an Ambassador in ordinary for <em>Spain</em>, and that great preparations are making for his reception and making king his <reg orig="Calvacate">Cavalcade</reg> in that City.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> March 9.</head>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 14 of March 1564. <em>stilo novo</em>. The States of <em>Languedo</em>, with much <reg orig="adoe">ado</reg> have yielded to pay to the King the sum of fifteen hundred thousand livers,<pb n="12" /> which is to be paid ready <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, although the quartering of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and other oppressions and grievances make them much incapable to effect it.</p>

<p>The Governor of St. Menehold having sent out two parties abroad, have made a great progress upon the Princes forces, having plundered several Villages near <em>Stenay</em>, and brought away great store of Cattle: now open <reg orig="warre">war</reg> being declared between <em>Clermont</em> of the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> party, and <em>Verdun</em> of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> side, they commit all acts of hostility that may be imagined, which is the more <reg orig="easie">easy</reg>, being so <reg orig="neare">near</reg> <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg>.</p> 

<p>The nineteenth instant the King went near to the City to take a view of his Regiment of the Guards who was then drawn out into the field.</p>

<p>The same day the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Brother, with several <reg orig="Councellors">Councillors</reg> of state went to the Court of <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg>, to see several Edicts passed, and among them, one for suppressing them called Elect.</p> 

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em> likewise went to another Court to see the same Edicts passed, and in both places they were approved and <reg orig="registred">registered</reg>.</p>

<p>The 11th instant the King went to the Castle of <em>Vecennes</em>, with the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, and were that day hunting in the Park, and fortuned to this City.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>Retz</em> doth still remain a close prisoner, and the intended Agreement cannot be brought yet to any perfection, which doth make the Clergy very full of discontent.</p><pb n="13" />

<p>The Duke of <em>Orleans</em> is still near <em>Blois</em>, and will not be induced to come to the Court. The report concerning the sending an extraordinary Ambassador for England, is not so frequent as formerly, the main thing looked upon here, is to see the conclusion of the peace between England and Holland, the credential letters being sent to Monsieur de Bourdeaux, to be received Ambassador, no doubt but the same will be effected, and so great conducing to a peace between us and England.</p>

<p>There are several <reg orig="Mariages">Marriages</reg> spoken here, but as yet nothing done. The Cardinal is very <reg orig="frolick">frolic</reg> with his new kindred, and no other talk but of new Alliances, in the mean time the Prince of <em>Conti</em> bearing great <reg orig="stroak">stroke</reg> at Court being highly in <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> with the King and Cardinal.</p>

<p><reg orig="An other">Another</reg> part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church falling down this week, at the great South Door, where a part fell before: It was under under consideration by the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> for taking it down, but nothing yet done in it.</p>

<p>Orders were issued from the Lord Protector, for all Officers concerned, to repair their charges in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p><i>All the Adventurers for Lands in <em>Ireland</em> are desired to take notice, that the Committee for <reg orig="Claimes">Claims</reg> have appointed a Lottery for <em>Narroines</em>, to be at Grocers Hall <em>London</em>, on Thursday the thirtieth of <em>March</em> 1654. to begin at eight of the Clock in the <reg orig="forenoone">forenoon</reg> of the same day.</i></p>
<p><i><em>William Tibbs</em> Clerk</i></p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em> and <em>Saturday</em> 10, 11.</head>

<p><em>Scarborough</em> the 6. of <em>March</em>, we are still visited by the Dutch Freebooter, who have of late taken some Barks which came from <em>Sunderland</em>, and caused another to run a <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg> near<pb n="14" /> <em><reg orig="Hartlepoole">Hartlepool</reg></em>: there are a great many ships ready to come from <em>Newcastle</em> so soon as the wind will permit.</p>

<p><em>Amsterdam</em> the 14. of <em>March</em>, there is arrived this week at the <em>Ulie</em> a Fleet of ships of about 140 <reg orig="Saile">Sail</reg>, which came from the <em>Eastland</em>, whereof a part is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up to this City, and the rest goeth to divers other parts in this County. The Commander <em>Ruyter</em> is chosen Vice-<reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> for this City: There is likewise come to the <em>Hague</em> an Agent or <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister of <em><reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg></em>, who is called the <em>Chevalier Palant</em>, he hath had audience of the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and after that hath delivered in certain Papers, wherein are expressed at large, the occasion of his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, and his demands, a Freebooter of <em>Enchuison</em> hath lately retaken a ship had been taken by the English near <em>Ulie</em>, here are two great ships also come from the <em>Charibdie</em> Islands. This week <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Middleton</em> is gone from hence to <em>Scotland</em>, having <reg orig="onely">only</reg> two men of war, the one of 20 Guns, and the other of 16 Guns, the greatest matter which they carry over with them, is some small quantity of Ammunitions, and about three hundred <reg orig="voluntiers">volunteers</reg>, few of them men of fortune.</p>

<p><em>Dover</em> the 9 of <em>March</em>, by a small Bark come this morning from <em>France</em>. we hear that a great Fleet of Dutch <reg orig="Marchant">Merchant</reg> men, consisting of about 140 Sail is gone to the Westward, sailing close by the Coast of <em>France</em>, and having a fair wind, <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> like they have <reg orig="past">passed</reg> without any interruption from our Fleet, whom we hear is still near <em>St <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point, this Dutch Fleet hath a Convoy of about 60 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of men of war, but they are to be divided, the Merchant ships being bound to several Countries and Ports: we are expecting some ships from <em><reg orig="Dunkerk">Dunkirk</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Ostende">Ostend</reg></em>, but as yet they are not arrived.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em> the 4 of March 1653. Since my last there is certain intelligence come of the Landing of Middleton at the <reg orig="Ferrey">Ferry</reg> of Uney in Southerland, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> was <reg orig="sennight">sevennight</reg>, about 12 of the clock at night in an Hoy, in which was some <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>: there came with him Sir <em>George Munroe</em>, the Lord <em>Nappier</em>, <em>Tho: Dyell</em>,<pb n="15" /> Alderman, Major Gen: <em>Dyell</em>, <em>Lodowick Drumland</em>, and above 100 more. The Vessel was unloaded, and sent away the next morning. They sent 40. of their men or thereabouts, up to <em>Achness</em> with 8 or 10 Horse Load of Arms, the rest they carried along with themselves, and go up Strath fleet, towards Assigne. It is reported, there is another Ship loaded in Strathnemer with Arms, but no men, they speak of meeting with Glencairn in the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of Murray, where they are to have their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and from thence to <reg orig="presse">press</reg> all the Countries of <em>Rise</em>.</p>

<p>The Articles of Agreement between the Dutch and us (as before mentioned) are not yet <reg orig="engrosed">engrossed</reg>, but the English Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to the Lord Protector, <em>viz</em>. the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Major General <em>Lambert</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Mr. <em>Lawrence</em>, Col. <em>Montague</em>, and Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, appointed to finish the business of the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, have had several meetings, and the results of all (as fairly conjectured) tends to a speedy Union. However, preparations for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> this <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> stately Fleet goes on a main, and 1000 private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> this week (besides Seamen) were drawn out of four Regiments about <em>London</em>, and sent on <reg orig="ship-board">shipboard</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly published, a Book <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, The Perfect Pharisee, under monkish Holiness, opposing the fundamental Principles of the Gospel and Scripture Practises, in a Generation of men called Quakers, or a Preservative against their <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> blasphemies and horrid delusions. (Published by the Ministers of Newcastle) sold by Rich: Tomlins, at the Son and Bible near Pie Corner.</p>

<p>A Plea for Anti-P&aelig;dobaptists, against the vanity and <reg orig="falshood">falsehood</reg> of the <reg orig="scribled">scribbled</reg> Papers, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, The Anabaptists <reg orig="anatomized">anatomised</reg> and silenced in a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> dispute at Avergaveny in Monmouthshire Septemb. 5. 1653. betwixt John Tombes, John Crag, &amp; Hen: Vaughan, teaching Instant <reg orig="Baptisme">Baptisms</reg>. By John Tombes B. D. Sold by Hen: Hills, at the sign of Sir John Newcastles in Pie-Corner.</p>

<p>A bright Bay pacing Mare, with a small <reg orig="Starre">Star</reg>, black mane and black Tail, <reg orig="dockt">docked</reg> somewhat short, great with <unclear><reg orig="feal">feel</reg></unclear>, with an old <reg orig="soare">sore</reg> upon the <reg orig="wythers">withers</reg>, healed up but no hair upon it, a little hip-shotten, but hardly to be discerned, 14 hand high, and 8 <reg orig="yeare">year</reg> old, she was lost from Hampton Court in Herefordshire, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Lancaster, about the end of Decemb. last, whosoever shall give notice of her to the place abovesaid, unto Mr. Leves, at the White Heart in St. Johns street, shall have twenty shillings for his pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>