<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn10">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 10</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The whole manner of the Treaty of Peace, and the most excellent Speech of the Lord <em>Beverling</em> to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the rest of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, with their several speeches to them again. Likewise a Narrative of the sad accident that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> the Troops at the Langer in Scotland: with a desperate and bloody fight at Sea between the Warwick <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, and Cap. <em>Beach</em> Admiral of the Brest Men of War: The manner of the fight, the number of men slain, and the taking of <em>Beach</em> and his ship, The coming of two <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> from <em>France</em>. The Signing of the <em>Articles</em>: With an Order for making of new Farthings.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 14. to <em>Tuesday</em> March 21. 1654.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday</i> March 14.</head>

<p>This day his Highness the Lord Protector received several petitions, and passed divers Orders for relief of poor people that made addresses to his Highness.</p>

<p>Also this say <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Desborow</em>, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty returned home from <em>Chattam</em> and came to <em>Whitehall</em>, the English Fleet being ready and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> by the Sea side ready to go on <reg orig="boord">board</reg>, if need be.</p>

<p>This day Major Bourn, and divers others, were robbed at Shooters Hill and bound in a wood, some in a Coach fought, but the Thieves slew one of the Gentlemen; another of the Gentlemen came to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg> M. <reg orig="Mollins">Mollins'</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-Lane">Shoe Lane</reg>, where one of the Thieves also came to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, but the Thief hearing that he was dressing one that was hurt at Shooters Hill, run away without his cloak, which he had put off in expectation to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, but M. Mollins having intelligence where he was gone, went presently and apprehended him, and from thence was brought to Newgate.</p>

<p>On Thursday <em>March</em> 16. a <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Minister out of <em>Flanders</em> from the Arch-Duke <em>Leopoldus</em>, had audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>From <em>Upsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, thus, Our affairs here have had a little pause, and are at a stand; The Lord Chancellor hath been very much indisposed in his health, but now he is abroad again: The Treaty goes on, and this afternoon my Lord Ambassador and he have had a meeting concerning it, we cannot but believe but we shall have a very good issue; yet they are a little stumbled here at our detention of their ships, and at the dilatoriness of the proceedings of the Court of Admiralty concerning them. There are many reports here of an Ambassador Extraordinary coming from France, and another from Russia, this Virgin Lady is much courted in this juncture of Time.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> thus: The 27. last <reg orig="past">passed</reg> the King and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> went a hunting to <em>Versailles</em>. The <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> of <em>Mercoeur</em> with the other Kindred of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazarine</em>, arrived in this City, and were extraordinary well received of their Majesties at the <em><reg orig="Lowre">Louvre</reg>.</em></p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>There is a strong report, that the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> is arrived in this <unclear>City and that he</unclear> will have his father come from <em>Rome</em> and live at Court, to that end he hath procured him from the King the Title of Duke and Peer of France, and that he doth purpose to buy him, as soon as may be, some Lands for him and his heirs, and Monsieur <em>de Lyonne</em> is to <reg orig="carrie">carry</reg> the letters to <em>Rome</em> upon that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Wednesday March 15.</head>

<p>On the second instant the King went to St. <em><reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg></em> to hunt a wild Boar, which had been brought into the Park by order of the Governor; after which he exercised himself in shooting of Birds flying, where he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> great dexterity and experience; and having spent most part of the day upon such exercise, as is fit for his quality and young years, he returned hither in the evening on horseback.</p>

<p>Our late Ambassador or at <em>Rome</em> is returned, and come to this city, to give his Majesty an account of his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, there is another to go thither very shortly, who will be ready to go about the middle of <em>April</em>, but some say not so soon.</p>

<p>From Brussels thus: <i>The Earl <em>de Fuensaldagne</em> being gone from thence, came the next day to <em>Delft</em>, and the two days following, the Officers of the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> Army came to meet him, what by his care and wisdom, <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the Authority of the Arch-Duke Leopoldus, and the good disposition in the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, he hath wrought so much upon them, as to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to obey the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em>, as they did formerly, whilst the arrival of the Duke <em>Francis</em> Brother to him that is now imprisoned, and having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things as well for that particular, as for those <reg orig="publike">public</reg> affairs which concern his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and came back upon Wednesday last to this City.</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 16.</i></head>

<p>This day came to my hands a Narrative of the said accident that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> the Troops of the Langer in Scotland published to prevent the mis-reports that perhaps <reg orig="som">some</reg> <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> spirits <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be ready to make of it.</p>

<p>On the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day Feb. 19. Cap. <em>Mason</em> being at <reg orig="Dunfriez">Dumfries</reg>, had intelligence that the enemy was at a place called the Lanker, about 16 miles from <reg orig="Dunfriez">Dumfries</reg>, upon which he forthwith marched with 80 of his troop, upon whose approach the enemy left the town, betaking them to the hills, Cap. <em>Mason</em> in the pursuit took a Cornet and, and two more, the rest their horses being fresh, and his almost weary with the march, escaped, Cap. <em>Mason</em> quartered in the <reg orig="towne">town</reg> that night, and about four in the morning Capt. <em>Palmer</em> came there with his party, having also had intelligence of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> being there, and knowing nothing what was done, took Capt. <reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg> troops to be the <reg orig="enemie">enemy</reg>, and a Scotchman one of the <reg orig="Dragoons">Dragoon's</reg> Scouts, being violently charged by Cap. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> men, who he thought to be the enemy, declared the spirit of a Scotchman by saying that he was for the King, to save his life, by which means he lost it.</p>

<p>The whole party then endeavouring to enter the town, the guard repulsed them; upon which Captain Palmer drew out a party of twenty to fire the guard house, by which time Cap. Mason had thirty or forty of his horse together, and with them beat out Capt. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> party, which <reg orig="hey">they</reg> took to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> the enemy, they pursued in the evening, and at the <reg orig="townsend">town's end</reg> Captain Palmer met them with the whole party, and fell upon them, both sides <reg orig="stil">still</reg> judging each other <reg orig="stil">still</reg> to be the enemy; in which unhappy engagement six were <reg orig="slaine">slain</reg> of both parties, and eight wounded, of which number Cap. Palmer is one hurt.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>At the Committee of Adventurers for Lands in Ireland the <reg orig="nineth">ninth</reg> day of March, 1654. at Grocers hall.</p>

<head level="2"><i>By direction of his Highness the Lord Protector, We desire the several Ministers, or Churchwardens of each Parish church and <reg orig="chappel">chapel</reg> within <em>London</em>, the liberties <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, and the late line of communication, to appoint some meet persons to give notice in their several Congregations upon next <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day, being the 12 instant, That all Adventurers for <reg orig="Rebels">Rebels'</reg> lands in Ireland, are requested to meet upon <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> next at 2 of the clock in the afternoon, to <reg orig="receiue">receive</reg> account of proceedings since the last general meeting.</i></head>

<p>Signed by Command of the Committee, <em>Richard Deacon</em>, Clerk, attending the Committee.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Friday, March 17.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lords <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> of <em>Holland</em>, were removing from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em> to Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> in <em>Channel-<reg orig="Roe">Row</reg></em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Palace yard <unclear>in</unclear> <em>Westminster</em>, which they have taken to reside in.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> we have received intelligence that the <em>Constant Warwick</em> and the <em>Porchmouth <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg></em> being together, met with the great Pirate Capt. <em>Beach</em>, who had newly taken two prizes, but <unclear>perceiving</unclear> that our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the prizes and was afterwards secured by the <unclear>night coming</unclear> on; The same night the <em>Porchmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and the <em>Constant Warwick</em> chanced to part company, and it so fell put about midnight, that <em>Beach</em> roving <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> lighted on the Constant Warwick all alone, <unclear><!--which--></unclear> before when he came <reg orig="neer">near</reg>, he took to be a Merchant man, and went on with an intent to <reg orig="boord">board</reg> her. But the <em>Warwick</em> demanding who he was, he replied, he was the <em>Portsmouth <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg></em>, and for <em>Whitehall</em>; but the <em>Warwick</em> suspecting him, bad him round off: then <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake, and seeing the <em>Warwick</em> to be a Man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, he presently made a way, but the <em>Warwick</em> being a good <reg orig="sailer">sailor</reg>, made after him, and kept company with him all night; about 6 in the morning, <em>Beach</em> began the fight, firing three guns, which were answered by the <em>Warwick</em>, the encounter lasted till two in the afternoon, At which time <em>Beach</em> and his men called for quarter, and had it, he had five foot water in the hole when he <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg>, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> has two hundred men, twenty whereof were killed, his <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> is a very gallant new <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> of two and forty guns, whereof but eight and thirty were mounted; there are taken aboard with him nine Captains, besides himself, and divers Gentlemen, who are all prisoners: <pb n="6" />This is that <em>Beach</em> the Ringleader Pirate, who hath done our Merchants so much mischief this winter, that he lived like a Prince at Brest, for which <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> like <reg orig="hee">he</reg> will receive his reward, being brought in hither with the rest of his companions.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday</i> March 18.</head>

<p>This day the two Ordinances touching Ministers, and touching the Law, is before a Committee, where Justice <em>Hales</em> Chairman; the particulars whereof you <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have in my next.</p>

<p>The Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, Sheriffs, and Common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the renowned City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, have presented a cordial Declaration to his Highness the Lord Protector, wherein they sincerely bless God for his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> protection of themselves and this Nation, and humbly desire a confirmation of the Liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> of that Corporation.</p>

<p>From <em>Leith</em>, March 13. thus: Major <em>Middleton</em> is landed at the <em>Ferry</em> of <em>Uney</em> in <em>Southerland</em>, in a <reg orig="Scztch">Scotch</reg> Hoy from the Hague about twelve <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night, <reg orig="rnd">and</reg> another <reg orig="vessell">vessel</reg> at <em>Strathnemer</em>, in both 150 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of powder, and 500 Chanas given out, and with him are Sir George Monroe, the Lord Nipper, Alderman Thandyel, Major Gen. Dyel, Lodowick Drumland, and above one hundred more most Officers; they sent about 40 of their men to Achness with eight horseload of Arms, and the rest they are gone towards Strathfleet towards Assign, they intend a <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> with Glencarn, in Murry, and to press all the Countries to rise.</p>

<p>The Treaty goes on hopefully, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> <reg orig="Ged">Gen</reg>. <em>Lambert</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Mr. <em>Lawrence</em>, Col: <em>Montagne</em> and M. <em>Strickland</em> are the Commissioners for the L. Protector, that treat with the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> from the States General of the united Provinces of Holland.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 20.</i></head>

<p>The Commissioners from the Lord Protector went from his Highness in two coaches, with the Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council, with their attendants, to the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>; they were met at the gate by the Lords Ambassadors, where the Lord <em>Beverling</em> made a speech to them, and they received them with great respect, and love on both sides, being come into the house and chamber appointed for their conference, they spent much time in order to the finishing of the peace; the main business this day was to confer their papers of the Agreement; and for those they have agreed, and they are <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> by each side.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Harwich</em> thus.</head>

<p>Sir by your Letter bearing date March 16. I am informed you have taken a Dutch ship of four hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts, and Iron, to a great value, by a private Man of War. The particulars whereof I <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> you to send in your next.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for appointing Commissioners for approving of Ministers throughout the Nation, is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>There is an excellent book come forth, called the <em><reg orig="Independents">Independent's</reg> Catechism</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>