<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn03">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 3</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>A great and bloody fight between the Highlanders and the English, and <unclear><!--3 characters--></unclear> the Victory obtained by the English. The safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of a rich Fleet from Dunkirk, consisting of about forty <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, laden with Silks, and divers other rich commodities. Also how the Dutch Deputies have made some further application to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, concerning peace, and their staying at Gravesend for that purpose. Likewise divers ships cast away in a great storm, and tempest, as they were going to <reg orig="Guernsay">Guernsey</reg>. The lamentable thunder and lightning <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Amsterdam, whereby five hundred houses were <unclear>burned</unclear>, forty <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships sunk, and divers <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> destroyed. With the choicest <unclear>Letters</unclear> from all parts of Europe.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday January 3.</em> to <em>Tuesday January 10.</em> 1653</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Begining">Beginning</reg> Tuesday January the 3.</i></head>

<p>The States assembled in <em>Provence</em> are now sitting at <em>Bagnolle</em>, where the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> the Governor, and the other Procurators are also gone; they <reg orig="doe">do</reg> sit daily, and hope to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> many abuses, and redress grievances which do much <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> the people there. The Commissioners appointed to draw out the Charge of high treason against the Prince of Conde have met <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times, and it is said that it is finished, only it wants <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>.</p>

<p>We received information that the Prince hath surprised a little town and a Castle in Champagne, and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> pitifully.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>General <em>Blake</em> is going to the <em>Hope</em>, a Fleet of 50 are already out together in the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg>, and more will suddenly be with them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Pembrook, Decemb. 27.</i></head>

<p>On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last we had here the fearfullest Thunder, Lightning and Rain, as hath been heard of, and some <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> destroyed thereby. The Lord speak peace to his people, many constructions poor people make thereof.</p>

<head level="3"><i>January 4. 1653</i></head>

<p><i>The Trustees for the sale of Forrest Lands, have appointed upon Tuesday next, the tenth of this instant January, in the forenoon, to sit for allowance of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Faith Bills to be doubled upon security of the said Lands, and thenceforth weekly every Tuesday in the forenoon, till the sum to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> doubled be full.</i></p>

<p>William Tayleure Secr. to the said Trustees.</p>

<p><i>Whitehall Jan.3.</i> The <em>Dutch Deputies</em> had their last conference and spent the whole day therein; but came to no conclusion. The next News we hear of them id, That Jan.3. they departed from their house, sent their Goods a shipboard, and themselves went after about nine of the clock the same night.</p>

<p>We hear no news from Sea, save that our fleet on the <em><reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg></em>: And that we have lost two ships of eighteen Guns, and four hundred <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>, laden with masts, and some other commodities; which were taken by certain <em>dutch</em> men of War this last week and carried into <em>Flushing</em>.</p>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with his honourable <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, had the large and last conference at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> with the Dutch Ambassadors, where his Highness insisted upon these ensuing propositions. <em>viz.</em></p>

<p>1. That Satisfaction given for all the injuries and wrongs sustained by the English, since the first affront offered by <em>Vantrump</em> upon the Downs.</p>

<p>2. That they shall pay the same contribution and <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> for fishing upon the Narrow seas, as was formerly paid in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>,</p>

<p>3. That the dominion of the Seas be invested upon the English, and that all such Vessels whatsoever that carries the <em>Dutch</em> <reg orig="colors">colours</reg>, shall strike sail unto the ships of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland or Ireland.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>4. That Security be given, for performance of all the particular Articles contained in the Treaty, &amp;c.</p>

<p>To which the Lord Ambassadors returned Answer, That they could not assent unto the proposals, without further Instructions, and <unclear>desired</unclear> a Convoy for their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might return an account of the Transactions of the Treaty, and be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> with further Instructions if convenient. Whereupon a convoy was appointed, and in the evening about 9 of the clock, they <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth in a stately Barge towards Gravesend.</p>

<p>The Spanish and <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> Ambassadors have likewise congratulated his Highness, and have so far agreed, that the Lord <em>Pontania Safa</em>, brother to the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> removed from Newgate to the Tower of London.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday Jan.9</i></head>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 31 December,</i> The enemy still go on with their levies in several parts of the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, and will be numerous, do what we can to prevent them, though I see not how they can hold together in a body when <reg orig="conjoyned">conjoined</reg>, the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> not being able to bear them. <em>Kenmore</em> lies up towards the Bray of Mane, and in the Glens that way, within the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Woods and Rivers, and all along in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> fast places from Lough Tay, towards the Brays of Stermont and Angus.</p>

<p><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Jan. 2.</i> The last Letters from <em>Holland</em> speak, that the people are generally for peace, and that the Dane begins to doubt that they will leave him in the lurch. He knows well enough how they have dealt with him, and have had a feeling of their practices heretofore.</p>

<p>The lofty <reg orig="termes">terms</reg> propounded by the French Ambassador at the Hague, are looked on as <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Court-gins, which will not take the costive <em>Hollander</em>, who know the odds betwixt a French promise and performance; nor is it imaginable, that this interposition of the Monsieur there should work <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> at all upon the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> supposed, the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> will have a stronger influence on that Horizon. We hear, that the <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> which convoyed his Lordship met with four Dutch Merchantmen, bound homeward from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> well laden.</p>

<p>The last Letters from <em>Stockholm</em> report, that the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> is on his way to <em>Upsalah</em>, within two days journey of the Court.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday Jan.5:</i></head>

<p><i>Warwick Jan 4.1653.</i> This day Mr <em>Bulstrode</em>, one of the <unclear>Judges</unclear> of North Wales, came hither by a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Commission of <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> delivery, he heard a Sermon early on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning, and went directly from thence to the Hall, where there was a very great appearance, and a very able grand jury, there hath not been a greater <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> known these many <reg orig="yeers">years</reg>: there is five men and one woman condemned to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>; seven likewise burned in the hand, and two men that would not plead to be <unclear>pressed</unclear>: the Judge used his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to plead, telling them what a bad condition they would bring themselves into; but the resolute villains were resolved to die in their wickedness, I will assure you the Judge carried the business very well, and gave the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> a great deal of satisfaction; he <reg orig="spake">spoke</reg> something in his charge In relation to the late Government, he said that it was now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon such a Basis as was like to conduce much to the happiness of all good people; he gave strict Orders to the Grand Jury, that if they heard of any that were Perturbers of this, that they should not fail to bring them to the Bar of justice, and a great deal more to the same effect.</p>

<p>From <i>Deal Jan.4.</i> We received this day intelligence, That some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken some Beclanders belonging to <em>Calice</em>, who were bound for <em>Roan</em> and <em>Cane</em> in <em>Normandy</em>, laden with divers forts of commodities, and carried them into Stoaks Bay, where we hear that <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monke</em> with his Squadron was about <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since: Those ships lately gone from hence bound for Roan are safely arrived there, and their Convoy is returned back.</p>

<p>On Wednesday morning a party of these Royal Pilferers met the Post-boy going from Leith with Letters for London, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Haddington took his horse and Letters, and some money, so that now it will be uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy.</p>

<head level="3">From the <em>Downs</em>, thus</head>

<p>Capt. Richard Newberry, Commander of the Lawrell, is come in hither, who had been out by order from the Generals, with his ship and the Ruby, the Kent and the Industry, who ply between the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> of Wight and the French coasts, there he took some prizes; when they were towards the French casts, they made a discovery of four <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of <unclear><!--approx. 16 characters, probably more than one word--></unclear> they gave chase, and followed them so close that <pb n="4" />they took two of them. Men were taken out of the ship <reg orig="call'd">called</reg> the Kent, to man one of the prizes, which is come hither into the <em>Downs</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em>, we are advertised thus. The enemy is departed from the hithermost parts of <em>Ahol</em>, and <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to <em>Kirkmichel</em> in order to their march Northwards; as I am informed <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarn</em> are both there, and their force reported to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> 500. Foot and 500. Horse; but those that gave me information that saw them, affirm they are not half that number, they lie under very many discouragements, and every place so eaten up where they come, that they are forced upon often <reg orig="removalls">removals</reg>, and now provision of Mutton and Beef begins to decay: I hear they intend for the North, that their Quarters upon the Lowlands may be more assured and broader, where they expect the landing of <reg orig="Forrain">Foreign</reg> Forces, Ammunition and Money from their Majesty and the States of <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p><em>Athol</em> doth nothing considerable; the people refuse to raise his men according to command, one that saw him and his <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, faith, he hath not got above forty Foot, and Major <em>Mercer</em> is there with about 60 Horse.</p>

<p>Captain <em>Elsemore</em>, of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Riches</em> Regiment, sent out a party the other day from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, who took one Captain <em>Stuart</em>, who had a Commission from <em>Lorne</em> to raise Forces, and four others, and killed three on the place. The Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> last week at his house of <em>Bogygeith</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Darwicke</em>, we have intelligence, thus: A private Man of War hath brought into Holy Land two Dutch Vessels, coming from the East Country, both being about an hundred and fifty <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> laden with Tar, Pitch, and the like Commodities.</p>

<p>From Falmouth, the 2 instant, we received intelligence, That there were many ships in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> which are now all gone to their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> intended Ports: The Dutch are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts, so that it is very hard to pass by the Lands end without a good Convoy. They have, we hear, taken a ship of London, coming from New-England, laden with Masts, Beaver-skins, and the like commodities. Here hath been some of the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships to wash and tallow, and to take in fresh water, but they are all at Sea again, there remaining none at present in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From Rotterdam there is little News to write at present there being no Post come this week as yet, which doth cause us to suspect that you have once more dissolved the Parliament. In the meantime, we only expect the resolutions of your <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> to make peace or war, being equally disposed to the one or the other, for our rest, or for our reputation; and as there is more likelihood for us to continue the war, seeing you do not answer our good intentions, by <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> yourselves so high in your demands, there is a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> willingness to contribute sufficiently, every one according to his estate and means, towards the maintaining of necessary <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> for the defence of our Provinces. And for this purpose we are building of ships in all our Ports, where do arrive several ships from all parts richly laden to support our Trade; and some of them have brought us Guns, Bullets, <reg orig="Salt-peter">Saltpetre</reg>, and other Ammunition of <reg orig="warre">war</reg>, which we stood in great need of, notwithstanding all this, we should be glad of a peace upon any reasonable terms: For if the war continue we must expect to have our Trade quite ruined by it, which consequently will be the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: and although we do please ourselves with fine words how that the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scot's</reg> <unclear>affairs</unclear> thrives in Scotland, and that many of the Nobility begin to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Highlanders, to whom there hath been sent from hence six or seven thousand Arms and Ammunition of all sorts which are said to be safely arrived in those parts. Yet the wise and sober minded men amongst us look upon them as a company of plunderers that are go together to rob and steal, and so to return to their holes again when the season of the <reg orig="yeere">year</reg> will permit to pursue them; and do conclude that this <reg orig="Countries">Country's</reg> safest way and chiefest good <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be to conclude a peace with England, though it be upon <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg> terms to us, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to continue in so chargeable war, as it hath proved to be ever since we <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into it.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday Jan. 6.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> <em>Whitemore</em> of <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Regiment</em> went up lately to the Hills, and took forty sheep and five Cows, which Sir <em>Mungoe Murtag</em> their Quartermaster General sent forth of the Highlands to be kept <reg orig="neer">near</reg> his own house, Sir <em><reg orig="Mungoes">Mungoe's</reg></em> man, and one horse of the Laird of <em>Lenes</em>, who took Capt. <em>Townsend</em> and Capt. <em>Scroop</em> but the Rider <reg orig="escapt">escaped</reg>; Yesterday a party of the Tories met with four of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Levingston</em> house, about ten miles from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, whom they barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, one of them fled into the house for safety, but the people would not protect him, but left him to the cruelty of those Villains. A party of our Dragoons from the Bray of <em>Mane</em>, fell upon the enemy, killed one, wounded three, and <reg orig="foure">four</reg> horses, I cannot think there is a pack of more merciless Miscreants in the whole world than these now gathered together in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and many of them were at <em>Dunbar</em>, and <em>Worcester</em>, and had liberty granted them through our too much lenity.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> Jan.5. The last News from our Army in <em>Asatia</em> imply, That the Marshall <em>de la Perte</em> hath invested <em>Beffort</em>, and is now making his Lines of Communication, and other works belonging to a siege; there hath been several piece of Ordinance drawn out of <em>Nancy</em>, which are on the way, and will come to the Leagure as soon as any Batteries will be raised for to plant them upon: The Marquis <em>de Uxelles</em> is to be <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and is expected there with three thousand men. This Design hath much <reg orig="allarmed">alarmed</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so much the more since the <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up of the strong Castle of <em>Philpsburgh</em>, which was taken by a <reg orig="surprizall">surprisal</reg> without the loss of one man. The manner thus: The Deputy Governor being gone a hunting, with some of the high Officers of that Garrison, notice being given to one of the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> creatures, he <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg> with alacrity that occasion, and being come into the place, he prevailed upon the Garrison, that he became Master of the place, and this Deputy Governor being come in the evening, knowing not what had passed, found the Bridge drawn up, and the entrance <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> him, whereupon he was forced to retire speedily. The Duke <em>d'Amville</em> being sent by the King to <em>Blois</em> to try once more whether he could prevail with the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, and so bring him again to the Court, returned back this week, and the report is at the Court, that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath brought a very good Answer, and that he will be shortly in this City; but others are of a contrary opinion.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>From Weymouth Jan.3. we received intelligence, <i>That a <reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg> Vessel went Saturday last out of this Harbour homewards, but the same night a very great storm rose at Sea, and brought the ship back again upon our coast, where she with some others, was cast away in the West-Bay, between Portland and <unclear>Rotberry</unclear>, all the men being cast away but the Shipman, and two Passengers that were <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> going over to Jersey or <reg orig="Guernsay">Guernsey</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>From Milford Haven the 3 January. There are <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Vessells">Vessels</reg> here bound for <em>Ireland</em>, but stayed here by reason of the contrary Winds; we have not of late heard ant news from thence; The Pickeroons are still plying about the Isle of Lundy, and often come into the Severn mouth, where sometimes they catch some of out small Vessels.</i></p>

<p><i>There is nothing more from our Fleet, but that part of them are about Plymouth, and others places to the Westward, some lie out towards the coast of <reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg>, to try if they can meet the Brest Men of War, who have got now good ships, and have a considerable strength at Sea.</i></p>

<p><i>This week is arrived the Fleet from Dunkirk, consisting of about forty sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg>, &amp;c. There is come likewise five ships from the Eastland, as also one from Zant with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet not come up the River.</i></p>

<p><i>The Dutch Commissioners, whom we mentioned before to be gone to Gravesend in order to take shipping for Holland, have not yet set sail, but <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> there, and have have<!--have is repeated here--> made some further application to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, which whether or no it will occasion their coming back again to make an absolute Agreement, a short time will discover.</i></p>

<p><i>By an Express from Holland, we received certain intelligence, That upon Tuesday last they had about Amsterdam a most fearful Thunder, lightning and Tempest, and that by this Thunder and lightning there were about 500 houses burnt, and destroyed in and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Amsterdam, besides above 40. <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships sunk in the Texel, and many other great damages, the particulars whereof you shall have in my next, when a fuller account comes.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="2">LONDON, Printed by T. LOCK. 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>