<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn15">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 15</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The last <reg orig="wil">will</reg> and testament of Lieut. Col. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Lilburn, The whole manner of his trial, with the <reg orig="ful">full</reg></i> particulars how he was executed in the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> of <reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg>. A great and bloody Engagement in Scotland, and the event and success thereof. Also a <reg orig="Lettey">Letter</reg> of great concernment sent from the Duke of York to the King of Scots, concerning the <reg orig="qaising">raising</reg> of <unclear>divers</unclear> men, with store of Arms and Ammunition, Likewise, a great victory obtained against the Rebels in Ireland, and the number killed and taken. With variety of other intelligence from <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> parts.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> May 8. to <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> May 15. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Begining">Beginning</reg> <i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> May 8.</i></head>

<p>By Letters this day from the West, we received intelligence, that the Brest men of War lately took an English ship coming from <unclear>Merlex</unclear>. Also by another letter we are advertised that our Men of war have taken six French Merchantmen, laden with rich commodities.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday <unclear>May 9.</unclear></i></head>

<p><i><unclear><!--two and a half lines--></unclear> and <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> Morgan continue in the same <unclear><!--6 letters--></unclear>; only the Enemy are often quarrelling among themselves: The last was between Glengary and Sir Arthur Forbes: Kenmore took Forbes his part, <unclear>but</unclear> Middleton parted them. The <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> intends next week to march towards <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, and so for the Hills. The Lord Graighall, one of the Judges at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> died this day.</i></p>

<p>The Marshal de Grance hath raised an army 330 foot Companies and 120 Troops.</p>

<p>Several Letters to Merchants and others confirm the intelligence, that a firm and lasting peace is now concluded betwixt England and Sweden.</p>

<p>The Articles will not be published before the Lord Ambassador Whitlock is returned into England, which if the wind serve may be about a <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> or six weeks.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> we are advertised thus. The only news is; that my Lord Ambassador whitlock hath finished his affair at <em>Upsal</em>, and we expect his Lordship in this City within 20 days. There is a firm Alliance and friendship made, which is as much as either side could expect or desire, as things stand.</p>

<p>You Tantalise our expectation about the issue of the Dutch Treaty, touching which our <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> works stronger than our faith.</p>

<p><i>From Upsal we are advertised that The Duke of Muscovy wrote Letters of late to the Qu: of Sweden, wherein he signified the cause of his War with the Pole, two reasons be mentioned; one because a certain poland Poet writing a Narration of former Wars, wherein the Pole had the better, said, they had beaten the Muscovite, <pb n="2" />without adding his Title, plain Muscovite. The other because in quoting something touching the Genealogy of the <reg orig="Muscovites">Muscovite's</reg> Ancestors, he named an as father which was his son; and for these two grand offences, he demanded of the Pole the <reg orig="offenders">offender's</reg> head, which being denied, he makes <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> upon them and hath taken one City, and besieged one of the most considerable in Poland. These were the contents of his Letters. In his long title he hath of late called himself Dominus parentum &amp; anorum <unclear>suarutu</unclear>. The Queen being forced to answer something, because he asked her advice, returned, Thus, That she neither approved nor disapproved, his reasons, but thanking him for his civil Communication, wished that he might receive good satisfaction from the Pole, being troubled that Christian Princes should disagree.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 10.</i></head>

<p><i>From paris this day we received Intelligence that the French Court is still at Fontainbleau; and great preparations are making for his Coronation at Rehims, which will be within a fortnight after his Return hither from the said fontainbleau. All the <reg orig="foraign">foreign</reg> Ministers are invited to the Coronation, and a day appointed for their meeting at Rehims.</i></p>

<p><i>The Protestant Commissioners are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> after the Court supposing the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> will be better at leisure to hear their complaints where he is, them when he is here in Town.</i></p>

<p><i>The Princess of Conde hath petitioned to the Parliament to have her Jointure secured, and <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon her: And the Prince of Conti hath also petitioned to have his <reg orig="fathers">father's</reg> Will <reg orig="annull'd">annulled</reg>, <reg orig="alleadging">alleging</reg> there are many things contained therein which to tend very much to his prejudice, wherein he ought to have <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg>: Both their petitions were referred back to his Majesties <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>Here <unclear>is news</unclear> that the Prince of Harcourt hath in the <pb n="3" />end agreed with Spain; so that all <unclear>Brisac</unclear> and alsatia except Philipsbourg, will be delivered into the hands of the Spaniards, of whom he hath received a good sum of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and his Brother are also in the <reg orig="Coutrt">Country</reg> taking the fresh <reg orig="aire">air</reg>, during the absence of the French <reg orig="Cort">Court</reg>, to whose return he thinks to remove out of France, if the <reg orig="mony">money</reg> be ready which he expects from them.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 11</i></head>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Upsal</reg></em> we are advertised thus. We can now in measure make you a <reg orig="requitall">requital</reg> of News, by telling you that his excellency hath concluded the Treaty here to a full and large satisfaction on both sides, and that within Fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after he began to Treat with those noble persons that were <reg orig="Commissionae">Commissioned</reg> for that purpose <!--??"by?"??-->her Majesty. We must confess it was beyond our expectation, when we considered the difficulties, the greatness of the business, the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> to obstruct it, and the <reg orig="aversness">averseness</reg> of divers great ones toward it. But the grand <reg orig="Chancelor">Chancellor</reg>, and his son Count <em>Erick</em>, who were the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Commissioners, came off with good respect to my Lord protector, and to my Lord Ambassador also himself, who with great wisdom and dexterity hath managed this business. The Queen also hath manifested incomparable affection to his Highness, and <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> to my Lord Ambassador, with whom she hath kept her word very <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg>. She told my Lord Ambassador, That she would have the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> to make the Alliance <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> with my Lord Protector, and in respect to him, and she said, because my Lord Ambassador treated with her like a <reg orig="Gentlemen">Gentleman</reg>, <i>avec toute la <unclear>francoise</unclear> et rondeur, et non pas comme un <unclear>Marchaud</unclear></i>, she did consent to more <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other could have obtained from her.</p>

<p>It hath pleased God to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> much mercy to us in our voyage hither, and in our business here, and we <pb n="4" />hope, to enjoy the like in our return, which will be now out of hand.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> May 6</i> thus</head>

<p>This Post brought Letters of great stirrings, and preparations in <em>Scotland</em> on both sides <em>Middleton</em>, and the rest of that Crew do all they can to increase their numbers, and Gen. <em>Monk</em> is as active in drawing together his forces towards the Mountains, and by keeping them there (<reg orig="til">till</reg> they have spent their provisions) they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> afterwards be forced to fight, or <i>lay down their Arms; In the <reg orig="meanwhile">mean while</reg> they keep their old trade of stealing down by parties, and doing what mischief they can, and some Country people run <reg orig="awey">away</reg> with them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and some, Towns are so base unto us, that they have made stay of English passengers that were but travelling through them. A party of ours met with about 30 Countrymen in a knot, going to the Enemy; After that they met with a party of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> horse, with whom they had a great fight, killed six, and took fifteen prisoners; the like was also done by another party. The Enemy stands not long to it, except he be in a place of great advantage.</i></p>

<p><i>This day we had further Intelligence from Sweden that that<!--repeated in original over a line break--> the Articles of peace betwixt England and her Majesty the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> are signed, and are to be brought hither to be Ratified by his Highness the Lord Protector. The Lord Ambassador from the K. of <em>Spain</em> had Audience by the Lord <em>Protector</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>The <em>English</em> Fleet are now at <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> in the Downs, both <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em> are very jealous what will be the ensuing design, and strong Guards are kept upon the Frontiers of both Kingdoms, a <em>Spanish</em> ship was lately cast away, wherein fifteen <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of Gold</i></p>

<p><i>This week was a groundless Report</i>, that Lieut. Col. <em>John </em><unclear><em>Lilicorne</em></unclear> was tried for his life again in <unclear><em>Jersey</em></unclear>, condemned, and Executed, or came to some other end, whereas the Letters say: that he is <reg orig="wel">well</reg> in health in the Castle.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> May 12.</i></head>

<p>This day there was a paper presented to his Highness the Lord Protector, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, the humble representations of the Justices of peace, chief Officers of Corporations, Ministers of the Gospel, and the Grand jury at the Assizes held at Sallop, wherein they declare, that they bless God that so suitable a Remedy (amongst so many changes) should be applied to our growing Maladies, by raising up his Highness, &amp;c.</p>

<p>This Day afforded memorable Intelligences from several places as that the <reg orig="tituler">titular</reg> King of <em>Scots</em> is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> fallen out with Prince <em>Rupert</em>, for selling the Guns belonging to the great ship called the <em>Swallow</em>, <reg orig="ther">there</reg> was in her fifty brass <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of, Ordinance; the <reg orig="tituler">titular</reg> King of the Scots was seldom seen so much out of his own temper, which it is <reg orig="thougt">thought</reg> would have declared <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> by some effects, had not the certain Mews of the peace betwixt <em>England </em>and, and<!--and repeated here--> <em>Holland</em> made them shake hands. Two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> who had a long time exercised their <reg orig="pyracy">piracy</reg> about the Bay of Biscay, having sent their men on <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg> for fresh meat, had their men <reg orig="intrapped">entrapped</reg>; and the two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> were taken by the Men of war of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Dukes">Duke's</reg> Letters to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty.</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>Having long attended with patience; and not finding <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> either in the conduct of my present life, or in the memory of my forpast-time, which might justly cast me into a worse condition, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the rest of your Subjects. Nevertheless (Sir) your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> will doth so regulate mine, that had it not been for necessity the strongest master of all. I had not at this season made further addresses to your Majesty <pb n="6" />, for that which I held so well bestowed in your service <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> I and every man drives at his own ends, it hath taught me a lesson, that I live not in an Age wherein I shall be fed with vanity. Yet I so not withal suppose your Majesty doth so slightly esteem of my service, as not to make any further use of me, nor do I find myself so <reg orig="unusefull">unuseful</reg> as to be forced instead of better <reg orig="imployments">employments</reg>, only to let you known what News is stirring, &amp; to give you an account of ordinary <reg orig="rumors">rumours</reg>; I must humbly beseech your Majesty to suffer me to <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in this <reg orig="oppiniod">opinion</reg>, I have of myself, and however it happen (Sir) or how badly soever I be <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg>, I am determined to continue resolute in well-doing; And your Majesty may be assured, that neither time, which affordeth occasions to most miserable to raise their fortunes, not often favouring their resentments, no necessity which causeth their actions to seem Just, shall ever transport me from remaining with the same affection I ever have done to be.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday May 13.</i></head>

<p>This day we understood that about twenty Pinks and small ships are newly come into the River of Thames, with several sorts of <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>, we have also a great number of Merchant men, going out some for the Canaries, others for <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> and other parts. <reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> we hear that our fleet keep their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs, and the Dutch <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> near the Texel. The brest men of War have done some late prejudice to us in the West, they rage exceedingly now, for that they think <reg orig="there">their</reg> time is short, we hear that a squadron of our Fleet are to sail Northward, to prevent the coming over into Scotland to the enemy, any Arms, Ammunition or Forces.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>Admiral <em>Van-Trump</em> is yet with his squadron about the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>, you will shortly hear o f some design, that the gallant Fleets of these high and considerable <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, will sail upon some honourable action.</p>

<p>By Letters from Newcastle we are advertised, that a great fleet of Colliers, are laden coming for London.</p>

<p>The last Letters from Paris say, that <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and the Duke of York are yet there, the news of the peace of Holland makes their friends backward in supplying the <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever they were; neither the difference between <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and Rupert is not taken up yet; Cardinal <unclear>Retz</unclear> remaineth a close prisoner at Natz, we hear of an English Merchant ship cast away by a storm <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Sicilia.</p>

<p>There came to my hands this day a copy of the last <reg orig="wil">will</reg> and testament of <reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. Col. <em>John Lilburn</em>: The substance whereof take as follows.</p>

<p>In the name of God, Amen. I John Lilburn of London Gent. Being aged 39 <reg orig="yeers">years</reg>, now in the evening of my life do here ordain this to be my last will and testament, being in perfect remembrance, that no contention or strife may <unclear><!--4 characters--></unclear> after my decease, concerning my estate, in manner and form following.</p>

<p>Inprimis, my I bequeath my soul to the hands of the almighty, in whom I have put my trust, hoping by the merits of Christ <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, my only Lord and Saviour, that I shall be saved from <reg orig="hel">hell</reg> and damnation. And that I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <reg orig="wrapt">wrapped</reg> up unto the third heaven, prepared for all true believers.</p>

<p>And for my body, in regard it hath <reg orig="indured">endured</reg> a fiery trial, and hath been patient and long suffering, It is my desire my friend Cornelius may have the burial thereof.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>