<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn05">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 5</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The great strength of the Highlanders, how they increase in their Levies, the young Marquis of <em>Montross</em> and <em>Huntley</em> being <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with them. Also how seventeen Dutch ships are arrived in <em>Scotland</em> with sixteen hundred <reg orig="Forraigners">Foreigners</reg>, two hundred Horse, and store of Arms and Ammunition. The humble <reg orig="Adress">Address</reg> of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army to his Highness the Lord Protector: Also a Letter from the Earl of <em>Gelncarn</em> to the Governor of <em>Badgenoth</em> Castle, and his answer thereunto; The safe arrival of ten Merchant ships from Dunkirk to Gottenburgh, laden with divers rich commodities. With variety of other intelligence from all parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday January 17.</em> to <em>Tuesday January 24.</em> 1653</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Begining Tuesday January the 17.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from, Scotland we are advertised, That the Highlanders increase in their Levies, and confirm, that the young Marquis of <em>Montress</em> and <em>Huntley</em> are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with them. Also we received a Letter from <em>Aberdeen</em> that faith, that 17 Dutch ships are arrived in <em>Scotland</em> with 1500 <reg orig="Forraigners">Foreigners</reg>, two hundred horse, and store of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>From Milan thus: <i> The Marquis of <unclear>Caratina</unclear> our Governor is gone from hence to Uercel, and from thence to Trin, as also all the high Officers who were all come to this City to pass the time of the Truce, and are all come to the Army to observe the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> march.</i></p>

<head level="3">By Letters from <em>Holland</em> as followeth,</head>

<p> Here hath again been a great loss to this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, both by fire and water, and all occasioned by a great storm or wind last Tuesday, all day and all night. But the first cause is doubtless the wrath of God against this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which is so evident that truly <reg orig="every body">everybody</reg> feels it, and few that have any grace but <reg orig="wil">will</reg> confess it also: But are <reg orig="stil">still</reg> as ignorant how to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg> this anger of the Lord, as if they never had had <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Word amongst them. It is true, the common <reg orig="sinnes">sins</reg> of Pride, Whoredom, Drunkenness, and Excess, are generally <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out against, as the cause of all our miseries, and doubtless these sins do much provoke the Lord, being come to so great a height in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: But these <reg orig="sinns">sins</reg> are too common to all Nations, especially in prosperity, and therefore the wiser sort do find fault with one another, <em>Adam</em> and <em>Eve</em>-like, but very few that lay these things to heart, so as to say, this sin of mine is a cause, and so forsake the same.</p>

<p>The last news from <em>Warsovia</em> import, that the King with all his Army consisting of about eighty thousand men Horse and Foot, was upon their March to encounter the Tartars, and <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together, but remain asunder, being in two distinct bodies: By some prisoners lately brought to his Majesty, we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that the General of the Cossacks hath made a particular Treaty with the <reg orig="Karn">Kahn</reg> of the Tartars, which if true will exclude him from making any peace or accommodation with the Crown of <em>Poland</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday Jan. 18.</i></head>

<p>From Regensburgh thus: The <em>Diet</em> is not yet concluded, there being new differences <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> between the Prince Elector<pb n="2" />, and his <reg orig="Vncle">Uncle</reg> the Duke of <em>Simmeren</em>, about the enjoying of some Land which each other pretended to be his. Some Commissioners are appointed to examine the matter, and so to report it: as also some differences between the Landgraves William, and the Earnest of Haffia.</p>

<p>From <em>Dusseldorf</em> we are advertised thus: The duke of <em>Newburgh</em> is still at Mulheim, being not well pleased with the Assembly met in this City, by reason that they have denied him the sums of money which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> demanded of them.</p>

<p>The difference between the City of <em>Cullen</em> and their Elector is <reg orig="neer">near</reg> agreed, he having set at liberty all the Barges and Boats which by his order had been stopped at the <em>Bonna</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Italie">Italy</reg></em> and parts adjacent came information thus: The Infanta Maria of Saucy is here at Rome, but as yet <em>incognito</em>; she intends to remain here for some time.</p>

<p>The Pope hath also given several <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg>, and other good Benefices to <reg orig="som">some</reg> of his <reg orig="domestique">domestic</reg> Servants, and appointed new <reg orig="Nuntioes">Nuncios</reg> to go into several places of those parts.</p>

<p>From Genoa thus: <i>We hear from Madrid, that an Express was come to the Court to inform his Majesty that there was landed at Coronna in Galazia, three thousand Irish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were to Winter Quarters, which doth something startle the Portugals, who made a <reg orig="shew">show</reg> as is they would have besieged Cindad Rodrigo. The Duke of Tursie is also expected at Barulona with four Galleys, who are to bring good store of Ammunition and Moneys for the payment of the Garrison: One of the Spanish Galleys hath lately taken a very rich prize upon the French, being a ship bound for Marscillis.</i></p>

<p>Concerning our Fleet by Letters from Portsmouth thus, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Blake</em> and General <em>Monk</em> being now at London, General <em>Pen</em> rides as Admiral of the Fleet without St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em> point, three Leagues from Portsmouth, with forty <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of gallant ships ready upon any advice of the Dutch ships coming out to Sea: Some part of them are already sent out to ply between this place and the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, and over upon the coast of France, to suppress the Brest and Dutch Pickeroons, who of late begin to be strong, and have done much harm upon the Western Coast.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday Jan. 19.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Lime</em> we are advertised by a Barque that came from <em><reg orig="Brittannia">Britannia</reg></em>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch Pickerooneer <em>Vshant</em>, gave him chase, and followed so close, that he forced him to run on ground on the hither side of the Bay of Camaret, and by reason of his shooting hard at him, made the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to come down to the Water side; it happened that some shot did make execution on the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, there being four killed and wounded; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> being all <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg> thereby could not fetch her off; but ours put to Sea again, to <reg orig="cleare">clear</reg> from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Letters from Scotland we received information to this effects.</p>

<p>The Highlanders continue their stealing, and plundering of their own <reg orig="Countreymen">Countrymen</reg> that will not rise with them, or pay the Contribution-Money that they lay upon them, though I am confident many have not <reg orig="wherewithall">wherewithal</reg> to subsist, paying likewise their <reg orig="Assessements">Assessments</reg> for the maintenance of the English Army; but when Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em>, Commissary General <em>Whalley's</em> Regiment of Horse, with Sir <em>William Constables</em> Regiment of Foot, which we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> are upon their march are come in to us, we doubt not but to send this Heathenish and plundering Enemy so far <reg orig="backe">back</reg> into the Highlands, as that they shall not dare to approach the Lowlands, whereby to so the Inhabitants any considerable hurt: And how the Highlanders are able to keep and horse foot, <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be imagined, all their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> being upon <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> with the Dutch for Money and Arms; but a peace with Holland, (which we hear is in a very probable way for a very speedy conclusion) disperses them to their several mountainous habitations, without ever drawing the sword against them; and then the Lords and Chieftains amongst them, may expect a liberal reward of Justice for doing <pb n="4" />their Master such rebellious service, which hath been, and is destructive to the generality of Scotland, that a few months continuance will bring them to the sad condition of the Irish, that have been forced to eat the <reg orig="corps">corpses</reg> of their deceased Friends after many days interment; yet are not the people of Scotland very much to be pitied, in regard they will <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> give notice to any of our Garrisons, when any party of the Enemy marches through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might be the better preserved from their violences and cruelty, choosing rather to be willingly destroyed by them, then be treacherous, as they call it, to their own <reg orig="Countrey-men">Countrymen</reg>.</p>

<p>Further by Letters from Scotland came as followeth, A Letter from the Earl of Glencarn to the Governor of Badgenorth Castle, and his answer thereunto. With a Letter from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, to the Gentlemen of Badgenorth.</p>

<p>Sir, I have sent a Letter of yours directed to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenorth</em>, wherein you have expressed so much fidelity to your unjust Masters, from whom you are trusted, that it makes me conceive if those principles of yours were rightly founded upon the warrantable grounds of legality, you might yet redeem your former failings, and those principles of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> which are now darkened in you, being out of their proper channel, may shine eminently when unclouded from under those fatal ways and snares wherein many gallant spirits are <reg orig="insnared">ensnared</reg>. Thus much I have conceived it fit to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> you, that I might undeceive in <reg orig="som">some</reg> opinions, upon which I find you ground your arguments in your Letters to the Gentlemen of Badgenorth &amp;c. I have given you this right view of the present condition of affairs, because I have been informed of your gallantry, that when you reckon betwixt God and you alone, and deals impartially with <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg>, you may do <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> that right to <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> that <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> God hath given you in the most approved way by him, wherein if you find I can serve you may freely command your friend and servant</p>

<p><i>January 1.1653. Glencairn</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Friday Jan 21.</i></head>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is not yet arrived, but is expected here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>; there is a strong report that this Prince intends to match with one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces, but many are of a contrary opinion, which is truest, will be known very shortly.</p>

<p>The Lord Chancellor hath been this week at the Parliament, to have a <reg orig="Supersedeas">Supersedes</reg> to the passing the Declaration which is drawn up against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, the same to continue for six weeks.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> doth still lie a close prisoner, there being little hopes as yet of any <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>, his Antagonist the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> being very obstinate in the demand <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath made so many times, that he should resign his <reg orig="Coadjutership">Coadjudorship</reg> of Paris, and to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> him the more, there is offered him the two rich <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg> of S. <em>Denis</em> and <em>Cluni</em>, which offer he will by no means accept.</p>

<p>There are yet come no Letters from Holland, since the Dutch Deputies were come back there; but private Letters from thence dated Friday last, say, that the States were very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in preparing a sudden Dispatch for their Answer, which report tends probably to peace (in their judgement) their Deputy Monsieur <em>Borrel</em> in France gives out report there, that the States have agreed to the English offers for peace.</p>

<p>From Dartmouth, <reg orig="Iann">Jan</reg>. 12. thus: The Hector hath sent in a ship hither, which hath in her 3000. Cheeses. The ship is of Amsterdam, and took in her lading at the Elve. There is a private Man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> hath brought in a ship Rotterdam, laden with Herrings and Holland cheeses, and about ten <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of Pepper, and some Cloves.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday Jan.21.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother is by on Order of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, removed back from the Tower to Newgate.</p>

<p>By Letters from on <reg orig="boord">board</reg> the Swift-Sure, dated the 13 of January 1653. was certified the Examinations of some <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> Ships that came in to find Market for Deals, Pitch, Tar, Iron, Steel, and other commodities, &amp;c.</p>

<p>The Officers from the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Garrisons and Regiments, are very unanimous in signing the said Address which is from most parts of England already sent up to his Highness, and the rest <reg orig="neere">near</reg> finished, as is expressed by Letters from their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Quarters.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dublin</em> in <em>Ireland</em>, was this day certified, That <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg>-General Fleetwood and the Commissioners, are at <em>Dublin</em>, all is quiet there, and content at the New Government in <em>England</em>, and satisfied in it. That the Lord <em>Musgrove</em> is to be tried the beginning of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>; That all is very quiet in <em>Ireland</em>, save some small parties of the Tories, which are chiefly about the Country of <em>Carlow</em>, where they lately <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> upon, and wounded <reg orig="som">some</reg> of the Surveyors, and do <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> rob and steal where they dare venture, and fly away <reg orig="againe">again</reg> presently.</p>

<p>An Ambassador from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> was this day to congratulate His Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>His Highness and also the Council, were this upon matters of great concernment.</p>

<p>From <em>Scilly Jan. 2.</em> thus. The <em>Elias</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> is come into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, and brought us six months pay which we were in arrears, other news, all being quiet, this place affords not any.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>This day <reg orig="wee">we</reg> received intelligence by a ship that came from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, (and also divers other ships from Dunkirk) that ten of our Merchant men are come safely to <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, laden with all Eastern commodities, and five of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> were convoy to them, who have also homewards bound made several prizes upon the coast of Norway, which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in England very shortly.</p>

<p>All persons are desired to take notice <reg orig="ahat">that</reg> the Committee for Claims for Lands in Ireland, have appointed Thursday the <reg orig="nineth">ninth</reg> of February 1653. for Adventurers to draw lots at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> hall London, for <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>, and that all persons who intend then to draw lots, do before that day pay their pence.</p>

<p><i>William Tibbs</i></p>

<p>From Milford Haven January 18. we received intelligence, That some Vessels that come lately from Ireland brings <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, that all things there are very peaceable, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Tories sometimes in <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> parties do much mischief, endeavouring to make up a body of an Army, and of late some encounter was between a party of ours and them, but they were forced back again into the Bogs, their great Sanctuary, with some loss. The Plague is not yet ceased but remaineth in many parts, but not so violent as formerly.</p>

<p><i>This is Extracted out of the Original papers, and licensed according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>T. Lock</em>, living in Seacole-Lane, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the sign of S. <em>George.</em></p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>