<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn13">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 13</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The full particulars of of<!--repetition present in original--> a great fight in Scotland, A List of the names of the prisoners taken, with the number killed and taken, and the particular loss on both sides. The landing of a great store of Arms and Ammunition in Scotland and the <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> of three thousand Loughaber men more to <em>Gen. Middleton</em>. Also, the great hurt and spoil done by the Scottish party in Cumberland, and other places upon the borders of England. The advancing of <em>General Monk</em> into Leith. The coming in of a rich ship laden with <reg orig="foure">four</reg> chests of silver, besides other rich commodities of great value. With the last Letters from Ireland, and other parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> April 24. to <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> May 1. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 24.</i></head>

<p>By Letters this day from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, we are certified, that there is great store of Arms and Ammunition landed there for the enemy, who now boast that they are about four of 5 thousand Horse and Foot in sutherland, well <unclear>armed</unclear> <unclear><!--remainder of paragraph, 1 or 2 lines--></unclear></p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 25.</i></head>

<p>This day the Proclamation for peace was <reg orig="Proclamed">Proclaimed</reg> by 12 Trumpets, and 4 Heralds at Arms, first at Whitehall before his Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Concil">Council</reg> (both Courts being full of people)</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector</head>

<head level="3">A Proclamation of the peace made between this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and that of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> provinces of the Netherlands.</head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. Considering how necessary it is not only to preserve peace and Quiet at home, but as far as in him lies, to live in Amity and friendship with his neighbours, hath by the blessing of God, with the advice of his Council, made and concluded a peace, <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg> and Confederation to continue for ever, between this Commonwealth of the one part, and of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> provinces of the Low Countries of the other part; their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, <reg orig="Dominione">Dominion</reg>, <reg orig="Teritories">Territories</reg>, Places and people, by Sea, Land, fresh waters and elsewhere. By the which peace it is agreed, that all Enmity, Hostility, Discord and War between the said Commonwealths, their people and Subjects shall cease, and all injuries and wrongs whatsoever done since the 18 &amp; 23. of <em>May</em>, One thousand six hundred fifty two, shall cease and be forgotten, except such Depredations as shall be committed by either side in these Seas after twelve days, from the date of these presents, &amp;c. For want of room, I refer you to the printed copy for the rest.</p>

<p>This day are come out new farthings, weighing a quarter of and ounce fine pewter, which is but the price of new pewter; that so the people may never hereafter fear to loose much by them; with the Harp of one side, and a Crosse on the other, with T.K. above it.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 26.</i></head>

<p>This day passed an Ordinance of pardon and Grace to the people of Scotland after May 1654. except the persons following, and their estates.</p>

<p><em>Henrietta Maria</em>, late Queen. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> her son. <em>James Stuart</em> her son. <em>James</em> late Duke <em>Hamilton</em>. <em>William</em> late Duke <em>Hamilton</em>. Earl <em>Crawford Linsey</em>. Earl <em>Calender</em>. Earl <em>Marshal</em>. Earl <em>Kelly</em>. Earl <em>Lauderdale</em>. Earl <em>London</em>. Earl <em>Seaforth</em>. Earl <em>Athol</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Lord <em>Lorn</em>, Lord <em>Machlin</em>, Lord <em>Montgomery</em>, Lord <em>Spynie</em>, Lord <em>Crunston</em>, Major Gen. <em>Dalyel</em>, Lieut. Gen <em>Middleton</em>, Viscount <em>Newburgh</em>, Lord <em>Bargany</em>, Sir <em>Tho. Thomson</em>, Laird of <em>Womat</em>, Laird <em>Napier</em>, Earl of <em>Glencahn</em>. Divers others are fined to pay certain sums of moneys, <em>David Leshly</em> 4000 li. Marquis <em>Douglas</em>, 100 l. and several other sums.</p>

<p><i>A <reg orig="yeerly">yearly</reg> allowance given to their wives and children out of their <reg orig="Husbands">Husband's</reg> and <reg orig="fathers">father's</reg> estates</i></p>

<p>400 l. sterling to <em>Anne</em> Duke <em><reg orig="Hamiltons">Hamilton's</reg></em> daughter, paying 20 pound a <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> to the Lord Protector, and his successors.</p>

<p>Two hundred pound to her sister <em>Susan</em>, paying ten pound to his <reg orig="Highnessr">Highness</reg></p>

<p>Four hundred pound to <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> <em>Hamilton</em>, paying twenty pound.</p>

<p>Four hundred pound to Countess of <em>Craford</em>, paying twenty pound.</p>

<p>Four hundred pound to Countess <em>Lowdone</em>, paying twenty pound.</p>

<p>Countess of <em>Callender</em> her <reg orig="Joynture">Jointure</reg>, conveyed from her former Husband Earl of <em>Dunfermlin</em>:</p>

<p>200 l. to <em> Mary <reg orig="Eaal">Earl</reg> <reg orig="Marshals">Marshal's</reg></em> daughter, 150 l. on her three Sisters, paying 32 l. 10s.</p>

<p>300 l. to the countess of <em>Louderdale</em> paying 15 l.</p>

<p>200 l. to Lady cranston Paying 10 l.</p>

<p>250 l. to Lady <em>Bargany</em>, paying 12 l. 10 s.</p>

<p>120 l. to Lady <em>Thomson</em>, paying 6 l.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 27</i></head>

<p><i>From Upsal in Sweden, April 26</i>. I begin now to believe, that we hall receive a dispatch; and though in respect of some things they offer, we seem to be at some distance; yet I have such a <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the noble Lady will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> out such an expedient, that satisfaction will be amply given to both Nations. And this to be as the last act of her <reg orig="reigne">reign</reg>; which in my poor <reg orig="judgemen">judgement</reg> is a great pity, for certainly she is as accomplished a Princess, as ever had the honour of swaying a <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>; and though the French, being <reg orig="riged">rigged</reg> to their <reg orig="falique">phallic</reg> laws, will not permit the <reg orig="distaffe">distaff</reg> to intermeddle with a Crown; yet they had such a Virgin to rule amongst them, they would hereafter blot out such a law out of their records, as being mightily prejudicial to their advantage. on Thursday last, my Lord Ambassador and Count <em>Erick</em> had a meeting to debate upon the Articles of union. at which time Count Erick <reg orig="rendred">rendered</reg> several Article on the behalf of Sweden, most of which were the same my Lord First gave in; but <reg orig="soue">some</reg> did differ exceedingly.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Four Propositions of the Queen to the Prince.</i></head>

<p>1. she <reg orig="wil">will</reg> retain the best part of the Kingdom and the Customs to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>.</p>

<p>2. She will be no subject, but free of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> without <reg orig="Controll">Control</reg>.</p>

<p>3. She will <reg orig="Travil">Travel</reg> whither she pleaseth.</p>

<p>4. She will not revoke those Gifts of hers, which are <em>Predia Corone</em>, and were by her given, out of Favour, to Courtiers.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Prince his reply</i></head>

<p>1. He <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not be a King without a Kingdom, or at <pb n="4" />least without the better part of it.</p>

<p>2. He <reg orig="wil">will</reg> have no <reg orig="Rivall">Rival</reg>, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> she a Superior.</p>

<p>3. He will not hazard himself about her <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> abroad.</p>

<p>4. He will not be without a Revenue sufficient both for war and peace.</p>

<head level="3">A List of Dutch prizes lately come in.</head>

<p>A French vessel with 25 lasts of pitch and Tar in her, taken by the Assurance <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>A ship of Amsterdam of 200 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, <reg orig="rnd">and</reg> 5 Guns, taken by the Assurance and Amity.</p>

<p>Two more; one with Pitch, Linseed, and Deal-Boards belonging to <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>; the other a French ship taken by the Pearl.</p>

<p>Another vessel belonging to Flushing, with 26 Cases of Glass, <reg orig="trken">taken</reg> by the Draee <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>Also a small Pinck of Flushing, laden with wines from Bordeaux taken by the Non Such <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>A Private man of War, taken <reg orig="bo">by</reg> the Maremaid about Flamborough head.</p>

<p>The taking of the east-Indy ship mentioned in our last to be taken from the Dutch, is confirmed. she was of 800 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, 4 Chests of silver, and well laden with other Commodities.</p>


<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, we are advertised, that our small Garrisons <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Sterling have fallen with success into the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, and brought away divers prisoners, and amongst the rest a party from <unclear>Buchannon</unclear> marched into the parish of Strablain, where Capt. Cunningham and Capt. Edmiston were levying of horse and foot, took Capt. Cunningham, and very narrowly <reg orig="mist">missed</reg> cap. Edmiston.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>We received certain intelligence this day from Flanders that <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of Cullen, and the Arch Duke Leopoldus, have had a meeting at Louvain, tarrying there about two days; the Arch Duke at his departure, <unclear>presenting</unclear> him with some rich <reg orig="Tapistry">Tapestry</reg>, and four of his best horses. We have by Letters from Sedan, that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <unclear>Jamets</unclear> having made a design with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Mouton to beat up the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> quarters at Witton in the Province of <reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg>, they carried their work on so gallantly, that the several Troops there quartered, were for the most part slain, and the rest taken prisoners with a Company of Spanish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, who were left for the guard of that Town.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday April 28.</i></head>

<p>This day by letters from <em>Dalkeith</em> we are advertised, that col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched from <em>Dingwel</em> to <em>Tain</em>, with all his brigade. Yesterday there marched 1000. foot over the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> above <unclear><em>Brabas</em></unclear> towards <em>Sutherland</em>, which its supposed are the <em>Loughaber</em> men, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> add to the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> strength, which was before 4000. horse and foot. There was a quarrel between Sir <em>George Monroe</em> and the E. of <em>Glencarn</em>, for <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> of, and abusing the Laird of <em>Fowlis</em> (<em><reg orig="Monroes">Monroe's</reg></em> brother) who was extremely abused by them, which rose so high, that they appointed to Fight a combat, and accordingly on the last <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day in the morning they mounted and rid to the place appointed, and because <em>Monroe</em> would fight on Horseback, he took his pistols with him, but <em>Glencairn</em> bid him put away his pistols and they would Fight only on Horseback with their swords. in which Combat <em>Monro</em> had his right hand almost cut off and a cut in the forehead: <em>Glencairn</em> was likewise cut in the head. There was also a quarrel between <em>Athol</em> and <em>Glengary</em> about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> of place, and a field appointed, but the business was taken up by the commanders.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>On the 21 of this instant Month <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> an express at the Hague, with Letters from our Lords Ambassadors in England to the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, wherein they advise that the Peace was <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> finished and concluded, that the business of <em>Denmark</em> was determined, and the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> to be responsible for One hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling; That the ships detained in the Sound; should be restored within Fourteen days after that those should <reg orig="arive">arrive</reg> there who were to receive them; and that the damage shall be appraised by the First of May, by Four persons. upon this good News the States of Holland adjourned yesterday; leaving their Order and consent with the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> to <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> the Ratification, A few days after the Articles of the Treaty of peace signed on both sides, being sent over two <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> by two of the Gentlemen of the Lords Ambassadors, who arrived at the Hague, to the great contentment and joy of all the honest men in these parts. which were no sooner read, but presently Ratified by the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and the Ratification sent <reg orig="a way">away</reg> for England immediately. So that now we no longer doubt of this blessed Peace, which hath kept us in <reg orig="suspence">suspense</reg> thus long together, however our <reg orig="Critticks">Critics</reg> will not pardon the remissness of our Governors, for making such slow preparations. when their <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> arm so vigorously.</p>

<p>The Lieut. <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> Opdam is at present at the Hague, with the vice <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> Witte Wittesen, Ruyter, and John Everrson, with several other Sea-Captains, who have received order from the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> to furnish the ships with all things necessary with all speed, The <reg orig="Randexvoux">Rendezvous</reg> for the Merchants ships is to be at Goree; and no ship is to be suffered to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Sea till the peace be published: and much variety of opinions here passeth upon the great preparations of the English and the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> they have in hand with their great Fleet.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday April 29.</i></head>

<p>This day by Letters from <em>Scotland</em>, we received intelligence, that there hath been a great fight between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Scottish</em> Army, the particulars are thus.</p>

<p>A party of the enemy commanded by Captain <unclear><em>Irwin</em></unclear>, got Westward, and came upon the borders of <em>England</em> in <em>Cumberland</em>, and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> and spoiled all they could meet with, and carried away diverse prisoners. But as they were marching along to do some further mischief, a party of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> met with them, who presently fell upon them, rescued the prisoners they had taken, and killed and wounded many, and at last forced them to fly back to the place where their whole body lay.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> with all his whole body had got as <reg orig="neer">near</reg> as possibly he could to force them to fight: which the Enemy perceiving, and seeing no ways to escape, mustered up all their whole strength both horse and foot into several parties and at last the both <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg>: the dispute was very hot for a long time, but at last ours had the better of them. They give out, that they have routed us, and took many of our men prisoners, and killed <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em>, but as yet we hear no such thing.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>The most <reg orig="easie">easy</reg>, cheap, certain, and speedy way of curing the <em>French Pox</em>, and <em>Running of the <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear></em>, without confining the patient, either to keeping of house, or extremity of fluxing <reg orig="physick">physic</reg>; and without leaving the least <reg orig="symptome">symptom</reg> of the Disease behind, either inward by pains, or outward by pustules, is carefully performed,</i></p>

<p><i>By the Physician at the tiled <reg orig="porcht">porched</reg> house in Maiden head Court in Aldergate street, over against <em>Peterhouse</em></i></p>

<p>He is to be spoken with constantly in the forenoon, between eight and twelve.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>