<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn09">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 9</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The landing of an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> for Lord <em>Williamson</em> from Denmark with <reg orig="ful">full</reg> power to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> and conclude a peace betwixt both nations. The whole manner of the Treaty, and the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech to his highness the Lord protector in the Banqueting house at Whitehall. The <reg orig="imbarquing">embarking</reg> of the Lord <em>Cromwell</em>, and his great deliverance out of the mighty storm that arose as he were going for Ireland. The great <reg orig="spoile">spoil</reg> of the Tories, and their strength. With several other intelligence from <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 7. to <em>Tuesday</em> March 14.</head>
<hr />

<p>Peace is a thing much desired of almost all people, <i>Lord grant a good issue of the Treaty</i>: the Dutch Ambassadors being shortly to have their audience, and other Ambassadors also coming from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <em>Princes</em>: The great room at the <em>Banqueting house</em> at <em>Whitehall</em> is ordered to be made ready, and is to be hung with Hangings. And what shall one answer the Ambassadors and Messengers of the Nation? Surely the Lord <em>Protector</em> hath a sweet <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters, possibly more than one word--></unclear> God. <em> </em><i>That the Lord hath founded <em>Zion</em>, and<em> </em><unclear><!--whole line is unclear--></unclear></i></p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>This day, the three Lord Ambassadors from the States General of the united Provinces, <em>viz.</em> the Lord <em>Beverling</em>, the Lord <em>Newport</em>, and the Lord <em>Youngstal</em>, passed through the Cities of London and Westminster, to Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his house in the Palace yard at Westminster in his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness'</reg> Coach, with Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Master of<em> </em>the Ceremonies, and Mr. <em>Claypool</em>, Gentleman of the Horse, and divers other Gentlemen, and his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness'</reg> footmen attending on both sides of the Coach, and also the Coaches and Gentlemen of the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, and the Resident of the King of <em>France</em>, and above fifty coaches more of divers of the English Nobility and Gentry, whereof above twenty of the said coaches were with six horses, and <reg orig="neere">near</reg> twenty of them with four horses <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>, and the rest two good horses and furniture; and as soon as they alighted, in the palace yard, they were saluted with a noise of Trumpets.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Holland thus</i></head>

<p>The Letters from <em>Holland</em> say, that their judgement there is, that the Treaty of peace between the two Nations is so far advanced, that there is very few do make any doubt of it, since all the Provinces sent their consent thereunto, to the Lords the States General, amongst whom those of <reg orig="groning">groningen</reg> were the last; and so the Ratification by the States was then sent to the Lord <em>Beverling</em> to England, and upon his answer to the States, Ambassadors were chosen to go to England to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the peace, and accordingly the Lords <em>Newport</em> and <em>Youngstall</em> were Commissionated, there were two others chosen, but they excused; and after them one <em>Young</em>, who because of much business and other reasons, had leave to stay, at least for a time, and power was given to the Lords <em>Beverling, Newport</em>, and <em>Youngstall</em>, to conclude and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the peace with England.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>His Highness appointed that the Lords Ambassadors from the States General of the united Provinces should have <reg orig="publique">public</reg> audience on the morrow; and Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em> Mr. of the Ceremonies, had orders to attend their Lordships to the Banqueting house at Whitehall accordingly.</p>

<p>This day the Lords Ambassadors from the States of the seven <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of <em>Holland, Zealand,</em> &amp;c. had audience by his Highness the Lord Protector in the Banqueting house at Whitehall, which was hung with extraordinary rich hangings, and divers Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, Officers of the Army, and thousands of people in the said room present, and all the Galleries round the room full of people, besides many in the courts and other places about, that could not get up.</p>

<p>They were fetched from their lodging in the palace yard at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em>, by Sir Oliver <em>Flemming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, and with him two of the Lords of the Council, <em>Strickland</em> and <em>Jones</em>, who were all three with the Ambassadors brought in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coach, and his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> footmen, besides the <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassadors'</reg> footmen, to run by the Coach and after the said Coach followed a great many Coaches, belonging to several Lords, and others, most with six horses, in which rid several persons of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, and the Gentlemen belonging to the Ambassadors.</p>

<p>First, his <reg orig="highnesse">highness</reg> the Lord protector came into the <reg orig="Bankqueting">Banqueting</reg> house, with the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and M. <em>Thurlos</em> Secretary of State, and Mr. <em>Claypole</em> Gentleman of the Horse; at whose coming in, all the people put off their hats and stood bare, and his highness put off his hat to the people; and went up to the Chair, but did not sit down in it at all, all the while, neither before, at, nor after the audience; his highness stood on the left side of the <reg orig="Chaire">Chair</reg>, with his hat on and the Lords of the Council, and M. <em>Secretary</em> <pb n="3" />and M. <em>Claypole</em> were within the Rails, some on the one side, and some on the other, all of them bare all the while. In this Equipage his <reg orig="highnesse">highness</reg> waited a short time for the reception of the Ambassadors, and a lane was made for the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> to come up to his <reg orig="highnesse">highness</reg> from the one end of the room to the other.</p>

<p>So soon as the Ambassadors were come into the room, they put off their hats to salute His Highness, and again two or three times as they came <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> to his Highness; and when they came up to the place where the Chairs, Stools and Carpets were, where his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> was, with the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and after a low salute of his Highness, and the Lords Ambassadors each to other, the <em>Lord Protector</em> put on his hat, and the Ambassadors put on theirs also; and the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and all others being bare, his Highness and the Ambassadors all stood up.</p>

<p>Then the Lord <em>Youngstall</em> made a Speech to his Highness, and his Highness made presently another Speech to the Ambassadors, often in both their Speeches putting off their hats to salute each other.</p>

<head level="2"><i>The <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech.</i></head>

<p><i>May it please your Highness.</i></p>

<p>The business of our coming here, is, To renew the old Friendship, which hath been for many <reg orig="yeers">years</reg>, and to make and settle a more firm peace and <reg orig="aliance">alliance</reg> than ever heretofore; and that to this purpose Our Superiors, the Lords the States of the united <pb n="4" /><em>Provinces</em> of the Netherlands do all of them agree and consent.</p>

<p>Afterwards his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Ambassadors saluted each other, and the Ambassadors turned three times to salute his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> also staying for that purpose saluted them, and they being gone down, his Highness, with the Lords of the Council, returned also by the <reg orig="privie">privy</reg> <reg orig="doore">door</reg>, through which he had come thither.</p>

<p>The Lords Ambassadors of the United Provinces of <em>Holland</em> say, that if the Articles can be engrossed in a day, they are ready to sign the Ratification of the peace; And likewise Commissioners are appointed by his Highness the Lord Protector for a speedy dispatch with them.</p>

<p>From <em>Leith</em> thus. <i>The Lord <em>Athol</em>, the Lord <em>Bruce</em>. and others have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> what forces they can get together, and are marching Northwards, to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with Glencarn, Kenmore, Glencary, and the rest, upon whose conjunction they threaten to be revenged of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan for the last rent, and perhaps he may make them amends with such another. <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> foot are much discontented, and leave him daily, complaining much of the cowardice of their horse, so that now they have few foot but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Runagadoes from the Lowlands. They have taken off the Root from the Garrison of Weems, and intend now to keep no Garrisons, but run the same courses that Montross did, and keep their Ammunition in woods, or little villages in the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>We hear there is an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> landed from Denmark to make application to his <em><reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg></em> upon the success of the Dutch Treaty, his name is <em>Williamson</em>. Of which I shall give you a further account in my next.</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>On Thursday <em>March 2.</em> a <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <unclear>Minister out of</unclear> <em>Flanders</em> from the Arch-Duke <em>Leopoldus</em> had audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, with some of the Aldermen and Recorder, on behalf of the City and the Magistrates of the City of <em>Westminster</em>, this day according to order, attended his Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, upon the business of a Corporation to be granted to the City of <em>Westminster</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Chester</em> we are informed, that on Wednesday the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> took ship for <em>Ireland</em>, at the point of Air; we hear that he is not got over as yet, because there fell out very violent storms and a great deal of tempestuous weather presently after his <reg orig="imbarquing">embarking</reg>, insomuch that the Main Topmast of the ship was taken down.</p>

<p>From <em>Upsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, thus. Our affairs here have had a little pause, and are at a stand; The Lord Chancellor hath been very much indisposed in his health, but now he is abroad again. The Treaty goes on, and this afternoon my Lord Ambassador and he have had a meeting concerning it, we cannot but believe but we shall have a very good issue; yet they are a little stumbled here at our detention of their ships, and at the dilatoriness of the proceedings of the Court of Admiralty concerning them. There are many reports here of an Ambassador Extraordinary coming from France, and another from Russia, this Virgin Lady is much courted in this juncture of Time.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> thus: The 27. last <reg orig="past">passed</reg> the King and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> went a hunting to <em>Versailles</em>. The <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> if <em>Mercoeur</em> with the other Kindred of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazarine</em>, arrived in this City, and were extraordinary well received of their Majesties at the <em><reg orig="Lowre">Louvre</reg></em>.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>There is a strong report, that the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> is arrived in this City, and that he will have hid father come from <em>Rome</em> and live at Court, to that end he hath procured him from the King the <unclear>Title</unclear> of Duke and Peer of France, and that he doth purpose to buy him, as soon as may be, some Lands for him and his heirs, and Monsieur <em>de Lyonne</em> is to <reg orig="carrie">carry</reg> the letters to <em>Rome</em> upon that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>.</p>

<p>On the second instant the King went to St: <em><reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg></em> to hunt a wild Boar, which had been brought into the Park by order of the Governor; after which he exercised himself in shooting of Birds flying, where he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> great dexterity and experience; and having spent most part of the day upon such exercise as is fit for his quality and young years, he returned hither in the evening on horseback.</p>

<p>Our late Ambassador at <em>Rome</em> is returned, and come to this city, to give his Majesty an account of his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, there is another to go thither very shortly, who will be ready to go about the middle of <em>April</em>, but some say not so soon.</p>

<p>From Brussels thus: <i>The Earl <em>de Fuensaldagne</em> being gone from thence, came the next day to <em>Delft</em>, and the two days following, the Officers of the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> Army came to meet him, what by his care and wisdom, <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the Authority of the Arch-Duke Leopoldus, and the good disposition in the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, he hath wrought so much upon them, as to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to obey the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em>, as they did formerly, whilst the arrival of the Duke <em>Francis</em> Brother to him that is now imprisoned, and having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things as well for that particular, as for those <reg orig="publike">public</reg> affairs which concern his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and came back upon Wednesday last to this City.</i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>There is fallen down the last week <reg orig="an other">another</reg> part of that ancient and Metropolitan Church of S. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the South <reg orig="dore">door</reg>, where it <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> before; it has been under consideration by the Council for the taking of it down but nothing yet is done in it.</p>

<p>As concerning the Treaty with the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>, all is concluded on, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the engrossing of the Articles: But the English Commissioners, of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to the Lord Protector, viz. The Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Major Gen: <em>Lambert</em>, Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Col. <em>Montague</em>, Mr. <em>Lawrence</em>, are appointed to finish the Agreement with the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>, and have had diverse meetings about it, and the conclusion tends to speedy <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg>.</p>

<p>We are advertised from Scotland, that there are diverse commanders and eminent Officers landed at the <reg orig="Ferrey">Ferry</reg> of <reg orig="Vney">Uney</reg> in Southerland. A List of their names I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> here insert:</p>

<p><reg orig="Liev">Lieu</reg>. Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, The lord <em>Douglas</em>, the lord <em>Murrey</em>, Sir <em>George Monroe</em>, Sir <em>Alexander Ennis</em>, Major Gen. <em>Dyel</em>, Col. <em>Dyel</em>, col. <em>Lodowick Drumland</em>, col. <em>Stuart</em>, col. <em>Gibson</em>, 25 captains, 30 lieutenants, and about 100 other Officers and Gentlemen of quality; with store of Arms and Ammunition.</p>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven we received intelligence, that there are some lately come from Ireland, who <reg orig="tels">tells</reg> us no more as for new, but that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Mortague</em>, there are great numbers of Irish ready to take shipping for Flanders to serve the King of Spain; but yet there are still small parties of <em>Tories</em>, who lie lurking in the Bogs and Woods, and do great <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg>, and much disquiet the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, which is still in great want of people <unclear>to</unclear> inhabit those parts.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>