<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn11">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 11</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The great preparations made by the Spaniard in the <reg orig="Dutchy">Duchy</reg> of Milan for War, and the great fortifications of the Towns of <unclear>Verua</unclear> and <unclear>Cresccntino</unclear> for that purpose. The return of the Answer of the <em>States</em> of <em>Holland</em> to his Highness the Lord Protector concerning the signing and sealing of the Agreement. Also the great spoil and hurt done by the Brest <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in the Channel, and how they have taken several vessels of considerable value, which belonged to Bristol, The passing of an Ordinance for the keeping of the last Return of Easter Term. With divers other Letters from <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> April 11. to <em>Tuesday</em> <reg orig="Aril">April</reg> 18. 1653</head>
<hr />

<p>There are Letters come this day from the Isle of Wight, which <reg orig="certifes">certifies</reg> <unclear><!--2 characters--></unclear> that our Fleet hath weighed Anchor from <reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg> Point, being in a very good condition, and is now riding in Stoke Bay; those ships that were gone into Portsmouth to take in their provisions, are now ready, and fit to put <unclear>forth</unclear>.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>From <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 8, thus. Notwithstanding all the several beatings those which raise <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> meet with, yet so inveterate is the malice of these people against us, that they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be barking: several Parties of them that have been up in <em>Galloway</em> have been met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and within these 4 or 5 days Maj. <em>Bridges</em> with, a party of Col. <em><reg orig="Okies">Okie's</reg></em> took 8 of the Rebels, and 12. Horse in one place, in another place killed 3. took 8 and 25. Horse. Cornet <em>Kennet</em> with a party of 20 horse of Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment, coming from <em><reg orig="Dunfreeze">Dumfries</reg></em>, a party of 40 of the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg> made an attempt upon them, they received the onset, and them charged through them, routed the Rebels, killed 4 on the place, took 9 (whereof 3 mortally wounded) and divers horse. The next day Lieut. <em>Hickman</em> of that same Regiment <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with him <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> a party of 80 of the Rebels, took 11 prisoners, and about 20 horse, Cap. <em>Campbel</em> who commanded them was shot in the back, his horse taken, but himself escaped.</p>

<p><em>Glencairn, Glengary</em>, &amp;c. are gone over <em>Tayne</em> into <em>Sutherland</em> to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, they give themselves out to be 4000. but I doubt not but Col. Morgan <reg orig="wil">will</reg> engage them with his party. Montrosse and the Lord Dudhop are raising their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of Angus, they two <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be met withal in time.</p>

<p><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg> April, 3, thus. Lieutenant Hickman whom Col, Cooper sent out with a party of Horse towards Galloway, met with the Enemy about 80 Horse, who routed them and took 23 horse, wounded the Capt. that commanded the party, killed 5 men, and wounded divers, took 11 prisoners-</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 11.</i></head>

<p>This day was published this following Ordinance.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p><i>An Ordinance for Adjourning part of <em>Easter Term</em>, 1654. And Repealing the former Ordinance of the <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> of this present <em>April</em>.</i></p>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, it is held convenient and necessary part of the next Term of Easter: be it therefore Ordained by his highness the Lord Protector by and with the consent of his Council that part of the said Term of Easter now next coming be adjourned, that is to say from and after the First Return called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, unto the last Return of the said Easter Term, called the <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>; and all and every Person or persons, which have cause or commandment to appear in any of the Courts at Westminster, in or at any day or time from and after the said Return called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, may tarry at their dwellings, or where their Business <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> lie without resorting to any of the said Courts for that cause, until the said last Return called <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>, without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf.</p>

<p>And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that Writs of adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, and <reg orig="Barrons">Barons</reg> of the <em>Exchequer</em>, giving them authority to adjourn the said part of the Term of Easter, as aforesaid, that is to say from &amp; after the said First Return, called <em>Quindena pasche</em>, until the said last Return of the said Term, called <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>, as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained, that all matters, causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> <pb n="3" />depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained, That a former Ordinance of the sixth day of this instant <em>April</em>, for the Adjourning of part of the said Term, until the First Return of Trinity Term next, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em> be from henceforth repealed and void, And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that the Sheriffs of London and Middlesex, and all other Sheriffs both in England and Wales, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the chief Market Towns and usual places within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 12 April.</i></head>

<p>It is advertised That the Peace is welcome <reg orig="newes">news</reg> to the States of Holland, &amp;c., and that they will <reg orig="subdenly">suddenly</reg> send a Messenger <reg orig="winh">with</reg> Thanks to their Ambassadors, and their approbation; and then it is to be published by both, one the same day.</p>

<p><i>The substance of the Peace agreed upon between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, &amp;c. is to this effect viz.</i></p>

<p>That <reg orig="their">there</reg> shall be a closer <reg orig="Aliance">Alliance</reg> and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of England, and the States of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> provinces <reg orig="then">than</reg> was ever heretofore, that the Peace be published by both Commonwealths, <reg orig="mpon">upon</reg> the same day; after which, all acts of Hostility to cease after 10 days in the British Seas; from thence to the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em> after six weeks, and to the Mediterranean Sea after ten weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="monethe">month</reg>; after which, all prizes to be restored. That all acts past be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither <pb n="4" />to act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other. That all Hostility cease between <em>England</em> and <em>Denmark</em>; none to assist the Rebels of either Nation with any supply, but assist each other against them, and the one not to receive those the other declares to be <reg orig="enimies">enemies</reg>, but cause them upon notice to depart within 18 days, upon pain of death. That no private persons be suffered to assist the enemies of either, not to pay to either greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> other the States ships to strike their flags to the English in the British Seas; no retreat to be given to pirates in any of the Ports of either; each comprehended the other in any Treaty with any Nation, if desired. That if any <reg orig="perticuler">particular</reg> person break the peace, it shall not break the national Confederacy, but those that do it to be punished, the Subjects of each to travel through all quarters of each, by water of Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and submitting to the Laws where they are. That in storms each may have <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> under other, if they break not Bulk, without paying of <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg>. The Merchants or Mariners of either Commonwealth not to be pressed to serve under the other, inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction, That in each others Country, they pass between their Ships and Inns with <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> weapons, Offensive and Defensive. That <reg orig="al">all</reg> ships of both Commonwealths defend each other against <reg orig="al">all</reg> whosoever, sailing their course together. If any other take any ships out of either of their Dominions, both parties to engage against them, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> restitution be made. The Searchers of both to take no more of any of either, <reg orig="then">than</reg> their Instructions. Letters of Reprisal not to be given for damage caused, if in 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, satisfaction may be had. That such as have Private Commissions, put in good security not to damage the Subjects of either Commonwealth, That not above 8 ships of War <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> in any Port of the others Commonwealth, without consent. That Justice <pb n="5" />be done by the States on those that are alive, that murdered the English in <em>Amboyna.</em></p>

<p>That there be Commissioners on both sides to examine the differences of the Inhabitants of both Nations in the East Indies, Greenland, Muscovia, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg>, or other places and if they cannot agree within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> to refer it to be determined by the Protestant <unclear>Switzers</unclear></p>

<p>Security is already given for payment of the monies to the Eastland Companies, upon the business of Denmark, and the sum agreed upon.</p>

<p>Some Merchants have received Letters that the Messenger is coming from the States, and that the Peace will be proclaimed <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> sevennight, and that an Agent is coming from <em>Denmark</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 13.</i></head>

<p>This day was sent from the King of <em>France</em> a Messenger to the French Ambassador here. Also Ambassadors are coming from several other Princes.</p>

<p>The Scots rise in several parties in the Lowlands, and four or five hundred hath been lately dispersed in several parties, and divers of them killed and taken: General <em>Monk</em> is gone to take the command of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, An Ordinance is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> tendering pardon, only with some Exceptions, one hundred of the <em>Scots</em> have gotten leave to be transported to serve the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, or the grand Duke of <em>Muscovy</em>, which they please.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Preachers sit at <em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the great gate:</p>

<p><reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> his Highness intends to come to <em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and is to dine there:</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday April 14.</i></head>

<p>This day several Letters came from the Hague intimating <pb n="6" />, That there is a Messenger coming for England with a Return of the Instrument of peace, and a Ratification of signing and sealing under the Hand of the States General; so that now there is nothing wanting for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> of this great work, but the signing O. <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>, whose <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> intends to come to <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg> on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> next, being lately returned from Hampton Court, <i>a place for a Prince</i>. Monsieur <em>Rosenwing</em> the Danish Agent is safely arrived; and a Messenger is also come from the King of France to the French Ambassador with further Instructions to conclude a peace. His Majesty has sent to the little Queen desiring Her, and the Princely Issue, to retire our of his Estates, and that their pension should be sent them where they pleased. Whereupon the Queen is preparing to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> and dwell at <em>Angers</em>, the K. of Scots and his brother <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> are bound with Rupert for Chantilly, and from thence either for Germany or Scotland, where Montross and the L. Dudhop are levying of forces, and many of the Lairds sent out their first and second sons for promoting of the service. Gen. <em>Glengarn</em> hath ferried over Tayn to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em> in <em>Southerland</em>, who hath <reg orig="garrison'd">garrisoned</reg> certain places to hinder the passage of the English, so that they have made the Ferries unfeasible in many places.</p>

<p>They have intercepted the English Letters going to Lewis <reg orig="Iland">Island</reg>, which doth somewhat impede our work at present, and are descended as far as Norwood Plain. They speak themselves to be above ten thousand horse, foot, bowmen, and <reg orig="Curiaziers">Cuirassiers</reg>; but <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Monk</em> and <reg orig="Maior">Major</reg> <em>Bridges</em> hath repelled and dissipated some of them; they begin to burn and kindle new <reg orig="coles">coals</reg>, but <reg orig="ealiant">valiant</reg> Gen. <em>Monk</em> is <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> down to allay the flame. Three <em>English</em> Ships richly laden coming from Smyrna were set upon by three <reg orig="Freenchmen">Frenchmen</reg> of War, and after a lamentable Fight, one of them was taken by the French, another stranded, but the third fled by <em>Mesina</em>.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday &amp; <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Apr. 15.17.</i></head>

<p>We received intelligence this day from Inverness, that the Enemy had a general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> in <em>Sutherland</em> near <em>Skilbo</em>, they were about 1200 Foot, and 800 Horse, (500 little better than baggage Horses, and many wanting pistols) and after the <reg orig="receit">receipt</reg> of Orders from Lieut: Generalissimo <em>Middleton</em>, most were to march for the South Highlands, and the rest to continue in the North, <reg orig="ond">and</reg> both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. <em>Middleton</em> added to their number at the <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about 200 Horse and foot, and hath ordered to be levied out of <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>250<em>, Sutherland </em>300<em>, <reg orig="Cathnesse">Caithness</reg></em>600, and <em>Stranarvar</em> 300. He expects hourly <em>Seaford</em> with 500. and <em>Mackoldwy</em> to be ready with his Levies; He gives out that he hath brought a great store of Spanish gold lent his Master by the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, from whom is expected a great Loan, and many men, which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> and to be brought by his brother-in-law, which he had <reg orig="stayd">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends for his often failing in his promised coming to them. this day <reg orig="Leiut">Lieut</reg>. Col. <em>Mirchel</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> hither with 9 Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of Horse, and a Commanded party 180, with 5 troops of Dragoons, which are to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to <em>Braham</em>, to which are added 4 troops of Horse, and 3 companies of Foot. the use of the march is to keep a Pass at <em>Dinghill</em> which by a numerous concurrence of knowing men of the Country, <reg orig="wil">will</reg> force them to Fight us, stay where they are, or Hazard the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of their Horse, by length, badness of way and want of provisions, if they march to the South by the Northwest <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, they having no other way to march otherwise.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>