<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="DutchDiurn15#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The true and Perfect Dutch-Diurnall, Issue 15#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="3">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Dutch-Diurnall">Dutch Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="3">OF SEVERAL PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS,</head>
<head level="3">Of and in Relation to the</head>
<head level="2">STATES of HOLLAND.</head>
<head level="3">Impartially <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg></head>

<p><i>The full particulars of a great and bloody fight <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Hills in Scotland. A List of the names of the prisoners taken, and the number killed and wounded. Also, a Declaration of the Commanders in chief of the Scottish forces for the pardoning of all them that <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> comply with them, A Proclamation by his Highness the Lord Protector for the setting apart Tuesday being the 23 instant, for a day of Thanksgiving, for the Peace concluded on between the two Commonwealths. Likewise a Declaration of Gen. Monk with other Letters from the K. of Scots concerning his sending and raising more Men, Arms, and Ammunition to Glencarn, and Kenmore.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> May 15. to <em>Tuesday</em> May 22. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> May 15.</i></head>

<p>A Letter came this day to my hands, from Scotland, intimating, that there hath <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> an engagement <reg orig="betwen">between</reg> Gen. Monk and a party of <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg>. In which fight we killed and wounded 100 of them, <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> divers prisoners, and totally routed them.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> May 15</i></head>

<p>From Dalkeith we are advertised thus, That the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Forces do not now increase, and I hope they will shortly diminish very much, a great part of them having more mind to come in, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to stay out in Arms.</p>

<p><em>Glencairn</em> is come to Athol with about Two hundred Horse and Foot to assist Montross in his Levies; and now to help a little their dying hopes, they give out that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> will be here shortly. I having nothing further at this time, but refer you to the ensuing Declaration; a Copy whereof followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in chief of all the forces in</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>SCOTLAND</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness and affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg> with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the Liberties and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="Expence">Expense</reg> of so much Blood and Treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge of which this Nation undergoeth no more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the equal proportion with <em>England</em>, against their enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of peace; yet divers lewd persons broken in their Fortunes, and dissolute in their Lives, are run into Rebellion, and being assisted and connived at by their parents, Brethren, Tutors, Masters, and people among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the <reg orig="day time">daytime</reg>, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation <pb n="2" />are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in peace. And to the end that no Peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof, I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, do declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except as such as are excepted in the Acts of grace) who shall within twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication <reg orig="herof">hereof</reg>, come in, and submit him or themselves to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next <em>English</em> Garrison, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned for any offence, Spoil or Plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion, the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.</p>

<p>And I do declare, that if any parents, Brethren, or Tutors, who have assisted &amp; connived at any of their Sons, Brothers, or pupils, now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publication hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers, or pupils, to render themselves, and give Security as aforesaid; That <i>then the said parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are <reg orig="herby">hereby</reg> freely pardoned; but if otherwise, then the said parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, shall be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion.</i></p>

<p><i>And in regard this present rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Middleton, the Earl of Athol, the Earl of Seaforth, Viscount Kenmore, Donald MacDonald Laird of Glengary, and Major General Dayell, I do hereby therefore declare, That what person or persons soever of this Nation, except such as are before excepted, shall kill any of the said principle contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any English Garrisons, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner as aforesaid, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not only be pardoned for anything <pb n="3" />he or they have acted in this late Rebellion, <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> also shall receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of Two hundred pounds sterling, for every person so killed or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</i></p>

<p><i>Given under my hand at Dalkeith,</i></p>

<p><i>This 4. day of May 1654. George Monke.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 17.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em> this day we received Intelligence that his highness the Lord Protector was proclaimed at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> with great acclamation. Twelve <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of our men of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> are going from <em>Leith</em> to. Gen. <em><reg orig="Monek">Monke</reg></em> is going <reg orig="twords">towards</reg> <em>Sterling</em> <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</p>

<p>Middleton hath sent out <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Commanders for Levies <em>Drommond</em> to <em>Lougtay</em>, and Glencairn to secure him 100 horse Col. Murray to <em>Athol</em>: Montrosse to Branar, and <reg orig="othhrs">others</reg> places, but we shall shortly be among them. Col. Morgan hath had hard duties but the Enemy will not come near him, but gives him the Slip among the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>. The Scotch Ministers even in our quarters pray for <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, whom it seems they have a hope to see again among them, so besotted they are and mad; two ships from Dunkirk have brought Men Arms, and Ammunition to Middleton, but of all that <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them we hear of few that have estates to subsist on, but the Ring leaders.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Lubeck, and Lunenburgh, May 6.</i></head>

<p>These Countries here receive great benefit by the lying of the English Fleet continually in the Channel, or in the sight of the French Coasts whereby the French are fain to keep their Army upon their own Territories, to Guard their Coasts, and reinforce their <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> and <reg orig="strong holds">strongholds</reg> for fear of some <reg orig="surprisall">surprisal</reg> by the English; so that these parts are all quiet at present, but it is not likely they will continue long so; there is a <reg orig="Rumor">Rumour</reg> that the French Army is under the Command of the <reg orig="Mareschall">Marshall</reg> Turenne, is already on <pb n="4" />their march towards these <reg orig="countreys">countries</reg>. And because they may be ready likewise to <reg orig="oppse">oppose</reg> the French.</p>

<p>The Arch-Duke hath given order for the speedy marching of the whole Spanish Army to a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> <em>Franhis</em> Duke of Lorain with his two Sons is going from hence to take upon him the Command of the <em>Lorain</em> Forces, &amp; to conduct them also to the <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>; He hath taken a good <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> with him to pay his <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and to have them sworn, that they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> unto him.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 18.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from Scotland they write, that General Monk was lately in Sterling, and is now on his advance towards the Highlanders, to whom divers Renegadoes do resort. Their <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of new provision for the War doth much <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> them, so that their Levies of late do much increase. Middleton knowing what an Enemy he hath to deal with. he doth manage the War with great dexterity. Some Letters do represent, that he will fight with Col. Morgan before the <reg orig="acoesse">access</reg> are added to him. There was lately a great dispute at the maintaining of a Pass, in which Sir Arthur Forbs was routed, and divers killed and taken. The titular King of Scotland hath sent a Letter to Middleton, in which he exhorteth and conjureth the commanders to an <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg> in this time of their greatest necessity.</p>

<p>From Naples, There hath been lately mustered here 22 Companies, and about 5 Troops of horses, being all of the new Levies, but the Companies and Troops being all very thin, and wanting much of their full number, <reg orig="som">some</reg> small quantity of monies being given to each <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> thereby to make him go more <reg orig="chearfully">cheerfully</reg> in the service. One of the chief of the <reg orig="Bandity">Banditry</reg> whom they call King <em>Siul</em> having with 16 of his men met the Post going to Bari at the Bridge of Lavignano <pb n="5" />had robbed him of all, and as he was about to strip him, there happened some <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of Montefolcoli, who having fought with him, not only made him leave all his prey, but also killed him, one Officer, and took one of his men prisoner, and chased the rest for many miles: They write us from Oranta that there hath been lately in those parts two great Earthquakes, which hat caused much <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> among the inhabitants.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday May 19.</i></head>

<p>The discontents in <em>Holland</em>, and what hath been some about it, is only thus. The Princess Dowager, and the Princess <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg>, and the rest of the Family of <em>Nassaw</em>, have made an application by paper presented to the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, bemoaning their condition as sad by the late Articles of peace with <em>England</em>. And some forty women cane weeping and crying out bemoaning the Prince of <em>Orange</em> saying, <i>Ah! poor prince, what hast thou done that <unclear>thou</unclear> <reg orig="shouldest">shouldst</reg> be thus used? ah poor <reg orig="childe">child</reg> what a sad condition art thou in?</i> and the like expressions; which was not much regarded, and that is all the business. All being quiet and in very good order, and if that Family will live peaceably, they may; The last week was the Fair kept at the <em><reg orig="Haugh">Hague</reg></em>, at which time the Trained band (as they use to do every year) went out into the field in their gallantry.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is passed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, with advice of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, for the relief of poor Creditors in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for the Courts that use to be kept in <em>Chester</em> City, to be kept at <em>Northwich</em> during the time of Sickness being in <em>Chester</em> City.</p>

<p>An additional Ordinance passed for mending the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>.</p>

<p>There is nothing yet concluded in our Treaty with <pb n="6" />the <em>French</em> Ambassador, but what may be time <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<p>The Committee met about the Law, but find it a hard work to alter the old <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg>, But it is believed something will be dispatched about a fortnight hence for the Committee at <reg orig="Salters">Salter's</reg> Hill to act by.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday May 20.</i></head>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> being come to Town from the Fleet, he with the Lord Mayor, and some Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> dined this day with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, Genera <em>Pen</em> is with the Fleet in the Downs the Northern Squadron that convey the Coals will shortly be there God willing, the Brest Men are out, and do mischief upon the Western <reg orig="costs">coasts</reg>.</p>

<p>By Letters from several places we are advertised, that the peace hath been proclaimed with great joy, and the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> affection more and more enlarged to his Highness the Lord Protector; as for instance one Letter from <unclear>Rarwick</unclear>, the like whereof hath been from many other places.</p>

<head level="3">The substance of the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> proposition to the States of <em>Bohemia</em>.</head>

<p><i>1. That they use their utmost <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> for the propagating of the <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That they <reg orig="selebrate">celebrate</reg> the Feast of St. <em>Joseph</em> as the rest of the Patrons of the Kingdom use to do.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That they pay a considerable <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> to the Emperor for the maintenance of his Household Officers, Ambassador, Residents and Attendants.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That they pay their proportion for maintenance of the Frontier places of <em>Hungaria</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>5. That they continue the maintenance of the <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> forces quartered in that Kingdom, and pay those which his Majesty shall disband.</i></p>

<p><i>6. That they suffer not the importation of foreign <unclear>Salt</unclear></i> without paying the usual Customs and <unclear>Duties</unclear>.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p><i>7. That they neither suffer the importation, nor in any thing the use of the bad Turkish <reg orig="wooll">wool</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>8. That they incessantly cause the River of <em>Elve</em> to be made navigable as far as this Town.</i></p>

<p><i>9. That they perform whatsoever hath been agreed on in former Assemblies touching the other Affairs of the Kingdom.</i></p>

<p>This day we received Intelligence, that the Deputies of the City of <em>Rehims</em> arrived here to assure His Majesty that the Inhabitants are about with a great care, befitting their zeal and fidelity to make all things ready for his Reception, against the Ceremony of his Coronation. The 11 instant the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> having <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> the French <reg orig="Accademy">Academy</reg>, with her picture, it was presented to them at the <reg orig="Chancellors">Chancellor's</reg> house in <em>Paris</em>, where they met and received as a precious testimony of that learned and worthy <reg orig="Pricesses">Princess's</reg> affection, Mr. <unclear>Deujat</unclear> then president of the <reg orig="Accademy">Academy</reg> in Nr. <em>de la Brosse <reg orig="Montmors">Montmor's</reg></em> absence, who is their Director, having made a rare Speech in commendation of the excellent <reg orig="qualaties">qualities</reg> of the said Queen.</p>

<p>By Letter from the <em>Isle</em> of <em>Jersey</em>, we are advertised that the Government of <em>Jersey</em> is near finished. Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em> has received his <em>Habeas Corpus</em> from the Upper Bench, and is to brought thither, where he is to have his <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> very suddenly.</p>

<p>Some Letters the last week did confirm that he was dead, but since we hear he is living.</p>

<p>The last news from Scotland <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> grow numerous, and that they spake themselves to be above 11000 at the last <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, being resolved to fight us; which is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> desired by the merry Redcoats, so that by our next, no doubt but you will hear of action.</p>

<p>It is confirmed from Brazil, that the <unclear>Hollanders</unclear> are almost totally banished from those parts; and are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> threatened in other parts.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>