<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$15">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $15</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>A Message from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> to the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>, and their going to meet her Majesty at the <em>Spaw</em> upon a Treaty of great concernment. The <em>Highlanders</em> falling down into the <em>Lowlands</em> of <em>Scotland</em>, and their burning and destroying all that stands before them: The Treaty of Peace between <em>France</em>, and <em>Spain</em>. The taking of <em>42</em> French Merchants ships by the <em>English</em>; and the new, and secret Instructions sent to the <em>English</em> Generals at Sea. The proceedings concerning Regulation of the Law, and taking away <reg orig="chargable">chargeable</reg> Offices. A Message to Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Coll</reg>: <em>John Lilburn</em>. And other Intelligence of great concernment.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 28 of <em>April</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 5 of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, April 28.</head>
<p>The Committee for the Law have several excellent things under consideration for Regulation thereof, and it is likely that for the case of the People the <em>Phillesers</em> Office, the <em>Exigent</em> Office, and some of the chief Offices of charge to the People, will be taken away, or lessened.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Sympson</em> and Mr: <em>Feak</em> are very cheerful at <em><reg orig="Winsor">Windsor</reg></em>, and as confident as ever.</p>
<p>The Officers in <em>Ireland</em> have signed a Congratulatory Letter for his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 29.</head>
<p>This Day came to our hands a perfect Copy of the Articles of Peace, as they were Printed, Published, and Proclaimed in <em>Holland, viz:</em></p>
<p><i>The Articles of the perpetual Peace concluded between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. on the one part, and his High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the United <em>Netherlandish</em> Provinces on the other part.</i></p>
<p>1. That from hence forward there shall be a firm, and <reg orig="unchangable">unchangeable</reg> Peace, sincere friendship, and <reg orig="straiter">straighter</reg> Alliance, confederation and Union, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever heretofore between the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, the States General of the United <em>Provinces</em> of the <em>Netherlands</em>, and the respective Lands, Countries, and Cities <reg orig="every where">everywhere</reg> under their obedience, and their people, and Inhabitants.</p>
<p>2. That from henceforth all enmity, discontention; and War between the said two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, and their people, and Subjects shall cease.</p>
<p>3. That all offences, injuries, costs, and damages which either party hath suffered by the other, shall be abolished, and forgotten.</p>
<p>4. That all prisoners on both sides, of what condition, or quality soever they be, shall be released without paying <reg orig="ransome">ransom</reg>.</p>
<p>5. That the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> remain confederate friends, against all whomsoever, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> endeavour to <reg orig="disturbe">disturb</reg> either State by sea, or Land, or being declared enemies to the freedoms, and liberties of the people <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> shelter themselves under either of the said Governments.</p>
<p>6. That neither of the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> may make, do, act, deal, or undertake against the other, but <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> actually oppose all whosoever, who shall act, or deal, or undertake <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against either <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>7. That neither <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, nor the people dwelling or residing therein, shall give, or lend any help, counsel, or favour to the Enemies, or Rebels of either, upon pain of Treason.</p>
<p>8. That the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> assist each other as need shall require by sea and Land, with men and ships, at the charge of the parties who desire the same.</p>
<p>9. That neither of the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, or the people thereof shall receive any person or persons, which by their <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> shall be declared Enemies, Rebels, or Fugitives.</p>
<p>10. That in case either <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> by their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Letters shall declare unto the other, that any persons are their Enemies, <em>&amp;c</em>: then upon such notice the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> where such person or persons resideth, shall warn them to depart within 28. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death, and loss of Lands.</p>
<p>11. That no Rebel of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> shall be received, or suffered to remain in any of the Castles, Cities, Havens, and Cricks, or other places <reg orig="priviledged">privileged</reg> within the Jurisdiction of the <em>United Provinces</em>.</p>
<p>12. That the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the people <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, and the <em>United Provinces</em>, and the Inhabitants of the same, shall be bound to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> each other with all love, and friendship.</p>
<p>13. That the ships of the <em>United Provinces</em> meeting in the Narrow Seas any of the English Men of War, shall strike the <reg orig="Flagg">Flag</reg> as in former times.</p>
<p>14. That neither of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall receive in any of their <reg orig="harbors">harbours</reg>, or assist, or <unclear>refresh</unclear> any <em><reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg></em>, or Sea Rovers.</p>
<p>15. That either of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> do make a Treaty of Amity with any <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg>, Princes, or States, they shall comprehend each other, in case they desire it.</p>
<p>16. That if <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> shall be done, or committed by any of the People of either party against this Treaty, by Land or Sea, the confederation <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be broken, but the particular party <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be punished, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>17. That the People of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> may freely, and with all safety travel through all quarters of the <em>United Provinces</em> <pb n="3" /> to drive their Trade, armed, or unarmed, and the people of the <em>United Provinces</em> shall have the like <reg orig="priviledg">privilege</reg> here.</p>
<p>18. That in case any Merchants ships of either State by any accidents be driven into any havens, <em>&amp;c.</em> they may depart at their pleasure without paying Customs, if they break not Bulk.</p>
<p>19. That the Merchants, Skippers, <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg>, <em>&amp;c.</em> of either <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their ships, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall not be Arrested, nor seized to serve at War, unless upon inevitable necessity.</p>
<p>20. That the Merchants, and Skippers on both sides, when they go on Land, may carry any weapons of defence, and offence.</p>
<p>21. That the Men of War of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> meeting, and holding one course, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> defend, and protect each other.</p>
<p>22. That if any ships be taken by a third party, they shall do their endeavour to recover the same, and restore it at the charges of the owners.</p>
<p>23. That the Searchers, and other Officers shall regulate themselves according to the Laws of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>
<p>24. That in case any injury be done by any people of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> contrary to this treaty, no Letters of <unclear>Mark</unclear> shall be granted until Justice have been sought in an ordinary way.</p>
<p>25. That all persons on both sides going to sea with particular Commissions, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give security that they shall do no <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> to either side.</p>
<p>26. That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be lawful for the People on either side to repair to any Port <em>&amp;c.</em> with Merchants ships, &amp; Men of War to victual, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<p>27. That Justice be done against such as are living which had a hand in the business of <em>Amboyna</em>.</p>
<p>28. That the King of <em>Denmark</em> pay 14000 <em>l.</em> for seizing some <em>English</em> ships, and Goods, and other injuries, are referred to arbitration.</p>
<p>29. That all discords, <em>&amp;c:</em> shall be forgotten in eternal oblivion betwixt this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the said King.</p>
<p>30. That Commissioners to meet of injuries, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall meet in <em>London</em> the 18 of this instant <em>May</em>.</p>
<p>31. That both parties shall firmly keep this Treaty.</p>
<p>32. That such as the States at <reg orig="any time">anytime</reg> shall make Captain General, <em>&amp;c</em>: <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be bound by Oath to confirm this Treaty.</p>
<p>33. That all this Treaty shall be confirmed by the Lord Protector, and the States General.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 1.</head>
<p>This Day the Council sate upon great and weighty affairs. Some things were this day referred to Committees.</p>
<p>The Committee hath made some progress in the business of the Law.</p>
<p><i>Dublin <em>26</em> April.</i> The General Council have met, and are shortly to sit again; The Lord Deputy, and the Commissioners have lately had great consultations for the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of this Nation, now (blessed be God) in a condition ready to be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> if it were but peopled: and there are two Officers gone over from hence towards his Highness the Lord Protector, who will give an account of all things here, and by whom you will understand that (blessed be God) we are in a good condition.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Texel <em>26</em> April.</i></head>
<p>Five Men of War are ready to sail towards <em>Brazil</em>, and three others to cross towards our Freebooters to <reg orig="cal">call</reg> them in. Here is a gallant Fleet of Merchant ships of about 100 sail, ready to sail for <em>France, Spain</em>, and other places. The 22. instant those Galliots that went to Sea from hence the day before, were driven in again by three English Freebooters, who took one of them. The 23 in the morning a Fleet of our Merchant ships, and Men of War went to Sea.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From the Hague the <em>21</em> of April.</i></head>
<p>A Day of Thanksgiving to God Almighty shall be appointed here for the Peace with <em>England</em>, the Lord having been pleased to take away the evil of the War, and all former differences between both Nations, and to desire him that the Peace may for his glory be continued <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, that we may <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> upon that blessing between both people, who stand in so great need thereof, as well in regard of the common Protestant Religion, as of the Commerce of all the world, hoping that the time shall make us reap the fruits that blessed Peace.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 2.</head>
<p>This Day some progress was made about the Law.</p>
<p><reg orig="Somthing">Something</reg> considered of about the <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg> of Money.</p>
<p>Some Forces are passing from the North of <em>Ireland</em> to the Islands in the North of <em>Scotland</em>, that upon their landing there, they may Alarum <em>Middleton</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 3.</head>
<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>
<head level="2">A PROCLAMATION.</head>
<p>OLIVER Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging. Whereas the Commissioners appointed by Us to treat with the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the United Provinces; and the said Ambassadors, by way of Explanation of the third of those Articles of Peace, lately concluded between this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> and that of the United <em>Netherlands</em>, and for removing of all questions and differences that may arise thence from. Have agreed, and concluded the following Article, <i>viz: That whereas in the third of those Articles of Peace, Union, and Confederations made established and promulged between the Lord Protector of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Lords of the States General of the United Provinces, it is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges, and <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, which either party hath sustained by the other since the <em>18</em> of <em>May</em> in the year one thousand and six hundred fifty two shall be taken away, and forgotten in such manner, as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other, so for or upon occasion of any aforesaid Injuries, Charges, and <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, but that there shall be a perfect abolition of all, and every of them until this present day. And all actions for the same shall be held, and reputed void and null, excepting such depredations as shall be committed by either side in these Seas after the space of twelve <reg orig="days">days</reg>, and in all other places on this side the Cape of Saint <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks, and from thence within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranean">Mediterranean</reg></em> Sea, and to the <em>Equinoctial</em> Line after ten weeks, and beyond the<em> Equinoctial</em> Line, after the space of eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, or <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places.</i> And whereas certain questions may possibly arise about the fore rehearsed words, which may minister occasion of debates, and disputes, The said Lord Protector, and the States General, to the end all manner of <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg>, and difference may be removed, which might arise by reason of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the aforesaid Article contained, have unanimously accorded and agreed, and do by these presents publish and declare to all and singular <pb n="6" /> their people and Subjects respectively, that after the Publication of the Treaty of Peace, which is already done, all acts of Hostility shall <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> cease in all places expressed in the said Article, and in all others whatsoever. And that all Depredations, <reg orig="dammages">damages</reg>, and injuries which shall be done, or committed by one party against the other, after the fourth day of this instant <em>May</em> in all places whatsoever, mentioned in the foresaid Article, or elsewhere, as well on this side the Line as beyond, shall be accounted for; And all things taken or seized after the <reg orig="abovesaid">above said</reg>. of <em>May</em>, shall be restored without any form of Process, as also damages growing by occasion thereof. And to the end this Agreement and Article may be the better known, both parties <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> Publish the same within their respective Territories and Dominions, and straitly charge and command as well their ships of War, as others whether in Port, or at Sea, to observe the same.</p>
<p>Wherefore we having considered what is agreed as aforesaid, have confirmed and ratified, as we do confirm, and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same by these presents, which we have caused to be Published, that all Persons concerned therein may take notice thereof. And to the end none may pretend ignorance herein, The Commissioners of the Admiralty are also by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of these presents forthwith to call in upon their several Securities given in that Court, all such Ships as have been set forth upon private Commissions against the United Provinces or the People thereof. <i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em> this first of May, in the year <em>1654</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>In Witness whereof as well the Lords Commissioners of his Highness, as the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the States General, have signed these presents with their own hands. Done at <em>Westminster</em> the <em>28</em> of April Old style, in the year <em>1654</em>.</i></p>
<p>H. Laurence Pres, Gil: Pickering, E. Montagu, Wal: Strickland, H. Beverningck, Will: Nieupoort, Alan P. Jongestall.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 4.</head>
<p>By the Post from <em>Leith</em> in <em>Scotland</em> thus. We conceive the enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagued with their inroads upon the Lowlands, where they burnt and destroyed all that stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reason of these mischiefs, and our loss is want of Intelligence from amongst them, for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce squeeze ten true words out of them, we hear that <em>Middleton</em> is gotten out of <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, wherein <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="intrapt">entrapped</reg> his Horse, or force him to fight, but now it is believed there will be no fight until some greater numbers be added to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em>, and then it's likely the Enemy <reg orig="wil">will</reg> play fast and loose, in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming to them, and then all the Country voluntarily to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, but it's thought the Peace with <em>Holland</em> will cross their expectations; and indeed the Letters from <em>Holland</em> say, that there is News, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em> are going to the <em>Spaw</em> in expectation to meet the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after her resigning of the Government; the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> <reg orig="wil">will</reg> shortly return thence.</p>
<p>In <em>Holland</em> there is also News that <em>France</em>, and <em>Spain</em> have had a Treaty for making a League for ten years, but some say it will not take effect.</p>
<p>They report that the <em>English</em> have taken very lately 42 <em>French</em> Merchants ships, and they are in great fear of an invasion.</p>
<p>Gen: <em>Pen</em> is gone to Gen: <em>Blake</em> with the Fleet, and hath carried down Instructions from the Lord Protector, and his Council, which are not yet fit to be published.</p>
<p>The <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador had late Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>His Highness have a foot Guard to his Person, and to carry up meat of 60, they have not Coats with Cullissances after the old fashion, but have grey Cloaks with black velvet <reg orig="Collers">Collars</reg>, and black velvet, and silver lace, they have 50 <em>l. per annum</em> a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> <reg orig="sallary">salary</reg>.</p>
<p>Lieut <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em><reg orig="Lilburns">Lilburn's</reg></em> Friends have sent to him about a <em>Habeas Corpus</em>, they are not yet returned.</p> 

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>