<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$11">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $11</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>A great Fight between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Dutch</em>; the number of the <em>Dutch</em> Fleet besides fifty Fire-ships, and a List of the ships taken; With outable satisfaction concerning the proceedings between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Dutch</em> about the Articles of Peace, and the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> General Letters to their Ambassadors here. Ten thousand Foot and seven thousand Horses raised in <em>Scotland</em> by Gen: <em>Middleton, Glencarn, Seafort</em>, and others, a particular touching their <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, with the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> throwing up of their caps, and crying out <em>Vive le Roy</em>. The differences, and fighting betwixt the <em>French</em> Gentlemen, and the <em>Portugals</em> at <em><reg orig="Tower-hill">Tower hill</reg></em> at the Ambassadors coming in.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 24 of <em>March</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 31 of <em>March</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, March 24.</head>
<p>A Petition was presented to the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of the City for the <reg orig="Hangmans">Hangman's</reg> place, wherein the Petitioner <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> that the old Hangman was incapable of Esquire, of the Hectors, saying that he was not good either at Knot, or Knife; which business was so far taken into consideration, that the Petitioner carried the place to the dishonour of the old Esquire of the Triple Trade.</p>
<p>Several Vessels have been cast away this week upon the River of <em>Thames</em> by Tempests.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>An Ordinance was published for continuing the Act of laying an imposition upon the Coals, towards the building and maintaining ships for the guarding of the Seas, to be in force until the 26. of March 1655.</p>
<p>An Ordinance for the passing custodies for Idiots, and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<p>Also an Ordinance for continuing the Act of impressing of Seamen, to be in force until Novemb: 1. 1654.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From Milford Haven, March <em>18</em>.</i></head>
<p>There is arrived this week from <em>Ireland</em> three Vessels laden with Irish commodities, and brought over some few passengers; they say little for News from thence, only that the Country in many parts wants people to <reg orig="til">till</reg> the ground; that the Tories, and others, of that <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> crew are very <reg orig="neer">near</reg> all <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg>, there being only very <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties remaining on foot, but dare not to stand to any engagement with such parties of ours as are sent to destroy them, and so clear the Country of them, upon the least report that they hear of our men approaching they presently run into the Woods and Boggs, where there is little or no access to them. We have been little troubled of late with any <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, one <reg orig="onely">only</reg> was seen the beginning of this week to the Westward of the isle of <em>Lundy</em>; but upon the report made him by a <reg orig="Fisherboat">Fisher boat</reg>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> appointed to keep the Seas was in pursuit, he <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> went away, and left this Channel, sailing towards the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, he hath about six guns, and 60 men, being a <em>Dutch</em> Vessel, but a singular good sailer.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday, March <em>25</em>.</i></head>
<head level="3"><i>From Scarborough March <em>20</em>.</i></head>
<p>Since that the Fleet of Colliers bound for the Southward hath passed by, there hath not sailed this way many ships, save only a few bound for <em>Newcastle, Berwick</em>, and the Frith in <em>Scotland</em>; two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since two <em>Dutch Freebooters</em> were seen about <em>Fylie Bay</em>, and seeing nothing to pray upon, the went about <em>Flamborough</em> into the Bay, and seeing nothing ready to be <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg> up, they sailed into the Sea, and were seen this evening hovering about the mouth of <em>Humber</em>.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<head level="3"><em>Leith, March</em> 18.</head>
<p>There is no account yet come of the <em>Highlanders</em> great <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be about Wednesday last in <em>Badgenoth</em>, in order to which all their Forces are drawn Northwards, where they will arm those that want, and <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to raise <em>Sutherland, Gaithnesse</em>, and <em>Rosse</em>, and so drain the Country of all the sensible men they can get together, though I suppose when that is done, they will not be able to keep the, which if they once become more numerous they will attempt.</p>
<p>By another Letter further thus: <em>Seafort</em> hath raised his number to 700, and the last general <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of them <reg orig="al">all</reg>, they spake themselves to be seven thousand Armed, but have no monies, only are fed with great hopes of <reg orig="summes">sums</reg> to come out of <em>Germany</em>, and that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> is to bring from thence an additional supply of men under his conduct, and on this depends the great expectation of <em><reg orig="Charls Stuarts">Charles Stuart's</reg></em> arrival amongst them. In the interim they march towards our Borders, forcing their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> throughout their march.</p>
<p><em>Saturday</em> morning about three of the clock the Male with the <em>Dutch</em> Letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, was <reg orig="seised">seized</reg>, and broke open by Thieves within a mile of <em>St: <reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> Church, which they did as supposed upon the hopes to find money, but finding none, broke open all the Letters that were in packets, and throwed them on the ground, and turned the man back again.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 27.</head>
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador (of whom we made mention before) had Audience this Day by his Highness the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <em>Whitehall</em>, where stood a Chair of State, and his Highness by it. The Ambassador is a man of Eminency in <em>France</em>, having the advantage of a very large Revenue, as an Ornament <pb n="3" />for his natural endowments, and <reg orig="shews">shows</reg> himself so true a <em>Monsieur</em>, that he made three low congies to his Highness the Ld: Protector at his coming up to make his Speech, or Oration to him, which was partly congratulatory, wherein he wanted not words to demonstrate the <reg orig="joyes">joys</reg> of his Master, and how happy he apprehends the people to be, that are under so good a Governor; with whom that <em>Most Christian King</em> desireth to enter into League, and Confederacy. He therefore in the first place doth desire a Treaty for a free Trade, and Commerce, and that acts of hostility may cease, with some other things which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> to, if it may be done with <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg> and safety to the Nation.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of several Prizes taken by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance</em>, and <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> since February, <em>1653</em>.</i></head>
<p><em>March</em> 2. taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot hoy, whose malt being shot by the board, she was burnt.</p>
<p>Taken the same day by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Hope</em> of <em>Housdown</em> burthen 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>
<p>Taken then also by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix</em> the <em>Clans</em> of <em>Housdown</em>, burthen 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 14. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaids">Mermaid's</reg></em> Boat, the <em>Skell-fish</em> of <em>Mazeland Slays</em> with Fish, Salt, and some empty Cask.</p>
<p>Taken the same day also by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix</em> her Boat, the <em>Phampart</em> of <em>Mazeland Slays</em>, burthen thirty <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 12. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> the <em>Providence</em> of <em>Mazeland Slays</em>, burthen 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 17. Brought by the Lee by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix</em>, and her boat sent on board, and afterward run on board by the <em>Newcastle</em>, who broke her head, and Boltsprit, and forced the <em>Ph&aelig;nix</em> her Boat off, <em>viz:</em> the <em>Fortune</em> of <em>Delfs haven</em>, burthen 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with brandy Wine, French Wine, prunes, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>Taken the same day by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix</em> the <em>Blew pigeon</em> of <em>Pumurland</em>, burthen 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden also with Brandy Wine, French Wines, and Prunes.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 18. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, burthen 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 19. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> two <em>Scotch</em> Vessels; the one laden with Beef, Flower, Train <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, <reg orig="Deer-skins">Deer skins</reg>, and Sugars, the <pb n="4" />other had only Ballast; both of them were going for <em>Holland</em>, having been first taken by a private Man of War belonging to <em>Enchuisen</em>, but thus recovered.</p>
<p><em>March</em> 20. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> the <em>Waking Buy</em> of <em>Enchuysen</em>, and with her eight guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable, twelve Pikes, ten Muskets, eight Pistols, and a Boat with four Oars.</p>
<p>It is advertised by Letters from <em>Scotland</em> that since <em>Middleton</em>, there is a Lord landed with some more men, and Arms.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 28.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From the Hague the <em>27</em> March.</i></head>
<p>The last Thursday were brought here in a Pink sent for that purpose Letters of the 20 Instant from the Lord Ambassadors now in <em>England</em>, whereby we hear they give advice to the <reg orig="Lords">Lords'</reg> States, that the Treaty of Peace was not yet concluded, but that preparations for Sea were made there in <reg orig="al">all</reg> <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, the occasion <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> was unknown to them, which caused some <reg orig="suspitions">suspicions</reg>, and jealousies amongst the said <reg orig="Lords">Lords'</reg> States; Insomuch that the Vice Admiral <em>Ruyter</em>, and the Scout by night, <em>Tromp</em>, with other Captains received Orders to resort presently to <em>Amsterdam</em>, which they did accordingly Wednesday morning, as also several Messengers were dispatched to the Counsels of the Admiralties. The Lieut: Admiral: the Lord <em>Van Opdam</em> was likewise commanded to come from <em>Brabant</em> where he was, hither.</p>
<p>And yet we cannot understand by the Letters come from <em>London</em> the night between the 20. and 21. that any difficulties should have arisen wherefore the Treaty should not go on, so that it is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> that the same may have a good success, and that those preparations made there may be for some other design. We have very little certainty of the Scottish Affairs. It is presumed that <em>Middleton</em> is arrived in <em>Scotland</em> to gather what forces he can to restore the titular King his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> Fortune. Last night a Pink hath been by the <reg orig="Lords">Lords'</reg> States dispatched from <em>Scheveling</em> into <em>England</em>, though he be but stirring up <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> to <reg orig="boyl">boil</reg>, which without question will break this Spring.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 29.</head>
<p>There is a Relation come to our hands, printed in <em>Holland, France</em>, and <em>Flanders</em>, and hath been <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> upon as a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of Rarity in <reg orig="al">all</reg> places where it came, <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> at the first publishing of it in England, me thinks it should be thought as Rare, as it is proved acceptable in other places; the thing is this.</p>
<p>In the time of the Wars in France between the King, and the P: of Conde, <reg orig="wher">where</reg> the Town of <em>Mollorayes</em> was besieged, two Virgins (more <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> for <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> of descent) being tender of Age, and sensible of the violations of unruly soldiers, apprehending that upon the <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up of the Forts of the Town, the fortresses of their chastity would also be shaken, whereupon they <reg orig="studdy">study</reg> a way as much as in them lies) to defend both, and so betake themselves to <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> apparel, and come into trail a Pike amongst the rest of the Volunteers.</p>
<p>Under which condition they behaved themselves very gallantly, and after that in several other Warlike <reg orig="atcheivements">achievements</reg>, they both gained honour, and applause, and yet more particularly one of them, who named <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> <em>Anthony Lesperance</em>, was advanced to the degree of a Captain, in a short time, and at seven several fights <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg>, so much valour, and gallantry, that she obtained the place of a <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>, shortly after there <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> another great Fight at St: Cruses, where the other Comrade (which was then no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Captain was slain in <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, whereof this valiant Colonelless has speedy notice, and commanded a party to rescue the dead body of this <reg orig="Virgine">Virgin</reg> Captain, chiefly because the Sex should be undiscovered.</p>
<p>This <reg orig="busines">business</reg> met with great opposition, and cost above 500 <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> lives, but after all the body was taken away by <pb n="6" />this <em>Anthony Lesperance</em> and that party; after which the said <em>Anthony Lesperance</em> gave a Captain charge of the<reg orig="Corps">Corpse</reg>, and that the thing might be carried with the more secrecy, acquainted the Captain that it was the Body of a Woman who had <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> herself valiant in the Wars and for the Honour of her sex, and therefore gave him a charge to bury the body in private.</p>
<p>Shortly after this <em>Anthony Lesperance</em> was taken Prisoner at the <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg> of <em>Ashenburgh</em>, and falling into the hands of unruly soldiers, was so <reg orig="neerly">nearly</reg> <reg orig="stript">stripped</reg> that the sex was discovered, and made good the rescue of her Modesty, and having preserved her chastity amongst variety of Adventurers, resolved to spend her whole <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> a sacrifice to Piety, and so for her Honour was admitted in November last into the <reg orig="Cloyster">Cloister</reg> of <em>St: <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em>, where she now remains amongst the Daughters of Noble Personages.</p>
<p>Letters from <em>France</em> represent, that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is very sorry to understand the taking of Capt: <em>Beach</em> by the <em>Warnick</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, which being noised over all the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> in the morning, was contradicted at noon, but confirmed again in the evening; the taking of this Admiral hath possessed the rest with so great a fear, that the Letters say, they are afraid to venture <reg orig="any more">anymore</reg> in the Narrow, but are all going to <em>Toulon</em>, in the service of the King of <em>France</em>.</p>
<p>The killing of one of the Marquis of Plossermen, and the wounding of another by Pr: <em>Rupert</em>, one of his Gentlemen is so ill resented, that an Order was coming forth for the banishment of the said Prince from the court, and Kingdom of <em>France</em>, which is since demurred upon, this makes little for the affairs of the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, whose condition was there low enough before. We have taken his week (say the Letters from <em>Scotland</em>) divers who were going to assist the <em>Highlanders</em>, whose Army is marched more Northwards <reg orig="then">than</reg> it was; there is a Report that the titular <em>Scots</em> King was to Marry the Daughter of <em>Lorraign</em>, and that the Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> is to marry the Son of the Emperor of <em>Germany</em>; this is all for the present.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 30.</head>
<p>What more thunderbolts yet? Is this all we can say of Peace during all this Treaty betwixt us and <em>Holland</em> would nor any man think it sufficient, when that men are to treat upon indifference which concern themselves, that they should agree for themselves, and leave the rest to stand or fall upon their own <reg orig="legges">legs</reg> is not sufficient that we are like to loose money by the parties themselves, but upon their account we should loose more by others; but me thinks this doth not <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the Reader, therefore more particularly thus: these Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> have protracted much time to little purpose, unless they suddenly conclude for themselves amp; leave out <em>Denmark</em>, about which they pretend they must have new Instructions, or Orders from their Superiors, and have sent Letters accordingly, and the States have sent Letters unto them: In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> Action grows ripe both for Sea and Land, (and truly we have seldom failed of good success after a Fast)</p>
<p>At a late <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of the <em>Holland</em> Fleet they talk of 300 sail, besides 50 <reg orig="Fireships">Fire ships</reg>, and at a Land <reg orig="randezvous">rendezvous</reg> in <em>Scotland</em> they give forth of themselves, that they are 10000 Foot, and 7000 <reg orig="pitifull">pitiful</reg> Horse; and still they are forcing the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and fed with such fond thoughts from beyond Sea, that the common <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> begin to vapour, and say that at their next <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> they will cry, <em>Vive Le Roy</em>.</p>
<p>Now to let you understand how this business is <reg orig="ballanced">balanced</reg>, take notice that the English fleet is floating upon the Narrow seat in a most stately <reg orig="Equippage">Equipage</reg>, both for gallantry, and number. Also the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> <em>Ireland</em> in a gallant posture of Peace, and <reg orig="quietnes">quietness</reg>, is returned safe, and in <em>Scotland</em> (for all the proud boasts of the Enemy) our Army desire nothing more, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to have a fair combat with them.</p>
<p>We have given satisfaction before of the Audience of the <em>French</em> Ambassador, and his Speech. I wish the difference (which brake forth into blows) between the <em>French</em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Gentlemen, and the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassadors at <em><reg orig="Towerhill">Tower hill</reg></em> after their landing, may not prove a bad <em>Omen</em>.</p>
<p>We have Intelligence of 5 ships more taken this week, and of a fight about an hour long betwixt 5 of the <em>Dutch</em>, and 3 English, and the <em>English</em> took 2 of the <em>Dutch</em>.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>