<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell09">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Every Day's Intelligence, Issue 9</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Publisher of Every <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1">Army, under the Command of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg></head>
<head level="2">The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Cromwell</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland, Ireland,</em> and other parts.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 16 of <em>Decemb.</em> to <em>Friday</em> the 23. of <em>December,</em> 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">LONDON, Printed by <i>J.C. &amp; T.W</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday,</i> December, 16.</head> 
<p>Changes are agreeable to the nature of man, be it for better, or for the worse, and it is the event crowneth all things : Of all the Changes that have been of late years, this is most probably good for the whole Nation, for now the Government is invested in those hands that are (under God) able and willing to protect us from Invasion, maintain peace at home, Treat with <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Nations, and in due time ease us of our burdens, encourage (and not put down) our Ministers, and <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Debts, in furtherance whereof the late Parliament have made an Act of the <em>26.</em> of <em>September</em> last, whereby they have granted Lands to the Adventurers, and likewise Bills and Debenters, which I suppose will be a good Accommodation for those who intend there to inhabit or plant. And it is remarkable <pb n="1" /> what <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> provision they have made therein for desolate <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg>, &amp; c. But to speak as the truth is, they have not therein made Provision for <unclear>stating</unclear> your Debenters, who have not served in <em>Ireland</em>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they do (in a manner) promise it yet by the Act <unclear>of the</unclear> 19. of <em>October</em> last, they have <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> the Committee of <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> Army, to <unclear>cause the</unclear> <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> of all Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that either are or were in the Service of this Commonwealth at any time since the 15. of <em>January</em>, 1647. to be stated, audited, and cast <unclear>up</unclear>. But not for those who were disbanded before.</p>
<p>Nevertheless though some were contented to accept of Lands in <em>Ireland</em>, the rest would not be satisfied, but expected payment of their Bills and Debenters, from the <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg> and Chases, which was given by the old Parliament, for <reg orig="Collaterall">Collateral</reg> Security, in the Act of the 15. of <em>July</em>, 164 , But incontinently this late dissolved Parliament have put the <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Faith upon doubling thereupon wherein it is to be feared there will be double dealing, and that the needy Creditors will be exposed (as it were) to be sold for a little silver, and the poor for the price of a pair of <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>; for they being not able to double, must be constrained in the midst of their great extremities to sell their <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Debts at an inconsiderable value, with many <reg orig="sighes">sighs</reg> and tears into the bargain: And of all the <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg> they have reserved but four for the <reg orig="Collaterall">Collateral</reg> Security for the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers'</reg> Bills chargeable upon the late <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Lands, and that with such <reg orig="delatory">dilatory</reg> Conditions, whereby their <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear> are frustrate, though they earned their wages with <unclear>the <!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> of their lives and dearest blood.</p>
<p>The Act of the 7. of <em>October</em> last, which is for <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> <unclear>Creditors</unclear> to bring or send in their Claims of <unclear>the <!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> to the <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> others therein named, is said to be for the duty rating and clearing of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Debts in order to their payment. It also promiseth payment to the discoverer of his proper Debt : But as the Act for Marriage is deficient, without telling how long they shall hold together, So this act is lame in <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> respects, It tells you of stating, and of paying, but not by whom, nor when; therefore it is not amiss for you to Petition for an <reg orig="Additionall">Additional</reg> Act, or that the remains of that Bill which was read, and ordered to be read again by the old Parliament, <em>Novemb.</em> 30. 1652. may pass for your better Security. And the 12. Undertakers be sufficiently <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> upon this, certain men have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> to discover 500000.l. for payment of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Debts: I know many of you are very <unclear><!--approx 14 characters--></unclear> either, though more able; cannot spare money out <pb n="2" /> of their Trading to double. You have waited many years with such patience, and have laboured many <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, and attained experience of the sad Calamities of the people more <reg orig="then">than</reg> before, I have in my progress seen the dissolution of a Golden Parliament, coveting profit, And a Parliament choice as silver, labouring for Credit, consisting (as was said) most of Religious and conscientious men, in whom the best affected had hopes of good, But a House divided against <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> cannot stand. The News of this will go to <em>Rome</em>, but let not the uncircumcised in heart <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> and triumph. Most men upon this dissolution take occasion to cry Aha, Aha, and to speak their pleasure, but prudence may teach them when and how to speak. Indeed, the occasion of their dissolution is known to many, but few do rightly consider the cause to be that in matters <reg orig="Fundamentall">Fundamental</reg> they laid aside <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> most <reg orig="rightcous">righteous</reg> Law, and leaned to their own; wherefore their dissolution was of God, who <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, <em>I will have mercy, and not sacrifice</em>. It proceeds from the Lord of Hosts, who hath determined to <reg orig="staine">stain</reg> the pride of all Glory, and to bring into contempt all the <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> of the Earth.</p>
<p>This evening that Reverend Divine Dr. <em>Gouge</em> of <reg orig="Black-Fryers">Blackfriars</reg>, was buried.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb. 17.</head>
<p>The late Parliament having upon their dissolution delivered up the Power which they received from his Excellency at their first sitting, by a Writing under their Hands and <reg orig="Seall">Seal</reg>, his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg> thereupon called a Council of Officers, and advised with other persons of Interest in the Nation, how this great <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of governing <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, with the Armies therein, and Navy at Sea should be <reg orig="born">borne</reg>, and by whom; who after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> seeking of God, and advising therein. It was resolved that a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of godly, able, and discreet persons should be named, consisting of 21. And that his Excellency should be chosen Lord <reg orig="Protectour">Protector</reg> of the three Nations. In pursuance hereof <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons of Eminency and worth, are already made choice of to be of the said Council, which are not fit to be mentioned <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear>. And His Excellency came down to <em>Westminster</em>; and was installed Lord Protector of the three Nations, the same time.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Decemb. 19.</head>
<p>Yesterday Mr. <em>Peters</em> <reg orig="preacht">preached</reg> at <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> before the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg>, &amp; c. His Text was <em>Cant</em>. 2. 17. <em>Hasten my well beloved, and be like a Roe, or a young Hart upon the Mountains of Spices.</em></p>
<p>The point that he raised was, That the Saints or people of God do earnestly desire the coming of Jesus Christ unto the last Judgment, for then shall they see him as he is. They shall be glorified with him, and they shall be righted of all the wrongs, injuries, or oppressions done unto them.</p>
<p>His <reg orig="counsell">counsel</reg> was then to the people of God (that look for the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of CHRIST) that they should keep at home in the <reg orig="exercize">exercise</reg> of Truth and Peace; Illustrating it by the <reg orig="comparrison">comparison</reg> of a Loving Wife, who would be <reg orig="carefull">careful</reg> not to be abroad when she expected her Husband to come home. He exhorted them earnestly to increase and grow in grace and holiness, reprehending such as lay aside the Law, and maintain errors; thinking themselves the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> People, and would have all the World submit unto them, though envy, hatred, and malice was never more rife <reg orig="then">than</reg> at this Day.</p>
<p>He also exhorted the people to remember, that although the Government of the State were as changeable as the Prophet <em>Jeremy</em> speaketh of the Government in his time (which he compareth to a way-faring man) yet their duty, was to desire and look for the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of Christ.</p>
<p>He commended the time past when there was heard singing of <reg orig="Psalmes">Psalms</reg>, &amp; c. and reproved <reg orig="Errours">Errors</reg>.</p>
<p>He also <reg orig="spake">spoke</reg> favourably of those on the other side of the water, and concluded with advice to the present Governors, that they should exercise their places in the <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> distributing of Justice and Right unto all.</p>
<p>This day the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> of <em>London</em>, the Sheriffs and Aldermen with their Officers (all in their Gowns) met at <em>Guild-Hall</em>, and from thence went to <reg orig="Temple-Barre">Temple-Bar</reg>, where they met the <reg orig="Heraulds">Heralds</reg> at Arms, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> of the States in their Coaches, and from <reg orig="Temple-Barre">Temple-Bar</reg> they came to <em>Cheapside</em> and the <em><reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Exchange</em> and published this Proclamation following with sound of Trumpets in great state.</p>
<head level="2">BY THE COUNCIL</head>
<p><go>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving <unclear>themselves</unclear>, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, by a <pb n="4" /> LORD PROTECTOR, and successive <reg orig="Trienniall">Triennial</reg> Parliaments, is now established; And whereas OLIVER CROWELL Captain General of all the forces of this Commonwealth is declared LORD PROTECTOR of the said nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make publication of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, and strictly to Charge and Command all, and every person and persons, of what quality or condition soever, in any of the said three nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, <reg orig="Maiors">Mayors</reg> Bailiffs, and other <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Ministers, and Officers, whom this may concern, are required to cause this PROCLAMATION to be <unclear>forthwith</unclear> published in their respective Counties, Cities, Corporations, and <unclear>Market Towns</unclear>, To the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</go> Given at White-Hall this 16. of December. 1653.</p>
<p><em>Dalkeith</em> 15. Decemb. 1653. Yesterday there came Intelligence, That the 10. instant Cap. <em>Lisle</em> of Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> Regiment, hearing of a party <reg orig="off">of</reg> the enemy about ten miles of his Quarters marched in the night from <em>Munros</em> with 100. Horse and <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg>, and fell upon them by break of day, near <em><reg orig="Glams">Glamis</reg></em>, took 40. Horse, and 19. private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, two Captains of Horse, one Cornet, and one <reg orig="Quarter-master">Quartermaster</reg>, and killed nine or ten of them, all of them of the Earl of <reg orig="Kinouls">Kinoul's</reg> Regiment, which he was raising in <em>Angus</em> and the <em>Mearns</em>. The next day Col. <em>Morgan</em> having notice of a party of them in <em>Eghil</em> a strong house in <em>Angus</em>, near the Hills marched towards it, but the enemy having notice, fled away upon his approach, he pursued and took 15. Horse, but the Lord <em>Kinoule</em>, and his Lieutenant Col. <em>Ramsey</em>, who were with them, escaped. They still go on with their Levies, and stealing Horses, though they spoil many good horses through hard riding, and ill looking to, and lately 15. <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> out of one <reg orig="Lairds">Laird's</reg> ground. Another party of ours took some of these Bobtails <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Aberdeen</em>, yet they increase; most of them are now gone Northward to receive some Arms landed from <em>Holland</em>.</p>
<p>A party of Major Gen. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Regiment were at the heels of Col. <em>Wogan</em>, and those that came with him at <em>Kelfish</em>, but they recovered the Hills before they could have full scent of them: It's supposed he and some others landed in Lancashire, have Commissions and Instructions from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<p><em>Pool</em>, Decemb. 9. Here hath not occurred anything worthy of your cognisance. About 14. days since, Capt. <em>Green</em>, Commander of a private Man of War, brought a Prize into this Harbour, pretending to be a Dunkirk, she hath about 114. <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of French Wine on board, &amp; <reg orig="cam">came</reg> from <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg>, the Master is a Scotchman, put in as is supposed for colour only, which with other circumstances, give great expectation that she will prove a Prize.</p>
<p>By letters from <em>Scotland</em> we understand, that the desperate people of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Factions (great in their numbers, but few in Arms) have made many <reg orig="inrodes">inroads</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <em>English</em> Garrisons, for they came into <em>Fife</em> and took seven or eight good Horses from the Earl of <em>Weems</em>. Another small Party came within 4. miles of <em>Leith</em>, and meeting with an English Gentleman, who was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by the Commissioners to gather in the Rents of the <reg orig="Cole-Pits">Coal Pits</reg>, <reg orig="stab'd">stabbed</reg> him to the heart; other exploits of this nature have been done <reg orig="neere">near</reg> <em>Barwick</em> by such as are <reg orig="tearmed">termed</reg> Moss-Troopers, a few whereof possessing themselves of a piece of boggy ground in the West of <em>Scotland</em>, get out upon parties, carrying a board along with them, and when they have done what mischief they can abroad, if they <reg orig="finde">find</reg> themselves pursued, they retreat into the said boggy place, and run their horses over the <reg orig="Flote">Float</reg> upon the board, over which it is both difficult and dangerous for any to follow them.</p>
<p>By a Letter intercepted from one of their own party, thus. All our Commissioned Officers are going now to their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Localltties">Localities</reg> for Levies (which was not till now determined upon) both of Horses and Foot: The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses in Perthshire, and the whole Foot thereof: <em>Kinoule</em> hath the Horses of the shire of Angus and Mearns: <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> is to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses out of Caithness, Sutherland, Rosse, and Murray, and to be Commander in chief of the Forth levied there. <em>Kenmore</em> is to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> the Horses of the shire of Aberdeen. Col. <em>Blakader</em> of Tulliallen is to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> in a part of the shire of <em>Fife</em>. Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> left us two nights, being discontented for not getting a Locality on the North side of Forth; he was and is Gentleman Quartermaster, and is again reconciled, and is to have Sterlingshire for a Locality, for levying the horses there.</p>
<p>We are now about 1000. good, well armed, resolute foot, and five hundred Horse, the Riders are singularly good, they and the Horses are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> ill equipaged, saddles and bridles that are <pb n="6" /> good, are rare here: I have sent you a purse-penny. I <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> that <reg orig="mite">might</reg> be not a word of two others. This is all, I remain, &amp; c.</p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Lilburn hath set out this Engagement to be <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the People as followeth.</p>
<p><i>I A. B. do hereby oblige me my being and executors, That I shall and will live peaceably under the Command of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, and that I, or any other under my Command shall not act <unclear><!--approx. 6 characters--></unclear> in prejudice of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England aforesaid, in aiding and assisting the Highlanders and others now in arms, and who hereafter shall be in arms against the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in Person or in <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg>, advice, means, or any other <unclear>manner</unclear> of way whatsoever, under the penalty of <unclear>forfeiture</unclear> of <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--> and of the</unclear>, and to be proceeded against as the Parliament of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, or those <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> by them shall appoint, In witness whereof I have subscribed the same the day of <unclear><!--approx. 7 charcters--></unclear> in the year of our Lord 1653.</i></p>
<p>It is advertised, that one Deputed from the K. of <em>France</em> came to <reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg>, where he had audience before the Senate to whom he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> his Commission to arrest all English Merchants and their Goods, in the <reg orig="reprisall">reprisal</reg> of 14. Nuns, who intending from <em>France</em> to <em>Poland</em> were taken by the English at Sea. The Senate at <em><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg></em> hath taken this into consideration.</p>
<p><i>From the <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> we hear that the French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> do fly <reg orig="too">to</reg> and again about the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> <unclear>end</unclear> and have lately taken a small Vessel of <unclear>ours</unclear> belonging to Bristol, <unclear>herewith</unclear> also, news that the Dutch have lately taken two English <unclear>Merchant</unclear> men coming from <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> France <reg orig="ladin">laden</reg> with <unclear><reg orig="Brandey wine">Brandywine</reg></unclear>, the <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> was 50. <reg orig="tun">ton</reg>; And she the other 60.</i></p>
<p><i>The last <unclear>Letters</unclear> from <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> <reg orig="advertize">advertise</reg> that the French have raised the <reg orig="seige">siege</reg> at <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters--></unclear> but they have taken a thousand Spaniards amongst whom were three Hundred Officers.</i></p>
<p><i>The titular Scots King is very merry; the <reg orig="rumur">rumour</reg> <unclear><reg orig="gos">goes</reg></unclear> that he will leave France this next summer, Some say he will go for <em>Germany</em>, but others say <unclear><!--approx. 13 characters--></unclear> according to his expectations he will turn his <reg orig="cours">course</reg> for the North.</i></p>
<p><i>The last <unclear>mention but</unclear> letters from the Lord <em>Scaford</em> and others of those Lords in <em>Scotland</em>, who boast highly of their increase in numbers, <reg orig="perswading">persuading</reg> him that the <em>English</em> scarce dare to <reg orig="peepe">peep</reg> out of their Garrisons, and they wonder that he is able to send them no <reg orig="ayde">aid</reg>, neither in men nor money, desiring him to be with in what he formerly Promised unto them.</i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="2">An Instrument for settling the present</head>
<p>Government, In substance is as followeth,</p>
<p>1. <i>That the <em><reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg></em> <reg orig="Legisletive">Legislative</reg> power of <em>England</em> Scotland and Ireland, shall be and reside in one single Person, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of thirteen at the least, and twenty one at the most, and the Commons assembled in Parliament.</i></p>
<p>2. <i>That this single person shall be called <em>The Lord Protector</em> of <em>England Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>
<p>3. <i>That there be constant <reg orig="Trianial">Triennial</reg> Parliaments, and the first to begin the third of September <em>1654</em></i></p>
<p>4. <i>That the <em>Parliament</em> shall have power of making Laws, except in some Cases relating to the safety of the <em><reg orig="Common-Wealth">Commonwealth</reg></em> of the three <em>Nations</em>, and matters of <em>Religion</em>, for which there is particular provision made in the <em>Instrument</em> containing the <em>Government</em>.</i></p>
<p>5. <i>That all <em>Bills</em> that pass in <em>Parliament</em> shall be offered to the Lord <em>Protector</em> for his consent, and if he consent not within 20 days, this are to notwithstanding to become Laws.</i></p>
<p>6. <i>That the Lord <em>Protector</em> is to be <em>Elective</em> and not <em><reg orig="Hereditory">Hereditary</reg></em> and to be chosen by the <em>Council</em>, <reg orig="immeadiatly">immediately</reg> after the death of the L. <em>Protector</em>.</i></p>
<head level="2">The Names of the Council.</head>
<p>Mr. Laurence, president.</p>
<p><reg orig="Maior">Major</reg> General Lambert.</p>
<p><reg orig="Maior">Major</reg> General Skipon.</p>
<p><reg orig="Maior">Major</reg> Gen. Disbrow.</p>
<p>Sir Charles Worsly.</p>
<p>Mr. Rouse.</p>
<p>Lord Viscount Lisle.</p>
<p>Colonel Jones.</p>
<p>Colonel Seyclamham.</p><p>Sir Gilbert Pickering.</p>
<p>Mr Anthony Ashley Cooper.</p>
<p>Mr. Strickland</p>
<p>Mr. Mayor Esquir.</p>
<p>His Highness hath set forth a Proclamation with the consent of his said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; for continuing all Persons being in Office, for the executing <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Justice till his Highness further direction.</p>
<head level="3">Thus have you Passages concerning,</head>
<p><i>An <em>Instrument</em> or <em>Writing</em> of the present <em>Government</em> both of the <em>Church</em> and <em>State</em> of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, subscribed by his <em>Highness</em> the Lord <em>Protector</em>, with his <em><reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg></em> Speech, and the names of the <em>Council</em>. A Sermon preached by Mr. <em>Peters</em> upon the present change of <em>Government</em>. The time of calling another <em>Parliament</em>, And a fight between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, With the Lord <em>Protector's</em> Proclamation.</i></p> 

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>