<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell12">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue 12</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Publisher of Every <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1">Army, under the Command of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg></head>
<head level="2">The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> CROMWELL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland, Ireland,</em> and other parts.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 6. of <em>January.</em> to <em>Friday</em> the 13. of <em>January</em>, 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">LONDON, Printed by <i>J.C. &amp; T.W</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, January 6.</head> 
<p>The Deputies from <em>Holland</em> having taken their leave, and going down to <em>Gravesend</em>, in order to their return home, without giving that satisfaction as was expected touching the Treaty, the chief Council of this Nation sent a Letter after them, by way of explanation of some things in the Articles which had been Treated on, wherein the Dutch Deputies seemed not to be <reg orig="satified">satisfied</reg> at the time of their going away; and <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Desbrow</em> having some further conference with them at <em>Gravesend</em>, they made some further application to to the Council, whereof more hereafter; Now it is observable, that about the time they broke off the Treaty there was the fearfullest Tempest at <em>Amsterdam</em> that we have read of, the manner thus:</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>This day the great calamity in <em>Holland</em> was certified thus, That the Lightning leaping from the clouds, whom the Thunder chid, the Houses began to take fire, and that 500. of them suddenly were devoured by it. At the same time the wind arising, the Billows in vast tumults began to move towards the Town, as if they made haste to put out the fire. By the high workings of the Sea the Mariners did presage the danger 10. <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> and therefore used all their art and care to keep their Ships at a distance, lest in the foulness of the weather, they should fall foul on one another, but their diligence could not make that quick <reg orig="dispacsh">dispatch</reg>, before a most violent gust clapped them together, and being involved in one danger, about 40. of them did suffer in one <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>
<p>But other (to whom rather I incline) do affirm that the fire was four miles from <em>Amsterdam</em>, at their Rope Mills, where were their stores both of Hemp and <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, which served to increase the flame, 400. houses are said to be there burned, and about 30. ships sunk by the Tempest.</p>
<head level="3">January the 10.</head>
<p>By this Post from Scotland it was certified, that by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a pretended Commission from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, <em>Glencarn</em>, whom the Highlanders call their <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, issueth forth Warrants for the levying of men, horse, and Arms in a high nature, beginning thus:</p>
<p><em>James</em> <em>Earl of Glencarn and Kenmore</em>, <unclear><!-- approx. 2 characters--></unclear>. The care straightly to charge and command you, to levy and have in readiness out of your <reg orig="Shierdome">Shiredom</reg>, 100. horse well manned and <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters--></unclear>, by the day of <em>January</em>; at which time you shall receive further Orders from me, to repair to such place of <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> as shall be appointed: Whereof you are not to <unclear>fail</unclear>.</p>
<p>Our men are drawn forth of <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and other Garrisons, and are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> chasing the Enemy from place to place, and daily take many of these Thieving Villains, and their Regiments are marched from hence towards Scotland. It is likely they would soon be <reg orig="quell'd">quelled</reg> if they would stand to fight.</p>
<p>From <em>Portsmouth</em> they write, That a <reg orig="Squdron">Squadron</reg> of our Fleet have taken very lately six Prizes from the Hollanders.</p>
<p>The preparations in <em>Holland</em> for war is very great, and they talk of some great matters agreed upon betwixt them and the French, but nothing openly declared, till they <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> what becomes of their Treaty with England.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Holland</em> thus</i>,</head>
<p>We daily expect 150 ships from the Sound, <reg orig="severall">several</reg> men of War are gone for their Convoy. The Ordnance brought from Sweden have been <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> at Amsterdam, there are 500 Pieces, most part half Garrows. Captain Nicholas Pater hath taken an English Ketch before Hull, another at Flamborough head, a Flute of 12 Guns, and 4 of Wood, of about 130 Lasts, with Hemp, Flax, Coals, and some Salt-peter. Also near Whitebay <reg orig="Pinuace">Pinnace</reg> of six Guns, with refined Salt, and one by the Hover, Laden with Salmon, <reg orig="Sheep-skins">Sheep skins</reg>, and Herrings; but the loss of Captain Hans <reg orig="Maigarens">Maigaren's</reg> ship, a man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> with 18 Guns, which we hear the English have taken near Newcastle, is worth almost all these; and we hear of eight ships taken from the Caribes, with Sugar, Tobacco, and other Merchandize, with their Convoy of 30. Guns. Eight of the <reg orig="New-foundland">Newfoundland</reg> Fleet we took, are made men of War. We have taken a Turkish ship, and another in Smyrna. One Goldshalk hath rowed an English prize 12 Guns into Brest. An English <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> met with 5 French ships of St. <em>Malla</em> took one called the Year of Grace, the Three Kings hardly escaped, not yet heard of, the other three are at Calice.</p>
<p>Cornelius Joast, with Thymen Theaneste, with the Ammunition are safely arrived from hence into Muscovia.</p>
<p>There came Letters of the Lord <em>Whitlock</em>, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, Novem. 18. of his Voyage and reception there, as followeth.</p>
<p>We began to set sail from <em>Gravesend</em>, Novemb. 8. <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> coming too much into the North, and being not able to get clear of the sands that day, we were enforced to cast Anchor near <em>Luinborow</em>, The next day the <reg orig="Winde">Wind</reg> standing fair, we set sail again, and made a very large course, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> about noon the day after, at which time the wind turned full against us, so that we were afraid that we should have been necessitated to put into <em>Yarmouth</em> Road. But the Wind <reg orig="favored">favoured</reg> us again for a little time, and we made forwards, yet it was not long ere we were very much becalmed; and so we were exercised with uncertainties of <reg orig="Windes">Winds</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 12instant, when there came a very fair <reg orig="Winde">Wind</reg>, which carried us on with full Sail, so that on the 14 instant at Night, we cast Anchor on this side the <em>Seagen</em>, and we came on the 15th betimes into the River. As we came along our Ship met with some Holland Fishermen, and boarded one of them, but my Lord Ambassador willing to pass peaceably over the Sea, released it again, which did <pb n="3" />exceedingly overjoy them, who had been undone in his own thoughts before; yet the <em>Elizabeth</em>, being one of the <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg> that <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> some of our Company, staying <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg> to bring up one of the Baggage ships, met with a <reg orig="finall">final</reg> Dutch Caper, and boarded it and brought it along with them. The next day we landed at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, where we were very nobly received by the <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> <reg orig="Majestrates">Magistrates</reg> of the town, and had much <reg orig="civillity">civility</reg> <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> us.</p>
<p>The Queen is now at <reg orig="Vpsahla">Uppsala</reg>, and we shall repair towards her Court with all convenient speed, but it is many miles and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are <reg orig="constained">constrained</reg> to <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> all the way by sand.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday; January</em> 9.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith</i>, January 3.</head>
<p>The 23. of <em>December</em>, the Enemy had a <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Hangh (a place of plain ground <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Weyme.) The parts about Weyme are miserably wasted, and the Gentlemen of <reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg> III resenting their oppression, <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glengary</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> North with about 200. Horse and Foot, intending to meet <em>Seafors</em> at Lagennongham Drum where their whole body intends to <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>: Before <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> going there was a falling out between <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glengary</em> and a Duel appointed, but prevented by the endeavours and wits of their Associates. <em>Wogan</em> with his 20. Cavaliers, are at present with <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Logiret, well mounted, Armed, and several of them in rich Apparel, which adds encouragement to the Highland fury. The Enemy have severally spoiled most of such horses as they have taken from <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's'</reg> stables, their bellies almost dived<em> </em>up with <unclear><!-- 5 characters--></unclear>, too much Corn, <unclear><!-- 4 characters--></unclear> ill drillings: Their Levies in Perthshire are at a stand; they get no men but some poor Rogues; and the penalty they impose upon the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> is, if they can take a rich man, they keep him till he can <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters--></unclear> himself; and take <reg orig="severall">several</reg> able bodied men out of their beds, and force them into forms, or make them hire others; but what addition they will have in the North is very uncertain.</p>
<p>On Friday last, the Earl of <reg orig="Kenole">Kinole</reg>, about 8. in the morning, appeared near <reg orig="Glams">Glamis</reg> with a party of Horse, consisting of 70. or thereabouts: his Design was to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the Horse belonging to <reg orig="Glams">Glamis</reg>, as they came from watering, lying in a covert place for that purpose, thinking thereby to increase his numbers, and to <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters--></unclear> exchange for his men taken at Edgill, and <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> at most with a small party riding into <reg orig="Glams">Glamis</reg>, took three of our men, which Major <em>Dufket</em> (who commanded Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Riches'</reg></em> Troop then) <pb n="4" />having notice, sent out his Quartermaster with 20. horse, to discover his party, who advancing with two files of Foot that were to make a good bridge, gave them a charge, and routed and dispersed their whole party, took the Lord Kinole and 14. more, all much wounded; about 35. horse; And at the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> away of the Letter, has sent out a party to gather up the rest, all quitting their Horses and betaking to the Bogs; Major Ramsay was there, but escaped. We had one man killed, and seven wounded all rightly; three of the Enemy were killed on the place, and our men that were taken; rescued.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January 10.</head>
<p>A Declaration by the Commander in Chief of the</p>
<p>Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p><go>Forasmuch as it is apparent, That not withstanding my Proclamation of Septemb. 27. last) many serviceable horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters--></unclear> of the Peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters--></unclear> of the <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> or Possessors: These are therefore <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> to require all manner of persons who <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear> are, in hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable Horses or shares, exceeding the value of <em>5</em>. l. sterling, to being the same within 48. hours next after the publication hereof, unto the next adjacent Garrison, or Quarters of our Army under the penalty not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of forfeiting treble the value of such horses and shares <unclear><!-- two words--></unclear> not be brought or; the one <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> thereof to two <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> of the State, and the other <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> to the party informing, but also be deemed an open Enemy, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly: Which Horses and shares <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters--></unclear> in, shall nevertheless be at the Droners <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear>, either to here meet satisfaction for them, as they shall be reasonably worth, or keep them within the said Garrisons or Quarters of our Army; And the respective Sheriffs and their Deputies within their Sheriffdoms, are hereby required, to cause these presents solemnly to be proclaimed and published, according to the accustomed manner of publishing Proclamations. And afterwards, (that none may pretend ignorance) to cause to be distributed to the several <reg orig="Pres">Press</reg> by <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> or within their said Sheriffdoms a competent number hereof.</go></p>
<p>Given under my hand and seal G. LILBURN.</p>
<p>At Dalkeith, 14. Decem. 1653.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> Janu. 11.</head>
<p><i>The Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassadors'</reg> Brother being removed from, Newgate to the Tower, is to receive his <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> at the Upper Bench Bar.</i></p>
<p>There is a Gentleman of quality who hath <reg orig="applyed">applied</reg> much of his industry in keeping in Memory those things which have happened of late years, and especially those things which Presage a Change or Alteration amongst the great Ones, and his Observation is this, That at the beginning of the <reg orig="Warres">Wars</reg> betwixt England and Holland, they had a great Inundation by Water, which proved very <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> to the whole Nation, and that in the time of a <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> of Treaty; So now about the time of breaking off the late Treaty with England, the before mentioned Thunder, Lightning and Tempest did them more hurt <reg orig="then">than</reg> the first, yea more <reg orig="then">than</reg> in the former Relations hath been declared, for that is <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> with such violence on the Capital <em>Church</em> at <em>Amsterdam</em>, that many living then did not only lose their Lives, but some of the dead were tumbled out of their Graves White sail <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> this may be to that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, we cannot of <unclear><!-- approx 5 characters--></unclear> in my conclude, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> looking back, we have observed, that before the late <reg orig="Warres">Wars</reg> in <em>England</em> much hurt was done in the streets, fields and High <reg orig="High wayes">Highways</reg> both in and about the City of <em>London</em> and elsewhere, and when the <em>Bishops</em> were upon the brink of their <reg orig="down-fall">downfall</reg>, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> found such a <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> and Tempest in the West upon the <reg orig="Lords">Lords'</reg> Day, that many were killed in the Church very strangely, and other the like Example in other Places.</p>
<p><i>From Newbottle it is certified, That Major <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters--></unclear> had Intelligence.</i></p>
<p><i>Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> being at the Kirk of Asterisk very fore bounded, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> had taken him had not an old K. near Peebles sent him notice of our Parties coming thither, whereupon he and one Capt. Steward fled towards the Hills, our party pursuing as far as they could <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> and a Moss-Trooper.</i></p>
<p><i>The enemy have now a garrison in Kolden about to <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters--></unclear> from <unclear>Dunbarton</unclear>, from whence they came come <reg orig="ayded">aided</reg> by <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> Galgrave, with about <em>80</em> foot last week to Dunbarton, and in the dead of the night took two of the Bailiff, and other principal men of the Town, to the number of thirty six, whom they <reg orig="threaton">threaten</reg> to keep till they send them in four horsemen, and <em>37</em> footmen for their levies.</i></p>
<p><i>The Commissioners for Creditors and poor prisoners, sit constantly <pb n="6" />in Salters Hall, all <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> done much good during the time of their sitting.</i></p>
<p><i>From France the Letters say, that there be twenty six Articles of High Treason drawn up against the Prince of Conde, and though he was once so exceeding popular that he was for a time able to maintain a war against the King; yet now be is fallen from the top of that slippery <reg orig="Pinacle">Pinnacle</reg> on which he <reg orig="climed">climbed</reg>, there be but few that can afford him a good word.</i></p>
<p><i>From Paris, Janua. <em>10. 1654. stilo novo</em>. The last news from our Army in Alsatia imply, That the Marshal de la Fevte hath invited Defort, and is now making his Lines of Communication, and other marks belonging to a Siege; there hath been several pieces of Ordnance drawn but of Nancy, which are on the way, and will come to the Leaguer as soon as any Batteries will be raised to plant them upon; the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> do Uxelles is to be Lieutenant General, and is expected to be there with <em>3000</em> men. This design hath much alarmed the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so much the more, since the yielding up of the strong Castle of Philipsburgh, which was taken by a surprisal without the loss of one: the manner thus, The Deputy <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> being gone a hunting with some of the high Officers of that Garrison, notice being given to <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> of the Cardinals creatures, be <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear> with alacrity that occasion, and being come into the place, be so prevailed upon the garrison, that be became <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> of the place, and this Deputy <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> being come in the evening, knowing not what had passed, found the bridge drawn up, and <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters--></unclear> denied him, whereupon he was forced to retire speedily. The Duke <unclear>d' Amville</unclear> being sent by the King <reg orig="ot">to</reg> Blois, to try once more whether he could prevail with the Duke of Orleans, and so bring him again to the Court, returned back this week, and the report is at Court, that he hath brought a very good answer, and that he will be shortly in this City, but others are of a contrary opinion. The Duke de Guise is still going on in his preparations for his intended design for Naples against the next Spring.</i></p>
<p><i>The States assembled in Provence are now sitting at Bagnole, where the Duke of Mercoeun the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and the other Procurators are also gone: they sit daily, and hope to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> many abuses, and redress grievances which much burthen the people there. The Charge of High Treason against the Prince of Conde is finished, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> it wants to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>. The Prince hath <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> a little Town and a Castle in Champagne, and plundered the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> pitifully. A List hath been brought to his Majesty of the Regiment of the Guard, which is found to consist of about <em>6000</em> men sit for service.</i></p> 
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> 12 <em><reg orig="Januury">January</reg></em>.</head>
<p>We had other Letters from Scotland, which <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Athol</em> being acquainted with the foregoing Declaration of Col. <em><reg orig="Lilburns">Lilburn's</reg></em>, he hath given order that his men shall seize upon all the horse they can fight on, saying that that the English do the like. There is certainly landed in the North of Scotland a ship laden with Arms from France, and <em>John A-Gaunt</em> a renowned <em>Highlander</em> who lives by the <reg orig="Sea side">Seaside</reg> on the utmost part of Scotland within 5 or 6 Leagues of Ireland, is very active in wasting over in small Hoys, such <reg orig="fugetive">fugitive</reg> <em>Irish</em> as will come unto them, Some of the Prisoners we have also lately taken, say that many of the Irish which went over into Spain are gotten away, and do render their service to the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorke">York</reg></em>, and indeed there is just cause to believe that there is some great <reg orig="designe">design</reg> carrying on to France; for that those of the <reg orig="war-like">warlike</reg> <reg orig="rase">race</reg> of the late King of <em>England</em> are all met together at <em>Paris</em>; viz. The titular King of Scots, the Duke of York, the Duke of Gloucester and Prince Rupert, and the K. of Scots made a great Feast at the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal, at which, was present also, the King of France and many Lords and <reg orig="Ladys">Ladies</reg> of the Court.</p>
<p><i>A List of the Prisoners taken at the late fight in Scotland.</i></p>
<p>The Lord <reg orig="Kinoule">Kinole</reg>, Captain Jo. English, Patrick Rosse of Dunder, William Meward, John Hamilton, Cap. James Blayer of Dalth, Capt. William Menis, Capt. Robert Linsey, Mr. David Grimes, Capt. Nipper, Capt. James Bowter, Henry Fetchery, Patrick Knock, Robert Jackson, Patrick Lane, John Stuart, Theodoe Barbow, Thomas Matins.</p>
<p>This day Gen. Blake, Gen. Desbrow and Gen. <reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg> sat in Council and Whitehall, and Gen. Pen is with the fleet at Sea.</p>
<p>The French Ambassador newly come over hath had Audience, and the Dutch Ambassadors may be at home by this time.</p>
<p>Thus have you Passages concerning,</p>
<p><i>The bringing of men and Arms into <em>Scotland</em> by <em>John A-Gaunt</em>. The <em>Highlanders</em> <reg orig="seting">setting</reg> up of their <em>Standard</em> at <em>Lough Tay</em>, and the <em>Orders</em> they have given for seizing all the <em>Horses</em> in the <em><reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg></em>. A great and mighty <em>Feast</em> and <em>Masking</em> made by the K. of <em>Scots</em> at which there was the King of <em>France</em>, the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorke">York</reg></em>, the Duke of <em>Gloucester</em>, Prince <em>Rupert</em> and many Lords and Ladies. The daily Proceedings of the Lord <em>Protector</em>, and Gen. <em>Blake</em>, <em>Gen.</em> <em><reg orig="Monke">Monck</reg></em>, and <em>Gen. Desbrow</em>. A List of <em>Prisoners</em> taken, and the <em>Declaration</em> of <em><reg orig="Coloneell">Colonel</reg> Lilburn</em>.</i> FINIS.</p>


<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>