<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$14#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $14#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> <reg orig="Ingaging">engaging</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, and a Fight in <em>Scotland</em>; A party of the <em>Highlanders</em> <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg>, and carrying away of prisoners from the borders of <em>England</em>; The landing of more Arms, and a thousand more Men <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the Enemy: A ship taken with four great Chests of silver. The Articles of Peace betwixt <em>England, Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em> now Proclaimed; the paying unto <em>England</em> one hundred and forty thousand pounds, and making further satisfaction. The Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> propositions, with the Articles t6reated upon there, and a notable Reply to the same; The <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> at Sea; And the making of new Farthings to pass through this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 21 of <em>April</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 28 of <em>April</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, April 21.</head>
<p>An Ordinance of pardon, and Grace to the People(and Subjects) of <em>Scotland</em>, is set forth by the Lord Protector; the effect whereof thus. His Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> with the advice of his Council, doth freely acquit, and discharge from all forfeitures, pains, penalties, restraints, Imprisonments, all persons not therein Excepted, for any matter, or thing by them, or any of them committed or done by Sea, or Land in relation to the late War, from and after the first of <em>May</em>, 1654 and the Persons, &amp; Estates particularly Excepted, are these, <pb n="1" /><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, James Stuart</em>, Sons of the late King of <em>England</em>, <em>James</em> late Duke of <em>Hamilton</em>, <em>John</em> Earl of <em>Crawford</em>, <em>James</em> Earl of <em>Callender</em>, The Earl of <em>Marshall</em>, The Earl of <em>Kelley</em>, <em>John</em> Earl of <em>Lawderdail</em>, <em>John</em> Earl of <em>Lowdown</em>, The Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, The Earl of <em>Athol</em>, The Lord Vic: of <em>Kenmore</em>, The Lord <em>Lorne</em>, The Lord <em>Machlin</em>, The Lord <em>Mountgomery</em>, <em>George</em> Lord <em>Spyvie</em>, The Lord <em>Chranston</em>, The Lord <em>Sincleer</em>, <em>Thomas Dayel, John Middleton</em>, <em>James</em> Vic: <em>Newburgh</em>, Lord <em>Bargany</em>, The Lord <em>Nappier</em>, Sir <em>Thomas Thompson</em>, <em>James Edmesser</em>, The Laird of <em>Womat</em>, <em>William</em> Earl of <em>Glencarn</em>.</p>
<p>Nevertheless provision is made in, and by the said Ordinance for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> a component Estate upon the Lady <em>Hamilton</em>, and other Ladies, and their Heirs <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> paying a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> yearly Revenue to the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and his Successors. And provision is also made that the persons hereafter named, do pay unto his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> his <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="Receit">Receipt</reg>, the several sums of money following, in respect of his, and their Estates.</p>
<p>(That is to say)</p>
<p><em>David Lesley</em> 4000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of <em>Douglas</em> 1000 <em>l.sterling</em>, Lord <em>Augus</em> 1000 <em>l.sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Selerig</em> 1000 <em>l.sterling</em>, The Heirs of the late Earl of <em>Buclench</em> deceased, 15000 <em>l.sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Galloway</em> 4000 <em>l.sterling</em>, <em>William</em> Earl of <em>Roxburgh</em>, 6000 <em>l.sterling</em>, <em>William</em> Lord <em>Cockeram</em> 5000 <em>l.sterling</em>, <em>James</em> Lord <em>Forrester</em> 2500 <em>l sterling</em>, <em>Philip Amstether</em> 1000 marks <em>sterling</em>, <em>James Drummond</em> 500 <em>l sterling</em>, <em>Henry Mawbe</em> 2500 <em>l.sterling</em>, <pb n="2" />Sir <em>James Levingston</em> 1500 <em>l sterling</em>, <em>William Murrey</em> 1500 <em>l sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Buchane</em> 1000 <em>l. sterling</em>, Lord Visc: <em>Dudup</em> 1500 <em>l.sterling</em>, Lord <em>Preston</em> 1500 <em>l: sterling</em>, Sir <em>Andrew Flesher</em> 5000 <em>l. sterling</em>, Sir <em>John Wancha</em> 2000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Berren</em> 5000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Winton</em> 2000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Buimater</em> 1000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Vivay</em> 3000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Quinsburgh</em> 4000 <em>l. sterling</em>, The earl of <em>Fitby</em> 6000 <em>l sterling</em>, Lord <em>Oustes</em> 1500 <em>l. sterling</em>, Lord <em>Gray</em> 1500 <em>l. sterling</em>, Sir <em>Henry Nicbet</em> 1000 <em>l sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Paumure</em> 10000 <em>l. sterling</em>, Lord <em>Dundee</em> 1000 <em>l. sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Arroll</em> 2000 <em>l sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Tullibardine</em> 1500 <em>l. sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Southisk</em> 3000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Hartfield</em> 2002 <em>l: sterling</em>, <em>William</em> Lord <em>Rosse</em> 3000 <em>l: sterling</em>, The Earl of <em>Dalhousie</em> 1500 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord Sample 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord <em>Boade</em> 1500 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord <em>Elphinston</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, <em>James</em> Lord <em>Cooper</em> 3000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord <em>Balnaude</em> 1500 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord <em>Rollock</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Earl of <em>Kingborn</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Lord <em>Bamfe</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Mr: <em>Robert Meldrum</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Sir <em>Robert Graham</em> 1000 <em>l: sterling</em>, Sir <em>Wil: Scot</em> of <em>Harden</em> 3000 <em>l: sterling</em>.</p>
<p>And many others upon the like account, which we have not room here to put in.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 24.</head>
<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April 18. <i>The Commander in chief being willing to use all means possible to prevent the further spreading of this Insurrection, (in which the people are mad from all parts to be <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg>) hath published the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Proclamation. The Forces in the North are much in the same posture our Horse is yet at <em>Dingwel</em>, and the Enemy in <em>Sutherland</em>, where it is very probable they cannot get away without <reg orig="Ingaging">engaging</reg>. Amongst the party which were defeated about nine <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since at <em>Kilowoch</em>, the Earl of <em>Selkeithe</em>, who was just run to the Enemy was one, the Rebels at his coming to <em>Abersoyl</em> took him for an Enemy shot him in the face, and wounded two others of his party. A party from <em>Dalkeith</em> this day took eleven Horse, and yet nothing but <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, or the Gallows will tame, or <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg> these Rogues.</i></p>
<head level="3">A PROCLAMATION.</head>
<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in chief of all the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>
<p>Whereas (amongst other things) by Proclamation of the 27 of <em>Septemb</em>. 1653. al <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> and Officers of Burghs and Parishes, and all other persons whatsoever, are required to secure, or give Intelligence of all suspected persons, travelling through, or abiding within their bounds, or jurisdictions, as in and by the said Proclamation more particularly is expressed: Notwithstanding nothing to this time hath been effectually done, but on the contrary, divers Rebels, as well considerable numbers as Spies, have been, and still are frequently permitted and suffered to pass, march through, and abide in any Burgh or Parish within the quarters of our Army unquestioned, as if no rebellion were, who thereby take opportunity, not only to get Intelligence, but also to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> many loose persons to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in Rebellion; and commit frequent Robberies, and barbarous <reg orig="Murthers">Murders</reg>, and other outrages upon the persons, goods, and <reg orig="geer">gear</reg>, as well of <em>Scots</em> as of <em>English</em>. These are therefore strictly to charge and command, that no person or persons, of what degree or quality soever (not being a Member of the English Army) do presume after ten days next after publication hereof, to pass above five miles from his, and their respective abodes or habitations, unless he or they have first obtained a Pass from <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, or the Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, for the time being, or from the next chief Officer of the English Army, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 25.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Opsal in Sweden, March <em>24</em>.</i></head>
<p>I Begin now to believe, that we shall receive a Dispatch; and though in respect of some things they offer, we seem to be at some distance; yet I have such a <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the noble Lady will find out such an expedient, that satisfaction will be amply given to both Nations And this to be as the last Act of her Reign, which in my poor <reg orig="judgment">judgement</reg> is a great pity, for certainly she is as accomplished a Princess, as ever had the honour of swaying a <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>; and though the <em>French</em>, being <reg orig="riged">rigged</reg> to their salique laws, will not permit the distaff to intermeddle with a Crown; yet had they such a Virgin to rule amongst them, they would hereafter blot out such a law out of their Records as being mightily prejudicial to their advantage. On Thursday last, my Lord Ambassador, and Count <em>Erick</em> had a meeting to Debate upon the articles of Union; at which time Count <em>Erick</em> <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> several Articles on the behalf of <em>Sweden</em>, most of which were the same my Lord first gave in, but some did differ exceedingly, so that my Lord has totally waved them. Yesterday his Excellency went to the Queen to give in his Exceptions, and reasons why he could not admit of them, but this day Count <em>Erick</em> came again to my Lord, and did very much press, that his Articles propose I might be admitted, but my Lord is very positive not to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> thereunto.</p>
<head level="3"><i>March <em>25</em>. Four Propositions of the Queen to the Prince.</i></head>
<p>1. She will retain the best part of the Kingdom, and the Customs to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>.</p>
<p>2. She will be no Subject, but free of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> without control.</p>
<p>3. She will travel whither she pleaseth.</p>
<p>4. She will not revoke those Gifts of hers; which are <unclear><!-- two words--></unclear>, and were by her given, out of favour, to Courtiers.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Prince his Reply.</i></head>
<p>1. He <reg orig=" wil "> will </reg> not be a King without a Kingdom, or at least without the better part of it.</p>
<p>2. He <reg orig=" wil "> will </reg> have no Rival, more than she a Superior.</p>
<p>3. He will not hazard himself about her Designs abroad.</p>
<p>4. He will not be without a Revenue sufficient both for Wars and Peace.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, April 25.</head>
<p>This Day we had News from Saint <em>Mallo</em> in <em>France</em>, that the Governor hath made stay of all the <em>English</em> Merchants there.</p>
<p>A man come from Rye yesterday, affirmed, that about <em>Friday</em> the last week a ship was brought Prize in thither, laden with 300 Chests of money, besides great quantity of Sugars, Nutmegs and other Spices; so that Sugars were sold some for 3 <em>d.</em> some for 4 <em>d.</em> the pound, and Nutmegs, some for 2 <em>d</em>, some for 3 <em>d.</em> the hundred, <em>&amp; c.</em></p>
<p>This Day was <reg orig="Poclaimed">Proclaimed</reg> the long expected Peace with <em>Holland</em>: There was present at the Royal Exchange the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of the City of <em>London</em> in their scarlet Robes, <reg orig="accomodated">accommodated</reg> with their Officers, and many Trumpeters. After the Proclamation was read, the People made a great shout, and the Proclamation, or Ordinance then Proclaimed, was this.</p>
<head level="3"><i>By the Council at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</i></head> 
<p>Whereas a Peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <em>States General</em> of the <em>United Provinces</em> of the <em>Low <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg></em>. And the Lord Protector considering how necessary it is to preserve Peace, and Unity, hath concluded Peace to continue <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> between this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the United Provinces from this Day; From which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after 10 days, within these Seas; And in all other places on this side the Cape of Saint <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks; And from thence, within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranian">Mediterranean</reg></em> Sea, and to the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line, after ten weeks; And beyond the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em>, after the space of eight <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg>: Which several spaces were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to all others, whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof; To the end, they may have warning, to provide for their own safety, <pb n="6" />and not expose their Ships to danger within the several, and respective times aforesaid. Signed, O: P.</p>
<p>Having given you the Generals of the manner of Proclaiming the said Peace, we shall a little look back again upon the particulars, <em>viz</em>. About 12 of the clock this day (at full Change) appeared in <em>Corahill</em> (after they had been in Cheapside a considerable number of Horsemen, and Officers of the Army in a gallant <reg orig="Equippage">Equipage</reg>, (as Gentlemen) without Pistol, or holster, before whom there marched five Trumpeters sounding as they went, and five more in the next Division. Then the Lord Mayor lately Knighted by his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em>, the Sheriffs, and Aldermen of <em>London</em>, with their Officers, and Attendants, with 8 Heralds at Arms in great state, came <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Conduit against the Exchange, where the common <reg orig=" Cryer "> Crier </reg> of the City (an Esq; by place, published, and proclaimed the Ordinance of Peace aforesaid, to the great joy of those that heard it. And we hope it will not be taken ill, if by way of Caution we should admonish all men of both <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, that they should make diligent use of <em>Peace</em> whilst they have it, and behave themselves as becometh the Gospel of Jesus Christ; otherwise the Scripture proclaimeth that</p>
<head level="2"><i>There is no Peace to the wicked.</i></head>
<p>This Day we received Letters from Mr. <em>John Hill</em> Secretary to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> out of <em>Scotland</em>, thus.</p>
<p>We hear that some more Arms, and Ammunition is to come to the Enemy, who is about four thousand Horse and Foot in <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> is within twelve miles of them, <em>Middleton</em> hath taken upon him the sole Command of that <reg orig="Brigard">Brigand</reg>, and blames <em>Glencarn</em> for bringing them into a Penfold; they say they will fight on; which we are ready to <reg orig="imbrace">embrace</reg>, and provoke them to it daily.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 27.</head>
<p>Now the Peace is proclaimed, wherein <em>Denmark</em> is included, we shall briefly let you know what the <em>Hollander</em> hath undertaken in behalf of that King, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<p>1. <i>That <reg orig="foure">four</reg> hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling shall be answered towards satisfaction of the wrongs done unto <em>England</em>.</i></p>
<p>2. <i>That the <em>English</em> Ships detained in the <em>Sound</em> shall be discharged within <em>15</em> days after ours come to receive them.</i></p>
<p>3. <i>That all other Damages shall be <reg orig="appraized">appraised</reg> by the first of <em>May</em> by four persons.</i></p>
<p>We have lately taken a <em>Dutch</em> East India ship of 800 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, wherein is four Chests of Silver, and other rich Commodities: we have also taken a private Man of war in the West.</p>
<p><i>Thus do you see how good fortune, joy, and glory (the three things <em><reg orig="Thesius">Theseus</reg></em> asked of the Gods) attend the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> undertakings, and be who seeketh glory for virtue, and noble Acts, doth not commit <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> dishonourable either towards himself, or others.</i></p>
<p>We had more news from <em>Scotland</em> thus. A party of the Enemy commanded by Capt: <em>Erwin</em> lately got Westward, and came upon the Borders of <em>England</em> in <em>Cumberland</em>, and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> and robbed all they could meet with, and carried away some prisoners. The Earl of <em>Glencarn</em>, and Sir <em>Geo: Munro</em> lately fought a Duel, and were both slightly wounded. A thousand more Foot are come over the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> to their Army in <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> is gotten as <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to them as possible he can, endeavouring to force them to fight, and they give out that they will do it speedily, some parties of ours have engaged with others of theirs, and always gotten the better of them. They talk of more Arms lately landed in the North. General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is newly come to <em>Leith</em>.</p>
<p>There will shortly be new Farthings for necessary changes, and the good of the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg>.</p>
<hr />
<p>The most <reg orig="easie">easy</reg>, cheap, certain, and <reg orig="speedie">speedy</reg> way of curing the <em>French Pox</em>, and <em>running of the Reins</em>, without confining the Patient, either to keeping of house, or <reg orig="extremitie">extremity</reg> of Fluxing <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>; and without leaving the least <reg orig="symptome">symptom</reg> of the Disease behind, either inward by pains, or outward by pustules; is carefully performed. By the <reg orig="Physitian">Physician</reg> at the <reg orig="til'd">tiled</reg> <!--might be just "porch"--><reg orig="porcht">porched</reg> House in <reg orig="Maiden-head">Maidenhead</reg> Court in Aldersgate-street, over against Peter-house.</p>
<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>