<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$12">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $12</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Ratification of the Articles of Peace betwixt <em>England, Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, Signed by the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, and the Commissioners for his Highness the Lord Protector. The dispatching Letters presently away to the States General; the time when this Peace shall be Proclaimed in <em>England, Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>; and the manner how it must be done. Another Fight in <em>Scotland</em>, and the taking many of Gen: <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Men; with the Names of the chief Commanders of their several Brigades. The Letters, and Resolution of Mr. <em>Feak</em>, and Mr: <em>Sympson</em>, sent to their friends in <em>England</em>. Many great Prizes taken at Sea. The proceedings of the Treaty with the <em>French</em> Ambassador: And the Demands of the Knights of <em>Malta</em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 31 of <em>March</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 7 of <em>April</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, March 31.</head>
<p>At <em>Kensington</em> (<reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>London</em>) found out the nest of deceitful Vermin, such as fill the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> with base and counterfeit <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg>, but having their spies abroad, those that came to apprehend them were discovered a little to soon, for they made an escape at a back door, yet were put to such a sudden fright, that they left some of their cloaks behind them, and some store of their base <reg orig="Mettal">Metal</reg>, with meat roasting at the fire, but the <reg orig="jolley">jolly</reg> <reg orig="Houskeepers">Housekeepers</reg> were gone, <em>the more was the pity</em>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg> March</em> 25.</head>
<p>The Commander in chief having issued forth a Proclamation, requiring all <reg orig="Burroughs">Boroughs</reg>, and other Parishes to secure all <reg orig="suspitious">suspicious</reg> persons, or otherwise to give Intelligence of them to the next adjacent Garrison, or Quarters, under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present Government, and proceeded against accordingly: Several Towns have been found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a court Martial for the same. The last week the Parish of <em>Liberten</em>, two miles from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, for harbouring fifteen of the Enemy by the space of a night, and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving Intelligence of the, and the <em>Tories</em> at their going away stealing fifteen horses, the Parish as for that offence fined 200 <em>l. sterling</em>, the person in whose house they were concealed sentenced to imprisonment during pleasure, and the house where they were harboured to be raced to the ground, and a pair of Gallows to be built there. There are divers other Parishes are summoned into the Court Martials upon the very same account, who <reg orig="wil">will</reg> suffer for it. It is hoped this course will in time compel the <em>Scots</em> not to give any entertainment unto the <em>Tories</em>, but give notice of them <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> they shall come; otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>

<p>The 21 instant Col: <em>Cooper</em> with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em>, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of <em>Leven</em>, where about 300 of the Enemy quartered (about four in the morning) took <em>Mac <reg orig="Naughtons">Naughton's</reg></em> Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, and narrowly missed <em>Mac Naughton</em>, and <em>Newark</em>, who were both there. They killed 12, whereof one of them (as the Enemy coafesse) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 horse, and some Arms, totally scattered the whole party, and returned without any <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>
<p>This week Captain <em>Ortan</em> Commander of the <em>Sun</em>, and Captain <em>Lilburn</em> of the <em>Union</em> came into <em>Leith</em> Road, from <em>Lewis</em> and <em>Orkney</em>, and brought three Companies of <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> Regiment, and thee with a particular relation of the late infall of the Lord <em>Seafort</em> into <em>Lewis Island</em>, much to the same purpose formerly related.</p>
<p><em>Plymouth</em> Fort, <em>March</em> 24. The news this place affords is, The Commander of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a <em>Dutch</em> Prize, <pb n="2" />which hath no lading, only some few barrels of Pitch, <em>&amp;c</em>. This week <em>Paul</em> a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met with a <em>Flushing</em> Man of War in the Channel, who after five hours fight took her, and this day brought her in hither; we lost not any man in the fight, but sustained some <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> in Masts, Sails, and Rigging; the enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and the ship much torn, she hath some silver in her, and <reg orig="smal">small</reg> quantity of Wines.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 1.</head>
<p>The Letters further this Post from <em>Scotland</em> advertise us, that parties which have been sent out by <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> have dispersed two other parties, which were sent out by the enemy to plunder, and steal away <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> out of the <em>Lowlands</em>. But their main body doth not yet appear, for that they are not in an <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg> to take the field; therefore they wait, and earnestly expect the further supplies that were promised from beyond Sea, by the late Letters they had from the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council taking into consideration the great abuses which have been practised in the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Cockpits by reason of Matches of <reg orig="Cock-fighting">Cock fighting</reg>: An Ordinance is issued forth, <reg orig="straightly">straitly</reg> forbidding all such set meetings at <reg orig="Cock-fightings">Cock fightings</reg>; and all Justices of the peace, and other Officers are required to take notice hereof, and to punish all such persons as shall be found to offend contrary to the said Ordinance.</p>
<p>There is another Ordinance for continuing the Act of the late Parliament, touching the Probate of <reg orig="Wils">Wills</reg>, and granting Letters of Administration.</p>
<p>Also a third Ordinance for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of <em>Farmlingham</em> and <em>Sextead</em> in the County of <em>Suffolk</em>, (given by Will by Sir <em>Robert Hitcham</em>, late Sergeant at Law) to charitable uses.</p>
<p>On Thursday next there is to be sold at the Sale Office in Beer lane, above thirty several parcels of good commodities, as Wines, Sugars, Silks, Stuffs, and divers other commodities, which were taken prizes.</p>
<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> they write, That a Private Man of War hath brought into that Port a Prize laden with Tobacco, and divers other commodities. The <em>Brest</em> Men of War are often seen about the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, and near the <em>Isle of Scilly</em>; we hear that they took the last week an English Vessel belonging to <em>Bristol</em>, but what her lading was, we cannot yet learn.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 3.</head>
<p>This Day was the business of Peace with <em>Holland</em> carried on as far as might be, all is fully agreed, and one thing after another, <reg orig="every thing">everything</reg> is done in order, The Merchants came this day, and were present by the <em>Dutch</em> to sign for security for payment of the monies to the Merchants for the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> by them sustained in the business of <em>Denmark</em> for <em>Denmark</em> is wholly taken in also into the Peace, and in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> all will be concluded, and totally finished, that the Peace may be ready to be Proclaimed.</p>
<p>The business for appointing Commissioners for the Great Seal, was ordered to be on the morrow, in order to which, several things were this day done by way of preparation.</p>
<p>The <em>Swedish</em> Agent made Address to his Highness the Lord Protector and it was ordered that he should have Audience on the morrow, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies was appointed to attend accordingly.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday, April</em> 4.</head>
<p>This Day the Lords of the Council, and Mr: Secretary of State attended his Highness the Lord Protector at the <reg orig="Cock-pit">Cockpit</reg>, after which they sat in Council in <em>White hall</em>, and several businesses of great consequence were transacted.</p> 
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador is removed from Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> to his own Lodgings in Convent Garden.</p>
<p>This day the Agent from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had Audience by his Highness, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his Highness divers Lords of the Council, and Mr: Secretary of State.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Thomas Wethrington</em>, and the Lord Commissioner <em>Lisle</em> were this day sworn Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, for the Court of Chancery, by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, in the <reg orig="Council-Chamber">Council Chamber</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">White hall</reg></em>, the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> who is now in <em>Sweden</em>, is also to be one with them.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Dalkeith, March</em> 28.</head>
<p>Our Forces from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> have taken sixty horse, and 36 prisoners beyond <em>Dunbarton</em> Castle; since which, one of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Captains was taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Haddington</em>, with six more. About fifty Gentlemen were gone from the West to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, with good Horses, Arms, <em>&amp;c.</em> of which, some Knights, and two of the Lord <em>De la </em><pb n="4" /><em><reg orig="Banks">Bank's</reg></em> Brothers. <em>Glencarn, Kenmore, Athol, Forbs,</em> and <em>Glengary, &amp;c.</em> are gone Northward to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton, Seafort</em>, and the Lord <em>Ray</em>, and so to force <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, to rise with them; their return it is thought will be about a fortnight hence, <em>Seafort, Middleton</em>, and <em>Raget</em> men, surprised a Vessel of ours going to the <em>Lewis</em> by some Boats they sent out; we had in her fourteen men, Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for that Garrison. <em>Middleton</em> hath besieged <em>Cinkeler</em> Castle in <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, but they bad his defiance. Coll: <em>Morgan</em> returned from <em><reg orig="Inverness">Innernes</reg></em> the 21 instant, over the Hill for <em>Aberdeen</em>. The enemy have been cruel in burning, and destroying the Country that do not freely <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; yet Sir <em>James Mac Donald</em>, and the Captain of the <em>Clans Renolds</em>, are in Arms against <em>Middleton</em> in the Hills, for preservation of their Country.</p>
<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> March</em> 28. An <em>Ostend</em> Man of War is brought in by the <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and three <em>Dutch</em> Prizes are also brought into this Port, one with <reg orig="Figgs">Figs</reg>, and Raisins from St: <em>Lucas</em>, the other two with French Wines.</p>
<p><em>Ellins</em> 1 <em>April</em>, <reg orig="Yesternight">Yester night</reg> the <em>Reserve</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one of our Scouts brought into the Fleet a Prize called the <em>John Baptist</em> loaden with some Pepper, and <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg>, her burthen is about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> from St: <em>Mallows</em>, bound for <em>Amsterdam</em>, the Captain of her a <em>French</em> man, made short dispute, and then <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg>.</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Rous</em> is added to the Committee of the Admiralty, and Navy. The Committee for approbation of Ministers sit on <em><reg orig="Mondayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdaies">Wednesdays</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Fridaies">Fridays</reg></em> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">White hall</reg></em>.</p>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> they write, that at the Request of the English Resident <em>Monsieur Bradshaw</em>, the Senate hath imprisoned an English revolted Merchant, whose name is <em>Waites</em>, who will now be made to answer dearly for his former Treachery.</p>
<p>A <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Pink from <em>Holland</em> came with some few Passengers, and Letters from the States to their Ambassadors here in <em>England</em>, and they that came with them say, that the contents of those Letters are, that their Ambassadors should hasten the Ratification of the Peace with <em>England</em>.</p>
<p>The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> hath given his consent that his Brother <em>Franck</em> shall be Commander in chief of his Army.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, April 25.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsal">Upsala</reg> the <em>27 Feb: 1654. S. N.</em></i></head>
<p>All the actions of our great Queen are as so many wonders, and continual effects of her royal virtues, and of the greatness of her incomparable courage, but some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in special she did give such proof thereof, that the same may be called the Crown of <reg orig="al">all</reg> her other actions, seeing it doth manifest to the world how this admirable Princess hath set <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> above the Crowns, under which men commonly do seek their satisfaction and glory. The 23 of this Instant she having summoned all the Senators of the Land, they all made their appearance, except 9. who were out of the Land upon <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>; there this Princess did declare unto them the design she had to leave the charge of the Kingdom, and to that end, that she was resolved to go to <em>Nicoping</em> to confer with the Prince Palatine of <em>Sweden</em> her Cousin, having sent him Letters to invite him thither, and withal, to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to accept the charge of the Kingdom, and the managing of the State affairs; this Prince is the same who was heretofore Generalissimo of the <em>Swedish</em> Armies in <em>Germany</em>, concluded first a Peace with the Duke <em>Picolomini</em> and in the year 1650, at the Coronation of the Queen, was then declared Heir apparent to the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, and by the States and Commonalty acknowledged so, having made their Oath of Allegiance to him, as unto their future King, after the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> death.</p>
<p>It is advertised that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is yet in <em>France</em>, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty <reg orig="wil">will</reg> produce betwixt <em>England</em> and <em>France</em>. He had a Present given him a little before <em>Easter</em> by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom.</p>
<p>In the <reg orig="Holydayes">Holidays</reg> his Mother came to see him in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal, and the King her Nephew in the <em>Lovure</em>, and on the next day returned to her devotions in the Nunnery. There is a Report of two <em>English</em> ships brought into <em>Tholoon</em>, which it is said, were taken by the <em>French</em> not far from <em>Messina</em>.</p>
<p>The Letters fro <em>Scotland</em> speak of the <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg></em> Army <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> all into one Body, which no doubt will be dispersed again into several parties for the Countries where they are, are so wasted, that they cannot maintain them, and it is probable they will not <pb n="6" />draw together with an intent to give <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg> until the middle of <em>May</em>, before which time the Peace with <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em> will so startle them, that they will have but little Resolution to fight.</p>
<p>The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War of fourteen Guns, and sent her into <em>Burlington Bay</em>; This was one of the four <em>Capers</em> that did much annoy us on the Northern Seas. The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> lay cruising three or four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before he <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> could snap her.</p>
<p>An Ordinance was passed for suspending the proceedings of the Judges in the Act <reg orig="Intituled">entitled</reg>, <em>The Act for Relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</em>, it is to this effect.</p>
<p>Whereas upon perusal, and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Intituled">entitled</reg>, <em>An Act for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</em>, many doubts, and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorized for sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot <reg orig="inshort">in short</reg> time be effected, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<p>We understand further from <em>Sweden</em>, that that (Second <em>Elizabeth</em>) being exceeding valiant, is notwithstanding so exceeding humble, and devoted to piety, that she very earnestly desires the good will of her Nobles, that she may resign her Crown to another, which seems very strange, if we consider what fighting and contention there is in other parts of the world to gain but a temporal Crown, what might we not imagine that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> would do to get such a <em>Gem</em>, yet we see his destiny was to <reg orig="loose">lose</reg> at the first, and it is unlikely he should win at the last, yet he strives, and hopes, and <reg orig="stayes">stays</reg> in <em>France</em> a little longer, to see what will certainly become of the Treaty betwixt <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>.</p>
<p>This Day the Sessions began in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>, there is a full Goal, and divers Persons for notorious <reg orig="Murthers">Murders</reg>, Robberies, and other outrages of which more hereafter.</p>
<p>There be three of those men apprehended lately, which committed the late Robbery on <em>Blackheath</em>, upon Major <em>Bourn</em>, and other Gent: who quitted themselves so <reg orig="valliantly">valiantly</reg>, that two of these three <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> were sore wounded.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 6.</head>
<p>O how magnificently looks this day, and glorious to behold, wherein with truth and confidence we can declare Peace not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> at home, but also to <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Nations and Kingdoms; and long happy may <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> be under their respective Governments; now also let dignity and renown be the joy of Peace, and a Government established in freedom an Anchor to both.</p>
<p>The last night about nine of the clock the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> signed the ratification of the Articles of Peace, so did likewise the Commissioners in behalf of his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>The great work this day was the dispatching away of a Pink with the said Articles and Ratification to be Signed by the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and upon the return again of the said Ratification, his Highness the Lord Protector <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> also, and the major part of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>
<p>In this accord and agreement <em>Denmark</em> is also fully included, so that Peace is likewise made with him.</p>
<p>The <em>French</em> puts in very strongly for Peace too, whereupon our Merchants are required to bring in an Account what damages they have sustained by the <em>French</em>. In this <reg orig="Ambassey">Embassy</reg> the Knights of <em>Malta</em> claim some old Arrears from <em>England</em>.</p>
<p>Within a few days the Guard, <reg orig="Pentioners">Pensioners</reg>, and other Officers and Attendants for his Highness (chosen with the approbation of the Lords of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>) will be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in their respective places. His Highness was lately at Hampton Court, and Orders are given for repairing that House.</p>
<p>It is said that a Squadron of our fleet is designed for the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Feaks</em> and Mr: <em>Sympson</em> are yet as highly resolved in their former ways as ever, say some of their Letters to their friends in <em>London</em>. Yesterday a man for a wager undertook to drive a <reg orig="Wheel-barrow">Wheelbarrow</reg> with 14 pound weight in it, from <em>London</em> to St: <em>Albans</em>, and back again from 5 of the clock in the morning, <reg orig="til">till</reg> 7 of the clock at night, but he was tired by that time he came back to <em>Highgate</em>.</p>
<p>When the Articles of Peace, and Ratification are returned back Signed by the States, and so again here as aforesaid, you may expect to have it Proclaimed with great solemnity both in <em>England</em>, and <em>Holland</em>, all which may be done in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; We are likely also to have a <reg orig="neet">neat</reg> Alliance with <em>Sweden</em>.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>