<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$04">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $4</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Lord Mayor, and the <reg orig="Recorders">Recorder's</reg> Speeches to his Highness the Lord Protector at Temple bar, upon delivering unto his Highness the Sword, and his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Speech again to the Lord Mayor concerning the Charter, Liberties, and Freedom of this famous city. The manner of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> entertainment when he came to <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall; a Sonnet to be sung, and other Speeches made there. A wonder seen upon the <em>Thames</em>, by the often flowing, and ebbing of the water. The Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> Letter to the King of <em>Scots</em>. The mustering of sixteen thousand men. The taking of a Garrison in <em>Scotland</em> by the Lord <em>Seafort</em>. A List of new Judges in England. And further probability of Peace with <em>Holland</em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 3 of <em>February</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 10 of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, February 3.</head>
<p>By Letters of this Day from <em>Dover</em> it was advertised, that two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> met with two <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> Men of <em>France</em>, and a man of War for their Convoy these had a dispute for the space of half an hour, and at the first the <em>English</em> seemed to have the worst of it, yet in the conclusion providence ordered otherwise, for the English laid the <em>French</em> Man of War aboard, and brought her away, she was a ship of 80 Guns, and double manned; the two Merchant men made their escape while the Men of War were in the heat of that Engagement.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>In our last we told you that the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of <em>London</em> had invited his Highness the Lord Protector to dinner on such a Day as his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> should appoint which Day is appointed to be on <em>Wednesday</em> next, <em>commonly called <reg orig="Ashwednesday">Ash Wednesday</reg></em>, whereof more in the last page of this Intelligence.</p>
<p>We shall in the next place give you this effect of an Order of his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, wherein they have nominated, and appointed a new Committee for the Army, and the Names of which Committee are as followeth.</p>
<!--formatted as list with "Esquires" applied to (all names? The last four?) via a brace-->
<p><i>John Clerk. Edward Cludd. Richard Euey. Richard Horseman. <em>Captain</em> Adam Banes. James Philips, Edward Gill, John Hildsley Jarvis Bennet Esquires.</i></p>
<p>The Treasurers are these.</p>
<p><em>John Blackwell</em> the younger, and <em>Richard Deane</em> Esquires.</p>
<p>There is also added to the Commissioners for the <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg> <reg orig="Assessementt">Assessment</reg> for the County of <em>Lincoln</em>.</p>
<p><i>Thomas Raud. William Palmar. Robert Yarbrow. Nehemiah Rawson. William Fervey. Willaim Wesbey.</i> Esquires. And the Mayor of <em>Lincoln</em> for the time being.</p>
<p>It was this Day advertised, that our Fleet is put forth to Sea, General <em>Pen</em> set forth first with about fifty stout Men of War, he was seconded by General <em>Blake</em>, with twenty gallant ships, the whole Fleet met not far from <em>Portland</em>, where about this time <reg orig="twelve-moneth">twelve month</reg> was that dreadful Fight betwixt the <em>English</em>, &amp; the <em>Dutch</em>. It was ordered that our fleet should be divided into three Squadrons, the better to secure the Channel, and to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> the Seas; It is likely enough they may meet with the <em>Dutch</em> Merchants, who bound for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, and the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straights</reg></em> are numerous, and not adventuring through the Channel, have thought it their safer course to steer round about on the backside of <em>Ireland</em>.</p>
<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Hume</em> with sixteen more well mounted, is gone out of <em>Berwickshire</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the <em>Highlanders</em>. The Earl of <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> since his Defeat at <em>Dunkel</em>, hath endeavoured to raise the Countries, but hath yet but a very slender appearance.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>Those who were slain, and taken in the Defeat, given to the <em>Scots</em> were.</p>
<p>The Laird <em>Ballichan</em>, Captain <em>Hunter</em>, Captain <em>Robertson</em>, Captain <em>Mackland</em>, Major <em>Mercer</em> wounded, Captain <em>Sibbel</em> taken, Cornet <em>Graham</em> taken, Six more taken, and seven killed.</p>
<p>On our side there were two killed, and some wounded. Col: <em>Morgan</em> hath made a hard march into the <em>Highlands</em>, to find out the Enemy in this Winter season, but they fly back as he advanceth, the Winter will not yet permit to prosecute what was intended, and the Country <reg orig="yeelds">yields</reg> no provision but what we carry with us; several <reg orig="straglers">stragglers</reg> have been taken.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Febr: 4.</head>
<p>Master <em>Hales</em> of <em><reg orig="Lincolns Inne">Lincoln's Inn</reg></em> is to be a <reg orig="Judg">Judge</reg> for that he is a man unblemished in his conversation, and so profound a Lawyer, that the Name of <em>young Noy</em> was put upon him twenty years since, and for this many years past there hath not been greater hopes to <reg orig="reforme">reform</reg> enormities in the Law, and other abuses in Courts, and Corporations, <reg orig="then">than</reg> there is now, yet it is hard matter to please <reg orig="al">all</reg> therefore some which aimed at all, falling now in despair, are pleased to utter their spleen in such language as this, <em>viz: Now we are slaves indeed, <reg orig="farewel">farewell</reg> then our Laws, and Liberties,</em> and <em>ad placitum, our lives also</em>, for the Soldiery will, and may as they list, and we as we see plainly that the Sword domineers, rules, and revels it, and plays reaks circularly, for it selfly dissolves, and then creates, and then dissolves again our <em>Parliaments, ad placitum</em>, and so recreates <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> with such pastimes, it <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> from, and would none of Monarchy, nor Kinghood, but Anarchy only, that so it might turn to them the better, to serve its own turn, for it did but out face them, and then face about, and so <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> to both again, and Anarchy also; so we are where, and as we were, only <reg orig="Annarchy">Anarchy</reg> is added to <reg orig="substract">subtract</reg>, divide, and confound us. Names, Persons, and some presentments are changed, but natures are the same; why then all this ado, except to undo all? If Kinghood was intended again, as it was <reg orig="pretendid">pretended</reg> against, why kept we not him we had? or why have we not him we should have? and last of all, why have we him we should not have? why say others, any King at all? not rather <em>Parliaments</em>, or <em><reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg> of State</em>.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Febr: 6.</head>
<p>The Benches in <em>Westminster Hall</em> are now filling with able learned Judges. Those already are.</p>
<p>Lord Chief Justice <em>Roll</em>, and Justice <em>Ask</em> for the Upper Bench.</p>
<p>Lord Chief Justice <em>Saint John</em>, Justice <em>Atkins</em>, and Justice <em>Hale</em> for the Common Pleas.</p>
<p>Baron <em>Thorp</em>, and Baron <em>Nichols</em> for the Exchequer.</p>
<p>And five new <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> are made who are to make Judges to fill the Benches, (<em>viz:</em>) Mr: <em>Maynard</em>, Mr: <em>Steel</em>, Mr: <em>Windham</em>, Mr: <em>Newdegate</em>, and Mr: <em>Twisden</em>.</p>
<p>The Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are the same that were.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Upsal</em> the 29 of January.</i></head>
<p>My Lord <em>Whitlock</em>, the English Extraordinary Ambassador, is feasted at the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> charges, with his whole suit, which consisteth of one hundred persons, amongst whom there is four high Officers, four Pages, eight Footmen, two Trumpeters, one Doctor, two Ministers, two Coaches, and forty saddle Horses. These are highly esteemed here by the <em>Swedes</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Febr. 7.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From the <em>Hague</em> the (6 of February) 27 of January.</i></head>
<p>When the Lords States of <em>Holland</em> shall meet again, which is to be the 10 of this instant, that is January 31. by the English account, We hope that all the other Provinces shall bring in their Resolves concerning the Ratification of the Articles, with the present Government in <em>England</em>. It is thought that the same shall be conform to the Resolutions of the Province of <em>Holland</em> (although some will say that there is yet somewhat that sticks) and some <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> shall be sent to recover us the liberty of the Seas. We heard that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had written a Letter to <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, at the instance of his Agent, wherein her Majesty doth excuse <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, that the present condition of her affairs doth not suffer her to give satisfaction upon his demands, intimating that she pities his misfortune. We have a confirmation of the Peace concluded between the King of <em>Poland</em>, and the <em>Tartarians</em>, and <em>Cossacks</em>. And it is said, that an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> is come to <em>Upsal</em> in <em>Swedenland</em> from the great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em>, to make known that his Master is ready to declare the War to the said King of <em>Poland</em>, to which end he hath mustered 160000 men, he shall in all <pb n="4" />appearance move the Crown of <em>Swedenland</em> to declare also against him. Yesterday there arrived here 140 Seamen, which are come from <em>England</em>, having been Prisoners there, they have received conduct money, and shall be sent toward <em>Amsterdam</em>, having the most part of their Habitations there, and in the Northern parts.</p>
<p><reg orig="Somthing">Something</reg> was considered of in order to M: Gen: <em><reg orig="Browns">Brown's</reg></em> liberty.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Falmouth</em> February 1.</i></head>
<p>In the <em>Patrick</em> of <em>Liverpool</em> which we lately recovered from the <em>Brest</em> Men of War, was one <em>Walter Roch</em>, who was to carry her to <em>Brest</em>, and he informed us that there are these ships following belonging to <em>Brest</em>, who do so vex us in these Seas, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Royal James</em>, with 38 guns, <em>Richard Beach</em> Commander.</p>
<p>The <em>Michael</em>, 14 guns, <em>James Smith</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Briget</em> with 8 guns, <em>William Smith</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> 10 guns, <em>Meldrum</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Mall</em> 10 guns, <em>Covel</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Loyal James</em> with 12 guns, <em>James Dillon</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Saint Mary</em> 4 guns, <em>Richard Dillon</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> with 10 guns, <em>William Durant</em>.</p>
<p>The - with 8 guns, <em>Jones</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Margaret</em> with 3 guns, <em>Heldish</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> with 22 guns, <em>Martin</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Patrick</em> with 18 guns, <em>Swart</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Katherine</em> with 6 guns, <em>Estmond</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Saint Michael</em> with 6 guns, <em>Peters</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Snow</em> with 4 guns <em>Nich: Murro</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Adventure</em> with two guns, <em>George Lodde</em>.</p>
<p>Three <em>French men</em> with 15. 18. 20.</p>
<p>Three in the Stocks of 4 guns a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Dalkeith in</em> Scotland</i> 31 January.</head>
<p>On <em>Saturday</em> last a party of ours fell upon the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Guards, took a captain, a Lieutenant, Cornet, and 15 other Prisoners, with 20 horse, and killed 9 or 10 in all. The Ministers in all parts daily praying for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and their King for which they pretend conscience. There is a very strange report here, that the Ld: of <em>Seafort</em> hath stormed our Fort at <em>Lewis Island</em> with 1400 men, and taken it, which I cannot <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> in regard the Governor there was confident to defend it against thousands, yet it is certain that <em>Seafort</em> was preparing to attempt it, and we had no ship on those coasts.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday,</em> and <em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 8. 9.</head>
<p>This being the Day appointed for entertaining his Highness the Lord Protector in the City of <em>London</em>, in the morning the streets from <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> hall in the Poultery to Temple Bar, were railed in on both sides the way, and the four and twenty Companies met at their several <reg orig="Hals">Halls</reg>, and about eleven of the clock they took their places within the said Rails, and all along the said Rails were set up a great many <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg>, and streams bearing the Arms of the respective Companies, and the Rails themselves were covered with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg>. Then the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen (on horseback) went to meet his Highness at Temple Bar, the <reg orig="sword-bearer">sword bearer</reg> carrying the Sword before him and when his Highness came the Ld: Mayor took the Sword, and presented it to his Highness, and then his Highness delivered it back again unto him, and after some other Ceremonies performed, his Highness came through the City attended in this manner, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<p>First came a Marshal, and after him five Trumpets sounding, then came about sixty Gentlemen in gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg>, and well mounted, after them came six Trumpeters, and four heralds at Arms, next after them were carried nine white <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg>, and after them the Lord <reg orig="Mayors">Mayor's</reg> Officers, and the Clerks, <reg orig="Attornies">Attorneys</reg>, and other Officers belonging to the City, all on foot, then came the Sheriff, and Aldermen on horseback all in their scarlet Gowns, and next before his Highness the Lord Mayor <reg orig="bare-headed">bare headed</reg>, carrying the Sword himself before him, his Highness having on a musk coloured Suit, richly <reg orig="imbrothered">embroidered</reg> with Gold, and a rich <reg orig="imbrothered">embroidered</reg> Saddle.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>As his Highness passed by, the People were uncovered, and his Highness as he went, continually moved his hat to the People; there followed after his Highness about three-score <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg>, and other Superior Officers in very rich habits, and after them came two rich Coaches of his Highness with six stately Horses a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>, the Postillions, and Coachmen riding bare, only with black velvet caps; after them followed thirteen other Coaches, all with six Horses <reg orig="apeece">apiece</reg>, in which were most of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Council, and seventeen other Coaches followed after them: The shops were shut up in Cheapside, and so to <reg orig="Temple-bar">Temple bar</reg>, and the <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> rung in every steeple. When his Highness came to <reg orig="Grocers-Hall">Grocers' Hall</reg> (which was a little after two of the clock) he was most Royally entertained, with abundance of the <reg orig="choisest">choicest</reg> delicates this rich and plentiful <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> could afford, and were I not confined to one sheet, I could make another by adding in this place the bill of Fare, but because reading will not fill empty bellies, I shall not mention any of the Dishes, but present you in Verse what may a little <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> your ear, and <reg orig="fantasie">fantasy</reg>, touching so noble a Feast now it is ended.</p>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Come away, blest soul no more</line> 
<line>Feed your eyes with what is poor;</line>
</stanza> 
<stanza>
<line>It is enough that you have blest</line> 
<line>What was rude, what was <reg orig="undrest">undressed</reg>.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Come away, and cast your eyes</line>
<line>On this humble Sacrifice:</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>We no golden apples give,</line>
<line><reg orig="Her's">Here's</reg> no <em>Adam</em>, <reg orig="her's">here's</reg> no <em>Eve</em>?</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Not a Serpent dares appear,</line>
<line>Whilst your Highness stayeth here.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Oh then sit, and take your due,</line>
<line>Those the first fruits are that grew.</line> 
</stanza>
</poem>
<pb n="7" />
<p>The Sonnet of entertainment being ended, his Highness took his place in the middle of the upper Table in the great Hall, and his Son the Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> on the left hand, and the Lord Mayor on the right hand; and at the Table on each side of them sat the Council, with Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em>, Commissary Gen: <em>Whaley</em>, <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Pride</em>, <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Hewsan</em>, and other <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg> and Officers of the Army, and <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg> and Singing continued all Dinner while. The Dinner being ended, the Lord Mayor conducted his Highness <reg orig="up stairs">upstairs</reg> to a rich and stately Banquet; and about six of the clock at night his Highness and his Retinue repaired again towards <em><reg orig="Whitehall">White Hall</reg></em>.</p>
<p>We shall in the next place give you the substance of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Speeches made this day, and,</p>
<p>First, at <em><reg orig="Temple-bar">Temple Bar</reg></em> the Recorder of <em>London</em> made an eloquent Speech to his Highness, wherein he set forth the good affection of the chief Magistracy of the City, and this was illustrated by their readiness and forwardness to receive his Highness (as Lord Protector) into the Liberties of the said City; all which was acknowledged but their duty, &amp;c.</p>
<p>2. The Lord Mayor made a short Speech at the delivering up his Sword, declaring his submission to the Authority which is invested in him and his Council, and acknowledged that he acted under the same Authority; Whereupon his Highness made a modest reply, and returned the Sword, speaking to this effect, <em>That he had confidence his Lordship was <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg>, and every way endowed with gifts befitting the place wherein he was</em>.</p>
<p>3. At <em><reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall</em> (where his Highness dined) the <em>Recorder</em> made another Speech, congratulating the happiness of this City, being sensible of the great benefits they are like to enjoy under his protection.</p>
<p>4. His Highness accepted of what was so freely <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> him in behalf of this famous City, and was pleased to speak very favourable of their Charter, and other things tending to the making thereof more famous and glorious. Major Gen: <em>Harrison</em> and his Church spent this day in prayer, &amp;c.</p>
<p>The post from <em>Holland</em> brings news, <em>viz</em>: That the Provinces of <em>Zealand, Utrecht</em>, and three other Provinces (besides <em>Holland</em> and <em>Westfreisland</em>) have had meetings by their Deputies, and they do approve of signing the Articles of the Treaty as the others do, yet <em>Frisland</em> is utterly against it.</p>
<p>Many of the Watermen upon the River of <em>Thames</em> do affirm, that on <em>Candlemasday</em> last; there was 3 Floods and one Ebb in 12 hours, what it may presage the Lord knows.</p> 
<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>