<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$18">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $18</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Examination of twenty of the Conspirators against his Highness the Lord Protector, and the present Government; with the Names of the Knights, Gentlemen, and others that are committed for that Design; And a Proclamation that no person shall presume to go beyond the Line of Communication, or change the place or habitation for the space of ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. A Declaration of the States of <em>Holland</em> touching the late troubles. Also a great fight in <em>Scotland</em> between the Forces commanded by Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em>, and the Armies of the <em>Highlanders</em>, with the number killed, and taken. The Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming into <em>Scotland</em>. The Resolution of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> Stuart, and the Progress of Prince <em>Rupert</em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 19 of <em>May</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 26 of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, May 19.</head>
<p>Many of the Native <em>Irish</em> are reduced into <em>Connaught</em>, and a Declaration is issued forth touching such as came not thither by the first of <em>May</em> last.</p>
<p>The News which was in the double Sheeted Diurnal this last week concerning the usage of the <em>English</em>, at Saint <em>Mallows</em> in <em>France</em>, is absolutely false, and fained.</p>
<p>The Lord <em><reg orig="Witlock">Whitlock</reg></em> is at <em>Lubeck</em>, it is uncertain <reg orig="whither">whether</reg> he will take shipping there for <em>England</em>, or rather at <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>.</p> 
<pb n="1" />
<p><em>Leith</em> 12 <em>May</em>. General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> having made good some passages beyond <em>Dalkeith</em> to prevent the inroads of the Enemy after he is marched further, hath now taken the field, and is gathering up, and driving together his heathenish Enemy as fast as he can, and we are now so active in the business, that there is not a day passeth, wherein we take not some of them. General <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Brother, and divers others Officers were lately taken in a party within our Quarters, two of them are executed already as Spies, and more are like to go the same way, this is not a People to be dallied with, for the better they are used, the more insolent they grow.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, <reg orig="M y">May</reg> 20.</head>
<p>This Day was published two Ordinances, the one an Ordinance for Explanation of a former Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordinance for better Amending, and Keeping in Repair the Common <reg orig="High wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation</em>. The other, An Ordinance for Relief of Debtors in <em>Scotland</em> in some cases of Extremity. The former of these two being of most <reg orig="publick">public</reg> concernment, here take as followeth.</p>
<p>Whereas by an Ordinance <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>,<em> An Ordinance for better Amending, and Keeping in Repair the Common <reg orig="High wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation</em>, amongst other things, It is Ordained, That if any <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg> Carts, or Carriages wherein any burdens of dead commodities or wares shall at any time from and after the first day of <em>May</em>, then next, be drawn upon any such <reg orig="Highwayes">Highways</reg> Roads, or Streets, with above five Horses or mares, or six Oxen, and one Horse or mare, in any one Cart, or Wagon, That then it shall be lawful to or for any Constable or Surveyor of <reg orig="Highwayes">Highways</reg>, or other Inhabitant in any Parish where such loaden Wagon, Cart, or Carriage shall pass, and be drawn as aforesaid, to distrain, and seize all such supernumerary Horses, Mares, or Oxen, as he shall find in any such Wagon, Car, or Carriage, over or above the number of five Horses or Mares, or six Oxen, and one Horse or Mare respectively, and the same supernumerary Horses, Oxen, and mares respectively to detain and keep, until such Owner or Driver have paid and answered into the hands of the <pb n="2" />Surveyors of the <reg orig="High wayes">Highways</reg> within the Parish where such Distress and seizure shall be made, or one of them, the sum of twenty shillings for every such supernumerary Horse, Mare, or Ox. Be it now Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland, &amp;c.</em> by and with the consent of his Council, That the said Ordinance or any Clause therein contained, shall not extend to any Carts or Carriages at any time used in the conveying, draught, or carriage of any Ordnance, Timber, or Artillery, of any sort or kind whatsoever, for the use of the Army or Navy. But that such such Carts, Draughts, or Carriages may be drawn with any number of Horses or Oxen, necessary for the drawing thereof, without incurring any of the said penalties in the said Ordinance mentioned, or without any stop, molestation or disturbance of any Constable, Officer, or other person whatsoever, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance notwithstanding, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>Civil May 10. The concluding of Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, we hope will produce such effects, that the <em>English</em> Merchants here shall not suffer so much for the future as they have done in times past <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>1. <i>The farmers use to value our goods, and force us to pay what Custom they please.</i></p>
<p>2. <i>All the Canary Islands are rented by one Farmer, who forceth the English to pay two, three, and four times <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> for one and the same goods when they send them from one Island to another to <reg orig="sel">sell</reg> them.</i></p>
<p>3. <i>They usually keep ships in the <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg>, before they suffer them to discharge their goods after they arrive, and it is long before they will dispatch them when they would depart; and cause the Masters to pay twenty shillings each time for the boats that carry them aboard the ship, &amp;c.</i></p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 23.</head>
<p>What a horrible madness is it for men whose fortunes are low, to wander so fast astray as to make the <reg orig="Theater">Theatre</reg> of Honour the Subject of their malice and hatred; This Mother Vice hath her <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> in a Din, end hollow vault, and it an enemy to Peace and Concord, <reg orig="ingendred">engendered</reg> by the ugly <em>Megera</em> of Hell, that crams her gorge with dragons, and foams forth deadly <reg orig="poyson">poison</reg>. This Day was discovered a horrid Plot; whereby many Persons confederated and conspired together, most basely and treacherously to take away the life of his Highness the Lord Protector, and turn the state into blood. Many of the Conspirators were apprehended, and after examination five were sent to the Tower.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Names of the Persons sent this Day to the Tower of <em>London</em>.</i></head>
<p><em>Gilbert Gerard</em> Esquire, a <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> for the late King, <em>John Gerard</em> his Brother, <em>Humphrey Bayly</em> Serv: to the Earl of <em>Kingson</em>, <em>Signey Fotherby</em>, <em>Thomas Tinder</em> an Apothecary, <em>John James</em> an <em>Apothecary</em>.</p>
<p>Several other persons are in hold for this business, whereof more in the last page.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From Glasgow in Scotland, May <em>14</em>.</i></head>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Cooper</em> having occasion to send his Wife, and his Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: to the Garrison of <em>Ayr</em>, sent a party of 22 Dragoons to convey them. As the Dragoons were returning back, they met with a party of the Enemy rambling about the Country, being 60 horse under command of the Laird of <em>Cairdennis</em>, and charged and routed them, killed the Laird <em>Cairdennis</em> himself, with two Cornets, and nine more upon the place, took divers horse and men, and the rest fled for it. This is all the action, and enemy that hath of late been in these parts, which was indeed very <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> performed, not one of our me being lost, and but two wounded, which are upon recovery.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 25.</head>
<p>His Highness the lord Protector, and his Council taking into consideration the Plots and Conspiracies of the Enemies of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, this Proclamation was set forth as followeth.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="2">O. P.</head>
<head level="3"><i>By the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em>.</i></head>
<p>Whereas the Enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal providences of God in frustrating of their former Counsels and malicious Designs) do appear <reg orig="stil">still</reg> restless in their attempts to involve this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in blood and confusion. In order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. His Highness with the advice of his Council, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby express Charge and Command, That for the better discovery of Persons ill affected to the Peace of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the Publication hereof repair to the several Houses within their respective Parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">House holders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as now do, or did <reg orig="lodg">lodge</reg> in their respective Houses on <em>Friday</em> night last, being the 19 of this instant <em>May</em>, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">House holders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such manes upon peril of being reputed and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, as Complices and Partakers in the said Designs, which Lists so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em> and Lines of Communication, are within 48 hours to deliver to the Lord Mayor of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Southwark</em>, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to fail at their utmost peril. And the Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Council at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the <reg orig="receit">receipt</reg> thereof. And his Highness doth likewise strictly command and require, that no Person or Persons whatsoever, lodging within the lines of Communication, do change his or their several and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of 10 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the date hereof, without the special Licence and Pass in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, or <em>Southwark, &amp;c</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 24.</head>
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, and had the usual Ceremonies; He seems to prosecute a real intention of concluding a Peace with his Highness, in behalf of his Master the <em>most Christian King</em>, and because he is not ignorant that <em>England</em> hath had many injuries, and late affronts from the <em>French</em> Nation, for which we do require satisfaction; this Ambassador <em>Monsieur Bourdeux</em> by way of extenuation of those injuries offered by the <em>French</em>, offers unto consideration the detaining of Revenue due to the Knights of <em>Malta, (alias)</em> Knights of <em><reg orig="Jerusalam">Jerusalem</reg></em>, which doth little concern that King. He also <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that the <em>Spaniard</em> got <em>Dunkirk</em> out of the hands of the <em>French</em>, by the help of the <em>English</em>.</p>
<p>By Letters of a very late date cut of <em>Germany</em> thus. The long distressed City of <em>Bremen</em> have often expected <reg orig="ayd">aid</reg> and assistance from other free States, but every one having enough to do of his own, or rather studying how to strengthen himself then relieve the wants and necessities of his friends, and Neighbours, none have yet appeared to any purpose, only the City of <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> have sent Commissioners to treat, and step in if they can, as Moderators between the General of the <em>Swedish</em> Forces, (who have taken several Villages, and almost blocks up the City) and the Magistrates of that place, but it's feared words will avail but little, where the sword is so ripe of Action.</p>
<p>The <em>Diet</em> is now ended at <em>Regensburgh</em> in some kind of discontent, for that there hath not been such dispatch of Affairs of State as was expected, wherefore many things of great concernment remain yet to be done; Nevertheless the Emperor hath adjourned, or dissolved the <em>Diet</em> not to meet again in two years after.</p>
<p>The <em>Swedes</em> do yet keep the <reg orig="Bishopprick">Bishopric</reg> of <em>Munster</em>, notwithstanding there was an Agreement made with the Commander in chief that they should surrender it.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>The Report is, that two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are seized upon at Saint <em>Mallows</em>, that some of our Men of War lying <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em>Saint Mallows</em>, threescore of our men being too bold to adventure for fresh Victuals, did go <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg>, and endeavoured to drive away some Cattle, but the country receiving the Alarum, they rescued the Cattle, being assisted by some horse, and divers of our <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> were killed, and the rest pursued to the ships, two of which the Tide going forth, were stranded, whereupon great Guns were brought from Saint <em>Mallows</em> to batter the ships, which they did begin to do, but the Tide coming in, the ships got off without any great hurt. The Governor of Saint <em>Mallows</em> apprehending this to be a design against the town, did take occasion to turn out all the English Merchants, and to seize upon all their Goods in the Warehouses, and hath got all for the present into his own custody. Complaints have been made hereof, and the business as yet under examination.</p>
<p>The Duke of <em>Lorraign</em> a prisoner in <em>Antwerp</em> hath now the liberty of the walks of the Castle, and his Daughter hath her Diamonds and Jewels of great value restored to her. Those who are chief in attendance on him are now at liberty, and did go forth with those, who in a most gallant equipage did ride out of the City to congratulate the arrival of his brother Prince <em>Francis</em>, who hath the reputation to be virtuous, and <reg orig="couragious">courageous</reg> Gentleman.</p>
<p>The <em>Italian Comedy</em> hath been often acted with much Ceremony in <em>Paris</em>, the next great solemnity will be the consecration of the King at <em>Rheims</em>, for which great preparations are made. At the last acting of the Comedy at <em>Paris</em>, the properties whereof are to be Translated to Rimes, and to be acted there also, there were present the late Queen of <em>England</em>, the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, and the titular Duke of <em>York</em>, and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>. The next day the Queen Regent came to give a Visit to the late Queen of <em>England</em>, the Civility was the next day returned by her, the next day saving one, who with her Son did give a Visit to their Majesties at the <em>Louvre</em>, and after supper, being entertained with a pleasure of a Mask, they returned to the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 25.</head>
<p>The Letters this Day from <em>Holland</em> advertise, that <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters--></unclear> of the averse party there are pretty well <reg orig="stopt">stopped</reg>, and <unclear><!-- approx 8 characters--></unclear>, and the States have set forth this ensuing Declaration.</p>
<p>The States General of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, to all persons to whom these presents shall come, <em>greeting</em>.</p>
<p><i>Whereas (to the praise of Almighty God, the advancement of the general good of the United Provinces, and of every portion or person, Articles of Peace Union, and Consideration are concluded and agreed between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, that they do <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> and submit to the said Peace so Ratified, and to obey the Ratification in all places, without any breach thereof; upon pain of being punished as disturbers of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, without expectation of any favour or grace but to be proceeded against according to justice.</i> Given at the meeting of the States General at the <em>Hague</em> 7 <em>(alias)</em> 17 <em>May</em>: 1654. <em>Jacob Vetch</em> President <em>pro tempore</em>. N: <em>Ruysch</em>, Clerk to the States General.</p>
<p>There be other Persons besides those already named in hold, concerning the Plot newly discovered, and many more are likely to be found out; A List of such as have been already examined, and remain under commitment are these:</p>
<p>Doctor <em>Naudin</em>, Anabaptist, Major <em>Mason</em>, <em>Gilbert Gerard</em> Knighted by the late King, Mr: <em>Hill</em>, Mr. <em>Brown</em>, Mr: <em>Bayley</em> Secretary to the Earl of <em>Kingston, alias</em>, the Marques of <em>Dorchester</em>, <em>John Gerard</em> Gent, Mr. <em>Tuedor</em> an Apothecary, Mr: <em>Jones</em> Apothecary, A Drapers Man in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard</em>, An Haberdashers man <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the old Change, And some at <em>Dover</em>, and other Port Towns.</p>
<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is still in <em>France</em>, but the Duke of <em>York</em> is said to be designed for <em>Scotland</em> if he could hear but of one Victory obtained by <em>Middleton</em>, and the rest of those he <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> friends in <em>Scotland</em>, Prince <em>Rupert</em> is going for <em>Germany</em>.</p>
<p>Gen. <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is now in the Field, the next <reg orig="weeks">week's</reg> Intelligence is like to be of great concernment from thence.</p>     

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>