<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$13">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $13</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>A Declaration of the States of <em>Holland</em>, and the last Articles of Peace signed by them. An Ordinance of General Pardon <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice of his Council, to the <em>Scottish Highlanders</em> which shall come in by a certain day; and Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> gone to <reg orig="mannage">manage</reg> the affairs there. The high Resolution of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. A great Council held by the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, in which it was resolved that the late Queen of <em>England</em> shall go to <em>Argeirs</em>, her Eldest Son to <em>Chantily</em>; the Duke of <em>York</em> to <em>Scotland</em>, and Pr: <em>Rupert</em> for <em>Germany</em>. The Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coming to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, and a strange Apparition of a very tall black man clothed in white.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 7 of <em>April</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 14 of <em>April</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, April 7.</head>
<p>There being found out some new matter against Lieutenant Colonel <em>John <reg orig="Lilburne">Lilburn</reg></em>, he was for the better securing of the Peace of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, Ordered to be carried from the Tower of <em>London</em>, to a place more remote.</p>
<p>By Letters from <em>Germany</em> we had Intelligence, that a <em><reg orig="Rabbie">Rabbi</reg></em> of that Country hath taken so much notice of the Warlike actions, and other Heroical, and <reg orig="pollitick">politic</reg> behaviour, that he hath thought it worthy of publishing the same in Print throughout that Nation, which adds much unto his <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg>, that <pb n="1" />those of desert in <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> Nations, should be <reg orig="sencible">sensible</reg> of those things which many undeserving People of our own Country are ignorant of, or at least have not the heart cordially to <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 8.</head>
<p>The Prisoners belonging to the Upper Bench have Petitioned his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em>, and thereunto annexed certain proposals <em>viz</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Proposals of the Prisoners in the Upper Bench, to his Highness the Lord Protector.</i></head>
<p>1. That in case the said act be thought fit to be continued which we hope will not be, being so much against Law, and the custom of the Nation, as to make so many noble Knights, and Gentlemen Bankrupts, a thing never yet done, your Petitioners may be an Act by you to be made, by way of addition, or explanation of the former, enjoy their liberty not only <reg orig="til">till</reg> <em>April</em> now at hand, but for six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> longer, and may have time till then to pay their debt, being the time is so far relapsed, and your Petitioners <reg orig="stil">still</reg> kept in prison, though they petitioned <reg orig="Salters">Salter's</reg> Hall for their liberty <reg orig="til">till</reg> April, so shall they not be <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg>, and their Estates sold at half the value, which otherwise cannot be avoided to the utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of them, and theirs.</p>
<p>2. That your Petitioners may have the same relief, and remedy against such who <reg orig="ow">owe</reg> them monies, as their Creditors have against them, in case they pay not within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, else how can your Petitioners pay their Debts?</p>
<p>3. That your Petitioners may not be so wholly deprived of their Estates, but that they may receive such a pittance thereout, that they and their Wives, and Children perish not in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, and that when their Estates be sold, some regard may be had to preserve the chief house, and <em>4th. </em>or <em>5th.</em> part of the Estate for the relief of Wife, and Children, for that was allowed to such who were accounted <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>.</p>
<p>4. That the Judges in the said Act mentioned, or some others, may have power when they have truly stated all debts, to force the Creditor to take Land for their monies either at 20. years purchase, being monies is at <em>6 per Centum</em>, or at so many years purchase as is usual in the Country where the Lands <reg orig="lie">lye</reg>, at least to <pb n="2" />take so much by way of <reg orig="Morgage">Mortgage</reg>, where the Debtor, and Trustees, or such who have interest in the same, shall consent to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> it, as will <em>per annum</em> amount to the interest of his money for some time for the security, as the said Judges, or any others persons to be so <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> shall think fit, and order, upon hearing both sides. And in case the <reg orig="Debter">Debtor</reg> pay not in that time, that the Creditor giving him every twenty pound more in every 100 l. shall have a full and absolute Estate for him, and his Heirs <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>; and that the said Judges may have power to proceed as a Bankrupt against such as shall refuse to stand to one of these, in case you will have it so, and also to <reg orig="qualifie">qualify</reg> interest during the War, as the Lords Commissioners are enabled to do.</p>
<p>5. That they may have power also where they find any Prisoner grievously <reg orig="opprest">oppressed</reg>, or kept wrongfully in prison, either for a pre-satisfied Debt, or by <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg> <reg orig="surreptuously">surreptitiously</reg> obtained by the fraud, and knavery of Attorneys, or otherwise, to give the party injured good <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, either from the Prosecutor, or Attorney, as cause shall require, as well as not for Declaring.</p>
<p>6. That whereas the said Act makes all such <em>ipso facto</em> to be Bankrupts, that pay not their Debts before the first of April, that your Highness, and your <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council will declare, what Debts is thereby intended, whether <reg orig="al">all</reg> the Debts they <reg orig="ow">owe</reg> (which if so, all are Bankrupts; neither is all their Debts yet due, nor demanded, or only such for which they be charged in Execution, before the 20. of Octob. which they conceive to be the true meaning of the Act, and not leave the same arbitrarily to the Judges, who are of different <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg> therein, lest the Prisoner be thereby ensnared, and ruined.</p>
<p>7. That for the better Execution, and performance of the premises, an Oath may be given to the said Judges, <pb n="3" />that they shall execute the power to them given, according to the best of their <reg orig="skil">skill</reg> and <reg orig="judgment">judgement</reg>, uprightly and truly, without respect of persons, <reg orig="partiallity">partiality</reg>, or any sinister respect whatsoever, which is no more <reg orig="then">than</reg> all the Judges and Justices of <em>England</em> are sworn to do; and that so much the rather, for that the said Judges are accountable to none but a Parliament, which is not to be till September next, so that we may in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> be destroyed: But by this means the Creditors are sure to have their just Debts, and Interest in a short time, and your Petitioners, Wives, Children, and posterities preserved from utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 10.</head>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg> <em>3</em> April.</i></head>
<p>Notwithstanding all the several beatings those which raise <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> meet with, yet so inveterate is the malice of these people against us, that they will be barking: several parties of them that have been up in <em>Galloway</em> have been met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and within these four or five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> Major <em>Bridges</em> with a party of Col: <em><reg orig="Okies">Okies'</reg></em> took 8 of the Rebels, and 12 Horse in one place, in another place killed 3. took 8 and 25 horse. Cornet <em>Kennes</em> with a party of 20 Horse of Major Gen: <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment coming from <em><reg orig="Dunfreeze">Dumfries</reg></em>, a party of 40 of the Enemy made an attempt upon them, they received the onset, and then charged them, routed the Rebels, killed 4 on the place, took 6 (whereof three mortally wounded) and divers horse. The next day Lieut: <em>Hickman</em> of that same Regiment <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with him, <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> a party of 80 of the Rebels, took 11 prisoners, and above 20 horse; Captain <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em> who commanded them was shot in the back, his horse taken, but himself escaped.</p>
<p><em>Glencarn Glengary</em> &amp;c. are gone over <em>Tayne</em> in <em>Sutherland</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, they give themselves out to be 4000 but I doubt not but <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> will engage them with his party. <em>Montrosse</em>, and the Lord <em>Dudhop</em> are raising their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Angus</em>, they two will be met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> in time.</p>
<p><i><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg> <em>3</em> April</i> thus: Lieutenant <em>Hickman</em> whom <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Cooper</em> sent out with a party of horse towards <em>Galloway</em>, met with the Enemy about 80 Horse, who routed them, and took 23 horse, wounded the Captain that commanded the party, killed 5 men, and wounded divers, and took 11 prisoners.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>It is advertised that the Peace is welcome news to the States of <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em> and that they will suddenly send a Messenger with Thanks to their Ambassadors, and their approbation; and then it is to be published by both, on the same day.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The substance of the Peace agreed upon between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> &amp;c. to this effect but much more large in the particulars, viz.</i></head>
<p>That there shall be a closer <reg orig="Aliance">Alliance</reg> and confederacy between the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> was ever heretofore. That the Peace be published by both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> upon one and the same day; after which, all acts of hostility to cease after ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Seas; from thence to the Cape of St: <em>Vincent</em> after six weeks, and to the <reg orig="Medeterranean">Mediterranean</reg> Sea after six weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>; after which all Prizes to be restored. That all acts past be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither to act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other. That all hostility cease between <em>England</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, none to assist each other against them; and the one not to receive those the other declares to be enemies, but cause them upon notice to depart within 28. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death. That no private persons be suffered to assist the enemies of either, not to pay to either greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> others. The <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships to strike their <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg> to the English in the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Seas; no retreat to be given to <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of the Ports of either; each to comprehend the other in any Treaty with any Nation, if desired. That if any particular Persons break the Peace, it shall not break the National Confederacy: but those that do it to be punished. The Subject of each to travel freely through all quarters of each, by Water or Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and submitting to the laws where they are. That in storms each may have Harbour under other, if they break not bulk, without paying of Customs. The Merchants or <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> not to be pressed to serve under the other, but upon the inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction. That in each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Country, they pass between their Ships, and Inns with lawful Weapons, both Offensive, and Defensive. That all ships of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> defend each other against all whomsoever, sailing their course to either, <em>&amp;c.</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, April 10.</head>
<p>At a meeting of several of the Commissioners for <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>, and approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preaching Ministers, it was thought fit that a Letter should be sent abroad to their Brethren, in these words.</p>
<p><em>Dear Brethren:</em> There being nothing under Heaven of greater importance, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the preaching of the glorious Gospel of Jesus Christ, you cannot but be very <reg orig="sencible">sensible</reg> of what weight and concernment it is to take a right estimate of all that offer themselves, as pass a due approbation of such only, as Christ himself would have admitted to that great employment. A great part of which service in this Nation the Lord by his providence hath cast upon us, and is by us undertaken, as with much fear and trembling, so with a deep <reg orig="sence">sense</reg>, that the effectual accomplishment thereof will much depend upon the Testimonial exhibited to us, concerning the holy and good Conversation of such as seek for approbation from us. Wherefore considering how easily, and frequently abuses creep into businesses of this nature, partly through the endeavours of those who are ill deserving, and partly through the <reg orig="non-attendance">non attendance</reg> of others, who are better minded. For the prevention of any such miscarriage, we have thought it our duty, hereby humbly, and earnestly to beseech all the People of <em>God</em> throughout the Land, who shall send any <em>Certificate</em> to us, that they would not take things upon the opinion and report of others, but (according to the good provision made in the Ordinance, designing us to this Service) to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their own personal <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> and experience, so as neither any, whom God accepteth; may want the testimony of his servants, not any be recommended by them whom he disalloweth; lest guilt be contracted by you, to whose testimonials so much is referred, <pb n="6" />as that through carelessness or partiality therein, very unworthy men may unawares be admitted, to the dishonour of God, the prejudice of his Church, and the utter frustrating of the pious intentions of our Governors, and we also be accounted <reg orig="blame-worthy">blame worthy</reg>, if through your misinformation, way being made for our mistakes, we should at any time act amiss. This we are, and shall be more liable to, by reason of the difficulty of our making discovery in a short time of several <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> graces and gifts, in so full and ample a manner, as would be desired for just satisfaction, without the faithful help of such as having been observers of them, and conversant with them, do more fully know, not only the <reg orig="tenour">tenure</reg> of their Doctrine, but the constant course of their lives. It being a much more <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> thing to be able to describe what a godly man should be, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be one indeed. Nor may we doubt, but there are some men, who having first willingly deceived themselves by a false apprehension and <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg> of their own condition, and estate in grace, will think it <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to deceive us, by giving a false account of that condition. But as such do well to consider that he who <reg orig="trieth">tryeth</reg> the Spirit is not mocked, neither can <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> be hid from his eyes, and that they must undergo another kind of <em>Test</em>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> this slender scrutiny of ours, when the secret of all hearts shall be laid open, and brought to light: So our <em>Brethren</em> may please to consider what opportunity is put into their hand by this <em><reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg></em> made unto them for the avoiding of such mistakes, and the inconveniences which may follow upon them through their neglect; besides the blot which will deservedly stick to them, not only for the present, but with posterity, and succeeding times, forasmuch as the <em>Certificates</em> now exhibited will appear upon Record, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 14.</head>
<p>From <em>Portsmouth</em> thus. The last <em>Monday</em> <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Haynes</em> the Governor of <em>Jersey</em>, Capt: <em>Willet</em> and other Officers came to this Port from <em>London</em>, and with them Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>John Lilburn</em>: They are now gone for <em>Jersey</em>, and having fair wind it is thought that by this time <em>Lilburn</em> is in possession of those Lodgings in the Castle wherein Mr. <em>Prin</em> heretofore had better quarters <reg orig="then">than</reg> his Friends expected.</p>
<p>Upon the return of the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors into <em>Holland</em> with an Olive branch of peace, we hear that Bonfires were made at <em>Amsterdam</em>. The States General have declared their readiness to <reg orig="Signe">Sign</reg> and Seal, and had a full meeting the 10th of <em>April</em>.</p>
<p>An Agent from the King of <em>Denmark</em> is arrived here with Addresses to the Lord Protector, and is to have Audience this week. The Treaty with the <em>French</em> also goes on apace. Great probability is also of Peace with <em>Sweden</em>, and it is <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> upon as the last great and renowned act which that Queen will accomplish, for she is resolved so soon as that is done to give over the Government.</p>
<p>Having thus far made way with <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Princes, his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council (for the perfecting of a firm peace throughout this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>) have passed an Ordinance, offering pardon to the <em>Scottish Highlanders</em> which come in at or before a certain day. Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> set forwards for <em>Scotland</em> on <em>Thursday</em> last. About the middle of the next week the Lord Protector settles in <em><reg orig="Whitehall">White Hall</reg></em>, the lodgings, Offices, and Officers, being now all sitted and in a readiness.</p>
<p>We have <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one more to mention from <em>Scotland, viz:</em> there hath <reg orig="oftentimes">often times</reg> of late appeared very strange sights <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, which hath given such an occasion of talk, that the beholders have been examined before the Judge of <em>Nasserrveld</em>, and they <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, that they have often seen a Troop of black Horse, a rich Coach, and some <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>, and many Footmen come out of a Wood, and another in white, led by a very tall black man, which put the rest to flight.</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> we had certain Intelligence, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> held lately a great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, whereat it was resolved, that the little Queen his Mother should go to <em>Argiers</em>, himself to <em>Chantilly</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em> into <em>Scotland</em>; their stipends from <em>France</em> being promised to be paid.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector is generally commended in all the printed sheets which come forth in <em>Holland, France</em> and <em>Germany</em>.</p> 

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>