<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$07">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $7</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Proclaiming of Peace with the necessity, and benefits thereof redounding to both Nations (and additional Articles) published in <em>England</em>, and in <em>Holland</em>; the <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg> of laying down Arms. The hopes os the taking away of Taxes. The Proclamation of the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em> and the Commissioners in <em>Ireland</em>. The Declaration of the Arch Duke <em>Leopold</em>, and his <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassadors'</reg> Addresses to his Highness the Lord Protector. Several Letters, Papers, and Commissions of the titular King of <em>Scots</em> taken; with his instructions and directions to Lieut: Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, how he should carry on the War against <em>England</em>. With other things of great concernment.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 24 of <em>February</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 3 of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, February 24.</head>
<p>Sir <em>John Lenthal</em> having cleared himself of the Murders, and other <reg orig="hainous">heinous</reg> crimes laid to his charge (and there having been many escapes made, as well since he was out of his place, as before, notwithstanding <reg orig="al">all</reg> the care and diligence of that deserving Gentleman, who officiated the place) the said Sir <em>John </em>is to enjoy the said place of the <reg orig="Upper-Bench">Upper Bench</reg> Prison as formerly.</p>
<p>At this Sessions in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg> were many eminent <reg orig="Tryals">Trials</reg>, <pb n="1" /><em>viz</em>: One <em>Mary Peak</em>, otherwise <em>Mary Moggs</em>, otherwise <em>Mary Norton</em>, was Indicted for having two Husbands, and it appeared by the Evidence that she and one Moggs lived many years together, as Man and Wife, a little within <em>Newgate</em>, and that since (that is to say about three years since) she married with one Sir <em>Edward Norton</em> Baronet, the said <em>Moggs</em> being then, and yet living, to make out the first Marriage unto <em>Moggs</em>, the Church Book of Saint <em><reg orig="Hellins">Hellin's</reg></em> was produced, wherein it appeared that a Man and Woman of their Names were married about 15 years since, but none could prove this to be the very same Woman that was married to <em>Moggs</em>; The Marriage to Sir <em>Edward Norton</em> was laid in little Saint <em><reg orig="Batholomews">Batholomew's</reg></em>, several Witnesses produced tp prove the same; when the <reg orig="Womans">Woman's</reg> terms came to make her defence, she acknowledged the Knight to be her Husband, but absolutely denied that ever she was married to Mr: <em>Moggs</em>, and pleaded that some of the Witnesses spake out of ill will, and the like, and after the whole matter was heard on both sides, the Jury acquitted her.</p>
<p>There was also a Man Indicted for having two Wives, but there was nothing <reg orig="to">too</reg> remarkable in that <unclear><!-- 3 characters--></unclear> so remarkable, as in the former.</p>
<p>One <em>Fern</em> was Indicted for perjury, and he very ingeniously confessed himself guilty, and said that he was drawn thereunto by one <em>Bishop</em>, and that he had five pounds to forswear himself in a <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of Houses and Land, which he said that he took, in regard he was in great necessity, having been about three quarters of a year in Prison, and almost ready to famish with want: he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> himself very penitent.</p>
<p>The Wife of one <em>Beard</em> in <em><reg orig="Thames-street">Thames street</reg> London</em>, was Indicted for Witchcraft; the thing particularly charged against her was, that about four <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> since she by her Witchcraft strook a Child lame, first on the left <reg orig="legg">leg</reg>, and afterwards in the right arm, nay the torture of the poor Child stayed not here, but in a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time she sometimes raged as one stark mad, and at another time was <reg orig="speechles">speechless</reg> and foamed at the mouth, and her hands closed up or fast clinched, and thus she continued many weeks together, at last this Goody <em>Beard</em> came by that way, which the child perceiving, immediately fell a raving and squeaking, and made signs at her, whereupon the Parents of the child <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> a Warrant for <pb n="2" />this Woman, and the Justice found cause to commit her to <em>Newgate</em>, and now upon the examination of Witnesses, she was found guilty, she had three Tears more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary about her.</p>
<p>Three Men, and one Woman were found guilty of the Robbery lately committed at the <em>Greyhound</em> Tavern in <em><reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg></em>, and wounding Mr: <em>Hancock</em> the Master of the House; the Woman was one that had long served the House with Meal, and too much confidence was reposed in her, for she knew what money was in the House, and where the Plate lay, which made her (being evil minded) lay her Plot the deeper. The crime being very notorious and wicked, it was the pleasure of the Bench that these four Persons should be hanged <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the door of the House where they committed the Robbery.</p>
<p>A Woman that took a Lodging at the <reg orig="Horshoe">Horseshoe</reg> in <em>Carter lane London</em>, finding the People of the House diligent in reading and hearing, and in the performance of other orders becoming Christians, this Lodger took upon her a cloak of Religion, till she found a fit opportunity to rob the House, which she did when all the rest were at Church: she was upon <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> found guilty.</p>
<p>The <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother was not <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> this Sessions (as was expected) but there is an Order that the matter shall be examined a new before four Justices of the Peace in order to his <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> the next Sessions.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Febr: 25.</head>
<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> it was this Day advertised, that the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, Sir <em>Arthur Forbs, Glencarn</em>, and <em>Kenmore</em>, are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together in one Body, but their Forces are so broken, and discouraged, that they are unable to make any present opposition, there were taken in the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> House, Two Lieutenants, One Ensign with blew, One Quartermaster, Two <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg>, Two Cornets, 120 <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, Fourscore Muskets, One hundred Pikes, Fifteen case of Pistols, Store of swords, and other Arms, Sixteen barrels of Powder, Five and twenty Troop horses, Great store of Meal, Malt, and Oats.</p>
<p>I have this morning seen a Letter which informs that the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors are landed at <em>Harwich</em>; it is believed that this Day they will come to <em>London</em>; Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em> House in the Palace yard is prepared for them.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Febr: 27.</head>
<p>There came certain Intelligence that <em>Mineheir Newport</em>, and <em>Mineheir Youngstall</em> two Lords Ambassadors from the <em>Netherlands</em> were arrived at <em>Dover</em>, they are <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> Peace. The Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Council gave Order that the Master of the Ceremonies, and others with the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Barge should hasten down to receive them.</p>
<p>The substance of some of the Articles have been formerly printed, but because some were not then mentioned, here followeth an Abstract of the whole.</p>
<head level="3"><i>An Extract of all the Articles of Peace between the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, of <em>England</em> and the <em>Netherlands</em>, which was left out of the Articles formerly printed.</i></head>
<p>1. That from hence forward there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be a more sure, and inviolable Peace, sincere friendship, and a closer Alliance, and Confederacy between the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been ever heretofore, and of their respective Lands, Cities, and Countries, and of all under their obedience wheresoever, and of what condition soever.</p>
<p>2. That all wrongs and offences suffered either by the one or the other party shall be forgotten; and neither party <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> thereupon. All actions past shall be nulled, except those that shall be done in the <em>British </em>Seas, after the time of twelve <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, and from that Sea to the Cape of S <em>Vincent</em> in the Mediterranean Sea, as far as the line after the time of ten weeks, and at the other side of the line in the time of eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> to be reckoned from the time of the publication of the Peace, and all prizes taken after that time, shall be restored.</p>
<p>3. That the States shall cause restitution to be made of all the Ships and Goods seized upon the <em>English</em> by the King of <em>Denmark</em>, that are yet in being, as also a full compensation of the worth of those Goods that may be sold already, and likewise that all the damages or spoil of goods shall be made good to the Owners, by estimation, and when such satisfaction shall be done by the said King, then all hostility shall cease between <em>England</em> and <em>Denmark</em>.</p>
<p>4. That both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall be confederate friends to defend one the other against whomsoever.</p>
<p>5.That if it so fall out that any Ships of either State shall by storm or <em><reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> be driven into any of the Havens of the one or the <pb n="4" />other State, they shall have liberty to got to Sea again at their pleasure with their ships and goods without paying any custom, or Impost, provided that they break not the bulk, behaving themselves according to the laws and customs of the place where they shall take <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg>.</p> 
<p>6. That Men of War of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, or <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships meeting together at Sea, they shall defend each other against all whomsoever that shall offer to make any attempt upon either of them, so long as they sail on course.</p>
<p>7. That all persons of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> going to Sea with particular Commission (before their Commissions be granted) they shall be obliged by sufficient sureties, before the Judges of the Court where they receive their Commissions (that have no part nor portion in the said ships (that they shall do no damage to any Subjects of either <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>
<p>8. Lastly, That there shall be Commissioners established to examine the wrongs or injuries done, or pretended to be done or suffered by the Inhabitants of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in the <em><reg orig="East-Indies">East Indies</reg>, Greenland, <reg orig="Muscovey">Muscovy</reg>, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>, or other places. And if the Commissioners cannot agree thereupon within the time of 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>. Then the aforesaid differences to be referred to the <reg orig="Judgment">Judgement</reg> of the Protestant <em>Switzers</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Febr: 28.</head>
<p>In our last we told you that the Duke of <em>Lorraign</em> was imprisoned by the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Arch Duke</reg>, we should therefore in this place have given you the <reg orig="Arch-Dukes">Arch Duke's</reg> Declaration touching the same, but room is wanting.</p>
<p>The Citizens of <em>Westminster</em> have made several applications to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, about establishing upon them a corporation, and a Committee of the City of <em>London</em> were with his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Council upon the same account, and it is very probable that something will shortly be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in this business, wherein his Highness and his Council <reg orig="wil">will</reg> also have a special care and regard that nothing therein shall prove prejudicial to any that have approved themselves faithful, and are industrious to live in honest vocations.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 1.</head>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> by Letters of the 20th. of February, it was certified, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> intended to go from thence the Monday following with all his train, there being to attend upon him seven Lords, four Knights, besides many Esqs, and Gentlemen, and the report goes, that he intends for <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em>, where there lately appeared a Star in the day time in the sky, as there did over London this day sevenight, of very great <reg orig="bignes">bigness</reg>, and having many shining streams round about it. The last Thursday the Scots King, and his Brother were feasted at the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Court, and there was great Masquing at night. Prince Rupert is returned again to Nants. The great probability of making a firm League and Amity <reg orig="betwix">betwixt</reg> England and Holland is much laid to heart by the English Royalists.</p>
<p>The Duke of Lorraign remains close Prisoner in the Castle of Antwerp, under the Arrest of the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Arch duke</reg>, who chargeth him with many violations of Treaties, and for spoils and <reg orig="ruines">ruins</reg> that he hath made, by making inroads into his Country.</p>
<p>It was also this Day advertised, that the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg>, and the constant Warwick, had rescued the <reg orig="Samaritane">Samaritan</reg> of Bristol, and a Pink belonging to Plymouth, which were both taken by Captain <em>Beach</em>, who was <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to leave them and had much to do to escape himself, but a companion of his, an old Picaro was taken in the Samaritane, and is now in the hold in the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>.</p>
<p>By Letters from the North it is advertised, that Captain <em>Pack</em> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War, who for 7 hours together fought very stoutly, but was at the last <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to submit; we flew 7 of his men, and wounded 15. At the first beginning of the fight her <reg orig="Topmast">Top mast</reg> was shot, by the <reg orig="bord">board</reg>, and in her fall, her tackling being unable to hold her up, she was fain to submit.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>The Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> so long expected to confirm the Peace between both Nations, are now come, we shall in its proper place say more hereof, and in this place give you the Copy of a paper, in commendations of Peace, and Amity.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of a Paper concerning Peace, and Published at <em>Amsterdam</em>.</i></head>
<p>Place is a <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> that purchaseth the security, and quietness of Nations, suppresseth all tumults, uproars, and factions, planting quietness, and tranquillity of life, and (as <em>Cicero</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, Peace is the end of War, dignity and renown the joy of Peace, and in all well established Government an Anchor to both, without which no life is quiet, no estate well stayed, nor no affairs rightly <reg orig="mannaged">managed</reg>, therefore they that with the want hereof, and refuse honourable conditions, may rightly be said to deserve the sword of War; which no man except he be void of reason, and <reg orig="senceless">senseless</reg> would willingly desire, for there is nothing so much to be wished for as Peace, by which not only those things which have <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> in them by nature, but also the very <reg orig="wals">walls</reg>, and Houses do seem to glory, and <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> thereat, for when there is no trouble of War, the spirit is quiet, and fit for every kind of honest rest, Justice flourisheth, <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> <reg orig="sheweth">showeth</reg> her effects, Vice languisheth, the zeal of pity increaseth, the Discipline of the Church is Authorized, both the Noble, and mean man preserveth, and governeth his wealth, trade, and <reg orig="traffique">traffic</reg> is free, briefly <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> receiveth good, and so consequently the whole body of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>
<p>This Day was sold at the Prize Office by candle, a ship called the white Cat, and a parcel of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> Wine.</p>
<p>We hear of an Ambassador coming from <em>France</em> to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 2.</head>
<p>It is our happiness that it is now so <reg orig="fals">falls</reg> out that the time of the coming forth of this Intelligence makes him in effect a Harbinger of <em>Peace</em>, and a <reg orig="fore-runner">forerunner</reg> of Proclaiming the same; yea this day the very streets do sound of <em>Peace</em>, and the <em>taking off heavy burdens, and letting the oppressed go free</em>: and when this shall be read, others may behold the sweet harmony of the two great and potent new united <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their freedom <unclear>in</unclear> entertainment, brotherly <reg orig="imbracements">embracements</reg>, with Congratulations of the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> happiness.</p>
<p><i>For, 1. Peace triumpheth where Reason ruleth; and Security reigneth, where wisdom directeth.</i></p>
<p><i>2ly, It is a sign of godliness to be at peace with men, and at war with vices.</i></p>
<p><i>3ly, Peace from the mouth of a Tyrant is often promised, but seldom performed.</i></p>
<p>There hath been much talk of late of some divisions in <em>Ireland</em>, but the present Letters from thence, wherein was <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> (which here followeth) advertise thus, that Lieut: Gen: <em>Fleetwood</em> is very well, and all things there reconciled, in such a manner that both Officers, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, do solemnly engage to live and die true and faithful to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Government now established.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector being proclaimed at <em>Dublin</em>, the Commissioners issued forth these Warrants following.</p>
<head level="3"><i><em>IRELAND</em>. By the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> for the Affairs of <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>
<p>The Proclamation above mentioned lately coming to our knowledge, we held it our duty for prevention of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> disturbances and interruptions in the administration of Justice, to publish the same: To the end that all Sheriffs, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Officers and Ministers in this Nation, whom the same doth concern, may take notice thereof; Requiring all Officers and Soldiers of the Army, and all Sheriffs, Judges, Justices of the Peace, Commissioners for Administration of Justice, and all others who are entrusted with the management of any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Affairs, to be vigilant in their respective charges and Trusts, That the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> service may be carried on, and that the common Enemy, upon this change of Government, may not take any advantage to contrive or act new disturbances against the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace. Dated at Dublin the thirtieth day of January, 1653. Signed by Order and command of the said Commissioners. JO HUGHES Sec:</p> 

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>