<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$03">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $3</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>A Declaration of the <em>Hollanders</em> upon the late Treaty, and desires of a cessation of Hostility, and their sending over other Ambassadors. Likewise a Declaration of the Generals, Officers, and Commanders at Sea, with their Addresses to his Highness the Lord Protector. A great fight between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Highlanders</em>, five hundred killed, wounded, taken, and dispersed. The <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg></em> besieging a Garrison of ours called <em>Burgie</em>, and keeping their Guards along upon the River of <em>Findern</em>. Capt: <em>Ker</em>, and Capt: <em>Elsmore</em> killed. General <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> taking up of his head Quarters at <em>Elgan</em>. Eighteen <em>Irishmen</em> condemned for Treason. With other News from <em>France, Denmark</em>, and <em>Sweden</em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 27 of <em>January</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 3 of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, January 20.</head>
<p><em><reg orig="Heer">Heir</reg> Beverlin</em> (one of the Deputies of <em>Holland</em> which lately went away) being returned again into <em>England</em>, this Day made his Address to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, the substance whereof was this; That he was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by the States of the Province of <em>Holland</em>, to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> to his Highness, and his Council, that the States of that Province, and the Province of <em>Westfriezland</em> had a meeting, to consult upon the negotiations and transactions of the late Treaty between them, and the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and at length they came to this result, that <pb n="1" />they signed the Articles which were sent from <em>England</em>, and he presented some Papers confirming what he had said, desiring there might be a cessation of Arms on both sides for a certain time, which would be <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg>, could we have assurance that a firm Peace would be concluded with these, and the other Provinces, and <reg orig="til">till</reg> then we have little reason to hearken unto words, considering how they have played fast and loose, not only with us, but with other Nations.</p>
<p>The Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord Mayor of <em>London</em>, and the Worshipful Aldermen of the same, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> as well in this, as otherwise their good affection to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the present Government, thought good that his Highness, and his Council, with other Honourable Persons, should be invited to a Dinner in the City, and thereupon some eminent Persons were appointed to <reg orig="envite">invite</reg> his Highness as aforesaid, and in regard of the weighty affairs of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, it was left to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> election, what time he pleased to make choice of to receive the entertainment of the City.</p>
<p>About three of the clock this afternoon part of the Rough of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the South door <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> down, and one or two <reg orig="boyes">boys</reg> of those which were playing there, were sorely wounded with the stones, and Rubbish which fell, and had it not been at a time when others were at School, in all probability much hurt had been done. <em>This is the fourth time that sad accidents have <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> since <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> was pulling down</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Wallwine</em> who was lately a Prisoner in the Tower of <em>London</em>, hath his liberty; and Mr: <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em> of <em>Butholphus <reg orig="Bushops">Bishop's</reg> gate</em>, and Mr: <em>Feake</em> that <reg orig="Preacht">Preached</reg> at <em>Christ church</em> being sent for before the Council, were charged to utter many dangerous things, yet one of them pleading ignorance, though the Ordinance was printed, and published before, and upon the examination of the whole matter, they were both committed to custody.</p>
<p>It may be here remembered, that when Mr. <em>Feake</em> was called before the said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> some few weeks before this, when he attended in that which is called the <em>Presence Chamber</em>, next where the Council sit; he kneeled down before he was called in, and fell to Prayers, <em>but now he did not so</em>.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Januar: 28.</head>
<p>The Letters from <em>Sweden</em> do highly <reg orig="extoll">extol</reg> the respects <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> to the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, and his Attendants there; as also that the Lord Ambassador doth much admire the wisdom, and Majesty of the said Queen, and her great abilities in State affairs, and in this place we shall give you the substance of the Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> Speech at his Audience before her Majesty.</p>
<p>He declared, that although the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> are not <reg orig="incouraged">encouraged</reg> to send abroad when they reflect upon the barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places, yea in her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Government they have not the least <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>, but gracefully acknowledged their experience to the contrary; From thence he proceeded to the deliverances of the Armies of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, which have been <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg>; and touched upon the excellencies of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Person and Government, making a comparison betwixt her and Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>. He then made mention of the Wars of her Father for the orthodox Religion, and just liberties, which were also the occasions of the Wars of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> both in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em> in which GOD was <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> pleased to determine for the Parliament, and after 8 tenders of the Treaty for Peace to change the Government of <em>England</em> which was occasioned through the extremity of the ill government of the Successors of the Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, who although <reg orig="forreiners">foreigners</reg> had otherwise received all obedience and subjection from her people. He then made a similitude betwixt the Nations of <em>England</em> and <em>Swedenland</em> in language, manners, and dispositions; and that in no Age there hath been a declared War against them, which being considered to lay a stronger obligation upon both Nations by which, their tranquillity may be preserved, her Majesty having to that purpose sent her late <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers into <em>England</em>, the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how acceptable those overtures were, do not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> renew the former amity between both Nations, but have <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> her to enter into a more strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath yet been for the good of both.</p>
<p>The Letters out of <em><reg orig="Mengomeryshiere">Mengomeryshire</reg></em> relate some strange Passages concerning Mr: <em>Vavassar Powell</em>, and a Book was put forth in print this week in <em>London</em>, called <em>A Hue and Cry after him</em>, wherein he is charged with absurdities, which (if true) befitted not a man of his profession.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<p><em>Dalkeith 26 Jan</em>: One Troop of Col: <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Dragoons being relieved are gone after him in the North, from whom we have not heard since he marched from <em>Aberdeen</em>. The Regiments in <em>Scotland</em> do well approve of the New Government in <em>England</em>, and the Officers generally send in their Addresses, to be sent to his Highness, to that purpose; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some few of the Major General <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment, chiefly of the <reg orig="Welch">Welsh</reg> Troop, the Quartermaster, and some Soldiers are gone off towards <em>England</em>, and the Chaplain to the Regiment. There was a Shallop built up, and four Guns put into her, to secure Trade in the River <em>Clyde</em>, and prevent the <em>Highlanders</em> falling into <em>Renfrewshire</em>, which they often did before; but there being present no other considerable Vessel to assist, (as was expected) three or four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> agone one Lieutenant Co': <em>Harriot</em> with some Boats from the Loughs in the Hills, <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> the Vessel. A Lieutenant of Gen: <em><reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg></em> Regiment, and seven or eight other, (most Officers) were lately taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Falkirk</em>, by a party, and carried to the Hills. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Humphreys">Humphrey's</reg></em> Troop is come to <em>Musleborough</em>, we long much for the other two Regiments.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Jan: 30.</head>
<p><i>A Declaration of the Admiralty of <em>Holland</em>, sitting at</i></p>
<p><em>Amsterdam</em>.</p>
<p>Let it be known, that it being conceived, thought, and apparent, that upon the coming of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Deputies of this State from <em>England</em>, so make Report how far the Treaty is by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> grace and favour effected: Some <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg>, and Masters of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, upon presumption of a cessation of hostility, have been so forward as to have brought out their ships, and goods, and have beyond their hope suffered <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>
<p>We have therefore found good, and resolved to give warning unto all whom it concerneth; That the former hostility doth yet continue, and that it is not fit, nor convenient, that one should in regard of the Treaty think himself secure, before upon the continuation of the Negotiation, there shall be a cessation of the aforesaid hostility Proclaimed.</p>
<p><i>Acted in the Assembly of the said Council, the 16 Jan: 1653.</i></p> 
<p><i>F: Herberts.</i></p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Jan: 31.</head>
<p>A Declaration hath been presented from the Fleet to his Highness as followeth, (<em>Viz.</em>)</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p><i>For his Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>,<em> Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>The DECLARATION with the humble Address of the Generals, and several Commanders present in the Fleet, by them severally subscribed.</i></p>
<p>That these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, having been for some years like the Bush which burned, but is not consumed: And though the Nations round about us stand gazing on to see us made a desolation, as well as a hissing unto them; yet we are hitherto by the mighty power of the Lord, and his wonderful outgoings amongst us, mae rather an astonishment in our preservation, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a reproach, by our <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and devastation.</p>
<p>In which great work of the Lord, we <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> with thankfulness Your Highness hath been a glorious Instrument; and hath undergone many hardships, and hazard of all that was near and dear unto you, even to life <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, and understanding by providence Your Highness <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with, and hath accepted of the Protection of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in the Government thereof.</p>
<p>We are in hope that the Lord intends a settlement of Peace to these poor distracted Nations; and that <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with all the People of the Lord shall <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg>, and partake of the same under your protection, according to the Rule of the Lord Jesus. And <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> we have thought it necessary as a duty incumbent on us to declare, that we shall willingly be obedient, and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to Your Highness in performance of Your great Trust, and also in the utmost hazard of our lives, (with what else is near and dear unto us) be serviceable unto you in the station the Lord hath placed You, against Yours, and the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Enemies in our <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places and capacities during our employments.</p>
<p>And having had good testimony of Your great affection, and earning bowels after the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> People, we are <reg orig="imboldned">emboldened</reg> and encouraged to make this following Address.</p>
<p>That Your Highness will be pleased to have a more special eye of favour unto them above all others, in regards they are near and dear unto him, who is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, even our Lord Jesus. For which cause he is not ashamed to call them Brethren; And do humbly apprehend that their <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> will be Your <reg orig="Priviledg">Privilege</reg>. And to account of them as of your greatest Jewels, which will doubtless turn to you great advantage <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<!-- end of page has a "preview" of the word "Wednesday", as used in the daily headings; however the rest of the heading is not present on the next page -->
<pb n="5" />
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we understand, that the Enemy make a great bustle, and though it is thought it will be to little purpose, yet see how high their General <em>Glencarn</em> flies in the words of his Proclamation.</p>
<head level="3">A PROCLAMATION</head>
<head level="3"><i>William Earl of Glencarn, Lord <reg orig="Kilmares">Kilmores</reg>, Commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of Scotland.</i></head>
<p>Forasmuch as to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and advancement of <em>our to <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> old Enemy</em> the Kingdom of <em>England</em>, who by their perfidious practise, and all unlawful means still pretending the good advancement of the Protestant Religion, hath endeavoured the reducement, and <reg orig="inslaving">enslaving</reg> of us, our predecessors, and Country to their subjection. Many pretended Countrymen of several qualities, within the Shires of <em>Dunbarton, Ayr, Rantfrew</em>, and other adjacent places upon the Southside of the Farth, are not ashamed to bring in, tell, and deliver to several Officers of Garrisons belonging to the said grand Enemy, the whole serviceable Arms, and other offensive weapons, they either have, or possibly can acquire, whereby his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> in most part of the said <reg orig="shieres">shires</reg>, are greatly impeded far contrary to our natural Countrymen, inhabiting the Northern shires, who by their good example, laying to heart the bleeding condition of this native Country, do all unanimously take up arms, and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with us for relief, and recovery thereof, we do therefore by these presents <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> and declare, that whatsoever person or persons of whatsoever quality, within any of the said shires of <em>Dunbarton, Ayr, <reg orig="Rantfew">Rantfrew</reg></em>, or places adjacent, shall upon whatsoever pretence after publication hereof, presume to sell, give, or deliver up to any belonging to the said common Enemy, any serviceable Horse or Arms to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service of <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> of Horse and Foot, <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon any of them, that the whole good and <reg orig="geir">gear</reg> of the person or persons disobeyers <pb n="6" />of this our command (without respect of any) shall be sequestrate, and confiscate for the use of any whatsoever can first apprehend them, for <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with, and effectuating whereof, these presents shall be an <reg orig="irreduceable">irreducible</reg> Warrant, and ordains publication hereof at the Market Cross of <em>Dunbarton</em>, whereby they, <reg orig="no-none">no none</reg> of the Shires of <em><reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfrew">Rantfrew</reg></em>, or places adjacent pretend ignorance hereof.</p>
<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="Weims">Weems</reg></em> this 22 of December, <em>1653</em> sic subscribitur</i></p>
<p>GLENCARN.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Jan: 20.</head>
<p>The Letters from <em>Paris</em> make mention that the Court proceeds against such as were <reg orig="ayding">aiding</reg>, and assisting to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, against the King in the late Wars. <em>Monsieur Fonguat</em> hath obtained his enlargement out of Prison, but sentence of <reg orig="Excilement">Exilement</reg> is pronounced against him, during the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> pleasure. The famous Town of Rusa is Relieved with all kind of necessaries, and the <em>Spaniards</em> hath deserted the siege, and hath taken up his Quarters further off.</p>
<p>The Prince of Conti is not yet come in, or his Brother the Prince of Conde taken, though violently pursued.</p>
<p>From Bristol they write, that they have come to that Port good quantities of Sugars, yet the Brest Men of War ply up and down about the Landsend, and have taken lately many <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels of ours. They have also taken two London ships, the one going to the <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, and the other coming from thence, but we hope some care will be taken shortly to clear these Coasts of them. We have news from <em>Ireland</em> that the <em>Tories</em> are abroad again in many parts, robbing and thieving, and very manfully run <reg orig="for't">for it</reg> when they have done.</p>
<p>From the <em>Isle of Man</em> we understand that an <em>Irish</em> <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> lately took a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> English Vessel, bound for a Garrison of ours in the West of <em>Scotland</em>. Two Vessels have been cast away on this Coast by Tempest.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 2.</head>
<p>Besides the Declaration before recited from <em>Holland</em>, we had other news as followeth. The <reg orig="States">State's</reg> General do sit daily at the <em>Hague</em>, and placets are gone forth for calling together the Deputies of the several Provinces in order to the full concluding of a Peace with <em>England</em>; but some being backwarder <reg orig="then">than</reg> others herein, it is thought it will be <em>March</em> before we know the full result of these things. In the mean time they prepare as fast for War as you can do in <em>England</em>, and are possessed with some fear more than ordinary, <reg orig="b'cause">because</reg> they hear your Fleet is out at Sea already.</p>
<p>The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> hath declared, that he hath had many injuries and affronts from the Elector of <em>Collen</em>. The said Duke hath taken <em>Orsey</em> Castle, where he found 300 Horse, and 750 Pistols with other Arms.</p>
<p>Eighteen <em>Irish</em> are condemned for Treason, being of the number of those which had a plot to betray the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Armentiers</em>.</p>
<p>There is great contest betwixt the Emperors Forces and the <em>Swedes</em> about the Town of <em>Bremen</em>, they both claim right to it, but the Emperor hath gotten the possession.</p>
<p>There was the 19. of <em>Januar</em>: a fight in <em>Scotland</em> between a party of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Forces which were come down to <em>Dunkel</em>, 200 of our Horse and Dragoons commanded by Capt: <em>Ashby</em> killed, wounded, took and <reg orig="disperst">dispersed</reg> 500 of theirs.</p>
<p>General <em>Glencarn</em> keeps his head quarters at <em>Elgan</em>, his Forces there are estimated to be 1200 Foot, and 500 Horse and Dragoons. <em>Kenmore</em> quarters at <em>Ferrers</em> with about the same number, he sets his Guards along upon the River of <em>Findern</em>. The Enemy hath also besieged a Garrison of ours called <em>Burgie</em>, which we are seeking to relieve. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> is marched towards part of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemies'</reg> Forces; we take divers prisoners. The coming of General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is much longed for here.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, have under consideration the Regulation of the Law, and particularly the high Court of <em>Chancery</em>.</p>
<p>The Last Letters from <em>Falmouth</em> say, that two <em>Dutch</em> Prizes, and one <em>French</em> Prize are brought in thither.</p>
<p>Out of <em>France</em>, we hear, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, and Prince <em>Rupert</em> are yet at <em>Paris</em>; they send often Letters to the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>; the Duke of <em>York</em> is gone to the Army.</p> 

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>