<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$14">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $14</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Articles of Peace returned to the Lord Protector in a costly silver Box; the passing them under the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, and an Order for the Proclaiming thereof by Heralds of Arms sounding of Trumpets, and white <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg>. The Lord Protector <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, with the number of his standing Guard. The discovery of a further Design of the Enemy in <em>Scotland</em>, the going of many <em>English</em> unto them, with two Clerks belonging to the Courts of Justice at <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>; Divers Soldiers out of <em>Leith</em>, and <em>50</em> from <em>Sterling</em>. A Letter from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> touching <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>. A Declaration of the Pope. A List of several Prizes taken at Sea; And the proceedings of the Commissioners for <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of Ministers at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 14 of <em>April</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 21 of <em>April</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, April 14.</head>
<p>Now we arrive at the Haven so much desired, and yet (through distrust of the Pilots) great doubts were in the hearts of the People. That which we shall chiefly treat upon is, the Ratification of the Peace betwixt Us and <em>Holland</em>, whereof we had Letters this day, that in some measure give satisfaction, for they speak as followeth.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>The States General of <em>Holland</em> sat the tenth Instant, upon the Articles of Peace between <em>England</em>, and them, as they came over signed, and Sealed by their own Ambassadors in <em>England</em>, and after a <reg orig="ful">full</reg> consideration one of the Deputies of every Province did also Sign, and Seal, and ordered that Proclamation should be made at a day then appointed for establishing the said Articles of Peace, and the <reg orig="re-uniting">reuniting</reg> of these <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, wherein regard was had to the time when it should be Proclaimed in <em>England</em>, and a special Messenger was <reg orig="dispatch'd">dispatched</reg> away to give notice to the Lord Protector, and his Council of their unanimous consent, and accord with them.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday, April</em> 15.</head>
<p>By the last Post from <em>Rochel</em> we have received advertisement, that the Treaty between <em>England</em> &amp; the United Provinces of the Low Countries being concluded, the report thereof, and of a mighty English Fleet ready to go to Sea, riding <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Portsmouth</em>, the whole Country thereabouts took a strong Alarum, every Governor, and Commander of Port, Castle, and Fort, causing strong guard to be kept, fearing lest the said Fleet should have any design to land some Forces there; they likewise sent to the court to know his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure therein, and to desire assistance in case his Majesty shall think the same requisite; what the issue will be, we as yet know not.</p>
<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>, Dated <em>April</em> 4 thus. Lieut: <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Mitchel</em> marched hither with 9 Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of Horse, and a commanded Party of about 180, with 5 Troops of Dragoons, which marched yesterday to <em>Brahan</em>, to which 4 troops of Horse and three Companies of Foot are added. The cause of this march is to keep a Pass at <em>Dinghill</em>, which in the <reg orig="judgment">judgement</reg> of many knowing men of the Country, will constrain them either to fight with us, stay in the place where they are, or run the hazard of losing their Horse by the length, badness of way, and want of provisions, in case they march by the <reg orig="North-west">North West</reg> <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> to the South one or other of which exigencies they cannot avoid. The Enemy had a general <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> on the first of this Instant, near the Castle of <em>Skilbo</em> in <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, where (as they give out) appeared between <pb n="2" />four and five hundred horse and Foot; upon better information we hear they were not fully 3000, viz. about 1600 foot, and about one thousand horse, the one half of which are very unfit for the service of war, and many not half armed, some wanting swords, and some pistols, <em>Middleton</em> has added to the number about 200 horse and foot. At this <reg orig="Randevvous">Rendezvous</reg> <em>Middleton</em> declared, that he had brought some good quantity of Gold with him into <em>Scotland</em>, which he said the Emperor of Germany had sent his Master, and that the said Emperor was raising a far greater sum, and a great number of men, which he said he would have staid, and brought with him, but that he heard there was some discontent amongst his friends, arising from his often failing in his promised coming to them; He then exhorted them to prosecute the work they had in hand effectually, and to use their utmost endeavours to force the enemy to depart the Country.</p>
<p>After this, he gave Order that the most of them should march for the South Highlands, and the rest to continue in the North, and both to go on vigorously to prosecute their new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. He hath ordered 250 to be <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> out of <em>Ross</em>, 300 out of <em>Sutherland, Caithness</em> 600, and <em>Stranarvar</em> 300. He hourly expects <em>Seafort</em> with 500 men, and <em>Mackoldwy</em> to be ready with his <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 17.</head>
<p>A Return came from <em>Holland</em>, concerning the signing, and sealing the Articles of Peace, and the Ratification by the States General of the 7. United Provinces; as <reg orig="al">all</reg>. so the day which they have prefixed for Proclaiming the said Articles of Peace in <em>Holland</em>, at which time the same will likewise be Proclaimed in <em>England</em>: All which his <pb n="3" />Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council have debated of, and all things here go on in a way of Love, and sweet harmony of Peace, not only with <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, but also with <em>France, Sweden, Portugal</em>, and other Kingdoms.</p>
<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement, concerning the Commissioners appointed for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers sitting at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</i></head>
<p>The Commissioners for <em>Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers</em> sit on <em><reg orig="Mondayes, Wednesdayes">Mondays, Wednesdays</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Fridayes">Fridays</reg></em>; of which <em><reg orig="Fridayes">Fridays</reg></em> for <em>Augmentations</em>.</p>
<p>In all the Transactions there is no respect had to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> so much as grace in <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> hearts, some University men, for defect thereof, have been laid by, and some who never were University men, yet furnished with Gifts and Graces, have been received and welcomed.</p>
<p>No difference at all among the Commissioners themselves, though they be of divers <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg> about <reg orig="Church-matters">Church matters</reg>, all minding the advancement of the Gospel.</p>
<p>They being 38 in number are severed into three divisions, each division sitting their <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, so that the Work will go constantly on.</p>
<p>Nor partiality used in their <reg orig="tryals">trials</reg>. Testimonies, and Certificates are narrowly looked into, because much depends upon them.</p>
<p>If Patrons would present good men, it would much help on this work.</p>
<p>Some of the men who have been already tried, have preached at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable others will hereafter be put upon this way of exercising their Gifts.</p>
<p>If the carriage of this business were in the view of the Nation, the Censures of men would be <reg orig="forborn">forborne</reg>; and whereas some are of opinion, that these Triers ought to have been sent from Churches, men are to know, that the Magistrate only looks to the sending forth Preachers, and takes not upon him to set down Church Officers; but out of the number of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, Church officers may afterwards be chosen, if Congregations see cause.</p>
<p>An extraordinary number of Preachers are continually attending upon these Commissioners to receive their <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg>; and yet <pb n="4" />there will be want of thousands. They usually sit upon the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before mentioned, from 8 <reg orig="til">till</reg> 12 in the morning; and <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> every day, because of the abundance of business pressing upon them.</p>
<p>No Certificates are approved but such as come subscribed under the hands of such persons as are known to the Commissioners or some of them.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 15.</head>
<head level="3"><em>Cornwall</em>, by the last.</head>
<p>Mrs <em>Hannah Trapnel</em> she that lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, hath for some time been in these parts. There seem to be two convincing Reasons against her Spirit; the one is, that it withdraws from Ordinances, and the other is, that it is <reg orig="non-sensical">nonsensical</reg>. There are in her Company one Mr: <em>Langdon</em>, and Mr: <em>Banden</em>, two Members of the late <reg orig="short-lived">short lived</reg> Parliament. The Justices of this County have taken notice of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, and practises; and Mr: <em>Lobb</em> giving the charge here this last Sessions, willed the Jury to enquire, 1 concerning Vagrants, 2 such as occasioned unlawful meetings. 3 Such as speak against the present Government. There were two Indictments drawn against her, <em>Langdon</em> and <em>Bandon</em> her Compeers, and abettors, endeavoured to make a learned Defence for her, but it was not suffered; only they <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into Bonds of three hundred pounds for her good behaviour, and appearance at the next Assizes. If you had <reg orig="inquired">enquired</reg> better into her business, when she tranced it at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, it might have prevented the staggering of many a spirit in <em>Cornwall</em>. The design intended to be made use of by means of this Woman is (it seems) to compass <em>England</em>, and pass from one good Town to another to vent her Prophesies, and thereby disaffect the People to the present Authority. It <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> to mind the old story of <em>Elizabeth Barton</em>, the holy maid of <em>Rent</em> (as she was called) in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of <em>Henry</em> the 8 who was made use of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests, by <reg orig="fained">feigned</reg> Miracles, and Trances, to raise admiration in the multitude, and <reg orig="soment">cement</reg> seditious <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> against the Government; for which she had in the end her reward.</p>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April</em> 13. The design of rising here <reg orig="dos">does</reg> appear every day more universal, not only the <em>Scots</em> flying out, but divers <em>English</em>; and amongst the rest three Clerks belonging to the Court of Justice at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>. Divers Soldiers out of <em>Leith</em>, and about 50 from <em>Sterling</em> are gone to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, April 19.</head>
<p>This Day arrived in the River of <em>Thames</em> divers <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, among which were 4. whose lading is chiefly with Currance.</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> they write, that the Governor of <em>Rochel</em> sent Letters to the King, acquainting his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> that a mighty Fleet of the <em>English</em> did lately give them a great Alarum, and desires his Majesty to take speedy order for the <reg orig="re-inforcing">re enforcing</reg> of the Castles, and Forts on that side of the Country, for now the Treaty is made up with <em>Holland</em>; he mistrusts that the English have a design to land some men in <em>France</em>, if the King make not also his Peace with <em>England</em> speedily.</p>
<p>A Letter from <em>Spanish</em> Merchant, to a person of <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg> concerning Trade, and Commerce.</p>
<p><em>Right Honourable</em>, In obedience to your Commands, I humbly render you these Propositions, as necessary for the good of the people of our <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (in relation to trade) to be articulated with the King of <em>Spain</em>; wherein I could not be so compendious as I intended, for that such is the importance of the Subject, such the <reg orig="limiatiton">limitation</reg> of the last articles (made betwixt that King, and the late Deceased, and those so ill observed, as hath been others, sit hence purchased for 1000 so many are the Ports and Countries of his Dominions of <em>L. Spain</em>, &amp; each enjoying distinct <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg>; so many new impositions have been introduced by that King, contrary to those articles, so many are the molestations, and exactions that his several Judges and Officers in all places inflict on our Factors, <reg orig="Ship-masters">Ship masters</reg>, and others of this Nation on every slight pretence, searching our Horses, taking <pb n="6" />away our Books, and papers, imprisoning, and fining at their pleasures, <reg orig="imbarguing">embargoing</reg> our ships, confiscating our goods, and to remain with our means, they never want evasions, and false suggestions, making white to appear black, by such persons, Informers, and inferior Officers; (as for to catch 5 shillings care not if 5000 <em>l</em>. be condemned or <reg orig="dammaged">damaged</reg>) and these are sharers in the booty, and as such introduce Witnesses interested with the <reg orig="Judg">Judge</reg>, Interpreter, and Scrivener, who takes the depositions by which the suits are adjudged, as they are also in <reg orig="appelation">appellation</reg> superior Tribunals (and not by <em>viva voce</em>.)</p>
<p>In this manner do they use the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Commissioners, and abuse his Authority in remote Ports) under a form and pretence of Justice, being ignorant of other Countries, imagining that all the world should be subject to them, violating the peace, offensive to God: So destructive to the commerce, the utility of our Peace with <em>Spain</em>) That the Merchants, and particular Members, are not only sensible hereof, but this whole Nation as a body <reg orig="intelectual">intellectual</reg>: Yet we <reg orig="alledg">allege</reg> not this so much for the past matter of interest, as the importance of the present matter, we treat not so much of having paid 50 or a hundred thousand pound <em>per annum</em> since the last Articles to the King, and his Officers, as to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how much it concerns the commerce, and this Nation; that such special regard be had to the making of new Articles; and to procure that they be so observed, as that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Officers for the time to come, may be disabled from their abuse, which your universal Providence, so vigilant for the conversation and advancement of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, can best prescribe: Wherein I pray God to direct You, <em>&amp;c. Your most humble, and faithful Servant,</em> R. B.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 20.</head>
<p>Now what say all you that are so full of distrust, that for all that hath been said hitherto, cannot <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> any reality of Peace betwixt <em>England</em> &amp; <em>Holland</em> (because it is not yet proclaimed) yet let this be added unto what hath been said already, <em>viz</em>: The Articles of Peace are certainly Signed and Sealed by the States General of the United Provinces, and are returned back again to his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> in a silver Box. It remaineth now that his Highness pass the same also under the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, to which he gives his Sign <em>Manual</em>, this Ceremony being over, and notice thereof given to the States General, Peace is to be proclaimed by Heralds at Arms, found of Trumpets, and white <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg> in both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>. In the <reg orig="mean while">meanwhile</reg> there hath been some late actions at Sea, and we have taken these prizes following.</p>
<p>The Rear admiral of St, The <em>Love Blanch</em> (<em>Mallows)</em>, The <em>St. Joques</em>, The <em>John Baptist</em>, The St. <em>Clement</em> sunk, A ship of 14 guns and 70 men sunk, The <em>Foundore</em> sunk, Another ship of 22 guns sunk.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector is now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in <em>Whitehall</em>, the Lodgings and Officers are for the most part ordered as they were formerly; and his Highness hath a guard of sixty proper stout men.</p>
<p>There were 2 persons stood in the Pillory yesterday at the Old Exchange, the one was for perjury, the other for forgoing of Letters.</p>
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador hath had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Treaties with some of the Lords of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Council.</p>
<p>The renowned Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath written a Letter to the <em>French</em> Ambassador concerning her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> resolution to surrender he Crown and Kingdom; it beginneth, and endeth thus.</p>
<p><i><em>G. R.</em> We have formerly given you an account of the Reasons which have prevailed with us to go on in our design of <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> up our Crown, yet shall we conserve you in our affection in whatsoever condition we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be; and we shall make it appear to you, that no change whatsoever may alter those <reg orig="sences">senses</reg> of my <reg orig="minde">mind</reg>, wherein we <reg orig="glorifie">glorify</reg> our self. You know all this, and <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg>, no doubt, that the greatest assurance we can give is to tell you that we shall ever be, <em>CHRISTIANA</em>.</i></p>
<p>The Pope hath set forth a Declaration against <em>Arminians</em>.</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Pride</em> is going with a Regiment into <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>