<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$06">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $6</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>A great and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight in <em>Scotland</em> betwixt the <em>English</em>, and the <em>Highlanders</em>, and the number killed and taken: With General <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> Proclamation for raising if every third man for the titular King of <em>Scots</em>. A great fight at Sea between part of the <em>English</em> Fleet, and the <em>Dutch</em>, and how many were sunk, killed, and wounded. The last Orders of the States of <em>Holland</em> to their Admirals. The landing of their Ambassadors at <em><reg orig="Graves-end">Gravesend</reg></em>, for ratifying the Articles of Peace. The Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> Orders touching damages done by the <em>English</em>. The Addresses of the <em>French</em> Ambassadors to the Lord Protector. And an Order touching farthings to pass throughout the Nation.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 17 of <em>February</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 24 of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, February 17.</head>
<p>What a mad Age live we in, that when men know not how to find fault with a cause, they will wilfully dash themselves against a Rock, is it not sufficient for <reg orig="Clergie men">Clergymen</reg> (that are of ability) to have liberty, yea and large encouragements to Preach the word in season, and out of season, <reg orig="withous">without</reg> <reg orig="rayling">railing</reg> upon their Governors, (for they know not what) and against Lawyers, and not to spare their own Tribe, but further, to teach themselves (as <pb n="1" /><em>Paul</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, and carry with them into the <reg orig="Pulpet">Pulpit</reg> a Declaration of an old date, promising Liberty and freedom to the People, &amp;c, and there to <reg orig="coment">comment</reg> his own thoughts upon it, as one did this week at Saint <em>Thomas <reg orig="Apostles">Apostle's</reg></em>, and how unsatisfied the People went away (as to the soul saving Doctrine) is left to themselves who were Auditors to <reg orig="judg">judge</reg>, as also how much good this, and other such like carriages do the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in general, for if he that hath cause to find fault rails when he should reason; he shall get no answer, but when we reason without <reg orig="rayling">railing</reg>, we may perchance get a bashfulness to dissent from us, and a reverence of the truth, which in time will bring forth a profession of it.</p>
<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance of explanation touching Treasons.</i></head>
<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordinance Declaring that the Offences therein mentioned, and no other, shall be adjudged High Treason within the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland</em>, it is, amongst other things, Ordained and Established, <em>That no Matter, Fact, Crime or Offence whatsoever, other than such as are therein mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken, or adjudged to be High Treason</em>. And whereas some doubts and question may arise, whether that Clause in the said Ordinance doth not extend to the Offences mentioned in the Instrument, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>The Government of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of </em>England, Scotland, <em>and</em> Ireland, <em>and the Dominions thereto belonging</em>, and which are thereby Declared to be High Treason; For clearing thereof, and removing all scruples thereupon, His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That neither the said Ordinance, nor any clause or thing therein contained, shall extend or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend to all or any the Offences declared by the said Instrument to be High Treason, but that all and every the said Offences are hereby adjudged, taken, and deemed to be High Treason, and that all and every the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg>, and <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> shall suffer the pains and penalties of High Treason, the said Ordinance, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein contained to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Feb: 18.</head>
<p>In my last was a discovery of a Plot against the Lord Protector, and the present Government, we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> in this place give you some further satisfaction therein (waving as much as may be what hath been already made known by former pens.) Many green heads who had little to do, begin to build Castles in the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, and for that they have in their <reg orig="yong">young</reg> experience seen several alterations of Government, they think it <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to add one more, in which they intended to promote the Interest of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and as it is said to murder his Highness the lord Protector, his Council, the chief of the officers of the Army, and a great part of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, and to that end some met once or twice in consultation; and finding some deficiency in themselves to compass what was intended, without the help of riper <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg>, and persons of greater Quality, they <reg orig="pitcht">pitched</reg> upon four select men for the chief managers of this business, which was all carried under an Oath of secrecy) one whereof being <reg orig="toucht">touched</reg> with Conscience, discovered the design, and gave Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>. Worsley, and other Officers notice of the meeting of some of the Complotters at such a time at the Ship tavern in the <reg orig="Old Baily">Old Bailey</reg>, where was apprehended accordingly <em>Mr. Joseph Sawyer, Mr. Thomas Dutton, Mr. William Jenkins, Mr. John Archer, M. Thomas Bunch,</em> Son to Alderman <em>Bunch, Mr. Joseph Parker, Mr. Roger Lee, Mr. Thomas Rosse, Mr. Christopher Watkins,</em> Captain <em>Smith</em> who <unclear><reg orig="soliciten">solicits</reg> </unclear> at <reg orig="Haberdashers-Hall">Haberdashers' Hall</reg>, <em>Mr. Roger Cotes, </em>and <em>Mr. Peter Middleton</em> was there, but escaped, all the rest after examination, were this Day sent Prisoners to the Tower, and Warrants are issued out against many more; It is said they have Commissions come from beyond sea, and intended to raise thirty thousand men, but nothing was found in the pockets of those first apprehended. Thus may you <pb n="3" />briefly see that the Plot wanted not either for <reg orig="bredth">breadth</reg> or length, yet fell short of depth, to make up the three <reg orig="Dementions">Dimensions</reg>; <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> now they would be glad if they were of no other sentence <reg orig="then">than</reg> the Poets feign upon the fifty Daughters of a King, who for killing their Husbands, were condemned <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> to be filling a Vessel <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of holes.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em> Febr: 20.</head>
<head level="3"><i>Col: <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Letter of a fight in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>
<p>SIR, I Marched out of <em>Aberdeen</em> on Wednesday last with five Companies of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg></em>, three of the late Major Gen: <em><reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg></em>, four Troops of Col: <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> horse, and two of <em><reg orig="Riches">Riches'</reg></em>, and the party that came from the <em>Merns</em>, and <em>Angus</em>, with three Troops of my own Dragoons. And upon Thursday about two a clock we came to the <em>Lough</em> at the head of <em>Cromar</em>, where <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, where after a little Dispute we totally routed their Army, but being so near the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> we could do no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> to take and kill about 140, having pursued them seven miles in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, their General hardly escaping with about 40 Horse. All the rest being quite dispersed. Major <em>Knight</em> came up even when we were going to engage; we are now upon our march towards the Garrison of <em>Kildmury</em>, which we hope to give you a good account of, I shall give you the particulars in my next: no more but that I am. <em>Lowrie</em> 10 <em>Febr</em>. 1653, at 6 <em>in the morning</em>. <em>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> humble Servant</em>, Tho: Morgan.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Febr: 21.</head>
<p><em>Grimsby</em> 16 <em>Feb</em>: Capt: <em>Pack</em> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War, who fought seven hours before she would <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, we slew 7 of his men, and wounded 15; his fore <reg orig="Topmast">Top mast</reg> was shot by the board, and the ship so torn between wind and water, that she was nigh sinking, and so towed hither, her name is the <em>Sandenburgh</em> of <em>Syrick sea</em>, one Cap: <em>J. Arionson Blanker</em> commander, she had 20 guns, we lost but one man, <em>viz</em>: our Cook, and four wounded.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg> Proclamation in Scotland.</i></head>
<p>Whereas it hath pleased his Majesty to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>, for opposing the common Enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his justice hath <pb n="4" />permitted to overcome, and to be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we could turn to him by <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> repentance. And to the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires, Parishes, and head Burghs by open Proclamation, that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> may make his several proportions ready to be delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under out of hand wheresoever the foresaid Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, will move to their duty, may be proceeded against with fire and sword, unworthy to be looked upon as <em>Scotchmen</em>, to the terror of all <reg orig="falsehearted">false hearted</reg> <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>, who by their treacheries and rebellions against their lawful King, and his just power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</p>
<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses has been brought forth from any well affected person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said Horses has been taken, that they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> meet, and <unclear><!-- 5 characters--></unclear> themselves equally, for having equal burden, and resound the persons from whom any Horses has been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of Horses now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries forth of every thousand pound of Rent: and the proportion of foot, every third man; and what Dragoons are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one Dragoon. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes; where no Burghs are, the Provost and Baylies of Burghs to Proclaim this at the Market Cross of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as you will answer to the contrary at their highest peril. Given under our hand the first day of <em>February</em>, 1654. <em>Sic subscribitur <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg>. God save King</em> <reg orig="CHARLS">CHARLES</reg> <em>the second</em>.</p> 
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Febr: 22.</head>
<p>More strange News yet, for the Letters this Day from <em>Bristol</em> say, that a ship is come thither which came round about <em>Scotland</em>, and that the Master, and others in her report that the Highlanders have played <reg orig="reaks">reeks</reg> at <em>Aberdeen</em>, killed many that opposed them, and were possessed of that City, what this Report may be, we shall not much heed at the present, and therefore proceed to what we have now received from very sure hands, viz: It is certain that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Drummond</em> is come to the <em>Highlanders</em> out of <em>France</em>, from the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that he was purposely <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by him, to take a survey of the Forces raised by <em>Glencarn, Athol, Seafort</em>, and the rest of that Gang, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> him whether they were in such an <reg orig="Equippage">Equipage</reg> that he might in safety venture his person, (and the Duke of <em>York</em>) amongst them this summer. He <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> further, that the ship which <em>Charles Stuart</em> designed thither some <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> since with ten thousand Arms, was much of it lent unto him by such friends as he finds there. General <em>Glencarn</em> daily issueth forth Proclamations, wherein he threatens fire and sword to all that will not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, in sending in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>.</p>
<p>There was a very notable <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> at <reg orig="Guild-hall">Guild Hall</reg> London, betwixt an Informer (upon the late Act made (with grievous penalties against selling Meal in their shops, the case was thus. The Informer was heretofore Indicted for taking of Bribes of the Meal-men, and <reg orig="travessing">traversing</reg> the Indictment, he was at the last acquitted by the Jury; after which the Informer brings a special Action upon the Case in the Exchequer, against those that Indicted him, and the matter being heard this Day, (although several Witnesses spake fully as to the honesty, and good deportment of the Informer) the Baron upon the Bench delivered his opinion, that his Case was something unreasonable, saying that if <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> <pb n="6" />that is acquitted upon an Indictment, should have liberty to bring his action in this manner, many <reg orig="Fellons">Felons</reg> might do the like (who are often acquitted at Newgate. Nevertheless the Cause was like to go for the Informer, but at length the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for the Defendant found the Declaration not to agree with the Record, for reciting the Names of the former Jury, <em>Godscal</em> in the Record, was <em>Godstal</em> in the Declaration, and <em>Brockson</em> in the Record, was <em>Brocksom</em> in the Declaration: whereupon the Informer through negligence, or mistake, was forced to let a Non-suit pass, and pay good cost to the Meal-man.</p>
<p>By Letters from <em>Bedford</em> it is certified, that five Persons are lately committed to that <reg orig="Joal">Jail</reg> for forcible entry into <reg orig="mens">mens'</reg> Houses, and taking away, under pretence of necessity, what they thought fit, it seems they are men whose Consciences can easily <reg orig="dispence">dispense</reg> with <em>meam amp; tuam</em>; yet nothing grieves men so much as that two or three of them have taken upon them to be Teachers in <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>
<p>We have advertisement of a great Robbery lately committed on Salisbury plain, and of four or five killed, but the Particulars are not yet come.</p>
<p>Major Gen: <em>Brown</em> who for a long time was a prisoner at <em>Ludlow</em> Castle is enlarged, and returned home to <em>London</em>, to the great joy and comfort of his Family, and all his Friends.</p>
<p>I am informed that the titular Scotch King sent lately unto Holland, desiring the transportation of some thousands of Soldiers and Officers which he had got together: and that from thence a Dispatch <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> was made to the King of Denmark, to see what assistance he could get there. The Scots continue their <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in parties, and often times come short of home. It is advertised that it is impossible for the Highlanders to have any considerable Body of horse in the field until the middle of May.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 24.</head>
<p>It being a very clear sky yesterday, there was seen very transparent at noon day a Star in the South; many stood gazing at it, conceiving it a thing of a stranger nature than indeed it is.</p>
<p>The further hopes of perfecting the peace with the <em>Dutch</em> is revived again, (though some say that <em>Grave William </em>of <em>Nassaw </em>hath declared against it) and there came a Packet yesterday to the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassador here, signifying that the Ambassadors from the rest of the Provinces are certainly coming, and respected to land at <em>Gravesend</em> every hour; and after they are all come, and sealed, there will be a time prefixed for publication of the Peace: for it is thought in this they will prove <reg orig="reall">real</reg>, notwithstanding because till then there is no cessation of Arms, and they hear we have taken 13 or 14 of their Merchants lately; the <em>States</em> have given order to their Admirals to hasten their main Fleet out to Sea with all the speed they can.</p>
<p>From <em>Sweden</em> we understand that the <em>English</em> Ambassador is used very courteously, and the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> commends him to be a very gallant knowing man, and seems often to take delight in discoursing with him about State affairs; There is a great Army raising, and her Majesty hath given order to her Subjects to bring in a List of all the losses and damages they have of late <reg orig="yeers">years</reg> sustained by the <em>English</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador made some Addresses to his Highness the Lord Protector. The Lord <em>Hastings</em> holding himself very highly abused by some, as being named about the Plot, came to the Council to clear himself.</p>
<p>The Deputies from <em>Anceland</em> have almost finished their negotiations here, and will shortly return again to that Island, and make report (without doubt) to their great Lord of the civil favours and respect they received from his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>A <reg orig="triall">trial</reg> about Brass Farthings to be allowed on to pass throughout the Nation was presented to the Council, and it was ordered to be taken into consideration another time.</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> hath taken shipping for <em>Ireland</em>; that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> is so well approved of that many of the Adventurers intend to go thither themselves, if they can get an abatement of the Taxes.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>