<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell08">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue 8</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Moderate publisher of</head>
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><em>Army, under the Command of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg></em></head>
<head level="2">The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> CROMWELL</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland</em>,</head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland, Ireland</em>, and other parts.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 9, of <em>Decemb.</em> to <em>Friday</em> the 16. of <em>December</em>, 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">LONDON, Printed by <em>J.C. &amp; T.W.</em></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday, December, 9.</i></head>
<p>It <reg orig="mattes">matters</reg> not where we begin our Intelligence this week, <reg orig="feeing">feeling</reg> every day affordeth plenty from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts, and therefore though we already hear a <reg orig="noyse">noise</reg> at Westminster, yet let us see how the wind <reg orig="blowes">blows</reg> further <reg orig="of">off</reg>, especially in Scotland, from whence we had this Letter following, which was written by a sure hand.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Scotland.</i></head>
<p>The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is much discontented. The <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> comes not in unto him, according to his expectation. Those Gentlemen in whom he reposed greatest trust, do forsake him, and his
own Tenants refuse to pay him Rent. The <em>Highlanders</em> are not in haste, or in a resolution to fight with us. Three hundred of ours did what they could to engage four hundred of them, but they <pb n="1" /> durst not stand to it, but retreated to their <reg orig="Mountaines">Mountains</reg> to protect them.</p>
<p>I made mention in my last that Colonel <em>Lilburn</em> was advanced towards <em>Sterling</em>. The <em>Highlanders</em> have drawn a considerable body to a <unclear><reg orig="pesle">post</reg></unclear> betwixt <em>Sterling</em> and St. <em>Johnstons</em>, where they begin to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg>, but no doubt will suddenly be removed. They have stolen so many sheep from the <em>Lowlands</em>, that knowing not where to keep them, two of them (according to their proportion) which they do allow themselves do eat up a sheep a day.</p>
<p>Two Troops of their Horse (which they have distributed into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Parties) taking the opportunity of Colonel <em><reg orig="Lilburns">Lilburn's</reg></em> being at <em>Sterling</em>, are come down this side <reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg>, and in the <em>Mey</em>, and <em>Tivisdale</em>, have taken away a great number of Horse, they came so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em>Berwick</em>, that they seized upon two <reg orig="Souldiers">soldiers</reg> of that Garrison, they have come into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> Houses in that <reg orig="Countrey">Country,</reg> and have disarmed them: The <em>Lowlands</em> are said to be as Malignant as ever. The <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> usage of our Officers and Commanders hath not at all <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> them to the <em>English</em> <em>Interest</em>. They <reg orig="oneley">only</reg> do wait an opportunity, when the <em>Highlanders</em> under <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Glencarn</em>, and the rest shall become so considerable, that they may rise as one man to destroy us. Our Horse and Foot in most parts of <em>Scotland</em> are often out in parties against the <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> <em>Highlanders</em>, but through want of timely Intelligence, cannot <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb. 10.</head>
<p>The House this day resumed the debate <reg orig="nuon">upon</reg> the Report made from the Committee of <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg> , which was as follows.</p>
<p>1. That it be presented to the Parliament as the best way for ejecting ignorant, <reg orig="prophane">profane</reg>, and scandalous Ministers; that Commissioners be sent from hence into all the Counties, divided into six Circuits (besides <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>) three Commissioners onto each Circuit, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with four or six in every County and each Riding in <em>Yorkshire</em> to be a County) and that in every County the said persons, or five of them (two of the Commissioners sent from hence being <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> present) be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to eject all Ministers (of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>) that are not of a good behaviour and holy in conversation, or that are not able and apt to teach, or in teaching hold not forth the <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Word; or be not diligent or labour not in the Word and Doctrine, or be greedy of filthy lucre: And be also <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to settle godly and able persons <pb n="2" /> to preach the Gospel in all void places, and to unite two or three Parishes together, so that none be above three miles from the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> meeting place.</p> 
<p>2. That it be presented to the Parliament, That Dr. <em>Arrowsmith</em> Col.<em>Goff</em>, Major <em>Hains</em>, Mr. <em>John Owen</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, Mr. <em>Ben</em> of <em>Dorchester</em>, Mr. <em>Faircloth</em> the elder, Mr. <em>Leckier</em>, Mr. <em>Caryl</em>, M. <em>Stephen Marshall</em>, Mr. <em>Worthington</em>, Mr. <em>Turner</em>, Mr. <em>Tomes</em>, Mr.<em>Martin Holbech</em>, Mr. <em>Cradock</em>, Mr. <em>Jessey</em>, Mr. <em>Arthur Barnardiston</em>, Mr. 
<em>William Greenbill</em>, <em><reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> Camfield</em>, Mr. <em>Dike</em>, Mr. <em>Stalham</em>, may be
sent Commissioners by three in a Circuit, for ejecting and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Ministers, according to the Rules prescribed.</p> 
<p>3. That all such as are shall be approved for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers of the Gospel in the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> meeting-Places, shall have and enjoy the maintenance already <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> by Law, and such other <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> as the Parliament already hath appointed, or hereafter shall appoint: And that where any scruple is made of payment of <em><reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg></em>, the three <reg orig="nexr">next</reg> Justices of the Peace, or two of them, and by the Oaths of <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> <reg orig="Wihnesses">Witnesses,</reg> shall duly apportion the value of the said <em><reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg></em>, to be paid either in money or Land, by them to be set out according to the said value, to be held and enjoyed by him that was to have the said <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>; and in case such approved value be not duly paid or <reg orig="injoyed">enjoyed</reg> according to the Order of said Justices, the <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg> shall be paid in kind, and shall be recovered in any Court of Record.</p>
<p>4. That upon hearing and considering what hath been offered to the Committee <reg orig="tonching">touching</reg> propriety in <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>, of Incumbents <unclear>Rectors</unclear>, Possessors of Donatives or <reg orig="ptopriate">propriate</reg> <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>. It is the opinion of this Committee, and resolved to be reported to the Parliament: that the said Persons have a <reg orig="legall">legal</reg> propriety in <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>.</p>
<p>The House having spent <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Dayes">Days</reg> in debate of the whole Report, and especially of the first of the four parts thereof; and the Question being put, That this House doth agree with the first Clause of the Report, it passed in the Negative.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday,</reg></i> Novemb.12.</head>
<head level="2">The world is at no certainty, to day a man, tomorrow a &mdash;</head> 
<pb n="3" />
<p>It being moved in the House this Day, That the sitting of this Parliament any longer as now constituted, will not be for the good of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> - and that therefore it was requisite to deliver up unto the Lord General <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> the Powers which they received from him; and that motion being seconded by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Members, the House rose, and the <em>Speaker</em> with many of the Members of the House departed out of the House to <unclear><em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em></unclear>; where they being the greater number of the Members sitting in Parliament, did by a writing under their hands resign unto his Excellency their said Powers, and Master <em>Speaker</em> attended with the Members, did present the same unto his Excellency accordingly.</p>
<p>His Excellency the Lord General <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers met this day, at which meeting, after a most Excellent Wise, Gracious, and <reg orig="Pyous">Pious</reg> Speech made by His Excellency, full of Religion towards God, Prudence towards the State, and love and care towards this distracted Nation; some things were transacted in Order to a settlement, and sweet composure; the Union of all that <reg orig="feare">fear</reg> the Lord is much desired; that so we may sit down comfortably under a safe and well-grounded Peace.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 16. December.</i></head>
<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Excester">Exeter</reg>, Decemb. 7.</i></head>
<p>Sir, In a Letter even now received, my servant writes me word, that the <em>Hound</em>, a Man of War of the States, hath sent into <em>Plymouth</em> a Ship belonging to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and bound home, from <em>Lisbon</em> with Salt and Sugar, burden 300.<reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>: and that Captain <em>Martin</em>, Commander of the <em><reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg></em>, who with some other <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> and Ships, doth <reg orig="plie">ply</reg> in the mouth of the Channel, hath sent into <em>Plymouth</em> two ships, who pretend of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>, and bound thither, the one is four hundred <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, 14 Guns: the other 100. <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, both laden with Sugar and <reg orig="Oyles">Oils</reg>, to a great value. When please God I come home, I shall endeavour to find out the truth, of which you shall hear.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Sterling</i>, 28. <i>of November.</i></head>
<p><i>There are still gathering together a rude rabble of desperate people in the <em>Highlands</em>, headed by the Lord <em>Kenmore</em>, and some other Gentlemen of mean fortune, and in debt, and their numbers increasing by some loose and vagabond people, both <em>English</em>, <em>Irish</em>, and <em>Scots</em>, who <pb n="4" /> having no other <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>, make the pretence of engaging for the <em>Scots</em> King a cloak for their robbing and <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which is all their way of livelihood; and might have been prevented, if some way had been thought of to have encouraged their transportation beyond Sea, for <reg orig="publike">public</reg> service, which some of the chief of them were <reg orig="wiling">willing</reg> to; their chief heads are still in the Isle of <em>Monteith</em>, where they sit in <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, and expect some to come to them both from <em>England</em>, and from other parts, as also Ammunition from <em>Middleton</em> in <em>Holland</em>, which they are
a little troubled hath hitherto been so much delayed, their number is in all not <em>3000</em>. but are about a <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> of <em>5000</em>. more, yet they find the people that have a way of livelihood unwilling to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> them, though they are not <reg orig="cordiall">cordial</reg> with us. They steal out by parties and plunder, and rob, and presently are gone again. We had News of some of them some eight miles from this place come to put up a Garrison; but upon the march of a party of our Horse towards them, they soon took the Alarm, and retreated but carried away plunder, and forced some men.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>Hague, 5. December (alias 25 of November. 1653.</i></head>
<p>We have News here by <em>Middleton</em>, and others of the Scots <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Creatures, that the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em> are Masters of the Field, and that all of the <em>English</em> Army are driven out of <em>Scotland</em>, and into some Garrisons, and this is spoken with as much confidence as impudence; but the whisperings here are as if there was like to be a peace with <em>England</em>, but all is kept private, as to particulars; the States being under an Oath of Secrecy. The <reg orig="generall">general</reg> rout indeed cry out there will be no agreement, because they say that this State will not <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> to any thing that may be <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> to the interest of this Nation. Yet our Grandees tell some friends that they have instructed their Deputies with such Offers to <em>England</em>, as they hope will prove a good expedient. But as with you in <em>England</em>, so also here in <em>Holland</em> and <em>Zealand</em> are great preparations to Sea against the Spring. And the States have given out new Orders to build 30. new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> more. For our new Sea-Monster proves a <reg orig="Cymera">Chimera</reg>, and know not what to do to vindicate their repute in so ridiculous a folly, <reg orig="onley">only</reg> as Friar <em>Bacon</em> was <reg orig="confened">confined</reg> with the brazen-head, they lay the fault on the breaking of the <reg orig="Wheele-work">Wheel work</reg>, but it will serve to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in a gap to help towards the making up of one of their Breaches lately made by the Sea.</p> 
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday</i>, Novemb.14.</head>
<p>The Sessions began this day in the <em>Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em>, and divers Witnesses were examined to prove the <reg orig="heynousness">heinousness</reg> of the <reg orig="Ryot">Riot</reg> and murder committed by the <em><reg orig="Portugales">Portugals</reg></em> in the <em>New Exchange</em>, whereof more hereafter; But in the next place, take notice that the Council of State do declare as followeth;</p>
<p>That for as much as the said <em>Exchange</em> is a place of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> resort and Trade, The Council have therefore thought it necessary hereby to declare their resentment of those Proceedings, and their just Displeasure against the same. And as they intend vigorously to prosecute the <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, so, to the intent the like <reg orig="evills">evils</reg> may be better prevented in time to come, They do hereby strictly charge and require, That no Person or Persons, of what quality soever, do presume, at the said <em>Exchange</em>, or any other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> place, to occasion, Encourage or Abet, any tumultuous Meetings, or <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> a breach of the civil Peace, by Drawing there, or in any other such place, any Sword or other weapon, Discharging, Presenting or bearing any Gun or <reg orig="Pistoll">Pistol</reg>, or firing of Powder in Granados, or in any otherwise whatsoever. Of which command, it will be expected that all Persons whatsoever take notice, and demean themselves accordingly, upon peril of being reputed, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> as disturbers of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, Whereof a very strict account shall be taken: And all Justices of the Peace, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, are required carefully to perform their duties in this behalf; as also to use their utmost endeavours to prevent and restrain all immodest, and unhandsome <reg orig="demeanors">demeanours</reg> of such as shall resort to the said <em>Exchange</em>, That so no just cause of offence may be given to sober <reg orig="mindes">minds</reg>, or anything there acted <reg orig="dishonorable">dishonourable</reg> to Religion, or the Nation.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Stockholm, the 12. of November, S.V.</i></head>
<p>From hence no News at all for the present, the Court remaining at <em>Upsahla</em>, where all is in expectation to hear of <em>English</em> Extraordinary Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> at <em>Gottenburgh</em>, who is said here to be departed from <em>England</em>, with a very stately Train; her Majesty having ordered, that as soon as they hear of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> landing, some of the chief Noblemen of this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> should go down to receive and conduct his Excellency <pb n="6" /> to the Court. We hear from <em>England</em> of our Commissary Mr. <em>Lagerfelts</em> taking leave and departure thence, as is said, with very good contentment and expedition; some were of opinion that he was to come along with the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em>, but we hear since of his journey over Land, and expect his <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> shortly.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Dantzick, the 29. of November.</i></head>
<p>Two days ago one deputed from the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty, came to this City, and having obtained audience before the Senate, <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> unto them the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Commission, <reg orig="impowering">empowering</reg> him to Arrest all the English Merchants and their Goods, in <reg orig="Reprizall">Reprisal</reg> of 14. Nuns, who intending from <em>France</em> to <em><reg orig="Polana">Poland</reg></em> some weeks ago, were taken at Sea by the English, and robbed of all their Baggage. But the Senate hath took this in consideration, being resolved to take <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> with the Commonalty about it, and to see whether amongst their <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> they can find none which might free them from <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with, or mixing themselves in any Reprisals: Whereupon the said Deputy went to <em>Elbing</em> and <em>Koingsbergh</em>, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> unto them also his Commission. The Plague (praised be God) decreaseth with these Winter <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> more and more, there being but 195. persons buried here this week: The Lord avert further Judgement.</p> 
<head level="3"><i>Copenhagen, the 22.of November, S.N.</i></head>
<p>From hence no News at all since my last, all our expectations are to hear of the issue of the Dutch Treaty with <em>England</em>, which is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> will come to a sudden rupture. <em>Charles <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> Agent <em>Wentworth</em>, hath had his last Audience, but no other Answer <reg orig="then">than</reg> he had in <em>August</em> last, That the State of <em>Denmark</em> can, nor will in this conjuncture of time, meddle with the <em>Scots <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg></em> Affairs, wherefore he is going hence <reg orig="male-content">malcontent</reg> for <em>Lubeck</em> by water, and so meet his Master in <em>Cleve</em>; he applauds the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and Princes of <em>Germany</em>, for their liberality of 300000. <reg orig="Crownes">Crowns</reg>, procured by the Lord <em>Wilmoth</em> at <em>Regensbergh</em>.</p>
<head level="3">From <em>Regensbergh</em> and the Empire no News at all this week.</head>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday</i>, Novemb.16.</head>
<p>The Letters do Thunder it out with Intelligence from <em>Scotland</em>, for now they say that the Enemy had a <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Sterlin">Sterling</reg></em>, and that they have mustered there 1000 horse, and 2500 Foot, they had also another <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> at <em>Loughtaine</em>, of 3000 Horse and foot under <em>Lorne</em>, with whom are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> the Lord <em>Athol</em> and <em>Seaford</em>, and in another party are <em>Glencairne</em> (their <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>
<em>Glegary</em> and <em>Kenmore</em>. They declare for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and expect the D. of <em>York</em> to bring some Officers with him out of <em>France</em>, and <em>Middleton</em> with a great quantity of Ammunition and Money from <em>Holland</em>; They increase their number daily, all men of desperate Fortunes Flocking to them, <em>Glencairne</em> hath also <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg> 1000 men out of one County, &amp; sends forth his Warrants as followeth.</p> 
<head level="3"><i>Gentlemen.</i></head>
<p><go>You are hereby required to deliver unto as much good <em>Scottish</em> <reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg> as will <reg orig="cloathe">clothe</reg> <em>200</em> foot <unclear><reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg></unclear>, together with as much <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> and <reg orig="Shooes">Shoes</reg>, as will furnish the same number, each of them with two shirts, and a pair of <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg> or <em>2000 li</em>. of Scottish money, between this and the 2 Day of <em>December</em> next. If this you do perform accordingly, in regard of the season of the year, I do hereby promise you protection from any further trouble; but if ye delay to give obedience to this, you may expect I will exact this by force; Wherein if you suffer more prejudice, I <unclear>am not</unclear> to be blamed</go>. So expecting your Obedience to this, as you will answer it at your <reg orig="perill">peril</reg>.</p>
<p><i>Given under my hand at <em>Balloch</em> 7 <em>Novemb</em>.1653.</i></p>
<p>GLENCARNE.</p>
<p>A strange sight of flaming fire was seen over <em><reg orig="Edenbrough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, passing towards <em>England</em>, which occasions much talk there. The <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother escaping from <em>Newgate</em>, was last night taken again in <em>Coven Garden</em>, and carried to <em>Newgate</em>.</p>
<p>The Lord Gen. and the council of State meet every day in consultation about settling the Government of this Com. Wealth.</p>
<p>Thus have you the Passages concerning,</p>
<p><i>The <em>Declaration</em> of the Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> and Council of State for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Government of this Nation, and preservation of the Peace thereof, The <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>. The number of their Hose and Foot. Their Declaration for the King of Scots. The coming to them of the D. of <em>York</em> and Gen. <em>Middleton</em> with Ammunition and Money out of <em>Holland</em>. A strange sight seen in the <reg orig="Ayre">Air</reg> over <em><reg orig="Edenboroughh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and the passing thereof from thence towards <em>England</em>. With the <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg> of the <em><reg orig="Portugales">Portugals</reg></em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>