<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell10">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue 9</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Publisher of Every <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, under the Command of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg></i></head>
<head level="2">The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>CROMWELL</em>.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland, Ireland,</em> and other parts.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 23 of <em>Decemb.</em> to <em>Friday</em> the 30. of <em>December,</em> 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">LONDON, Printed by <i>J.C. &amp; T.W</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday,</em> December, 23.</head> 
<p>At a Council of Officers of the Army they agreed, and did unanimously declare, <i>That they will adventure their lives, and all that is dear unto them, in defence of His Highness the Lord PROTECTOR, and the Government now established in England</i>.</p>
<p>His <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Proclamation (which you had in our last) was sent to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties of <em>England</em>, &amp; c. (for them to Proclaim) with a great Seale, since which we hear that in many places in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> where His Highness hath been proclaimed PROTECTOR, the People have expressed great joy by making Bonfires, Ringing of Bells, and the like.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, December 18.</head>
<p>Affairs here seem troublesome, though the <em>Highlanders</em> have for certain divided themselves, conceiving it for the present more for their Accommodation and Design, <reg orig="then">than</reg> in a body; <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> Territories is the West, <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>, and Marshes; Sir <em>Arthur Forbus</em> and <em>Ramsey</em> the Breas off the Hills in Angus and Mearness Earl of <em>Athol</em> in <em>Athol</em> and those Clans above St. <unclear><!--9 characters--></unclear>; <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Glengary</em> towards the North parts about <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>; and thus this new purloined <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Army have disposed their Quarters; but a party of Horse from hence with Col. <em>Morgan</em> somewhat disturbed their Levies in Angus, for they have taken about 40. men, and 60. horses, and had unregimented <em>Kinmoule</em>, if the hills had not been friend to a few.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Dalkeith</em>, Decemb. 17. thus:</head>
<p>The Enemy is departed from the hithermost parts of <em>Athol</em>, and gone to <em>Kirkmiebel</em>, in order to their march Northwards; as I am informed <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarn</em> are both there, and their Force reported to be 500. foot, and 500. horse, but those that gave me information that saw them, affirm they are not half that number, they lye under very many discouragements, and every place so eaten up where they come, that they are forced upon often removals; and now provision of Mutton and Beef begin to decay: I hear they intend for the North; that their Quarters upon the Lowlands may be more assured and broader, where they expect the Landing of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> forces, Ammunition and Money from their Majesty, and the States of <em>Holland</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Further from Scotland</em>, Decemb. 19.</head>
<p>The Enemies dispersing themselves into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parties is affirmed; They are now endeavouring to <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> their Levies into form, by laying them upon all the <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> Parishes to the Hills, but their demand's so high, that it is impossible the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> (though willing) should be able to bear them. We have information, that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to <unclear>raise</unclear> and force men, horses, and moneys in the South and intends to make some inroads into the borders of <em>England</em>, unless prevented; which is more probable by that information which we received from <em>Durham</em>, That 20. Horsemen well mounted, and armed with Pistols and Swords, went through that Town on Tuesday last by break of day, amongst them a person of Quality. The same number lay at <unclear><!--6 characters--></unclear> on Saturday night last, and wit them Col. <em>Wogan</em>, formerly <pb n="2" />a Captain of Dragoons in the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> Army. Thursday night last, Lieutenant <em>Whitmore</em> going with a party towards the Hills, took one Major <em>Morehead</em> (a prisoner of War, and yet upon parole and security) well mounted and armed, going to the Enemy, as himself <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg>.</p>
<p>They do much hearten their party, that their King is come into <em>Holland</em>; That Col. <em>Drummond</em> is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 1500. <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>, Armies, and Ammunition: And that the Dutch have left off treating with the English; with all which they feign a Post came lately from their King.</p>
<p>On Friday morning last a party of these <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Pilferers met the <reg orig="Post-boy">post boy</reg> <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <em>Leith</em> with Letters for <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Haddington</em> took his horse and Letters, and some Money, so that now it will be very uncertain sending of Letters without a Convoy.</p>
<p>It is certified from <em><reg orig="Edenbrough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, That the Writs issued out against persons in debt, do make many of the Lowlanders to run to the Highlands. It is said that there are about 4000. Writs issued out against <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons who have neither <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, nor estates to pay their Debts. Proposals therefore have been <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the Commander in chief, for relief of poor Debtors.</p>
<p>1. That the Debts of the Inhabitants of <em>Scotland</em>, may be judged according to Law; and that those who are not able to pay their Debts presently, may give security to pay it in a reasonable time, at a day appointed, without any use.</p>
<p>2. That such as will have benefit of the <reg orig="Infefment">Investment</reg> upon Land, may have the Land made over to them at such a rate as it would have yielded at such time as the Monies was lent upon it.</p>
<p>3. That the Act of pardon and confiscation may be passed with much mercy for time past.</p>
<p>4. That a Proclamation be issued out, that after the said Act of Favour, those that are to receive benefit thereof, may be so curbed. That if any person contemn, or shall hereafter rise in Arms against the Power of the Commonwealth; that they be banished the three Nations, and all their Estates to be confiscated.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb. 24.</head>
<p>From <em><unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear></em> in <em>France</em> thus: The people are in great fear and discontent here, by reason of the building of two Castles <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the City, for which they conclude, that they are a-new enslaved <pb n="3" />with the Kingly Yoke. There is very little Trade, the <em>Spanish</em> Men of War lying still about the <reg orig="Rivers">River's</reg> mouth. The Duke of <em>Orleans</em> is not yet come to Court, though he hath been often invited thither.</p>
<p>There is great preparations at <em>Toulon</em> for a Fleet to be ready next Spring, and those men of War which were gone out with Letters of <unclear>Matt</unclear>, are commanded in, and against they come, great store of <reg orig="Bisket">Biscuit</reg> is making, and a good quantity of Arms and Ammunition, what the <reg orig="enterprize">enterprise</reg> will be, is not yet known, but it looked upon as the beginning of a new <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, where ever it happeneth.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Decem. 26.</head>
<p>The Lord PROTECTOR set forth an Ordinance for alteration of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Names and Forms heretofore used in Courts, Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, &amp;c. and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Proceedings in Courts of Law, Justice, and Equity, within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em> according to the present Government, wherein it is declared, That the said LORD PROTECTOR finding it to be most necessary, that some speedy and <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> course be taken for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Names, and Forms to be used in Patents, Commissions, and Proceedings in Courts of Justice, the said LORD PROTECTOR, by, and with the Advice and Consent of His said Council, and in pursuance of, and according to the Power and trust reposed in him and them, doth declare and Ordain, And be it by the Authority aforesaid declared and Ordained, That in all Courts of Law, Justice, or Equity, and in all Writs, Grants, patents, Commissions, Indictments, Informations, Suits, Returns of Writs, and in all Fines, Recoveries, Exemplifications, Recognizances, Process, and proceedings of Law, Justice, or Equity, within the said Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, instead of the Names, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title, and Test (of <em>The Keepers of the Liberty of England by Authority of Parliament</em>) heretofore used, that from and after the six and twentieth day of <em>December</em>, 1653. the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title and Test of the LORD PROTECTOR, for the time being, of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, shall be used, and no other: And the date shall be in the year of our Lord, and no other.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb. 27.</head>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we further understand, that Gen. <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> are marched towards the North, to secure the landing of Dutch Forces, Arms, and Ammunition, which the expect.</p>
<head level="2">William <reg orig="Earle">Earle</reg> of Glencarn, Lord of</head>
<p><em>Kilmore</em>, Commander in Chief of all His Majesties Forces within the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission granted to me by His Majesty, for levying of Forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>, for opposing the common Enemy, I do by these presents appoint <em>Alexander Blackader</em> to levy out of the shire of <em>Cleckmennen</em> one sufficient Troop, Horse and Men well armed, out of every thousand pound of Rent, with certification if they fail after fight of my Order they shall be esteemed Enemies to their King: And the said <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Alexander Blackader</em>, or any having his power, are hereby Authorized to take the persons of the Deficients, and bring them prisoners to the Army, and to drive away all their Goods, while they do Duty. Given under my Hand at <em>Glenertie</em> the sixth of December, 1653.</p>
<p>Subscribed, GLENCARNE.</p>
<p><em>Loving Friend</em>, I desire that ye will intimate this Order to all the Gentlemen in <em><reg orig="Clackmennen-shire">Clackmennenshire</reg></em>, and send me the just <reg orig="Rentall">Rental</reg> of every <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Estate with this bearer; and if ye shall incur any danger by giving you this Order, He answer for it. No more, but expect your diligence, and your Answer, as you will have your selves freed from trouble, and rest.</p>
<p><em>Comerie, Decem</em>. 10. 1653. <em>Your Loving Friend</em>,</p>
<p>JOHN BLACKEDOR.</p>
<p><em>For his loving Friend William Morris, Clark in Alloway</em>.</p>
<p>By Letters from the <em>Hague</em>, it is written, that the <em>French</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> there, said for certain of late; That if the Dutch would break off the Treaty with <em>England</em>, he would assure them of the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, which may have somewhat more <reg orig="then">than</reg> a <em>French</em> Brag, since all men know how straightly that Queen is allied to <em>France</em>, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> possible your <em>English</em> <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg> may move that Queen to mind her <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> Interest.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> Decemb. 28.</head>
<p>One Mr. <em>Rogers</em> a Minister of the Gospel of <em>Jesus Christ</em>, presented to his <reg orig="HIGHNESSE">HIGHNESSE</reg> the LORD PROTECTOR some <reg orig="cautionall">cautional</reg> <reg orig="Proposalls">Proposals</reg> concerning the present Government managed by His <reg orig="HIGHNESSE">HIGHNESS</reg> and His <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council; the <reg orig="materiall">material</reg> parts are these,</p>
<p>Take heed of <em>Protecting</em> the Carnal, National Antichristian <em>Clergy</em> (though they come in the Name of Orthodox or Learned, for so did the <em>Scribes</em> and <em>Pharisees</em>.) <em>Zedekiah's</em> indulgence to the Priests and false Prophets of the Nation, <reg orig="imboldened">emboldened</reg> <em>Hananiah</em> in his Lies <em>Jer</em>.28.1. &amp;c. Which (<em>Zedekiah</em> believing) persecuted the true Prophets, and brought <reg orig="dreadfull">dreadful</reg> destruction upon his own head. So <em>Ahab</em> (a notable Politician) did protect his <reg orig="Nationall">National</reg> Clergy, or Prophets (who were his, not the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg>, 2 <em>Chre</em>. 18. 5. and by their suggestion, hared and persecuted the true Prophet <em>Mioaiah</em>, which proved his <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>. Thus the Rulers that were led by the Priests, proved Tyrants to the true Ministers of the New Testament, <em>Acts</em> 4.16,17. And whiles they would defend them, they destroyed themselves. Thus the worldly Clergy do ever fly to worldly Powers for Protection (having none from God.) and for this end it is, they flatter great men, to engage them to their <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>; so do <em>Antichrists</em>, now they are <reg orig="neer">near</reg> falling, and (without the <em>Lord</em> hear <em>Prayers</em> for you, and deliver you, from this <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> danger)they will ensnare you, and cast you asleep with their <reg orig="Inchantments">Enchantments</reg>, and render you unfit to follow Christ any further, but (under the Name of the Ministry) most miserably <reg orig="intangle">entangle</reg>, and <reg orig="subtilly">subtly</reg> seduce you into <em><reg orig="Antichrists">Antichrist's</reg></em> cause: Which if they do, will be your utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, as <em>Revel</em>.4.9,10. If any worship the Beast or his Image, and receive his mark in their forehead, or in his head, or in his Hand, the same shall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God; &amp;c. <em>Rev</em>. 19.2. And the Beast was taken, and with him the false Prophets, with whom he deceived them that received the mark of the Beast, and them that worshipped the Beast; these were cast alive into the Lake burning with brimstone. Therefore (my LORD) if a word from Jehovah on high, may (as yet) be received, look about you I and before you! with an <unclear><em>ecute irretorto</em></unclear>! Make haste (my LORD) for <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> Protection! against the Plagues that are (as sure as God is righteous) <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <em>Babylon</em>, and all that will cleave to her <em>Interest</em>. <em>Luther</em> was not too bold (in the Name of the LORD) to tell his Lord <em>Protector</em>, the Elector of <em>Saxony</em>; <i>That by his prayers he had gained him more safety and Protection, <reg orig="then">than</reg> he had received from him;</i> <pb n="6" /><i>and that the Cause of Christ needed not his Protection, but he needed <reg orig="thats">that's</reg> Protection. The Power of Man <em>(indeed)</em> protects <reg orig="Antichrists">Antichrist's</reg> Causes, but it is the Power of God <em>(set awork by Faith and Prayer)</em> that Protects <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg></i>. And <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, <i>Whether you will believe it or no, yet this Way I will undertake to secure and Protect your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> Soul, Body, Estate, and all, (viz. <em>by Faith and Prayer)</em> if you <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> freely in the Cause of Christ against Antichrist.</i> So say I (my LORD) in that Name which sent me (which fills me with Courage and Confidence) that if you will freely oblige for Christ and his Interest, this <reg orig="loud-crying">loud crying</reg> faith and incessant <reg orig="high-spirited">high spirited</reg> Prayers of the Saints, will all <reg orig="Ingage">Engage</reg> against you and never give <em>Jehovah Nissi</em>, the Lord our Protector rest, till the Excellency of <em>Jacob</em> have prevailed, 2 <em>Chron</em>.19.6. <em>Take heed what you <reg orig="doe">do</reg></em>.</p>
<p>Thus the Lord hath stirred me up by an irresistible and restless <em>Power</em> (once more) to lay his Work before you; for that he hath used You as a most glorious Instrument in the Three Nations (by the faith and Prayers of his People) to make way for this Work; which if you reject, will reject you, and be the <reg orig="infalliable">infallible</reg> fore-runner of your fall: Which that God may prevent, is the fervent Prayers of the <reg orig="Faithfull">Faithful</reg> People night and day, whose souls mourn in secret for you, whose hearts <reg orig="ake">ache</reg> and bleed abundantly on your behalf; as for a man (most dear in their souls, but) under most desperate <reg orig="Temtations">Temptations</reg> and dangers.</p> 
<p>In these <em>Proposals</em> I am sure, I have kept my sphere, and followeth the strong impulse of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> own Spirit in me, and many others; however it be taken. Wherefore the Great God awake you to his work! else the time will come when God will say, <em>Let him alone be <reg orig="injoyned">enjoined</reg> to Idols</em>. Hos.4.17.</p>
<p>Now that the Hand of the Lord may be with you, see what these five fingers point at, to you; which if you practise, will be able to Protect you, as well as direct you in this <reg orig="dreadfull">dreadful</reg> Day of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> for <em>Sion</em>: They concern you (my LORD) more <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em><reg orig="Caesars">Caesar's</reg></em> Paper did him. Now that they may prove a Hand writing against you (and a Cup of Trembling put into your hands) they are strengthened with a Divine generosity, and shall struggle with you in the Faith, Tears, and Prayers of many, who pray and mourn for you and amongst other.</p>
<p><em>Your (afflicted) <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servant,</em></p>
<p><em>for the Interest of the Lord Jesus,</em></p>
<p><em>John Rogers.</em></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Decemb. 29.</head>
<p>A <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> was shot to death for killing a Seaman. Cap. <em>Crispin</em> hath brought into <em><reg orig="Plimmouth">Plymouth</reg></em> a Dutch Ship laden with wine from <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em>: He fought with two Brest Men of war, but they lying <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the shore, got away. The <em>Dutch</em> hath taken a Ship of ours <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <em>New-England</em>.</p>
<p>Gen. <em>Monck</em> hath sent out many Scouts from the <em>Downes</em>, and they have already brought in 10. or 12. Prizes.</p>
<p>The Old Lodgings at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> are making ready for his Highness and his Court, and the old <reg orig="Councel-Chamber">Council Chamber</reg> is fitting for his Honourable Council, unto whom Mr. <em>Scobel</em> and Mr. <em>Jesen</em> are Clerks, and Mr. <em>Thurlo</em> Secretary of State.</p>
<p>The Dutch Ambassadors had a <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> Treaty with the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>, Sir <em>Gil. Pickering</em>, Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, or Mr. <em>Thurlo</em>, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said that peace is concluded, both with them and <em>Denmark</em>, with satisfaction, Honour and safety: Let us then say of His Highness, <em>Beati pacifici</em>. This will be a check to the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, and all those that carried on that design, though they talk of Prince <em><reg orig="Ruperts">Rupert's</reg></em> <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> thither to be <em>Generalissimo</em>.</p>
<p>The Scots King hath sent a Letter to <em>Glencarn</em>, assuring him that the K. of <em>France</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, the Duke of <em>Brendenburgh</em>, the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, and all the Princes of <em>Germany</em> will assist him with Arms, Ammunition and Money, and that he will come to them in person presently after <em>Dezmond</em> hath landed. <em>Middleton</em> also writes to them out of <em>Holland</em>, that Colonel <em>Dezmond</em> was <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> away from <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> the 26. of <em>November</em>, with 1500. <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg> of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Nations, and Ammunition, and bids them not doubt of further supplies. The <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> brother is removed from <em>Newgate</em> to the Tower of <em>London</em>.</p>
<p>Thus have you Passages concerning,</p>
<p><i>The <em>K.</em> of <em><reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg></em> Letter to the Lord General of the <em>Highlanders</em>. The assistance of <em><reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition</em> promised unto him by the <em>K.</em> of <em>France</em>, the <em>K.</em> of <em>Denmark</em>, and all the Princes of <em>Germany</em> fifteen hundred <em>Volunteers</em> sent unto <em>Scotland</em> from Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, and <em>P. <reg orig="Ruperts">Rupert's</reg></em> going thither. The concluding of a Peace between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Hollanders</em> and <em>Denmark</em>. A Declaration of the Officers of the <em>Army</em>, and some <em>Proposals</em> to his <em>Highness</em> the Lord <em>Protector</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>