<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every day's Intelligence, Issue $2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Declaration of the States of <em>Holland</em> concerning the late Treaty with <em>England</em>, and the Proposals of sixteen Ambassadors at the <em>Hague</em>, from several Kings, and Princes concerning <em>Charles Stuart</em>; and the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Government in <em>England</em>. Mr: <em><reg orig="Feaks">Feak's</reg></em> Preaching, and Mr: <reg orig="Powels">Powell's</reg> listing to little purpose. A sheet printed in <em>Holland</em>, called, <em>Peace between England, and the Dutch</em>. The Names of several Officers newly added to the Court of the Lord Protector. The violent incursions of the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, with a List of the number of Regiments they have raised, and the English that are there to oppose them.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 20 of <em>January</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 27 of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, January 20.</head>
<p>A <reg orig="Barbar">Barber</reg> in <em>London</em> lately married a Wife after the <reg orig="o'd">old</reg> fashion, and never came before the civil Magistrate, according to the Direction of the new Act, which makes the other way of marrying <reg orig="nul">null</reg> and void. This being found out, the man was sent to <em>Newgate</em>, and the Woman to <em>Bridewell</em>.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council set forth an Ordinance declaring, that it shall be high Treason for any person (not being an Officer, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Member of the Army) to plot, contrive, or endeavour the stirring up of any mutiny <pb n="1" />in the said Army, or if any Person shall invite, or assist any <reg orig="Forraigners">Foreigners</reg> invading <em>England, Scotland</em>, or <em>Ireland</em>, or if any person <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the betraying or <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up any City, Town, Fort, Ship, or Vessel, belonging to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, or if any person shall <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg>, or imagine the death of the Lord Protector, for the time being, or if any person shall maliciously, or advisedly, either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector, and the people in Parliament assembled, are not the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, or if any person or persons whatsoever, shall proclaim, declare, publish, or any way promote <em>Charles Stuart</em> eldest Son of the late King, or <em>James Stuart</em> one other of his Sons, or any other the issue, or posterity of the said late King, or any other person or persons, claiming by, from, or under him or them, or either or any of them, or any of the Dominions to them, or either or any of them belonging; or if any person or persons shall give, keep, or hold any Intelligence whatsoever, by Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said <em>Charles Stuart, James Stuart</em>, the late Queen their Mother, or any of them; or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the money of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (knowing such money to be false) to the intent to merchandize, or otherwise; or if any person or persons shall hereafter <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> forge, or counterfeit any such kind of <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, either of Gold or Silver, which is not the proper <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and yet is, or shall be current within the same; or shall bring from the arts beyond the Seas into this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, or into any the Dominions of the same, any such false, or counterfeit <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> of money, to the intent to utter, or make payment with the same, within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. Or if any person or persons shall impair, <reg orig="falsifie">falsify</reg>, clip, wash, round, file, and scale, or lighten any the proper monies, or <reg orig="coyns">coins</reg> of any other place allowed, or suffered to be current within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p> 
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Jan: 21.</head>
<p>This morning it was advertised again, that the King of <em>France</em> hath for the present made a stop of <reg orig="al">all</reg> English ships in the <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg> of <em>France</em>. The titular King of <em>England</em> is for certain, as yet in <em>France</em>, whatsoever is whispered to the contrary. Prince <em>Rupert</em> hath been so fortunate this Christmas at play, that he hath won 12000 crowns of some of the Lords of that Kingdom.</p> 
<pb n="2" />
<p>An unhappy accident lately fell out in the <em>Isle of Ely</em>; Some Gentlemen distasting the drink of the Inn, sent to <em>Wisbich</em> for Wine. Another company of Gentlemen in the said Inn understating it, desired to partake of their wine, whereupon a <reg orig="Bottel">Bottle</reg> was sent, but some sinister interpretation being given, a curious desire possessed one of the Gentlemen that sent for the Wine, to see who were those that desired it at the Inn, whereupon he took one of his Friends with him. Being come together, they fell from words to blows, the candle being struck out, one Mr: <em>Mallory</em> was killed, which was presumed to be done by one Mr: <em>Dymonds</em> who is fled, which adds to the <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>, and the Gentlemen upon his death did charge the said Mr: <em>Dymonds</em>. The other is in durance for the Fact.</p>
<p>It is affirmed, that the <em>Highlanders</em> do carry such an influence on them, that they do increase in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, their musters being made more numerous by the <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of the Marquis of <em>Huntley</em>, and the Marquis of <em>Montrosse</em>. The <em>Highlanders</em> fall often down into the <em>Lowlands</em>, after their accustomed manner, and having plundered the Countries, return with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary speed, for fear of being circumvented.</p>
<p>It is certified by Letters from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, that ten of our Merchants, laden with commodities from the <em><reg orig="East-Indies">East Indies</reg></em>, are come safely to <em>Gottenburgh</em>, five of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are there, as a Convoy to them. The eight <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> commanded to ply about the Lands end, &amp; to guard the Channel, are come in again, another part are sent out to be upon Duty in their places, General <em>Pen</em> is still riding at <em><reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg> point</em>, not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>.</p>
<p>There hath been a conflict betwixt the Inhabitants of the <reg orig="Bishoprick">Bishopric</reg> of <em>Leige</em>, and the Forces of <em>Conde</em>, and <em>Lorraign</em>, who have possessed themselves of two small Towns, and have Quartered themselves therein.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, January 23.</head>
<head level="3">From <i>Dalkeith</i> January 17.</head>
<p>The enemy are part in <em>Badgnoth</em>, and part in the Laird of <em><reg orig="Grants">Grant's</reg></em> bounds. The party that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> drew from <em>Aberdeen</em> towards <em><reg orig="Innernes">Inverness</reg></em>, could not get over <em>Spey</em>, the waters were so high. The <em>Boggygeith</em> is a very useful Garrison, the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg></em> Lady being removed to <em>Strathhigie</em>: The Enemy are much startled at <em><reg orig="Argiles">Argyle's</reg></em> Son <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> revolt, and think there is a greater design in the same, <reg orig="then">than</reg> is presently apparent. There is to be a great meeting in <em><reg orig="Argile">Argyle</reg></em> of all <em>Clan <reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em>; it is said to offer some proposals to the commander in Chief, Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> yet lies wounded in some part of <em>Monteith</em>.</p>
<p>On <em>Thursday</em> last <em>Athol</em> and <em>Lorn</em> were at the House of <em>Ballock</em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Lough Tay</em>, since which <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> is very sick, and in <em><reg orig="Weems">Weem's</reg></em> Garrison, and <em>Lorn</em> pretends his father is not <reg orig="reconcileable">reconcilable</reg> to him, whereupon he goes not home. The 14 instant the Captain Lieutenant to <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Okey</em> with a party from S: <em><reg orig="Johnstons">Johnston's</reg></em> fell into the Quarters of about 40 of the Enemies Horse about <em>Stahaughan</em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> little <em>Dunkel</em> under Lieutenant <em>Ramsey</em>, took ten Prisoners, and 16 Horses, and killed two on the place. But Captain <em><reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg></em> Troop from <em>Drummond</em> had not so good success, for the Lieutenant being sent out with a party of 30 horse, to rescue some sheep taken by the Enemy <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Garrison, pursued so far as to rout them; but another party of 60 Horse, and 100 or 200 Foot lying in ambuscado, our men had a very difficult retreat, yet twenty charged through, the Lieutenant was killed, the Cornet, one Corporal, two Trumpeters, and 7 Troopers taken, and the Quartermaster wounded. Divers of the Enemy were killed, and amongst the rest (it is supposed) <em>Wogan</em>, for he and the English with him, gave the first charge.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From Plymouth January</i> 20.</head>
<p>Since the writing of my Letter, Captain <em>Godfrey</em> in the <em><reg orig="Middle'orough">Middleborough</reg></em> is come in, and hath brought with him two ships, laden with Wine, Brandy, the one of which I suppose will prove very good Prize, she is about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, and the other is more questionable.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January 24.</head>
<p>You have already the heads of the Ordinance for Treason, and it is good that you duly observe them; for there be some <pb n="4" />persons already apprehended for Treason upon the said Ordinance.</p>
<p>The news from <em>Holland</em> is yet <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg>, notwithstanding all that the <em>Dutch</em> say.</p>
<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is highly favoured by the Qu: of <em>Sweden</em>, and honoured by the people.</p>
<p><em>Dalkeith</em>, 19 <em>Jan</em>: The chief Body of the Enemy is now <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> into <em>Murrayland</em>, where they are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in levying their <unclear><!-- 4 characters--></unclear>, and intend to debar correspondence between <em>Aberdeen</em> and <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>. Col: <em>Morgan</em> is drawing all the Forces of the Northern parts together to attempt their driving out thence. <em>Athol</em> was lately in <em>Strathardle</em>, where he enjoyed all men to rise, and got together about 500. who had not staid long with him, but 300 departed without leave. Whereupon he gave liberty to all but sixty to be ready upon occasion. The Enemy I am confident were no gainers by the loss of Capt: <em><reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg></em> party from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, he that commanded the first party (supposed to be Col: <em>Wogan</em>) was slain, and many of his men. The party consisted of <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> English being 30, and about 40 of Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forb's</reg></em> his men that were beaten in the South; and the other were Major <em><reg orig="Mercers">Mercer's</reg></em> men that belong to <em>Athol</em>. <em>Wogan</em> and his men stood valiantly to it, otherwise we had totally routed the <em>Scots</em> Lieut: <em>Caleh Leigh</em> is certainly killed.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes taken since the last week.</i></head>
<p>By Letters from the Generals at Sea, dated 20 January in the Channel, it is advertised, that the <em>Diamond</em> hath forced on <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, on the <em>French</em> side, a Vessel from <em>New Haven</em>, where it is supposed she is bulged.</p>
<p>A Prize of Wines taken by the <em><reg orig="Middleborugh">Middleborough</reg></em>, is brought into <em>Plymouth</em>.</p>
<p>A <em>French</em> man taken by Captain <em>Heaton</em>, laden with Wines, sent into <em>Plymouth</em>.</p>
<p>A Fly Boat called the <em>spotted Ox</em>. an <em>Holland</em> Merchant ship coming from <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, laden with Wine, of 140 Last, taken by Capt: <em>Hide</em> sent into <em>Dartmouth</em>.</p>
<p>A <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessel called the <em>Hope of Campheir</em>, with Deal boards, and ballast, brought in by the <em>Expedition</em>.</p>
<p>A <em>Holland Virginia</em> Merchant ship run on board, and sunk by the <em>Ruby</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Jan: 18.</head>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we are advertised by certain Letters, that great preparations are on both sides for another War. The Enemy lay their <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> in the <em>Lowlands</em>, and though they dare not appear there in a Body in the day time, yet they make many inroads by night, and do much mischief, often stealing Horses, and carrying away some of our men, they give out in speeches, that they have twelve Regiments already of Horse, and Foot, but want Arms, and their General (as they call him) sets forth these Papers, or Warrants, which I only hinted at in my last.</p>
<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to us by his Majesty, for <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> of Forces, Horse and Foot, for <reg orig="surpressing">suppressing</reg> the Common Enemy within this Kingdom, we do hereby require you, and every of you, upon fight thereof, to send forth of every thousand pound Rent, one sufficient well mounted man, with Pistols, and other furniture, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>We forgot to <reg orig="tel">tell</reg> you before, that six men, and two women were executed at <em>Tyburn</em>, condemned the last Sessions and a Maidservant adjudged to perpetual Imprisonment, for uttering false, and counterfeit half crowns, she knowing them to be so, and was promised a profit for uttering of them by her <reg orig="Mistresse">Mistress</reg>, who is fled upon it.</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> we understand, that the court soars very high, and many are called to question which thought they should have been esteemed rather serviceable to the King, <reg orig="then">than</reg> siders with the Prince of <em>Conde</em> in the late War. There is come to our hands a Letter to the King, from the Duke of <em>Espernon</em>, which deserves your attention as well for the <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, as for the variety of matter therein contained.</p>
<p><i>A Letter from the Duke of <em>Espernon</em>, to the <em>French</em> King.</i></p>
<p>SIR:</p>
<p>If your Majesty hath mistaken my intentions, before you were clearly informed of them, I am <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> I have <pb n="6" />at this present justified my proceedings, as there is no further need to defend them by my words. Truly I may justly say that the conduct I have used hath been such, as not mat king use of the advantages which might arise, by causing mischief to continue, or by giving way to such designs, the event whereof would sufficiently commend the Resolution had they not been <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg> unto you: I have contented <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> to <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> to all <em>France</em>, that I have respect to your Authority, even in the hands of mine Enemies, whereby Sir I trust I have caused my occasions to be so pure, and unspotted, that you remain fully satisfied, nor will you <em>I</em> hope <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> <em>I</em> have erred in following a Cause <em>I</em> might probably suppose could not be separated from Yours. Now therefore since your Majesty hath <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> what seemed deficient in the felicity of your <reg orig="Raign">Reign</reg>, and to settle peace in your State, all your true Subjects Sir, are so much the more obliged to rely on your <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> word, and the same having been given to the Queen your Mother, besides your obligation thereto by God and nature, your very reputation confirmeth the same, and taking your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> memory to <reg orig="witnes">witness</reg>, that <em>I</em> have at all times faithfully, though it hath not <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> been by ordinary and common <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>. I assure <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> you will be pleased to permit me henceforward to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the rest of my <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in peace, and now at length to leave me in the Haven whereinto <em>I</em> have been cast by so many Tempests; however if you shall otherwise determine of me, I hope I shall conserve the Quality I have ever hitherto inviolably kept off.</p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> most humble, obedient, and most <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Subject, and Servant,</i></p>
<p>ESPERNONE.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> Jan: 26.</head>
<p>This Day produced multiplicity of Intelligence from several parts, which we shall communicate in order, as followeth.</p>
<p>1. The Enemy in <em>Scotland</em> have 12 formidable Regiments of Horse and Foot, and about fourteen days since we gave you a list of the chief Commanders, some recruits do daily come unto them out of the <em>Lowlands</em>, and further <reg orig="ayd">aid</reg> out of <em>Holland, France</em>, and other parts; Some say that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> hath already landed Forces in <em>Ireland</em>, which are to go round about for <em>Scotland</em>, or else a new commotion will arise in <em>Ireland</em>, what the issue or <reg orig="successe">success</reg> hereof may be, we yet know not, but we fear commotions in all parts.</p>
<p>2. Therefore no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> 16 Ambassadors, and Agents are in <em>Holland</em>, to hinder the conjunctions to these two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, the agreement whereof they look upon, as a thing destructive to all the Monarchies in <em>Europe</em>.</p>
<p>3. Having given you the number of the enemy in <em>Scotland</em>, we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> impart a List of the Regiments of the other part in that Country. <i>A List of the Regiments in <em>Scotland</em></i>. General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Redes">Rede's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Oklyes">Oklye's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Fenwicks">Fenwick's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Riches">Riches'</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Fairfaxes">Fairfax's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Overtons">Overton's</reg></em>, That which was M:G. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Alureds">Alured's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniels'</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Cobbets">Cobbet's</reg></em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Salmono</em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em>, Part of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Sandersons">Sanderson's</reg></em>, The company at <em>Dunbarton</em>, Besides going to <em>Scotland</em> Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em>, Commis:Gen: <em><reg orig="Whaleyes">Whaley's</reg></em>, Part of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em>.</p>
<p>4. His Highness the Lord Protector hath entertained divers Gentlemen Ushers; there is a Court forming (for the honour of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>) Mr. <em>Long</em> and Mr. <em>Sadler</em> are Masters of Requests, and Mr. <em>Hatter</em> (sometimes beonging to the Lord <em>Fairfax</em>) is Secretary unto them. The Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Mother is a <reg orig="vertuous">virtuous</reg> Lady, but sick of late. His Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> do now sit in <em>Whitehall</em>, where the late <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in his prosperity did sit.</p>
<hr />   
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>