<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$10">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $10</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The providing of one hundred and sixty thousand Dollars for the King of <em>Scots</em>; and the raising of thirty Regiments of Horse and Foot; with the Duke of; and the raising of thirty Regiments of Horse and Foot; with the Duke of <reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg> going into <em>Scotland</em>. Major General <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Message to the Lord <em>Ree</em>; the number of the Forces appeared at their <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, and their making a Garrison at <em><reg orig="Lough-Tay">Loch Tay</reg></em>; With their expecting the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and others with great Supplies out of <em>Germany</em>. Some late Conferences betwixt is Highness the Lord Protector, and the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, and other proceedings touching the Treaty of Peace. Two and twenty of our ships lately taken, and cast away. And an Ordinance for continuing the payment of the Customs, &amp;c.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 17 of <em>March</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 24 of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, March 17.</head>
<p>That necessary Ordinance for appointing faithful, and able Commissioners in every County throughout the Nation, for the allowance; and <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of able Ministers, this Day past his Highness, and his Council.</p>
<p>As also an Ordinance for continuing the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> for one year longer: the Reasons are declared in the Preface which here followeth; as also the Names of the Commissioners, and those unto whom any Person <reg orig="agrieved">aggrieved</reg> is to make his appeal.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuing of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>.</i></head>
<p>The late Ordinance of the 24 of <em>December</em> 1653 for continuance of the Receipt of the <em><reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg></em>, and New Impost, extending no further <reg orig="then">than</reg> the 25 of this instant March, and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <unclear>Debts</unclear> assigned upon the <reg orig="Receits">Receipts</reg> thereof, being not possibly to be discharged within that time, and it being necessary to provide a continual supply for the carrying on the weighty Affairs of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> out of this Revenue, which is still found to be the most equal, and indifferent <reg orig="Leavie">Levy</reg> that can be laid on the People. His highness the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, doth Ordain, and be it Ordained, That from and after the said 25 day of this present March the several Rates and Charges set down, and every of them, and none other, in the right of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, shall be set, laid, and imposed, and are hereby laid, let, and imposed, to be had <reg orig="leavyed">levied</reg>, demanded, and collected, recovered amp; paid in and through <em>England</em>, and <em>Wales</em>, and Town and Port of <em>Barwick</em>.</p>
<p>And it is likewise Ordained, That from and after the 25 day of March instant, <em>Thomas Allen</em> Alderman of the City of <em>London</em>, <em>Thomas Wood, Richard Bury, George Langham</em> Esquires, and <em>George Foxcroft</em> Merchant, and none others, are and shall be, and are hereby declared, constituted, and appointed, Commissioners and Governors of the Excise, and put in execution all and every the powers and authorities given or granted by, or contained in all or any the said Acts, Ordinances, or Orders of Parliament touching the Excise and new Impost, as well for the collecting and receiving the several rates in this present Ordinance imposed and set, as the arrears upon any former <reg orig="Shedule">Schedule</reg>, or Rates due, and concerning the Government, and Ordering of the Excise, and New Impost, as fully and amply as any Commissioners for the Excise at the first of March aforesaid, might or ought to have done, and shall observe such Orders and Directions as they shall from time to time receive from his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council touching the same; and the said Commissioners for their care, pains, and service therein shall have and pay themselves quarterly, in every twenty shillings raised and levied free and clear from <pb n="2" />all abatements, and allowances for exportations or otherwise, for one year after they shall be dismissed from this trust, and no longer.</p>
<p>And it is further ordained by the Lord Protector, with the consent of his Council, That Sir <em>William Roberts</em>, Knight, <em>John Stone</em>, and <em>Henry Elsing, Adam Bains</em>, and <em>John Becket</em> Esqs; or any three of them, be and shall be hereby authorized to receive all appeals, and to hear, decide and determine the same, and to consider and examine by Oath or otherwise, what arrears of Excise are not yet paid, and what hereafter may accrue, either remaining in the hands of any Farmer, Commissioner, <reg orig="Sub-commissioner">Sub commissioner</reg>, Collector, Importer, Seller, Buyer, Planter, Grower or Maker, or of any commodities Excisable whatsoever, or for which any person whatsoever, by bond, <reg orig="bil">bill</reg>, entry, promise, or other engagement, hath been, may or shall become obliged, and to send for all persons, accounts, articles, <reg orig="receits">receipts</reg>, bonds, or any writings concerning the Excise, or in any wise relating thereunto, and to hear all parties, and to determine all differences concerning the Premises. And if any <reg orig="Sub-commissioner">Sub commissioner</reg>, Collector, Farmer, or any of their Deputies, or any Sureties for them, or any of them, or any Importer, Buyer, or Seller, Carrier or Conveyer of any the Excisable commodities, or any person engaged for them, or any of them, shall refuse to delay to pay into the Treasury of the Excise, any arrears, Fines, forfeitures, or other sums of money, which by the said last <reg orig="receited">receipted</reg> Commissioners or any three of them, shall be adjudged due to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> and ordered to be paid, upon such default certified under the hand of the Treasurer, and from the last recited Commissioners, or any three of them, unto the Commissioners for <reg orig="mannaging">managing</reg> the Estates now under sequestration the said Commissioners for managing Estates under sequestration, shall, and hereby required to sequester the <pb n="3" />Estate of all such Persons, both personal and real, <reg orig="til">till</reg> such Arrears, Fines, Forfeitures, and sums of money be fully paid with damages.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em> March 20.</head>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>
<p>SIR: Since <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing the Enemy are very active in all parts, and will leave no stone unturned. There hath been a conjunction of Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em>, Mr: <em>Gregor</em>, and Mr: <em>Naughton</em> lately, and their general; <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> was to be the 14 instant at <em>Rethemacchos</em>, or <em>Abernathy</em>. <em>Glengary</em> hath obtained a man out of every Plough in <em>Stratbrick</em>, and is to have Horse and money according to the former <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and requires the like from <em>Strathspey, Straddowne, Glenrennos, Bellevine, Murreland</em>, and of <em>Frazers</em> in <em>Straglas</em>, and if they fail to send in their proportions according to several Warrants, they must expect fire and sword.</p>
<p><em>Glencarn</em> with his men are in <em>Baganoth</em>, from whom a Servant of one Lieut: Col: <em>Smith</em> with his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> horse ran into our Garrison at <em>Ruthven</em> Castle; they report that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor. There came with <em>Middleton</em> sixty and odd Officers, the least a Captain, and amongst the rest 9besides those I formerly hinted to you) Col: <em>Henderson Monroe</em>, and others of them had very cold entertainment in <em>Southerland</em>. The Earl of <em>Athol</em>, and Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> had a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> on Wednesday last of about 300 horse, and 250 foot, they have placed a Garrison in a little house upon <em>Lough Tay</em>, where they intend to have a store of Provisions, of about 1500 <reg orig="Bolles">Bolls</reg> of Victual and to send such of the Commissioners and Heritors thither, as refuse to send in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>. On Saturday last Major <em>Holmes</em> at <em>Linlithgow</em> having notice of a party of the Enemy in the Country sent out a Quartermaster of <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> Regiment with a party who took a Cornet, and some others of the enemy, and eleven Horse. <em>Dalkeith</em> 14 <em>March</em>, 1653.</p>
<p>This morning the Lord Ambassadors of the seven United Provinces of <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em> had audience by his Highness the Ld: Protector whether they were attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, Major Gen: <em>Lambert </em>waited on them betwixt his Highness person, and the <reg orig="Park-gate">Park gate</reg>.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>The said Lords Ambassadors being now removed from Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em>, to Sir <em>John Trevers</em> in <em>Channil Roe</em>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard. The Commissioners of the Council appointed to confer with them, that met at the Conference on Wednesday last at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em>, were this day appointed to meet them at a Conference at Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trevers'</reg></em> this night. There hath been much pairs on both sides since the former Conference, to make all things in as great forwardness as may be.</p>
<p>This night accordingly (about five <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>) the Commissioners with Mr: <em>Thurloe</em> Secretary of State, and Mr: <em>Jesop</em> Clerk to the Council, in the <em>Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg></em> Coaches, and Attendants, were carried to the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors; who when they came to the Gate, were met by the Ambassadors who came out and saluted them; and with great <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg> and respect entertained them: And they went presently to Conference in a Chamber, by the Ambassadors sitted in Sir <em>John <reg orig="Tevers">Tevers'</reg></em> House for that purpose, where they treated until it was late at night.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday, March</em> 21.</head>
<p><em>Newcastle 16 March</em>. Our Fleet is gone from hence, a great Fleet for <em>London</em>, and other parts that way; they had a good Convoy; there were a few <reg orig="smal">small</reg> ship, more should have gone with them from <em>Sunderland</em>, but got not out soon enough, they lost a tide or two; and there was such a strong and seasonable wind, that the fleet thought it not discretion to stay, when they had so fair opportunity; yet there were 10 ships that got out on Monday last from <em>Sunderland</em>, and though they had no convoy with them, yet they thought they might venture between <em>Newcastle</em>, and the Fleet there so lately put out before, and accordingly they put out to follow the Fleet; but were presently set upon by the <em>Capers</em> and <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be taken, they were forced to run their ten ships all <reg orig="agroand">aground</reg>; but the <em>Capers</em> pursued them, and after the men were got out, the <em>Capers</em> got off five of them, and the other five are lost; so that within about a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time we have lost 22 Coal ships</p>
<p>Letters from the <em>Downs March</em> 19. advertise, That that day the Fleet from <em>Newcastle</em>, and the convoy are come safe, and are in the River of <em>Thames</em>, so that there are now good store of Coals in the River, and the price is like to be very reasonable.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 22.</head>
<head level="3"><i>A Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector, Inviting the People of England and Wales, to a Day of Solemn Fasting, and Humiliation.</i></head>
<p>The common and notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised amongst us, notwithstanding all our Deliverances and Mercies, together with the present Rod of an Exceeding and Unusual Drought, which hath layen upon us for some years, and still continues, and increasing upon us, threatening Famine and Mortality, are no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> the voice of God, calling aloud in our ears to Fasting, and mourning, and great Abasement of soul before him.</p>
<p>And although the General End and Intendment of inviting to a Day of Fast, be, that all of every Condition and Quality whatever, do try and examine their heart and way more especially, according to their own Light, and in the use of such Helps and Means as the Lord in his Providence shall afford to each one, before and upon the said day of Meeting; yet finding some thoughts set seriously upon our heart, We judged it not amiss to recommend the same to Christian consideration, not to impose them upon any, or to confine any within the compass thereof; but leaving every man free to the Grace of God, and to the work of his Spirit, who worketh all things in the hearts of the Sons of Men, according to the <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg>, and Good pleasure of his own Will.</p>
<p>It cannot be denied but that God hath vouchsafed to appear very much in working the deliverance of the Nation from their bondage and <reg orig="thraldome">thraldom</reg>, both spiritual and Civil, and procuring for them a just Liberty by his own People.</p>
<p>Do we now walk worthy of our high Calling in humbleness and lowliness of mind, holding forth the Virtues of <pb n="6" />Christ in time of Peace, which was our strength, by the efficacy of which all our great things were accomplished in time of War.</p>
<p>Have we a heart prepared as willingly to communicate the said Just Freedom and Liberty to one another, as we were industrious to get it?</p>
<p>Do we thankfully <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> our mercy in the Liberty of Worshipping God in Holiness and Righteousness without fear, being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies?</p>
<p>Is Brotherly Love, and a Healing Spirit of that force and value amongst us that it ought?</p>
<p>Do we own one another more for the grace of God, and for the spiritual Regeneration, and for the Image of Christ in each other, or for our agreement with each other in this or that form, or opinion?</p>
<p>Do we first search for the Kingdom of Christ within us, before we seek one without us? Or do we listen to them that say concerning the coming of Christ, Lo here, and lo there?</p>
<p>Do we not more contend for Saints having Rule in the world, than over their own hearts?</p>
<p>Are there not too many amongst us that cry up the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, Joy, peace, Meekness, Patience, Goodness, Temperance, <reg orig="Long-suffering">Long suffering</reg>, Forbearance, Brotherly kindness, Charity, which are the fruits of the Spirit?</p>
<p>How do we carry <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> not only to the Churches of God, and the Saints, but towards them that are without.</p>
<p>Do not some of us affirm <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to be the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> true Ministry, and true Churches of Christ, and only to have the Ordinances in purity, excluding our Brethren, though of equal gifts, and having as large a seal of their Ministry, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 23.</head>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> they write that <em>Middleton</em> hath sent for the Ld: <em>Ree</em> to come and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, and hath given him express command to raise all the people within his territories to come and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; they have two or three <reg orig="Rendezvouse">Rendezvous</reg> lately in the <em>Highlands</em>, and talk of great numbers of Horse and Foot to come out of the Hills; and they are carried aloft with great expectations of store of aid coming from <em>Holland</em>: thus are the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> people ensnared, and drawn to destroy themselves, a little to trouble us. They talk of a certainty that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> will be there this <reg orig="Sommer">Summer</reg>, and say that the Emperor hath raised one hundred and sixty thousand Dollars, to raise 30 Regiments for the <em>Scotch</em> King; nay they report further, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> is to marry the daughter of the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, with whom he is to have 4 Millions; but the Letters from <em>Flanders</em> say that this Lady hath lately lost two Millions in Jewels, and that her Father is now <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> upon as a lost Prince, and in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the K: of <em>Scots</em> is <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> by the <reg orig="legg">leg</reg> at <em>Paris</em> for want of money to carry him thence for want of payment of the stipend promised. The last week the king of <em>France</em> was in person in Parliament at the pronouncing sentence of death against the Pr: of <em>Conde</em>. That State seems to cover very much a peace with <em>England</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for Continuation of an Act of <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for the Continuation of the Customs <reg orig="untill">until</reg> <em>26 March</em> in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> <em>1653</em>.</i></head> 
<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Continuation of the Customs until the 26 of <em>March</em>, in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> 1653. and all Powers and Clauses therein contained, be, and are hereby continued, and shall, and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 day of <em>March</em>, in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> of our Lord, 1658. And be it further Ordained, that Commissioners of the Customs <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not hereafter make repayment of half <reg orig="Subsidie">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported, which have been, or hereafter <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be sold unto, or in the possession or any <reg orig="Shop-keeper">Shop keeper</reg> or retailer of the said Commodity, or any such goods where the property, form, or nature of the Commodity once imported, is any wise altered, mingled, amended or confounded. And it be hereby further Ordained, That the Commissioners for the Customs for the time being shall have and receive upon every 20 shillings coming clear unto the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> upon their account such <reg orig="salarie">salary</reg> of Poundage as us or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for Regulating the Customs, or any other thereunto authorized by his Highness and his Council.</p> 

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>