<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$09">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $9</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The admirable speech of the Lord <em>Beverling</em>, one of the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, to the Commissioners for the Lord Protector, at a conference about the Articles of Peace. The <em>Dutch</em> Men of War appearing upon the <em>Downs</em>, and forcing <em>12</em> English ships ashore. An Army of forty thousand Horse and Foot prepared by the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. The <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of Gen: <em>Glencarn</em>, and <em>Middleton</em> in <em>Scotland</em>; the Proposals of the <em>Highlanders</em>, and the <em>Scots</em> <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Letter published in the head of the Army; With a sad fight accidentally there betwixt two parties of the <em>English</em>. Also several Orders of the Lord Protector, and his Council, touching Ministers, the Laws of <em>England</em>, and Farthing Tokens.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 10 of <em>March</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 17 of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, March 10.</head>
<p>A New Prophet is risen very lately; it's said he was once of <em><reg orig="Grayes Inne">Gray's Inn</reg></em>, he hath a Book in the <reg orig="Presse">Press</reg>, wherein he takes upon him to fore <reg orig="tel">tell</reg> things to <reg orig="com">come</reg>, but for a <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> at the present, he takes upon him the cure of desperate Diseases in Men, Women, and Children; If you have a mind to hear further of him, you may enquire about <em><reg orig="Goodmans">Goodman's</reg></em> close.</p>
<p>The Prest masters for the Fleet sought diligently about the out-parts of the City of <em>London</em> for Seamen: <em>It is good to prepare for War in time of Peace</em>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>Some part more of Saint <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> <reg orig="downit">down it</reg>; were good all the rest were laid flat, or rudified, to prevent future dangers.</p>
<p>It was this day advertised by Letters from the North, that the <em>Dutch</em> Freebooters have taken six or seven <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels which came from <em>Sunderland</em>, and caused another to run ashore <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Hartlepool</em>. A <em>Freebooter</em> of <em>Enchuisers</em> hath lately <reg orig="re taken">retaken</reg> the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ship called <em>The <reg orig="Chestnut-tree">Chestnut tree</reg> of Amsterdam</em> which had been taken by our ships not far from the <em><unclear><!-- 4 characters--></unclear></em>. There is arrived at the <em><unclear><!-- 4 characters--></unclear></em> a fleet of 140 sail, which came from the <em><reg orig="Eastlands">East lands</reg></em>, a great part whereof are come to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and the rest to several other Ports in that Country, their lading is chiefly Corn, and materials for setting forth of ships.</p>
<p>By Letters from <em>Deal</em> it was advertised, that on Thursday last another Fleet of Merchants belonging to the <em>Dutch</em>, consisting of about one hundred and fifty sail did steer Westwards, they sailed close by the Coast of <em>France</em>, and had a fair wind, which was the reason that our Fleet lying at Saint <em><reg orig="Ellenspoint">Ellen's point</reg></em>, could not so suddenly discover them, nor easily overtake them. This <em>Dutch</em> fleet had a fear they should be <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> in their passage, they had <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> a strong Convoy with them consisting of 60 Men of War, but having brought them beyond the danger which they feared, a great part of them returned the same way they came, the others did go along with the fleet, being bound to several Ports lying on the Western Seas.</p>
<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> we make great preparation for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> our <reg orig="summers">summer's</reg> Fleet, 1000 private soldiers, besides seamen, were on <em>Monday</em> last drawn out of the 4 Regiments about <em>London</em>, and sent on ship <reg orig="bord">board</reg>.</p>
<p>It was this day also by Letters advertised, that Gen <em>Middleton</em> is come again to <em>Scotland</em> with two Men of War, the greatest part of their lading was Arms, and Ammunition, some Corn, and some say some quantery of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, he landed at <em>Uny</em> in <em>Southerland</em>, there came with him, Sir <em>George Monro</em> the <reg orig="yonger">younger</reg>, <em>Thomas Dyall</em>, The Lord <em>Nappeir</em>, Major Gen: <em>Dyel</em>, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Gordon</em>, <em>Lodowick Drumland</em>.</p>
<p>The rest are said to be Soldiers of Fortune, and not any one man of Fortune amongst them, the Letters from <em>Holland</em> do <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> <pb n="2" />them to be three hundred in number, but the Letters from <em>Scotland</em> do not <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> them to be so many, they were no sooner landed, but as if they were per advertised of the necessities of their Countrymen, they <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> dispatched fifty <reg orig="pick'd">picked</reg> men under the command of Major Gen: <em>Dyel</em>, with ten Horse load of Arms, the rest they carried along with them, intending to meet with <em>Glencarn</em> in the Brayes of <em>Murray</em>, where they are to have their Rendezvous.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector hath issued forth Orders that all Officers concerned <reg orig="therin">therein</reg>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> repair to their charges in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p>The Commissioners chosen out of the Council of the Lord Protector, did this Day meet again on the Articles of Agreement with the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, which it is hoped will suddenly come to a good conclusion.</p>
<p>The Names of the Commissioners are, <em>Philip</em> Lord <em>Lile</em>, Major General <em>Lambert</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, <em>John Laurence</em> Esquire, <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>George Montague</em>, <em>Walter Strickland</em> Esquire.</p>
<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that since the arrival of Gen: <em>Middleton</em> the <em>Highlanders</em> do grow numerous; at the Rendezvous in <em><reg orig="Murray-land">Murray land</reg></em> the Arms were distributed, some monies received, &amp; Letters read from their titular King, promising his assistance to the uttermost of his power, at which some signs of great joy were made, which were suddenly cooled by the tidings of the approach of our Army, of which more in the next.</p>
<p>The titular King of <em>Scots</em> of his own accord did choose to go into <em>Germany</em>, it being a Journey a long time in his intention. The Qu: of <em>Bohemia</em> is going to <em>Frankendale</em> which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place, and of great frequentation, it being the middle way betwixt <em>Worms</em>, and <em>Spiers</em>, where she will do the best she can to entertain him; I have heard of Letters which affirm that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> is no way discouraged at his removal out of <em>France</em>, so familiar are his misfortunes with him.</p>
<p>Great was the joy the other day at <em><reg orig="Wollidg">Wollidge</reg></em>, at the <reg orig="lanching">launching</reg> forth of the new <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> which carrieth 60 guns, and was then <reg orig="christned">christened</reg> <em><reg orig="Marston-moor">Marston moor</reg></em>. There is building another great ship for War, which is as broad, and longer <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <em><reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, March 12.</head>
<p>The Merchant Adventurers for <em>Ireland</em> are to meet at <reg orig="Grocers-Hal">Grocer's Hall</reg> <em>London</em> on <em>Thursday</em> next, foe making a <reg orig="Lotterie">Lottery</reg> for the Narronies. The Committee for Obstructions sitting at <em><reg orig="Worcester-house">Worcester house</reg></em> in the <em>Strand</em>, have adjourned <reg orig="til">till</reg> the 13. <em>April</em> next, at which time the Commissioners for the sale of the Lands, &amp;c. belonging to the late King, Queen, and Prince sit there again.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 13.</head>
<p>An Ordinance is preparing by a Committee, (whereof Justice <em>Hayle</em> hath the Chair) for Regulation of the Law.</p>
<p><reg orig="Some thing">Something</reg> hath been under consideration concerning Farthing Tokens, and an Order made therein, but it is uncertain what will be done.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the King of <em>France</em> to the Elector of <em>Cullen</em>.</i></head>
<p><em>My Cousin</em>, As soon as I had Intelligence of the hostile usage of your Countries by some Neighbours of mine, I did present my present help to free your Subjects from that pressure which they felt: Had not the particular respect that I bear to your Neighbourship forced me to this, yet my sincerity of assisting you in order to the Treaties of Peace at <em>Munster</em>, make me not neglect it, by reason that the Princes, and States of the whole Empire ought to have security of that Peace granted by the former Treaty.</p>
<p>Therefore I have sent you a relief out of my Army, commanded by the Marquis of <em>Faber</em>, to assist you against the hostile proceedings of the Troops of the Duke of <em>Lorraign</em>, and the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, in the Land of <em>Leige</em>. And I have further ordered him to keep his Army in good Discipline, having no other end, but only for the perfecting of the Treaty of Peace, and by my force to free the Prices of the Empire from <reg orig="al">all</reg> violence. So <reg orig="Cousen">Cousin</reg>, I commend you to the protection of the Almighty. <em>Paris</em> 18 <em>Jan</em>: 1653. <em>LOUIS</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the Marquis of <em>Faber</em> to the Elector of <em>Cullen</em>.</i></head>
<p><em>My Lord</em>, By the Copy of the Letter which my Master sent to the Emperor, your highness will see what command I have received from his Majesty to march into the <em><reg orig="Leidg">Leidge</reg></em>, which is only to free them from the violence that is offered to them by the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and the Duke of <em>Lorraign</em>, to the prejudice of the Treaty at <em>Munster</em>. So that there is no doubt to be made, but that the intent of his Majesty is to secure the conditions of that Treaty, and to free the Subjects of your Highness from those unjust oppressions which they have suffered. So that his Majesty sends these Forces as relief for their conversation, to keep them from utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>And in case there be such opposition, I am to use means to open the way by force, to make the Enemy leave the Country. My Master hath no other intention but only to expel them, and then for the Forces to return.</p>
<p>This is all that I can assure your Highness from my Master, and that I am <em>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> most obedient, most humble Servant. FABERT. Sidan </em>11 <em>Febr.</em> 1653.</p>
<p><i><em>Leopoldus Guilleimus</em> <em>by </em>the Grace of God, Arch Bishop of<em> Austrick</em>, Duke of <em>Burgundy</em>, and <reg orig="Stateholder">State holder</reg>, Governor, and Captain General of our <reg orig="Low-Countries">Low Countries</reg> and of <em>Burgundy</em>, &amp;c.</i></p>
<p>To all High Officers, Commanders, Masters of the Camps, <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg>, and Soldiers, bearing Arms under the Colours of the Lord Duke, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> of <em>Lorraign</em>. Salute. Be it known, that having this Day taken into safe custody, for some time, the Person of the foresaid Duke of <em>Lorraign</em>, according to the Order and Command received for that effect from our Lord the King, for the own welfare of the House of <em>Lorraign</em>, and other high considerations, relating to the welfare of the State, and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace. His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> intent, and ours is, that the body of his Army should remain under the command of the Earl of <em>Lignevile</em>, in the same service as it now is, <reg orig="til">till</reg> the Lord Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorraign</em> shall repair here, as it is like he will in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, to be invested of the command of the said Army, for the preservation of the Rights of the said Lord Duke, and of the House of <em>Lorraign</em> under the protection of his Majesty, declaring that none of that Army, nor any Officers, or soldiers of the same shall be liable to any questioning under what pretence soever, for the excesses that they may have committed under the Government of the aforesaid Lord Duke, as also we do by this present, forbid them to take service under any Potentate, or neighbour State, whether friends or foes, upon penalty of Corporal punishment, and <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of Estates, of the vassals, and natural Subjects of his Majesty, and of those that have formerly <reg orig="enroled">enrolled</reg>, and lifted themselves, and for all other strangers upon pain of being punished as <reg orig="Runnawaies">Runaways</reg>, with provision nevertheless that those that have formerly Lifted in the service of his Majesty, and are gone away from their colours without leave, shall have return to the same, without fear of being questioned for it, &amp;.c.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<p>His Highness the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Council sat in Debate of some things propounded by divers Godly Ministers, (though of several <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg>) and the said Council being sensible of the great necessity there is, that matters of Religion should be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in the Church, as well as temporal Government in the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, are advising of a way whereby the Godly, and able Ministry shall be encouraged, and that false and <unclear>idle</unclear> <reg orig="shepheards">shepherds</reg> may be removed, and kept out for the future.</p>
<p>There be some Copies of Letters intercepted from <em>Scotland</em>, sent to <em>London</em>, which in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will be made <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>
<p>From <em>Amsterdam</em> they write of a stately Fleet almost in a readiness, and say, that far exceeds the number they have yet had forth to fight, and their <em>Prospective</em> out of <em>England</em> a Reciprocal, and say some of the Letters <reg orig="al">all</reg> Christendom <unclear><!-- 2 words 'stanam azed'--></unclear> at the transaction of these two so mighty, and considerable <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, yet they seem not to doubt but their Ambassadors have before this time ratified the Peace with <em>England</em>, saying that they had but six weeks allotted them for their stay in <em>England</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Orange</em> party are indifferent quiet for the present, though they talk very high, but being they are put to play an <reg orig="after-game">after game</reg>, the manner is so much the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> considerable.</p>
<p>We told you before of some Letters, and papers taken in <em>Scotland</em>, one was a Letter from <em>Charles Stuart</em> to the Lord General (as they call him) <em>Glencarn</em>, beginning thus.</p>
<head level="3">CHARLES <reg orig="STUARTS">STUART'S</reg> Letter to the Lord General <em>Glencarn</em>.</head>
<p><i>After our hearty commendations, <em>&amp;c.</em> We cannot but give you thanks for your <reg orig="activenes">activeness</reg> in doing of us, and our Kingdom service, and we do hereby give you further to understand, that <pb n="6" />we do highly value, and approve of your endeavours in a service which doth so much import us, and to the end you may receive some other <reg orig="incouragements">encouragements</reg> from <reg orig="our self">ourself</reg>, we have given special order to <em>Middleton</em> to hasten unto you: He hath provided in <em>Holland</em> a considerable number of able Commanders, every way fit for our service. The arms which we sent from <em>Nants</em> may happily be with you before this Letter, we wish that the late differences between <em>Seafort</em> and you, may not be prejudicial to our affairs; we bid you right heartily <reg orig="farwel">farewell</reg>. <em>Signed C. Rex.</em></i></p>
<p>Upon the Intelligence that M<em>iddleton</em> was landed in <em>Scotland</em>, <em>Glencarn</em> set forth this Proclamation.</p>
<p>To all whom it may concern. I do hereby strictly will, require, and command all Officers, soldiers, Horse, and Foot: now under my command, that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the publishing hereof, they and every of them do repair to their several Quarters, and be ready to perform their duties in their several places, and that they nor any of them do presume upon any pretence whatsoever, to depart from their Colours, without special Licence. And I do further Require, and Command all the chief Officers of the several Regiments of Horse and Foot to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> me from time to time the particular Names of such several Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> under them, who have been negligent in the prosecution of any my former Warrants, for the speedy effecting, and bring in of <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, or who shall neglect, or wilfully contemn this command. Commanding all Officers and soldiers to be obedient hereunto, that they may be ready to appear upon summons, at what place shall be appointed for their Rendezvous, as they will answer the contrary at their utmost perils. <em>Subscribiter Glencarn</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 16.</head>
<p>The Privy Lodgings for his Highness the Lord Protector in <em><reg orig="Whitehall">White Hall</reg></em> are now in a readiness, as also the Lodgings for his Lady Protectoress; and likewise the privy <reg orig="Kitchin">Kitchen</reg>, and other <reg orig="Kitchins">Kitchens</reg>, Butteries, and Offices; and it is conceived the whole Family will be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> there before <em>Easter</em>.</p>
<p><i>The Tables of <reg orig="Dres">Dress</reg> prepared are these.</i> A Table for his Highness, A Table for the Protectoress, A Table for Chaplains and Strangers, A Table for the Steward and Gentlemen, A Table for the Gentlewomen, A Table for Coachmen, <reg orig="Groomes">Grooms</reg>, and other <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Servants, A Table for the Inferiors or Subservants.</p>
<p>At a Conference in the afternoon yesterday betwixt the Commissioners for the Ld: Protector and the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, there was very large expressions of Love and Amity; and the Ld: <em>Beverling</em> expressed in a Speech, that they were clear and unwreathed in their intentions for making a firm League. After this both parts of the Articles were compared, and they are now Engrossing.</p>
<p>An unhappy business lately <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> out in <em>Scotland</em>, at a place called <em>Lanker</em>, where Capt <em>Mason</em> beat out a party of the Enemy; and Capt: <em>Palmer</em> coming soon after (hearing that the Enemy was there) attempted the Town by force, and Capt: <em>Mason</em> not knowing but it might have been another party of the Enemy, defended the Town, and engaged with Capt: <em>Palmer</em>; in which Engagement 6 were slain, and 8 wounded before they knew one the other.</p>
<p>Some of the chief of the <em>Highlanders</em> have made overtures or Propositions to allay the present distempers without shedding more blood, (but they have not prosecuted them).</p>
<p>1. <i>That Sequestration of <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> Estates hath made many desperate, and put themselves in Arms.</i></p>
<p>2. <i>That <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> Arrests may cease, and Creditors contented to take all the Lands and Goods they find, for satisfaction.</i></p>
<p>3. <i>That <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> of Fortune who have spent their best days and got nothing, might be considered, and transported.</i></p>
<p>Some <em>Dutch</em> Men of War were discovered <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Goodwins">Goodwin's</reg> Sands</em> lately, they forced 12 <em>English</em> Vessels to run <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg> between <em>Falmouth</em> and <em>Scarborough</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>English</em> Fleet is about 140 Sail stately and brave: we have this week taken 15 ships great and small from the Enemy.</p>
<p>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is in <em>Flanders</em> with the Archduke, his Bother <em>Conti</em> is to command the <em>French</em> Army. One hundred and fifty sail of Eastland Merchants are newly come into <em>Holland</em>.</p> 
<p>Major <em>Bourn</em> and other Gent: were robbed this week on <em>Shooters Hill</em> in <em>Kent</em>, and one man was killed.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>