<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$01">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every day's Intelligence, Issue $1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Publisher</head>
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Answer of the States of <em>Holland</em>, to the late Treaty with <em>England</em>. The Proposals of the <em>German</em> Princes. The landing of fifteen hundred men, and two hundred Horse in <em>Scotland</em>, with Ammunition brought by a <em>Dutch</em> Fleet, consisting of seventeen sail. The Orders of the Sours of Admiralty for paying of Soldiers and Seamen. A Declaration of the Officers, and Soldiers touching the <em>Lord Protector</em>; the plots against him. And <em>Hannah</em> the Prophetess prayer, and advice to his Highness, after she hath <reg orig="layn">lain</reg> fifteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in a Trance. The sentence of condemnation pronounced against the Price of <em>Conde</em>. With the News at this Sessions in the <em>Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em>.</i></p> 
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 13 of <em>January</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 20 of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday,</em> January 13.</head> 
<p>In the Parish of <em>Giles Cripplegate</em> a man hanged himself, he said a little before he did it, <em>that nothing troubled him but that he did not wash his hands in the late <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> blood</em>.</p>
<p>There is a Woman which <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> herself a Prophetess at <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, she speaks of strange things to come, and hath <reg orig="layn">lain</reg> in a kind of trance many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> together, she hath neither eat nor drunk three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> together yet in the <reg orig="intervales">intervals</reg> she utters strange words, touching the revolution of the Government, and often makes mention of <em>Charles Stuart</em>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>About this time was committed a great <reg orig="Robery">Robbery</reg> in the <em>Strand</em> over against the <em>Savoy</em> in a Victualling House, the manner thus. Three men came in, in the habit of Gentlewomen, and were directed up one pair of stairs to drink a cup of beer or ale, and finding the key in another door, they went into that room, where they found keys which directed them to a chest, wherein was <em>600 l</em>. and paying their Reckoning, they carried the rest away, without question.</p>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> we understand, that the <em>Dutch</em> Deputies that were in <em>England</em>, are safely landed, though as yet not come unto the <em>Hague</em>, yet are every hour expected. In the mean time the <em>Orange</em> Party leap for joy, and say, nothing will now be concluded on with <em>England</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador at the <em>Hague</em> is in great esteem; and it is said here, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> intends suddenly to remove from <em>Paris</em>, but unto what place he goes next, is not yet known. Yet, <em>Middleton, Massey, Bunce</em>, and other English are yet here, though they have had many invitations by the <em>Highlanders</em> of <em>Scotland</em>. It is conceived they will not hazard themselves in person upon such a slender Engagement, as that is looked upon by the more solid sort of People to be.</p>
<p>The late great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> that <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> at <em>Amsterdam</em> by Thunder, and Lightning, with great Storms and Tempests, is some hindrance to the present Undertakings; and great <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> is made to amend and repair the shipping, which received prejudice therein. Two <reg orig="smal">small</reg> English Vessels were lately brought into <em>Zealand</em>, which were taken in the North. Their great Fleet is almost in a <reg orig="readines">readiness</reg>, Men, and Provisions are shipping as fast as may be; yet many are desirous to have peace with <em>England</em>, saying, That they shall all be undone if the Wars continue; and if they seal not to the Articles with <em>England</em>, you may expect a Declaration shortly.</p>
<p>But nothing doth more startle them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the celerity, industry, and the resolution of the <em>English</em>. We have fifty lusty ships which have met already in one Rendezvous, the <em><reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em> will speedily be ready at <em>Portsmouth</em>. The <em>Rainbow</em> is going from <em>Chattam</em>. The <em><reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg></em> is already set forth from thence, she was seen yesterday morning beyond the Castle. Four lusty ships more are going from <em>Chattam</em>. And there are ten ships more at the <em>Hope</em> <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> under sail, amongst which are the <em>Lyon</em>, and the <em>George</em>. The <em>Resolution</em> <pb n="2" />which hath carried <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> so stoutly during all these Wars with <em>Holland</em>, is now going to be equipped at <em>Chattam</em>. We shall have speedily abroad one hundred gallant ships, enough not only to daunt the <em>Hollander</em>, but per adventure the World.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Jan: 14.</head>
<p>From <em>Gottenburgh</em> Novemb: 29. After Capt: <em>Welsh</em> had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, he put to Sea again, and met with two <em>Hollanders</em>, riding at the <em>Scah</em>, the one of 400, the other of 350 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burthen, laden with Wheat, Rye, Wool, Planks, of both which he took the charge, and brought them away with him, and by storm was forced to come a little way within this Port for shelter, but remained without the command of the Forts.</p>
<p>The Lord Ambassador was earnestly pressed to send for the Captain, and to discharge the Prizes, but answer was returned, That it was conceived a matter not appertaining either to himself, or to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen'</reg> Officers to meddle with, ere.</p>
<p>Letters are received from <em>Portugal</em>, informing, that the <em>Spaniards</em> have driven from the <em>Portugals</em> 1200. head of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>, the <em>Portugals</em> who were in a gallant body of about one thousand Horse, fell upon the <em>Spaniards</em> who were 1500 and maintained the charge with so much resolution, that they utterly routed the <em>Spaniards</em>, and followed the pursuit so close, that many gallant Commanders <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> of the <em>Spanish</em> party, 300 <em>Spaniards</em> were killed on the place, and 400 taken Prisoners, and about 800 Horse: It is said that on the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portugals'</reg></em> side, there was no Officer slain but one Major only.</p>
<p>It is mentioned in some extraordinaries from beyond the Seas, that the great Tomb of <em>Mahomet</em> is fallen down at <em><reg orig="Mecha">Mecca</reg></em>, from the roof of his Temple; the Iron chest which <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> his Body, and hung in the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, was so <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> covered with rust that the loadstones could no longer exercise their <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, and uphold the miracle betwixt Heaven, and Earth; the earth immediately opened to receive it, but not without a dismal fire and <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg>, which continued for the space of half an hour, as horrid to the eye, as it was odious to the <reg orig="smel">smell</reg>.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, January 16.</head>
<p>A Paper or Declaration subscribed by the Officers, and</p>
<p>Soldiers of the Army.</p>
<p><i>To his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, Our Lord General.</i></p>
<p><i>The humble Address of the Officers, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army.</i></p>
<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services, wherein through the blessing of God upon the vigilancy, and endeavours of your Highness, we have in some measure been Instrumental in our places to free the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> from enemies: So we cannot but above <reg orig="al">all</reg> worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations, after all the shakings which have been in the midst of us, set up upon its true, and proper Basis and Foundation, and thereby brought into a <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of rest and safety. The <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your Highness, and the whole Nation at this time, when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment, by inclining you to accept of the Government, and Protection of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the People, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> it highly incumbent upon us to make our humble address unto you, and to declare that we shall not only be obedient unto you, in the performance of your great Trust; but in other places most faithfully, and diligently to the hazard of our lives, and whatsoever is near and dear unto us, be serviceable to you in the station God hath placed you against all opposition: Not doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; So you will to the utmost of your power and endeavours lay forth <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> for the glory of God, and the good of this People, amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of Faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take this boldness most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> Your Highness more especially to spread the wing of you protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, which you continuing to do. We are confident their Father which is in Heaven will be unto you a Buckler, and a Shield, and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>
<p><em>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> most humble, and faithful Servants.</em></p> 
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January 17.</head>
<p>From our Fleet at Sea came news, that we have since the fourth of <em>January</em> these ships following.</p>
<p>The <em>Golden Fawken</em> laden with Pitch Tan ere. The <em>Katherine of Gottenburgh</em>. The <em>St John</em> of <em>Lueck</em> laden with Deals. The <em>Saint John</em> of <em>Dantzig</em> richly laden.</p>
<p>We made mention before of a Woman which lay in a Trance, or the like (which some call a Prophetess) at <em>White Hall</em>, unto which may be added; that in fifteen <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> time she neither eat nor drunk, save only <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> a cup of ale, and a <unclear><!-- 4 characters--></unclear>, and for the most part she lay as if she were asleep, yet <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> she was heard to pray, and at other times to flag, her name is <em>Hannah</em> a Maid, and now she's gone to <em>Hackney</em> of her own accord, where she <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg>, but before she went from <em>White Hall</em>, she made a Prayer for the Lord Protector.</p>
<p><i>The Prophetess <em>Hannah</em>'s Prayer for the Lord Protector.</i></p>
<p>I Beseech thee <em>O Lord</em> that thou wilt keep the Lord Protector close to thy self, as he hath hitherto, so still to have his heart set upon the things of the Lord, not to be vain, nor regard earthly pomp and pleasure and things below; but the things of God, and his People, that he may be delivered from carnal Counsels, and being seduced to please the men of the World, and those that seek Righteousness, that he may not leave the counsel of the Godly, to hearken to those who are Worldly wise and earthly <reg orig="polititians">politicians</reg>, but wise in the wisdom of God. That the Soldiery, whom God hath made Instrumental to overcome the enemy without, and in the World, may not be overcome of their inward spiritual enemies, to provoke God to lay them aside, and make use of others in the perfecting of that work, in which God hath so far <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> them. That the Merchants of this Nation would not so far seek and mind their great profit by Trade at Sea, to <reg orig="fil">fill</reg> their own <reg orig="Ware houses">Warehouses</reg>, and <reg orig="Baggs">Bags</reg>, and be great in the World, as thereby to provoke an ungodly and wicked peace with the <em>Dutch</em> to the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of God, and hindrance of the carrying on of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> work. That the People of God may not (as some of them have done) revile and scandalize the Lord protector behind his back, and speak reproachful words against him to others.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, January 18.</head>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> thus. Notwithstanding the Court flourisheth, yet this City is in a great distraction, and full of fears, our Governors set very great taxes upon us, and all is because his Majesty wants money to maintain his Pomp, and state, (with other things which are pretended) we hear the Prince of <em>Conde</em> was lately in danger of being <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg>, and had it been so, he had soon been brought upon his <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>, there being a Charge already drawn against him. Indeed the Court is very high, and for such as have means to spend there, they are feasted, and fare <reg orig="delitiously">deliciously</reg> every day, but I find it quite contrary to the manner of our Saviour, for in his Court the hungry are filled with good things, and the poor are sent empty away, but here the rich are filled &amp;c. and the poor are sent empty away. They talk here, as if the Peace betwixt England and Holland were agreed, yet at Paris it is resented other <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, we hear of a great change in England; and it is conceived that if Holland and England conclude a peace, they need not fear for all the world.</p>
<p>There is Woman accused for a Witch, to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> this Sessions at the Old<reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>.</p>
<p><i>An Order by the <em>COMMISSIONERS</em> of the Admiralty, and the Navy, concerning the payment of the <em><reg orig="Prize-money">Prize money</reg></em> due to Seamen, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and their Widows, that have served at Sea, in the last <reg orig="years">year's</reg> Expedition.</i></p>
<p><i><em>16</em> January; <em>1653</em>.</i></p>
<p>By the Commissioners for the Admiralty and Navy.</p> 
<p>Upon consideration had of the Results of a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War, held aboard the <em>Swiftfare</em>, in the Fleet, the first of December, 1653. concerning the Prize money, due to Seamen and Soldiers that have served at Sea in this last <reg orig="years">year's</reg> Expedition. It is hereby declared and Ordered as followeth.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>1. That all Seamen and Soldiers that have served in the Fleet in the three last Engagements against the Dutch, and shall list themselves aboard any of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, at or before the last of March next, shall have their respective shares of Prizes, twenty shillings.</p>
<p>2. That such as have been in two of the said Engagements shall have thirteen shillings four pence.</p>
<p>3. That those who served only in one of the said Engagements, shall have six shillings eight pence.</p>
<p>4. That all such Seamen and Soldiers as have been disabled by sickness, or wounds received in the service: As also the Widows of any such Seamen, or Soldiers slain in any of the said Engagements, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have paid unto them their <reg orig="ful">full</reg> shares of Prize money, viz: twenty shillings.</p>
<p>5. That such of the Soldiers as are now again entertained in the Army (having Tickets for their Prize money) do produce unto the said Commissioners, a Certificate under the hand of the Captain, under which they now serve. As also a Copy of the last Muster Roll of the Companies to which they respectively belong, Or in default thereof, a Certificate under the hand of the <reg orig="Muster-master">Muster master</reg>, testifying their being in the service; whereupon Order shall be given for payment of the shares of Prizes due unto them.</p>
<p><i>John Disbrone, George Monck, Robert Blake, Vin: Gookin, John Stone, John Clerk.</i></p>
<p>Three thousand <em>Irish</em>, under the command of the <em>Spaniard</em>, are brought up towards <em>Galizia</em>, who being all old Soldiers, do <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> trouble the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, fearing they may put a stop to the progress of their success. The <em>Irish</em> in <em>France</em> boast that these in <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> will take an opportunity to come unto them, they do boast also, but no man <reg orig="beleeves">believes</reg> them, of a great Victory which lately they have got in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, January 19.</head>
<p>The preparations at <em><reg orig="Whitehall">White Hall</reg></em> for the <em>Lord Protector</em> are great; and stately Lodgings making ready both for his Highness and the <em>Protectoress</em>. There be also thoughts of places for <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons of eminency. Mr. <em>Lisburn Long</em> is already made Mr. of Requests. The debates of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have also been upon <reg orig="divers">diverse</reg> high matters this week, and a private consultation at the <em>Cock-pit</em>, some dangerous persons are found out to plot against his <em>Highness</em> there is one committed for beginning to act strange things, and suggesting a private way of a Parliament.</p>
<p>But what shall we say to the affairs in <em>Scotland</em>, for the Enemy still increasing, the Lord <em>Gourdon</em>, young <em>Montross</em>, and others are gone to them. And another Letter<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that a Fleet of 17 Sail of <em>Dutch</em> ships have landed 1500 Men, and 200 Horse in the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p>The last Letters we have from <em>Holland</em> say, That the <em>States</em> are preparing an Answer to the Treaty with <em>England</em>, but whether it will amount to War or Peace they cannot yet tell; and we fear it the more, because the <em>French</em> bid high for War, and the princes of <em>Germany</em> and other parts do the same, being envious to think that two such formidable <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> should <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> together.</p>
<p>The Articles against the Price of <em><reg orig="Condy">Conde</reg></em> have been proved, and sentence of death pronounced with consent of the Parliament at <em>Paris. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is preparing to go from thence.</p>
<p>This day the Sessions ended at the <em>Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em>, and the <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> is put off <reg orig="til">till</reg> another time: Many accused as great Malefactors, received sentence according to Law. One (that in zeal would have been admitted of a gathered Congregation for Witchcraft; another for Rape. A man for two Wives, and a Woman for two Husbands: and divers for <reg orig="Roberies">Robberies</reg>.</p>
<p>Two <em>Dutch</em> Prizes were brought into <em>Dartmouth</em> the beginning of this week.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">London, Printed by F. Neile: 1654.</head>   

<p><unclear><!-- one line--></unclear></p>
<p>Role in <unclear><!-- approx. 3 words--></unclear> Sir John Norwich at Brampton by Dingly in <reg orig="Northamtonshire">Northamptonshire</reg></p>
<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

 
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>