<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell11">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>every Day's Intelligence, Issue 11</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Publisher of Every <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, under the Command of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg></i></head>
<head level="2">The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>CROMWELL</em>.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland, Ireland,</em> and other parts.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 23 of <em>Decemb.</em> to <em>Friday</em> the 30. of <em>December,</em> 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">LONDON, Printed by <i>J.C. &amp; T.W</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday,</em> December, 30.</head> 
<p>The Commissioners for the sale of the <reg orig="Forrrest">Forest</reg> Lands sit at <em>Worcester house</em> in the <em>Strand</em>, and very large <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of Money are already advanced upon that account, the lowest rate of sale being no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 14 years Purchase.</p>
<p><reg orig="Wee">We</reg> thought that we might have assured you this Week that Peace was concluded betwixt <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, but the Adversary will not have it so yet, for when we thought all would have <reg orig="centered">centred</reg> in Peace and Love, the Dutch Commissioners <reg orig="pack'd">packed</reg> away; therefore it may justly be feared that these two States may once more appear upon the Ocean like two Pitchers, ready to clash one against another.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>In the mean time <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg> by Letters out of <em>Scotland</em> That the Forces under <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> (: being about 5000. Horse and Foot)are marched by the <em>Bray</em> towards the <em>North</em>, and Eight of Colonel <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Troopers met with some, which were well Armed and Mounted, marching towards the Hills, and hastily saluting each other, two of ours were slain, and one of them, and presently came in a greater number of the Enemy, and fell on so furiously, that but two of ours escaped, and that very narrowly. The Highlanders <reg orig="sweare">swear</reg> by their great <em>Mac-Galla</em> that they will fight stoutly if they come to <reg orig="battell">battle</reg> with the English. They <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> by <reg orig="Heapes">Heaps</reg> and Tribes upon the <reg orig="Mountaines">Mountains</reg>, and when they have eaten one Place clean, they remove their Quarters to another like other <reg orig="Cattell">Cattle</reg> which change their Pasture after they have eaten it bare.</p>
<p>They <reg orig="talke">talk</reg> of great expectations of <reg orig="ayde">aid</reg> of Men as well as Arms and Ammunition from <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> Parts, but surely they will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> the <em>French</em> wiser <reg orig="then">than</reg> to put themselves upon such <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg>, savage, cold and comfortless account, where their <reg orig="bellyes">bellies</reg> cannot be filled, their backs <reg orig="cloathed">clothed</reg>, or have <reg orig="ought">aught</reg> for their pains, but knocks.</p> 
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb. 31.</head>
<p>In this place you shall have <reg orig="truely">truly</reg> (though briefly set down the present <em>Government</em> of the <reg orig="Common Wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, as it was <reg orig="publikly">publicly</reg> declared at <em>Westminster</em>, the 16. of December, 1653.</p>
<p>1. <i>That the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative Authority shall be and reside in one Person, and the People assembled at <em>Westminster</em>, <unclear>style</unclear> of which Person shall be Lord PROTECTOR.</i></p>
<p>2. <i>That the exercise of the Chief <reg orig="Magistracie">Magistracy</reg> shall be in the LORD PROTECTOR, assisted with a Council.</i></p>
<p>3. <i>That all <reg orig="Writts">Writs</reg>, <reg orig="Prosseses">Processes</reg> &amp;c. shall run in the Name of the LORD PROTECTOR.</i></p>
<p>4. <i>That the LORD PROTECTOR in Parliament time shall dispose and order the <em>Militia</em> both by Sea and Land, and with the advice of his Council in the Intervals of Parliament.</i></p>
<p>5. <i>That the LORD PROTECTOR shall by the advice of his said Council, direct in all things concerning <reg orig="correspondencie">correspondence</reg> with <reg orig="Forreine">Foreign</reg> Kings, &amp;c.</i></p>
<p>6. <i>That the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> shall not be altered, suspended repealed, nor any tax &amp;c. laid upon the People, but by consent of Parliament, except as in the 30 Article.</i></p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>7. <i>That there shall be a Parliament summoned to meet at <em>Westminster</em> the third of <em>September</em> next, and from thenceforth once in three years.</i></p>
<p>8. <i>That no Parliament shall be dissolved adjourned, &amp;c. during the time of <unclear><!--1 character--></unclear> <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg> without their consent.</i></p>
<p>9. <i>That the Persons to be chosen for <em>England</em> shall not exceed <em>400.</em> for <em>Scotland 30.</em> and for <em>Ireland</em> Thirty.</i></p>
<p>10. <i>That the Summons to the Parliament shall be by Writ under the great Seal of <em>England</em> directed to the Sheriff of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties.</i></p>
<p>11. <i>That at the Day and place of Election, the Sheriff of each County, and the <unclear>Marors</unclear>, &amp;c. shall view the said Election, and make return into the <em>Chancery</em> within 20. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>.</i></p>
<p>12. <i>That the Sheriff that shall neglect his duty, or make false return shall forfeit <em>300</em>. marks.</i></p>
<p>13. <i>That all Persons who have <reg orig="ayded">aided</reg>, &amp;c. against the Parliament shall be disabled and uncapable of being Elected, or to give any Vote.</i></p>
<p>14. <i>That such as have advised or abetted the Rebellion in <em>Ireland</em>, shall not be Elected, or be capable of Vote.</i></p>
<p>15. <i>That if any uncapable shall give his Vote, &amp;c. he shall forfeit one <reg orig="years">year's</reg> value of his recall estate.</i></p>
<p>16. <i>That the Persons elected shall be such as fear God, and of a good conversation, of <em>21</em> years at the least.</i></p>
<p>17. <i>That all Persons (not excepted as before) seized to his own use of an Estate real or <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, to the value of <em>200.l.</em> is capable to Elect Members of Parliament.</i></p>
<p>18. <i>That the Chancellor, Commissioner or Keeper of the Great Seal shall be sworn truly and faithfully to send forth Writs to Parliament at the times in manner <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>.</i></p>
<p>19. <i>That if Writs be not issued forth by the Chancellor, Keeper, &amp;c. for <em>calling a Parliament</em> as aforesaid, then the Sheriffs, &amp;c. of the several Counties and <em>Corporations</em> shall within <em>30 <reg orig="Dayes">Days</reg></em> cause members to be chosen for their said respective Counties, &amp;c.</i></p>
<p>20. <i>That the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common-Wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in <em>Chancery</em>, shall the next day after return made <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> the Names of the Persons chosen unto the Council.</i></p>
<p>21. <i>That the Persons so chosen, and assembled, or any sixty of them shall be deemed a Parliament of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>
<p>22. <i>That the Lord PROTECTOR with the advice of his Council shall at any time when <reg orig="necessitie">necessity</reg> requires summon Parliaments, and in Case of future War with any <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> State, a <em>Parliament</em> shall be forthwith summoned.</i></p>  
<pb n="3" />
<p>23. <i>That all Bills agreed upon in <em>Parliament</em>, shall be presented to the <em>Lord Protector</em>, for his consent, and if he consent not, then is he to give satisfaction to the <em>Parliament</em>, or else they are to become <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> notwithstanding.</i></p>
<p>24. <i>That in case any of the <em>Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg></em> <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> shall <reg orig="dye">die</reg>, or be removed, the Parliament shall nominate six persons of ability for every one dead or removed, out of which the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> shall name two, and present them to the <em>Lord Protector</em>, of which he shall nominate one.</i></p>
<p>25. <i>That before the <reg orig="nezt">next</reg> Parliament the <em>Lord Protector</em> and his Council may <reg orig="adde">add</reg> more persons to the Council, provided they exceed not in all the number of <em>21</em>.</i></p>
<p>26. <i>That a constant yearly Revenue be raised for maintaining <em>10000</em> Horse and Dragoons, and <em>20000</em>. Foot.</i></p>
<p>27. <i>That the said Revenue <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be paid into the Treasury, and thence issued out for the use aforesaid.</i></p>
<p>28. <i>That in case so great a number be not for Defence, the Money which will be saved shall remain in <reg orig="banck">bank</reg> for the <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Service.</i></p>
<p>29. <i>That the Lord Protector shall have power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the meeting of the next Parliament, to raise Money for the purposes aforesaid, and to make Laws and Ordinances for the Peace and welfare of these Nations.</i></p>
<p>30. <i>That the Lands, Tenements, Rents, Royalties, &amp;c. which remain yet unsold, or undisposed of by Act or Ordinance belonging to the Commonwealth (except the <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg> and Chases, the Lands of Rebels in <em>Ireland</em> lying in four Counties, the Lands forfeited by the people in <em>Scotland</em>, who have not yet compounded) shall be invested in the Lord Protector, to hold to him and his <reg orig="Successours">Successors</reg> Lord <reg orig="Protectours">Protectors</reg>.</i></p>
<p>31. <i>That the Office of the Lord <reg orig="Protectour">Protector</reg> shall be Elective, and not Hereditary.</i></p>
<p>32. <i>That <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> shall be Lord <reg orig="Protectour">Protector</reg> for his life.</i></p>
<p>33. <i>That the Christian Religion, held forth as the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Profession of these Nations, be observed, and as soon as may be, a provision less subject to scruple, and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present be made, and till then the present maintenance is not to be taken away.</i></p>
<p>34. <i>That every Lord <reg orig="Protectour">Protector</reg> shall take and subscribe a solemn Oath.</i></p>
<head level="3">The Oath taken by His Highness <em>Oliver Cromwell</em> the LORD <reg orig="PROTECTOUR">PROTECTOR</reg>.</head>
<p><go>Whereas the major part of the last Parliament (judging that their sitting any longer, as then constituted; would <pb n="4" />not be for the good of this Commonwealth) did dissolve the same, and by a Writing under their hands, dated the <em>12</em>. of this instant <em>December</em>, resigned unto me their powers and Authorities; And whereas it was necessary thereupon, That some speedy course should be taken for the settlement of these Nations upon such a <reg orig="Bases">Basis</reg> and Foundation, as, by the blessing of God, might be lasting, secure Property, and answer those great ends of Religion and Liberty, so long contended for; And upon full and mature Consideration had of the Form of Government hereinto <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear>, being satisfied that the same, through Divine assistance, may <unclear>answer</unclear> the ends afore mentioned: And having also been desired and advised, as well by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons of Interest and Fidelity in this Commonwealth, as the Officers of the Army, to take upon me the Protection and Government of these Nations in the manner expressed in the said Form of Government, I have accepted thereof, and do hereby declare my acceptance accordingly. And do promise in the presence of God, That I will not violate, or infringe the matters and things contained therein, but, to my power, observe the same, and cause them to be observed; And shall in all other things, to the best of my understanding, Govern these Nations according to the Laws, Statutes, and <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, seeking their Peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>. <em>O. CROMWELL.</em></go></p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January 3.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Pembroke</i>, <em>Decem</em>. 23. 1653.</head>
<p>On Monday last we had here the fearfullest Thunder, Lightning, and Rain, as hath been heard of, and some <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg> destroyed thereby: The Lord speak peace to his people, many constructions poor people make.</p>
<head level="3"><em>January</em> 4. 1653.</head>
<p>The Trustees for the sale of <reg orig="Forrest-Lands">Forest Lands</reg> have appointed upon Tuesday next, the tenth of this instant <em>January</em> in the forenoon to fit for allowance of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Faith Bills to be doubled upon security of the said Lands, and thenceforth weekly every Tuesday in the forenoon, till the sum to be doubled be full.</p>
<p><em>William Tayleure</em>, Secretary to the said Trustees.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></i>, <em>Decemb</em>. 20.</head>
<p>The last Letters from <em>Holland</em> speak that people generally for peace, &amp; the <em>Dane</em> begins to doubt they will lurch him. He knows them, &amp; hath had a feeling of their practises upon him heretofore.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> Janu. 4.</head>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Dover</em>, Jan</i>. 4. 1653.</head>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p>I Thank you for the book you sent me, entitled, <em>The Government of the Commonwealth of England</em>, and in perusing it over, I <reg orig="finde">find</reg> those things contained in it for matter and substance, which were enjoyed when <em>England</em> was its chiefest prosperity, for here we <reg orig="finde">find</reg> Magistracy, Laws, and <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg> Discipline, which are absolutely necessary in every good and perfect Commonwealth, for where no Laws nor Magistrates are, there no God, no men, nor no Society can be continued, but where a well ordered Government is established without cruelty and insufferable oppression, there is as it were a Conspiracy of all degrees of men to maintain Liberty, Law, Justice, Fidelity, Religion and quietness in the Commonwealth; and indeed the greatest hopes of continuing peace and quietness in a Nation is, when all men consent in all times, and all things, to the preservation thereof, and do in Council consult with unity and concord, for discord is the <reg orig="poyson">poison</reg> of all Commonwealths, and there was never any <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, Tyrant, or <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, that prevailed against consent. <em>Agesilnus</em> King of <em>Lacedemonia</em>, being asked why <em>Sparta</em> was not <reg orig="invironed">environed</reg> with Walls, answered, That the Citizens lived united and Armed, saying, These are all the Walls of <em>Sparta</em>. And these are the only Walls for <em>England</em>, and if we can be <reg orig="invironed">environed</reg> with those Walls, we need not fear all our Enemies; If we have the happiness to come <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to the Government that was in Queen <em><reg orig="Elizabeths">Elizabeth's</reg></em> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, why should not we be of one mind as the people then were, If we know more now, then ought we to know this saying better, <em>That by Unity small things increase, but by <reg orig="Discention">Dissention</reg> the greatest are consumed</em>.</p>
<p>From abroad the <em>Marmaduke <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg></em> it is certified, That we have a very gallant Fleet of <reg orig="neer">near</reg> 80. <reg orig="Sayl">Sail</reg> already fitted, and upon the <em>Downs</em>, or gone forth in service. Two Dutch Prizes were brought in last Friday, and one small French Vessel. We have a squadron gone <reg orig="Westwerd">Westward</reg>, and some towards <em>Harwich</em>, besides Scouts which ply up and down; Sixteen <reg orig="Sayl">Sail</reg> more are in the Hope, which we expect shortly. Some Seamen and others have lately been punished for <reg orig="criminall">criminal</reg> offences.</p>
<pb n="6" /> 
<p>Letters from Holland say, That they are building 30. more new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which will be ready to launch about the beginning of February, when (they say) their whole Fleet shall come forth; they do what they can to maintain trade abroad, and say, If the Treaty with <em>England</em> break off, it will prove a very hot Summer.</p>
<p><em>Middleton</em> hath sent some Schellums to Scotland, gathered up of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Nations. The Agents for <em>Charles Stuart</em> speak against his going thither, till he <reg orig="soe">so</reg> if they will stand a Field Fight: Many are here for Peace, and many against it; They also speak of great divisions in <em>England</em>. There is a speech of a new Declaration <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> forth of the States of the United Provinces, of which more hereafter.</p>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That Captain <em>Crispin</em> with the Assistance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, is come in hither, he was in a storm <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Scilly</em>, but afterward sailed Eastward of <unclear><em>Tor Bay</em></unclear>, he hath been with Capt. <em>Hatsel</em>, and went from thence the 10. instant, and hath been a great check to the Brest Men of War, after which he with the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> that went out with him, on the 16. instant Anchored in Conquet Road, where the Boats were sent to fetch off two Vessels, one laden with Wine from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>, the other light, and there were then in the same place <reg orig="neer">near</reg> 30. <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> more, two of which were supposed to be Men of War, who with the rest hauled close under the houses, which were lined with what <reg orig="Musketiers">Musketeers</reg> that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> could afford, with which (it being half <reg orig="ebbe">ebb</reg>) beat off our Boats, but by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> providence without loss to us; the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> Boat going in with a small Gun, ours also returned with them, and attempted to set the said Vessels on fire, but could not make way for our Boats, so that Capt. <em>Crispin</em> was constrained to fire out of his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Town, and upon the Vessels, against whom he made about 230. great shot, which in sight of our men did the enemy very much spoil; The Enemy made use of <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one Gun, which they did keep playing all the time at our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> we did beat them from it.</p>
<p>The 21. of <em>Decemb</em>. the Bailiffs of the Town of <em>Yarmouth</em> received the Proclamation to proclaim the Lord PROTECTOR, with an order for publishing it in that Town, and the 22. day accordingly it was proclaimed in a solemn manner in four places of this Town. The Bailiffs and Aldermen in Scarlet, and 48. in their Gowns. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and some of the Officers also accompanied them; and as soon as the Proclamation was published, the great Guns in the Town and Forts were fired. The generality of people there, are very well satisfied.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, 5. <em>January</em></head>
<p>Post after Post, and Packet upon Packet, come daily from Scotland, and every one speaks higher <reg orig="then">than</reg> the other of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemies'</reg> increase in men horse and Arms, the last week a party of theirs killed four of our Dragoons within ten <reg orig="mils">miles</reg> of<reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, they are most <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in the night time, and they have made a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Roseden <reg orig="neer">near</reg> unto Dunbarton. Three days since a party of ours met with eighty of the Enemy and had a hot fight with them for the space of half an hour in which time 6 of the Scots were killed and the rest put to flight: It is reported that their King (as they call him) hath sent them seven thousand <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition of all sorts out of France. They go on with their Levies apace, and many great ones run to them.</p>
<p>Glencarn, <reg orig="Glengerry">Glengarry</reg>; and Kenmore are yet in the North Glancarry raiseth forces about <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>. Ramsey raiseth in the Hills of Angus. The Earl of Athol about Dunkel. Adavanple and Mac Nab in <reg orig="Perthshier">Perthshire</reg>, in which place they raise one whole Regiment of Horse and two of foot. They have laid up great store of Provisions in their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Weems, Lieut. Colonel Wilks is come safe to Lieth from London, and Gen. Monck is expected there.</p>
<p>The Dutch Deputies which treated <reg orig="hear">here</reg> concerning Peace, are <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> away, <em>God send us fair weather after them</em>.</p>
<p>Gen. <em>Blake</em> is with our Fleet at Sea.</p>
<p>The Letters this week from France say that it is agreed at the Prince of <em>Conde</em> shall be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> upon a charge of high Treason.</p>
<p>The Lord Ambassador Whitlock is gallantly received in Sweden, he was brought into the City attended with 100. Coaches, by the next you will hear what Audience he hath.</p>
<p>Thus have you Passages concerning,</p>
<p>The sending of seven thousand Arms and Ammunition to the Highlanders. A great fight betwixt them and the English, with the new Oath and Engagement they have taken, The numbers of their new raised forces, The <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> they have made, and the murders they have <reg orig="commited">committed</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>. Two ships taken by the <em>Dutch</em>, their building 30 new <reg orig="Frigars">Frigates</reg>, and the new Orders of the States to their Admirals. The proceedings of the Lord PROTECTOR and his Council, An Order for <reg orig="satifying">satisfying</reg> the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Faith, and other things of great moment.</p>   


<head level="3">Licensed and Entered according to the late Act for Printing.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>