<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$17">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $17</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The lamentable Remonstrance of the House of <em>Nassaw</em>, and that whole Family to the States General of the united Provinces about the Articles of Peace, and the pitiful cries and complaints made in behalf of the Princes of <em>Orange</em>. Gen: <em><reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg></em> Declaration in <em>Scotland</em>, offering two hundred pounds sterling to him that shall kill, or bring in one man of the Enemies. The new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> of Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, and the rest of the <em>Scots</em> Commanders, and his great boast what he will do to engage the Soldiery, and of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming thither. The Summoning of another Parliament in <em>England</em>, by his Highness the Lord Protector. With variety of other Intelligence.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 12 of <em>May</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 19 of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, May 12.</head>
<p>The <em>Habeas Corpus</em> sent to Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>John Lilburn</em> is not yet obeyed.</p>
<p>Gen: <em>Blake</em> sat in Council at <em><reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg></em> and Gen: <em>Pen</em> is with the Fleet upon the <em>Downs</em>, we hear a Squadron is designed to go further off. The <em>Spanish</em> Silver Fleet is expected to come home (if no body meddle with them) the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, very rich from the <em>West Ladies</em>. We have lately taken two <em>French</em> Prizes.</p>
<p>The sickness increaseth again at <em>Chester</em>, the Courts that were kept shore are kept at <em>Northwich</em>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>4. This Day came General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> from <em>Dalkeith</em> to <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, attended by the chief Officers of the Army, who were received at the <em>Netherbow</em> by the English Judges in their scarlet Robes, and the Town Magistrates, the Provost and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> in theirs likewise. The General, and the Officers alighting from their horses, marched with those that met them up the high street to the Cross, which was adorned with tapestry, and there Advocate General <em>Whaley</em> proclaimed his Highness Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland, &amp;c.</em> as also the Ordinance for Uniting <em>Scotland</em> to <em>England</em>, before a great concourse of people, Drums beating, Trumpets sounding, and voices echoing forth Proclamations. After this was done, a great dinner was provided by the Magistrates of this Town to entertain the General, his Officers, and others; and to close the solemnity, this night was variety of fireworks, which continued <reg orig="til">till</reg> 11 of the clock. There is 12 sail of our Men of War now riding in <em>Leith</em> Road, which together with the <reg orig="Generals">General's</reg> speedy preparations for a march into the field, strikes terror into the spirits of the <em>Highland</em> spoilers.</p>
<p>Further from <em>Edenburgh</em> May 6. 1654. Major Gen: <em>Drummond</em> came from <em>Middleton</em> to <em>Lough-Tay</em> about the 3 instant, and <em>Glencarn</em> with about 100 horse, and one <em>Mrray</em> with the like number of Foot came into <em>Athol</em> about the 4 instant. They give out, they <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> in a mist, but it is supposed they came by <em>Loughaber</em>. They intend to hasten their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and speed to the north to surround <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em>. <em>Montross</em> is raising his <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> at <em>Branar</em>, and some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties which come from <em>Middleton</em> are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with him. They say they expect <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> when their design is a little more ripe. Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> five companies are come up. The General will be at <em>Sterling</em> the next week.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 12.</head>
<p>From <em>Deal</em> we understand by Letters that a Squadron of our Fleet are gone Northward to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> those seas, and to prevent the coming over of assistance to the Enemy in <em>Scotland</em>: but they could not come thither time enough to meet with the late supplies of men, money, and ammunition, which was conveyed into <em>Scotland</em> out of <em>France</em>, by the way of <em>Dunkirk</em>. Another part of our <pb n="2" />Fleet are gone Westward, to chase away the <em>Brest</em> Men of War, who have done us much mischief at several times upon the West of <em>England</em>, but the main Body of the Fleet are appointed for a greater design.</p>
<p>The Committee sit daily for Regulation of the law, or at least the course of proceedings, for which we find much reason to do it; but as for the fundamental Laws, or the common Laws of this Nation, they are so <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of reason, that it were even against Reason to alter them.</p>
<p>The Letters from <em>Scotland</em> do advertise, that Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> was lately in <em>Sterling</em>, and is now on his advance towards the <em>Highlanders</em>, to whom divers Renegadoes do <reg orig="stil">still</reg> resort. Their access of new provision for the War doth much <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> them, so that their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> of late do much increase. <em>Middleton</em> knowing what an Enemy he hath to deal with, doth manage the War with great dexterity. Some Letters do represent, that he will fight with <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> before the access of more Forces are added to him. There was lately a great dispute at the maintaining of a pass, in which Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> was Routed, and divers killed, and taken. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> hath sent a Letter to <em>Middleton</em>, in which he exhorteth and conjureth the Commanders to an Union in time of their greatest necessity.</p>
<p>This morning we received the welcome News of 300. sail of Coals which are come into the River from <em>Newcastle</em>, but the wind which hath blown this fortnight from the East, and North-east, hath not been altogether so favourable to some ships of ours bound for the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p>It is certain that the last week a Woman in this City coming casually into a room where she found her Husband killing another Woman, she <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> departed to her own house, and for all the declarations, and protestations of her Husband, she refused to be comforted, having her heart so much contracted with the suddenness of that most ungrateful sight, that the next day she <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> for grief.</p>
<p>Whereas the Report is frequent that Count <em>William of Nassau</em> having called the Army together, they all declared, to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with him, and they have since seized upon <em>Horn</em>, and <em>Enchuysen</em>, and some other considerable Towns in <em>Holland</em>, and are now sat down before <em>Amsterdam, &amp;c</em>.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 15.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Upsal April <em>15</em>.</i></head>
<p>You cannot but by this time understand that which will please you; that (blessed be God) my Lord Ambassador is come to a good conclusion of his business here: For, when by Letters from <em>England</em> we understood the state of your Treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>, it being in such condition that the affair in this place could have no reflection upon it, it was then high time for his spirits, and put on the business more than formerly; which to <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> so good effect, that in fourteen f=days after this beginning we were come to a full agreement; and now there remains nothing but the signing and sealing of the Articles, which I presume will be done upon the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> return hither, and to meet with the Prince Royal, her successor, to confer about the great business of her Resigning of the Government; we look for her to be back again the next week, in the mean time my Lord Ambassador is forced to make another halt.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 16.</head>
<p>Since General <em><reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg></em> coming into<em> Scotland</em>, he set forth this Declaration.</p>
<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in Chief of all the Forces in <em>SCOTLAND</em>.</i></head>
<p>The <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness, and affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much blood and treasure) and by daily protecting them with their equal proportion with <em>England</em>) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace; Yet divers lewd persons broken in their fortunes, and dissolute <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> are run into Rebellion, and being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Tutors, Masters, and People among whom they live, who secretly <pb n="4" />conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof, I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his Highness, and his Council, do Declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the Governor of the next English Garrison, and give security for his, or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons freely pardoned, for any Offence, Spoil, or Plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion, the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.) That if the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned; But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said parish or Presbytery two shillings six pence a day for each horseman, and ten pence a day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their ordinary <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear>, out of the said Presbytery, which the Governor of the next English Garrison is hereby authorized to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> and receive <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, during the time the said persons shall so continue in <reg orig="Rellion">Rebellion</reg>. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, <reg orig="somented">cemented</reg>, and is now obstinately maintained by Major Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Donald MacDonald</em> Laird of <em>Glengary</em>, and Major Gen: <em>Dayel</em>; I do hereby <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> Declare, That what person or persons soever of this Nation, (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal Contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any Governor of any <em>English</em> Garrison, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only be pardoned, but also receive a Reward of his good service, the sum of 200 <em>l. sterling, &amp;c</em>. <i>Given under my hand at <em>Dalkeith</em>, this <em>4</em> day of May <em>1654</em>.</i> <em>George Monck</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 17.</head>
<p><em>Paris</em> 15 May. His Majesty is returned from his pleasure in Hunting at <em>Fountainlean</em> to this City, and <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is likewise returned out of the Country to meet his Majesty here, in hopes to get that Money which he wants, and hath been long promised him. The Duke of <em>York</em> went lately to the Army, and is not yet returned, he hath far more love, and respect of the Soldiery <reg orig="then">than</reg> his Elder Brother, here is great talk of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> going to <em>Rhemies</em> to be Crowned about ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hence. They talk much here of the Leagues which <reg orig="Forrain">Foreign</reg> Nations are ready to make with <em>England</em>, and how far Kings can be reconciled, and in amity with <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, though there be a kind of <unclear>Antipaths</unclear> in nature so to do.</p>
<p>The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath given express order to General <em>Kovingsmark</em> to use all the means he can to block up the City of <em>Bremen</em>; in order whereunto he hath already taken in some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Towns near unto it, and forceth the Country people to bear Arms, and assist him, but others are of opinion that it is more safe to be in the City, and therefore they chose rather to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, and the City hath sent summons to all their friends to come and aid them, expecting also some considerable relief from their Neighbouring Nations which are free States, and especially they do <reg orig="relye">rely</reg> upon <em>Holland</em>, but many think that <em>Holland</em> will be backward in doing <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> for them, for fear they should bring upon themselves the great Army which is prepared in <em>Sweden</em>, and make themselves more Enemies <reg orig="then">than</reg> they have now friends.</p>
<p>From <em>Chester</em> thus. Blessed be God the sickness is stayed here; Those that came from <em>Ireland</em> this way <reg orig="tel">tell</reg> us, that all things are well, and peaceable there, and were there but Planters sufficient, it would be a gallant Country quickly.</p>
<p>Many <em><reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> have been lately seen upon the Sea betwixt <em>Chester</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, they took three English Barques, the last week, as they were passing between <em>Liverpool</em>, and this Town.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<head level="3">AN ORDINANCE For continuing and Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, An Act for relief of Cretors, and poor Prisoners</em>, until the 31 day of <em>May</em> instant.</head>
<p>Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector by and with the advice and consent of his Council, Tat one Ordinance of the eighteenth of <em>April</em> one thousand six hundred fifty and four, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordnance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, An Act for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</em>, to be continued and shall stand in force until the one and thirtieth day of <em>May</em> instant; And that the several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any of the Estates real or personal of any of the Prisoners, or other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in, or by the said Act, nor <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> otherwise Intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any the Powers or Authorities given by the same, until the said one and twentieth day of <em>May</em> instant, otherwise then as in the said Ordinance is <reg orig="limitted">limited</reg>, and that all other Acts and things to be done by the said respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the said Act from henceforth, until the one and thirtieth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, shall be, and are hereby declared to be utterly null and void.</p>
<p>By Letters from the West of <em>England</em> it is advertised, that the <em>Indians</em> in <em>Virginia</em> has assembled themselves into a great number, and had an intent to fall upon the <em>English</em>, who being forewarned of it by one of their Enemies, whose humanity made him forget that he was a salvage, care <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be taken to prevent their <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> design.</p>
<p>The <em><reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> of <em>Brest</em> are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, not only on the Southern, and Western Seas, but some of them have adventured as far as the <em>Isle of Man</em>, and so upwards towards the <em>Scottish</em> Seas.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 18.</head>
<p><em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, 10 <em>May</em>: Sir, I sent you by the last Post, a <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of General <em><reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg></em> Declaration, since the publishing whereof he is gone towards <em>Sterling</em>, and thereabouts will be a Rendezvous of our Forces, and then shall we steer our course with all expedition to find out the Enemy, which keeps <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> waking, and yet flies from him.</p>
<p>The late supplies the Enemy hath had of men, money, and Ammunition by the way of <em>Dunkirk</em> adds some further life to those desperadoes that were engaged before; and to exasperate them the more, <em>Middleton</em> appeared in the head of some of his ragged Regiments with a bag of money in his hand, encouraging them to fight, and money would not be wanting. They prosecute their Levies with all the <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> that can be; yet if we can but climb well, we shall scatter them quickly. They are confident that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart </em>or the D: of <em>York</em> will be with them if they stand but two months longer, and the Ministers will hardly be kept from praying for them in <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, even in our own quarters. Divers Merchant men are gone forth to Sea from <em>Leith</em>.</p>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> thus. All do not <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> at the Peace with <em>England</em>, for the Princess <em>Dowager</em>, and the whole family of <em>Nassaw</em> make heavy complaints to the States General in a Remonstrance, that they are all utterly undone by the conditions in the Articles; and there be many flock to see the young Pr: of <em>Orange</em> and with paleness of cheeks, and eyes overflowing, with tears utters these words. <em>O how sad a case is this that an Instant should be banished, that never imagined or acted <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that's <reg orig="evill">evil</reg>: Ah! poor innocent Child, what a sad condition art thou in, and many hundreds besides; which say;</em></p>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line><em>Now <reg orig="wee'l">we'll</reg> <reg orig="contemn">condemn</reg> the fury of the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg></em>,</line>
<line><em>And scorn as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> their Censure, as their praise.</em></line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>Yet many regard not this, for they know that if that Family will content themselves to live peaceably, they may continue there happily, and all things are like to be quiet.</p>
<p>There is Summons preparing to be issuing forth for another Parliament in <em>England</em> against the 3. of <em>September</em> next, there must be forth <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> between the <em>Test</em>, and the <em>Return</em>.</p> 
<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>