<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$08">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $8</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Order of his Highness the Lord Protector for <reg orig="Ingrossing">Engrossing</reg> the Articles, and ratification of Peace between this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the seven United Provinces of <em>Holland</em>. The Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> designed to go to her Son the <em>Palsgrave</em>; the late Queen of <em>England</em> to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>; and the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, the Dukes of <em>York</em>, and <em>Gloucester</em> into <em>Germany</em>. General <em>Desbrow</em>, and General <em><reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg></em> going down to <em>Chattam</em>. The <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> </i> of the <em>English</em> Fleet upon the <em>Downs</em>. And the adding of sixty new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> to the <em><reg orig="Hollanders">Hollanders'</reg></em> Fleet. With Mr. <em><reg orig="Sympsons">Sympson's</reg></em> Letter directed to particular Congregations.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 3 of <em>March</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 10 of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, March 3.</head>
<p>Now <em>Phebus</em> is exalted, let him <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself when the High and Mighty States Ambassadors make their glittering approaches towards him; We have told you before of some that would set the Beacon on fire, and others that would quench it, <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> fire and water fall out, and oppose, and in revenge (to right themselves, or to overcome by might) would destroy one the other, yet both would be <reg orig="comply'd">complied</reg> to, and yet it may be neither can, but a third must, then give me leave to ask the question, how the wisest, and <pb n="1" />best Governor shall do to keep the Beacon burning, and yet quench it.</p>
<p>We should tell you here of the magnificent entertainment o the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, who this day were received in great state, and Heroically conducted through the City of <em>London</em>, his Highness the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coach going first, and after <reg orig="neer">near</reg> upon 60 more, with six Horses a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>, as also that one of the Ambassadors brought over his Lady with him, and other things of note, which might be ranked under this <reg orig="Dayes">Day's</reg> Intelligence, but in regard they have been mentioned by other Pens, the Reader shall not be troubled with them again in this sheet.</p>
<p>A Man and a Woman being in company together in <em>Old street</em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>London</em>, upon some private difference the Man <reg orig="stabb'd">stabbed</reg> the Woman so mortally, that she sunk down dead <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg>, which the Man seeing, did as sudden fall down upon her, and kissing of her, uttered these words. <em>Alas poor wretch art thou dead? I wish thou were alive again, for now I am sure to be hanged for thee</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, March 4.</head>
<p>This Afternoon the Lord Protector gave Audience to the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the subject whereof was partly congratulatory to his Highness, but the greatest part Declaratory to renew the old League which was between the two Nations before the late Wars did unhappily discontinue it, to which purpose the seven United Provinces did all consent to the agreement of Peace, which they have received <reg orig="ful">full</reg> power to confirm, they therefore desire a speedy cessation of Arms, assuring that on their sides all acts of Hostility <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters--></unclear> to the uttermost of their power be suspended, so that safely we may conclude, that the Peace will fully, and speedily be established.</p>
<p>It was this day advertised, that our Fleet rideth still not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>, some squadrons are at the <em>Spits head</em>, and others at Saint <em><reg orig="Ellens point">Ellen's point</reg></em>, they are ready to put forth to Sea in the most gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg> that may be, and the contented Seamen from several parts are making their <reg orig="dispaches">dispatches</reg> thither to their <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>. We have now in one body the bravest Fleet that <em>England</em> hath put forth since the Wars began.</p>
<p>It is confirmed that Mr: <em>Williamson</em> who was Ambassador here before from <em>Denmark</em>, is <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> again by that Crown into <em>England</em>, to make application to his Highness upon the success of the Treaty with the United Provinces.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>It is confirmed by Letters this day from <em>Scotland</em>, that whilst our Horse are in more Northern parts of that Nation, Sir<em> Arthur Forbs</em> who is again recovered of his wounds, is marched Southwards to see what parties he can find <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg>, or what booty he can get about <em>Lensx</em>, or <em>Tivesdale</em>.</p>
<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Earl of <em>Glencarn</em> is in the North, and not daring to hazard all his strength on the uncertainty of one <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, doth divide his Forces into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parties, that he might thereby be better enabled to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the importunity of their bellies, and <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> or <reg orig="inforce">enforce</reg> the Countries to increase their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>; the fiery crosses have had their run, and <reg orig="whitled">whittled</reg> from place to place in several Countries, but to no effect; it is wonderful indeed to consider what an impression <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> supernatural hath in all ages left in the minds of the common soldiers; to <reg orig="demurr">demur</reg> therefore from the <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> of new forces in the <reg orig="unsetled">unsettled</reg> Countries, it hath been reported wheresoever the Recruits are to be railed, that a Gentleman in the County of <em>Fife</em> had a Vision, in which he was <reg orig="admonish'd">admonished</reg> by a young man with all speed to address himself to <em>Glencarn</em> his Kinsman, and to acquaint him with the anger of God to call on him, and all his Forces, if they pursued such destructive courses. The Gentleman disobedient to the Angel on the first night, was struck dumb the second, because he <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> not his voice as he was commanded; this Report hath been of more efficacy to trouble the <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and discourage the old Soldiers of <em>Glencarn</em>, then the certain arrival of our Regiments, and of 3 ships laden with Tents, <reg orig="cloathes">clothes</reg>, an all manner of provision both for life and death.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector with the advice of his Council passé an Ordinance for reviving the Jurisdiction of the County <reg orig="Pallatine">Palatine</reg> of <em>Chester</em>, and holding an Assizes there, and <em>Mathew Hales</em> one of the Justices of the common Pleas, and <em>Hugh Windham</em> <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at Law, are appointed Justices of Assizes, and <reg orig="Joal">Jail</reg> delivery, and <em>Thomas Fell</em> Esquire, is Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County Palatine, <reg orig="til">till</reg> further Order.</p>
<p>From <em>Ireland</em> thus, according to the late Articles, and Treaty with <em>Mac O Mortague</em>, about 500 <em>Irish</em> are <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> away for the service of the King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> in <em>Flanders</em>, and we hope they will return no more hither, for they have left too many <unclear><!-- approx 3 characters--></unclear> themselves yet behind them, for the <em>Tories</em> run up and down in many places <pb n="3" />robbing, and <reg orig="theiving">thieving</reg> as formerly. The Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> and Col: <em>Hewson</em> are come safe hither, and all things are <reg orig="wel">well</reg> and quiet, yet <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought some Officers will be changed.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 6.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Upsall, Febr: 3. <em>S.V</em>.</i></head>
<p>The Treaty with the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is followed very close; so that it is said that in the last conference between his Lordship, and the grand Chancellor as they were in debate together, the Chancellor professed, That he had received <reg orig="ful">full</reg> satisfaction to all his Objections; and afterwards related so much to the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>. The grand Chancellor of the Kingdom meets the next week; and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed the <reg orig="ful">full</reg> determination of things is deferred <reg orig="til">till</reg> then. Sir <em>William Ballantines</em> and some of the Cavaliers are observed about this Court, lurking to do what mischief they may.</p>
<p>There was <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> remarkable omitted touching the Audience of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors of the United Provinces which here followeth; The said Ambassadors had Audience given by his Highness the lord Protector, in the Banqueting House. The Room was richly adorned with Hangings, and a rich Chair of State set for the Lord Protector, who was attended by his Council The Entertainment was stately; the Ambassadors bowing several times, as they came up the Room, his Highness rose up when they drew <reg orig="neer">near</reg>. The subject of this Audience was partly Congratulatory; but the main was to declare the intent of their coming which was to make and settle a firm Peace, and to renew the ancient friendship between the Nations. And to assure his Highness, that to this purpose their Superiors of the seven United Provinces do all of them unanimously consent to the agreement of Peace and that they as their Ambassadors Extraordinary, are <reg orig="impower'd">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same, desiring a speedy Cessation of Arms, and that there may be a Cessation of hostility on both sides. This is the effect of what was by them <reg orig="deliver'd">delivered</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 7.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith</i> Febr: 28.</head>
<p>The last week Lieut: <em>Hellin</em>, Lieut. To Major <em><reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons having notice that one Capt: <em>Thompson</em>, and Lieut: <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Ramfers">Ramfer's</reg></em> Lieutenant with five more of the enemy were come down into the <em>Mearns</em> presently mounted with six more of <pb n="4" />Troop, traced them about ten miles into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and at last took them, their horses, with their arms, and one of them being an Englishman, refused to take quarter, and was killed. A party of the <reg orig="enemies">enemies'</reg> horse and foot being before <em>Downe</em> Castle, five miles from <em>Sterling</em>. Major <em>Bridges</em> went forth with a party of 60 horse, upon which the enemy fled, our men pursued, and about 4 miles from <em>Downe</em> came in sight of them, but most of them got into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, we took only 6 prisoners, and about 19 or 20 Horse. Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> was there, and escaped very narrowly, as did Captain <em>Hamilton</em>, whose horse was taken, but he escaped over a <reg orig="bogg">bog</reg>. The 10 of March is appointed for the Enemies great Rendezvous about <em>Badgenoth</em>. <em>Montross</em>, and Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> came with Orders to <em>Athol</em> when he slighted <em>Weems</em>, to prepare all the Forces he could against that time. There was a late falling out amongst them, and one <em>Graham</em> shot <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Groom through the head, and young <em>Montrosse</em> had like to have killed <em>Lorn</em>. The enemy have put in a garrison of 30 men into <em>Gaith</em> Castle, about a mile from <em>Weyms</em>, I have sent you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> one of Sir <em>Mungo <reg orig="Murrays">Murray's</reg></em> Warrants, threatening fire and sword.</p>
<p><i>These are to require the Gentlemen Heritors, and others concerned in the Parish of <em>Drummond</em>, and <em>Buchannan</em>, that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after sight hereof they send to the <em>Craig</em> of <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters--></unclear>, out of every hundred pounds of Rent half Bell Cane, one <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> meat, one Turf of Hay, one <reg orig="Legg">Leg</reg> of Beef, one stone Cheese, four Hens, or satisfaction therefore, as also to be <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> at the appointed place with your proportion of Troop horses, every thousand pounds being one well mounted <reg orig="Troop-horse">Troop horse</reg> with Certificate; If you fail I will pursue you with fire and sword, according to the general Order. From <em>Braniavard</em> in <em>Dummond, Febr: 23.</em> M. Murray.</i></p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector answered several Petitions read unto him by one of the Masters of Requests.</p>
<p>There is <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> under consideration for taking a strict course with such as disturb <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people in their solemn meetings.</p>
<p>Divers Ministers of diversity of <reg orig="Judgments">Judgements</reg> have offered many things to consideration, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable that very speedily some <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Order will be made therein.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 8.</head>
<p>A Minister in <em>London</em> lately summoned in part of his Parish before the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord Mayor, for non payment of their Tithes, when the Case came to be heard, the Minister was much opposed by one of his Parishioners, who (after the matter was <reg orig="wav'd">waved</reg> in point of Law) began to dispute it out in Divinity, saying that a Bishop ought to be no striker <em>&amp;c</em>. that he ought to govern his own <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg>, but this <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> Wife governed him, <em>&amp;c.</em> yet this would not serve turn, but according to the Act he was Ordered to pay Tithes to the Minister.</p>
<p>Letters from <em>Newcastle</em> say, that the <em>French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg></em>, and <em>Freebooters</em> do very much infest that Coast, and lately took two <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels of ours within sight of <em>Tinmouth Castle</em>, which makes the Colliers tearful to come, especially hearing there is such great probability of Peace, to be concluded on shortly.</p>
<p>The <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors had a private conference with his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council at <em><reg orig="Whitehall">White hall</reg></em>, they press hard for a present cessation of Arms.</p>
<p>Last Sabbath day Major Gen: <em>Harrison</em> taught at <em>London house</em>, after the exercise was ended, a Letter was read which was directed to that Congregation from <em>Mr: Sympson</em>, wherein he expressed a hearty desire, that the spirit of meekness, love and unity might increase amongst them, but he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that he findeth not the sprinkling of Infants in the <reg orig="New-Testament">New Testament</reg>, which is a thing that M. <em>Feak</em>, and he have often argued upon since their confinement at <em>Winsor</em>. Mr. <em>Crarlick</em>, and divers other Friends have been to visit them lately.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>The Letters this Post from <em>Scotland</em> make mention, that by reason of the coldness of the season, and the great store of snow lately fallen in the Northern parts, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan </em>returned back (from pursuing the Enemy to <em>Aberdeen</em>, but another party of ours have had another <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> with a party of about <unclear><!-- approx. 2 characters--></unclear> of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Horse, they fought at the first very stoutly; but soon turned their backs, and fled to save themselves, in this fight we took one Lieutenant, and about 20 more prisoners, their main design at the present is to Rob and spoil what they can, and therefore divide themselves into divers <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties.</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> thus. There have been some motions made of late by friends in behalf of Cardinal <em>de Retz</em>, yet hath he not his enlargement.</p>
<head level="3"><i>This ensuing Letter is said to be written by the Cardinal to the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>.</i></head>
<p>SIR: I can no longer live without writing, for I understand the Court hath done some kind of Justice wherewith you are reasonably well pleased, but if this content be not absolute, I am resolved not to rejoice; and truly it is a shame to see the bounties of Princes in the hands of such persons, who can neither be useful, nor pleasing unto them, and that honest men must <reg orig="stil">still</reg> <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves with the only testimony of a good conscience, and in the content they receive in well doing, for my part I will not complain of fortune, if others must have the use of her. Now if the Ministers of State understood my secret, and that for satisfying of two, it were only necessary to oblige one, by acquitting themselves of what they owe another, they might easily spare what they have done unto me.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 9.</head> 
<p>From <em>Deal</em> they write, that our Fleet are to have a Rendezvous upon the <em>Downs</em> this week; The <em>Hollanders</em> have also a <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters--></unclear> great Fleet in readiness; and if these two <reg orig="Armadoes">Armadas</reg> have the happiness to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> as one in League and <reg orig="Amitie">Amity</reg>, all the Enemies of these Nations may say as the Devil did when he was sheering of a Hogg, <em>There is a great cry for a little <reg orig="wooll">wool</reg></em>.</p>
<p>The next Passage seems to give no discontent unto any here, except Officers belonging to the Prize Office, the Admiralty, and Captains of Private Men of War; and the thing is this. The Articles of Peace are ordered to be engrossed with all haste, and the Ratification is speedily to be Signed: and that nothing may be wanting on our part, His Highness the Lord Protector hath appointed Commissioners to expedite the whole matter with the Ambassadors of the seven united Provinces of <em>Holland</em>.</p>
<p>By this the Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> and some others depart <em>Holland</em>, she goes to her eldest Son the <em>Palsgrave</em>.</p>
<p>The Treaty goes on also very effectually with the <em>French</em> Resident: The late Queen of <em>England</em> is to depart <em>France</em>, and go to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>. Her Son <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and the Dukes of <em>York</em> and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, are to go into <em>Germany</em>, they not finding the affairs in <em>Scotland</em> to suit with their desires.</p>
<p>It is thought that Monsieur <em>Berdeox</em> the <em>French</em> Ambassador, being a Person of a very large Revenue of his own, will come in State through the City <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> or next day; why may we not then expect shortly to drink a quart of Claret for <reg orig="eightpence">eight pence</reg>?</p>
<p>Monsieur <em>Williamson</em> Ambassador for <em>Denmark</em> is also expected to make his Application to His Highness the Lord Protector very suddenly.</p>
<p>General <em>Desbrowe</em>, and Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> and the Commissioners of the Admiralty are at <em>Chattam</em>; The <reg orig="brest-men">brest men</reg> are put on board, and many <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army: the <em>Dutch</em> having added sixty new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> to their Fleet, so you see what readiness the Fleets are in on both sides; and if a Peace should be concluded, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> likely that the greatest <reg orig="blowe">blow</reg> would be struck that hath been yet, but it is thought there is not any question now of a <reg orig="ful">full</reg> agreement.</p>
<p>Four <em>Dutch</em> ships were lately sunk by storm <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Enchufen</em>. An <em>English</em> Prize called, <em>The Bee-hive</em> is lately carried into the <em>Texel</em>, she is valued to be worth 3000 li. sterling. The <em>Cantons</em> of <em>Switzerland</em> have renewed their League with <em>France</em>.</p>

<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em>: 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>