<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="EveryDayIntell$16">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Every Day's Intelligence, Issue $16</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Certain Passages</head> 
<head level="1">OF</head> 
<head level="1">Every <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Intelligence</head>
<head level="2">FROM THE</head>
<head level="1"><i>Army, and his Highness the Lord Protector,</i></head>
<head level="2">and his COUNCIL.</head>
<head level="3">With other remarkable Proceedings in <em>England, Holland,</em></head>
<head level="3"><em>France, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these particulars.</head>
<p><i>The Articles of Peace between her Royal Majesty the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, and his Highness the Lord Protector signed, and confirmed. Two great Fights in <em>Scotland</em> betwixt the <em>English</em>, and the <em>Highlanders</em>, with the number killed, and taken. A Ship cast away with fifteen <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of Gold. The appearing of a strange blazing Star, and what is judged to be the fore runner of. The Audience of the <em>Spanish</em> Ambassador by his Highness the Lord Protector, the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of strong Guards upon the Coasts of <em>Spain</em>, and <em>France</em> for fear of the <em>English</em>. The injuries offered the <em>English</em> at Saint <em>Malloes</em>. And Letters from <em>Jersey</em> concerning Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>John Lilburn</em>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Friday</em> the 5 of <em>May</em>: to <em>Friday</em> the 12 of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Friday</em>, May 5.</head>
<p>This Day the Ambassador from the King of <em>Denmark</em> had Audience, before his Highness the Lord Protector, being attended by the master of the Ceremonies.</p>
<p>This Day a great number of <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Pinks, and other Trading Vessels came into the River of <em>Thames</em>.</p>
<p>The Commissioners for approbation of Ministers sat this Day at <em><reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg></em> upon presentations, and appointed to sit tomorrow upon Augmentations.</p> 
<pb n="1" />
<p>By Letters from the West we understood, that the <em>Brest</em> Men o War lately took an English ship coming from <em>Morlex</em>.</p>
<p>Another Letter <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that some of our Men of War have this week taken five <em>French</em> Merchant Men, and were in pursuit of five more.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 6.</head>
<head level="3"><i>An Additional Ordinance for the Excise.</i></head>
<p>Whereas by an Ordinance of the seventeenth of March last, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordinance for continuing the Excise</em>, it is next after the Rates therein specified, generally declared and provided, <em>That all other Goods and Merchandizes (except Bullion, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of brass, or iron imported, or to be imported) not specified or therein rated, should pay after the arte of five pounds </em>per centem,<em> according on the same are changed by the book of rates, for the customs to be <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> by the first Buyer one shilling.</em></p>
<p>Be it Ordained, and it is hereby Ordained, and Declared by his Highness, with the advice and consent of his Council, that the said Clause be <reg orig="ful">full</reg> and void, and instead thereof, be it hereby ordained, and declared, That all other goods and Merchandizes men <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> in the Book of Rates for the Customs, except Bullion, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of brass or iron, and Wools of sheep) imported, or to be imported which are not in the said Rates of Excise, before or otherwise charged, shall hereafter pay Excise, before or otherwise charged, shall hereafter pay Excise after the rates of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant, or Importer, and the same is to be collected accordingly.</p>
<p>And to the end the whole <reg orig="receits">receipts</reg> of the Excise may be the better reduced into one Cash, and the charge, and number of Officers thereby retrenched, It is hereby ordained by Authority aforesaid, That from and after the 25 of March last, the Revenue of the Excise shall be but one <reg orig="Receit">Receipt</reg>, and so accounted for, and that all <reg orig="Receits">Receipts</reg> and accounts heretofore taken or kept of any payments of Excise, or new Impost, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of an Additional Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, and designed to any <reg orig="seperate">separate</reg> use or uses <pb n="2" />whatsoever, shall from henceforth cease, and be void, and be brought and reduced to one general Cash, and <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> Revenue, Provided nevertheless, that the <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> of all Fines, and Forfeitures, imposed and received since the 25 of March last, or that hereafter shall be imposed and received, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be kept in an account apart, and be paid out towards the maintenance of <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg>, and maimed Soldiers, according to Ordnance of Parliament of the 13 of <em>July</em> 1647.</p>
<p>And it is hereby, for the further relief of <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg>, and maimed Soldiers, Ordained, That from and after the said 25 of March last, there shall be, out of the general Cash and Revenue of the Excise, allowed the certain yearly sum of 26260 <em>l</em>. to be paid weekly by equal portions out of the said <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> <reg orig="Receit">Receipt</reg> unto such person or persons as is, are, or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be appointed thereunto by his Highness, and his Council, and be <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for <reg orig="imploying">employing</reg> and disposing thereof to the use aforesaid. Which said yearly sum of 26260 <em>l</em>: is to be in lieu of all and every sum and sums of money assigned by any Act, Ordinance or Order of Parliament, out of any the <reg orig="Receits">Receipts</reg> of the Excise, for relief of the said <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg>, and maimed Soldiers, other <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> of Fines and forfeitures before excepted; and the present Commissioners of the Excise, or any three of them, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have power from time to time to issue out all monies, either delivered over unto them, or which hath, or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be received by them since the 25 of March last, according as they are, or shall be directed by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, or by Authority thereof. And the said Commissioners of Excise, and their Sub-Commissioners are hereby <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to make <reg orig="repaiment">repayment</reg> of the Excise to any person whatsoever, for any goods imported upon the exportation thereof, in such sort as the late Commissioners might have done before the 25 of March last, It appearing unto them, that the duty of the said Goods have been fully paid, any former Clause, Article, or Provision to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the differences amongst the Grand Commanders of the <em>Highlanders</em> do still continue, and yet for all that, many daily are flocking to them. Those of <em>Loughaber</em> who were about 1200. in number, were all marching homewards again, but some say by the <reg orig="sollicitations">solicitations</reg> of the Lord <em>Lorn</em> they returned.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 15.</head>
<head level="3"><i>From Upsal April 7.</i></head>
<p>We can now in some measure make you a requital of News by telling you that his Excellency hath concluded the Treaty here, to a <reg orig="ful">full</reg> and large satisfaction on both sides, and that within fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after he began to Treat with those Noble Persons that were Commissionate for that purpose by her Majesty. We must confess it was beyond our expectation, when we considered the difficulties, the greatness of the business, the designs to obstruct it, and the <reg orig="aversness">averseness</reg> of divers great ones towards it: But the grand Chancellor, and his Son Count <em>Erick</em>, who were the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Commissioners came off with good respect to my Ld: Protector, and to my Lord Ambassador also himself, who with great wisdom and dexterity hath managed this business. The Queen also hath manifested incomparable affect on to his Highness, and favour to my Lord Ambassador, with whom she hath kept her word very honourably. She told my Lord Ambassador, That she would have the honour to make the Alliance <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> with my Lord Protector, and in respect to him, and she said, because my Ld: Ambassador treated with her like a Gentleman, <i>avec toute la franchise es rondour, et non pas comme un Marchand</i>, she did consent to more <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other could have obtained from her.</p>
<p>It hath pleased God to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> much mercy to us in our voyage hither and in our business here, and we hope to enjoy the like in our return, which will be now out of hand.</p>
<head level="3"><i>From Upsal, April 8.</i></head>
<p>The Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> wrote Letters of late to the Q: of <em>Sweden</em>, wherein he signified the cause of his War with the <em>Pole</em>. Two reasons he mentioned: one because a certain <em>Poland</em> Poet writing a Narration of former Wars, wherein the <em>Pole</em> had; he better, said, they had beaten the <em>Muscovite</em>, without adding his Title <em>plain Muscovite</em>. The other, because in quoting <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> touching the Genealogy of the <em><reg orig="Muscovites">Muscovites'</reg></em> Ancestors, he named one as Father, which was the Son; and for these two grand offences, he demanded of the <em>Pole</em> the <reg orig="offenders">offender's</reg> head; which being denied, he makes War upon them, and hath taken one City, an besieged one of the most considerable in <em>Poland</em>. These were the contents of his Letters. In <pb n="4" />his long title he hath of late called himself <em>Dominus parentum &amp; <unclear>aunum</unclear> suorum</em>. The Queen being forced to answer something, because he asked her advice, returned, that she neither approved, nor disapproved his reasons, but thanking him for his civil communication, wished that he might receive good satisfaction from the <em>Pole</em>, being troubled that Christian Princes should disagree.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 9.</head>
<p>A Declaration is set forth by his Highness the lord <em>Protector</em> for a Day of Thanksgiving for the Peace with <em>Holland</em>, and for the late seasonable Rain, as it here follows.</p>
<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings, in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the out stretched arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment and wonder, Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter, and they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> and indeed the dispensations of the Lord have been as if he had said, <em>England</em> thou art my <reg orig="first-born">first born</reg>, my delight amongst the Nations, under the whole Heavens the lord hath not deals, so with any of the people round about us.</p>
<p>The Lord having added another Link to this golden Chain of his loving <reg orig="kindnes">kindness</reg>, by giving us a Peace with our Neighbours the <em>United Provinces</em>, (whereby he hath not only stopped a great issue of blood, but We trust also given us hearts to unite Our blood and strength for the mutual defence of each other) <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>
<p>Is it therefore thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, &amp; for the thankful Acknowledgment of this blessing of Peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other blessings.</p>
<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up, that it threatened <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg>, and did cause the Beast of the field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into the expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord imparted this mercy to us, did any amongst us <reg orig="fore-know">fore know</reg> it was coming, was it not stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, &amp; that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy <em>&amp;c</em>?</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 3.</head>
<p>By Letters from <em>Paris</em> thus, the Duke of <em>Espernone</em> having lately made suit unto the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty for the recovery of one hundred and fifty thousand Livers, which he disbursed in his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, in the late Wars: Answer was returned him, that his majesty had many <reg orig="waighty">weighty</reg> affairs now in hand, and that he had very great occasions for money at the present, and withal intimated that <em>Mazarin</em>, and some other <reg orig="favourits">favourites</reg> first.</p>
<p>This Answer did not <reg orig="wel">well</reg> <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the said Duke, especially in regard of his present occasions, and want of money, therefore he writes a Letter to his Majesty as followeth.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Dukes">Duke's</reg> Letter to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty.</i></head>
<p>Sir: Having long attended with patience, and not finding <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> either in conduct of my present life, or in the memory of my <reg orig="fore-past">fore past</reg> time, which might justly cast me into a worse condition, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the rest of your Subjects. Nevertheless (Sir) your Majesties will doth so Regulate mine, that had it not been for necessity the strongest master of all) I had not at this season made further addresses to your Majesty, for that which I held so well bestowed in your service, but seeing I find that every man drives at his own ends, it hath taught me a lesson, that I live not in an Age wherein I shall be fed with vanity. Yet I do not withal suppose your Majesty doth so slightly esteem of service, as not to make any farther use of me; nor do I find <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> so unuseful as to be forced instead of better <reg orig="imployments">employments</reg>, only to let you know what News I stirring, &amp; to give you an account of ordinary <reg orig="rumors">rumours</reg>; I must humbly beseech your Majesty to suffer me to <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in this opinion, I have of <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, and however it happen (Sir) or how badly <pb n="6" />soever <em>I</em> be <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg>, <em>I</em> am determined to continue resolute in <reg orig="well-doing">well doing</reg>; And your Majesty may be assured, that neither time, which affordeth occasions to the most miserable to raise their fortunes, nor place often favouring their resentments, no necessity which causeth their actions to seem just, shall ever transport me from remaining with the same affection <em>I</em> ever have done to be, 2 <em>May</em>, 1654. <i>Sir, your most obedient, most humble, and most faithful Subject, and Servant, <em>Espernon</em>.</i></p>
<p>There was a paper presented to his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <em>The humble representations of the Justices of Peace, chief Officers of Corporations, Ministers of the Gospel, and the Grand Jury at the Assizes held at Sallop</em>, wherein they declare, that they bless God that so suitable a Remedy (amongst so many changes) should be applied to our growing Maladies, by raising up his Highness, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>
<p>This Day affordeth memorable Intelligence from several places as that the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> fallen out with Prince <em>Rupert</em>, for selling the Guns belonging to the great ship called the <em>Swallow</em>, there was in her fifty brass <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance; the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> was seldom seen so much out of his own temper, which it is thought would have declared <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> by some effects, had not the certain News of the Peace betwixt <em>England</em>, and <em>Holland</em> made them shake hands. Two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> who had a long time exercised their <reg orig="Pyracy">Piracy</reg> about the Bay of <em>Biscay</em>, having sent their men on <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg> for fresh meat, had their men <reg orig="intrapped">entrapped</reg>, and the two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> were taken by the Men of War of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 11.</head>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Duncaster">Doncaster</reg></em> they write, that a Regiment of about twelve hundred stout men are marched that way towards <em>Scotland</em>, they say that they belong to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Okey</em>.</p>
<p>This Post brought Letters of great stirrings, and preparations in <em>Scotland</em> on both sides <em>Middleton</em>, and the rest of that Crew do all they can to increase their numbers, and Gen: <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is as active in drawing together his Forces towards the Mountains, and by keeping them there (<reg orig="til">till</reg> they have spent their provisions) they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> afterwards be forced to fight, or lay down their Arms; In the mean while they keep their old trade of stealing down by parties, and doing what mischief they can, and some Country People run away with them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and some Towns are so base unto us, that they have made stay of <em>English</em> Passengers that were but travelling through them. A party of ours met with about 30 Countrymen in a knot, going to the Enemy; After that they met with a party of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> horse, with whom they had a great fight, killed six, and took fifteen Prisoners; the like was also done by another party; The Enemy stands not long to it, except he in a place of great advantage.</p>
<p>This day we had further Intelligence from <em>Sweden</em>, that the Articles of Peace betwixt <em>England</em>, and her Majesty the Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> are signed, and are to be brought hither to be Ratified by his Highness the Lord Protector. The Lord Ambassador from the K. of <em>Spain</em> had Audience by the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>The <em>English</em> Fleet are now at a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Downs</em>, both <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em> are very jealous what will be the ensuing design, and strong Guards are kept upon the Frontiers of both Kingdoms. A <em>Spanish</em> ship was lately cast away, wherein was 15 <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of Gold.</p>
<p>This week was a groundless Report, that Lieut: Col: <em>John Lilburn</em> was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> for his life again in <em>Jersey</em>, condemned, and Executed, or came to some other end, whereas the Letters say, that he is <reg orig="wel">well</reg> in health in the Castle.</p>
<hr />
<p>A dark bay <reg orig="Nagg">Nag</reg> with a white slip down his forehead, with a little white slip on his upper lip, about 14 hand high, his further foot behind is white to the fast <reg orig="joynt">joint</reg> he had a lock on one foot afore, a young <reg orig="Nagg">Nag</reg> about 4 years old; Lost the 3. of <em>May</em> 1654 out of the grouping of Mr: <em>Glover</em> and <em>Enfeld</em> in the <em>Middle</em>, ex; to bring Intelligence to <em>William</em> <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters--></unclear> <em>Tabots</em> in <em>Holborn</em> at the <em>Bell</em>, he shall be <reg orig="wel">well</reg> satisfied for his pains.</p>
<hr /> 
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F: N.</em> 1654.</head>


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>