<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout157">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 157
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p><i>The Articles, Oath, and Instrument, signed by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, for the governing of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; With the manner and frame how the <em><reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg></em> are to be constituted, <em>Religion</em> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, the <em>Ministry</em> maintained, the peace of the Nations preserved, the liberties of the people defended, and the Grievances of the Poor and Oppressed, relieved and redressed. With a <em>List</em> of the Names of the great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <em>England</em>, and his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> Speech, and Proclamation, agreed upon on Wednesday last. The coming of his Highness into the City yesterday; and the great Transaction of important businesses at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall. The proceedings of the Navies at Sea; and the landing of col. <em>Wogan</em>, and divers others, from the K. of Scots, in Lancashire. The sending of Arms and Ammunition to the Highlanders; and a famous Victory obtained by the <em>Lowlanders</em></i>.</p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 16 of <em>Decemb.</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 23 of <em>December.</em>. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, Decemb. 16.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>As <unclear>Malice</unclear> drinketh for the most part her own <reg orig="poyson">poison</reg>, so Envy <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> <em>Aristotle</em>, hurteth more the envious <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the thing that it envieth. Like as the <reg orig="sloathful">slothful</reg> in war, or <unclear>Darnel</unclear> amongst Wheat, so is the envious in a City: not so sad for his own miseries and calamities, as he lamenteth the hap and felicity of others. Wherefore the Philosopher <em>Socrates</em> calleth the Enemy <em>serrom anima</em>, the Sow of the soul, for that it cutteth the heart of the envious to see the prosperity of others. For as it is a grief to good and <reg orig="vertuous">virtuous</reg> men to see evil men rule: so contrarily to the evil most harm is to see good men <unclear>thrive</unclear>. Therefore, the first disturber of <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, and last destroyer of good <unclear>States</unclear>, the beginner of all <reg orig="sorrowes">sorrows</reg>, the <unclear>end</unclear> of all <reg orig="joyes">joys</reg>: the cause of all <pb n="1" /> evil, and the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> let of all <reg orig="goddnesse">goodness</reg>, is envy. How prospered <em>Greece?</em> <unclear>Had</unclear> flourished <em>Rome?</em> How quiet was the whole world, <unclear><reg orig="befor">before</reg> a</unclear> envy began to practise with malice, two Daughters of tyranny, never seen, but hidden in the hearts of flatterers? Then, I say, Greece was glorious, Rome was famous, their names were honoured, their <reg orig="prowesse">prowess</reg> feared, their policy commended, their knowledge extolled, their fame <unclear>spread</unclear> over all the whole world: but when envy began to sojourn in Greece, and malice to build her <unclear><reg orig="Bower">Power</reg></unclear> in Rome; these sisters (like two Monsters, or two grim Gorgons) oppressed Castles, destroyed Countries, subdued Kingdoms, depopulated Cities: in <unclear>fine</unclear>, <reg orig="tryumph'd">triumphed</reg> over all Greece and Italy. And many there are in this our Age, who placing their delights in things approximate to Sense and Reason, against those who have <reg orig="out-stript">outstripped</reg> them in Honour and Dignity, are <unclear><reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> with</unclear> impetuous malice against those new Constitutions they now <reg orig="breath">breathe</reg> under, and fain would involve these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, into a most deplorable, and inextricable Labyrinth. But I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="center">centre</reg> no longer (at present) upon the Bird-witted Ideas of our Times; but desire (rather) that they would confide and render that honour and obedience, to whom (under God) it now belongs unto: And <unclear>so proceed to</unclear> the Effects and Cause of this great Change and Revolution, <em>VIZ.</em></p>
<p>The Parliament having upon their Dissolution delivered up the power which they received from his Excellency at their first sitting, by a Writing under their hands and seal, his Excellency thereupon called a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, and advised how this great Burden of governing <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, with the Armies therein, and Navy at sea should be born, and by whom; who after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> seeking of God and advising <unclear>them</unclear>, It was resolved that a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of godly able and discreet persons should be named, consisting of 21. And that his Excellency should be chosen Lord Protector of the three Nations, which was accordingly solemnized of Friday <unclear>last</unclear>, in manner and form as followeth:</p>
<p>His Excellency about one of the clock in the afternoon went from <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> to Westminster, to the Chancery court, attended by the Lords commissioners of the great Seal of England, Barons of the Exchequer, and Judges in their Robes; after them, the <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of the commonwealth, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Recorder of the city of <em>London</em>, in their scarlet Gowns: then came his Excellency attended with many of the chief Officers of the Army, and a chair of State being set in the said court of chancery, his Excellency stood on the left hand thereof uncovered, till a large Writing in parchment, <pb n="2" /> in the nature of an Oath, was read; there being the power with which his Excellency was invested, and how his Excellency is to govern the three Nations; which his Excellency accepted of, and subscribed in the face of the court; and immediately hereupon sate down covered in the said chair, the Lord commissioners and every one standing bare. After which, <unclear><reg orig="the">they</reg></unclear> presented Him with the great Seal, the city Sword, and cap of Maintenance, which were returned to <unclear>them</unclear> again. The court then rose, and his Excellency returned to <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the Lord Mayor uncovered, carrying the Sword before the Protector all the way. Being come to <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, a Sermon was made by one M. <unclear><em>Lockier</em></unclear> (Chaplain to the protector. Thus, after a stately solemnization, the <unclear>fame</unclear> thereof soon <reg orig="eccho'd">echoed</reg> forth with great acclamations of joy both from the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, and others; the Bells ringing, the Muskets <reg orig="ratling">rattling</reg>, and the Canons roaring.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday Decemb. 17.</head>
<p>From Scotland thus: The Highlanders again play <em>Rex</em> upon the Lowlanders, and descend down in several places, like so many billows into the Ocean sea, where they swallow justice, as an <reg orig="Oxe">Ox</reg> doth water, taking no remorse nor pity upon poor souls; but committing sundry and <reg orig="unparalel'd">unparalleled</reg> outrages.</p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Decemb. 19.</head>
<p>The Lord Major and Aldermen being returned from this great solemnization, in pursuance thereof, this day went in their scarlet Gowns, to meet the <reg orig="Herauld">Herald</reg> of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and to proclaim the Lord Protector, which was accordingly done by 12 Trumpets both in Cheapside, and at the Royal Exchange, where the ensuing Proclamation was <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> read, to the end, that all men may conform and submit themselves to this present Government.</p>
<head level="3"><!-- need code for  which appears here --> <i>By the Council</i>.</head>
<p>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their powers and Authorities, The Government of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, Ireland, by a Lord Protector, and successive <reg orig="Trienial">Triennial</reg> Parliaments, is now established; And whereas O. <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> Capt. General of all the forces of this Commonwealth is declared Lord Protector of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make publication of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, and strictly to charge and command <pb n="3" /> all, and every person or persons, of what quality and condition soever, in any of the said three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, Majors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Ministers, and Officers, whom this may concern, are required to cause this Proclamation to be forthwith published in their respective counties, cities, corporations, and Market towns; to the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance <reg orig="in">on</reg> this behalf.</p>
<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 16 day of December, 1653.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Decemb. 20.</i></head>
<p>Having already communicated the manner of the solemnization, the next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view, is, the frame and constitution of the Government established, with the Title of the Instrument aforesaid, which is thus:</p>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em></i>.</p>
<p>And the substance of the said Instrument, thus:</p>
<p>1 That the <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Legislative power of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, shall be, and reside in one single person, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of 13 at least, and 21 at most, and the Commons assembled in Parliament.</p>
<p>2 That this single person shall be called; <i>The Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</i></p>
<p>3 That there be constant <reg orig="Triennal">Triennial</reg> Parliaments, and the first to begin on the 3. of <em>Septemb.</em> next, 1654. and so from 3 years to 3 years.</p>
<p>4 That Parliaments shall be chosen by the people, and that the time of their sitting be for five <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p>
<p>5 That the <em>Parliament</em> shall have power of making all Laws, saving some cases relating to the Guards of the <reg orig="common-wealth">commonwealth</reg>, and Matters of Religion (for which there is particular provision made in the Instrument) containing the Government.</p>
<p>6 That such Laws as shall be agreed on in <em>Parliament</em>, shall be presented to the Lord protector for his assent, which is he do not consent unto within 20 days, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not with withstanding become a Law, and stand in full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>; provided, they contain nothing contrary to the Matters expressed in the said Instrument.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>7 That all Writs, <unclear><reg orig="processe">process</reg></unclear>, &amp;c. shall issue forth in the name of the Lord protector.</p>
<p>8 That the Ministry of the Gospel <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be maintained, and the present way of their maintenance continued, till some other way more convenient shall be found out and provided.</p>
<p>9 That Articles of War shall be made good.</p>
<p>10 That the Lord protector is to be Elective, and not Hereditary, and to be chosen by the Council, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> upon the death of the Lord protector.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Scotland.</i></head>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p><i>On the 10 instant Cap. <em>Lisle</em> of col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> Regiment hearing of a party of the enemy about 10 miles from his quarters, marched in the night from <em><reg orig="Monros">Montrose</reg></em></i> with a 100 Horse and Dragoons, and fell upon them by break of day near <em><reg orig="Glans">Glens</reg></em>, took 40 horse, 19 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, two captains of horse, one Cornet, one Quartermaster, and killed 9 or 10 or them. The next day col. <em>Morgan</em> having notice of a party of them in <em>Eghil</em>, a strong house in <em>Angus</em> near the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, marched towards it; but the enemy having notice, fled away upon his approach; he pursued and took 15 horse; but the Lord <em><reg orig="Kinoul">Kinoule</reg></em>, and col. <em>Ramsey</em> escaped. They increase daily, and are gone Northwards to receive <unclear>arms</unclear> lately landed from Holland. But at their return, we took some of their <unclear>Lobtails</unclear> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Aberdeen</em>.</p>
<p>A party of Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Harisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Regiment were at the heels of col. <em>Wogan</em> and those that came with him at <em><reg orig="Kelsith">Kilsyth</reg></em>; but they gave them the run, and got safe to the Mountains. It is supposed, that he and some others landed in <em>Lancashire</em>, and have commissions and Instruments from their Master <em>Charles Stuart</em>.</p>
<head level="3">Dalkeith Decemb. 15. 1653.</head>
<head level="3">An Advertisement.</head>
<p><i>All persons who are Adventurers for lands in <em>Ireland</em>, are desired to take notice, That the committee for claims for lands on Thursday the 12 of Jan. next coming to be a day of lottery at <em><reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall London</em>, for provinces and counties; and Thursday the 19 of Jan. to be a lottery for counties for all such Adventurers who have made their choice in provinces; and after the said 19 of Jan. the said committee intend to fit three mornings in a week, <em>viz.</em> <reg orig="Tuesdayes">Tuesdays</reg>, <reg orig="Thursdayes">Thursdays</reg>, and <reg orig="Saturdayes">Saturdays</reg>, for preparing <reg orig="certificats">certificates</reg> for such Adventurers as have, or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> by this time draw their lots.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Wednesday Decemb. 21.</head>
<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord protector has spent some time with the great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Nation, about the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the Government, both in Church and State, the satisfying of the people, and taking off Oppressions. In Him therefore let Us confide, and render that honour, worship, and fear, which is due unto his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> under God.</p>
<p>The last Intelligence from <em>Dover</em> bringeth news, <i>That the Royal party in the Netherlands are very high in <unclear>their consultations</unclear>, and with <reg orig="aery">airy</reg> fancies cast some reflections upon our Commonwealth; and forsooth, in a bird-witted way, would fain <unclear>usher</unclear> over a <unclear>flight</unclear> into <unclear>these three</unclear> Nations, <unclear>saying</unclear>, that the Du. of <reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> exchange his <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> for Ireland; the Prince of Conde to be made King of Scotland; and young Charles to be content with England alone. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, Middleton is making all the haste he can to transport from hence great store of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition to the assistance of the Highlanders, who have declared <unclear>for</unclear> Charles Stuart; and (as they say) want nothing but <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> to beat the <unclear>English out</unclear> of Scotland. The Earl of <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg> &amp; <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> are raising divers Regiments of horse and foot, and great assistance is expected from the German <unclear>Princes</unclear>; but to this there is little probability; nor need we in the least fear <unclear>them since the</unclear> Queen of Sweden has declared for the interest of this Commonwealth; and withal has sent propositions to the States of Holland, adjuring them once more upon pain of her Royal Revenge not to infringe her <reg orig="Mejesties">Majesty's</reg> Liberties, by violating of her trade and <reg orig="traffique">traffic</reg>. The King of Denmark has likewise declared a great inability to a war with England; but looks with a notable <unclear><reg orig="sheeps">sheep's</reg></unclear> eye upon the North of Scotland.</i></p>
<head level="3"><unclear>Westminster</unclear> 21.</head>
<p>As touching the <unclear>cause</unclear> and manner of the Dissolution of the late Parliament, I hold it needful by <unclear>reason of various</unclear> Reports, to give you a brief account of the business; the sum whereof take as followeth:</p>
<p>The House being sundry times divided; the prevalent party at last began to oppose the Anabaptists, and to interwove their speeches with some bitter Invectives, saying, That they <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> to destroy the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, as appeared by their Vote upon Saturday. In consideration whereof the Presbyterian party declared, That they <em>could</em> not <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves to sit any longer, and so be guilty <pb n="6" /> of bringing confusion and desolation upon the Nation.</p>
<p>2 The Church-party urged, that the Dissenters had dealt disingenuously with the Army, in moving that the Officers should be treated with to lay down their pay, and likewise to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the casting out the Bill of <reg orig="Assessement">Assessment</reg>. To which, they answer, That as to what was urged as disingenuity to them, in <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to retrench some of the <reg orig="Officers">Officers'</reg> pay. It was moved indeed in order to the abatement of the Tax; That in respect of their great <em>estates</em> already gotten, and the little pains and hazard they were now at in this time of peace, and the sore and heavy burden that was upon the people, That the chief Officers would for one year in this time of <reg orig="streight">strait</reg>, serve the commonwealth freely, as they had called the <em>Parl.</em> to do. And concerning the motion of casting out the Bill of <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> was upon this ground, That it was an unequal and oppressive way of Levy, which yet, least then the emergent affairs of the nation should suffer, it was waved, hoping ere another <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> should be laid, it might be done by a pound rate, or some other more equal way of <reg orig="Assesse">Assess</reg>, instance being given of some Towns and Counties in the Commonwealth, paying 12 and 13 s. in the pound, and others but two and three. So that the Debate growing high, divers members <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> their <em>Protest</em> in dissatisfaction to the thing moved, and without <reg orig="puting">putting</reg> it to the Question, or adjourning to any other place, the Speaker left the chair, and with divers members went hastily out of the House with them: some 30 and odd staid within, who mutually declaring, that they had <reg orig="profest">professed</reg> in the presence of the Lord, that they were called of God to that place, which was the principal motive that drew them thither; and that they apprehended their said call was chiefly for promoting the interest of Jesus Christ. Beginning therefore to consider what to do, col. <em>Goff</em>, and Lieu. Col. <em>White</em> came in and entreated them earnestly to go out, pressing it often. It was as earnestly <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> to them, that at their personal Request they could not; but desired them to withdraw, unless <reg orig="the">they</reg> had command to put them forth; which when they perceived, they commanded in some <reg orig="Musqueteers">Musketeers</reg>; upon which they withdrew: soon after, several <em>were</em> sent for to come to Whitehall, where an Instrument was drawn up for resigning the power to the General, which was subscribed by many, but refused by others. This the late speaker, M. <em>Rous</em>, with a short preamble delivered to the General, saying, That whereas they <pb n="7" /> did <reg orig="fore-see">foresee</reg> that their waitings and expectations of ever coming on to things of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> good, were utterly disappointed.</p>
<p>This day his Highness the Lord Protector sate with the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, which are 13 in number, in the Council chamber at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, and several things were transacted in order to a quiet and peaceable settlement of the three Nations: After which, his Highness, in a sweet speech, pressed them to act for God, and the peace and good of the Nations, and particularly recommended to them, to consider and relieve the distresses of the poor and oppressed. So that <unclear>we</unclear> have great cause abundantly to bless God for this new <i>Change of Government.</i></p>
<p><unclear>The Lord Protector has set forth A Proclamation</unclear>, with the <unclear>consent</unclear> of his <unclear>Council, <!-- 1 word --> continuing</unclear> all <unclear>persons</unclear> being in <unclear>Office, for</unclear> the Execution of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, until his <unclear><reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> pleasure be further</unclear> known.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Names of the great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <em>England</em></i>.</head>
<p>Mr. <em>Lawrence</em> President.</p>
<p>Major Gen. <em>Lambert</em>,</p>
<p>Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em>,</p>
<p>General <unclear><em>Disborow</em></unclear>,</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <unclear><em>Skippon</em></unclear>.</p>
<p>Sir <unclear><em>Anthony-Ashley Cooper</em></unclear>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Strickland</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilb. Pickering</em>,</p>
<p>Sir <em>Charles Woolsley</em>,</p>
<p>col. <em>Sydenham</em>,</p>
<p>col. <em>Jones</em>,</p>
<p>col. <em>Montogue</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Rous</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Major</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Thursday Decemb. 22.</i></head>
<p>By an Express from the fleet it is certified, That Gen. <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is at S. <unclear><em><reg orig="Ellins">Ellin's</reg></em></unclear> Road with 30 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, &amp; has sent out his <em>Scouts</em>, who have brought in several prizes: the <em>Dutch</em> have also taken some English Merchandizes. This day his Highness the Lord Protector came into the city of <unclear><em>London</em></unclear>, about some things of great importance, which for want of room, I shall refer you to my next.</p>
<hr />
<p><i><unclear>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg></unclear> below the Church over against <unclear>the Stile</unclear> that goes to Stepney, in <unclear>Trumpet yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg></unclear> <em>L.M.</em> Student in <unclear>Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg></unclear>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the <unclear>swelling</unclear> of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness of</unclear> the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues; of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many <unclear>that</unclear> have been thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg> in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him. The History of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year, 1652. With the Names of all their Governors, Magistrates, and eminent Ministers. Printed for <em>Nath. Brook</em> at the Angel in <reg orig="Corn hil">Cornhill</reg>, 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, Printed by R. WOOD, 1653.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>