<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout180">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 180
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>A Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector, concerning the Dukes, Marquesses, <reg orig="Earles">Earls</reg>, Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, that shall presume to disturb the Peace of this Nation; and his Resolution touching Sir <em>Gilbert Gerard,</em> Major <em>Mason, Dr.</em> Naudin, and the rest of the Gentlemen now prisoners in the Tower of <em>London.</em> The discovery of a further Plot against his <em>Highness</em>, <reg orig="th">the</reg> taking of a French ship and the Conspirators, and the chief Actor <em>Mr Fitz James (</em> that should have <reg orig="murther'd">murdered</reg> <em>Him )</em> escaping and cozening the English, by leaping into the sea, and drowning himself: An exact Narrative of the whole business, the confession of the Actors, and the time when this Treason should have been executed. A Proclamation of the States of <em>Holland,</em> the calling back of their messenger from England, and the particulars of a desperate fight in Scotland.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 19. to <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 26. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>May</em> the 19.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>It is recited in <em><reg orig="Speeds">Speed's</reg> Chronicle,</em> That Dr <em>Cranmer</em>, with the Earl of <em>Wiltshire</em> , and some others, being sent by King <em>Henry</em> the 8th to the Pope, about his Divorce from Queen <reg orig="Katherin">Katherine</reg>, when the day of hearing was come, and the Pope sitting in his <em>Pontificalitus</em> put forth his foot to be kissed of the Ambassadors, an unmannerly Spaniel of the <reg orig="Earles">Earls</reg> ran and caught his great Toe in his teeth: so that the Ambassadors disdaining to <reg orig="kisse">kiss</reg> where the Dog had taken <unclear>an assay</unclear>, let the Pope draw back his foot, and so they <reg orig="loft">left</reg> the especial favour offered unto them. But Pope <em>Innocentius</em> the 4th, a bloody &amp; turbulent man, after many wicked and abominable pranks, as he was in <em>Naples,</em> a <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> was heard in his Court: <i>Surge <unclear>miser</unclear>, &amp; veni ad judicium</i> : Arise, oh wretch, and come <pb n="1" /> to judgement, and the day following he was found dead in his bed, all black and <reg orig="blew">blue</reg>, as though he had been beaten with Bats: But of such Historical Relations, (both Foreign and <reg orig="Domestique">Domestic</reg> more hereafter. &mdash;</p>
<p>Gen. <em>Monk</em> hath sent a Letter to his Highness the Lord Protector, whereby he signified, That he was advanced beyond <em><reg orig="sterling">Stirling</reg></em> toward the Highlanders from whence he intends, after <unclear>securing</unclear> of some few passes, to take the field. In the interim, col. <em><reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em> hath performed a singular piece of service, by <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> col. <em>Middleton</em> (brother to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>) and after a sharp Dispute, took prisoner this valiant <reg orig="Heroe">Hero</reg> and divers other Commanders, routed the whole party (<em>but they were not many</em>) and pursued them towards <em>Caithness</em>, making good their Retreat, with little loss.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> is about <em>Tane</em>, watching opportunities to engage them, and the Highlanders are preparing to receive them; having fortified several passes, and made them inaccessible. Gen. <em>Monk</em> hath caused two Gentlemen to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> as <reg orig="Spyes">Spies</reg>, burnt the Inn at <em>Muscleborough</em> that harboured them, and erected a <reg orig="Gibbit">Gibbet</reg> in the same place.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 16.</head>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> it is certified, That the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador has received audience of his Majesty, to whom he imparted the joyful <reg orig="Tydings">Tidings</reg> of a Victory obtained by the <em>Portugal</em> fleet against the <em>Hollanders</em> in <em><unclear>Brazil</unclear></em>; and of the taking of <em>Reclif</em>, and about 40 other Towns and Castles from them. Which doth not a little <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> the Royal Family: <i>Win gold, and wear it; 'tis fit <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> should have their own.</i> Upon a delicate Banquet between the King and Queen, on the 3 of May, the K of <em>Scots</em>, and his afflicted Mother were both invited, in whose presence, his Maj. danced the great <em>Ballet</em>; but the young <em>Charles</em> exceeds him far in the Italian Comedy. Propositions are preparing to be sent to the K of <em>Spain</em> for a ten years Truce.</p>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That since the concluding of a peace there hath been great discontents; and that the Princess Dowager, the Princess Royal, and the rest of the family of Nassaw, have presented a Declaration to the States General, bemoaning and applying their condition as sad by the late Articles of peace with England; and the very women have <reg orig="address'd">addressed</reg> themselves <reg orig="in">on</reg> the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> behalf, wringing <pb n="2" /> their hands, and crying out, <i>Ah! poor Prince, what hast thou done that thou shouldest be thus used? Ah poor Child! what a sad condition art thou in?</i> and the like penetrate expressions; whereupon, its conceived, the States will have compassion on them, and permit them to live peaceably, if they please. The great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> has sent an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> to the Hague, demanding Officers and warlike Ammunition: from thence he goes to <em>France</em>, where their <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Lord the King to be all in arms.</p>
<p>&#x261e; On Saturday last there was a great Plot discovered against his Highness the Lord protector and his Council, and many of the Conspirators being examined on the <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> following, before the council, an Order passed for their restraint, &amp; accordingly they were committed to the Tower, as intending to be Actors, the <em>Plot</em> being <reg orig="contiv'd">contrived</reg> in <em>France</em>, and so to have taken away the life of his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, the Lord protector, and to have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the council, and to have massacred all those that should have stood in opposition against them: Nay, this was not all; but their Design was wholly to subdue, extirpate, and break asunder, those Chains of Mercies, and <reg orig="Linkes">Links</reg> of Liberties, so long contended for, and at last happily effected, though with the loss and <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of the <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> of many thousand Saints.</p>
<p>It is confirmed from <em>Brazil</em>, that the <em>Hollanders</em> are almost totally banished from those parts; and are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> in other places. The last news from <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the Royal party grow numerous, and that they spake themselves to be above 11000 at the last <reg orig="Rendevous">Rendezvous</reg>, being resolved to fight us; which is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> desired by the merry Redcoats: so that by our next, no doubt but you will hear of action.</p>
<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is arrived at <em>Lubeck</em>: The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> will certainly resign the Crown to her kinsman <em>Carolus Adolphus</em>; his brother Prince <em>John Adolphus</em> having laid down his Patent of the Lord High Marshal of <em>Sweden</em>, is gone to Stockholm, to confer with his elder brother, who will shortly be invested with the Royal Dignity.</p>
<p>Gen. <em><unclear>Oxenstern</unclear></em> is appointed to go as an Ambassador into <em>England</em> with a great Retinue, and a gallant Train both by Sea and Land are expediting forth.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<!-- page doesn't seem to follow on --> <p><reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, and hath <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the Venetian Ambassador in close prison, not so much as <reg orig="rendring">rendering</reg> a reason for it, or intending to have any further Treaty or capitulation with the Duke of <em>Venice</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em>, May 22.</head>
<p>The States General of the United Provinces have set forth a <em>Proclamation</em> for prevention of disturbances, or breach of the peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, that all persons whatsoever shall acknowledge and submit to the <unclear>Ratification</unclear>, and obey their Superiors in all places. <i>Excellent good? but who do they tell their tale to? A Leathern Cloak for such Creatures: Come, there's a time for all things.</i></p>
<p>For, observe, 't was a <em><reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg></em> in the days of our <reg orig="Fore-fathers">Forefathers</reg> <i>(and those were good, I am confident) That pride would have a fall:</i> Truly, <em>Gentlemen</em>, Experience makes it out in this our Age; and not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of those who have revolted from the most excellent Bonds of Loyalty; but likewise reflecting upon many that have formerly usurped a <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg>, <em>that is</em>, in coveting of thy <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours'</reg> goods, &amp; making <reg orig="thy self">thyself</reg> great, by the sweat of their brows. Alas! 'tis <reg orig="pitty">pity</reg>, <i>Really, I <reg orig="cou'd">could</reg> wish every man had his own; forbearance is no acquittance.</i></p>
<p>In the interim, thus much give me leave to present you with, that the great <reg orig="Belgick">Belgian</reg> Champion, Vice Admiral <em>Dewit</em>, and all the rest of their men of War, strikes both flag and topsail to the English, &amp; have done Homage, (<em>that is,</em> to <unclear>cringe</unclear> like a Spaniel) in the very place, or near to it, where they endeavoured to have destroyed them about 3 years ago. <i>Deus nobis <unclear>h&oelig;cotia</unclear> fecit.</i> &mdash;</p>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> they write, That Gen. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> forces increaseth, &amp; that the taking of his brother, and hanging up of two Gentlemen as <reg orig="Spyes">spies</reg>, doth so far exasperate his <reg orig="undanted">undaunted</reg> spirit, that he, nor none of his, are resolved neither to give, or take quarter. <i>Happy be <reg orig="luckie">lucky</reg>, the longest liver take all:</i> And seeing that so just a quarrel must be disputed with fiery Arguments from the mouth of the <em>Canon</em>, <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> but Trophies of Honour will crown our renowned <em>Heroes</em>, with <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> <reg orig="Atchievements">achievements</reg>: for, truly, we have dissipated them in several places, and upon the last <unclear>Onset</unclear> a party of col. <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> <reg orig="Daagoons">Dragoons</reg> meeting with the Lord of <em>Cairdennis</em>, and his party, charged gallantly, and routed them desperately, killed his Lordship, two Cornets, &amp; 9 more upon the place, took 35 prisoners, and as many horse, <i>if our intelligence <reg orig="failes">fails</reg> us not: Must we not take it from the letter of the Times?</i></p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> thus: His Majesty hath deferred his day of Coronation, <pb n="4" /> until the day of Holy Trinity, and the commissioners of <em>Rheims</em> have made great preparations for his entertainment, by the humble and loyal subjects of that city: <i>A good <unclear>bearing</unclear></i>. Tis said, there is a league offensive between this Crown, and <em>Portugal</em>, who doth undertake to set forth a fleet to assist them; <i>Who minds 'em?</i> And that Pr. <em>Rupert</em> is said to go suddenly for <em>Germany</em>, and the K of <em>Scots</em>, and his brother <em>James</em>, for the Highlanders; <i>but I have not faith enough to believe that, as yet.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday</i></head>
<p>Discovery was made of a barbarous Conspiracy, by villainous Assassinations, to have turned the State into blood and confusion. And whereas the enemies of the peace of this Nation, do appear still restless in their attempts to involve this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in blood and confusion: In order whereunto, divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> from beyond the seas, as from several parts of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> with the advice of his Council, hath set forth a <em>Proclamation</em>, expressly charging and commanding, That for the better discovery of persons ill affected to the peace of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, the Constables of the respective parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <unclear><reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg></unclear> of <em>Southwark</em>, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication of the same, repair to the several houses within their respective parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as <em>now</em> do, or did lodge in their respective houses on Friday night last, being the 19 of this instant May, or at any time since, with their several <unclear>qualities</unclear> and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg>, are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names, upon peril of being reputed and dealt <unclear>with all</unclear>, as <reg orig="Complices">accomplices</reg> and partakers in the said Designs. Which Lists so delivered, the respective Constables of the parishes aforesaid, are within 48 hours, to deliver to the Lord Mayor of London, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to fail at their utmost peril. And the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received to his Highness Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, immediately after the receipt thereof. And his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> doth likewise <unclear>strictly</unclear> command and require, that no persons whatsoever lodging within the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several and respective Lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten days after the date hereof, without a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> License and Pass in <unclear>that</unclear> behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor, or <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of Westminster and Southwark respectively, under their respective hand and <unclear>seals</unclear>; which <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> are authorized to give to all such persons concerning whom they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be satisfied, that they have no ill intentions or designs against the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to none else. And if any shall presume to depart without Licence, it shall be reputed a contempt of his Highness command, and be punished according to its merit. The names of those sent to the Tower, are, Sr <em>Gilbert Gerard</em>, Col <em>Gerard</em>, Mr <em>Fotherby</em>, Mr <em>Bagaley</em>, Mr <em>Jones</em>, Mr <em>Tudor</em>, Dr. <em>Naudin</em>, Maj <em>Mason</em>, M <em>Brown</em>, M. <em>Hill</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 24.</head>
<p>The Hollanders do already begin to find the benefit of the peace with England and about 20 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> are come to the River of <em>Thames</em> with great store of cheese and <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg>.</p>
<p>Divers Colliers are likewise safely arrived, and the great fleet is suddenly expected.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Copy of a Letter from Amsterdam.</i></head>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p><i>Great are the discontents in these parts by the house of <em>William</em> of <em>Nassaw</em>, and all that are that way <reg orig="alleyed">allied</reg> or affected, declare, that they knew not but of one or two of the Articles of peace till they were concluded and published; and therefore determinate, to set the Royal bellows at work, to <reg orig="blew">blow</reg> new Embers, and kindle a consummating fire within the bowels of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>; in order whereunto, Count <em>William</em> is calling his Army to a general <reg orig="Rendevous">Rendezvous</reg>, and declares very high for the Royal Interest: so that we are constrained to keep very strong Guards, both here and at other places, and do expect new Commotions to be had very suddenly; very high words they give forth, <reg orig="in">on</reg> behalf of the young Prince of <em>Orange</em>, yet they seem rather to proceed from abundance of affection, <reg orig="then">than</reg> judgement, valour, or anything that may add life, nerves, and sinews to <unclear>an <reg orig="wwar">war</reg></unclear>. Upon the beating <unclear>upon</unclear> Drums both here, and in France, the discontented persons come in, and list themselves <unclear>voluntarily</unclear>, and, if Report speaks truth, many are sent <unclear>from</unclear> thence into Scotland. We hear that the foreign Ambassadors have had audience with Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, in order to the carrying on of a general peace. The Prince of Conde hath had new Propositions sent to him for an agreement since his effigies were hanged up in Paris; and his brother Conti, who is now in great favour, <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to be an effectual Mediator between his brother and the Court, who have a sum of money for the King of Scots; but the pittance was so small, that he is like to have occasion (poor Gentleman) to make new addresses for more before he can get out of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</i></p>
<p>Amsterdam, May 19, 1654.</p>
<p>This week the Packet Boat coming for England from beyond sea, was taken by the out-lying <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> abroad: some of the English passengers were drowned, and those that they saved were <reg orig="stript">stripped</reg> to the skin; but the next morning the Master, one woman, and two more, had pieces of broken <reg orig="sayls">sails</reg> given them to cover their nakedness, and put into an old <reg orig="Cock-Boat">Cockboat</reg> to shift for themselves.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>From <em><reg orig="Guernzey">Guernsey</reg></em> they write, That the <em>Hector</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> attending without St. <em>Mallows</em> divers <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> for conveying the English from thence who are still detained under the arrest, a Shallop was sent out of the Town to tell the Captain that the English should have all freedom; but this was found to be <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> a Decoy, to draw him in, and so not trusted.</p>
<p>For, we hear, that two of our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> are seized upon, and that upon the going of 60 of our men ashore for fresh victuals, endeavoured to drive away some cattle; but the country receiving the <reg orig="allarm">alarm</reg>, rescued the cattle, fell upon our men, and <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>, wounded, and took above 30, pursuing the rest to the ships, two of which were stranded upon going forth of the Tide: whereupon the great Guns were brought from St. <em>Mallows</em>, to batter the ships, which they did begin to do, but the Tide coming in, the ships got off without any great hurt. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> apprehending this to be a design against the Town, took an occasion to turn out all the English Merchants, and to seize upon all their Goods in the Warehouses, and hath got all for the present in his own custody. Complaints hath been made hereof, and the French Ambassador hath had audience, so that the business is under examination.</p>
<p>&#x261e; There was a man most barbarously murdered the last week, and being cut to pieces, was put into a bag, and thrown into a Ditch not far from <em>Paddington, (the ready Road to Tyburn)</em> he was so <reg orig="mortifi'd">mortified</reg> and <reg orig="dismembred">dismembered</reg>, that none can make a discovery what he is; for not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> his head and nose were separated from his body, but his hands arms, legs, and thighs, were also cut off: This was done by one man and a woman, who falling out in Turnball street on Saturday night last, she discovered him, and immediately he was apprehended and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> before a Justice, who asked him, how he could find in his heart to commit so unmerciless and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> an act, he made answer, <i>pish, Justice <unclear>Ass</unclear>, that's a thing of nothing, I could serve you so, if I had you in Place where.</i></p>
<p>The <unclear><reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg></unclear> in the Western seas are as bold, and as <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, as ever; but dare not adventure Easterly, where Gen. <em>Pen</em> <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> with the Fleet in the Downs, in a gallant Equippage. And the next main design 'tis thought will be to help the Venetians against the great Turk, for that he is the common enemy of all Christendom; and as he is making of himself stronger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, so doth he <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself more insolent</p><pb n="7" />
<!-- page doesn't seem to follow on -->
<pb n="8" /> <head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 25.</head>
<p>By an Express from <em>Holland</em> it is certified, That the Royal party mount up like so many sturdy Cedars; and great is the noise of a secret Article, which is said to be added by the States of Holland, without being communicated to the States General; whereby the Pr. of <em>Orange</em> and his whole Race and Posterity, in case he hate any, are to be excluded out of all the <unclear>charges</unclear> and dignities, which the deceased P. of <em>Orange</em> did possess. This <unclear>caused</unclear> some of the cities to protest against it, and the other 6 Provinces <unclear>desire</unclear> a copy of what the <em>States</em> of Holland had agreed and concluded <unclear>upon</unclear> this subject. Nay, more, 'tis said, the States have sent an Express into England, to recall their Messenger that was <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg> by them with this private Article a little before, to prevent the delivery thereof to the Lord protector. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, they debate about the <unclear>disposal</unclear> of their fleet, which is said will be <unclear>sent for Brazil</unclear>; (<em>high time</em> where <em>Francisco Barretto</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> for the <em>Portugals</em>) having obtained several advantages upon the Hollanders, blocked up their strong <unclear>fort</unclear> of <em>Becif</em>, with the small forces he had, notwithstanding the 28 forts the Dutch had round about; and at length by the assistance of the <em>Portugal</em> fleet of 65 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, who blocked up the place by sea, and landed some forces there; on the 5 of <em>Jan.</em> last he stormed and took the Fort of <em>Salines</em>; The 6 he came before the Fort of <unclear>Furaco</unclear>, which was presently abandoned, &amp; blown up by those within, He came after to the new Fort, next to the <em>Recif</em>, and very strong and well manned; but after a stout resistance they were forced to yield, <i><reg orig="thohgh">though</reg> notwithstanding they had above 1500 men, and 6 months provisions, and in defiance of the Portugals, had kept it 24 years.</i></p>
<p>We hear that divers other eminent persons are apprehended (upon suspicion) as Actors in the late conspiracy; and that a Vessel is taken with Letters from <em>France</em>; and he whom they say should have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> his Highness, <reg orig="leap'd">leaped</reg> <reg orig="over board">overboard</reg> and drowned himself, his name was <em>Fitz James</em>, an <unclear>Irish</unclear> man, and divers of those taken, confess the plot was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> execution, upon <unclear>effecting</unclear> whereof, the people were to rise in several parts of the Nation, the K. of <em>Scots</em> were to enter, and be proclaimed King: so that had it <reg orig="taked">taken</reg>, it would probably have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> the <reg orig="bloudiest">bloodiest</reg> day that ever was in <em>England</em>.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>