<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton171">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scovt, Issue 171</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE FAITHFUL</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>

<head level="3">COMMUNICATING,</head>

<p><i>The Resolutions of Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, Earl of <em>Athol</em>, Lord <em>Seaforth</em>, Lord <em>Ray</em>, <em>Glengary</em>, and Sir <em>George Monro</em> to have a Rendezvous at <em>Inra</em> with their whole force, consisting of 12000. horse and foot. To prevent which our Commander in chief in <em>Scotland</em> hath taken the field. With a true and perfect account of the state of our Navy, and a List of 15. prizes, taken by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance</em> and <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>: Together with a perfect account of the State of affairs in Ireland, as they were reported by the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> who is safe returned from thence: Also the Speeches that passed between the Lord Protector, and the Lord Ambassador <em>Burdeux</em> from the King of France, when he had Audience in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> March 24.. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> March 31.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON. Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday March 24.</i></head>

<p>The Lord <em>Ray</em> hath sent to <em>Skelco</em> for Arms for his men, <em>Seafort</em> was expected the ten instant within five mile of <em>Carbsdale</em> with his men, Sir <em>George Monro</em> and <em>Middleton</em> were then in <em><reg orig="Stranraver">Stranraer</reg></em>, and to meet <em>Seafort</em> and <em>Ray</em> at <em>Inra</em> with their whole force, where also <em>Glengary</em> with his rabble are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them and so force <em>Sutherland</em> and <em>Caithness</em> to rise. It is reported that since <em>Middleton</em>, a Lord is landed with store of Arms, and they threaten to destroy and plunder all that shall not side with them.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday March 25.</i></head>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Upsal</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em>, thus: The Treaty goes on, but slowly; yet doubtless, if the Transactions between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> take effect they will soon be <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> in new Councils; for her Maj. promiseth fair to the L. <em>Whitlock</em>; and hath revived her former Overtures of resigning up the Government to her Successor, and desires the liberty of retiring into privacy. The great Taxes upon the people is conceived <reg orig="wil">will</reg> push them forward to some notable design, which causeth the Senators to sit very close in <reg orig="councel">council</reg>. They are consulting what Answer to return to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proposals, for resigning up the Crown and <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>, to her Successor, or Lord Protector. But by another Abstract we are given to understand, that the Marriage between the King of Scots, and her Royal Majesty is, ratified and agreed upon by the Princes and Peers of the General Assembly at the <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg>, withal, that the great Duke of <em>Holstein</em> is to marry the Lady Elizabeth Princess of <em>Orange</em>. Alas! alas! too high fortunes, to be interwoven with so fatal and deplorable conditions: For, the Post Letters of a later date <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> inclination is to merit the King of the Romans, eldest Son to the Emperor of Germany; but that business being <reg orig="deter'd">deterred</reg> by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, 'tis probable she will again renew her former Proposals for to <reg orig="center">centre</reg> in Solitudes. Notwithstanding, the hearts of her Subjects are exceeding averse to the change of Government, and with great acclamations of joy sounds forth her praises with a cordial and loyal <reg orig="Eccho">Echo</reg>, <i>Long live Queen <em>Christina</em>.</i></p>

<p>The English Fleet are divided into four Squadrons, the better to scour and secure the Narrow Seas, they are excellently well equipped, and as bravely <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>: Nothing wanting, but a resolute Enemy to fight <reg orig="then">than</reg>; which neither curled Waves, nor Weltick Ocean can bear, in case the Belgick Canons be <reg orig="silenc'd">silenced</reg>. They have already forced some of the <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, Rovers, and Irish <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg>, from Brest to Toulon in France, where they have now time enough to sing the second part to the same tune, <em>O bone, on bone</em>. We have taken another of their men of War, and a Dutch Merchant laden with extraordinary good commodities.</p>

<p>The Dutch Letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning last about 3 of the clock, was seized and broke open by 5 Hectorian Knights of Fortune, within a mile of S. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em><pb n="2" /> Church; but finding no <reg orig="moneyes">moneys</reg> in the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg>, broke open the Letters, cast them upon the ground, and turned the Messenger back again, with a Belgick Flea in his ear. Some of these Letters made mention of a final Agreement between the two Republics of England and Holland. And Monsieur <em>Bourdeaux Neusuille</em>, Ambassador from the King of France, was brought in state through the City in the 27 instant, to Sir Abraham Williams in the Palace-yard: He is to receive audience in the 28 instant.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 28.</i></head>

<p>This day, being the 27 of this instant <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, there came a <em>Post</em> from Scotland, intimating, That the Royal party increaseth and that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise <em>Southerland, Caithness</em>, and the county of <em>Ross</em>, and so to drain the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, even as a <reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> sucketh in Water, of all the able, stout, and resolute hearts, that are able to bear Arms from sixteen to sixty; with a Resolution to descend down into the Lowlands: for, indeed, they grow numerous, and swell up as a <reg orig="Snow-Ball">Snowball</reg> doth in its rolling; but may as soon dissolve again in the like Element. The Lord <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to seven hundred the Earl of <em>Athol</em> five hundred, Col. <em>Forbs</em> five hundred, and the last general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, no less then seven thousand horse and foot they spake themselves to be <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> armed, but have not obtained as yet the silver Instrument, which is the life of the Cause, and the very sinew of War: but their expectation is great from <em>Germany</em>, and for ought I know, long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for may come at last: in the interim, they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p>

<p>From Scotland it is further <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath sent a Letter to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, declaring, That it was not unknown what amicable <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> they had <reg orig="us'd">used</reg>, to avoid the effusion of Christian blood, since they came into those parts, which thought hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they should never <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the same; <i><reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> further</i>, That their Arms were still <reg orig="stretcht">stretched</reg> out ready to embrace them, when ever God should incline them to come in, and that they sought not domination over them, to enslave them, nor to <!-- surely depress? --> depness them in any lawful way, but to carry on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Work: And that if they would still be blinded, and persist in the gain-saying and opposing, then<pb n="3" /> what further misery befell their Nation by famine or sword, would <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> heavy upon them. This Letter (though savouring so much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adversaries; for <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> thereupon, an Answer was returned; which being briefly contracted, the genuine sense take as followeth; That in case they were not in a capacity against the unjust proceedings of the English, yet were in they in a capacity to suffer, and should submit to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Will, either by doing or suffering, until the time of their deliverance come; and that if it were their happiness to perish in their Duty and Loyalty, it would be a sufficient mercy to them: and when the persecution had arrive to its height, their captivity should be returned. But doubtless, but that in time we shall be able to put a Hook into the Nostrils, and a Bridle into the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of these high and mighty Youngsters, who threaten nothing but fire and sword to all that shall oppose them. There has been a Summons sent to the castle of Lough by col. <em>Morgan</em>, in the name of the Lord Protector, demanding a rendition. But the Governor returned Answer, That as for the castle it stood upon a Rock, and as for the Lord Protector he knew no such man: in consideration whereof, he was resolved to dispute the Walls by inches, and to fight it out to the last man.</p>

<p>The 28 instant, the French Ambassador had Audience before his Highness the Lord Protector, at which time, upon the presenting of his Letters Credential from his Master the King, he made a very learned and excellent Oration, touching his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, and the renewing of a more stricter League and Union between both Nations. Of which, more in our next.</p>

<p>From Dublin thus: The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, when he comes back to you will confute those false Reports that were raised of us here, he having had a reception as a Prince, with 300 horse out of the City (most of them Citizens) with <reg orig="bone-fires">bonfires</reg> at night throughout the City.</p>

<head level="3"><em>March</em> the 24.</head>

<p>No news, but that upon a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> invitation the City should so solemnly observe a Day of fasting and humiliation, and it is wished that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> this day fortnight may keep it no worse: for we have great cause to bury our <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the drift for our notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised among us, and to consider the Rod of God upon us, in an universal Drought for some years, and still<pb n="4" /> continued <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <reg orig="famin">famine</reg> and mortality: for true it is, that in the North of England, and several other parts of this Nation, the Springs, River, and <reg orig="Brookes">Brooks</reg>, are almost dry for 20 miles distant. O then consider!</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line><i>To Fasting why should sensual flesh be <reg orig="loth">loath</reg>:</i></line>
<line><i>Fasting is good for soul and body both.</i></line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>By a Letter from <em>Harwich</em> it is advertised, that there is a Dutch ship of 400 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts, and Iron, to a great value brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>

<head level="3"><em>March</em> the 24.</head>

<p>The Lord Protector set forth a Declaration, inviting the People of <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to a solemn day of fasting and humiliation, and ordered that <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the 24 instant should be set apart for the cities of London and Westminster, and the same day fortnight for all the Counties in general in England and Wales. The Causes are, first, the common notorious sins impenitently practised amongst us. Secondly, the present long drought, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> famine and mortality. The sins taken notice of by his Highness are, Notwithstanding the just Liberty Spiritual and Civil, God hath procured by his own people, yet want of humble walking in the <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg> of Christ, or to communicate that liberty one to another. Or thankfully to acknowledge our liberty of worshipping God in holiness, want of brotherly love. Not owning one another for the grace of God more <reg orig="then">than</reg> form: Not seeking the Kingdom of Christ within us, before one without us. <reg orig="Listning">Listening</reg> to false Christs: Temporal Rule for Saints. A crying up of the Spirit; with a neglect of Love, and the other fruits of the Spirit: And an evil carriage towards them without: crying down Ministers that have a large seal of their Ministry, want of old Puritan self <reg orig="deniall">denial</reg>; Mercy to the poor uprightness, justice, and contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, as it ought to be apostatizings of many running after notions and fancies against Magistracy, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, Scriptures, and Ordinances, contempt of the Gospel, and sincere Professors of it, even for the Image of Christ in them. Oaths, Drunkenness, Revellings, and all manner of <reg orig="licentionsness">licentiousness</reg>. And the impunity of these things, through neglect of the Magistracy in several parts of the Nation.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3">Wednesday March 29.</head>

<p>Came to my hands the Copy of an Act for Reformation of sundry abuses practised by divers persons in the common market and streets of the City of London: the genuine sense whereof runs thus:</p>

<p><go>Whereas several good Laws and Ordinances have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> heretofore made, as well by the Court of Lord Mayor and Aldermen, as by others, for the <reg orig="wel">well</reg> ordering of the Markets of the City of <em>London</em>, for <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> of several abuses of Butchers, Victuallers, and others thereunto <unclear>resorting</unclear>, for sale of their <unclear>flesh victuals</unclear>, and other commodities in the several markets of this City, and assigning places and times for the said Markets to be kept and held, Which said Laws and Ordinances by daily experience are found not effectual to prevent some present and growing inconveniences no; have wrought that good effect, as was intended thereby. For <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> whereof. be it enacted by the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord Major, Aldermen and Commons in Common <reg orig="councel">council</reg> assembled, that no Butcher or <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, farmer, Victualler, or other person or persons whatsoever, either free of the City of <em>London</em> or not free of the said City, from and after the first day of <em>Decemb</em>. next after the publication of this Act shall sell, utter, or put to open them or sale in the streets or white markets in within this City, that is to say, <em><unclear>Leaden</unclear> hall street</em> without the Hall, <em>Cheapside</em> and <em>Newgatemarket</em> any Beef upon pain that every person or persons that from and after the time aforesaid shall sell <unclear>utter</unclear> put to sale, or such in any the said <unclear>Pork</unclear> to any Beef, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> forfeit and lose 20 s. for every time so offending and further be it enacted That all and every Butcher, free or not free of the <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> of <em>London</em> who keepeth no Butcher shop or shops within the said City and Liberties thereof or within <unclear>100</unclear> miles distance of the Liberties thereof shall and may sell, utter, <reg orig="shew">show</reg>, and put to sale, his or those Beef Mutton Veal Lamb <unclear>Pork</unclear> &amp; other Butchery ware at certain stalls and places in that behalf appointed in <em>Leaden-hall</em> &amp; the <em>Green-yard</em> there, that <reg orig="onely">only</reg> upon <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg> and <reg orig="Saturdayes">Saturdays</reg> weekly, and not in any other place or places within the said City of <em>London</em> and Liberties thereof, upon pain of 20 s. forfeit And whereas of late times, many of the standings and halls within <em>Leaden-hall</em> and the <em>Greenyard</em> there have, and <unclear>put use</unclear> in the occupations of several persons who are not Butchers by trade who let them out at dear rates to others; and likewise many of the said stalls are in the possession of Butchers who live within the City of London and Liberties thereof who keep the said stalls and likewise their shops: By means whereof the Country Butchers and other Butchers who keep no shops within the said City, or within two miles of the Liberties of the City of London &amp; would furnish the said Markets with Butchery ware can get no convenient room there, and so are necessitated to sell and utter<pb n="6" /> their Commodities in the White-markets, and other places, or to forbear the Markets whereby prices are <reg orig="innhaunsed">enhanced</reg>, and the said Market disfurnished. for remedy whereof, be it enacted by the Authority aforesaid. That all the ground where the standings and places for sale &amp; uttering of flesh and Butchery ware within Leaden hall and the Greenyard there, be resumed and taken into the <reg orig="Cities">City's</reg> hands, and actual possession, before the said first day of Decemb. next ensuing. and further, that no stall, standing, or place within Leadenhall or the Greenyard there, shall from <reg orig="henc">hence</reg> forth be letted or farmed out unto any Butcher or Butchers who doth or shall keep any Butcher shop or shops within the City of London or Liberties thereof, or within two miles of the Liberties of the said City for so long time as he, or they shall keep any <reg orig="Butchers">Butcher's</reg> shop within the Limits aforesaid.</go></p>

<p><go>And that from thenceforth the Stalls, standings, and places in <reg orig="Leadenhal">Leadenhall</reg> and the Greenyard there be let unto <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Butchers, or such freemen who are Butchers, and keep not any Butcher shop or shops within the City of London and Liberties thereof, or within two miles distance of the Liberties of the said City, and for so long time <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as be or they shall furnish the said stalls, standings and places with <reg orig="wholsom">wholesome</reg> Beef, Mutton, Veal, Lamb, <reg orig="Porke">Pork</reg> or other Butchery ware upon Wednesdays and Saturday s, being the usual Market days, and not as Servant or servants to others.</go></p>

<p><go>And further, That no Butcher whatsoever shall have and <unclear>enlop</unclear> more <reg orig="then">than</reg> one stall, standing or place within <reg orig="Leadenhal">Leadenhall</reg> or the Greenyard there at one time. Provided always, That the Butchers freemen of the City of London shall and may at all times convenient sell, utter, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> and put to sale their flesh and Butchery wares in their shops within the said City of London, and Liberties thereof as formerly: <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in this Act to the contrary notwithstanding. Provided that the Country farmer, Lader, or Bidder as to all <reg orig="wholsom">wholesome</reg> flesh victuals and other Commodities except Beef, may have liberty to sell, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> and utter the same in the Common and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Whitemarkets within the City of London and Liberties thereof in market times: this Act or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> contained therein to the contrary. And forasmuch as of late the <reg orig="forain">foreign</reg> Butchers, Victuallers and other people resorting to the Markets of the City of London to sell their fresh victuals &amp; other Commodities d continue and keep their Markets all the day, &amp; until night not observing the hours appointed for their Departure by former Acts and Ordinances, To the end the streets map in due time be cleansed for the health of the Inhabitants of those places; which doing of theirs tendeth much to the disorder of the said Markets, <reg orig="inhaunsing">enhancing</reg> the prices of Commodities, Disturbance and <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> of Passengers and Tradesmen dwelling near the said places, and by reason thereof the streets cannot be cleansed as they ought to be, to the scandal of the Government of the City of London, and is very necessary to be reformed.</go></p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 30.</i></head>

<p>Yesterday the L. Ambassador <em><reg orig="Burdeux">Bordeaux</reg></em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Audience in the Banqueting house in <em>Whitehall</em>, which was richly hung with stately Hangings, and thousands of people present. Being carried in the L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and with him some of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, &amp; Sir Oliver <em>Fleming</em> Master of Ceremonies, attended by divers Noble persons, being in all above forty Coaches, most with six horse <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>. Where he was received by his Highness the Lord Protector, his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> being with his Highness at the upper end of the Banqueting house: where after several Congies each to other, the L. Ambassador made a speech to his Highness, and after his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> answer and salutings, he returned back again. The sum of the L. <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech was to declare that he came from the K. of <em>France</em> his Master to treat in order to a firm peace to be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> with England. Touching which he had a <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> answer.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of 18. Prizes taken by the Ph&oelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance, and <reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a Galliot Hoy, whose Mast being shot by the Board she was burnt. 2. Taken by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the Hope of Hous-down, burthen 50. <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 3. Taken by the Ph&oelig;nix, the Claus of Housdown burthen 50 Tuns. 4. Taken by the <reg orig="Maremaids">Mermaid's</reg> Boat, the Fortune of Mazeland Sluys, burthen 32 Tons, wherein were many barrels of Fish, and 6. of Salt, with about 40 empty Cask. 5. Taken by the same day by the <em><reg orig="Newcastles">Newcastle's</reg></em> Boat, the Skell-fish of Mazeland Sluys, with Fish, Salt, &amp; empty Cask. 6. Taken by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat, the Plumpert of Mazeland Sluys, burthen 30 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise. 7. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the Providence of Mazeland Sluys, 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading. 8. Taken likewise the Fortune of Delfs-haven, burthen 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Brandywine, French wine, Prunes &amp;c. 9. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, burthen 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 10. Taken by the <reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg>, two Scotch vessels, laden with Beef, Flower, Train-<reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, Deer-skins and Sugars. 11. Taken by the <reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg>, the Working Boy of Enchuysen a private man of War, of 8 Guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable. 12. Pikes 10. Muskets, eight Pistols and a Boat with four Oars. 12. A Merchant ship brought in prize into <em>Rye</em>. 13. A Denmark ship brought into <em>Scarborough</em>. 14. A rich prize, laden with Sugar and other Merchandizes, taken by a private man of War worth, with Sugar, and other Merchandizes, taken by a private man of War worth 150000 l. A private man of War belonging to <em>Zealand</em>, taken by the <em>Paul</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> with 15 piece of Ordinance and 60 men, after six hours dispute, she is brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> returned from <em>Ireland</em> and is (blessed be God) safely arrived at the <reg orig="Cock-pit">Cockpit</reg>. All is quiet and in a good condition in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>Extracted out of the original Papers, licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>