<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton169">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scovt, Issue 169</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE FAITHFUL</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>

<head level="3">COMMUNICATING,</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of the proceedings of the Treaty between the English and the Dutch, and the Papers of Agreement between his most Excellent Highness, <em>OLIVER</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em> and the States General of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces With a Narrative of the exact particulars read and examined on Wednesday last at a Conference by Mr. <em>Henry Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council and confirmed and approved by the Lord Commissioners constituted by his Highness for finishing of the Peace. The Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> Resolution for war, and her raising of forty thousand horse and foot. The setting forth of the Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> and a bloody fight between the English and the K. of Scots Admiral: the number killed, wounded, and taken, and ten valiant Captains brought prisoners to Plymouth to be tried for their lives. The sad and lamentable engagement between the English Troops in Scotland, and the manner how they charged each other very desperately killing and wounding divers.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> March 10. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> March 17.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON. Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday March 10.</i></head>

<p>The Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg> have taken into consideration the abuse of farthings, and have debated the allowance of tokens to be made by one that will make them of intrisical value. The Queen of Sweden is sending a message to the Lord Protector <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>, by way of congratulation; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> has set down her Resolution for War against the Emperor, having in readiness 39000 horse and foot. Maj. Bourn &amp; divers others were <reg orig="rob'd">robbed</reg> at Shooters hill, and bound in a Wood: some in a Coach fought, but the thieves slew one of the Gentlemen: another Gentleman of them came to be dressed at M. Mollins in <reg orig="Shoo-lane">Shoe lane</reg>, where one of the thieves came to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, but hearing he was dressing one hurt at Shooters hill, run away without his Cloak, which he had put off in expectation to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>The last <em>Intelligence</em> from Col. <em>Dan. Serl</em>, Governor of the <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, advertiseth, That on the 13 of <em>December</em> last, was held a General Sessions for Gaol-Delivery, and Common-pleas, which continued for the space of five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; amongst others, who received corporal punishments, one <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Barkley</em>, a Scots man, was <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> for buggering an <em>Asnegno Mare</em>, which Mare was brought to the place of execution, and there <reg orig="ty'd">tied</reg> to a Wooden stake, where she was burnt to Ashes, in presence of the said <em>Barkley</em>, who was afterwards <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> executed. After which, one Mr. <em>Robert Richards</em> was hanged for killing an <reg orig="Irish-man">Irishman</reg>, that was a servant in this <em>island</em>, and three Negro-men at the same time were hanged about a <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> some nine months since committed in the night time by several Negroes, who beset the house of one Mr. <em><reg orig="Dobs">Dobbs</reg></em> a Planter, killed him, his wife, and child: So just is the most <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg>, honoured, and very much approved noble Colonel <em>Serles</em>, to administer equal justice upon all <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, that the very <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg> of the <reg orig="Skales">Scales</reg> are rightly terminated upon all Facts, Crimes, <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>, and Actions: Which, indeed, will remain as a <reg orig="Trophicall">Tropical</reg> Palm to eternize his Name throughout all Ages. And so tender is the said Governor likewise in managing of the weighty <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> of that Island, that for the suppressing of runaway Negroes, and to prevent the increase of their great Numbers, He commanded some three hundred men to hunt and range the words, who the first day killed two of the Negroes, one whereof was conceived to be the chief of them afterward seven other Negro men were brought in, and upon <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> found guilty of the said <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, four of them had first their right hands cut off and then hanged; the other three were also executed. About a fortnight since came in sight of the <em>Island</em> a small Dutch man of War, which stood <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the shore, and put forth the English Colours, and a Parliament Jack, and made as if he intended to come in: Upon which four Shallops going from the Bridge to the Leeward, part of this <em>Island</em> with Commodities, thinking it had been an English ship, and standing towards her, were <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> and taken which was a considerable loss.</p>

<p>The Articles of Agreement between the Dutch and Us (as before mentioned) are not yet <reg orig="engrosed">engrossed</reg> the English Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to the Lord Protector, <em>viz</em>.</p><pb n="2" />

<!-- what follows is written as a two column list, with each name separated from the adjacent name by a square bracket which covers three lines -->

<p>The Lord <em>Lisle</em> Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>,</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Lambert</em>, Col. <em>Montague</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, Mr <em>Laurence</em>.</p>

<p>Appointed to finish the business of the Dutch Ambassadors, have had several meetings, and the Results of all (as fairly conjectured) tends to a speedy Union.</p>

<p>The last Post from Holland advertiseth, that there is arrived at the Uly about 140 sail of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships that came from the Eastland, whereof divers are going up to Amsterdam, the rest to other Ports. The Commander Ruittier is chosen Vice-<reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> for that City, and great are their preparations in most places. There is come to the Hague an Agent from the great Duke of <reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg>, who is called the Chevalier Palant; he hath had Audience of the States General, and after that delivered in certain papers, wherein are expressed at large the occasion of his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, and his Demands. The two great ships (so long expected) are now safely arrived at the Uly from the Charibde Islands, and some few ships taken by the English are again re-taken by the Dutch. Nay, further, they have taken some of our ships on the Northern Coast, towards Bridlington Bay, <reg orig="Scarbrough">Scarborough</reg>, and Newcastle, and stranded other <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hartlepool: there is a great Fleet coming from Newcastle, <reg orig="soo">so</reg> soon as the Wind will permit, and a Convoy is ready to attend their motion. There is another great Fleet of Dutch Merchant-men (consisting of no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> one hundred and fifty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> ) gone to the Westward, sailing close by the Coast of France, and having a fair Wind, gave our Fleet the go-by: they have a Convoy of 60 men of war<pb n="3" /> and well <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>, and are to return speedily to the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday March 8.</head>

<p>The Queen of <em>Bohemia</em> (sister to the late King of Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg> ) is going to <em>Frankendale</em>, which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place, and of great frequentation, it being the <reg orig="mid-way">midway</reg> betwixt <em>Wormes</em> and <em>Spiers</em>, where she will do the best she can to entertain young <em>Charles</em>, and to accommodate him in the present juncture of <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg>. His brother JAMES second Son to his late Majesty is as valiant as Hector in the King of France's Army; but the little Queen (his Mother) is of a sudden struck very solentary. The Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> do with much importunity press upon the loyal breasts of the English in several places to support the weak distressed Estate of their Prince; especially at the city of Hamborough, where the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> did <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="solicite">solicit</reg> and importune the Treasurer of the English company, who fearing his power, and loath to part with those monies which belonged to all the English Merchants who <reg orig="traffick">traffic</reg> in those parts, acquainted the President of the English Companies with it, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> the inconveniences that would arise, if he <reg orig="shold">should</reg> deliver <reg orig="moneyes">moneys</reg> to him. Whereupon the President weighing the truth of the Reasons made his complaint to the Senate, who <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> not to exact any sums of money of the Treasurer, unless he was able to put in good security for the re-disbursing of them. <i>Ha! ha! 'tis good to be merry and wise.</i></p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 13.</head>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence that the Constant Warwick, and the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> being together, met with the great <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> Cap. <em>Beach</em>, who had newly take two prizes; but perceiving that our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the Prizes, and was afterward secured by the night coming on. The same night the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> and the constant Warwick chanced to part company, and it so fell out about midnight that Beach towing about, lighted on the <em>Constant Warwick</em> all alone, which before he came near, he took to be a Merchant man, and went on with an intent to board him; but the <em>Warwick</em> demanding who he was, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> he was<pb n="4" /> the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and for <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>. But the <em>Warwick</em> suspecting him, bade him round off. Then <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake, and seeing the <em>Warwick</em> to be a man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, he presently made away; but the <em>Warwick</em> being a good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg>, made after him, and kept company with him all night. About 6 in the morning, <em>Beach</em> began the fight, firing 3. Guns, which were answered by the <em>Warwick</em>. The encounter lasted till two in the afternoon, at which time Beach and his men called for Quarter, and had it. He had five foot water in the hold when he yielded; he had 200 men, 20 whereof were killed; his <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> is a gallant new Vessel, of 42 Guns, whereof but thirty eight were mounted. There are taken aboard with him nine Captains besides himself, and divers Gentlemen, who are all prisoners. This is that <em>Beach</em>, the <reg orig="Ring-leader">Ringleader</reg> Pirate, who hath done our Merchants so much mischief this Winter, that he lived like a Prince at <em>Brest</em>; for which 'tis like he will receive his reward, being brought in hither, with the rest of his companions.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his most excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> by the Divine Providence, <em>Lord Protector</em> of the three Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></head>

<p>The Cordial Declaration and humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of the ancient and renowned City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, by the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg> and Common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> thereof, Signed and signified under the Common Seal of the said City, at a Common <reg orig="Councie">Council</reg> there holden.</p>

<p>Desert and Praise should <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> go together as Twins, where the one precedes it is an injury to <reg orig="with-hold">withhold</reg> the sequence of the other; So great hath been the desert of your most Excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> (through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God) in the eyes of all these Nations for divers years past, that we humbly conceive we should make <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> a scorn in the <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> of Foreigners for our ingratitude, if we should not make our Praises in some measure commensurable to Your <reg orig="vaste">vast</reg> <reg orig="Archievements">Achievements</reg>.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> sincerely in what we Declare, and do hope that Adulation will not by any good men be interpreted to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> couchant in our Expressions, for we shall speak the words of Truth and <reg orig="Sobernesse">Soberness</reg>. &amp;c.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3">Wednesday March 15.</head>

<p>The <em>Royal <reg orig="Soverain">Sovereign</reg></em> is now ready to spread her Canvass upon <reg orig="Neptunes">Neptune's</reg> curled Waves, and the two new <reg orig="Frygots">Frigates</reg> lately christened the <em>Naesby</em>, and the <em>Marston Moor</em>, will suddenly be equipped and rigged: the first <reg orig="carryes">carries</reg> 64 Guns: the other 60, if We mistake not, which is very seldom. There is building another great ship for War, which is as broad, and longer <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <em>Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em>, alias the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, &amp;c. So that the lines of a learned Gentleman may justly be inserted, to wit;</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Ye Wainscot-<reg orig="fac'd">faced</reg> Turks, glory ye no more</line>
<line>Of your great Fight upon the <unclear>Africk</unclear> shore,</line>
<line>Where great <em>Augustus</em> and <em>Mark Anthony</em></line>
<line>Did combat for the whole <reg orig="Worlds">World's</reg> Victory,</line>
<line>When <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg></em> of <em>Austria</em>, assisted by</line>
<line>The Church, and <em>Venice</em>, <reg orig="darkned">darkened</reg> the Sky,</line>
<line>Frighted the Ocean, Venice a free State</line>
<line>Fit for the Trident, and to fulminate</line>
<line>In dreadful accents Terror to affright,</line>
<line>And <reg orig="stupifie">stupefy</reg> <reg orig="Imposter">Impostor</reg> <em>Mahomet</em>;</line>
<line>Our <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Infant-State, <em>Alcides</em>-like,</line>
<line>Young in her Cradle did the Serpent strike,</line>
<line>That Serpent <em><unclear>Belgia</unclear></em>, and <reg orig="vip'rous">viperous</reg> Beast,</line>
<line>To eat the Bowels of her <em>Fostres</em>, least</line>
<line>She should eclipse her glory, Lyones</line>
<line>Loosing that brave Spirit, turned Tygres:</line>
<line>O <em>Belgia</em>! and I may here include</line>
<line>Your most unequal vile ingratitude:</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>But fith that <em>Providence</em> doth seem to promise Us a fair conclusion, after our late <reg orig="unparallel'd">unparalleled</reg> Engagements on the <em><reg orig="Brittish">British</reg></em> Ocean, we shall therefore draw to a conclusion with the final Results of the Treaty, <em>viz</em>. That the English Commissioners, and the Dutch Ambassadors have concluded upon the engrossing of the said Articles, which are to be transcribed <reg orig="fayrly">fairly</reg> into Vellum; and the Dutch Prisoners are already set at liberty, and are to have moneys to transport them home.</p>

<p>Another part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church falling down the last week at the<pb n="6" /> great South door, where a part fell before: it was under consideration by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for taking it down; but nothing yet done in it.</p>

<p>Our last <em>Post</em> from <em>Scotland</em> bringeth certain intelligence, That there are divers great Commanders, and eminent persons landed at the Ferrey of Uney in Southerland a List of their Names We <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> here present you with as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Lords, Knights, and Colonels, landed in Scotland, and the number of Officers, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>.</i></head>

<!-- following names set out as a two column list. The columns are separated by a vertical line -->

<p>Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, Col. <em>Stuart</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Douglas</em>, Col. <em>Gibson</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em><reg orig="Murrey">Murray</reg></em>, 24 Captains,</p>
<p>Sir <em>George Monroe</em>, 27 Lieutenants,</p>
<p>Sir <em>Alexander Ennis</em>, And about 60 other Officers and Gentlemen.</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Dyel</em></p>
<p>Col. <em>Dyel</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Lodowick Drawland</em>, Great store of Arms, Ammunition, and other warlike Provisions; by way of Tradition 'tis said, that they have brought over three white Flags, with the cross bloody Daggers, and that they are already marched up to Achness with divers Horse load of Arms from whence, they intend to march up to Strath-fleet, terminating to have a conjunction with Gen. <em>Glencarn</em> in the Highlands, and then to proceed with fire and sword against all those that shall oppose them in the Lowlands. But let them beware, that <reg orig="Valours">Valour's</reg> great <em>Elixir</em>, who do's three Nations aw, doth not once more with his brandish Sword give the Redshanks a Law, for which end, his Highness hath ordered all Officers to repair to their several charges.</p>

<p>But since their arrival, the Highlanders grow numerous; and at their late general <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> were distributed, some monies received, and Letters read from their King, promising his assistance to the uttermost of his power at which some <reg orig="signes">signs</reg> of great joy were made; but let them laugh that wins, May the justness of the Cause carry it.</p>

<p>The King of Scots of his own accord did chose to go for Germany rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> for Scotland at present, and is no way discouraged at his Removal out of France: <i>so familiar are his misfortunes with him.</i></p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Thursday March 16.</head>

<p>Yesterday the Commissioners from the Lord Protector went from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in two Coaches with the Secretary of State and the Clerk of the Council and their attendants to the Dutch Ambassadors, at Sir <reg orig="Abraham Williams">Abraham Williams's</reg> from whence they are not yet removed to Sir John <reg orig="Trevers">Trevers's</reg>: they were met at the gate by the Lords Ambassadors, where the Lord Beverling made a speech to them and they received them with great respect and love on both sides. Being come into the House and into a chamber appointed for their Conference; they spent much time in order to the finishing of the peace. The business this day, was to confer their Papers of the agreement, for though they have agreed, yet it is <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> by each side, and on Wednesday last they compared their papers; which when both compared together, do in all particulars agree; then they are to sign on both sides. And what they sign, the Dutch Ambassadors do in the name of the States General. But <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> more it is to be sent to the States, who are also to give their assent after the Ratification, and then they deliver the Articles on both sides, which its conceived will be done within the space of three weeks.</p>

<p>The two Ordinances touching Ministers and touching the law <unclear>is before</unclear> a Committee, whereof Justice Hales in the Chair. The particulars expect in my next.</p>

<p>The Highlanders increase in Scotland and Gen. Middleton begins to play <em>Rex</em> again: they had a <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the 11 instant, and are now marching towards the Lord <reg orig="Reaffs">Reaff's</reg> Bounds. There hath lately happened a great disaster between Cap. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> troop and Cap <reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg>, the manner thus: Cap. Palmer having pursued the enemy at last met with a party of horse, which he took to be the enemy whereupon he charged them desperately but were as gallantly repulsed by Cap. Mason, who charged them through and through, and for the space of half an hour the business was very disputable, in which unhappy engagement 6 were slain on both sides and 8 wounded, whereof Cap. Palmer is one.</p>

<p>From Plymouth our Scout bringeth intelligence, that the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath sent in 9 ships which was taken upon the French Coast and the <reg orig="Non">None</reg> -such <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath taken three delicate Vessels laden with Wine, Beans, and Salt. Nine more taken on the Coast of Scotland and Cap. Wilkins hath taken another, bravely fraught with rich <unclear>Mere</unclear> and <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> The Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> is now put forth to sea, and rides in Stoke bay. Two Merchants ships that were coming from Ipswich toward London, were taken by a Dutch man of war, they <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the English of both under the Decks of one of them, on the 4 of March, and then left them, sending them homeward; but the next day the English at a seasonable time lifted up the decks, relieved themselves, took the Dutch, and <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> them under the deck where they were, and brought away both their ships to the Downs, which are now safe in the River, with the prisoners.</p>
 
<hr />

<p><em>Gentlemen</em>, This is the ancient faithful SCOUT, composed by the same Head which formerly drew up the Original Copy, <reg orig="licensend">licensed</reg> and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Hall-book of the Company of Stationers for G. HORTON, and appointed to be published throughout all Cities, Towns, and Corporations, for information of the People, and to prevent the abuse of all false Copies under this Title.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>