<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout175">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 175
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>The Message sent from the States of Holland, to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Articles of Peace signed and sealed, and presented to Him in <unclear>a silver box.</unclear> The Letters sent to all the United Provinces, concerning the <unclear>K. of</unclear> Scots, &amp; the <unclear>House</unclear> of Orange. The proceedings of the Q of Sweden, touching the Marriage of P. <em>Charles</em>, and the coming down of D. Francis of <unclear><reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg></unclear> (<unclear>touch</unclear> <reg orig="Low-countries">Low Countries</reg>) with a stately Train. The number of <unclear>Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg></unclear>, revolted from the English, to Gen. Middleton, the <unclear>taking of Cap. Southwood</unclear>, and the white Raven; and the blowing up <unclear>of another</unclear> in <unclear><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></unclear> Road. A bloody fight between the English and French, the sinking of <unclear>the</unclear> <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Admiral, and the names &amp; number of the rest taken with the strange Order concerning yellow and black boots, strong water and Tobacco, &amp; the Articles &amp; Charge exhibited against <em><reg orig="Hanna">Hannah</reg> Trapnel</em>, the <unclear>Proprietoress</unclear> of <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, by Mr. <em>Lobb.</em></i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 14. to <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 21. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>April</em> the 14</i>.</head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>There are two eminent <reg orig="Markes">Marks</reg> of a Commonwealth or free people; and the first is Elections annual: the second is <unclear>Election of persons</unclear> for Government during <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear>. Indeed, the people are not so free that are governed by <em><unclear>Hereditary</unclear> Princes</em>, as those that are governed by <unclear>elected</unclear> <em>Princes</em> or <em>Governors</em>: in Elections <unclear><reg orig="Fooles">Fools</reg> ordinarily</unclear> are shut out, that may possibly come to lay claim to Government and power by a right of Succession. If wicked and corrupt persons could also be shut out by elections, it were then the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> way to be preferred <unclear>and esteemed</unclear> one good way for discovering such persons, so that before <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> is elected to the greatest Trusts, they ought to pass through most of the lesser Trusts in the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, in which they must give a Testimony both of their abilities and fidelity: yet <em>Nero</em> was not discovered in passing <pb n="1" /> through the several Trusts, before he arrived at the Empire, nor in 5 <reg orig="yeares">years</reg> after for <em>Tacitus</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the most virtuous Prince that came to the Empire, fell short of Nero's <unclear>first</unclear> five years. It is evident, that those that elect annually need not so <unclear>much</unclear> circumspection, as those that elect <em>Princes</em> or <em>Governors</em> for life: for <unclear>let one</unclear> be never so wicked that is called to Government but one year, he cannot do much hurt in that time, neither indeed will he: for that he knoweth he shall be put in the same condition with others of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: therefore it behoveth him to do that which shall be for the good of the people; for in so doing, he shall be a <reg orig="joynt">joint</reg> sharer.</p>
<p>And as there are many States that do <unclear>esteem</unclear> of annual Elections, so have they good Expedients to prevent <em>corruptions</em> in persons of inferior Trust. As for example, the <reg orig="Common-wealth"></reg> of <em>Genova</em> have for their Head a Duke elected out of the Citizens, who is to govern two years and during that time he liveth in a Palace like an absolute Prince; yet he cannot do or act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> but by and with his Council, which are 8, they are called <em>Governors</em>, and the Duke with <unclear>these</unclear> 8 <em>Governors</em> are called the <em>Seigniori</em>, who in matters of great concernment of the State in general, they call the <em>Senate</em>, where the Duke hath this <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> to propound whatsoever is fit to be considered <unclear>in</unclear> Senate. But the reason of that is, for that there be 28 Families of the Title of Gentlemen, who have the Government <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> amongst them; and the Duke being but to continue two years, <unclear>they</unclear> presume that he will not move <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in Senate that shall be in favour of one Family more than another. The Government was formerly endeavoured to be <unclear><reg orig="setled">settled</reg></unclear> in one family; but the <unclear>Contest</unclear> was like <unclear>to</unclear> have overthrown the Commonwealth, until that <em>Andrew <unclear>Doria</unclear></em> in the year <unclear>1528</unclear>. <unclear><reg orig="setled">settled</reg></unclear> it in an <unclear>equal <reg orig="poyze">poise</reg></unclear> amongst the 28 Families; at which time he <unclear>might have <reg orig="setled">settled</reg></unclear> it upon himself and posterity; and for that he did not, the <em>Genovois</em> did in memory to <unclear>him</unclear> praise, erect a <unclear>Statue</unclear> for his perpetual Glory. Indeed it is more worthy to <unclear><reg orig="asume">assume</reg> <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg></unclear> power to knock off Chains, and leave a people free, <reg orig="then">than</reg> it is to <unclear>usurp</unclear> to make people slaves.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>Genova</em> is governed by 4 men elected out of the Senate, called <reg orig="Sindicks">Syndics</reg>; these have the Charge for one year: the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> power is a Council of two hundred; out of them are elected 25 Senators, who assemble every day upon the Affairs of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; and out of them are chosen the <reg orig="Sindick">Syndic</reg>.</p>
<p>The State of Lucca are governed by a Council that are chosen annually; and out of <unclear>that</unclear> Council ten, which make a Seignori: Out of these ten, one hath command as Head of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> for three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; then another of the ten: so it cometh again to him that was first.</p>
<p>Many other States are ruled <unclear>altogether</unclear> by elective persons; and most <em><reg orig="Heriditary">Hereditary</reg> Princes</em> do so esteem of often elections of Ministers of State under them, as that they find it to be absolute necessary for the expelling of corruptions, and to prevent their people from being discontented; <unclear>as</unclear> the King of Spain sends every three years new <reg orig="Vice Royes">Viceroys</reg> into the Kingdom of Naples, Cicilla, <unclear>Aragon</unclear>, and the West Indies.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>For, alas! there is no such Remedy against Changes in a State, as to change the persons that govern; and if the Head, or Chief of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> be not changed, yet if those under him be, it will be all one as if He were. O such persons that thrust themselves into Commands, and great Power, are to be <unclear>suspected</unclear> as to their abilities: The fears that those must take upon themselves, and the danger they are in, would startle one that looketh upon Greatness in this World. It is an excellent Testimony in a man that is fit for great Trusts, when he doth <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to shun them; it argues that they know well the Nature of them. <em>Moses</em>, when God would have had him taken the conduct of <unclear>leading the people of Israel</unclear>, he had a great reluctancy of Spirit, and was afraid of his <unclear>inability</unclear> to perform so great an Undertaking.</p>
<p>Wonderful it is, certainly, that any <unclear>man</unclear> <em>Genius</em> should sore so high, <unclear>as absolutely to covet</unclear> the unwarrantable things below. It was not so in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of old, as evidently appears by that admirable <unclear>expression</unclear> of a <unclear>precious Emperor</unclear>, to a familiar friend of his, who upon his Election congratulated him, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he,</p>
<head level="2">If thou knewst the weight of the Crown upon my Head, and the <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg> in my Hand, thou <reg orig="would'st">wouldest</reg> not deem a Kingdom, or Empire, a desirable thing.</head>
<p>But to Intelligence, and the Work of the Day: His Highness: Lord Protector was attended from the <reg orig="Cock-pit">Cockpit</reg> to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, where he dined with his Council; and afterwards graciously vouchsafed to give audience to divers Petitions, referring them to a Committee: so that the grand Affair of the <unclear>Peace</unclear> between England and the United Provinces being over, believe it, Mr. <em><unclear>Sadier</unclear></em>, and Mr. <em>Long</em>, will not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be <unclear>Masters of Request</unclear>, but Masters of Grants, to the great Relief of the much affected, and oppressed people.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday April 15.</i></head>
<p>From <em>Ireland</em> we have received intelligence, that there is <unclear>scarce</unclear> anything wanting in that <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> but people to manure the <em>ground</em>, and a good conscience to hold forth their infallible practices, which indeed has been too much eclipsed in these our <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The plague is well <reg orig="appeas'd">appeased</reg> in many parts; yet notwithstanding the pestilence <unclear>rageth</unclear> too too much amongst many: From which, <em>Good Lord deliver us.</em></p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg><reg orig="Ayril">April</reg> 17.</i></head>
<p>The next thing that we shall present you <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, is, an Express from abroad the <em>Pearl</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> in <em>Dover</em> Road, signifying, That a Squadron of English ships are commanded to <em>Deep</em> in <em>France</em>, to conduct over the two <em>French</em> Lords, who have received further <em>Credentials</em> from their Master the King, for the concluding of a firm League and Union with his most Excellent Highness, <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector, &amp;c. So runs the Title of the Commission: from whence we may infer, that the <em>Harp</em> makes the sweetest Harmony: For, true it is, that many <em>Christian Princes</em> have resolved to congratulate his Highness; and to that end, sundry <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> are preparing: <i>So that they begin to work out their deliverance with fear and trembling.</i></p>
<p>From <em>Truro</em> in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, That Mrs. <em>Hannah Trapnel</em>, who lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, hath for some time <reg orig="bin">been</reg> in those parts, where she passed from Town to Town, to vent her Prophesies, and alienate the hearts of the people from the present Government: There are in her company one Mr. <em><unclear>Longdon</unclear></em>, and M. <em>Baudin</em>, two members of the late short-lived <em>Parliament</em>: but the <unclear>justices</unclear> having taking <unclear>practice</unclear> of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and practices, she was <unclear>apprehended: <!-- approx. 2 words --> giving the Charge</unclear> in the last <unclear>Session killed the <!-- approx. 3 words --></unclear> <em>Vagrants</em>, 2 such as <unclear>occasioned unlawful <!-- approx. 2 words --> as speak against the</unclear> present Government. There were two <unclear>Indictments</unclear> drawn against her; but M. <em>Langdon</em> and M. <em>Baudin</em>, endeavoured to make a <unclear>learned</unclear> Defence; and could not be suffered: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <unclear>they entered</unclear> into Bonds of 300 l. for her good <reg orig="behavior">behaviour</reg>, and appearance at the next Assizes. This passage reminds me of the old story of <em><unclear>Eliz. Baron</unclear></em>, the Holy Maid of <em>Kent</em>, as she was called in the days of <unclear>old</unclear> who was made use of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests, by <reg orig="feined">feigned</reg> Miracles &amp; Trances, to <unclear>raise</unclear> admiration in the multitude, and <unclear>some</unclear> seditious <unclear>Humours</unclear> against the Government; for which she and her accomplices were all hanged <em>but the head.</em></p>
<p>From sea, the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> news is, that a fleet of 40 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of <em>French <reg orig="Merchant-men">Merchantmen</reg></em> were met with off <unclear>of Ushant</unclear>, by the <em><unclear>Portsmouth</unclear></em> and <em>Middleburgh <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg></em>, who assailed them, and maintained a very hot Dispute, in which they sunk the <em>French</em> Admiral, and took 5. But the foulness of the weather separating our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg>, impeded their further <reg orig="persuit">pursuit</reg> of Victory and so the fleet escaped.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><i>A List of the Ships taken and sunk in the aforesaid Engagement.</i></head>
<p>1 The Admiral sunk, called the <em><unclear>Foundore</unclear>, 22 guns.</em></p>
<p>2 The St. <em>Clement</em> sunk, a ship of 14 guns.</p>
<p>3 The Rear-Admiral taken, called the <em>Leveirge</em>, a ship of 18 guns</p>
<p>4 The <em>Lough Blanch</em> taken, a ship of 11 guns.</p>
<p>5 The St. <em>Jaques</em>, a delicate ship of 18 guns.</p>
<p>6 The <em>John Baptist</em> 12 guns.</p>
<p>Those that escaped were,</p>
<p>The <em>Concord</em>, the <em>Protect</em>, the <em>Joseph</em>, the <em>George</em>, the <em><unclear>Chevalier</unclear></em>, the <em><reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg></em>, the <em>Peter</em>, the <em>Le Fume</em>, the <em>Palma</em>, the <em>Julia Lunia</em>, and some others.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 18</i></head>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That the States General have sent to all Provinces, and considerable cities to bring in their opinions and consents concerning the House of <em>Orange</em>, and the <em><reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart</reg></em> Family; <em>'tis hoped all things will prove for the best.</em> And 'tis conceived the Q of <em>Sweden</em> hath a good intention for the <em><reg orig="Low-Countries">Low Countries</reg></em>: Unto which confines, valiant Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em><reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg></em> is said to prosecute his journey with a stately Train. Their great <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg>, far bigger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, is designed to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth into the Deep about the merry month of <em>May</em>: at which time they intend to play strange pranks, <em>over the left shoulder.</em></p>
<p>The States have had several meetings for preventing of the <unclear>Designs</unclear> which may be intended against the <em>Sound</em>, and to preserve the <unclear>secure</unclear> right to the K. of <em>Denmark</em>; and upon the Result, sent Orders to the Admiralty of <em>Amsterdam</em>, to carry on the Naval <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> with expedition.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Advertisements from <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></i></head>
<p>The <em>Commissioners</em> for <em>approbation of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Preachers</em> sit on <em><reg orig="Modays">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg></em>; of which <em><reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg></em> for <em>Augmentations</em>. In all the Transactions, there is no respect had to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> so much as grace in <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> <unclear>hearts</unclear>; some University men, for defect thereof, have been laid by; and some who never were University men, yet furnished with gifts and graces, have been received, and welcomed. No Difference at all among the <em>Commissioners</em> themselves, though they be of divers <reg orig="judments">judgements</reg> about <em>Church matters</em>, all minding the <em><unclear>advancement</unclear> of the Gospel</em>. They being 38 in number are severed into three Divisions, each sitting their month. No partiality used in their <reg orig="Tryals">Trials</reg>; <unclear>nor</unclear> do certificates approved of, but such as come subscribed under the hands of such persons as are known to the <em>Commissioners</em>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 19.</i></head>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Minhead">Minehead</reg></em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the <em>Brest</em> men of war do much harm in that channel, having of late taketh several Vessels, whereof some of a considerable value which belonged to <em>Bristol</em>: others, of no great esteem, yet too good to be lost. Nay, they are grown to such a height, that they dare presume to come even into the very mouth of <em>Severn</em>, where they beat us with our own Weapons, by employing our own Vessels against Us.</p>
<p>The last Letters from <em>Germany</em> <reg orig="advertize">advertise</reg>, That the new Levies are almost finished, and <unclear>that</unclear> great is the expectation of the <reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg> playing a new Game with certain Christian Princes. They have reinforced the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Casal</em>, and the Dukes of <em>Florence, Parma</em> and <em><unclear>Modena</unclear></em> <unclear>are also</unclear> raising of divers <em>Military forces</em>.</p>
<p>But what their Design is, we cannot as yet give you an Account of; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, that there is a bloody war to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on vigorously this Summer. Indeed, all <em>Europe</em> seems to be in a Chaos of confusion; and nothing but war and <reg orig="Rumors">Rumours</reg> of war throughout most of the <em>Christian Territories:</em> The Vice King of <em>Naples</em> threatens destruction to <em>Catalonia</em>, and the King of <em>Spain</em> is determined to take field suddenly. The Prince of <em>Conde</em> begins to move, and has received new Instructions from the Council of <em>Spain</em>, which has given so great an <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> to the King of <em>France</em> that no less <unclear><reg orig="then">than</reg></unclear> fifty thousand <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> and foot are designed to impede their march, and Gen. <em><unclear>Thurene</unclear></em> is to advance forthwith into <em>Picardy</em>, and take a view of the Army, and to set it in a <unclear>posture fit</unclear> for a <unclear>march</unclear>: he has received Commission from his Master King <em><reg orig="Lewis">Louis</reg></em> as chief Generalissimo, and his Majesty and the great Court Favourite Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, are both resolved to honour him with their own persons in the field, and to take a view of all the <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> Towns and Castles.</p>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received Intelligence, that on the <unclear>first instance</unclear> General <em>Middleton</em> had a general <reg orig="Renevouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Skilbo</em> in <em>Southerland</em>; and after the receipt of Orders from this experienced Generalissimo, part of the Army marched for the South Highlands, the rest were to continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. Commissions are gone forth in the Name of their Master <em>Charles</em>, to <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> the Army.</p>
<p>And so proportionably in every country where they have command. The Lord <em><reg orig="Seaford">Seaforth</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Mackoldwie"></reg></em> are suddenly expected <pb n="6" /> with their Levies also, which are not a few; and this Son of <em>Mars</em> Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> gives out, that he hath brought great <unclear>store</unclear> of Spanish Gold, lent by his Master the Emperor, from whom is expected a great Loan, &amp; many men, with plenty of the Lord knows what, which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother-in-law, which he had <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends, for his often failing in his promised coming amongst them. Sometimes they make desperate incursions, but pay often for their bold attempts. Nay, this is not all, but 'tis said they have more Arms and Ammunition landed. Of which, more in due time.</p>
<p>In the interim, true it is, that many horse and foot are expediting down, and Lieu. Col. <em><reg orig="Mitchil">Mitchell</reg></em> is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> with 9 Companies of Foot, six Troops of Horse, and a gallant party of resolute Dragoons, which are to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to <em>Brahan</em>; to which are added 4 Troops of horse, and 3 companies of foot, all which, are to keep a pass at Dinghil, and to engage the enemy, if possible.</p>
<p>Since the Prince of <em>Conti's</em> coming in to the King, and taking the <em>Oath of <reg orig="Allegeance">Allegiance</reg></em>, his Majesty hath created him Vice King of <em>Naples</em>; and a very sumptuous and admirable Equipage is making ready for <unclear><reg orig="solemnizing">solemnising</reg></unclear> the Journey.</p>
<p>The 14 instant, was acted at the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em> the stately Italian <em>Comedy</em>, called, the Nuptials of <em>Peleus</em> and <em>Thetis</em>, being a thing of incomparable invention, and no less costly. There was a mighty affluence of people, amongst the rest, came the disconsolate Queen, her three Sons, <em>Charles, James</em>, and <em>Henry</em>, and the Princess her Daughter.</p>
<p>The Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg></em> doth still remain at <em>Antwerp</em> close prisoner, and there is a strong Report that he is to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> prisoner into <em>Spain</em>, which is <em>malum omen</em>, for the obtaining that liberty which he was promised, when he was apprehended. <i>Ha! ha! This is <unclear>as</unclear> like to prove as bad to him, as is already the disposing of all his estate that hath already been found in that estate.</i></p>
<p>By Letters further from <em>Holland</em> it is certified, That the States have fully ratified the Agreement for Peace with great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> and alacrity of Spirit, and that they have sent a <unclear>Return</unclear> of Instrument to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>All which particulars, appears to be evident; for that the English Fleet hath weighed anchor from S. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em> Point, and now rides with their white Flags and Streamers in Stokes-Bay.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 22.</i></head>
<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, that the grand design of Rising doth appear every day more universal, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Scots flying out, but divers English; and amongst the rest three Clerks, belonging to the Court of Justice at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, divers <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> out of <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg>, and about 50 from <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> are gone to the Hills; from whence they descend down <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> into the <reg orig="Low-lands">Lowlands</reg>, and amongst others, the E. of Salkirk, second son to the Marq. of <em>Douglas</em>, started out the other day, and took from Boggehal 60 horse. Nay, this is not all, but divers other <reg orig="English-men">Englishmen</reg> are got to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> under the command of an <reg orig="Irish-man">Irishman</reg>: so that <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Army consists of at least 800 horse &amp; 3000 foot, and are resolved to engage us. Whereupon col. <em>Morgan</em> with 850 horse, &amp; 1600 foot is <unclear>advanced</unclear> against them, and a sudden engagement is expected.</p>
<p>Cap. <unclear>Staner,</unclear> and Cap. Smith, Commanders of the Tonnington &amp; <unclear>Plymouth</unclear> <reg orig="frigots">frigates</reg>, have taken an Holland East-India ship outward bound of 800 <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg>, laden with 350 <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg> of goods, and 4 Chests of Silver. The <unclear>Constant</unclear> Warwick hath brought in <unclear>Prize</unclear> Brest-man of war with 8 guns, and 50 men into Plymouth.</p>
<p>Ay! But to this welcome <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, we have received very sad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg>, that is, on <unclear>Tuesday last</unclear> Cap. Southwood, commander of the White-Raven going from <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> <unclear>Road</unclear> toward Newcastle, was set upon by a 11 Dutch men of war, boarded and taken, and the 13 instant a private man of war of ours, was <reg orig="accidently">accidentally</reg> blown up in <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> Road, and 6 men killed.</p>
<p>The Articles of peace are delivered to his Highness the Lord protector in a silver box, signed and sealed by the States of the United provinces, all concurring; and his Highness hath appointed the like to being <unclear>offered</unclear> here, and to pass the Great Seal of England; and then he will sign it by his sign <em>Manual</em>, which then is to be put into a silver box, and be sent to the <em>Hague</em>, and after signification of the States General receiving thereof, it will be published in both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>
<p>From <em><unclear>Warsaw</unclear></em> they write, that the <em>Muscovites</em> before they would grant the <em>Cossacks</em> their protection, obliged them to renounce the Amity of the <em>Tartarians</em>, that they should never acknowledge their old Polish Lords, nor wear any habit after the polish <unclear>made</unclear>, or wear any red or yellow boots, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> black ones; and that they shall <unclear>drink no</unclear> strong waters, play at cards, or take tobacco &amp;c.</p>
<p>The French in <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em> are in a <reg orig="pannick">panic</reg> fear that the K. of Spain will deliver into the hands of the Lord protector of England, the town of Dunkirk for security of forces which they fear shall be sent over to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, for the service of the K. of Spain, against the Crown of France.</p>
<p>The Q of Sweden hath written a letter to the French Ambassador concerning her <unclear><reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Resolution of</unclear> <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> Her Crown and Kingdom to Pr. <em>Charles</em>, which is conceived to be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for promoting of the princess of <em>Orange</em> the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots's</reg> sister.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>