<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout161">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 161
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>Strange News from <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>; Or a perfect Relation, how one <em>Hannah</em> a Maid living at <em>Hackney</em>, came thither to deliver a Message to the <em>Council</em>; and how she fell into a Trance, and continued in it two or three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; with her speech after she arose out of her Trance, concerning the Lord Protector and the Government of this Commonwealth, and her desires that his Highness and his Council would not conclude an ungodly peace with the Dutch. A Declaration of the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, concerning the payment of Prize money due to <reg orig="sea-men">seamen</reg>; with the humble address of the Officers and Soldiers of the Army, to <unclear><!-- 2 words --></unclear> the L. Protector their General. The Proceedings of the Highlanders, the coming of <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> and the L. <em><reg orig="Gourdon">Gordon</reg></em> to them, and their <unclear>surrendering</unclear> of <em><reg orig="Ruthen">Ruthven</reg></em> Castle; Also the landing of 17 Dutch ships, with 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>, 200 horse, besides Arms and Ammunition; and the K. of <em><reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg></em> resolution to leave the <em>French</em> Court; with variety of <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> intelligence.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 13 of <em>January</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 20 of <em>January</em>. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, <em>January</em> 13.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>This day Col. <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> Regiment of Foot, marched forth of London, with much <unclear>alacrity</unclear> and cheerfulness, towards Scotland, and Major Gen. <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, and Commissary Gen. <reg orig="Whalleys">Whalley's</reg> Regiments of Horse are likewise upon their march. The <reg orig="Lorainers">Lorrainers</reg> having made some Incursions into the Land of <unclear>Naze</unclear>. The States of Holland have caused Proclamation to be made throughout the Netherlands, that all men be in a posture of defence against the common Enemy. The Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> are landed; and the common talk is, that they have made an agreement with England, at which the <unclear>Jesuitical</unclear> party seems to be very much offended; but the generality of the <reg orig="peple">people</reg> do <pb n="1" /> exceedingly <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>, and the States have appointed a Day of Humiliation.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, January 7.</head>
<p>There is a young maid come to <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, who hath declared great and wonderful things touching this present Government, and <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that she comes from God, to declare a message to the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; she hath been sundry times in a Trace at one M. <reg orig="Roberts">Roberts'</reg> house, where many eminent persons frequented and upon her wakening, she declared, That the eternal God was her refuge, and that he was leading her through the green Pastures to his sacred Pavilion, &amp;c. But more of this hereafter.</p>
<head level="3"><i>An Order by the Commissioners of the Admiralty and the Navy, concerning the payment of Prize-money due to <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg> and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and their <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg>, that have served at Sea in this last <reg orig="years">year's</reg> Expedition.</i></head>
<head level="3"><em><unclear>January</unclear></em> 16, 1653.</head>
<head level="3">By the Commissioners for the Admiralty and Navy.</head>
<p><i>Upon consideration had of the Results of a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War, held aboard the <unclear>Swiftsure</unclear>, in the Fleet, December 1. 1653. concerning the Prize-money due to <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg> and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that have served at Sea in this last <reg orig="years">year's</reg> Expedition, It is hereby declared and Ordered as followeth.</i></p>
<p>1. That all Seamen and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that have served in the Fleet in the three last <reg orig="ingagements">engagements</reg> against the Dutch, and shall list themselves aboard any of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, at or before the last of March next, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have for their respective shares of prizes, twenty shillings,</p>
<p>2. That such as have been in two of the said Engagements, shall have thirteen shillings four pence.</p>
<p>3. That those who served <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in one of the said Engagements, shall have six shillings eight pence.</p>
<p>4. That all such Seamen and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> as have been disabled by <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg>, or wounds received in the service as also the widows of any such seamen or <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, slain in any of the said Engagements, shall have paid unto them their full shares of <reg orig="Prize money">Prize-money</reg>, <em>viz.</em> twenty shillings.</p>
<p>5. That such of the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> as are now again entertained in the army (having Tickets for their <reg orig="prize money">prize-money</reg>) do produce unto the said Commissioners, a certificate under the hand of the Captain, under which they now serve: as also a Copy of the last <unclear>Muster</unclear> Role <pb n="2" /> of the companies to which they respectively belong, or in default thereof, a certificate under the hand of the Muster-master, certifying their being in the service; whereupon order shall be given for the payments of shares of prizes due unto them.</p>
<p><i>John <unclear>Disbrowe</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>George Monck.</i></p>
<p><i>Robert Blake.</i></p>
<p><i><unclear>Vin: Geokin.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Stone.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Clerk.</i></p>
<p>From Alsatia, we hear that the Marshal de la Forte is come before <unclear>Bedfort</unclear>, where the lines are near finished, and the Ordnance within a <reg orig="days">day's</reg> journey of the place; <unclear>are</unclear> on the other side, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Town intends to <unclear><!-- 3 words --></unclear>, which to effect, and for his better subsistence he hath commanded all the <unclear>Country</unclear> adjacent to bring in their corn, and all other the like provisions which are necessary for him. The 15 instant the Provost and <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> of this City went to the <unclear><reg orig="Lawne">Lawn</reg></unclear>, where they had audience, the subject being about those monies due to the Citizens upon the <reg orig="Town house">Townhouse</reg>. The next day Prince Rupert arrived here from Nanz to this City. The <unclear>same day returned</unclear> here from Catalonia, the <unclear>Marquess da Plessis Bathere</unclear>, who hath been for many years an eminent Commander in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army: there is little news at present, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> great preparations are made here fore the solemnizing his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> consecration the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p>
<p>From Champagne we hear that the <unclear>Irish</unclear> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> who were at St. <unclear><reg orig="Mepaholds">Mepahold's</reg></unclear>, are gone from thence to Chaalens; there remaining no more but those companies of Switzers, who were there at the reduction with the Regiment of Dambrole, and <unclear>six</unclear> companies more who upon agreement between the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and the Townsmen are jointly to have the guard of the City, there being an equal number of town with the <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, to watch day and night: Those of Clermont have not of late made many inroads the reason we <reg orig="here">hear</reg> is because many desert the place.</p>
<p>General Blake, and General <reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg> are now at <reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg>, General Pen in the <unclear>Swiftsure</unclear>, doth ride as Admiral of the fleet. The Fleet is at Spice head, not far from Portsmouth. Some part of them are sent out to ply between Portland and the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, and over upon the Coast of France, to suppress the French <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg>, and those of Holland who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to them.</p>
<p>The Diet is not yet concluded in Germany, there being new differences between the Prince Elector and his Uncle, about the enjoying of some Lands, which each pretend to be theirs.</p>
<p>The Dutch to their late griefs have wisely added one day of solemn sorrow, and this (on the beginning of the last week) was observed in a day of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Humiliation to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg>, or divert the anger of the Almighty. Their preparations at sea are great: Nothing is yet done as to the Answer which the Deputies brought from England, and nothing can be done till there be a general meeting of all their States, but it appears their inclinations are for war: <unclear>But</unclear> nothing doth more startle them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the celerity, <unclear>industry</unclear>, and magnanimous resolution of the English.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Jan, 16</head>
<p>This day produced intelligence from Whitehall which certified, That there came thither one <em>Hannah</em> a Maid that lives at Hackney near the City of London, the same that was formerly at Dunbar, a Member of Mr. John <reg orig="Simpsons">Simpson's</reg> Church (as is said) who lives at one Mr. <reg orig="Roberts">Roberts'</reg>, an <unclear>Ordinary</unclear> in Whitehall; to whom many hundreds daily come, to see and hear, who hath now been there about a fortnight: Those who look to her, and use to be with her, say, She <unclear><reg orig="naither">neither</reg></unclear> eateth nor drinketh, save <reg orig="onley">only</reg> sometimes a <unclear><reg orig="Tost">Toast</reg></unclear> and drink, and that she is in a Trances, and some say, that what she doth is by a mighty inspiration: others say, they suppose her to be of a troubled mind, and people flocking to her as they do, causeth her to continue this way; and some say worse: so everyone gives their opinion as they please. But this is visible to those that see and hear her. She is well in flesh and face, and seemingly lusty and strong; speaks to <reg orig="no body">nobody</reg>, but they that are about her <unclear>call it</unclear> lying in a Trance; she lies as if she were continually asleep, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> when she prays, sings, or drinks and eats the <reg orig="Tost">Toast</reg>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> she <reg orig="breaths">breathes</reg>, and sometimes she turns herself in her bed, and sometimes covers <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, but most often others, some say, doth it. In the afternoon (most commonly) every day she prays and sings, beginning about that <unclear>usual</unclear> time that people have dined, and continues sometimes two or three hours, sometimes four or five hours, never ceasing. Sometimes she prays an hour, sometimes two hours, and then sings two Hymns in two several Tunes, and prayeth again, and sometimes sings again. Her prayers are in exceedingly good method and order, good language, and such as indeed all that come do much admire what they hear from her, excellent words, and well placed, such as are not ordinary. Her matter is various, full of variety; for the Lord Protector, that God would keep him close to himself, as he hath hitherto, so still to have his heart set upon the things of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg>, not to be vain, nor regard earthly pomp and pleasure, and things <unclear>below</unclear>; but the things of God and people, that he may be delivered from carnal <reg orig="Councels">Counsels</reg>, and being <unclear>seduced</unclear> to please the men of the world, and those that seek <reg orig="unrighteousnesse">unrighteousness</reg>, that he may not leave the <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg> of the Godly, to hearken to those who are worldly wise, and earthly Politicians, but wise in the <reg orig="Wisdome">Wisdom</reg> of God. That the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, whom God hath made instrumental to overcome the enemy without, and in the world, may not be overcome of their inward spiritual enemies, to provoke God to lay them aside, and make use of others in the perfecting of that work, in which God hath so far employed them. That the Merchants of this Nation would not so far seek and mind their profit by Trade at Sea, to <unclear>fill</unclear> their own <reg orig="Ware-houses">Warehouses</reg> and Bags, and be great in the world, as thereby to provoke an ungodly and wicked peace with the Dutch, to the dishonour of God, and <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> of the carrying on of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> work. That the people of God may not, as some of them have done, revile and scandalize the Lord Protector behind his back, but to deal plainly with him. With divers other excellent things, which I want room to insert.</p> <pb n="4" />
<head level="3">Tuesday January, 17.</head>
<head level="3"><i>To his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. Our Lord General.</i></head>
<head level="3"><i>The humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army.</i></head>
<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services wherein through the blessing of God upon the vigilancy and <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, we have in some measure been instrumental in our places to free the Commonwealth from its enemies: So we now cannot but above all worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations after all the shakings which have been in the midst of us, set up upon its true and proper Basis and Foundations, and thereby brought into a harbour of rest and safety. The sense whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your Highness and the whole Nation at this time, when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment by inclining you to accept of the Government and Protection of this Commonwealth; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the people, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We judge it highly incumbent upon us to make our humble <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> unto you, and to declare that we shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be obedient unto you in the performance of your great Trust; but in our places most faithfully and diligently to the hazard of our lives, and whatsoever is near and dear unto us be serviceable unto you in the Station God hath placed you against all opposition: <unclear>Not</unclear> doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; So you will to the utmost of your power and <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> lay forth your <unclear>self for</unclear> the glory of God, and the good of this people amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take this <reg orig="boldnesse">boldness</reg>, most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, most especially to spread the wing of your protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, which you continuing to do. We are confident their Father which is in heaven, will be unto you a Buckler and a Shield and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> most humble and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servants.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Wednesday January 11.</head>
<p>From Deal thus. The fleet is now gone Westward from the Downs plying too and again upon the Road betwixt England and the coast of France. Many ships are going from England to the Barbadoes and other parts, I hope they shall have good convoys with them.</p>
<p>Scilly Jan. 2. The Elias <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come safe into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, and brought us six months pay which we were in, other news this place affords not.</p>
<p>By Letters from <em>Lime</em>: we hear by a Barque come from Britanis, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroon">Picaroon</reg> near <unclear>Ushant</unclear>, have him chase, and followed so close, that he forced him to run aground on the nether side of the Bay of <unclear>Camaret</unclear>, and by reason of his shooting hard at him made the Country to come down to the <reg orig="water side">waterside</reg>; it happened that some shot did make execution on the shore, there being four killed and wounded; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the Country being all <unclear><reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg></unclear> thereby, could not fetch her off; but ours put to sea again, to clear from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>
<p>By several other Letters from Scotland, which contracted speak to this effect: The Highlanders continue their stealing and plundering of their own Countrymen that will not rise with them, or pay the Contribution money that they lay upon them, though I am confident many have not <reg orig="wherewithall">wherewithal</reg> to submit, paying likewise their <reg orig="Assessements">Assessments</reg> for the maintenance of the English Army: but when Major General <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, Commissary General <reg orig="Whaleys">Whalley's</reg> Regiments of Horse, with Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> regiment of Foot, (which we <unclear>hear</unclear> are upon their march) are come into us, we doubt not but to send this Heathenish and plundering enemy, so far back into the Highlands, as that they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <unclear>not</unclear> dare to approach the Lowlands, whereby to do the inhabitants any considerable prejudice.</p>
<p>How the Highlanders are able to keep horse and man, is <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be imagined, all their dependence being upon <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, and his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> with the Dutch for money and Arms; but a peace with Holland (which we hear is in a very probable way for a very speedy conclusion) disperses them to their several mountainous habitations, without ever drawing the sword against them, and then the Lords <pb n="6" /> and Chieftains amongst them may expect a liberal reward of Justice for doing their Master such rebellious service, which hath been, <unclear>and is</unclear> destructive to the generality of Scotland, that a few <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> continuance will bring them to the sad condition of the Irish, that have been forced to eat the <reg orig="corps">corpses</reg> of their deceased friends after many days interment; yet are not the people of Scotland very much to be <reg orig="pittied">pitied</reg> in regard they will <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> give notice to any of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> when any party of the enemy marcheth through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might be the better preserved from their violence and cruelty, <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather to be willingly destroyed by them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> be treacherous (as they call it) to their own <reg orig="Countrey men">Countrymen</reg>: Some Arms they pretend are lately landed for the enemy in Scotland, but this is more to encourage their forced and naked party, <reg orig="then">than</reg> otherwise considerable.</p>
<p>Paris Jan. 17. 1654. By Letters from Perpignan, we hear that the Spanish army are quartered in and about Giron, although the plague doth rage much there still; one party is gone about Palamas, and the Field Marshal de Serra hath an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> Order from Don John d'Austrin, to take care that the country be not oppressed by the quartering of the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, but to keep them in a strict discipline.</p>
<p>There is a story lately printed in Spanish, whether it was penned for truth, or <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for delight I leave to the belief or credit of such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hear of it, and the thing is briefly this.</p>
<p>Upon a day dedicated by the Turks unto <em>Mahomet</em>, there was a great meeting at the Church or Temple called <em><reg orig="Mecha">Mecca</reg></em> where his Tomb or iron Chest did hang at the top or roof of that building, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of a Loadstone which was fixed there, and when the people were in the midst of their heathenish <unclear>worship</unclear> or adoration, in an instant the said Chest did fall down to the ground, and (if the story lie not) the ground forthwith opened and received it into the bowels of the earth in the sight of many hundred spectators, and out of the same place came flashes of fire, and a great smoke for the space of one quarter of an hour, after which the ground closed up again.</p>
<p>The loss which the Dutch received by the late fire and Tempest is said to be greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> was at first reported, both in houses, and ships; the hearts of the people being exceedingly overwhelmed with sadness at this desolation.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> Jan. 19.</head>
<p>Came intelligence from Paris that the K. with the Peers of France, have sentenced the Prince of Conde, that if he came not in within a <reg orig="moneths">month's</reg> time, his estate should be confiscated. The Pope hath sent an extraordinary <unclear>Courier</unclear> with Letters pressing his Majesty, to conclude a general peace with Spain, the like he hath sent to the Spanish Court, what this may produce time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>. Paris <unclear><reg orig="swels">swells</reg></unclear> with <reg orig="rumors">rumours</reg>, some report that one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> daughters is to be married to the Duke d'Enguzen, son to the Prince of Conde, others that he is to be bestowed on one of the Duke of <reg orig="Orleans">Orlean's</reg> daughters; and that the Queen of Sweden is to be married to the King of the Romans, son to the Emperor of Germany, and that the King of Scots intends to leave France and journey thither. About 50 or 60 Protestants were drowned returning from <unclear>Charenton</unclear> Church, among whom were two sons of the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquess</reg> de <unclear>Clerambaugh</unclear>, and the Chancellor of <reg orig="Polands">Poland's</reg> son. Boreel the Dutch <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> declares that the peace is agreed upon betwixt England and Holland, and the Articles concluded on and <unclear>assented</unclear> to on both sides, and that he hath received Letters of the 14 instant new <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, which confirm it.</p>
<p>Yesterday, <em>Hannah</em> the maid of Hackney, after she had lain certain days in her trance, as is formerly related, arose out of her bed, and went home very lustily.</p>
<p>Take here the <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of a Letter from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> in Scotland.</p>
<p><i>SIR, <em>Kenmore, <reg orig="Mac Aldore">MacAldore</reg></em>, and about 700 <unclear><!-- 1 character --></unclear> are about <reg orig="Straths-pey">Strathspey</reg>, and expect <em><reg orig="Seaforths">Seaforth's</reg></em> party to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> them, but Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath drawn out a party to engage them if possible they can be drawn from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. Young <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em>, and the Lord <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Gourdon">Gordon</reg></em> is gone unto them, and they proceed vigorously with their <unclear>levies</unclear>; but there hath been a difference between <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em> and <unclear>the</unclear> Lord <em><reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg></em>, which hath been some <unclear>obstructions</unclear>. They marched near <reg orig="Ruthen">Ruthven</reg> Castle, and sent in a Summons to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, telling him, that all Scotland was up in arms, and many were come out of England to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; but he returned a very noble and resolute answer. Our supplies came very seasonably out of England; and here came news this day from Aberdeen, that there is landed in the North 17 Dutch ships, who have brought over great store of Arms and Ammunition, 200 horse, and 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>; but we have no <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of it from any in <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> in those parts, which makes us doubt the certainty thereof.</i></p>
<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, Jan. 7.</p>
<p>The Hector hath sent a ship into Dartmouth, which hath in her 3000 <unclear>Cheeses</unclear>. The ship is of Amsterdam, and took in lading at the Elve. There is a private man of War hath brought in a ship of Rotterdam, laden with Herrings, and Holland Cheeses, and about 10 <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of Pepper, and Cloves.</p>
<p>The Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother is by an Order from the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, removed back from the Tower to Newgate: But I hear not that he hath been brought before the Bench.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, PRINTED by R. WOOD, 1654.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>