<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout156">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 156
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p><i><unclear>The Reasons</unclear> of the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> dissolution, and the Proceedings of His <unclear>Excellence and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of</unclear> Officers thereupon, with a most excellent and pious <unclear>Speech <!-- 1 word --> by the Lord General</unclear>, concerning the <unclear>composure</unclear> and <unclear>settlement of the affairs of this distracted Nation.</unclear> The D. of York chosen by <unclear>the Highlanders to be their</unclear> Commander in chief, <unclear>their</unclear> coming near <unclear><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, and col. <reg orig="Lilburn's">Lilburne's</reg> forcing them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. A Special Order</unclear> of the <unclear><reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <!-- half a line--> and the preventing of all <!-- almost 1 line --> on Tuesday last <!-- almost 2 lines --> also an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg></unclear> of the <unclear><!--half a line--></unclear> in England and Wales, for <unclear><!--half a line--> belonging</unclear> to this <unclear>Commonwealth <!-- approx. 3 words --> the taking of several French and Dutch Prizes, and the blowing up of the Sussex <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> at Portsmouth.</unclear></i></p>
<hr />
<p><unclear>From <em>Friday</em> the 9 of <em>Decemb.</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 16 of <em>December.</em>. 1653.</unclear></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, Decemb. 9.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p><unclear>The last Letters from <!-- 1 word --> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>; That the <!-- 3 words --> men of War, hath sent into the Harbour a  ship belonging to Amsterdam laden with <!-- 1 word --> and Sugar, but then 300 <!-- 1 word -->; and Captain <!-- 1 word --> Commander of the <em>Bristol</em>, which lies in the mouth of the Channel, hath <!-- 1 word --> two ships in <!-- approx. 10 words --> 14 Guns the other 100. <!-- approx. 2 words --> Sugar and <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, to a great value. And a French man was brought in on the <!-- -2 words -->, laden with 22 <!-- 1 word --> of <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg>, and <!-- 2 words -->. There hath likewise <!-- 1 word --> two very sad accidents, the gallant <!-- 1 word --> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> was blown</unclear> up by her own powder, and about 50 <unclear>men; And 2 <!-- 2 words --> Ship boat sunk</unclear> with about 30 men and women, 16 <unclear>were saved, the rest perished in the Sea.</unclear></p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>Yesterday was published in print the Act for the <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> (<reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for an <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> at the rate of one hundred and twenty thousand pounds by the <reg orig="Moneth">Month</reg> for 6 months, from the 25 of Decemb 1653. to the 24 of June next ensuing, towards the maintenance of the <unclear>Armies</unclear> and Navies of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>) the several Rates <unclear>the Counties assessed</unclear> at, are as followeth:</i></p>
<p><unclear>Upon</unclear> the County of <em>Bedford</em>, the sum of 1600 <em>l.</em></p>
<p><unclear>The county</unclear> of <em>Berks 1066 l. 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p><unclear>The county of <em>Buckingham. 2200 l.</em></unclear></p>
<p>The <unclear>county of <em>Cambridge</em></unclear> one thousand and eight hundred four<unclear><!-- 5 characters --></unclear> and ten <em>l.</em></p>
<p>The Isle of <unclear><em>Ely 63 l.</em></unclear></p>
<p>The county of <unclear><em>Chester 1320 l.</em></unclear></p>
<p>The city and county of the city of <em>Chester, 146 l. 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg> 2800 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Cumberland 185 l. 2 s. 8 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Derby 1600 l.</em>	</p>
<p>The county of <em>Devon 5149 l. 6 s. 8 d.</em></p>
<p>The city and county of the city of <em><unclear>Exon</unclear> 184 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Dorset 2248 l. 6 s. 8 d.</em></p>
<p>The Town and County of <em><reg orig="Pool">Poole</reg> 18 l. 6 s. 8 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Durham 263 l. 10 s. 2 d.</em> <reg orig="half-peny">half-penny</reg>.</p>
<p>The county of <em>York</em>, with the city and county of the city of <em>York, 5217 l. 6 s. 8 d.</em></p>
<p>The Town and county of <em>Kingston</em> upon <em>Hull 116 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Essex <unclear>600 l</unclear></em></p>
<p>The county of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg> 2888 l.</em></p>
<p>The city and county of the city of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg> 278 l. 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Hereford 2000 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Hartford 2400 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Huntington 166 l. 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Kent</em>, with the city and county of <em>Canterbury, 6266 l. 13 s 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Lancaster 1600 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Leicester, 1866 l 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Lincoln</em>, with the city &amp; county of Lincoln, <em>4666 l 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The city of London, 800 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Middlesex</em>, with the city and liberty of <em>Westminster, 3066 l. 13 s. 4 d.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Monmouth 800 l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Northampton <unclear>2400</unclear> l.</em></p>
<p>The county of <em>Nottingham</em> 1548 l. 8 s.</p>
<p>The Town and County of <em><reg orig="Notingham">Nottingham</reg></em>, 51 l. 12 s.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Norfolk</em>, 6213 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The city and county of the city of <em>Norwich</em>, 320 l.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Northumberland</em>, 308 l. 11 s. <reg orig="peny">penny</reg> <reg orig="half-peny">half-penny</reg></p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>The town of <em>Newcastle</em>, <unclear>63 l.</unclear></p>
<p>The county of <unclear><em>Oxen, 1933 l. 6 s.</em></unclear> 3 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Rutland,</em> 466 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Salop</em> <unclear>1266</unclear> l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Stafford</em>, with the city of <em>Lichfield</em>, 1600 l:</p>
<p>The county of <unclear><em>Somerset</em></unclear>, 4666 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The city and county of the city of <em>Bristol</em>, 293 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Southampton</em>, with the town and county of <em>Southhampton</em>, 3466 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Suffolk</em> 6266 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The county of <em>Surrey</em>, 2683 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The <unclear>Borough of Southwark</unclear>, 316 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <unclear>county of Sussex</unclear> 3266 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <unclear>county of <em>Warwick</em></unclear>, with the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> and <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> of <em>Coventry</em>, <unclear>2133 l.</unclear> 6 s. 8 d,</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Worcester, with the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> and <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> of Worcester, 2133 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Wilts, 3333 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Westmerland, 126 l. 16 s.</p>
<p>The Isle of Anglesey, 232 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Brecknock, 620 l.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Cardigan, 732 l.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Carmarthen, 604 l.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of <reg orig="Carnarvan">Carnarvon</reg>, 346 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Denbigh, 466 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Flint, <unclear>230</unclear> l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of Glamorgan, 786 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="countie">county</reg> of <reg orig="Merionesh">Merioneth</reg>, 213 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
<p>The county of Montgomery, 506 l. 13 s. 4 d.</p>
<p>The county of Pembroke, 696 l.</p>
<p>The county of Radnor, 436 l.</p>
<p>The Town of <unclear>Haveriorer</unclear> West, 25 l.</p>
<p>The Town of Berwick, 10 l.</p>
<p><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Novemb. 15. <i>S.V. From hence little of News, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that <unclear>some</unclear> five or six days ago, there passed through this city a Swedish Earl, called Earl of <unclear>Donau</unclear>, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from Sweden, and being sent by the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Majesty for Holland, who as is said, carries some 21 Articles along with him; <unclear>whereupon</unclear> he is to demand the States of <reg orig="Hollands">Holland's</reg> sudden and present <unclear>Resolution, and</unclear> so with all possible speed return homeward: what the contents of <unclear>such articles</unclear> may be, is unknown. The Magistrate here hath concluded in their <unclear>Senate</unclear> to take on some six ships more, besides these two they have <unclear><!-- approx. 4 words --></unclear>; and having provided them with men and guns, and other necessities <pb n="3" /> to send them down at the mouth of the River, to keep the same <unclear>safe</unclear> from all violation and hostility, but the Works go on very slowly.</i></p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> Decemb. 10.</head>
<p>From Scotland thus. The Highlanders give out that the Duke of York is to come from France to be their Commander in chief for his brother the Scots King. They have listed 6 or 7000 horse and foot; they have by plunder gotten horse, and most of the horse and foot have Arms, but not <unclear>armours</unclear> save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the chief Officers. They break open houses in the night, where contribution is refused to them, and are resolved to force it with much violence. And the last week were so bold, in the night, as to come within half a mile of this place, with a Troop of horse, and plundered some houses, and then rid away again. They have had 150 horse from Holland transported to them; which are to be charging horses for their Leaders. They <unclear><reg orig="preste">pressed</reg></unclear> the <unclear>Scots to</unclear> rise, but divers ran away. They had thoughts to storm Aberdeen and <reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg>, but they go not on upon that design.</p>
<p>They <unclear>seduce</unclear> many to run away with their Masters horses to them, upon <unclear>promises of share of their plunder</unclear>, which is their great design: So that they <unclear><!-- 1 word --> the most <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg>, <!-- 1 word --> rabble that hath gathered all these <!-- 1 word --> and <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> few Gentry that are with them, are such <!-- approx. 5 words --> that they are <!-- 2 words --> without <!-- half a line --></unclear></p>
<p><unclear>The enemy <!-- almost 1 line --></unclear> land are <unclear><reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> of being plundered <!-- half a line --> in large quarters upon the Lowlands. <!-- half a line --></unclear> to regain the Northern <unclear><reg orig="garisons">garrisons</reg> from <!-- half a line --></unclear>der upon our <unclear>borders will <!-- 1 word --> join with the Highlanders <!-- 1 word -->, for</unclear> fear they carry their <unclear>plunder away from them <!-- 3 words --></unclear> for that trade is the chief <unclear><!-- 6 characters --> they have. The <!-- 3 words --></unclear> old Moss Troopers are <unclear>eminent with them.</unclear></p>
<head level="3"><unclear><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Decemb. 12.</unclear></head>
<p>It being moved in the <unclear><!-- 2 words --> day. <!-- 5 characters --> the sitting of this Parliament any longer as <!-- 1 word --> concerned will not be for the <reg orig="goode">good</reg> of the</unclear> <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; and <unclear>that <!-- approx. 3 words --> to <!-- 1 word --> up</unclear> unto the Lord General <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> the <unclear><!-- 1 word --> which they received</unclear> from him; and that <unclear>motion being seconded by several other members</unclear>, the House rose, and the Speaker with many of the Members of <pb n="4" /> the House departed out of the House to Whitehall; where they being the greater number of the Members sitting in Parliament, did by a writing under their hands resign unto his Excellency their said powers, and Master Speaker attended with the Members, did present the same unto his Excellency accordingly. The further particulars (in reference unto the <unclear>true</unclear> Narration of this business) I shall present you with towards the conclusion.</p>
<head level="3">Tuesday Decemb. 13.</head>
<head level="3"><!-- need code for  which appears here --> By the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of STATE.</head>
<p><i>The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State taking notice of the Tumultuous and Barbarous actings at the new Exchange in the Strand in the County of Middlesex, upon the 21 and 22 of Novemb. last past, the same being accompanied with the drawing of Swords, discharging of Pistols, and such other high <reg orig="misdemeanors">misdemeanours</reg> as are <reg orig="fearce">fierce</reg> to be <reg orig="paralleld">paralleled</reg> by the actings of any persons living under the protection of a civil Government; and which, in the effects thereof, <unclear>produced not</unclear> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a very great and notorious Violation of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, but also the <reg orig="murthering">murdering</reg> of one, and the assaulting, wounding, and affrighting of many other of the People of this Nation, pursuing their ordinary callings and occasions: And for as much as the Exchange is a place of <unclear><reg orig="publick">public</reg> <!-- 6 characters --></unclear> and Trade, The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have therefore thought it necessary hereby to <unclear>declare</unclear> their resentment of those proceedings, and their just Displeasure <unclear>against</unclear> the same. And as they intend vigorously to prosecute the Offenders, <unclear>so to the intent the like</unclear> evils may be better prevented in time to come, They <unclear>do hereby <!-- 1 word --> require</unclear> and charge, That no person or persons, of what <unclear>quality <!-- approx. 2 words --></unclear>, at the said Exchange, or any other like <reg orig="publick">public</reg> place, to <unclear><!-- approx. 2 words --></unclear>, or abet, any tumultuous meetings, or hazard a breach of <unclear><!-- 1 word --> the Peace, by drawing</unclear> there, or in any other such place, any Sword or <unclear><!-- 1 word --> weapon,  discharging, presenting</unclear> or bearing <unclear>any</unclear> Gun or <unclear>Pistol</unclear>, or firing <unclear><!-- approx. 3 words --></unclear>, or in any otherwise whatsoever. Of <unclear>which command, it will be expected</unclear> that all persons whatsoever take notice, and a <unclear><!-- 2 words --> accordingly,</unclear> upon <unclear>peril of being</unclear> reputed and <unclear>dealt withal</unclear> as <unclear>disturbers of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg></unclear> Peace, whereof a very strict <unclear>account <!-- 1 word --> be</unclear> taken: And all Justices of the Peace, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, <unclear>are required carefully</unclear> to <unclear>perform their</unclear> duties <reg orig="in">on</reg> this behalf; as also to use their <unclear>utmost endeavours to</unclear> prevent and <unclear>restrain</unclear> all immodest and <unclear>unhandsome demeanours of such as shall <reg orig="refere">refer</reg> to the said</unclear> Exchange, that so no just cause or offence be given to sober minds, nor any thing there acted <reg orig="dishonorable">dishonourable</reg> to Religion, or the Nation.</i></p>
<p><i>Signed, <em>Jo. Thurloe</em>, <unclear>Sec.</unclear></i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<p>The <unclear>Letters from Scotland, say that the English <!-- 2 words --> are very active there, yet as vigilant as they are, the Highlanders on the one hand, and</unclear> the Moss Troopers on the <unclear>other, do much mischief in the very heart of the</unclear> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg> is <unclear>expected to <!-- 2 words --> towards  St. <reg orig="Johnstones">Johnston's</reg>,</unclear> and then let those Desperadoes look to themselves, <unclear>which have the business to attempt the fortifying</unclear> of themselves <unclear>betwixt that and <!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>The English fleet being sent into the Downs,</unclear> (to a considerable number) it is <unclear>thought they will <!-- 1 word --> upon some speedy <!-- 1 word -->; but the Dutch Fleet not being out at <!-- half a line --></unclear>) is the clearing of the coast of <unclear><!-- half a line --> both North and West.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>The House this day <!-- 1 words  --> the debate upon</unclear> the Report made from the <unclear>Committee <!-- half a line --> 1. That it be represented to the Parliament as the best way <!-- approx. 5 words --> and</unclear> scandalous Ministers; that <unclear><!-- half a line --> all the Counties divided into six Circuits (besides London and Middlesex, which I <!-- 1 word --> in my last) Commissioners into each Circuit, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg></unclear> with four or six in every County (and each Riding in Yorkshire to be as a County) and that in every County the said persons or five of them (two of the Commissioners sent from hence being <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> present) be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to eject all Ministers (of that Country) that are not of good behaviour and holy in conversation, or that are not apt and able to teach, or in teaching hold <unclear>not</unclear> forth the <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> world; or be not diligent; or labour not in the Word and Doctrine, or be greedy of filthy lucre: And be also <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to settle Godly and able persons to preach the Gospel in <unclear>all void</unclear> places, and to unite two or three Parishes together, so that none be above three miles from the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> meeting place. 2. That <unclear>it be presented to the Parliament, That</unclear> Dr. Arrowsmith, Col. Goff, <unclear>Maj <!-- 4 characters -->, Mr. John Owen. Mr Tho</unclear> Goodwyn, Mr. Ben of <unclear>Dorchester, Mr. <!-- 2 words --></unclear>, Mr. Lockier, Mr. Caryl, Mr. <unclear>Stephen Marshel, Mr. <!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear>, Mr. Turner, Mr. Tomes, Mr. <unclear><!-- 2 words -->, Mr. <!-- 7 characters --></unclear>, Mr. <unclear>Jessey</unclear>, Mr. Arthur <unclear>Barnardiston, Mr. William Greenind, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg></unclear> Campfield, Mr. Dyke, Mr. <unclear><!-- 8 characters --> may be sent Commissioners</unclear> by three in a Circuit, for <unclear>ejecting and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Ministers</unclear>, according to the Rules prescribed. 3. That all <unclear>such aware or shall</unclear> be approved for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers of the Gospel in the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Meeting-places, shall have and enjoy the maintenance already <unclear><!-- 6 characters --></unclear> by Law, and such other <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> as the <unclear>Parliament already hath</unclear> appointed, or hereafter shall appoint: And that where any scruple payment of <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>, the three next <pb n="6" /> Justices of the Peace, or two of them, and by the Oaths of <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> witnesses, shall duly apportion the value of the said <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>, to be paid either in Money or Land, by them to be set out according to the said value, to be held and <reg orig="enjoied">enjoyed</reg> by him that was to have the said Tithes; and in case such approved value be not duly paid or <reg orig="injoied">enjoyed</reg> according to the Order of the said Justices, the <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg> shall be paid in kind; and shall be recovered in any Court of Record. 4. That upon hearing and considering what hath been offered to the Committee touching propriety in <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>, <unclear>of</unclear> Incumbents, Rectors, Possessors of Donatives or propriate <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>. It is the opinion of this Committee, and resolved to be reported to the Parliament: That the said persons have a legal propriety in <reg orig="Tythes">Tithes</reg>. The House having spent several days in debate of the whole report, and especially of the first of the hour parts thereof; and the Question being put, That this house doth agree with the first Clause of the Report, it passed in the Negative.</p>
<head level="3">Wednesday Decemb. 14.</head>
<p><i>From <unclear>Legorn the 28 of</unclear> November, stilo novo.</i> Three days since a ship of <unclear><reg orig="Marseillis">Marseilles</reg></unclear> bound for Smyrna with good store of money and other rich goods being come to an anchor near this place under the command of one of our Castles, was set upon by a Dutch man of war, who had seized on her had not our Castle with her great <reg orig="gunnes">guns</reg> forced him away: We hear also that the Turks have lately taken two ships belonging to Marseilles, who were laden with provision and some ammunitions bound to relieve the Venetian Army in Candia.</p>
<p><i>Linlithgow Decemb. 3</i> Upon the <reg orig="enemies">enemies'</reg> removal from Loughern they left 30 or 40 plundering <unclear>Rogues</unclear> that are sometimes in <unclear>those</unclear> parts towards Lough Tar, and the <unclear>borders</unclear> of Atholl: The Earl of Atholl had got some men to appear for the encouragement of their late <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, who would go no further with him but returned to their homes, and have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> never to follow his Lordship more in <unclear>such</unclear> courses: The Gentry of the Country say, that Lord shall gang <unclear>his</unclear> own gate for them, in regard his entrance into this <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was without the advice of any of his solid friends, and the chief ground was the confidence he had that 6000 foot, and 4000 horse, would speedily land in the North with monies and other <reg orig="matterials">materials</reg> from the Dutch: Most of his Tenants refuse to pay him any rent, which much startleth him and the Gentlemen with him in most parts also, men do run <unclear>away</unclear> faster from them <reg orig="then">than</reg> they raise them.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, Decemb. 15.</i></head>
<p>The last Letters from Scotland <unclear>assure us, That</unclear> the insolence of the Highlanders, forced our <unclear>Commander in chief (though the weather was unreasonable) to march from <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> against them; but as  <!-- 1 word --> as he appeared,</unclear> they quitted their station, and <unclear><!-- 2 words --> towards <!-- 1 word -->, not daring to stand a shot, or strike one <reg orig="stroak">stroke</reg>. They increase their numbers <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> in the Highlands, all <!-- half a line --> They continue their excursions still, and expect <!-- half a line --> the Lowlands. They have attempted to <!-- half a line -->, but they will be to <!-- half a line --> amongst them, but they expect <!-- half a line --> Guards here <!-- three-quarters of a line -->, and so vanished, with <!-- 1 word --> occasion to give <!-- 2 words --></unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>Since the Parl. were pleased to put a period to their given authority, by resigning back their power; there hath been very many deliberations for a <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the government of this Nation in <!-- approx. 2 words --> and his Excellency the Lord General <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> and his Council of Officers being <!-- 1 word -->; he made a most excellent, wise, gracious, and <!-- 1 word --> speech <!-- 1 word --> Religion towards God prudence towards <!-- half a line --> distracted Nation: some things were transacted in order to <!-- 3 words -->, and sweet composure; the union of all <!-- 3 words --> Lord is much desired that so we <!-- 2 words --> down comfortably <!-- 1 word --> a safe and well grounded peace and there is a probability of a peace with the Dutch.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>General <reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg> is gone for the Downs, where the <!-- 1 word --> of the ships appointed of <!-- 2 words --> Guard, <!-- 4 words --></unclear></p>
<p><unclear>The Portugal <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> <!-- 2 words --> (<!-- 3 words --> coming to visit him on Tuesday night last, <!-- half a line --> in <reg orig="womens">women's</reg> <!-- 1 word -->) but by the in <!-- 1 word -->of the Keepers <!-- 3 words --> Wednesday night, and ordered to be put into the Dungeon of the <!-- 2 words -->, for <!-- 3 words --> his <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg></unclear>.</p>
<hr />
<p><unclear>There is published five new plays in one <reg orig="vollum">volume</reg>, <i>viz. The <!-- 3 words --> matches; The <!-- 6 characters -->, The <reg orig="Course">Coarse</reg> Beggar; The <!-- 3 words --></i>: all written by Richard Brown. <i>A Collection of these excellent <!-- 1 word --> to several <!-- approx. 7 characters --> of <!-- 1 word --></i>: written by John <!-- 6 words -->. Likewise <i>a Poem <reg orig="caled">called </reg> the <reg orig="Shepherds">Shepherd's</reg> Oracles, delivered in <!-- 2 words --></i> by <i>Francis Quarls. And the Poems, of John Donne <!-- 3 words --> St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></i> London; <i>With Elegies on the <reg orig="Authors">Author's</reg> death</i> to which is added divers <!-- 1 word --> under his own hand never before printed. All which are to be sold by <em>John Sweeting</em>, at the Angel in Popes-Head Alley.</unclear></p>
<hr />
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, Printed by R. WOOD, 1653.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>