<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout159">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 159
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The Proposals and Demands of his <em>Highness</em> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, to the <em>Lord Ambassadors</em> from the <em>States of Holland</em>, on <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> last at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, upon their great Conference and Treaty, touching the Dominion of the Sea, and the <unclear><reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg></unclear> of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>. With their <em><reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg></em> Answer thereunto; And their departure from <em>London</em> on Tuesday night last. The setting forth of the two great Fleets from <em>Denmark</em> and <em>Holland</em>; the landing of 500 piece of Canon from <em>Sweden</em>; and great store of Arms and Ammunition sent from most parts of Christendom. The advancing of the <em>English Fleet</em> against them; and the new Oath and Engagement to be taken and subscribed by all the forces both by <em>Sea</em> and <em>Land</em>. The arrival of the <em>Lord Ambassador Whitlock</em> at the Court of Sweden; and her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> gracious <unclear>Resolution.</unclear> The coming up of the Highlanders within ten miles of <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and the cruel murder, &amp; bloody execution done up on the English.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 30 of <em>December</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 6 of <em>January</em>. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, Decemb. 30.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The last Letters from Holland <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> us, That the whole <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> is full of discourses, concerning the Treaty, and that the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> is come to the Hague, and earnestly <unclear><reg orig="solicites">solicits</reg></unclear> the <unclear>States</unclear> in the name of her Majesty, that there may be a fair <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> betwixt England and Holland; But the French Agent Monsieur <unclear><em>Chanu</em></unclear>, <reg orig="solicites">solicits</reg> for a compliance betwixt them and his Master the King of France; <unclear><reg orig="awd">and</reg></unclear> offers, if they will break the Truce with Spain, four millions yearly for the defraying of the charges of the War, and 6000 men, besides 30 good ships to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Dutch fleet. Now if the Swedish <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> can prevail for an accommodation with this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, without doubt the Airy Monsieur <pb n="1" /> will be <unclear>slighted</unclear>; otherwise, it is probable they will strike up a Bargain.</p>
<p>This day the Lord Protector with his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and Officers of the Army kept a solemn Humiliation at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, where M. <em>Lockier</em>, M. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, and M. <em>Sterrey</em> prayed and preached</p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday, Decemb. 31.</i></head>
<head level="3"><i>A Narrative of the Government of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</i></head>
<p>That the Administration of the Government shall be in the Lord Protector assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, not to exceed 21. nor less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 13. That all Writs, Patents, Grants, &amp;c. shall run in the name of the Lord Protector, and he shall have the power of Pardons, and benefit of all Forfeitures for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> use. That his Highness by the advice aforesaid, shall direct in all things, concerning the holding and keeping a good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> Kings, Princes, and States, and also with the consent of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, have the power of peace and war. That the Laws shall not be altered, suspended, abrogated or repealed, nor any new Law made, nor any Tax, Charge or Imposition laid upon the people, but by common consent in Parliament; save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Lord Protector with the consent of the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for prevention of dangers both by Sea and Land, shall have power to raise money for the purposes aforesaid, and to make Laws for the peace and welfare of the Nation, which shall be binding until order be taken in Parliament concerning the same. That there shall be a Parliament summoned to meet at Westminster on the 3d of September, 1654. and so successively every 3 Years. That the number shall not exceed 400, for England, Wales, the Isles of Jersey, Guernsey, and the Town of <reg orig="Barwick upon Tweed">Berwick-upon-Tweed</reg>, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<p>For the County of <em>Bedford</em>, Town and Boroughs		  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Berks</em>, &amp;c.				  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Bucks</em>, &amp;c.				  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Cambridge</em>, and Isle of <unclear><em>Ely</em></unclear>, &amp;c.				  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Chester</em>					  5</p>
<p>For the county of <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>	12</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Cumberland</em>				  3</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Derby</em>					  5</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Devon</em>					20</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Dorset</em>					10</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Durham</em>					  3</p>
<p>For the county of <em>York</em>					12</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Essex</em>					16</p>
<p>For the county of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em> 6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Hereford</em>					  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Hartford</em>					  7</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Huntington</em>				  4</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Kent</em>					 18</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Lancaster</em>					  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Leicester</em>					  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Lincoln</em>					 16</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Middlesex</em>					  6</p>
<p>For the city of London							  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Monmouth</em>				  3</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Norfolk</em>					 16</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Northampton</em>				  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Nottingham</em>				  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Northumberland</em>				  5</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Oxford</em>					  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Rutland</em>					  2</p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>For the county of <em>Salop</em>					  8</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Stafford</em>					  6</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Somerset</em>					 16</p>
<p>For the City of <em>Bristol</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Southampton</em>				 14</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Suffolk</em>					 16</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Surrey</em>					 10</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Sussex</em>					 14</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Westmerland</em>				  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Warwick</em>					  7</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Worcester</em>					  7</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Wilts</em>					 14</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Anglesey</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Brecon</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Cardigan</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Carmarthen</em>				  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em><reg orig="Carnarvan">Carnarvon</reg></em> 2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Denbigh</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Flint</em>					  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Glamorgan</em>				  3</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Merioneth</em>					  1</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Montgomery</em>				  2</p>
<p>For the county of <em><reg orig="Pembrook">Pembroke</reg></em> 3</p>
<p>For the county of <em>Radnor</em>					  2</p>
<p>That a Parliament being chosen of four hundred persons, sixty of them shall be deemed the Parliament of England, &amp;c. And the Supreme Legislative Power is to reside in the Lord Protector and such a Parliament. The Parliaments are not to be adjourned, or dissolved without their own consent during the first three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> of their sitting, and in case of future War with any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Nation, a Parliament shall forthwith be summoned for their advice concerning the same. That a constant yearly Revenue <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> for the maintaining 10000 Horse and Dragoons, and 20000 Foot in the 3 Nations, for the security of them, and a convenient number of ships for guarding the Seas, and two hundred thousand pound yearly to defray the necessary charges for the <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government, which Revenue is to be raised by the Customs, and such other ways as the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> shall think fit. That in case there needs not so great a defence either at Land or Sea, that an abatement be made, and the money saved to be kept in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service. That the Lands, Rents, and Royalties yet unsold or indisposed by Parliament belonging to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (except the Forrests, <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg>, and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> belonging to the same, and some Lands forfeited in Ireland and Scotland, and the Lands of some Papists and Delinquents in England) be vested in the Lord Protector to hold to him and to his Successors. That the Christian Religion contained in the Scriptures be held forth, and that a provision less subject to scruple and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present be made for the <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> of painful Teachers, and confusion of Errors, and that to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <pb n="3" /> Profession held forth none shall be compelled by penalties, and that all such as <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> Faith in God by Jesus Christ, though differing in judgement from the Doctrine <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth, shall be protected in the profession of the said Faith and exercise of their Religion, so as they abuse not this liberty; provided it extend not to Popery or Prelacy.</p>
<p>The Oath taken by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord <em>Protector</em> was (some prelibations being before made) in these words. <i>I do accept, and take upon me the protection, and Government of these Nations in the manner as large expressed in the Form of <reg orig="Covernmenr">Government</reg>, and I do promise in the presence of God, that I will not violate, or infringe the matters, or things contained therein, but to my power will observe the same, and cause them to be observed, and shall in all other things to the best of my understanding govern these Nations, according to the Laws, Statutes, <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, seeking their peace, and causing Justice, and law to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg></i>.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan 2.</i></head>
<p>Further from Scotland advertiseth, That the Highlanders go on abundantly with their Levies, and grow numerous, their Gen. Kenmore lies up towards the Bray of Mane, and in the Glens that way, and <reg orig="Glenlarn">Glencairn</reg>, with a company of sturdy Redshanks, towards the <reg orig="Bray">Brae</reg> of Stermont and Angus: who lately advanced with a party to Levingston house about ten miles from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and fell upon some of col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Dragoons, whom they barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, ripping up their bellies, and cutting off their heads.</p>
<p>Gen. <reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg>, and Gen. Pen, with the English fleet are put out from Stoaks Bay to sea, consisting of 50 stout men of war; and that the Nonsuch <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> has taken a sweet and delicate prize, laden with Sugar and Wines; but great was their danger to have <reg orig="purchas'd">purchased</reg> them at a very dear rate; for upon their boarding her, the Dutch laid several Trains of match and powder to blow them up; but by the glimpse of one that wanted not above an inch of burning to the <em><reg orig="pouder">powder</reg></em>, the plot was prevented, and the conspirators all scattered. But these <reg orig="joyes">joys</reg> were soon clouded with the dismal <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> of the taking of two English ships, carrying 38 guns, and laden with Masts, pitch, tar, cordage, and other excellent commodities.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> Jan. 2.</head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, with his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council, had the large and last conference (at Whitehall) with the Dutch Ambassadors, where his Highness insisted upon the ensuing Propositions, <em>V I L.</em></p>
<p>1. That Satisfaction be given for all the Injuries and Wrongs sustained by the English, since the first Affront offered by Vantrump upon the Downs.</p>
<p><unclear>2.</unclear> That they shall pay the same contribution and <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> for <unclear>fishing upon</unclear> the Narrow seas, as was formerly paid in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of <unclear>Queen Elizabeth</unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>3. That</unclear> the Dominion of the seas be invested upon the English, <unclear>that</unclear> all such Vessels whatsoever that carries the Dutch colours, <unclear>strike</unclear> <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> unto the ships of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, <unclear>Scotland</unclear>, or Ireland.</p>
<p>4. That Security be given, for performance of all the particular Articles contained in the Treaty, &amp;c.</p>
<p>To which, the Lord Ambassadors returned answer, That they could not assent unto the Proposals, without further Instructions; &amp; desired a convoy for their own <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, whereby they might return an Account of the Transactions of the Treaty, and be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> with further Instructions, if convenient. Whereupon a convoy was appointed, and this evening (about 9 of the clock) they <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth in a stately Barge towards Gravesend.</p>
<p>The Spanish and Portugal Ambassadors have likewise congratulated his Highness, and have so far agreed, that the Lord <em>Pontania Sasa</em> (brother to the <em>Portugal</em>, be removed from Newgate to the <em>Tower</em> of London.</p>
<p>'Tis reported, that there is an eminent person escaped out of the Tower: But of this, more in my next.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church over against the Stile that goes to Stepney, in <unclear>Trumpet</unclear> yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, and deafness of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues; of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many that have been thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him. The History of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year, 1652.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Wednesday Decemb. 28.</head>
<p><i>Take this from France the 29 of Decemb.</i> His Majesty with the Brother, the Cardinal <unclear>Mazarini</unclear>, and many Noblemen went to <unclear>Chaliot</unclear> to visit the late Queen of England, who is very much <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> for the advancing her new Convent there: being she can do little good <reg orig="else where">elsewhere</reg>, Prince <em>Rupert</em> is expected here from Nants, having made an end of telling these ships and goods, which he had sent before, or brought along with him thither, and according to the French relation, the Cardinal Mazarine <unclear>compelled</unclear> him to make full restitution of the last ship and goods taken upon the English.</p>
<p><i>From Venice</i>: There are coming two ships lately from <unclear>Candia that</unclear> bring news how the <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> Foscole continuing to be <unclear>dangerous</unclear> sick, the Proveditor Morisini hath taken upon him the <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear> or absolute command, and hath brought one part thereof into <unclear>the</unclear> <em>Archipelago</em>: partly to keep his men in exercise, as also to take the contributions which this State doth raise yearly upon those Islands: we hear also that the ships lately gone from hence, were safely arrived in Candia, the Commissary <em>Francisco Barbaro</em> being gone hence with a considerable sum of money for the pay of the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>.</p>
<p>There fell a Thunderbolt lately at Tina, where it hath consumed a Magazine, wherein was besides other Ammunition, two hundred and fifty Barrels of powder, and a Church that was near it. That some of our forces being landed at <em>Spina Longa</em>, had got a good booty upon our enemy, and besides, had destroyed all the salt Pans which yield the Turk a very considerable sum yearly.</p>
<p><i>Further from Paris January 3. stilo novo.</i> We have here a strong report that P. <em>Rupert</em> is come to this City and about 20 men with him: others affirm he will be here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>. We hear also that the Prince was yesterday at <reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg>, and within two days will be in this City; thereupon his servants make all things ready for his reception: there is certain advice come from Brest, that there was arrived there, from the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg> nine ships of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg>, to what end or upon what design is not known.</p>
<p>The first instant, being <reg orig="New-years">New Year's</reg> day, the King, his brother, with the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, went into one of the <reg orig="Jesuits">Jesuits'</reg> Convents, where they assisted at evening prayer; there was at present the titular King of Scots, with his two brothers the Dukes of York and <pb n="6" /> <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>; after all was done, a collation was prepared for them, and then departed, the King, and his Brother, and the cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> returned to the Louvre, and other others to the Royal <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>.</p>
<p>There are come into Deal Road, several <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, who are most of them bound for London, among them are the two Morlex ships, besides divers others that are come from other places from the Southward; there are also many ships bound for Malaga, the canaries, and the West-Indies, who expect a fair wind, and a good convoy.</p>
<p>The Spanish Ambassador sent lately to the Lord Protector, to acquaint his Highness that he had something to tender to his consideration, and would be ready to attend his Highness when he would appoint the time; and the next day was the time appointed: at which time he congratulated his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in his new place of Government.</p>
<p>We have not had any news from Ireland of late considerable, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the last Letters say, that about 60 Tories were lately seen in a party, and about 30 in another, within 30 miles of Kilkenny. It seems their chiefest time is in the Winter; for by the swiftness of their feet, and the advantage of long and dark nights, they use to filch and steal away the <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> from the English.</p>
<p>From aboard the Marmaduke <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> it is certified, that we have a very gallant Fleet of near 80 sail already fitted, and upon the Downs, or gone forth in service. Two Dutch prizes were brought in last Friday, and one small French vessel. We have a squadron gone Westward, and some towards Harwich, besides Scouts which ply up and down; 16 sail more are in the Hope, which we expect shortly. Some Seamen and others have lately been punished for criminal offences.</p>
<p>Letters from Holland say, that they are building 30 more new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which will be ready to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> about the beginning of February, when (they say) their whole Fleet <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> come forth: they do what they can to maintain Trade abroad, and say, if the Treaty with England break off, it will prove a very hot summer. Middleton hath sent some Skellams to Scotland, gathered up of several nations. The Agents for <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart speak against his going thither, till he see if they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> stand a field fight. Many here are for peace, and many against it; they also speak of great divisions in England. There is a speech of <unclear><!-- 1 word --> declaration</unclear> coming forth of the States of the United Provinces, of which more <unclear>hereafter</unclear>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> Jan. 5.</head>
<p>Presents us with the mighty preparations for war from Holland, and of their building and setting forth ships from all ports, where are arrived abundance of shipping from all parts, with Ordnance, Arms, and Ammunition; and that the 500 <unclear>piece</unclear> of canon sent from Sweden are planted aboard their new <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg>. Eight of our <reg orig="Newfound land">Newfoundland</reg> ships taken by the Dutch, are made men of war; but can by no means possible supply them with men. Notwithstanding, they have a great Navy to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth, and Gen. <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> is in a posture to receive them. Unto whose assistance, Gen. <em>Blake</em> is advancing.</p>
<p>The Danes are <unclear>likewise</unclear> equipping a great fleet; but the Queen of Sweden works a most admirable interposit on upon them; from whence we have received intelligence, That her Royal Majesty has entertained the Lord Ambassador Whitlock in great state and <em><reg orig="honor">honour</reg></em>, and it is supposed, his Lordship will have a greater influence upon the gallantry of that Royal Horizon, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever any Deputies from the christian princes yet ever had.</p>
<p>By an Express from <em><reg orig="Pembrook">Pembroke</reg></em> it is certified, That there hath <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> a most dreadful Thunder, strange Lightning, and lamentable Rain, the like not seen, nor heard of in many Ages: For not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> many houses were laid waste; but divers <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> destroyed: insomuch, that the poor people make many constructions; but the <em>Lord</em> speak peace to them.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em>, and his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, have spent much time in <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Affairs of the Nation; and col. Ingoldsby's Regiment have taken the new Oath and Engagement to be true and cordial to the present Government, as it now stands established. The like is to be taken throughout all the Regiments in England, Scotland, and Ireland; and with great acclamations of joy have many already subscribed. <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> is making ready with all expedition for his Highness, and Officers of Honour will suddenly be made <reg orig="choise">choice</reg> of to attend the Court; and congratulate so pious, worthy, and renowned an Assertor, of England's just Rights, Liberties, and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late <unclear>Act</unclear> for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, Printed by R. WOOD, 1653.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>