<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout160">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 160
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The Message of His Highness the Lord Protector of England, to the high and <unclear>mighty</unclear> States of Holland, sent over by the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, and delivered by them to the States General at the <em>Hague</em>, and the proceedings of the <em>Hollanders</em> thereupon. The blowing down of the Cross of the Western Church in <em>Amsterdam</em>, the great loss the <em>Hollanders</em> sustained by <unclear>Tempest</unclear> in the <em>Texel</em>, and the burning of the Town of <em>Rype</em> in North <em>Holland</em> by Lightning; with other wonderful Apparitions seen in the <reg orig="Ayr">Air</reg>, to the admiration and astonishment of all the beholders. A <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight between the Dutch and the English on the Coast of Denmark; and the routing of 70 sail of Hollanders, and forcing them into the sound. Several desperate attempts of the Highlanders, their coming to <reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg> and taking the two Bailiffs, their <reg orig="murthering">murdering</reg> of some Dragoons not far from Edinburgh, and the landing Arms &amp; Ammunition from Holland at <unclear>Loqubsber</unclear>. The taking the E. of <unclear><reg orig="Kinnel">Kinoule</reg></unclear>, 35 horse, and other prisoners.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 6 of <em>January</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 13 of <em>January</em>. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, <em>January</em> 6.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>It is certified from <em>Cambridge</em>, that two <em>Petticoat-Preachers</em> came lately to <em><reg orig="Sidney-Colledge">Sidney College</reg></em>, and would needs enter into dispute with divers of the Collegians, who civilly and Scholastically answered all their positions; but those <em>weak vessels</em> being not able to resist such able opposers, used very uncivil language, telling the <reg orig="Schollers">Scholars</reg> <i>they were Antichrists, and their <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> a cage of unclean Birds, with divers other invective speeches, &amp;c.</i> Hereupon the Students made a complaint to the Mayor. who sent for them to appear before him; and demanded <pb n="1" /> whence they came, and where they lay the last night; they said, <i>They were strangers and knew not the name of the place, but they <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> for what they called for.</i> Then he asked them their names, they answered, <i>they were written in the Book of life</i>. Then desiring they would inform by what names their husbands were called, they answered, <i>they had no husbands but Jesus Christ</i>. The honest Mayor feeling them so obstinate, that they not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> slighted the <reg orig="Ministerty">Ministry</reg>, but likewise all civil Government, <reg orig="caus'd">caused</reg> them to be well <reg orig="lash'd">lashed</reg> for their obstinacy, and afterwards to be <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> forth of the Town.</p>
<p>From Holland 'tis certified, that the people murmur very much that the Treaty held so long with England, and fear nothing will come of it. Others there are (though but few) who are good Patriots, and desire an Union with England, as the greatest interest of their Country, but can do nothing, because <reg orig="over-powred">overpowered</reg> in all their <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg>. They are making great preparations against Spring, and 30 new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> are now upon the stocks, to be added to the former 30 already built; they say their fleet will consist of above 100 sail, and <em>Tromp</em> is ordered to go into the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em> with 12 Men of War to Lord it there; they have their eyes every way, both at home and abroad, which activity portends more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary Resolution in Action.</p>
<p>There hath been extraordinary Lightnings and <reg orig="Thunder-claps">Thunderclaps</reg> at Amsterdam and other parts adjacent, and 400 houses were consumed by Lightning at the Rope mills near the city, where their stores were of Hemp and <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, and about 30 ships perished in the Tempest that lay in the <em>Texel</em>. The Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadaors</reg> are yet at <em>Gravesend</em>. and have made some further applications to his Highness and his honourable Council, and it is hoped this accident will somewhat abate their pride, and force them endeavour to compose the difference betwixt their State and <em>England</em>.</p>
<p>By Letters from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> it is certified, that General <em><reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg></em> rides with our Fleet about the Channel, and Gen. <em>Blake</em> is gone down to the Hope to look after the rest of the Fleet, who are near ready to spread their canvas. Besides those two ships mentioned in my last, taken by the Dutch near the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> End <reg orig="home-ward">homeward</reg> bound from <em><reg orig="New-England">New England</reg></em>, there are two more safely arrived in the River coming from the same Country, laden with Masts, great store of <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg> skins, and the like commodities.</p>
<p>The Fleet also is arrived from <em>Dunkirk</em>, consisting of about forty sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg>, <reg orig="thred">thread</reg>, &amp;c. There are likewise five ships arrived <pb n="2" /> from the <reg orig="East-land">Eastland</reg>, and one from <em>Zant</em> with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet they are not come up the River.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, January 7.</head>
<p>From Warwick came intelligence, that on Saturday the last of <em>December</em>, Mr. <em>Bulstrode</em> one of the Judges of <reg orig="Northwales">North Wales</reg>, came thither by a special Commission of Coal delivery; he heard a Sermon early on Monday morning, and went directly from thence to the Hall, where there was a very great appearance, and a very able grand Jury, there hath not been a greater Goal known there these many years: There were five men and one woman condemned to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>, seven <reg orig="burnt">burned</reg> in the hand, and two men that would not plead to be <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg>; the Judge used his endeavours to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to plead, telling <reg orig="tham">them</reg> what a sad condition they would bring themselves into, but the resolute Villains were resolved to <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in their wickedness; The Judge carried the business very well, and gave the Country a great deal of satisfaction. He spake something in his charge in relation to the late Government, and said it was now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon such a Basis, as was like to conduce much to the happiness of all good people; he gave strict Orders to the Grand Jury, that if they heard of any that were perturbers of this, that they should not fail to bring them to the Bar of Justice, and a great deal more to the same effect.</p>
<head level="3">The Copy of a Letter from Scotland.</head>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p><i>The Enemy (for now we must call them so) still go on with their Levies in several parts of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and will do so, do we what we can to prevent  it, though there is little probability they should keep together when united, the Country being so barren. A party of the <em>Tories</em> met with 4 of Colonel <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Dragoons about ten miles from <reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg>, and barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> them. They have placed a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in <em>Roldew</em> about ten miles from <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em>, from whence they came commanded by one <em>Colgrave</em>, with about 80 feet (last week) to <reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg>, and in the dead of the night, took two of the Bailiffs and other principal men of the Town, to the number of 36, whom they threaten to keep, till they send them four horsemen, and 37 foot men, for their Levies.</i></p>
<p><i>Dalkeith, <em>Decemb.</em> 29.</i></p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 9.</i></head>
<p>Yesterday <unclear>was</unclear> a Court Martial held by the Officers of the Army, and several Offences were punished in the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>
<p>The English Fleet is still in the Channel, and General Pen with them, Gen. Blake, Gen. <reg orig="Monk">Monck</reg>, and Gen. Desbrough are returned to Whitehall.</p>
<p>Regensburgh, the 22 of Decemb. S.N. From hence little of news. His Majesty the Emperor was resolved to go a hunting in company of his Majesty the King his son, to Newstadt; but being since taken off with more earnest and important affairs, hath now excused himself and remains here. The 300000 <reg orig="Ryx-dollers">Rix-dollars</reg> that were heretofore, by some of the German Princes, ordered for the Scots King, are now concluded by the General Assembly to be given him: is being also enacted by the said Assembly, that no books or pasquils whatsoever, written against, or in disdain of the said King, should be suffered to be bought or sold in any part of Germany under the Roman Empire, by pain of life.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> Jan. 10.</head>
<p>Produced the Copy of a Letter from Haerlem in Holland, which gives a punctual relation of the late sad disasters which have happened in those parts, which take in <em>his vertis</em>.</p>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p>On Tuesday last there rise a very great storm, which continued all night, and there being between 50 and 60 Merchants riding at anchor at the Texel, a great many of them are sunk and cast away, we hear but of 17 of them saved; so that between 30 and 40 are at best spoiled, sunk, and run <reg orig="a ground">aground</reg>, and of them 20 quite lost, that is the least; amongst the rest there was one <reg orig="East-India">East India</reg> ship cast away called the Lilly that was going out, &amp; another <reg orig="East-India">East India</reg> ship called the Marigold is much hurt &amp; shattered. The loss is great, both ships, goods, and <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> lives, the ships rode very thick together, and many had their anchors <unclear>a ne ho n,</unclear> and drove aboard to other ships, and one tore and sunk another. It was sad to hear the <reg orig="scritching">screeching</reg> crying, tearing, <reg orig="callinp">calling</reg>, roaring, and <unclear>lamenting</unclear> that there was, when none could save hundreds that they saw drowning in this extremity, so that many are made widows, and <reg orig="fatherlesse">fatherless</reg>, whose extremities are great, and the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> hand is sore upon us: Divers of these ships have been driven ashore, and some upon Shelves and Rocks, and many are lost in several parts, yet some it is hoped will be gotten again: What the particular losses have been in all parts of this country and at sea cannot yet be collected: But we much fear our <reg orig="East-India">East India</reg> fleet, of about 150 ships, which we here at sea. At <em>Amsterdam</em> also some hurt was done by this storm, for without the gate of the <pb n="4" /> City, by the Utrechts Bole, a <reg orig="Maltmill">Malt mill</reg> of Shepen Paters fell on fire with the violence of the motion, which could not be staid in that mighty storm: The chasing of the violent motion thereof set it on fire, whereby not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Mill but four houses that stood by it were burnt, to the great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of Schepen Pater, who had much Malt lay there: But he is able enough to bear it, having gained a vast estate by brewing for the men of War. Also within the City of Amsterdam the iron <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> (that is about 20 foot long, and weighed some 4 or 1600 <em>l.</em>) that stood upon the Western Church newly built within few years, at the charge of the City, was by this violent storm blown down, with the Weathercock above it, and the great copper <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Bowl under it, which was said to hold near a Hogshead of Beer, was all blown down, nothing being left standing above the <reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg> Crown on the top of that Steeple. All the said weight fell down through the body of the Church, breaking the strongest corner of that new Church, and fell upon the <reg orig="grave stones">gravestones</reg>, brake them, and tore the dead bodies in their graves. But the <reg orig="graatest">greatest</reg> <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> I hear of was at Rype in North Holland, where an <reg orig="Oyl-mill">Oil mill</reg> by the <unclear>storm</unclear>, in a violent motion by its own heat took fire in the <reg orig="furiousnesse">furiousness</reg> of the storm, and that burning set divers houses on fire, and one house another <reg orig="untill">until</reg> some five or six hundred houses were <reg orig="destroied">destroyed</reg>, and in them many persons burnt alive; and abundance of goods, valued by many to a greater sum <reg orig="then">than</reg> I dare speak of; for this heavy Judgement by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> command made such quick dispatch, that many were taken in their beds, and others burnt alive before they could get out of <reg orig="dores">doors</reg>, I cannot describe unto you the thousand part of the miseries of that poor Town, where not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the private houses, but the two Churches, and Town house, and the weigh-house also, as is said, are <unclear>all</unclear> laid in ashes. The fire staid not in this Town, but flew over the River sixty foot broad, that goes about the Bemster, and there upon the inside of the Bank of the Bemster burnt divers houses also; and burnt the very ships (though small ones) and boats that lay in the Haven; besides what harm it hath done in other parts not herein mentioned.</p>
<p>From <em>Myler</em> in <reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg> by letters of the 2 of <em>Jan.</em> it is credibly informed, that there are 25 witches discovered thereabouts, who are apprehended and committed to Launceston Gaol.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Jan. 11.</head>
<p>There have been many various reports concerning the Lord Whitlock, who is gone <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> for Sweden: He was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon the account of the late Parliament, which dissolved themselves; and since that, some of the adverse party have given forth in speeches, that he was stabbed and killed: Now that the world may take notice what such discontented spirits may utter in a case of such consequence, be pleased to take a true relation, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> passage, but his safe arrival there, as it came from a known hand, in near <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> to his Honour.</p>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p>We began to set sail from <em>Gravesend</em> Novemb. 6. but the wind coming too much into the North, and being not able to get clear of the sands that day, we were enforced to cast Anchor near <em>Quinborough</em>. The next day the wind standing fair, we set sail again, and made a very large course, until about noon the day after; at which time the wind turned full against us, so that we were afraid that we should have been necessitated to put into Yarmouth Road. But the wind favoured us again for a little time, and we made forwards, yet it was not long ere we were very much becalmed; and so we were exercised with uncertainties of winds until the 12 instant when there came a very fair wind, which carried us on with full sail, so that on the 14 instant at night we cast anchor on this side the Scagen, and we came on the 15 betimes in the River.</p>
<p>As we came along our ship met with some Holland Fishermen, and boarded one of them, but my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> willing to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> peaceably over the sea, released it again, which did exceedingly overjoy them, who had been undone in his own thoughts before; yet the Elizabeth, being one of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that carried some of our Company, staying behind to bring up one of the Baggage ships, met with a small Dutch Caper, and boarded it, and brought it along with them. We were not altogether without rough and stormy weather, especially the last night, when we anchored at the Scagen, insomuch that we were afraid we should have lost one of the Baggage ships, which was but very slenderly provided with <unclear>tacklings</unclear>, yet (through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God) we were all come safe, and there is <pb n="6" /> none sick amongst us, nor <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> lost; As soon as ever we were come into the River, being weary of the sea, we made hast to the shore so that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Magistrates of the town could not be ready to give us that solemn reception as they intended. The next day the three Presidents, with the Magistrates, came to salute my Lord in a handsome Equipage, and one of the them made a Speech to him in <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, wherein he acquainted his Lordship, That they had received positive commands from the Queen to demonstrate all respects to the English <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, whom she had received notice would arrive here in a short time; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> desired his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> excuse, that they were not prepared to give him a more pompous entertainment at his first landing. Afterwards the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> came to give his Salutation, which he performed with great civility and respect. And indeed they are very ready to accommodate us in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>, and to give us all possible help and assistance in our intended <reg orig="journy">journey</reg> towards the Court. The Queen is at present at <reg orig="Upsalia">Uppsala</reg>, but we are uncertain whether she intends to <reg orig="recide">reside</reg> there all this <reg orig="wintar">winter</reg>; it is supposed that she may return again to Stockholm, there dying but two of the <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg> the last week; our <reg orig="journy">journey</reg> thither <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be very tedious and chargeable; and we now begin to find by experience that those that are <reg orig="imploied">employed</reg> upon such solemn Missions into so barren a Country, must needs be supplied with a very large purse. After that we have refreshed <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, and rested our horses here for a few days, we shall begin our journey, having already sent Letters to the Court of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> arrival; we must be <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to carry all our baggage by land; the Presidents of the City after consultation had amongst themselves giving us this advice, which will be a very vast charge.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Guttenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, November, 18, 1653.</i></head>
<hr />
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church over against the Stile that goes to Stepney, in <unclear>Trumpet</unclear> yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the <unclear>swelling</unclear> of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness</unclear> of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues; of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many that have been thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him. The History of <reg orig="New-England">New England</reg>, from the English <unclear>planting</unclear> in the year 1628. until the year, 1652.</i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> Jan. 12.</head>
<p>The King of France his <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> lately come over, the Ministers, six of the French Church, and a <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquess</reg>, have <unclear><reg orig="beene">been</reg></unclear> with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, to congratulate, declaring their sense of engagement to <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God for Him; and their hope of protection to themselves and the rest of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people from Him, And they received a very satisfying Answer: So that there is like to be that <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Protestant Churches of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> parts, which hath not yet been: which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be a great blow to Antichrist, and a great means to exalt the Throne of the Lord Jesus, when the multitudes of those that <unclear><reg orig="beleive">believe</reg></unclear> shall be of one heart, and one mind; for the Spirit of the Lord worketh by love.</p>
<p>There hath been <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> sights seen in the <reg orig="skie">sky</reg> at the Town of Perit near Holdin in Pomerania, <em>viz.</em> A Coffin with a black <reg orig="Cross">Crosse</reg>; also a Dutch Lord overcome by another Nation; after which was seen a fair Rainbow, and afterward the last <reg orig="Dooms day">Doomsday</reg>, at which sight many have been astonished.</p>
<p>From aboard the <reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> it is certified, That Captain <em>Foster</em> having landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> at <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, Decemb 21. discovered a fleet of Hollanders of about 80 sail, who upon our ships <unclear>firing</unclear> amongst them, about 70 sail cut their cables and ran towards the Sound; two men of War that were amongst them fought us some hours, but we forced them with some <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> in a sinking condition to retreat towards their fleet. The next day three Dutch men of War (two of them great ships, and Convoyers to the rest) came right before the wind upon our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>; whereupon we took all our men out of three <unclear>prizes</unclear> which we had taken, and would have fired them, but that we wanted time. They fought us furiously, and shot the chain of our <reg orig="fore-yard">foreyard</reg> in pieces, and two thirds of our main <reg orig="top-yards">topyards</reg>, and would have boarded us, had not we prevented them</p>
<p>This day came further intelligence from Scotland, <em>viz.</em> That a Dutch man hath landed some Arms and Ammunition at <reg orig="Loughaber">Lochaber</reg> in the Highlands; <em><reg orig="Mac Cloude">MacCloud</reg></em> came with 400 old Irish Rebels into Lewis Island to raise men but to little purpose: After he attempted to surprise some vessels of Captain <em>Bressie</em>, but he prevented his design by putting into an open Road. The Lord Kinoule came with a party of 70 horse into the <reg orig="Glans">Glens</reg> to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> our horse <unclear>there</unclear>; but was sighted on by a party of horse belonging to Maj <em>Duckei</em>, and himself and 14 more were taken, all sore wounded, and about 35 horse; the rest quitted their saddles, and betook themselves to the <unclear>Bogs</unclear>.</p>
<p>The Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> are arrived at the Hague, and have delivered a Message to the States from his Highness the Ld. Protector: so that yet there is some hopes there may be a conclusion of Peace, which will be within ten days, or <reg orig="els">else</reg> not likely: yet they make all the provision that may be for War, and promise the perform great matters the next Spring; but <i>great talkers <em>(<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> our English Proverb)</em> are but little doers.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><i><unclear>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg></unclear> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, <unclear>PRINTED</unclear> by R. WOOD, 1653.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>