<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout162">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 162
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>A New <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> sent over from the States of Holland into England, his landing at <em>Harwich</em> on Wednesday last; and his Message to His Highness the Lord Protector of England; With an abstract of the Peace concluded betwixt the States of the United Provinces and this Commonwealth. The Lord <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Letter to <em>Middleton</em> concerning his proceedings against the English; The Lord <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorne's</reg></em> revolting from the Enemy, and the taking of divers horse and prisoners by Col. <em>Okey's</em> Captain Lieutenant near <em><reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg></em>; with the <em>Scots</em> falling upon a party of ours commanded by Captain <em><reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg></em> Lieutenant, and killing the Cornet, one Corporal, two troopers, and took seven; but with loss of Col. <em>Wogan</em> and divers others. The coming in of the <em><reg orig="East-India">East India</reg></em> Fleet, and divers of them running <reg orig="a ground">aground</reg> in the <em>Vlie</em>. A List of the prizes taken this Week from the Dutch, some mischief done in <em>Ireland</em> by the Tories, and a Narrative of the L. <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> journey to the Swedish Court.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 20. of <em>January</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 27 of <em>January</em>. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, <em>January</em> 20.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>I Shall in this place present you with an Abstract of the Lord <reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg> <reg orig="journy">journey</reg> from <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg> to <reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg>. On the 29 of Novemb. he went from <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, his Train consisting of 83 saddle Horses, 2 Coaches, and about 60 <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>: The first night the L. <reg orig="Laggerfields">Laggerfield's</reg> Secretary was sent to <reg orig="accomodate">accommodate</reg> him; and having endured 14 days hard travel, they came to Encopin, a Town within 4 leagues of <reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg>, where her Maj. sent to him to desire him to repose himself 2 or 3 days; which his Lordship did. And then the Q sent the Mr. of the Ceremonies, with her own Coach, who conducted him, accompanied with 18 other Coaches, and a great many of her Maj. servants on Horseback, to the Court, and commanded he should want no manner of accommodation.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>We hear by a ship come from <reg orig="Hambrough">Hamburg</reg>, and also many ships this week come from Dunkirk, of ten of our merchant men come safely to <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, laden with all Eastern commodities, and five of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> convoy to them, who have also homewards bound made several prizes upon the coast of Norway, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be in England very shortly.</p>
<p>All persons are desired to take notice, that the Committee for <unclear>Claims</unclear> for Lands in Ireland, have appointed Thursday the ninth of <unclear>February</unclear>, 1653. for Adventurers to draw Lots at Grocers hall, London, for <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>, and that all persons who intend then to draw Lots, do before that day in their pence,</p>
<p>WILLIAM TIBBS.</p>
<p>The Letters out of Ireland, say, That the Tories begin to play their pranks again, and some hundreds have been discovered together in a body; yet if but a party of ten or twenty of our men do but appear, they all fly away, and hide themselves in the woods.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday, Jan. 21.</head>
<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his Honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, set forth an Ordinance declaring, That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be high Treason for any person (not being an Officer, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Member of the Army) to plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the stirring up of any mutiny in the said Army, or if any person shall invite or assist any <reg orig="Forrainers">Foreigners</reg> invading England, Scotland, or Ireland, or if any person shall plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the betraying or yielding up any City, Town, Fort, Ship or Vessel, belonging to this Commonwealth, or if any person shall <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg> or imagine the death of the Lord Protector for the time being, or if any person or persons shall maliciously or advisedly either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector, and the people in Parliament assembled, are not the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority of this Commonwealth, or if any person or person whatsoever, shall proclaim, declare, publish, or any way promote <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, eldest son to the late King, or <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em> one other of his sons, or any other the issue or posterity of the said late King, or any other person or persons, claiming by, from, or under him or them, or either or any of them, or any of the Dominions to them, or either or any of them belonging; or if any person or persons, shall give, keep, or hold any intelligence <pb n="2" /> whatsoever, by Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em>, the late Queen their mother, or any of them; or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the money of this Commonwealth: or shall bring any false money into this land, either counterfeit or other, like to the money of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (knowing such money to be false) to the intent to <reg orig="merchandize">merchandise</reg>, or otherwise; or if any person or persons shall hereafter <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> forge or counterfeit any such kind of Coin, either of Gold or Silver, which is not the proper <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> of this Commonwealth, and yet is or shall be current within the same; or shall bring from the parts beyond the Seas into this Commonwealth, or into any the Dominions of the same, any such false or <unclear>counterfeit</unclear> coin of money to the intent to utter or make payment with the same, within this Commonwealth. Or if any person or persons shall Impair, <reg orig="Falsifie">Falsify</reg>, <unclear>Clip, Wash, Round, File, and Scale</unclear>, of lighten any the proper monies of this Commonwealth, or of the monies or coins of any other places allowed, or suffered to be current within this Commonwealth.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Scotland.</i></head>
<p>Sir, These parts afford no news, the enemy is preparing to make ready for the season of the year, and do the utmost this Winter to promote their design, and do send into our <unclear>quarters</unclear>, their Warrants for their levies, but dare not come themselves to see performance, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <unclear>in the</unclear> night do come and steal horses, and at sometimes do carry away some men, you may by the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> see their Warrants, and what the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of this place Col. Cooper is constrained to do, to <reg orig="counter-work">counterwork</reg> them, or <unclear>else</unclear> the people would be willing to answer their expectations, no more but that I am</p>
<p>Sir,</p>
<head level="3">Glasgow, Jan. 12. 1653.</head>
<p><i>William Earl of Glencairn, Lord <reg orig="Killmarrs">Killmarr's</reg>, Commander in chief of His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of Scotland.</i></p>
<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to us by his Majesty, for levying of forces, Horse and foot, for suppressing the common enemy within this Kingdom; we <unclear>do hereby</unclear> require you &amp; every of you, within the shires of <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg> and Renfrew, upon sight thereof, to send forth for His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, forth of every Thousand pounds sent <unclear>within</unclear> your Shires respectively, one sufficient well mounted man, with Pistols, and <unclear>other furniture</unclear>, and weapons belonging there <unclear>o</unclear>, and to deliver the same at <unclear>Roldew</unclear>, to Lieut. Col. George Maxwel, Lieu. Col. George Herriot, and Cap. James Cunningham, or any having their Orders for that effect: <unclear>certifying</unclear> all persons of whatsoever quality, within the said <unclear>Shires</unclear> respectively, that doth either refuse or delay to give obedience to this our Order and Commands, they shall be taken notice of, and proceeded against as disloyal subjects, and professed enemies to the present Expedition. <unclear>Whereas</unclear> by the contrary, we do hereby oblige <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to protect and defend against all enemies whatsoever, all such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> willingly put forth their several proportions of the aforesaid Horse <pb n="3" /> <reg orig="levie">levy</reg>. And whatsoever horses, or any other goods shall be taken from any one of them so protected, in any disorderly manner, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be restored again, but the person or persons offenders, shall according to the quality of the offence, at the sight of the party offended, be severely punished, to the terror of others; And ordains this to be published at every Headborough, or Parish Church within the said Shires respectively, that every Heritor, and others therein contained, pretend no ignorance of the premises. Given at Garth, Decemb. 23. 1653.</p>
<p><reg orig="GLENCARN">GLENCAIRN</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> January 23.</head>
<p>This day produced intelligence of the proceeding of the States of Holland, a Copy whereof take as followeth.</p>
<p><em>Sir</em>, There is brought into Flushing two Virginia prizes, the one of 18, the other of 11 pieces of Ordinance, laden with Tobacco, Sugar, Indico, and <reg orig="Bever-wool">Beaver wool</reg>, taken near the English Channel; and two other prizes are brought into the <unclear>Vlie</unclear>. There are divers ships come from the <reg orig="Streights">Straights</reg>, and two hundred are expected from France; also some East India ships are come likewise into the <unclear>Vlie</unclear>, and the whole Fleet is said to be within sight of Land, but to our great grief we hear that four of five of them are stranded, and the goods like to be lost. He that takes an <em><reg orig="Eele">Eel</reg></em> by the <em>Tail</em> hath but <reg orig="sligpery">slippery</reg> hold, and however the Dutch pretend <em>Peace</em>, their actions <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the contrary; for in <em>Zealand</em> they are setting forth 20 new ships of War, of 150, 136 to 130 foot long, and from 30 to 33 foot broad. There are divers <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> come hither from several Princes, and it is feared, will rather <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to obstruct, <reg orig="then">than</reg> promote peace with England. Middleton hath lately received a Letter from <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, giving him notice that he hath made himself Master of Sterlingshire, and of the Northern quarter of Scotland, and that they <reg orig="onely">only</reg> want the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> presence, and some more Arms and Ammunition. The Deputies of the States arrived here yesterday from England, and thereupon the Lord States assembled this day, and the Deputies made report of these Negotiations; it is said that the English would exclude the King of Denmark in the Articles, and therefore that point remained undenied, till the ratification of the Articles.</p>
<p>I have sent you here <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>, a Narrative of a paper printed at <unclear>Haerlem</unclear>, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> <i>Peace, or true news of the Peace concluded between the United Provinces, and the Commonwealth of England.</i> 1. That the Deputies of Holland by the dissolution of the last Parliament, and <pb n="4" /> the transferring the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the said Commonwealth of England to <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector, had been interrupted three days in their Negotiation. 2. That on the third of January, 1653. they treated very close with the English Commissioners at Whitehall, and the eight very near perfected the Treaty, which was not brought to a full end because of some difficulty. 3. Thereupon the Lordships (as they had done sometimes before) declaring to be desirous to return home, and demanding a <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> to that effect; it was granted them the ninth day, and they being gone to Gravesend, the said Treaty hath there been resumed in hand by the English, and all the Articles renewed, whereupon the Allies and Confederates were comprehended in it. And that the fourteenth the Peace was there agreed on, concluded and signed, God Almighty be praised; being a great blessing for the Protestants throughout <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>. 4. That afterward the Lord Deputies of Holland, after many loving <reg orig="imbracements">embracements</reg>, went the 16 into a ship appointed for them and ready to set sail, and their Lordships arrived in the Mase the 21, and about noon arrived at Schiedam, from whence they came that evening to the Hague, where, upon their coming, and the report they have made of the peace concluded, and of all the circumstances, there hath been great rejoicing. 5. That the 22 the States sent Letters to all the Towns and Burroughs concerning this great and good <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> might be informed thereof. 6. The time will not yet give me leave (good Country men) to afford you more particulars of the Treaty; I shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="adde">add</reg>, that the Lords States <reg orig="wil">will</reg> speedily call for a meeting, to agree, <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, and approve the said Articles of Peace. God grant it. In Zealand they will not <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of the peace, but do persist for war; they say there that the English will not have a Peace <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they buy it at at a dear rate, and with ready money; which the Zealanders look upon as a peace that will be dishonourable, <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>, disadvantageous, and not lasting: but we that are Merchants must pray and desire peace, for if these miserable wars continue, we shall be quite undone for want of trade, which is the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> support of these countries.</p>
<p><i>Hague, Jan. 22 stilo novo, 1654.</i></p>
<p>This day the Term began, and the Judges <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> in the several Benches in Westminster hall.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Tuesday January 24.</head>
<p><i>This day was published in Print, an Ordinance for Repealing of several Acts, and Resolves of Parliament, made for, or touching the subscribing or taking the ENGAGEMENT.</i></p>
<p>Whereas many general promissory Oaths and Engagements, (in former times imposed upon the people of this Nation) have proved <em>burthens</em> and <em>snares</em> to <em>tender Consciences</em>, and yet have been <em>Exacted</em>, under several <em>Penalties, Forfeitures</em>, and <em>Losses</em>; Upon consideration whereof, and out of a <reg orig="tendernesse">tenderness</reg> of requiring such obligations, be it ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, by and with the advice and consent of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that one Act of Parliament, published in print the second day of January, one thousand six hundred forty and nine, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for subscribing the Engagement; And certain Orders, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, Resolves touching the subscribing to an Engagement, <em>&amp;c.</em> And all and every clause, branch, article, and sentence in them, and every or any of them <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, shall from and after the nineteenth day of January in the year of our Lord one thousand six hundred fifty and three, stand and be absolutely repealed a<em>n</em>d <reg orig="adnulled">annulled</reg>; and that all and every clause, branch, article, proviso or sentence contained in any other Act, Ordinance, Resolves or Order of Parliament, whereby the said Oath or Engagement is directed, and appointed to be taken, and <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>, and all and every the penalties, losses, incapacities, disabilities, and forfeitures for not taking, or subscribing the same, shall from and after the said nineteenth day of January, in the year of our Lord one thousand and six hundred fifty and three, (as to so much <reg orig="onely">only</reg> (and no more) as concerneth the said Engagement, and the penalties, losses, incapacities, disabilities, and forfeitures for not taking or subscribing the same), be, at date hereby, utterly repealed, and made void: And that the said Oath or Engagement, where the same is appointed to be <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> by <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, or where the same is inserted into any other Oath (as to so much <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as concerneth the said Engagement) shall not, from or after the said nineteenth day of January, in the year of our Lord one thousand six hundred fifty and three, be <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> unto, or taken by any Officer, Minister of Justice, or other person whatsoever; but the same shall from thenceforth be wholly taken away and abolished, to all intents and purposes <pb n="6" /> whatsoever. And that from and after the said nineteenth day of January, in the said year of our Lord one thousand six hundred fifty and three, no place or office of trust within this Commonwealth, shall be made void, by reason of the not taking or subscribing the said Engagement. And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That if any person or persons whatsoever have been delayed, <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg>, or prejudiced in any course or proceedings of Law, Justice, or Equity, or hath not or cannot have the full benefit thereof, by reason or means that such person or persons hath not or have not taken and subscribed the said Engagement, in such form, or at <unclear>such</unclear> time or times as hath or have been limited or appointed for the taking or subscribing thereof, such person or persons shall from henceforth by admitted unto, and have such course, pleadings and proceedings in Law, Justice, and Equity, as if such person or persons had taken or subscribed the said Engagement, in such manner and form, and at such time or times, as was or were directed or appointed for the taking or subscribing thereof, and not otherwise.</p>
<p><i>Ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that this Ordinance by forthwith printed and published.</i></p>
<p><i><unclear>Hen. Scobel</unclear> Clerk of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</i></p>
<p>The King of  France for the present <unclear>made a stop</unclear> of all English ships in the <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg> of France. The titular King of England is for certain as yet in France, whatsoever is whispered to the contrary. Prince Rupert hath been so fortunate this Christmas at play, that he hath won twelve thousand Crowns of some of the Lords of that Kingdom. It is reported that the Duke d'<em>Anguyen</em> is to be married to the Lord Protector of <reg orig="Englands">England's</reg> daughter; it would be well if he were born to so good a fortune; if he obtains her <unclear><reg orig="fathers">father's</reg></unclear> consent he may chance to give her a French Crown to her Dowry.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church over against the Stile that goes to Stepney, in <unclear>Trumpet</unclear> yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness</unclear> of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues; of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many that have been thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him. The History of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year, 1652.</i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday <em>Jan. 26.</em></i></head>
<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes lately taken from the Dutch.</i></head>
<p>A Vessel from New-Haven, forced on shore upon the French coast by the Diamond.</p>
<p>A prize of Wines taken by the Middleborough, is brought into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>.</p>
<p>A French man taken by Captain Heaton, laden with Wines, sent into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>.</p>
<p>A Fly-boat, called the Spotted <reg orig="Oxe">Ox</reg>, an Holland Merchant ship coming from <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, laden with Wines, of 140 Lasts, taken by Captain Hide, sent in to Dartmouth.</p>
<p>A small Vessel called the Hope of Campheir, with Deal boards, and ballast brought in by the Expedition.</p>
<p>An Holland Virginia Merchant ship run on board and sunk by the Ruby <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>
<p>A Dutch Merchant ship richly laden, sunk upon the coasts of France, upon a chase.</p>
<p>Two Dutch ships sunk near the coasts of Norway.</p>
<p>A Dutch Merchant ship taken upon the coasts of Scotland.</p>
<p>One Dutch ship sunk, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, near the Pole-head.</p>
<p>A Dutch Flute belonging to <unclear>Monnickdam</unclear>, taken near Gostenburgh.</p>
<p>Another ship coming from <unclear>Dantaick</unclear>, belonging to the same place.</p>
<p>Take this from Scotland. The Enemy is much startled at <reg orig="Lorns">Lorne's</reg> revolt, and think there is some design in it. Col. <reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg> Capt. Lieutenant fell into their quarters near <reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg> took 10 prisoners, 16 horses, and killed two on the place. But a party of Capt. Elsmore were not so <reg orig="succesfull">successful</reg>, his <reg orig="Lieutenaat">Lieutenant</reg> being sent with 30 horse to rescue some sheep taken by the Enemy, pursued them, and recovered their prize; but returning were Ambuscadoed, and had an intricate retreat; the Cornet, one Corporal, and two Troopers were killed, and 7 taken, but divers of the Enemy lost their lives, amongst the rest Col. Wogan is supposed to be one, who charged first with the English. The Spring comes on apace, and then our forces will take the field, and soon quell these insolent fellows. We have there at the least 20 <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> Regiments, which for satisfaction of the curious I <unclear>shall</unclear> here nominate.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of the Regiments in Scotland.</i></head>
<p>General <reg orig="Monks">Monck's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Fenwicks">Fenwick's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Fairfaxes">Fairfax's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Overtons">Overton's</reg>, that which was Major Gen. <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Alureds">Alured's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Cobbets">Cobbet's</reg>, <unclear>Col.</unclear> <reg orig="Salmons">Salmon's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Thomlinsons">Thomlinson's</reg>, part of Col. <reg orig="Sandersons">Sanderson's</reg>, the Company at <reg orig="Dunmarton">Dumbarton</reg>, besides going to Scotland, Major Gen. <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, Commis. Gen. <reg orig="Whalleys">Whalley's</reg>, part of Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg>.</p>
<p>This day came intelligence, That the States of Holland have sent over an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, to deliver a <em>M</em>essage from Them, to His Highness the Lord Protector of England; who is landed at Harwich, and this Evening is expected to come to London. <i>O that he might (like <em>Noah's</em> Dove) bring us the glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of</i> PEACE.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, PRINTED by R. WOOD, 1654.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>