<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton127">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scout (printed by George Horton), Issue 127</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE FAITHFUL</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>

<head level="3">Truly Representing,</head>

<p><i>The Declaration and Reports of the Dutch Ambassadors to the States of the United Provinces, concerning the concluding of a Peace with England; and the proceedings thereupon. The Extract and transcription of their Papers; and a perfect Narrative of the late violent &amp; lamentable Storm and Fire, wherein divers men, women, and children, perished in the dreadful Flames, many stately houses burnt, the Anabaptists Congregation house destroyed, and the great Cross, with the Golden Weathercock, the gilded Bowl (that held above a hogshead of Beer) and all that stood above the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Crown on the high steeple, totally cast down through the body of the new Church, and rent and tore the dead bodies in their <em>Graves</em>. The return of the English <em>Generals</em> from <em>Sea</em>, and the true state &amp; condition of the <em>Navy</em>. Together with a great Victory obtained <em>against the Highlanders</em>, and the <em>particulars</em> thereof.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Jan. 6. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Jan. 13.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON. Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<p>The last intelligence from them King of Scots <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that at the Palace Royal in Paris He hath feasted the French King with some Lords &amp; Ladies, and was accompanied by his two brothers the Dukes of York and Gloucester. Prince Rupert was likewise there; but his brother Prince Maurice is said to be drowned. We have advice from Pomerania that by the town of <unclear>Pirit</unclear> over Holdin, there hath been a sight in the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg>, of a Coffin with a black Cross, and there hath also appeared a <em>Dutch</em> Lord overcomed by another Nation: after which was seen a fair Rainbow, and afterward the last <reg orig="Dooms-day">Doomsday</reg>, at which sight many have been much astonished, and exceedingly affrighted.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>By our last <em>Post</em> and intelligence from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, we have received very certain and <unclear><!-- approx. 28 characters --></unclear> that Colonel <em>Charles James</em> having received a <unclear>Commission</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 18 characters --></unclear> Scots is <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth into the Deep with the Brest Men of War <unclear><!-- approx. 13 characters --></unclear> struck sail upon the Coast of <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>, and there set up his <unclear>Flag on the</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 18 characters --></unclear> called the Vice Ambral.</p>

<p><unclear><!-- approx. half a line --></unclear> or Sweden, our Post further advertisseth, that the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, with his Retinue was received in a most high and <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> manner by <unclear><!-- approx. 13 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, who made a speech to his Worship, by way of congratulation, in reference to his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> from the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England.</p>

<p>From <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> <unclear>further</unclear> certified that there hath <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> a very sad and lamentable <unclear>fire</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> <em>Amsterdam</em> <unclear>it is</unclear> said by some, but at a town some 3 miles off the said City <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> by <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear>, and stormy weather, a Rase Mill being driven with <unclear>such</unclear> force and violence, that they took fire with such fury and violence, that the Flames <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> forth in <unclear>such</unclear> Flakes, that no possible means could prevent this sad and dreadful devastation.</p>

<p>The like dreadful Thunder has been at <em>Pembroke</em> in Wales, where not long before the great Lightning, appeared a Blazing Star, to the great admiration of all that beheld it.</p>

<p>What these dreadful <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> from Heaven portend, I am not able to make out; but certainly they are <reg orig="Fore-runners">Forerunners</reg> of some wonderful Events.</p>

<p>There is arrived the Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em>, consisting of about forty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg>, &amp;c. There is likewise come five ships from the <reg orig="East-Land">East Land</reg>; as also one from <em>Zant</em>, with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet not come up the River.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Gravesend Jan. 9.</i></head>

<p><i>The Ambassadors from the States of Holland have made some further application to his Highness, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; and 'tis hoped there will be a firm and lasting Peace.</i></p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan. 9.</head>

<p>By an Express from Jersey it is certified, that there hath been a ship cast away upon that Coast, and most of the passengers and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> drowned.</p>

<p>The King of Scots Men of War are still plying about<pb n="2" /> the Isle of Lundy, and often came into the Severn mouth, where some time they sit very unhandsomely upon Our Jackets, and unworthily <reg orig="seiz">seize</reg> our small Vessels.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have likewise received intelligence, that the Highlanders <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> R E X upon the Lowlanders, and commits abundant of Outrages; they are very high in the Levies; but not altogether so successful in their Enterprises, though notwithstanding Fame reports them to be above seven thousand horse and foot (in skits) and that they expect additional supplies from beyond the seas. They have drawn forth their whole Army in a Regimental way, which consists of these ensuing Regiments, to with;</p>

<p>Gen. Glencarn, Col: Forbis,</p>
<p>Lieut. Gen. Lorn, Col. Brown,</p>
<p>Gen. Major Homes, Col: Middleton,</p>
<p>Colonel <reg orig="Macwait">McWait</reg>, Col: Melvin,</p>
<p>Col: <reg orig="Mac-Donel">McDonnell</reg>, Col: James,</p>
<p>Col: Hume, Col: Stuart,</p>
<p>Col: Ennis, Col: Straughan,</p>

<p>Col: Lilburn is very active, and useth all <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> possible to prevent and deter them from making inroads upon the English; but by reason of the Winter Season, great is their advantage upon Us; so that additional forces from England are preparing; and Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> Regiment are designed for the North: The Oath and Engagement is to be tendered to every Regiment before they march; and the Names of those that have already subscribed, are, Col: Ingoldsby, Col: Goff, Col: Whalen, &amp;c.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">Tuesday Jan. 10.</head>

<p>Produced Letters from Amsterdam, intimating, that their East India fleet, consisting of 150 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, is much feared to be cast away; such a mighty <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> hath not happened these hundred years; besides, many houses are burnt, &amp; the great iron cross, with the Weathercock, and <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Bowl under it, which was said to hold a Hogshead of Beer, was all blown down, and sailing upon the Graves, tore the dead bodies. At which time, began the great fire, at the Hemp Mill, which consumed all St. <reg orig="Jacobs">Jacob's</reg> street, the Anabaptists Congregation house with the Church house, &amp; Townhouse. So that the fire running with <reg orig="over-violency">over-violence</reg>, flew over to the Bremster Dike, and burnt the Bridge.</p>

<p>But the greatest loss I hear of was at <em>Rype</em> in <reg orig="Notrh">North</reg> Holland, where an <reg orig="Oyl-Mill">Oil Mill</reg> by the storm, in a violent motion by <reg orig="its">its'</reg> own heat, took fire, and burning furiously, destroyed about five hundred houses, and many men, women, and children, were burnt alive, and <reg orig="mony">money</reg> goods, valued to be worth forty hundred thousand pounds. Great was the lamentation and <reg orig="cryes">cries</reg> of children to their Parents, and husbands to their wives, but could not be helped: many a <reg orig="mothers">mother's</reg> bowels pressing her into the <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> and flame to save her child, lost her life, and her <reg orig="childs">child's</reg> also. So the destruction of this Town was in a moment; but the Lord divert and stay his heavy hand of judgment.</p>

<p>By an Express from the Navy, thus: The Fleet in the channel, and General Pen with them; but Gen: Blake, Gen: Monk, and Gen: Desborough are returned to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors are now gone over to Holland; and 'tis said, there is a Peace concluded: into the truth whereof, I shall make a diligent inquiry by my next.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador, newly come over from his Master the King, had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, whom he congratulated in his new Government.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador Whitlock is said to arrive at Upsal, four miles from Stockholm the 24 Decemb. where he is to have audience from the Queen.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3">Wednesday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 11.</head>

<p>Presents Us with a notable subject, called, An Answer to a paper <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, A true Narrative of the cause, ground, and manner of the dissolution of the late Parliament, &amp;c. Wherein, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> the Author, three things were evidently in the principles of divers of those men in the house (whom I, amongst others, thought it not safe to sit longer with) which though I will not determine but that they might be the issues of a deluded mind, yet looked very like the worst designs.</p>

<p>First, a general owning themselves to rule the Nation <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as Saints, to whom the right of civil Government did belong, as having an extraordinary call from Christ thereto, being the beginning of a <unclear>fife</unclear> Monarchy, which was never to cease, but to break in pieces all powers, by making war with them. In which, besides the dishonour cast upon the good ways of God and his people, and the abuse of many Truths, and in particular that of the Kingdom of Christ on earth, a thing to be expected and longed for, as the Scriptures hold it forth to us; 'tis no way hard to discern what a foundation was laid of exalting men (who should take to themselves the name of Saints, though never so unduly) in Government, and excluding all others who had never so great Interest in the Nation, and other fitness thereto, and have a civil Right to rule, when Providence <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give them a lawful Call thereto.</p>

<p>Secondly, how great a ground was this to put the stamp of infallibility upon all they should do, and conclude the Nation in whatsoever Impositions they should lay upon them, by pretending themselves Ruling Saints,</p>

<p>And that unquestionably by a Divine and extraordinary Right, a thing never before heard of as thus held forth; and which certainly if pursued to the utmost, would give them under that notion, a right to possess all <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> properties and estates, <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> as dispose and govern them, and introduce such Axioms, as would soon have turned the three Nations into blood and confusion. I intend not hereby any reflection upon the Name of Saints, which my soul honours nor upon the advantage of having godly men to rule; but upon the ill and dangerous use by <reg orig="Satans">Satan's</reg> Temptations may be made of such pretences, especially in these Times, wherein his Temptations lie mostly that way. The second was, their manifestly rigid Principles of Imposition<pb n="5" />, contended against with the blood of so many precious Saints, &amp; laying such foundations as would shortly have introduced the bitterest sorest persecution: To this none are so conscious, or can be, as those that sate <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> with them in the House, where they heard men unsainted, and <reg orig="condemn'd">condemned</reg> into the fourth Monarchy, and looked upon as <reg orig="obstructors">obstructers</reg> of Reformation, and no longer fit for the Work, if not <reg orig="through-paced">thoroughpaced</reg> to all the Principles of <em>Reformation</em>, held forth by Mr. <em>Feak</em> and others at <em>Black <reg orig="fryers">friars</reg></em>, and other places, and stickled for by some in the House. To this purpose, Letters are written to the Churches all the Nation over, to blast that part of the House that agreed not with them; and at a set meeting at a <reg orig="Members">Member's</reg> house, of divers Members, consultation had to leave the House, and demonstrate against them as hinderers of <em>Reformation</em>, and not fit to govern the Nation any longer. And things indeed amongst them was grown to that height that it was evident (in a short time scarce any should have been judged meet to publish the Gospel, or receive the <reg orig="Magistrates">Magistrate's</reg> countenance, that had not been baptized into their spirit and principle. And this I cannot but mention, that when the last great Debate was about ejecting scandalous Ministers, it was confidently averred, None should be countenanced by the Magistrate but such as disclaimed their Ordination: Which, though though I would not seem to <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> it in the least, how hard an Imposition it was to put men upon this Dilemma either to leave their present subsistence or disclaim the Ordination they had it may be <reg orig="conscienciously">conscientiously</reg> received either from Bishops or Presbyterians, is no hard thing to judge.</p>

<p>Thirdly, there appeared an evident Design to alter the Government of the Army, and have put it into such hands as would have perfectly corresponded with their principles, and given them a safe opportunity to have imposed whatsoever they had pleased upon the Nation; and as there was just cause to fear would have brought out what did not yet appear, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p><i>&mdash; Blood upon the Nation.</i></p>

<p>This was certainly given in direction to divers Members met together, to pull down some in the <reg orig="Aimy">Army</reg>, and set up others, either with or before them, as is most notoriously known: And what other signification, but to alter the Government of the Army, the endeavours of many in the House who came purposely prepared to<pb n="6" /> take away the Officers pay, could have, I know not, unless it were to make a dangerous breach between the Parliament, and the Army who called them thither, or else to breed animosities in the Army, and set them at variance among themselves. This could not but be judged a most destructive thing, considering the strength of the Nation, and the Interest of all the good people, was not a little bound up in the <reg orig="Armies">Army's</reg> safe and well consisting together. And thus I cannot but remember, that some of the chief of those men who declaimed so much against the Officers taking their pay, and not going a warfare at their own charge, did at the same time while they were gazing at the mote in their <reg orig="brethrens">brethren's</reg> eye, never reflect upon the beam in their own, they holding several places under the Commonwealth more beneficial <reg orig="then">than</reg> most individual Officers pay in the Army, so much declaimed against.</p>

<p>Now for the particulars expressed in the printed Narrative, I shall consider them apart, and give the true and genuine signification to divers things, there picked up, and put together with the greatest disadvantage and prejudice that is possible.</p>

<p>On the twelfth instant divers Members came to the House with an intention to inform them of our insufficiency to do that good we were called for, as so constituted, and to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to resign their Power (as being a thing most safe and advisable) whence they received it; and if their concurrence could not be had, <reg orig="iudged">judged</reg> it their duty to do it in their particulars, and did it accordingly, by withdrawing themselves accompanied with the Speaker, to the Horse-Chamber in <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> where near eighty Members voluntarily subscribed a Resignation of their Power to the Lord General, to which place none were compelled to come, and in which resignation none were desired to <reg orig="ioyn">join</reg> but such as had a freedom thereto, as was there often <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> by some Members present; which resignation by the Speaker, accompanied likewise with the said Members, was delivered to the Lord General. What happened to those few Members that remained in the House I know <reg orig="nat">not</reg>; but am conscious of no force (as is intimated) either intended or offered to the Parliament <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> a House was sitting.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Thursday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 13.</head>

<p>By an Express from Scotland thus: The Highlanders have had a great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Hough, from whence they marched North with a Body of horse and foot, intending to meet the Lord Seafort: who has made lamentable <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg> upon the English horse, which they stole out of the <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> stables. And the Earl of Kinoul lately appearing <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Glans with a party of horse, had a Design to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the horse belonging to the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> as they came from watering, lying in <reg orig="ambuscado">ambuscade</reg> for that purpose, thinking thereby to increase his number, and to procure exchange for his men taken at Eghil; and coming at first with a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> party riding into Glans, took three of our men, which Major Ducket, who commanded Col: <reg orig="Riches">Riche's</reg> Troop there, having notice of it, sent out his Quartermaster with twenty horse to discover his party, who advancing with two files of <reg orig="musquetiers">musketeers</reg> that were to make good a bridge, gave them a charge, and routed and dispersed their whole Body, took the Lord Kinoul, and fourteen men, all much wounded and divers horse; pursued the rest even to the very Bogs: but Major Ramsey escaped. We had one man killed, and three wounded; but the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> loss were far greater.</p>

<p>This day sevennight the Ministers and six of the Elders of the French Church, and a Marquis of France, were with his Highness the Lord Protector, to congratulate, declaring their <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of engagement to bless God for Him, and their hope of protection to themselves, and the rest of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people from him; to which, his Highness returned them a very satisfying Answer: So that there is like to be that <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Protestant Churches of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> parts, which yet hath not been, which will be a great blow to Antichrist, and the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> means to exalt the Throne of the Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Amsterdam </em>it is certified, That the Dutch Deputies are arrived, and have made their <em>Reverts</em> concerning the <em>Treaty</em>, which the people generally desire and comment upon, to be for &mdash;</p>

<head level="2">Peace, Peace.</head>

<hr />

<p><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>