<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout158">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 158
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2">Impartially comprising</head>
<p><i>The daily proceedings of <unclear>His Highness the</unclear> Lord Protector and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State, and the several <unclear>Ordinances</unclear> by those established, for the <unclear><reg orig="setling">settling</reg></unclear> of the weighty affairs of this <unclear>Commonwealth; With</unclear> the effect of the Treaty between His <unclear>Highness and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg></unclear> of the States of Holland, and the concluding of <unclear>a firm</unclear> Peace between <em>England, Holland</em> and <em>Denmark</em>, upon <unclear>honourable <reg orig="termes">terms</reg></unclear>, and promise of Satisfaction, and Security. The K. of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> Letter to <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>, and his promise not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to assist him with men, money and ammunition, but also with his person. Also a great Victory obtained in <em>Scotland</em> by the English, against Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg>, 16 killed on the place, Captain Stuart and 65 horse taken, and the whole party totally routed. Together with choice Intelligence from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, relating the gallant attempt of the None such and Assistance <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> against <unclear><em>Cooquet</em></unclear> in France, their shooting 230 great shot into the Town, and taking a Dutchman with eight Guns, as she was going into Brest.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> the 23 of <em>Decemb.</em>, to <em>Friday</em> the 30 of <em>December.</em>. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, Decemb. 23.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The King of France is <reg orig="return'd">returned</reg> from St. German to Paris, where great preparations are making for a BALL to be danced by all the great Ladies of the Court, wherewith His Majesty seems to be much taken, and hath spent some time <unclear>himself in giving</unclear> directions about it. The Commissioners appointed for the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of the Prince of Conde, have had several meetings, and have drawn up several Charges in Order thereunto. <em>Charles Stuart</em> and his Party have had several <unclear>Consultations</unclear> together at the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em>, concerning his affairs in England and Scotland, and it was concluded, that if they break off the Treaty with the Dutch, the States would doubtless make a diversion in Scotland, and send assistance to the Highlands, and so further his design against England.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>In my last Week, Scout <unclear>gave you</unclear> a hint of a proclamation published by the Lord Protector, which was this day extant in print, a copy whereof take as followeth.</p>
<head level="3">By the Lord Protector.</head>
<p><i><unclear>A PROCLAMATION</unclear> of His Highness, with the consent of his Council, for the <unclear>continuing</unclear> all Persons, being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, until his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> further direction.</i></p>
<p>OLIVER, Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, considering that whereas the <unclear>exercise</unclear> of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, is invested and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council, and left thereupon the <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and ordinary course of Justice in the Commonwealth (if remedy were not provided) might receive <unclear>interruption</unclear>, his Highness in his care of the State, and <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice thereof, <unclear>reserving</unclear> to future consideration the reformation and redress of any abuses of <reg orig="Mis-government">Misgovernment</reg>, upon better knowledge taken thereof, is pleased, and doth hereby expressly <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, declare and ordain, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, who have power until the meeting of the next Parliament, to make <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary; which shall be binding and in force until Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same: That all persons who on the tenth day of this instant December were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction or Government, within this Commonwealth, shall be, and shall so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and places respectively as formerly they held and enjoyed the same, and not otherwise, until his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which <unclear>respect</unclear> or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice, and all proceedings of what Nature soever, in Courts of common Law, or Equity, or in the court of Admiralty, or by commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said <pb n="2" /> tenth day of this instant December, <unclear>until</unclear> further order given by his Highness therein: And <unclear>that in the <!-- 1 word --></unclear> (for preservation of the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, and for safety of the State) all the said persons, of whatsoever place, Degree, or condition, may not fail every one severally according to his respective place, Office or charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> the former Government was in being.</p>
<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 21 of December, in the Year of Our <em>Lord</em>, 1653.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday, Decemb. 23.</i></head>
<p>The Western Letters <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, That the Dutch are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in those parts, insomuch, that it is very hard for any Vessel to pass by the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> End without a good Convoy; and they have lately taken a Ship of London coming from New-England, laden with Masts, <reg orig="Bever-skins">Beaver skins</reg>, and the like commodities. But in retaliation thereof, a private Man of War hath brought two Dutch Vessels into the Holy Island, laden with pitch, <reg orig="tarre">tar</reg>, and other useful commodities, of which there was some scarcity.</p>
<p><em>Kenmore</em> endeavours to raise men and monies in the South of Scotland, with whom he resolves to make inroads into the borders of <em>England</em> (if not timely prevented) and the new Levies are gone into the North, to receive monies, arms and ammunition, which they are induced to believe was sent from their King, by his Agents in Holland.</p>
<p>From Holland 'tis certified, that the people murmur very much that the Treaty holds so long with England, and <unclear>that</unclear> nothing will come of it. <unclear>Of these</unclear> there are (though but few) who are good <unclear>Patriots</unclear>, and <unclear>desire</unclear> an Union with England, as the <unclear>greatest interest</unclear> of their Country, but can do nothing, because <reg orig="over-powred">overpowered</reg> in all their <unclear><reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg></unclear>. They are making great preparations against Spring, and 30 new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> are now upon the <unclear>stocks</unclear>, to be added <unclear>to</unclear> the former 30 already built; they say, <unclear>the fleet</unclear> will consist of above 100 <unclear>sail, and <em>Tromp</em></unclear> is ordered to go into the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg> with <unclear>12 Men of War</unclear> to <unclear>Lord at <!-- 2 words -->; they have their eyes every where, both at home and abroad, which <!-- 2 words --> more than ordinary <!-- 1 word --> in <!-- 1 word -->.</unclear></p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Decemb. 26.</head>
<p>Papers were this day presented to the Right Honourable Council touching a Petition from the Town of Lin, concerning the Fen-drainers.</p>
<p>This day likewise a <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> was shot to death on Tower-hill, for killing a Seaman (presently after the late mutiny) in cool <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>.</p>
<p>From Scotland thus. The march Northwards of most of the <reg orig="enemies">enemies'</reg> forces goes forward, and they are drawing together about <reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg>. The 16 instant, in the Evening Col. Blakiter, and Major Crawford, with 22 Troops of horse and Dragoons being about 2000 came thither. Lord <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg> is come to Lough Tay with 500 horse and foot. About 100 horse and foot from <reg orig="Weem">Weems</reg>, and the Tutor of <reg orig="Macgrigger">Macgriggor</reg> with 300 from <reg orig="Loughaber">Lochaber</reg>, are marching thither, and <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> hath promised to return speedily, or spare them what strength he <reg orig="cen">can</reg>. What the design of this conjunction is, is not known, but they talk of having 3000 horse and foot at next <reg orig="Ranezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>: They have not left in Stermont, a part of Perthshire, so much as a <reg orig="plad">plaid</reg>, or any thing that is wearable, nor <reg orig="anp">any</reg> kind of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>.</p>
<p>Dalkeith <unclear>22</unclear> Decemb. A party of Cap. <reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg> took Cap. Stuart, and four more, killed three, besides divers other taken by parties in other places, among which <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> <unclear>Patwick</unclear> Hay, <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> Col. Cambal, the Laird Lugton, Cap. Crichton, and others of quality. Yesterday Cap. Hart pursued Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg> from Borthwick <reg orig="Bray">Brae</reg>, where he was at <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, traced them by the snow, routed them, took 65 horse, 16 prisoners, killed divers, few escaped without wound. Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg> and Major Erwin, his Major, both wounded and fled. We had one slain, and 16 wounded. <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> and most of their heads, are with 500 horse, and many foot, passed to the North, over the skirts of Bays William, 3 miles in the <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear> and <unclear>Tividale.</unclear>. Middleton sent a Letter to <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, that col. <unclear><reg orig="Drumond">Drummond</reg></unclear> was 26 November, <reg orig="imbarked">embarked</reg> from the <unclear>Brill</unclear> with <unclear>1500</unclear> <reg orig="Valuntiers">Volunteers</reg> of divers Nations. The titular Scots King also sent a Letter to <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, dated 12 November, telling him, That the Kings of France and Denmark, the Duke of <reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg>, the Emperor, and princes of Germany, are not willing to assist him with men, but have assured him of a large proportion of Arms, Ammunition and monies, and that he would be with them immediately after the receiving of <reg orig="Drumond">Drummond</reg> and his forces, whose <reg orig="Head-quarters">Headquarters</reg> <pb n="4" /> are to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> at Loughern, the most fortified place in the Highlands.</p>
<p><i>The 21 of December</i>, the Bailiffs of the Town of Yarmouth, received the Proclamation to proclaim the Lord Protector, with an <unclear>Order</unclear> for publishing it in that Town, and the 22 day accordingly it was proclaimed in a solemn <reg orig="maner">manner</reg> in four places of this Town. The Bailiffs and Aldermen in Scarlet, and 48 in their Gowns. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and some of the Officers accompanied them; and as soon as the Proclamation was published, the great guns in the Town and Forts were fired. The <reg orig="generallity">generality</reg> of people there, are very well satisfied.</p>
<p>The like Letters came from Bristol, <reg orig="Exceter">Exeter</reg>, Salop, and many other places, much to the same purpose.</p> 
<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> it is advertised, that captain <em>Crispin</em>, with the Assistance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, is come in hither, he was in a storm near Scilly, but afterward sailed Eastward of <reg orig="Tor Bay">Torbay</reg>, he hath been with cap. <em>Hatfel</em> and went from thence about the 10 instant, and hath been a great check to the Brest men of war, after which he with the Non-such that went out with him, on the 16 instant anchored in <unclear>couquet</unclear> road, where the boats were sent to fetch of two vessels, one laden with wine from Nantz, the other <unclear><reg orig="lsight">light</reg></unclear>, and there were then in the same place near 30 sail more, two of which were supposed to be men of war, who with the rest hauled close under the houses, which were lined with what <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> that country could afford, with which (it being half <reg orig="ebbe">ebb</reg>) they beat off our boats, but by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> providence without <unclear><reg orig="losse">loss</reg></unclear> to us; the Non-such boat going in with a small Gun ours also returned with them, and attempted to set the said vessels on fire, but could not make way for our boats, so that Cap. <em>Crispin</em> was constrained to fire out of his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Town, and upon the vessels, against whom he made about two hundred and thirty great shot, which in <unclear>sight</unclear> of our men did the enemy very much spoil; the enemy made use of <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one Gun, which they did keep playing all the time at our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> we did beat them from it.</p>
<p>That afternoon we discovered a ship of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> playing in towards Brest, and the Non-such sailed after her, and that evening took her, she being a great Holland Fly-boat of eight guns, laden with wine from Nantz.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Wednesday Decemb. 28.</head>
<p>The Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em> arrived at <unclear><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></unclear> the 15 of Nov. and was nobly <reg orig="entertain'd">entertained</reg> by the <unclear>Citizens</unclear>; from whence he sent Letters to Court, and <unclear><reg orig="stayes">stays</reg></unclear> in the City, till he receives answer of them from his Majesty. The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath sent an extraordinary <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> to the States of the United Provinces, with Proposition <unclear><!-- 2 characters -->nding</unclear> to the making an <reg orig="attonement">atonement</reg> and reconciliation between England and Holland; of which she seems to be very desirous, and earnestly endeavours the promoting of so pious and good work.</p>
<p>The King of <em>Denmark</em> is still at <reg orig="Coppenhagen">Copenhagen</reg>, and hath lately sent more Ships to the Sound, for the better <unclear>preservation</unclear> of that place from <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> Invasion; his guilty conscience making him <unclear>dread</unclear> the English.</p>
<p>The Imperial Diet in Germany is not yet ended, there being so many businesses in agitation, that either it <unclear>must <!-- 2 words --> a</unclear> long time, or else leave many things undecided <unclear>till</unclear> the next Diet; <unclear>chiefly</unclear> that great point concerning the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg>: some of the States of the Empire finding many difficulties in point of security, about the payment of the <unclear>first hundred</unclear> thousand pound: So that the King of Scots hath little hopes of Supplies from them who are not able to supply their own wants.</p>
<p>This day produced an Ordinance of the Lord Protector and his Council, For alteration of several Names and Forms heretofore used in Courts, Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, &amp;c. and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Proceedings in Courts of Law, Justice and equity, within the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and <unclear>Ireland</unclear>, according to the present Government. The effect whereof followeth:</p>
<p>That the Lord Protector finding it to be most necessary that some speedy and effectual course be taken, for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Names and Forms to be used in patents, commissions, and proceedings in courts of justice, the said Lord Protector, by, and with the consent of his said Council, and in performance of, and according to the power and trust reposed in him and them, doth Declare and Ordain, And be it by the Authority aforesaid declared and ordained, That in all courts of law, justice or equity, and in all writs, grants, patents, commissions, indictments, informations, suits, returns of writs, and in all fines recoveries, exemplifications, <unclear>recognizances, proofs</unclear> and proceedings of law, justice or equity, within the said commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, instead of the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title and <unclear><reg orig="Teste">Test</reg></unclear> of <i>the Keepers of the Liberty of England</i> <pb n="6" /> <i>by Authority of Parliament</i> (heretofore used, that from and after the six and twentieth day of December, 1653, the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title and <reg orig="Teste">Test</reg> of the <i>Lord Protector (for the time being) of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging</i>, shall be used, and no other; And the Date shall be, <i>In the Year of our Lord</i>, and no other.</p>
<p>And all duties, profits, penalties, fines, amerciamants, and forfeitures whatsoever, are to be prosecuted, sued forth, and recovered in the same manner, and all Judges, Justices, Officers and Ministers of Justice whatsoever, are to take notice hereof, and are required to <unclear>proceed</unclear> accordingly.</p>
<p>Likewise all <unclear>writs</unclear>, commissions, indictments, informations, actions, suits, <reg orig="bils">bills</reg> or <unclear>plaints</unclear> now depending in any of the courts of Record at Westminster, or any other court of Record, and all pleas, demurrers, <unclear>continuances</unclear>, and proceedings whatsoever in all and every such indictments, informations, actions, &amp;c shall be returnable as before specified.</p>
<p>And after the 16 day of December all indictments, presentments, inquisitions for treasons, felonies, <unclear><reg orig="mis prisions">misprisions</reg></unclear>, and other trespasses and <reg orig="misdemeanors">misdemeanours</reg>, shall be proceeded upon, for and on the behalf of the Lord Protector, in such sort manner and form, as they might have done before. And all indictments, &amp;c which did depend formerly <unclear><reg orig="in">on</reg></unclear> any court of Justice, <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of the Keepers of the Liberty, shall not be discontinued or put without day by this <unclear>change</unclear> of Government, but be prosecuted and sued forth in manner and form as formerly; And that there shall be no <unclear>variance touching</unclear> the proceedings in the Name of the Lord <em>Protector</em>, as concerning any error to be <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> or <unclear>objected for the same</unclear>.</p>
<p>And lastly, all Oaths to be given to any <unclear>Grand</unclear> or petty Jury, or to or for any Witnesses to give in evidence to any such Jury or Juries and all other Oaths where the <em>Keepers of the, &amp;c.</em> was wont to be used, the same shall be given in the Name of the Lord <em>Protector</em>, any Law, Usage or custom <reg orig="not withstanding">notwithstanding</reg>. And it is lastly Ordained, by the authority aforesaid, that such forms and course of proceedings as were used in the Name and time of the Keepers, &amp;c. in all causes of which no alteration is made in this Ordinance, shall stand and continue to be so used and observed as formerly; And all indictments &amp;c. made with such alterations as shall be necessary, to be good and effectual in law, any custom notwithstanding.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, December 29.</i></head>
<p>There are several other Ordinances published by the command of his Highness and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear>. <em>Viz</em>. For continuing the Rates and <unclear>Customs</unclear> of the Excise as formerly, till March 25 next ensuing. Also an Ordinance for continuation of one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Redemption of Captives</i>, to continue <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the third of October, 1654. Likewise they Ordered to be printed, an Ordinance for the <unclear>reviving</unclear> of an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for probate of <reg orig="Wils">Wills</reg>, and granting Administrations</i>, which is to continue in full power and force, until the <unclear>first</unclear> day of April <unclear>next</unclear>, And <i>Richard Lucy, John Hildesley, Nathaniel Barton, <unclear>Jervas Bennet, Anthony Rous</unclear>, Joachim Mathews, Edward Cludd, <unclear>Thomas Wood</unclear></i>, <unclear>Esquires, and <i> Robert Titchburne</i>, Alderman</unclear> of London, <unclear>has added to the Judges mentioned <!-- approx. 4 words -->, to execute all</unclear> and every of <unclear>the Powers given by the said Act, as <!-- 1 word --> as any of the Judges are renamed may do</unclear>.</p>
<p><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> is preparing for his <unclear><reg orig="Highnesses">Highness'</reg> residence</unclear>, and the Old <unclear><reg orig="Councel">Council</reg></unclear> Chamber is <unclear><!-- 4 characters -->ing for</unclear> His Honourable <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear> to <unclear>meet in the <!-- approx. 4 words --></unclear> have personally treated several times with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council, and I <unclear>confidently hope</unclear> (I may without offence affirm) there is a <reg orig="firme">firm</reg> Peace concluded <unclear>between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em></unclear>, all things concerning the matter being <unclear>assented</unclear> to on <unclear>both sides, but not</unclear> the Form and Ceremony: And for our comfort, they have promised <unclear>Satisfaction</unclear>, Honour and Security; Denmark also is to be included in the Articles. <i>Blessed therefore be the Lord who <unclear>administer all</unclear> our Changes and Revolutions hath brought such wonderful things to pass; for the good of this Nation, and the comfort of his people and Servants; O let his Name be established here <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, and his <unclear>praises</unclear> sung from Generation to Generation.</i></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Montague</em> is added to the Council of State, besides those whom I mentioned the last Week. Also Mr. <unclear><em>Touglogh</em></unclear> is made Secretary, and Mr. <em>Scobel</em> and Mr. <em>Jesop</em> are Clerks to the Council. Since the Members <unclear>delivered</unclear> their Declaration to His Highness, divers that were absent have <unclear>freely</unclear> subscribed.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church over against the Stile <unclear>that goes to Stepney</unclear>, in Trumpet yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in <unclear>Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg></unclear>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, <unclear>the swelling</unclear> of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness of the</unclear> ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues; of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many <unclear>that</unclear> have been thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg>. If you <unclear><reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at</unclear> the white <unclear>Lyon</unclear> in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in <unclear>Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they</unclear> will direct you to him. The History of New England, <unclear>from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year</unclear>, 1652. With the Names of all their <unclear>Governors, Magistrates, and eminent Ministers. Printed for <em>Nath. Brook</em> at the Angel in <reg orig="Corn hil">Cornhill</reg></unclear>, 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><i><unclear>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according</unclear> to the late <unclear>Act</unclear> for Printing.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><unclear><em>London</em>, Printed by</unclear> R. WOOD, 1653.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>