<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout178">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 178
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>The great Rising of the <reg orig="French-men">Frenchmen</reg> against the English; the furious charging and assaulting them at St. <em>Mallows</em>; the <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> event and <reg orig="successe">success</reg> thereof; the number killed and wounded; the plundering of all the English Merchants and <unclear>Factors</unclear>; and his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proclamation thereupon. The advancing of part of the English fleet towards the Coast of France, the setting up of the <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> Standard; the <unclear><reg orig="cleering">clearing</reg></unclear> of the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Ocean, the number of ships taken, &amp; the sinking of the stately Pelican with 15 <reg orig="Tuns">Tonnes</reg> of Gold. A great Victory obtained by the Portugals against the Dutch, the taking of about 40 Towns and Castles; and a Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector touching the Netherlands. The Royal Mandate of the Queen of Sweden touching England, the setting forth of 40 men of war, and 30 000 men; A true Relation of the present state and condition of <em>Mr. John <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em>; And lamentable news from <em>Scotland.</em></i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 5. to <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> <unclear>12. 1654.</unclear></p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>May</em> the 5.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>It is the interest of a wise Prince to own the Authority of the Officers of a Commonwealth, and it is more profitable and consistent with a National Freedom, for the people to seek after perfection and excellency of Government, to advance <unclear><reg orig="ehe">the</reg></unclear> Arts, Sciences, and Professions of Artificers, <reg orig="then">than</reg> it is for others to thirst after the Titles of high and mighty, magnificent and excellent, &amp;c. Pish, they are but vain things that <unclear>flatterets</unclear> through upon poor dust and ashes, in expectation of favours<i>: Colours by Painters are used to <reg orig="beautifie">beautify</reg> rotten <unclear>Posts</unclear></i>; mark that Gentlemen: For, had not <em>Nero</em> the wicked as great Titles as ever the best Emperor in the world deserved: Yet for <reg orig="vertue">virute</reg>, none could compare with pious <em><reg orig="Canutus">Canute</reg></em>, K. of <em>England</em>, who lived in the year of God, 1015.
<pb n="1" />
for, <em>observe</em>, being by one of his Courtiers told &amp; flattered how all things went according to his Will, and that all his Undertakings prospered, and not an Enemy ever stood before him, but be brought <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> Victories out of the field; thereupon he put him in mind of his <reg orig="Greatnesse">Greatness</reg>, and that he was like unto a <em>God</em> amongst men: But this good Prince being mindful of the inconstant estate of worldly Affairs, that he might let his flatterers see their <em>Error</em>, commanded his Chair of Estate to be placed upon the <reg orig="Sea shore">Seashore</reg>, at the beginning of the <reg orig="Floud">Flood</reg>; and as the Tide came in, he said thus: <i>This Land wherein I sit belongeth to me, none ever <reg orig="crost">crossed</reg> my <reg orig="commandement">commandment</reg> without punishment; I forbid thee to rise or enter upon my Dominion, therefore take heed that thou wet not any Limbs of thy Lords Body</i>. But the Sea coming on, as it was wont, without respect of wetting the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> feet, His Majesty thereupon removed back, and rising, said, <i>Let all the Inhabitants of the Earth know, that the power of Kings is frivolous and vain, and that no man is worthy of so great a Name, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> He, whom the Heaven, the Fire, the Earth, do obey, by a continual and <reg orig="unchangable">unchangeable</reg> decree</i>. After that day, <em><reg orig="Canutus">Canute</reg></em> wore not the Crown on his head; but did the duty of a Governor to the people, as their faithful Servant. <i>O God increase the number of such <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> in England, that the people may have cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>, and say, The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh, blessed be the Name of the Lord</i>. But to the subsequent matter.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and her Highness Protectress, are gone to <em>Hampton Court</em>. The Yeomen of his Highness Guard wait by turns Monthly, and Mr. <em>Ingoldsby</em> (brother to col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>) is made captain of the Guard. Their coats are grey cloth with black Velvet <reg orig="collers">collars</reg>, and black Velvet and silver lace and trimming. col. <em>Nathaniel Fiennes</em> is added a member to the council.</p>
<p>The French Ambassador makes many applications to his Highness, by way of negotiating a peace between <em>England</em> and his Majesty (who is now of years to be crowned very suddenly) if he propound <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg> safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, he need not doubt of his Errand, <i>For it is a sign of godliness to be at peace with all men; yet peace cannot <reg orig="tryumph">triumph</reg>, except Reason ruleth</i>.</p>
<p>The Ambassador from the King of <em>Denmark</em> has presented his Letters credential from the King his Master, and on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> last he had audience before his Highness, where he congratulated him in his place of Government, and seemed to acknowledge it a <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> that so much of the differences were taken up by the Treaty with the Dutch, and hoped all would conduce to a happy peace, to the advancement of the Protestant Religion, and stopping the <unclear>affusion</unclear> of <unclear><!-- approx. 2.5 lines --></unclear></p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>There is to be a general <reg orig="Rendevous">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs by the <em>English</em> fleet very suddenly; and Rear-Admiral <em>Lawson</em> is already gone towards the Northern parts with 20 men of war; the <em>Fairfax</em> is Admiral; and 'tis said he hath landed 6 or 7000 men near the Isles of <unclear><em>Orkney</em></unclear>, who intend to make up suddenly towards Gen. <em>Middleton,</em> who has sent the Lord <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> into the West with 500 resolute men of fortune to raise the people in general.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched to <em>Tain</em>, where he saw the enemy, but could not come at them, for want of Boats, the water being broad and very impetuous, which <reg orig="constrain'd">constrained</reg> him to return back to <em>Dingwel</em>.</p>
<p>From <em>Ireland</em> they write, That the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em>, and his <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of Officers, have ordered that 5000 horse and foot be sent to the North of <em>Scotland</em>, and col. <em>Venables</em> is taking care to transport 'em, <i>good shipping attend them</i>. The General <reg orig="councel">council</reg> hath cast Lots for the Provinces, for satisfying the Arrears of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, and the Lot of the General Officers is taken in <unclear><em>Munster</em></unclear>. The standing Army from <em>June</em> 1649. are content to take two Thirds at present. The Officers of the Army have <reg orig="joyntly">jointly</reg> subscribed a Letter to his Highness, owning the Government which is invested in Him.</p>
<p>Strange and various are the reports from the Isle of <em>Jersey</em>, touching Mr. <em>John <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em>; so that I shall <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to reduce my <em>Pen</em> from inserting <reg orig="any Thing">anything</reg> that may prove obnoxious, or disconsonant from the Rules of Verity; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, that by Tradition of Circumstances, 'tis made out, that he is <em><unclear>mortuus est</unclear></em>; But whether it be under the notion of feeling the pulses of the people, or alienating the minds of their affections from the present Government, I cannot administer any <em>Antidote</em>; though preventing <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg> be ever held more safe <reg orig="then">than</reg> removing. &mdash; But from all sudden and untimely Deaths, <i>Good Lord, deliver us.</i></p>
<p>By the last Express from <em>Scotland</em>, thus: We conceive the Enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Rendevous">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagued with their inroads upon the Lowlands, where they burnt and destroyed all the stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reason of their mischiefs and our <unclear><reg orig="losse">loss</reg></unclear> is want of  intelligence from amongst them; for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce <reg orig="squeez">squeeze</reg> ten true words out of them. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> we hear hath made his way out of <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, where col. <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> his horse,
<pb n="3" />
but it proved not feasible; for indeed we have an enemy as subtle as resolute, and they play fast and loose with us in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York</reg></em> coming to them, and their thoughts extend so far, that there will then be a general Rising of the people: <i>But alas (poor Gentlemen) 'tis dubious whether he will <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> in the Holy War, as the Scots calls it; or draw his Sword against those which are sanctified, as the Saints term it.</i></p>
<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em>, May 8.</head>
<p>Upon the advance of the English men of war towards <em>France</em> and seizing of 40 of their ships, the Frenchmen rose at St <em>Mallows</em>, assaulted the English Merchants in their houses, charged them with pistol and sword, plundered their houses, wounded many, whereof 7 are said to be dead; but the King hearing of it, set forth a <em>Proclamation</em> to protect the <em>English</em>. The <em>Dutch Pelican</em>, and a <em>Genoa</em> ship, are cast away by storm in the <em>Sicilian</em> Sea, with 15 <reg orig="Tuns">Tonnes</reg> of Gold.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 9.</head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector agreed upon a <em>Declaration</em> to be published, setting apart <em>Tuesday</em> the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, for a <reg orig="publique">public</reg> day of Thanksgiving, for the <em>Peace</em> concluded between this <em>Commonwealth</em>, and that of the <em>United Provinces</em>, and for the late seasonable Rain; a true copy whereof is here inserted.</p>
<p><unclear>That</unclear> this hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> a Nation of blessings, in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the <reg orig="out-stretched">outstretched</reg> arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment and wonder, <i>Who can deny?</i> Ask we the Nations of this matter, and they will <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>; and <unclear>indeed</unclear> the dispensations of the Lord have been, as if he had said, <i>England, thou art my <reg orig="first-born">firstborn</reg>, my delight among the Nations:</i> Under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us. The Lord having added another Link to this <em>golden Chain</em> of his loving <reg orig="kindnes">kindness</reg>, by giving us a peace with Our <em><reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg></em> the <em>United Provinces</em> (whereby he hath not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> stopped a great <unclear>issue</unclear> of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>; but <em>we</em> trust also given us hearts to unite our <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> and strength for the mutual defence of each other) <unclear><reg orig="cals">calls</reg></unclear> for great Return of Thanks for the same. It is hereby thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, &amp; <unclear>for</unclear> the thankful acknowledgement of this blessing of peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other blessings. And let us not forget our other Mercies; was not the Earth so unusually <unclear>prent</unclear> up, that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg>, and did cause the Beast of the field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth, that he hath turned those fears into the expectation <pb n="4" /> of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord imparted this mercy to us: Did any amongst us foreknow it was coming? Was it not by stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that immediately before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy? And doth not this bespeak? <i>1. That the manner of conveying this mercy is the best part of the mercy. 2. That the Lord has not cast us off, that his Spirit yet strives with us, that he hath a people of his love amongst us, and loves the Nation so far as to provoke it to be in love with calling upon the Name of the Lord for better things <reg orig="then">than</reg> Corn and Wine. 3. That he knows best how, and when to answer the expectation of the Husbandman, and when to hear, even the mourning of the brute Beast, who will yet much more hear the desires of him that fear him, and that in the <unclear>fittest</unclear> season. 4. That the Heavens having thus declared the glory of God, and the Earth answering thereunto in its fruitfulness, why should not we be melted and <reg orig="softned">softened</reg>, humbling <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> under these marvellous kindnesses, and abounding unto all fruitfulness in <unclear>a</unclear> very good word and work of love; And if every place hath been made partaker of his <unclear><reg orig="showres">showers</reg></unclear>, why <reg orig="shou'd">should</reg> not we (laying aside our differences) be <reg orig="inlarged">enlarged</reg> also each to other? 5. That seeing the Lord hath been thus universal in this mercy, why should we not universally turn from the National evils, and vain <unclear>prejudice</unclear>, which are yet too superstitiously and customarily exercised amongst us, which we need not repeat here, because they are too well-known, and We trust will be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg> by <unclear>the</unclear> godly Ministers who shall be called to preach unto the people upon this occasion?</i></p>
<head level="3">Given at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> this 9th of <em>May</em>, 1654.</head>
<p>The Lord Protector, and his Council, hath passed <i>An Ordinance for further doubling upon and finishing the sale of Deans, Deans and Chapters <unclear>hands</unclear>; and of <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories, <unclear>Gleab-lands</unclear></i>, &amp;c. Wherein is ordained, That over and above the sum of 300 000 l. appointed to be borrowed upon the security held forth by the first recited Act of Parl. and over and above the sum of 120 000 <em>li.</em> more, borrowed upon the Security held forth in the two last recited Acts, or either of them, the sum of 20 000 l. shall be further borrowed upon the security of such of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg> respectively exposed to sale by the said Acts, &amp;c.</p>
<p>As touching the Report of Mr. <em><reg orig="Lilburn's">Lilburne's</reg></em> being <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> and executed at <em>Jersey</em>, where indeed (<em>poor Gentleman</em>) he is a prisoner, 'tis false: <i>God forbid it should be so</i>: And this may <reg orig="onely">only</reg> serve for a confutation, that there was no such thing in agitation, but only a <unclear>settling</unclear> of the <em>Government</em>, and adding 7 <em>Jurats</em> to the Judge of the <unclear><em>Land.</em></unclear></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 10.</i></head>
<p>The Lord Protector and his Council have set forth an additional Ordinance for the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>; a copy whereof take as followeth:</p>
<p>Whereas by an Ordinance of the 17 of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for continuing the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg></i>, it is next after the Rates therein specified, generally declared and provided, <i>That all other goods and <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg> (except <unclear><reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg></unclear>, Coin, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron, imported, or to be imported) not specified, or therein rated, should pay after the rate of 5.1 per centum, according as the same are charged by the book of Rates, for the custom to be paid by the first buyer one shilling.</i></p>
<p>Be it ordained, and it is hereby ordained and declared by his Highness, with the advice and consent of his Council, That the said clause be null and void; and instead thereof, Be it hereby ordained and declared, That all other goods and <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg>, mentioned in the said book of Rates for the Customs, (except <reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg> Corn, Victual, <unclear>arms</unclear>, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron, and Wools of sheep) imported, or to be imported, which are not in the said Rates of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, before or otherwise charged, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hereafter pay <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, after the rate of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant or Importer, and the same is to be collected accordingly. And to the end, the whole Receipts of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> may be the better reduced into one Cash, and the charge and number of Officers thereby retrenched, It is hereby ordained by Authority aforesaid, That from and after the 25 day of <em>March</em> last, the Revenue of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> shall be <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> shall be but one Receipt, and so accounted for; and that all Receipts and <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> heretofore taken or kept of any payment of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> or new Import, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any additional Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, and designed to any separate use or uses whatsoever, shall from thenceforth cease and be void, and be brought and reduced to one general Cash and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Revenue. Provided nevertheless, that the <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg> of all fines and forfeitures, imported and received since the 25 of <em>March</em> last, or that hereafter shall be imposed and received, shall be still kept in an <reg orig="Accompt">Accompt</reg> apart, and be paid out towards the maintenance of widows and maimed <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, according to Ordinance of Parliament of the 13 of <em>July</em>, 1647.</p>
<p>And it is hereby for the further Relief of the said <reg orig="Widowes">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, ordained, That from and after the said 25 day of <pb n="6" /> <em>March</em> last, there shall be, out of the general Cash and Revenue of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, allowed the certain yearly sum of 26 260 pounds, to be paid weekly by equal portions out of the said <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Receipt, unto such person or persons, as is, are, or shall be appointed thereunto by his Highness and his Council, and be <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for <reg orig="imploying">employing</reg> and disposing thereof to the use aforesaid. Which said yearly <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of 26 260 pounds is to be in lieu of all and every sum and sums of money assigned by any Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, out of any the Receipts of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, for the relief of the said <reg orig="Widowes">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, other <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg> of fines and forfeitures before excepted; And the present Commissioners of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, or any three of them, shall have power from time to time to issue out all moneys, either delivered over unto them, by the commissioners preceding them, or which hath, or shall be received by them since the 25 of <em>March</em> last, according as they are, or shall be directed by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, or by Authority thereof. And the said Commissioners for <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, and their Sub commissioners, are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to make repayment of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> to any person whatsoever, for any goods imported upon the Exportation thereof, in such sort as the late commissioners might have done before the 25 day of <em>March</em> last, It appearing unto them that the duty of the <unclear>said</unclear> Goods have been fully paid; any former Clause, Article, or provision to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
<p><i>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>
<p>The Committee have spent some time in order to the regulating of the Law, and many gallant things are in agitation for <unclear>ease</unclear> of the people, and the due <unclear>administration</unclear> of Equity and Justice: in pursuance whereof, these particulars are said before them, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<p><i>1. That Justice is the Mother of <reg orig="Vertues">Virtues</reg>, the right Spouse of Fortitude, for which Governors are created; and by whose <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> they rule.</i></p>
<p><i>2. Justice allots not pardon to the Wicked, which might bring the hazard of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</i></p>
<p><i>3. Justice requireth Equity, Equity judgeth with Lenity, Lenity produceth Laws, which sometimes must extend to extremity.</i></p>
<p>There is great hopes of a universal Redemption from slavery, and the enjoyment of true Liberty and Freedom is now arriving at the <unclear>Haven of <em>England</em>, where 'tis housed the <reg orig="free born">freeborn</reg> people in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>, <!-- approx. 12 words --></unclear></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 11</head>
<p>This day afforded memorable intelligence from several parts; as the concluding of a firm <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> and friendship between <em>England</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, with ample satisfaction on both sides. Yet before it could be brought to a period, great were the obstructions against it, especially by the Nobility: But the grand Chancellor, and his son Count <em>Erick</em> (by the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Commissioners) did manage this great Work with so great wisdom and dexterity, that her Majesty was pleased to vouchsafe her Royal Condescensions, to a final Agreement, and to manifest incomparable affection to his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, declaring unto the Lord <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em>, That she would have the honour to make the <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> with the Lord Protector, and in respect to him, and she said, because my Lord Ambassador treated with her like a Gentleman, <i>Avec tout la franchise &amp; rondeur, &amp; non pas comme un. Marchand</i>, she did consent to more <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other could have obtained from her. Nevertheless, 40 men of war, and 30 000 Swedes are in a readiness to <unclear><reg orig="archieve">achieve</reg></unclear> something: Mum for that!</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> it is certified, That the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador has received audience of his Majesty, to whom he imparted the joyful <reg orig="Tydings">Tidings</reg> of a Victory obtained by the <em>Portugal</em> fleet against the <em>Hollanders</em> in <em>Brazil</em>; and of the taking of <em>Reclif</em> and about 40 other Towns and Castles from them. Which doth not a little <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> the Royal Family: <i>Win gold, and wear it; 'tis fit <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> should have their own.</i> Upon a delicate Banquet between the King and Queen, on the 3 of May, the K of <em>Scots</em>, and his <unclear>afflicted</unclear> Mother were both invited, in whose presence, his Maj. Danced the great <em>Ballet</em>; but young <em>Charles</em> exceeds him far in the Italian Comedy. Propositions are preparing to be sent to the K. of <em>Spain</em> for a ten years Truce.</p>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Monk</em> is advancing towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, and intends to cut his passage through the Hills, where <reg orig="politike">politick</reg> <em>Middleton</em> hath found a way to get through provisions, which causeth no little admiration; <i>for indeed we thought <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> too sure to have <reg orig="starv'd">starved</reg> him out there; but the wisest sometimes may be <reg orig="deceiv'd">deceived</reg></i>. He hath sent <em>Orders</em> to <em>the Highlands</em> to double their guards, and has placed his Army in <em><reg orig="battel">battle</reg> array:</em> yet no considerable action, but 7 sharp Disputes; <i>Let them laugh that wins; there's brave Heroes on both sides.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>