<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout179">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scout, Issue 179</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>The new Writ and Summons of his Highness the Lord Protector, for the calling of a free Parliament, and confirming unto the people their long promised Liberties His gracious Remonstrance touching <unclear>poor</unclear> prisoners; and the Order and Habeas Corpus granted out of the Upper Bench, and sent to Mr. J. <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg> in the Isle of Jersey. The Declaration of the Royal Princess in Holland, to the States; and their proceedings thereupon. The propositions of the Emperor of Germany, and the Demands of the Duke of <reg orig="Muscovie">Muscovy</reg>. The raising of a mighty Army in France, to be commanded by the Du. of <em>York</em>; and the sending of more forces into <em>Scotland</em>. The setting forth of a great fleet under the command of the Lord high Admiral the Duke of <em>Guise</em>, the number of English ships taken, the <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> of <em>Gen. Middleton</em>, the number of his forces, and their resolution to fight the English.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 12. to <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 19. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>May</em> the 12.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>It was the ingenuous saying of <em><reg orig="Machivil">Machiavelli</reg></em> the wise, <i>That a freeborn people are the best Guard of those in power, and the best Guardians of their own liberty</i>; for the Kings of <em>England</em> formerly found no other remedy to check the pride of the Nobility, but by doing acts of Justice to oblige the people, Read all Histories in the World, it <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> found, <i>that those who made the people their Sanctuary, have stood upon strong basis, and have been durable; but those that have made the Nobility their Sanctuary, have sundry times miscarried.</i> The same may be said of an Army, as of the Nobility; <i>but this by the way</i>. I shall present Thee (therefore with a pretty story of <pb n="1" /> horses, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how conformable to the Government of man the horse is above all other creatures. <em>Politian</em>, a Greek Author, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the <em>Sybarites</em> did give themselves to all manner of delights and sports; amongst the rest, they would bring into their places of Feasts horses taught to stand upright on their hinder feet, and at the sound of Flutes would dance and move their <reg orig="fore feet">forefeet</reg> very nimbly, like as a <em>Morris dancer</em> moveth his hands, and in this dancing would keep compass and measure: Now it happened that a certain Flute player had received some disgrace among the <em>Sybarites</em>, about the time that they were drawn into the field against the <em>Crotaniats,</em> (with whom they had war) the Flute player ran to the <em>Crotaniats</em>, and promised them, <reg orig="thas">that</reg> if they would trust to his fidelity, he would take a course that all the horsemen of the <em>Sabyrites</em> Army should be taken prisoners by them with ease: The <em>Crotania's</em> hereupon made him a <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>; and taking certain <reg orig="minstrils">minstrels</reg> of <em>Croton</em>, taught them on the Flute to play such a <unclear><reg orig="jigge">jig</reg></unclear>, that at the drawing forth of the <reg orig="battel">battle</reg>, and placing them on the Wings of the <reg orig="Battalians">Battalions</reg> opposite to the <em>Sybarites</em> horse, upon sounding their flutes, the horses fell a dancing, cast their Riders, and so they lost the day. In our next, we shall proceed to the plagues of mankind throughout the whole Universe, that is to say, <em>Tyrants</em>, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> make a discovery upon what political Basis they stand, that those who <reg orig="succced">succeed</reg> us, may be <reg orig="throughly">thoroughly</reg> instructed with Rules to prevent the like.</p>
<p>The Lord grant it.</p>
<p>There hath been a great plot discovered against the English in <em>Virginia</em>, by an <em>Indian</em>, who being privy to the design of the Natives, repaired to the Governor, unfolded the business, and told him that upon the 4 of this instant May, there was a conspiracy to fall upon the English, and to stab and cut the throats of all in general, both men, women, and children. Whereupon the Governor immediately called a council, and forthwith secured the chief Actors, hanging up divers in several places. <i>A just Reward for so detestable Miscreants; and nothing but a halter can reclaim them.</i></p>
<p>By the last Express from <em>Scotland</em>, thus: We conceive the Enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagued with their inroads upon the Lowlands, <pb n="2" /> where they burnt and destroyed all that stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reason of their mischiefs and our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is want of intelligence from amongst them; for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce <reg orig="squeez">squeeze</reg> ten true words out of them. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> we hear hath made his way out of <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em>, where col. <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> his horse, but it proved not feasible; for indeed we have an enemy as subtle as resolute, and they play fast and loose with us in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming to them, and their thoughts extend so far, that there will then be a general Rising of the people:</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> it is certified, That the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador has received audience of his Majesty, to whom he <unclear>imparted</unclear> the joyful <reg orig="Tydings">Tidings</reg> of a Victory obtained by the <em>Portugal</em> fleet against the <em>Hollanders</em> in <em>Brazil</em>; and of the taking of <em>Reclif</em> and about 40 other Towns and Castles from them. Which doth not a little <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> the Royal Family: <i>Win gold, and wear it; 'tis fit every one <reg orig="shou'd">should</reg> have their own.</i> Upon a delicate Banquet between the King and Queen, on the 3 of May, the K of <em>Scots</em>, and his afflicted Mother were both invited, in whose presence, his Maj. danced the great <unclear><em>Ballet</em></unclear>; but young <em>Charles</em> exceed him far in the Italian Comedy. Propositions are preparing to be sent to the K. of <em>Spain</em> for a ten years Truce.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 13.</head>
<p>This day afforded memorable intelligence from several parts; as the concluding of a firm <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> and friendship between <em>England</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, with ample satisfaction on both sides. Yet before it could be brought to a period, great were the obstructions against it, especially by the Nobility: But the grand Chancellor, and his son Count <em>Erick</em> (the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Commissioners) did manage this great Work with so great wisdom and dexterity, that her Majesty was pleased to vouchsafe her Royal Condescensions, to a final Agreement, and to manifest incomparable affection to his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, declaring unto the Lord <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em>, That she would have the honour to make the <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> with the Lord Protector, and in respect to him, and she said, because my Lord Ambassador treated with her like a Gentlemen, <i>Avec tout a la franchise &amp; rondeur, &amp; non pas comme un. Marchand</i>, she did consent to more than any other could have obtained from her. Nevertheless, 40 men of war, and 30000 Swedes are in a readiness to <unclear><reg orig="archieve">achieve</reg></unclear> something.</p> 
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em>, May 15</head>
<p>There are sundry new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> making ready at <em>Rochel</em>, and at several other places in <em>France</em>, where abundance of provisions are making for War, and most of the Garrisons are <reg orig="re-inforced">reinforced</reg> and filled with <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and their Castles and Magazines <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> with plenty of Ammunition. Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em> hath <unclear>issued</unclear> forth <em>Orders</em> for drawing down the Army towards the <unclear>sea</unclear> coast, where they have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="intrench'd">entrenched</reg> themselves, and <unclear>raised</unclear> great <em><unclear>Batteries</unclear></em>, but also planted above one hundred pieces of Canon; and expect nothing more than a sudden war.</p>
<p>His Majesty hath sent new Propositions to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, &amp; desires an Agreement. Notwithstanding great Levies are raising in all his Majesties Dominions, and Marshal <em>Thurene</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>, are to command a potent Army in <em>Flanders</em>. The D of <em>Joyeuse</em> is to be Lieu. Gen. of the Horse, and Duke <em>Bellieure</em> Lieu. Gen. of the foot. The Duke of <em>Guise</em> goes General of the fleet, and the L. <em>Pimontelly</em> Vice Admiral, they are to <reg orig="rendevouz">rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Rochel</em>, and so to strike sail (as one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> body) for <unclear><reg orig="cleering">clearing</reg></unclear> of the coast of <em>Campaigne, Brittany</em> and other places.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The Declaration of the General <em>Monk</em>.</i></head>
<p><i>The Commonwealth of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness &amp; affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a <reg orig="chargable">chargeable</reg> and bloody war) into union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much blood and treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge against their enemies both abroad and at home, that so they might enjoy the fruits and benefits of <unclear>peaces</unclear> yet divers lend persons broken in their fortunes, and dissolute in their lives, <unclear>are</unclear> run into Rebellion; for <unclear>prevent</unclear> on whereof, I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority given unto me by his Highness and his Council, do declare, that all such persons that are now in rebellion (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication <unclear>hereof</unclear>, come in, and submit him, or themselves, to the Governor of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, <unclear>it <reg orig="allike">alike</reg></unclear>, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned for any offence <unclear>spoil</unclear>, or plunders, committed by him or them in this present Rebellion (the killing of any person in cold blood <reg orig="onely">only</reg> excepted.) And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Maj. Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, the E. <pb n="4" /> of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Dayel">Dalziel</reg></em>, <!-- Dalziel reg is a guess here --> Laird <em>Glengary</em>, Laird <em>MacDonald</em>; I do hereby <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> declare, that what person or persons soever of this Nation (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner to any Governor of any English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> he or they have acted in this late rebellion, but also shall receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of <em>200 li.</em> sterling, for every person so <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</i> Given under my hand at Dalkeith this 4. day of May, 1654.</p>
<p>George Monk.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 16.</i></head>
<p>Came lamentable news from the West, signifying, That the <em>Brest</em> men of war have taken three ships coming from <em>Dublin</em> to <em><reg orig="Leverpool">Liverpool</reg></em>. and <em>Chester</em>, as also a <em>Bristol</em> ship; And a Bark coming from <em>Diep</em> to <em>Rye</em>, in which was many passengers, was set upon by an <em>Ostend</em> man of war and after a <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> conflict, she was sunk, only most of the passengers were saved, but 7 of the <em>Ostend</em> men were slain. They have taken two more in the Western channel; and we have taken 7 <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Landsend; <i>Ha, ha, let them laugh that wins</i>; For I can assure you, there is nothing yet concluded in the Treaty with the <em>French</em> Ambassador; so tender is his Excellency of the honour and preservation of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> Interest, that we may expect Tribute, and satisfaction for the horrid massacre of the Protestants, and the Isle of <em>Ree</em> business. On the last Lords day there preached before the Protector in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> learned Dr <em>Horton</em>, where his Highness <reg orig="writ">wrote</reg> down the Sermon, and desires it may be a <unclear>general</unclear> practice throughout the Nations. <i>Excellent graces, in so pious a Prince, and not to be <reg orig="paralleld">paralleled</reg> throughout all Europe.</i></p>
<p>Gen. <em>Blake</em> being come from the fleet to <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, dined this day with his Highness and the Lord Mayor, and divers members of the Council, were present. At which time, col. <em>Venables</em>, and col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>, presented their Addresses from the Council in <em>Ireland</em>, by way of <em>congratulation</em>, and owning the present Government.</p>
<p>The Committee met about the Law, but find it a hard work to alter the old channel, but it is believed <unclear>something</unclear> will be dispatched about a fortnight hence for the Committee at Salters Hall to act by. In the interim, an Ordinance is passed for relief of the poor creditors in <em>Scotland</em> Mr. <em>John <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em> has received his <em>Habeas Corpus</em> from the Upper Bench, and desires to be brought thither; which we hope <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be granted.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, May 17.</i></head>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> it is certified, That the States have set forth a Proclamation for the departure of the Royal party (according to the Articles) which doth exceedingly exasperate their spirits, insomuch that they begin to renounce obedience, and have already <unclear><reg orig="fir'd">fired</reg></unclear> one of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> houses; but strict Orders are issued forth, and many are taken, and committed to safe custody.</p>
<p>Another Express from <em>Scotland</em> certifieth, <i>That there is more men landed in Scotland, and that two ships from Dunkirk are come in to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, contrary to expectation, with Arms and Ammunition. Major General Drummond is come up as far as <reg orig="Loughtay">Loch Tay</reg>, and Lieu. Gen. <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> has reinforced <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg>, proceeding on very vigorously with their new Levies, and determining to <unclear>speed</unclear> Northwards to surround Col. Morgan, if they can. The E. of <reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg> is raising his Levies at <reg orig="Bramar">Braemar</reg>, and some of <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> forces are united with them. They do begin to interpose very notably, and have taken an Oath of Confederacy to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> together. They are in <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> expectation of their young Master, who has sent over sundry commissions to be disposed of by</i></p>
<p><em>Gen</em>. Middleton, Lieu. Gen. <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, Major Gen. Dayer, Maj. Gen. Drummond, The Earl of <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg>, The E. of Calender, The E. of Crawford, The E. of Marshal, The E. of Seaforth, The Lord Kenmore, The Lord <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>, The Lord Machlin, The Lord Montgomery, The Lord Spyvie, The Lord Cranston, The L. Sinclair, The L. Newburgh, The L. Bargany, The L. Napier, The L. Womat, The Lord Thompson, Sir Geo. Monroe, <em>And</em> Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Broghil</em> is come out of <em>Ireland</em>, with a congratulatory Message to his Highness, and the Lord Gen <em>Fleetwood</em> will be also in <em>England</em> suddenly. His Excellency hath caused ten men to be selected out of every company, for <em>Scotland</em>, which hath occasioned the <em>Irish</em> to gather to a Head in <em><reg orig="Conaught">Connaught</reg></em>.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, May 4.</i> This day came Gen. <em>Monk</em> from <em><reg orig="Dalkieth">Dalkeith</reg></em> to <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, attended by the chief Officers of the Army, who were received at the <em>Netherbow</em> by the <em>English</em> Judges in their scarlet Robes, and the Town Magistrates in theirs likewise. The streets were adorned with Tapestry, and a great concourse of people there was upon the proclaiming of his Highness Lord Protector, &amp;c. with Drums beating, Trumpets sounding, and Voices <reg orig="ecchoing">echoing</reg> <reg orig="fort">forte</reg> acclamations. Yet notwithstanding, the Ministers prayed for the exiled Prince the next day.</p>
<p><i>An Ordinance for continuing an Ordinance, <em><reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg></em>, An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act of Parliament, <em><reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg></em>, An Act for relief of Creditors and poor prisoners</i>,</p> 
<p><reg orig="Untill">Until</reg> the 31. day of <em>May</em> instant.</p>
<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector by and with <reg orig="he">the</reg> advice of his Council, That one Ordinance of the 18 of <em>April</em>, 1654. <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act,</i> <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors and poor prisoners</i>, be continued and shall stand in force until the 31 day of <em>May</em> instant; And that the several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any the estates real or personal of any of the prisoners, or other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in, or by the said Act, nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any the Powers and Authorities given by the same, until the 31 of <em>May</em> instant, otherwise <reg orig="then">than</reg> as in the said Ordinance is limited, and that all other Acts or things to be done by the said respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the said Act from henceforth until the <em>31</em> day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, than be and are hereby declared to be null and void.</p>
<p><em>Hen. Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>
<p>From <em>Paris</em> further thus: Here is arrived a Messenger from Scotland, which <reg orig="sweaks">speaks</reg> of a great Victory obtained against the English, and glorying very much at G. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> <reg orig="successe">success</reg> <unclear>since</unclear> his going thither. Whereupon <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said, that the K. of Scots, and his brother <em>James</em>, intends suddenly to leave <em>France</em>.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, May 18.</i></head>
<p>The Writs of his Highness the Lord Protector are preparing against the time they are to issue forth, for the calling of a Parliament, according to the Instrument of the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>; <i>so that 'tis hoped we shall then receive the full fruition of our long promised liberty.</i></p>
<p>His Highness hath <reg orig="past">passed</reg> an Ordinance for the Courts that <reg orig="use">used</reg> to be kept in <em>Chester</em> city, to be kept at <em><reg orig="North-wich">Northwich</reg></em>, during the time of the Sickness being in <em>Chester</em> city.</p>
<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That since the concluding of a peace there hath been great discontents; and that the Princess Dowager, the Princess Royal, and the rest of the family of Nassaw, have presented a Declaration to the States General, bemoaning and applying their condition as sad by the late Articles of peace with England; and the very women have <reg orig="address'd">addressed</reg> themselves <reg orig="in">on</reg> the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> behalf, wringing their hands, and crying out, <i>Ah! poor Prince, what hast thou done that thou <reg orig="shou'dest">shouldest</reg> be thus used? Ah poor Child! what a sad condition art thou in?</i> and the like penetrate expressions; whereupon, its conceived the States will have compassion on them, and permit them to live peaceably, if they please. The great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> has sent an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> to the Hague, demanding Officers and warlike Ammunition: from thence he goes to <em>France</em>, where the whole <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> have received special commandment from their <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Lord the King to be all in arms.</p>
<p>It is confirmed from <em>Brazil</em>, that the <em>Hollanders</em> are almost totally banished from those parts; and are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> in other places. The last news from <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the Royal party grow numerous, and that they spake themselves to be above 11000 at the last <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, being resolved to fight us; which is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> desired by the merry Redcoats: so that by our next, no doubt but you will hear of action.</p>
<p>The Emperor of <em>Germany</em> has sent Propositions to the States of <em><reg orig="Bohemiah">Bohemia</reg></em>, <unclear><reg orig="conjucing">conducing</reg></unclear> them, 1 That they use their utmost <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> for propagating of the <reg orig="Romish">Roman</reg> <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion. 2 That they <reg orig="celebrat">celebrate</reg> the Feast of St. <em>Joseph</em> as the rest of the Patrons of the Kingdom <reg orig="use">used</reg> to do. 3 That they pay a considerable sum to the Emperor.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>