<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout176">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 176
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>The Articles of Union between her Royal <em>Majesty</em> the Queen of Sweden, and his Highness the Lord Protector, the Proposals sent to the most illustrious and <reg orig="High-born">Highborn</reg> Son of Valour Prince <em>Charles</em>, and his Answer thereunto, touching the Crown and <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>, sent to most of the Christian Princes in Europe; the arrival of 7 Agents in Northumberland, the publishing of a Declaration at the Shields, the advancing of a <reg orig="forein">foreign</reg> Fleet towards Berwick, the fortifying of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> <em>Mount</em>, the sinking of the Royal James, and the Fox <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, the taking of a delicate sweet prize by the nimble <em>Drake</em>, the arrival of Gen. <em>Monk</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, the drawing up of both Armies to dispute the bloody field, the coming in of 1000 foot to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, the number of his forces, the proclaiming of an everlasting Peace between England and Holland, and the Lord Protectors speech touching the people.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 21. to <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 28. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>April</em> the 21.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The City or civil Society is a great Body, and compounded of many parts: It therefore behoveth those who have the Protectorship or government, to defend a <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> by His diligent care, and administering true Justice without respect of persons; for it is most certain, that if the people do not increase both in Affection and Riches, by the enjoyment of their just Rights and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, they must consequently decrease, by the infringing and chaining up their Liberties: But I hope the Freeborn people of England are, or will be, solely acquitted from the Bond of Slavery, by the <unclear>Constitution</unclear> of Government, so cordially invested in the hands of so <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> a Patriot, and true Assertor of the Golden Law, and Rule of Righteousness,</p>
<head level="2">Do as ye would be done unto.</head>
<pb n="1" />
<p>Let us then <unclear><reg orig="submith">submit</reg></unclear> with patience and alacrity, and doubtless, but <unclear>our</unclear> incorporated <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, bearing the Banner of two <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> Crosses, and the flourishing Harp, will become so Harmonious throughout all Europe, that most Christian Princes will even stand in admiration, and at last become instrumental to <reg orig="inlarge">enlarge</reg> our Territories, far beyond the <reg orig="Common-Wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of Rome, in the time of the Romans. But many object and say, Why did not the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of Venice, after they had redeemed themselves from bondage and slavery, <reg orig="inlarge">enlarge</reg> their Territories much more beyond its greatest Bounds <reg orig="then">than</reg> it ever had. Alas! To this I answer, That Venice tolerated Adultery, to divert men from the cursed sin of Sodomy; which ineffectual course is prohibited by the States of England. O the tolerating of Whoredom was one cause of the Venetians not <reg orig="inlarging">enlarging</reg> their Territories, for that they wanted men as well to defend what they had, as to undertake any new Conquest; by which they are reduced to entertain Mercenary Arms: Which indeed are not at all profitable to a <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; by reason it <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> standeth in fear of its own Arms, while they are in Mercenary hands, whose faith is not <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> firm, and will <reg orig="onely">only</reg> attend the Cause of a <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> <reg orig="whilest">whilest</reg> it thriveth, <em>as experience sheweth</em>; and are <reg orig="onely">only</reg> dutiful, when <reg orig="over-awed">overawed</reg> by a greater force of the Natives. Again, where <unclear>incess</unclear> of Adultery is prohibited, in that <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> springs up many fruitful <reg orig="Linages">Lineages</reg>: For, observe, <em>Fazel</em> in the History of <em><reg orig="Cicilia">Sicily</reg></em> writeth, That in his time <em>Jane Pancia</em>, being married to <em>Bernard Balvard</em>, a <reg orig="Cicilian">Sicilian</reg> of the City of <em><reg orig="Agrigent">Agrigento</reg></em>, was so fruitful, that in 30 <reg orig="Child-beds">Childbeds</reg> she was delivered of 73 Children: A thing something rare; yet it may not seem impossible, considering that many women now amongst Us, have had 30 children, and some three at a time, two more ordinarily. In <unclear>fact</unclear>, Histories report of the beginning of the WELFES, <em>Irmentrudes</em> the wife of <em>Isenbard</em> Earl of <em>Alterf</em>, had at one birth 12 male children, who lived <unclear>all</unclear> till they came to mans estate, of <em>whom</em> the honourable Race of the <em>Welfes</em> are that live this day. But to Intelligence:</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, April 18</i>.</head>
<p>Monsieur <em>Lodowick de Gand</em>, Lord of <em>Brachey</em>, and Resident here in <em>England</em> <reg orig="in">on</reg> behalf of the high and mighty Prince <em>Lewis</em>, Duke of <em>Guelders</em> and <em>Juliers</em>, Conte of <em>Egmont</em> and <em>Zutphen</em>, &amp;c. was this day, with many Gentlemen of quality accompanying him in coaches, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, unto his Highness the Lord Protector; The President <em>Laurence</em>, and some other Lords of the Council, with the Secretary of State, being present in his Highness chamber, where the said Lord Resident had audience, and made a congratulatory Speech, which was answered with abundance of respect from his Highness.</p>
<head level="2">By the Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></head>
<p><i>Whereas a peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the States General of the United Provinces <pb n="2" /> of the Low-countries. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof shall be made on both parts on <em>Wednesday</em> next, being the 26 of this instant <em>April</em>; from which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after 12 days, within these seas; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>; and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> sea, and to the &AElig;quinoctial Line, after ten weeks; and beyond the &AElig;quinoctial, after the space of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: which several spaces were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this Commonwealth, and to all others whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof; to the end, they may have warning to provide for their own safety, and not expose their ships to danger within the several and respective times aforesaid.</i></p>
<p><em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>
<p>From <em>Deal, April</em> 21, thus: This Afternoon arrived here the Express, who doth return into <em>Holland</em> to carry to the States General the <unclear><reg orig="ratificatiod">ratification period</reg></unclear> of the peace, signed and sealed by his Highness the L. Protector, which upon signification of their receiving, will suddenly be proclaimed both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday April 22</i></head>
<p>By an Express from <em>Scotland</em>, we have received very remarkable intelligence, intimating, That the Royal party increase, and have taken some few prisoners from the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills, the Lord <em>Forrester</em>, and the Lord <em><reg orig="Dudhop">Dudhope</reg></em> are in <em><reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg></em>, and very active in attending the motion of General <em>Middleton</em>. The rest of their forces in <em>Caithness</em> have left no means <unclear>unassayed</unclear> for raising of the whole <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>; but the people being timorous of rising, <reg orig="feariny">fearing</reg> <reg orig="least">lest</reg> the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Sinclair</em>, commanded by cap. <em>Langrish</em> of col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Regiment should punish them for their Loyalty, after <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> march from thence: wherefore for their encouragement, Maj. Gen. <em>Dyal</em> with a strong party of foot, and 100 stout horse, is ordered to sit down before it for the reducing of it, which is conceived to be a work of great difficulty, the place being situated on a very high <em>Rock</em>, yet if they prove successful in this <reg orig="Atchievement">Achievement</reg>, they intend then to attempt <em><reg orig="Ruthin">Ruthven</reg></em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>; but cap. <em>Hill</em> (the Governor) has <reg orig="re inforced">reinforced</reg> it with provisions, and is well provided for a siege.</p>
<p>The Armies on both sides are preparing to receive each other, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> has <reg orig="drain'd">drained</reg> <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg> </em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those forces which he <pb n="3" /> brought from <em>Aberdeen</em>, so that he lies with about 1200 Horse and Dragoons, and 2000 Foot, betwixt the enemy and the passes they must needs march through, if they intend to move out of the North corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, and 'tis said, they are resolved, there being no way left them to avoid it, but through such inaccessible bounds, as 'tis impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their foot, it being exceeding <reg orig="mountainovs">mountainous</reg>, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> they are in will not long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an account of some action betwixt him and <em>Middleton</em>; and what the success will be, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>; for, to speak truth, we have a very stout and stubborn enemy to deal <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and as potent they speak themselves to be as valiant, saying they <unclear>sourn</unclear> to prove perfidious (in the least) to so great a Cause wherein the interest of their King so much depends; but will rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to sacrifice their lives in the field, and dispute the mountainous passes by inches.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 24.</i></head>
<p>By the last Intelligence from the Navy, we are <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That divers Prizes have been this week taken; amongst the rest, a Dutch ship bound for the East Indies; the rest, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> where, for I do not: <reg orig="Onely">Only</reg> thus much be assured of, that the English Assurance hath taken the Non-Assurance belonging to France, laden with 25 Lasts of Tar and pitch, and likewise the <em>Confidence</em> of <em>Amsterdam</em>, gallantly fraught with Pitch, Linseed and <reg orig="Daal">Dhal</reg>, was <reg orig="constrain'd">constrained</reg> to yield, after a fair salute from the precious <em>Pearl</em>; <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, a French ship likewise; in which service, the captain, and one M. <em>Spilman</em>, deported <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> with singular courage: And after this honourable <reg orig="Atchievment">Achievement</reg>, as a testimony of their cordial affection to their love and <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, bare up with the nimble <em>Drake</em>, and boarded two stately <em>Flemmings</em> sweetly laden with Wines from <em>Bordeaux</em>: But alas! to these sweet comforts, we cannot <unclear>on</unclear> it, but present you with certain tart crudities, that is, the <em>Fox</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> striking <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> with the <em>Royal James</em> of <em>Brest</em>, and exchanging two broad sides, was so puissantly received that after many dry <reg orig="blowes">blows</reg> on both sides, and coming to grappling, they sunk each other; but by the <unclear>series</unclear> of <em>Providence</em> many of the men were miraculously saved, by plunging through the raging Billows upon the top of empty Hogsheads.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 25.</i></head>
<p>By an Express from <em>Newcastle</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Monk</em>, after some congratulation from the Mayor and Aldermen, by three sorts of Wine, Loaf-Sugar, Cakes, and <reg orig="Lemmons">Lemons</reg>, took his leave, and <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> journeyed for <em>Scotland</em>; upon whose departure a ship bound from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux ">Bordeaux</reg></em> was sunk near the Bar of <em>Tinmouth</em>, in which were 7 Agents from the K. of <em>Scots</em>, who providentially saved their lives by swimming, and safely arrived at the <em>Shields</em>, where they presumed to publish a Declaration, inviting the people to commotions, and endeavouring to alienate their affections, from whence they passed to <em>Anwick</em>, and from thence to <em>Barwick</em>, where 12 Dutch men of War plays the Devil upon Don's back, and nothing will allay their revenge, but a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> possession of the Harbour, which the <reg orig="Holy-Island">Holy Island</reg> perceiving, very devoutly gave them a welcome, and impeded their design from blocking up the <reg orig="Quay">Key</reg>, which indeed was a <unclear>thing</unclear> very unfeasible, by reason that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Mount (so called in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of old) and Qu. <em><reg orig="Elizabeths">Elizabeth's</reg></em> Flankers, has the full command of the Haven towards <em>Fern Island</em>, being sufficiently <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>, and as bravely fortified.</p>
<p>The Declaration and Petition of the Mayor and Inhabitants of the Town of <em>Guilford</em> being presented to his Highness, blessing God for taking upon his shoulders that great and ponderous <unclear><reg orig="burthen">burden</reg></unclear> of the Government of the three Nations, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> desiring a godly and learned Minister to supply the Benefice of <em>Trinity</em> and <em>Muries</em> Parishes <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of him lately deceased. &amp;c. This being presented, his Highness standing uncovered, vouchsafed this gracious Answer,</p>
<p><i><em>Gentlemen</em>, I have read your paper, wherein, what you there express touching my taking of the Government upon me, you say what is truth, I did not desire it, nor have I (I am sure) told you so; I believe God put it into your hearts. I shall desire your prayers, that I may do as you have expressed, for God is my Bottom, and in him <reg orig="onely">only</reg> do I trust: As for your desire of a <unclear>Minister</unclear>, I think I have not granted the Living away; and upon your making choice of such a one as your paper mentions, I shall take Order that you shall have your suit.</i></p>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received further advertisements, That the Royal party increaseth <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, <em>who can help it</em>; &amp; that many hundreds of foot are marched over the Hills towards Gen <em>Middleton</em>, who is very considerable, and acts his part somewhat high <i>I <unclear>must</unclear> speak truth, blame me not, take all and pay the Baker</i>, for col. <em>Morgan</em> is now advanced, with a gallant Train, and expects to engage the enemy suddenly.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 26.</i></head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, has set forth an Ordinance, declaring, That all persons of the Scottish Nation of what degree or quality soever (except the persons hereafter named) shall, from and after the 1 day of <em>May</em>, 1654. be freed, acquitted, &amp; discharged, from all Forfeitures, fines, Sequestrations, pains, penalties, imprisonments, or punishments whatsoever, for any matter or thing by them <reg orig="commited">committed</reg> by sea or land, in relation to the late war, or any preceding war between the two Nations; And that after the said 1 day of <em>May</em>, no sequestration, fine, or punishment, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be imposed, but the same to be put in perpetual Oblivion.</p>
<head level="3"><em>The Names of those exempted from Pardon and Grace.</em></head>
<p><em>Henrietta Maria</em>, the Queen of the late King <em>Charles</em> deceased.</p>
<p><em>Charles Stuart</em>, their eldest son,</p>
<p><em>James Stuart</em>, their second son.</p>
<p><em>James</em> late Duke of <em>Hamilton</em>, deceased</p>
<p><em>William</em> late Duke of <em>Hamilton</em> deceased.</p>
<p><em>John</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Crawford-Lindsey">Crawford-Lindsay</reg></em>,</p>
<p><em>James</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Kalender">Callander</reg></em>,</p>
<p><em>John</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Lawderdail">Lauderdale</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Kelley">Kelly</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Lowdon</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Viscount <em><reg orig="Kenmure">Kenmore</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em><reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg></em>, eldest son of the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> of <em><reg orig="Arguile">Argyle</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Machlin</em>, eldest son of the L. <em>Lowdon</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Montgomery</em>, eldest son of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Egglingtoun">Eglinton</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Spynie</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Cranston</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em><reg orig="Sinclare">Sinclair</reg></em>,</p>
<p><em>Thomas <reg orig="Dalyel">Dalziel</reg></em>, late Maj. Gen. of the foot in the Scottish Army.</p>
<p><em>John Middleton</em>, late Lieu. Gen. of the Horse in the Scottish army.</p>
<p>Viscount <em>Newburgh</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Bargany</em>,</p>
<p>Sir <em>Thomas <reg orig="Tompson">Thompson</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Napier</em>,</p>
<p>Laird <em><reg orig="Ddmeston">Edmonston</reg></em> of <em>Womar</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>,</p>
<p>And it is further ordained, that the several persons hereafter named, do pay unto his Highness the Lord Protector his <reg orig="publike">public</reg> receipt the several respective sums of money hereafter mentioned and expressed, as a fine and fines for and in respect of his or their estates, to be paid in such manner, and at such times, as is hereafter expressed, that is,</p>
<p><em>David <unclear><reg orig="Lesley">Leslie</reg></unclear></em>, late Lieu. Gen. of the Scotch Army 4000 <em>li. Sterling.</em></p>
<p>Marq. of <em>Douglas</em> 1000 <em>li. Sterling.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Angus</em> 1000 <em>l. Ster.</em></p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Selcrig">Selcraig</reg> 1000 l. Ster.</em></p>
<p>The Heirs of <em>Francis</em> late Earl of <em><reg orig="Bucleuch">Buccleuch</reg></em> deceased, 15000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Galloway</em> 4000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Roxburgh</em> 6000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Cockeram</em> 5000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Forrester</em> 2500 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Armstruther</em> 1000 marks <em>Ster.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Archibald Sterling</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em><reg orig="Drumond">Drummond</reg></em> 500 l.</p>
<p><em>Henry Mawl</em>, son to the E. of <em>Panmure</em>, 2500 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>James <reg orig="Levingston">Livingstone</reg></em> of <em><reg orig="Kilsith">Kilsyth</reg></em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Murrey</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Buchane">Buchan</reg></em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Viscount <em><reg orig="Dudhop">Dudhope</reg></em> 1500 l.</p>
<p><em>Preston</em> of <em><reg orig="Cragmiller">Craigmillar</reg></em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Andrew Flesher</em> 5000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>John <unclear>Winchab</unclear></em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Prith</em>, and Lord <em><reg orig="Drumond">Drummond</reg></em> his eldest son, 5000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Winton</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em><unclear>Findlater</unclear></em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Murry</em> 3500 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Quinsburgh</em> 4000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Eith">Airth</reg></em> 6000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Duffus</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Grey</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Panmure</em> 10000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Arrol</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Tullibardine</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Earl  of <em>Sowthesk</em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Dalhousie</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Hartfield</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Ross</em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Sample</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Elphinstone</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Boide</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Cooper</em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Balwaird</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Rollock</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Kinghorn</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Earl of <em><reg orig="Kinkardine">Kincardine</reg></em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Bamfe</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Meldrum</em> of <em>Tylliebody</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Robert Graham</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>William Scot</em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Arnot</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Hay</em> of <em>Bowsey</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Francis Reven</em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Scot</em> of <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> 3000 l.</p>
<p>Laird of <em>Rothemegordon</em> 500 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>John Scot</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Laird of <em>Gosfrid</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Laird of <em>Buchilton</em> 1500 l.</p>
<p>Lord <em>Rothes</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Lewis Stuart</em> 1000 l.</p>
<p>Sir <em>James Carmighil</em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>Laird of <em><reg orig="Stanhop">Stanhope</reg></em> 2000 l.</p>
<p>All and every which sum and sums of money; shall be paid unto <em>George Bilton</em>, Deputy Treasurer at <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em>; one <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> thereof, on, or by the 2 day of <em>August</em>, 1654; and the other <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> on, or by the 2. day of <em>Decemb.</em> then next ensuing; and in default of such payment, all and every the real and personal estate of every person and persons so making <unclear>default</unclear>, shall from thenceforth be absolutely confiscate; and the Commissioners for Sequestrations, are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to seize the same accordingly.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 27.</i></head>
<p>Yesterday the Peace between England and the United Provinces, was by <unclear>11</unclear> Trumpets, and 4 Heralds at Arms solemnly proclaimed; first, in <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> in presence of his Highness and the Council, and afterwards received at Temple-bar by the Lord Major and Aldermen, and thence conducted to the Royal Exchange, where it was again proclaimed in these following words:</p>
<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, considering how necessary it is, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to preserve peace and quiet at home, but as far as in him lies to live in friendship and amity with his <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg>, hath by the blessing of God, with the advice of his Council, made and concluded a Peace and Union to continue <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, between this Commonwealth of the one part, and that of the United Provinces of the Low-countries, of the other part, their Lands, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories places and people, by Sea, Land, fresh waters, and elsewhere; by the which peace it is agreed, that all enmity, hostility, discord, and war, between the said <reg orig="Dommon-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their people, and subjects, shall cease, and all injuries &amp; wrongs done since the 18 and 28 of May, 1652. shall cease and be forgotten, except such depredations as shall be committed by either side in these Seas, after 12 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, from the date of these presents; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St <unclear>Vincent</unclear> after 6 weeks, and from thence within the Mediterranean Sea, and to the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line, after ten weeks, and beyond the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line after 8 months, or <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after sufficient notice of the said peace given in those places And that the people and inhabitants of each party respectively, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> treat each other with love and friendship, and may freely and securely come into and pass through each other Countries, Towns, and Villages, and there stay and <unclear>abide</unclear>, and from thence depart again at their pleasure, and likewise have free Trade and Commerce, whereof all persons whatsoever in these Nations of England, Scotland, and Ireland, are to take notice and conform themselves accordingly.</p>
<head level="3">Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 26 day of April, 1654</head>
<head level="2">O.P.</head>
<p>The Articles of Union between England and Sweden have been debated by the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, and Count Erick, who has delivered in certain Articles on behalf of that Crown; but his Excellency has delivered in his <unclear>Exceptions</unclear> to the Queen, and the Reasons of non-admittance. So that the accord as yet seems dubious; in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, be pleased to take a view of her Majesties Proposals to Pr. <em>Charles</em>, to wit; 1 She will retain the <unclear>best</unclear> part of the Kingdom and Customs to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>. 2 She will be no subject, but free of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> without control. 3 She will travel where she pleaseth. 4 She will not revoke those Gifts of hers, which are <em><unclear>Predia Corone</unclear></em>, and were by her given out of favour to Courtiers. <em>The <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Answer</em>. 1 He will not be a King without a Kingdom or at least without the better part of it. 2 He will have no Rival, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> <unclear>she</unclear> a Superior. 3 He will not hazard himself about her designs abroad. 4 He will not <unclear>be</unclear> without a sufficient Revenue both for peace and war.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>


