<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout168">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 168
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>A more full and perfect Relation of all the Passages in the Treaty betwixt His Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> of the States of the United Provinces; The Auditing of their <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> by His Highness, and their resolutions concerning the Queen of <em>Bohemia</em>, the Princess of <em>Orange</em>, the late Queen of <em>England</em>, her son the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and his brethren the Dukes of <em>York</em> and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>; with the <unclear>engrossing</unclear> the Articles of <em>Peace</em>, and six Members of the Council appointed to treat with the Dutch Deputies. The proceedings of the Highlanders, and appointing a Central Rendezvous about <em><reg orig="Badgenoth">Badenoch</reg></em>, and their declaration <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> to destroy the <em>English</em> with Fire and Sword; with a <em>Scotch</em> Gentleman <reg orig="prophesie">prophesy</reg> of the destruction of <em><reg orig="Glencarne's">Glencairn's</reg></em> Army. Also, the great Duke of <em>Muscovite's</em> Decree to invade <em>Denmark</em> with three Armies, the last intelligence from the English and Dutch Navies at Sea, and Letters from Ireland: Together with an Order for the Trial of Ministers and thirty Commissioners appointed to put them in execution.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> March 3, to <em>Friday</em> March <em>the</em> 10. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>March</em> the 3.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The last Week I advised you of the Imprisonment of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg></em>, and now that <em><reg orig="Wolfe">Wolf</reg></em> sits confined in <em>Antwerp</em> Castle as quiet as a <em>Lamb</em>; having resigned up to his Highness the Archduke, his Person, Estate, and Army, and his Lieutenant General the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em>, hath took an oath of fidelity to the K. of <em>Spain</em>. The Archduke entreats <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg></em> nobly, and hath all service and honour done to him as becomes the person of a Prince; for besides the costly Table he keeps, his Highness the Archduke hath set him up a Court, and appointed several great persons to attend him; and hath made the E. of <unclear><em>Bruays</em></unclear> to be Overseer General of his whole Family; but the <em>old Fox</em> is like to pay for <reg orig="'t">it</reg> out of his <unclear><!-- 2 words --></unclear>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the North of Scotland, of the proceedings of the English Forces there.</i></head>
<p>SIR,</p>
<p>I Thought good to acquaint you, that Col. Tho. Morgan, Commander in Chief of the forces in the North of Scotland, understanding of the enemies approach within 24 miles of this Town, he drew forth about 1100 horse, dragoons, and foot, and upon the 9 instant after a very hard match, met with the forces under the <reg orig="comand">command</reg> of <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> and Kenmore, about the number of 1400 horse and foot: where after a short dispute, upon most base ground, he put them to a retreat, and forced them to a very strong <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg>, which 40 resolute men might have kept against 4000. yet so <reg orig="cow'd">cowed</reg> were the enemy, that in a short time Providence ordered it so, that we recovered the <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg>, and in time put them to the rout, pursued them through such invincible <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> (as were the truth of them related, would be imagined incredible) which never English men marched over before that time: there was about 120 of the enemy slain, 17 taken prisoners, about 80 horse, most of their Arms, all their Ammunition, Bag and Baggage, all which the Lord was pleased to carry on with great facility to us, for there was not so much as one man or ours wounded, and we had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 2 horses slain: there was indeed one of Captain <reg orig="Merimons">Merimon's</reg> troop shot through the head by one of his fellow <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> accidentally before the Engagement. The next day, having intelligence that the enemy had possessed a strong house called Kildrummy, where the Earl of <reg orig="Marr">Mar</reg> dwelt, who afterwards pretended he was <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by the enemy; yet so just are Scotchmen, that now they begin to appear in their colours, they through our lenity being grown to such a <reg orig="heighth">height</reg>, as that they <reg orig="mae">made</reg> good their old Character, <unclear>Turks</unclear> and Scots coequal.</p>
<p>We marched thither, and summoned it, and it was surrendered upon Articles: after the said Garrison was reduced, we marched to our winter quarters to this Town, where we was <reg orig="welcommed">welcomed</reg> with news from Johnstons, that col. Daniel with a considerable party out of Johnstons, and Dundee, resolved to make an attempt upon <reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg>, being informed that there was a considerable party of the enemies horse in that Town, and that <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg>, and <reg orig="Forbus">Forbes</reg> had <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> a <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> of about 60 persons in an old House in that place, and had victualled the same well for two <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p>
<p>Upon Wednesday the 15 instant by break of day col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg> forlorns fell into <reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg> with their Scouts, having <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> a quarter of an hour too short of surprising the Town; and for their escape they <pb n="2" /> were beholding to the <reg orig="nearnesse">nearness</reg> of the Hills, yet as quick as they were we took 40 of their horses, and after 1 hour and a half won the house, gaining room after room, in which time they were reduced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> upon terms for life, their number with those that were taken belonging to their horse, is about 120 and 4 or 5 killed, besides what is wounded, the enemy looking on, Col. <em>Daniel</em> blew up the house, and carried the prisoners to Johnston.</p>
<p>Upon <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> night being 17 instant, was one Captain Thompson, and <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> col. Ramstes <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> came down with 5 or 6 more into the Lowlands to plunder horses, and <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Hellen, <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> to Major Bramston, having intelligence thereof marched forth with 7 more Dragoons with him, out of the <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> of Thornston, and after he had pursued them ten miles through the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, <reg orig="catched">caught</reg> them about 5 in the morning, killed one of them, and brought the rest prisoners to <reg orig="Dunotter">Dunnottar</reg> Castle.</p>
<p>Sir, these blows are very seasonable, for the enemy were very high, and <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> all with fire and sword, that would not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. I am apt to <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> that the peace with the Dutch will vanish like smoke, though notwithstanding these Brushes they give out high language, and say that they resolve to gain their credit. I hope to hear from you <unclear>in I</unclear> remain,</p>
<p><i>Your affectionate Nephew.</i></p>
<p><i>I.H</i></p>
<p>Febr. 27. 1653.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday, March 3.</head>
<p>This afternoon the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> had Audience given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House at Whitehall, the <reg orig="Roome">Room</reg> was richly hung with hangings, and a rich chair of State set for the Lord Protector, and Chairs on the one side for the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, the entertainment was stately, and gallant, and the subject of this Audience was partly Congratulatory to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and to declare the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of their <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to make and settle a firm peace, and to <reg orig="renue">renew</reg> the old friendship which hath been for many years between the two Nations: And that to this purpose their Superiors the 7 United Provinces, do all of them agree and consent to the agreement or peace between us and them, which, they their <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> extraordinary, are <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <unclear><reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg></unclear>; desiring a speedy Cessation of arms, and that all acts of <unclear>hostility</unclear> may cease on <unclear>both sides</unclear>, so that undoubtedly, some few <unclear>circumstances being considered on, all</unclear> will be <unclear>concluded</unclear>, and a <unclear><reg orig="peace full">peaceful</reg> <!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear>, as we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <unclear>able to bring you further the particulars by the next.</unclear></p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 6.</i></head>
<p><i>A more <unclear>perfect Relation</unclear> concerning the proceedings in the Treaty, betwixt his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> of the States of Holland, with the manner of their <unclear>entertainment</unclear> at the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house, the conference that passed between them, and how <unclear>so</unclear> they are agreed as concerning Peace.</i></p>
<p>The Lords <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> from the States of the seven <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of <em>Holland, Zealand</em>, &amp;c. had Audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, in the <unclear><reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg></unclear> house at <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> (as is formerly related) which was hung with <unclear>extraordinary</unclear> hangings, and divers Lords, Knights and <reg orig="Gentleuen">Gentlemen</reg>, Officers of the Army, and thousands of people in the said room present, and all the <unclear><em><reg orig="Gallaries">Galleries</reg></em> round</unclear> the room, full of people, besides many in the Courts, and other places about that could not get in.</p>
<p>They were <unclear>fetched</unclear> from their lodgings in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>, by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Mr of the <unclear>Ceremonies</unclear>; and with him two of the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, <em>Srickland</em> and <unclear><em>Jones</em></unclear>, who were all three with the three <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, brought in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Footmen, besides the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors'</reg> Footmen to run by the Coach; and after the said Coach followed a great many Coaches belonging to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Lords and others, most with six horses, in which rode <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons of Honour, and the Gentlemen belonging to the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>.</p>
<p>There was set at the upper end of the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> a chair of State, very <unclear>rich</unclear>, for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and by it on the <unclear>right</unclear> hand three rich high stools for the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, and a place railed in covered with Carpets, and the ground spread with Carpets, whereon the chair and stools were set.</p>
<p>First his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector came into the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house, with the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and Mr. <em>Thurlow</em> Secretary of State, and Mr. <em>Claypool</em> Gentleman of the Horse, at whose <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in, all the people put off their Hats and stood bare, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> put off his Hat to the people, and went so to the Chair, but did not sit down in it at all, all the <unclear>while</unclear>, neither before, at, not after the Audience. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> stood on the left side of the Chair, with his Hat on, and the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and Mr Secretary, and Mr <em>Claypool</em> were within the <unclear>Rails</unclear>, some on the one side, and some on the other, all of them bare all the while, in this Equipage his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> waited a short time, for the reception of the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, and a lane was made for the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> to come unto his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> from the one end of the Room to the other.</p>
<p>So soon as the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> were come into the Room they put off their Hats to salute his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> did the like to them, and so again a second and a third time as they nearer to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and when they came up to the place where the Chair, Stools, and Carpets were, where his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector was, with the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and after a low salute of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Lords <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> each to other; the Lord Protector put on his Hat, and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> put on their Hats also, the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and all others being bare, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> all standing up.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>Then Lord <em>Yongstal</em> made a Speech to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> made presently another Speech to the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>. High <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> often in both the Speeches putting off their hats to salute each other, upon some words of Protestation of Affection of one Commonwealth to the other, and desire of firm Union.</p>
<p>The substance of the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors'</reg> speech was, To declare the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of their <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, to renew the old friendship which hath been for many years, and to make and settle a more firm Peace and Alliance <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore. And that to this purpose their Superiors, the Lords and the States of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of the Netherlands do all of them agree and consent to the agreement of peace between us and them, which they their <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> Extraordinary are <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, desiring a speedy cessation of Arms and that all Acts of hostility may cease on both sides; so that the <unclear>chiefest</unclear> thing that is yet behind is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the explaining some things in some of the Articles.</p>
<p>Afterwards his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> saluted each other, and the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> returned, three times turning back to <unclear>salute</unclear> his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> then also staying for that purpose, saluted them; and they being gone down, His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> with the Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, returned also by the privy door, through which he had come thither.</p>
<p>The Lords <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces declare, that they are willing to <unclear><reg orig="condiscend">condescend</reg></unclear> to the Articles, and say if they can be <unclear><reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg></unclear> in a day they are ready to sign the Ratification of the Peace, and the Articles of the Treaty are <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>, and six Members of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> are appointed Commissioners to meet with the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>; whereupon it is supposed Subscriptions will be made on either side, in order to the making a firm Peace and Amity.</p>
<p>It is agreed upon, That the Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> is to depart <em>Holland</em>, she returns to her son the <unclear><em>Pelsgrave</em></unclear>; the <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> <em>Mary</em> with her son stays still in <em>Holland</em>; The late Queen of <em>England</em> is to leave <em>France</em>, she goeth to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>, the <reg orig="Dutchesse">Dutchess</reg> being her sister. And Charles Stuart, with the Dukes of York, and <unclear>Gloucester</unclear>, are also to depart the French Territories, they intend to go for <unclear>Germany to the <em>Palsgrave</em></unclear>.</p>
<p>We hear from <em>Scotland</em>, that Major Gen. <em>Lambert</em>, and Com Gen. <em><reg orig="Whalleys">Whalley's</reg></em> regiments are very seasonably arrived there.</p>
<p><i>There hath been lately printed a <unclear>scandalous Pamphlet against his Highness</unclear> the Lord <unclear>Protector; it</unclear> being full of <unclear>injurious calumnies, tending to no other</unclear> end but to make the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> <unclear>odious</unclear>, and to <unclear>raise</unclear> further <unclear>Divisions between the two States.</unclear> And because it did, highly concern this State to prohibit the <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> and publishing of the <unclear>said Pamphlets</unclear>, the States have put <unclear>forth</unclear> their Ordinance, strictly forbidding the sale upon pain of bodily punishment; and whosoever <unclear>can <reg orig="discovor">discover</reg> the Author</unclear> or Printer, shall <unclear>have the sum of 500 l. given him, in case the party be apprehended; And his name that shall give the Information shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> kept private.</unclear></i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Tuesday March 7.</head>
<p>It is further confirmed by Letters from Scotland, that <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> our horse are in the more Northern parts of that Nation, Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg>, who is again recovered of his wounds, is marched Southwards, so see what parties he can find <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg>, or what booty he can get about Lenox, or Tivesdale.</p>
<p>In the meantime the <em>E</em>arl of <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> is in the North, and not daring to hazard all his strength on the uncertainty of one <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, doth divide his forces into <reg orig="severel">several</reg> parties, that he might thereby be enabled to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the importunity of their bellies, and encourage or enforce the <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> to <reg orig="encrease">increase</reg> their Levies; the fiery Crosses have had their run, and whirled from place to place in several <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>, but to no effect. It is <reg orig="woinderfull">wonderful</reg> indeed to consider what an impression <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> supernatural hath in all ages left in the minds of the common <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>: to demur therefore from the Levying of new forces, it hath been reported wheresoever the Recruits are to be raise, That a Gentleman in the Country of Fife had a Vision, in which he was admonished by a young man, with all speed to <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> himself to <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> his Kinsman, and to acquaint him with the anger of God to fall on him and all his forces, if they pursued such destructive <unclear>courses</unclear>. The Gentleman disobedient to the Angel on the first night, was struck dumb the second, because he <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> not his voice as he was commanded. This Report hath been of more efficacy to trouble the Levies, and discourage the old <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the certain arrival of our Regiments, and of 3 ships laden with Tents, <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> &amp; all manner of provisions both for life &amp; death.</p>
<p>Mr. Feak, and Mr. Vavaser Powel have made their addresses for their liberty; some Ministers have been with them, and advised them to be sensible of their mistakes.</p>
<p>Yesterday the Lord Newport and Yongstal the two <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> extraordinary from the States General of the united Provinces came from <unclear>Gravesend</unclear> to London attended with many rich <unclear>Barges</unclear>, and at their <unclear>landing</unclear> there attended his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coach, and many other rich Coaches to the number <unclear>of</unclear> 60 Coaches, <unclear>and</unclear> with 6 horses a piece, in which Coaches the said <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> their attendance, and many English Lords and Gentlemen, rode through the City to Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> house in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard, which was trimmed up very stately for them.</p>
<p>From Flanders they write, that the Arch Duke doth yet retain in custody the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg>, neither are all his <unclear>plundering</unclear> and thieving Regiments able to rescue him <unclear>out of the Castle</unclear> wherein he is now a prisoner.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>From Paris we hear that the strong garrison of <unclear>Beffort</unclear> is <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> to Marshal de la Ferte, the Defendants had conditions to march away to <reg orig="Luxenburgh">Luxembourg</reg>. Here is talk of sending another <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> for England; his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> (your Lord Protector) is looked upon here as a person very considerable; if the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> comes not very speedily, the Credentials of the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> that is in England already <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be renewed.</p>
<p>There is also an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> we hear landed from Denmark, to make application to his Highness upon the success of the Dutch Treaty, his name is <em><reg orig="Wil-liamson">Williamson</reg></em>.</p>
<p>From Milford Haven the 28 of February: Here are some lately come from Ireland, who telleth us no more as for news, but that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Mortagne</em>, there are great numbers of Irish ready to take shipping for Flanders, to serve the King of Spain, but yet there are still small parties of Tories, who lie lurking in the woods and Boggs, and do much disquiet the peace of the Country, which is still in great want of people to inhabit those parts. The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is safe arrived in Ireland. From Deal the 2 of March two days since all the Merchants ships as were here, and in Dover Road set sail, having a fair wind to go for France, and other parts to the Southward; also several convoys to bring them to their distinct places, there hath been likewise some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> here, but are gone all again Westward, where we hear out Fleet rids still near St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, by the Isle of Wight.</p>
<head level="3">Wednesday March 8</head>
<p>The Letters from new Sarum, that this day sevennight my Lo. Chief Justice <unclear>Rolls</unclear>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> Glyn, came into that City attended by the Sheriff, and many Gentlemen of the Country, the next day being the first of March the <unclear>Assizes</unclear> began there, and his Lordship made a very learned speech to the great satisfaction of the Country, under the present government.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <em><reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg></em> below the <em>Church</em>, over against the Stile that goes to <em>Stepney</em>, in <em>Trumpet</em> Yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="pysick">physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, and deafness of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, and all sorts of Agues, of which cure he never failed; with other <reg orig="rdiseases">diseases</reg> incident to men.</i></p>
<p><i>Also, he cureth perfectly all diseases peculiar to women, or their <reg orig="Sexe">Sex</reg>, be they either <reg orig="Chronical">Chronic</reg> or Acute; and hath cured many that have been thought to be past cure. If you <unclear><reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg></unclear> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him.</i></p>
<p><i>There is lately extant. The History of New-England, from the English planting; the year 1628. until the year, 1652. Printed for <em>Nathaniel Brook</em>, and are to be sold at his shop at the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> of the <em>Angel</em> in <em>Cornhil</em>.</i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, March 9.</i></head>
<p>The last letter from <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the Highlanders have appointed the tenth of March for their General <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about <em><reg orig="Badgenoth">Badenoch</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg></em> hath Orders to prepare all the forces he can against that time; and the Enemy have put a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> into <em><reg orig="Gairth">Garth</reg></em> castle, and threaten all that adhere to the English with fire and sword; as appears by this following Warrant.</p>
<p>These are to require the Gentlemen, Heritors, and others concerned in the parish of <reg orig="Drummund">Drummond</reg> and Buchanan, that immediately after sight hereof, they send to the Craig of Ern out of every hundred pounds of Rent half Bell Cane, one Furlet Meat, one Turf of Hay, one Leg of Beef, one stone cheese, four Hens, or satisfaction therefore; as also to be <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> at the appointed place with your proportion of Troop horses, every thousand pounds being one well mounted Troop horse with certificate; If you fail I will <reg orig="persue">pursue </reg> you with <unclear>fire and</unclear> sword, according to the general Order.</p>
<p><i>From <unclear>Blaniavard</unclear> in Drummond, Feb. 23.</i></p>
<p><i>M. Murray</i>.</p>
<p>The <unclear>inclination</unclear> of <em>Holland</em> and the rest of the Provinces to make a firm peace with England, hath filled the French court with the same affections: And the next thing that will be done to smooth the way, <unclear>will be how</unclear> to be <unclear><reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg></unclear> rod of <em>Charles Stuart</em> and his <unclear>Retinue, who they say, is already</unclear> providing to be gone; but <reg orig="whether">whither</reg> none <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>, unless it be to Germany.</p>
<p>By Letters from <unclear><em>Danzick</em></unclear>, it is certified, that the Tartars continue the robbing and plundering the Danes, and have taken <em>Sapiha</em> Commander of the 3000 horse sent out against them, and a great favourite of the <reg orig="Kings">King</reg>, with most of his horse. Also, that the Great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> hath decreed hostility against the King of <em>Denmark</em>, and is resolved to invade him with three Armies in <unclear><reg orig="thtee">three</reg></unclear> sundry places.</p>
<p>The Council are preparing an Ordinance, for the trial and approbation of Ministers; and 30 Commissioners (Ministers and others) will be appointed to put them in execution; but the Power extends only to the trying of such Ministers as have been admitted within these six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> last past, or that shall be admitted hereafter.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>This is the ancient <em>Faithful Scout</em>, and is by Special Authority appointed to be printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>; and to be published throughout <unclear>the Dominions</unclear> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; to prevent the abuse offered to the people, by <reg orig="anothers">another</reg> publishing a false Copy under this Title.</i></p>
<head level="2">FINIS</head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>