<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton164">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scovt, Issue 164</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE FAITHFUL</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>

<head level="3">COMMUNICATING,</head>

<p><i>The speeches between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord Mayor, and Recorder of the City of London, on Wednesday last, at Temple-Bar, and Grocers-Hall, upon the solemnizing of that great and magnificent Feast by the Citizens: With a Narrative of the full Particulars, the receiving of him with <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>, Voices, Drums, and Trumpets; the placing of his Son the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> of his left hand at the Stately Banquet; and the playing of his Highness out of the great Hall with <reg orig="Hoboyes">oboes</reg>, and other loud Instruments. The Letters sent from Mr. Feak and Mr. Simpson in Windsor Castle to the Lord Protector, and their Churches, and the Q. of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> Message to the K. of Scots; with the raising of above one hundred thousand men by the D. of <reg orig="Muscovie">Muscovy</reg>, the taking of the Royal Fort in Lewis Island from the English by the L. Seafort, and the Declaration &amp; <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg> of Arise Evans, concerning the present Government.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Feb. 3. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Feb. 10.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON. Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<p>The King of Scots is as merry as a Prince at Paris in France; and his brother Du. James as valiant as Hector in the field, having performed singular service against the Enemies of the Crown: Their youngest brother Duke Henry is at Chaliot with his Mother the Queen, who with great patience undergoes her abundant afflictions. Prince Rupert, and divers others of the Royal Party have sent forth their Emissaries, to make a discovery of the present Transactions between the English and Dutch.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>This day likewise there was a great blazing Star seen over the river of Thames, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Windsor castle, as it is <reg orig="ascertain'd">ascertained</reg> by many. This portend certainly some great alteration; but I dare not presume to predict the event of things: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much I desire, that the Series of <reg orig="Provdience">Providence</reg> may guide and protect those two faithful Saints, and Ministers of the Gospel, pious Mr. <em>Feak</em>, and zealous Mr. <em>Simpson</em>; and all others whatsoever now in Authority: I hope it is no Treason to pray for them, although some hold it not reason to act with them; yet I could wish, that if it might stand with the honour of God, and the glory of his Church, that all men would submit in peace and love: for, sure I am, that if we do but accord in Unity, God will so appear with power and glory, that all the Nations about Us shall be broken, or brought in with Us to the Government of <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>: That is, when God alone shall reign in men, and men reign in Righteousness, and Righteousness arise in Truth; then shall the Royal Law, and Rule of Christ be followed That Men and Magistrates shall do to all as they would be done unto; or rather, Do to men as God would. Otherwise, <reg orig="Wo">Woe</reg> be unto those who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> violate their <reg orig="Vowes">Vows</reg>, and persecute the Saints.</p>

<p>The English Fleet are now put to sea, being 80 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, and are divided into three Squadrons Gen. Pen commands the Van, Gen. Blake the right Wing, and Rear-Admiral Lawson the Rear; but upon any occasion can soon <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> into one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> Body, there being Scouts appointed, who are to give no <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> appearance of the <reg orig="enemys">enemies</reg>.</p>

<p>Several Letters are come from Scotland, to the Royal Party in Northumberland, to invite them to a Rising; but many were intercepted, and sent up to the Lord Protector. Notwithstanding they have continual Meetings, and have great <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> in hand, as <reg orig="appeares">appears</reg> by their sundry Risings in several places; yet dissolve of themselves. 'Tis <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> so to do, I conceive; for 'tis dangerous falling into the hands of great Ones: Blame me not, <unclear>I speak</unclear> it experimentally.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday Feb. 4.</head>

<p>From Scotland they write that Col. <em>Hume</em> (an excellent <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> ) and divers other <reg orig="experienc'd">experienced</reg> Commanders, and Sons of <em>Mars</em> have <reg orig="declar'd">declared</reg> for their Master CHARLES, and are gone from towards Berwick to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Highlanders. Sir Arthur Forbs, and valiant<pb n="2" /> Col. Wogan <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> wounded at Weims; but whether recoverable, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>: if not, their Deaths will be much lamented by the Royal party. The Earl of Athol hath had a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> for the KING, in the North; and Gen. Glencarn, and the Lord Kenmore are gone to the Hills, and have burnt and made great <reg orig="devastat">devastate</reg> upon the Lord <reg orig="Lothians">Lothian's</reg> houses and lands, for his disloyalty to his <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, and complying with the English at the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> late furious Assault on Dunkel, where was slain the Laird <unclear>Ballachan</unclear>, cap. Hunter, cap. Robertson, and some other young Lairds; but <reg orig="undanted">undaunted</reg> Major Mercer was mortally wounded with a Tuck.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Feb. 6.</head>

<p>Our <em>Scout</em> from Newcastle advertiseth, That there has been a high Contest between the Quakers and the Country people at Hasington: but after a sharp Dispute, many on both sides came off bleeding by weeping cross, <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> for their <reg orig="intrenching">entrenching</reg> upon other <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> Rights and principles. <i>Excellent measure! May the justness of each <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> cause carry at.</i></p>

<head level="3">Tuesday Feb. 7.</head>

<p>The Dutch Merchants have spread their Canvass, and <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth into the Deep; but young Tromp is their Convoy, and has given the English the go-by. Since which time, many English Merchants are put forth to sea, and are gone to several Ports in France.</p>

<head level="3">Wednesday Feb. 8.</head>

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of London having invited His Highness the Lord Protector to dinner at Grocers Hall, the several Companies of the City had this day) Order from the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> to meet at <reg orig="Guild-hall">Guildhall</reg> in their Gown and from thence to place <reg orig="them selves">themselves</reg> according to their superiority in the streets, from the lower end of <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> Temple-Bar, to attend the coming in of so great and honourable <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear>; is appeared by the high &amp; mighty preparations fit for the greatest Prince or Potentate; for the streets were <reg orig="rais'd">raised</reg>, as in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of the King; and the Rails were all hung with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> Cloth: The City Banners, and the Golden Streamers and Standards were all placed along the said <reg orig="Railes">Rails</reg> in a most delicate and stately manner: The which being erected and set up, the Lord Mayor, with the Mare, Sword, and Cap of Maintenance, and the<pb n="3" /> women in their Scarlet Gowns, rode as far as Temple Bar, where they met his Highness and all his magnificent Train: And his Highness had the sword delivered to him by the Lord Mayor, which was returned again; and after a short Oration, in congratulation of his Highness, so soon as He came out of His Coach, the manner of this great Solemnization was as followeth: First, came the City Marshal and some other Officers; then six Trumpeters, with his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Life-guard">Lifeguard</reg>; then eight Trumpets more, with the City Streamers, red and white; then the Aldermen in their Scarlet Gowns: Next after them the two Sheriff, and their Officers; then the Herald of Arms with rich Coats, adorned with the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Arms, <em>viz</em>. the Cross and Harp; then the Golden Mace and Cap of Maintenance: After which, came the Lord Mayor <reg orig="bare headed">bareheaded</reg>, <reg orig="carying">carrying</reg> the Sword; next after, rode two Gentlemen bare before his Highness; with whom went twelve of his <reg orig="foot-men">footmen</reg>, in <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> coats, and silver and black silk Lace: His Highness had a very rich coat <reg orig="empbroyder'd">embroidered</reg> with gold, and a gold Hatbond, who in the height of this Magnificency <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> abundance of humility to the people, moving his hath continually unto them all along the streets. After his Highness, cam Major General <em>Skippon</em>, and the rest of his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council: then the Officers of the Army, with renowned col. <em>Pride</em>, who was as plain as a <reg orig="Pike-staff">Pikestaff</reg>, in a <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> short coat: Then after them, divers Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, in a most excellent equipage, both on horseback and in Coaches. And coming to Grocers Hall, the Recorder made a Speech to his Highness, letting him understand, how <reg orig="bappy">happy</reg> the City were in the enjoyment of his Person. After he had done, his Highness having retired himself a while above <reg orig="staires">stairs</reg>, came down to dine in the great Hall, where he sat in the middle of a long Table, his Son the Lord <em>Henry</em> on the left hand, and the Lord Mayor on the right; &amp; on each side of them the Council, with Gen. <em>Monk</em>, Commis. Gen. <em>Whaley</em>, &amp; Mr. <em>Claypool</em>, master of the horse to his Highness, being entertained (besides rare <reg orig="Chear">Cheer</reg>, and delicate Dainties, with <reg orig="musick">music</reg>, <reg orig="Voyces">Voices</reg>, Drums and Trumpets. After this, his Highness was conducted <reg orig="up stairs">upstairs</reg> again, by the Lord Mayor, to a noble Banquet. This being done, his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> <unclear>departed</unclear> being <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> out by <reg orig="Heboys">Oboes</reg>, and other loud <reg orig="musick">music</reg>. In all <unclear><!-- approx. 3/4 of a line --></unclear> expressions of affection<pb n="4" /> given a <em>good</em> example to the rest of the Nation. I wish we may enjoy benefit under his protection. For, to speak truth, many are unsatisfied, and during the time of this magnificent Feasting, divers of the discontented (though not long since a precious) party betook <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> to praying. <i>The Lord unite the hearts of all his Saints.</i></p>

<p>By an Express from aboard the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>, thus: On the 26 of <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. We took the <em>Doggord</em> of <em>Flushing</em>, and on the 27 we recovered the <em>Patrick</em> of <em><reg orig="Leverpool">Liverpool</reg></em> from the Brest men of War, who act by commission from the K. of Scots. We chased cap. <em><reg orig="Dillons">Dillon's</reg></em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>, but she ran so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em><reg orig="Pensance">Penzance</reg></em> <reg orig="key">Quay</reg>, that we durst not follow her. The I intended to make up to the Lands-end; but by cross winds we were soon brought within sight of 4 ships of S. <em>Maloes</em> coming from <em>Marseilles</em>, bound for New haven, viz the St. <em>Martin</em> with 18 guns &amp; 44 men, the St <em>Helena</em> with 14 guns, and 32 men, the <em>Protection</em> with 21 guns, and 32 men and the <em>Francis</em> with ten guns, and 38 men laden with soap, <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, cotton, &amp;c. with whom we came up about one of the clock, and fought them 5 hours. The <em>Martin</em> and <em>Helena</em> had both yielded but we had none of our men aboard; it beginning to be dark, and We being ready to board the <em>Protection</em>, whom we had well paid with shot, bethought <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> that we should lose the other two in taking her &amp; so <reg orig="cleered">cleared</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with much ado, &amp; stood to the other, who being secured we were bearing for the other yet untaken; but these two ships we had taken were so much disabled, as we were forced to keep by them to save them from sinking, &amp; men to fit the Rigging, the Admiral not being able to bear <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, which occasioned the losing the other two. Our ships <reg orig="suffeced">suffered</reg> in hull, masts, rigging, &amp; sails, <em>viz</em>. in the <reg orig="main mast">mainmast</reg> three shot, the <reg orig="topmast">top mast</reg> two, our <reg orig="fore-yard">foreyard</reg> &amp; <reg orig="mizen">mizzen</reg> yard made unserviceable; we had several shot between wind &amp; water, 5 men killed, and 19 wounded: some having lost their legs &amp; others their arms: <i>A dismal sight to see</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Prizes taken the last week.</i></head>

<!-- What follows is two lists that appear alongside on another, separated by a vertical line. I've typed each line of both lists as a separate paragraph. The page break occurs directly after the lists, so I've marked it at the end of the second (right hand column) list -->

<p>One prize laden with Wine, taken by the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>.</p>
<p>One sweet Prize laden with Raisins &amp; Figs, taken by the old Warwick.</p>

<p>One man of war, with 20 guns, taken by the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg>.</p>
<p>Two private men of war taken to the Northward.</p>
<p><unclear>Two</unclear> ships laden with Almonds, taken by the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg> interpreted by Prophet <em>Evans</em>.</i></head>

<p>First, the Lily shall remain in a merry World, and he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be moved against the Seed of the <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, and he shall stand on one side amongst Thrones of his <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which Country is the Land of the Moon, which is to be dread throughout all the World. 2. And there shall come the Son of Man, bearing three wild Beasts in his <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, with a company of people he shall pass many waters, and he shall come to the Land of the <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, looking for help with Beasts of his own <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. 3 And in that year there shall come an Eagle out of the East, and his Wings spread with the <reg orig="beames">beams</reg> of the Son of Man. 4 And that year shall be destroyed Castles upon Thames, &amp; there shall be great fear over all the World, and in a part of the Land there shall be great <reg orig="Battels">Battles</reg> among many Kingdoms. 5 That day shall be the bloody field, and the Lilly shall lose the Crown, and therewith <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> crowned the Son of man. 6 And in the fourth year many <reg orig="battels">battles</reg> <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> for the faith, and most of the world <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> stoopen; but the Son of man with the Eagle <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> preferred, and there <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> universal peace over all the World: then shall the Son of man receive a marvellous token, and there <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> great plenty of all manner of fruits, and then <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> he go to the Land of the Cross.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Interpretation.</i></head>

<p>This Lilly is Mr. Lilly the Astrologer, and the merry <reg orig="Worln">World</reg> is a mad world that believe Astrologers contrary to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> mind. M. Lilly shall be moved against the Seed of the <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, that is, the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Seed, against whom he writ so bitterly. And Lilly shall stand on one side amongst Thrones of his <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, that is, he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand for the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: which <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> is the Land of the Moon: He compares England to the Moon, in regard of its changing from one thing to another as the Moon changeth every month: so England <reg orig="to day">today</reg> is a Protestant <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> a Presbyterian, next day an Independent, and you know not what; and all the world looking upon the distempers of England, is afraid lest some of this English Seed come amongst them, and infect them with the same disease, yea and conquer their Kings, and bring them also to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and destruction. 2 The Son of man is the King which crosseth the waters from France to Holland, and from Holland to Scotland, to seek help and assistance: <pb n="6" />And Scotland he calleth the Land of the <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg> in regard their King came from thence. 8 By this Eagle that comes from the East, is meant the Dutch, ships coming against England, and some of them bearing the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Colours. 1652. 4 By the Castles destroyed upon Thames, is meant the overthrow given to our ships in Decemb. 1652. 5 By that day, he <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> 1653. in which the bloody <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg> shall be fought, and the Lilly shall lose his Crown: here M. <em>Lillie</em> <reg orig="appeares">appears</reg> to be the white mock-king; for he hath <reg orig="domineer'd">domineered</reg> the most: And therefore <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> he and his lose their Crowns. 6 By the fourth year he means 1654. then <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> the World be in an Uproar fighting for Religion, but they must bow to the true Protestant Religion, and God will cause the Supporters thereof to be highly honoured in all parts of the World. Thus hoping I have spoken the truth to all, without respect of persons, wherein I am not their enemy, but their friend, being <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> servant in so doing, for his glory, and the peace and <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg> of his People,</p>

<p><em>Gentlemen</em> I hope I shall be clear from the blood of this Generation, being sent of God to declare the things hereafter mentioned: For it is evident, I <reg orig="fore-told">fore told</reg> the manner of the death of King Charles, and do herein <reg orig="fore see">foresee</reg> a great and mighty change. So that if the people now refuse to hear me, (who have had so many witnesses to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> that God is pleased to declare his determinate Will by me) they of all others will be the least excusable for despising me, and so the least capable of mercy. For have they not known how God by me declared the most remarkable things that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> these kingdoms since the wars began: How that 20 years ago I declared the things that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> my late <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, and that I suffered three <reg orig="yeares">years</reg> imprisonment for the same? How that I declared to the Earl of Essex 7 years before he was General, that he should be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> General against the King? Have they not known how that in the year 1646 I declared the <reg orig="downfal">downfall</reg> of the Presbyterians. How I declared, that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Son would come to England long before he came to Worcester, and his success likewise? How I declared to the Parl. that they should be destroyed long before their dissolution? Therefore, I beseech you, consider what I have declared, and so peace be with you all, <em>Amen</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Thursday Feb. 9.</head>

<p>From Windsor it is certified, That Mr. Feak and Mr. Simpson have sent a letter to the Lord Protector, and another to their Churches, to desire them to keep close together, and wait upon God, for that the Lord had spoke peace to their <reg orig="soules">souls</reg>, &amp; confident they were that deliverance was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> at hand. Some things are under consideration touching the restoring of Maj. Gen, Brown to liberty: 'tis time! But poor Judge Jenkins lies still captivated in Windsor Castle. The business of Sir Jo. Lenthal and the Upper Bench is likewise taken into consideration: of which an account will suddenly be given. The Queen of Sweden has sent a Letter to the K. of Scots, wherein her Majesty doth excuse <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> that the present condition of her affairs doth not suffer her to give him satisfaction upon his Demands, protesting that she pities his misfortune. Of this, more hereafter. The peace is concluded between the K. of Poland and the Cossacks; but the great Duke of Muscovy has sent a Letter to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Maj at Upsal, signifying, that he hath mustered a hundred and sixty thousand men, and desires her Maj. to declare and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him against the said King. The great Duke of <reg orig="Tuskany">Tuscany</reg> has sent an Ambassador to congratulate the Lord Protector, and the Lo. of Amiland in Holland has sent an Agent to his Highness with Credentials, desiring that they may be esteemed as Neutrals, to any <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. The United Provinces have not yet brought in their Resolves for ratification of the Articles; but go on pell-mell with their Navigable proceedings, and every man is constrained to work upon the Lords day. The K. of <reg orig="Scots">Scot's</reg> <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> increase, as appears by the ensuing list and daily infest the Western channel.</p>

<head level="3">A List of the Brest men of War, <em>&amp;c</em>.</head>

<!-- What follows are two lists which actually appear alongside one another in the original newsbook. I've done each line of both lists as a separate paragraph -->

<p>The Royal James with 38 guns, Richard Beach Captain.</p>
<p>The Michael 14 guns, Cap. James Smith.</p>
<p>The Bridget 8 guns Cap. Wil. Smith,</p>
<p>The Francis 10 guns, Cap. Meldrum,</p>
<p>The Mall 10 guns, Cap. Covel,</p>
<p>The loyal James 12 guns, Cap. Ia. Dillon</p>
<p>The Mary 4 guns, Cap. Rich. Dillon,</p>
<p>The St. Francis 20 guns, Cap. Durant,</p>
<p>The Charles 8 guns, Cap <reg orig="Iones">Jones</reg>.</p>

<p>The Blossome 22 guns, Cap. Martin,</p>
<p>Margaret 3 guns, Cap. Heldish,</p>
<p>Patrick 18 guns, cap. Swart,</p>
<p>Katherine 6 guns, Cap. Estmund.</p>
<p>Swiftsure 6 guns, Cap. Peters,</p>
<p>Frost 7 guns Cap. Rivers,</p>
<p>Snow 4 guns, Cap. Munro,</p>
<p>Adventure 12 guns, Cap. George,</p>
<p>Three French-men with 18 &amp; 20 Gu.</p>
<p>Three in the Stocks of 4 guns apiece.</p>

<p>From Scotland they report, that the L. Seaforth hath stormed the Fort at Lewis Island, with 1400 men, and taken it from the English; Of this, more in my next.</p>

<hr />

<p>A Brown bay Nag with a <unclear><!-- 20 characters approx., there's a stamp over it --></unclear> racks a little, with a little white on his nose, <unclear>scarce</unclear> discernible with a thick nostril, about 4 or 5 years of age: <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> with Mr. Tho. <unclear>Allan</unclear> at St <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> in Essex, a fortnight before Christmas: If any one can bring <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> to Mr. W. Allen in the Poultry, or to Mr. Ric. Kingsten a Grocer, under the Spread Eagle in Gracious street, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be well rewarded for their pains.</p>

<hr />
<p>Appointed to be printed; And extracted out of the Original Papers, licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>