<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout163">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 163
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>A Declaration of the States of Holland, prohibiting their Merchants from going out with their Ships, till the Cessation with England be confirmed and proclaimed. The proceedings of His Highness the Lord Protector and the Council, concerning the regulating of the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> of this Nation, and the propagation of the Gospel. The Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> Answer to the Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, with her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desires to renew the former Alliance, and conclude a firmer Union between England and Sweden. Also a Declaration of the two Generals of the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> concerning the New Government, with the Resolution of the Officers and Seamen thereupon, and the dissenting of some of Col. <reg orig="Harisons">Harison's</reg> Regiment. The K. of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> consultation with Prince <em>Rupert</em>, and two prizes taken out of the Harbour of <em>Brest</em>. <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg> beleaguering <em>Burgy</em> with 1500 men, and the routing of <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg>. With the committing of M. F<em>eak</em> and M. <em>Simpson</em> to Windsor, and some notable passages concerning Mr. <em>Vavasor Powel.</em></i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday January</em> 27, to <em>Friday</em> February <em>the</em> 3. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday, <em>January</em> 27.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p> The Regiments in <em>Scotland</em> (except some few of Major General <reg orig="Harisons">Harison's</reg> late Regiment, and those chiefly of the <reg orig="Welch">Welsh</reg> Troop) do well approve of the New Government, and the Officers generally send in their Addresses, to be sent to his Highness to that purpose. There was a Shallop lately built up, and four Guns put in her to secure Trade in the River <em>Clyde</em>, and to prevent the <reg orig="High landers">Highlanders</reg> falling into Renfrewshire, but one Col. Harriot came with some Boats from the Loughs and secured her. Also a Lieutenant and 7 or 8 Officers were taken and <reg orig="caried">carried</reg> to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>The last Letters from <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that there hath lately been some knocks given on both sides, and divers Officers of quality slain; The Scots having with extraordinary <reg orig="ods">odds</reg> routed a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> party of ours, were so <unclear>flesht</unclear>, that they came down to <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em> Town, but for all their bravado durst not stay above two hours, at their departure they left a Proclamation pasted on the <em>Market-cross</em>, prohibiting all persons in the Shires of Ayr, Dunbarton, <reg orig="Ranfew">Renfrew</reg> and the places adjacent, not to presume to <reg orig="sel">sell</reg>, give, or deliver up, to any belonging to the <em>Common Enemy</em> (as they term us) any serviceable horse or Arms, or <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> horse or Arms to the prejudice of <em>His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Service</em>, upon pain of being <reg orig="sequestred">sequestered</reg>, and their goods and chattels to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> for the use of any that shall first apprehend them. This was subscribed by that notable <em>Strong-water</em> sucker,</p>
<p><reg orig="GLENCARN">GLENCAIRN</reg>.</p>
<p>The last Week I gave the Reader notice in the <em>Scout</em> [if he was not <reg orig="deceiv'd">deceived</reg> with the <em>mock-Scout</em> printed with <em>G.H</em> his name to it] that there was an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> from Holland landed at Harwich, and that he was expected on Thursday to come to London; this <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> was Mons. <em>Beverlin</em> one of the Dutch Deputies that lately went from hence with the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Message to the States of Holland, who according to expectation arrived here on Thursday, and had Audience that day by His Excellency and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; he Declareth, that the States of the Province of <em>Holland</em> have consented to the Articles agreed upon with his Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and that there will speedily be Deputies from the rest of the Provinces, as also from <em>Holland</em>, to see it ratified on our part; but there is some suspect the <em>Zealanders</em> will not be very forward in promoting it.</p>
<p>There are divers Ships Windbound in <em>Falmouth</em> Harbour, who intend for London with the first opportunity: But there are many Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> riding between the Lands end and the Isle of <em>Scilly</em>, which makes them fearful to pass without a Convoy. Our Fleet rides still near St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em> point, ready upon the least appearance of the Dutch to set sail and fight them, if a peace ensue not.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday, Jan. 28.</i></head>
<p>The Town of <em>Argier</em> was not more famous for educating of the Turkish <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em>Brest</em> is for nursing up of the French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>: Our <em>Post</em> hath received Intelligence, that they have 20 <pb n="2" /> sail of Men of War out, whereof one hath 36 Guns, and 200 men, and others about 24 and 20 Guns, but most of 12 and under. They have lately taken two Barks belonging to Falmouth, and sent them into France. And in retaliation thereof, we have taken a French ship laden with <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> cloth, Paper, and other French goods.</p>
<p>This day came to my hand a Pamphlet, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> <i>Strena Vavasoriensis, A New <reg orig="Years">Year's</reg> guilt for the <unclear><reg orig="Welch-Itinerants">Welsh Itinerants</reg></unclear></i>; Or, <i>A <em>Hue-and-Cry</em> after <em>Mr.</em> Vavasor Powel.</i> Wherein the Author, after he had touched upon those places of Scripture (which with <reg orig="infinit">infinite</reg> others <em>Powel</em> wrested and <reg orig="mis-applied">misapplied</reg>) then he proceeded upon his <em>Seditions</em> and <em>Invective Accusations</em>. And <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg>, that first <i>Powel abused the <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council</i>, and called their Proclamation, <i>A Libel</i>. Secondly, <i>That <em>He</em> basely traduced the Commanders, Officers, and Soldiers of the Army; <em>nay, (their Wives and families escaped not the <unclear>last</unclear></em> [<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> my Author] <em>of</em> his Tongue; <em>and told the</em> <reg orig="Sword-men">Swordmen</reg> <em>in</em> General, <em>That</em> the Spirit of God was departed from them, that heretofore had been precious and Excellent men, and that their <em>Parks</em>, new <em>Houses</em>, and gallant <em>Wives (that which indeed all men are subject to <reg orig="doat">dote</reg> upon (perhaps he spoke experimentally)</em> had <reg orig="choaked">choked</reg> them. <em>Thirdly</em>, That they had all revolted from the Lord, and left his people Fatherless. <em>Fourthly</em>, that <em>Powel</em> also abused <em>His <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg></em> Chaplains, whom he said had thousands a Year to set up this New Government;</i> All which, the Author ingenuously and learnedly confuted, and wished, that if the Chaplains had their thousands, it might <reg orig="me">be</reg> multiplied to ten thousands; which with I second, and am confident that no honest <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> man but will do the like, <i>That not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they, but all other deserving men may be rewarded according to their deserts.</i></p>
<p>After this he printed his <em>Hymn</em> at <em>Christchurch</em>, with the <em>Antiphona</em> thereunto, a true Copy of which I have <em>verbatim</em> inserted.</p>
<head level="3">His Hymn at <em><reg orig="Christ Church">Christchurch</reg></em>, 18 Decemb, 1653.</head>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>To Christ <em>our King</em> let us praise <unclear>sing</unclear>,</line>
<line>Who is our Saviour dear,</line>
<line>Who is our <em>Protector</em> and our flock,</line>
<line>Who will come and soon appear</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>To humble his, and try their hearts,</line>
<line>And make them clean and pure,</line>
<line>To set his Kingdom upon Earth,</line>
<line>Which ever shall endure:</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His <em>Saints</em> <unclear>shall</unclear> reign with him on <em>Earth</em></line>
<line>And <em>Great Ones</em> then shall bow,</line>
<line>The Battle, and the <reg orig="Battle Ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>And men of War <unclear>shall</unclear> know,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>That he will arise, and he will rule,</line>
<line>And their power will fall,</line>
<line>And Christ our <em>Great Commander</em>, He</line>
<line>Shall be our <em>General</em>.</line>
</stanza>
<pb n="3" />
<stanza>
<line><reg orig="Hast">Haste</reg> Lord, come quickly down,</line>
<line>Thy Saints do wait and pray,</line>
<line>And men would fain, if they knew how</line>
<line>Thy Prophets kill and slay.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>But they shall live, and eke stand up,</line>
<line>And give their Testimony</line>
<line>Against the Monarchs of the Earth,</line>
<line>That lit, and reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line><i>The <em>Antiphona</em> thereunto.</i></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>The <em>Devil's</em> your King, his praise you sing,</line>
<line>His Spirit leads you here,</line>
<line>Who is your <em>Protector</em>, and your <em>Rock</em>,</line>
<line>And in you doth appear.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>'Tis he exalts and lifts your hearts,</line>
<line>To make you his most sure,</line>
<line>To set his <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> upon Earth,</line>
<line>Which shall not long endure:</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His Saints shall reign with him in Hell,</line>
<line>And to him they shall bow,</line>
<line>The Battle, and the <reg orig="Battle-ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>And men of War do know,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Though he <unclear>be</unclear> up, and his doth rule,</line>
<line>Yet his Power will fall,</line>
<line>Since <reg orig="Sathan">Satan</reg> your good Master, He</line>
<line>Is your great <em>General</em>.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>The Lord will come in his due time,</line>
<line>His Saints for to preserve,</line>
<line>And all your lying Prophets slay,</line>
<line>Who from his Word do swerve.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His <em>Word</em> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, his <em>Saints</em> shall live,</line>
<line>To give their Testimony</line>
<line>Against false Teachers of the Earth,</line>
<line>Who strive to reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Jan. 30.</head>
<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector hath consulted with his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, about the regulating of the Laws of this Nation, and particularly of the Chancery, for the general good of the Nation. Also an Order is appointed to be drawn up by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for propagating of the Gospel in the Northern Counties of England.</p>
<p>Mr. Feak, and Mr. Simpson were this day committed prisoners to Windsor Castle. And one was likewise set upon a wooden horse at Tower-hill, and had his <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --> cut</unclear>, for forging of an Order in the name of the Commissioners of the Navy, to <reg orig="cousen">cozen</reg> the State of nine pounds.</p>
<p>From Copenhagen it is certified, That the Dutch Fleet which were beaten in there again by some English <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> from <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, are resolved to Winter there. The City had suffered much by a late <unclear>fire</unclear>, had not the King and Court bestirred themselves to quench it, which <reg orig="onely">only</reg> consumed two or three houses. They hear every day of the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> great respect to the English Ambassador, which increaseth their fears and jealousies; and now they seem more afraid <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, that the Dutch will leave them in the <reg orig="bryers">briars</reg>. But they may comfort themselves in this, That they have not much wool to lose.</p>
<head level="3">A DECLARATION.</head>
<head level="3"><i>By the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at Amsterdam.</i></head>
<p>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the <unclear>Admiralty residing</unclear> at Amsterdam,</p> 
<p>To all those before whom these presents shall come, Greeting.</p>
<p>Let it be known, that it being conceived, though, and apparent, that upon the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of the Lords Deputies of this State from England, to make report <pb n="4" /> how far the Treaty there is by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> grace and favour effected, some Merchants and Masters of Merchants ships, upon presumption of a Cessation of hostility, have been so forward as to have brought out their ships and goods, and have beyond their hope suffered losses; We have found good, and resolved to give warning to all and <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> whom it concerneth, as also <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> is warned by these presents; That the former hostility doth yet continue, and that it is not <unclear>fit</unclear> nor convenient that <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> should in regard of the Treaty, think himself secure, before upon the continuation of the Negotiation, there shall be a Cessation of the aforesaid hostility proclaimed.</p>
<p><i>Acted in the Assembly of the said <reg orig="Cunncel">Council</reg> the 26 of January, 1653.4.</i></p>
<p>V. HERBERTS.</p>
<p>DAVID WILDT.</p>
<head level="3">Tuesday, Jan. 31.</head>
<p>It is further certified from Scotland, that the Enemy being in Dunkel, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. Johnstons sent out 100 horse, and 100 dragoons, who beat them from the <reg orig="Turn pike">Turnpike</reg>, and forced them out of the Town; there were 7 killed, but many wounded, and most <reg orig="Athols">Atholl's</reg> troopers made footmen, himself very narrowly escaped our men; we took 50 horse and 7 troopers, their foot escaped to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> hath beleaguered Burgy, with 1200 foot and 300 horse. Kenmore keeps his Guards upon the River Findern.</p>
<p>From <em><unclear>Beaand</unclear></em> our <em>Scout</em> brings Intelligence, that the States are gone to the Hague to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in confirmation of the Treaty with England. That the Assembly at the Hague is dissolved till the 20 of Febr. next, and that they desire a Cessation with England, till the rest of the provinces have ratified the Articles of peace. The French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> hath audience, but his propositions are kept secret.</p>
<p><em>Conde</em> refuseth to come to the King of <em>France</em>, and his Brother <em>Conti</em> <reg orig="enclines">inclines</reg> to the marriage with <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>. The titular King of <em>Scots</em> hath with prince <em>Rupert</em> and others of his council, been several times deliberating about weighty <reg orig="affaairs">affairs</reg>, and his friends report, that Gen. <em>O'Brian</em> hath got a body in <em>Ireland</em> of 4000 foot and 1000 horse, and doth fence the Castle of <em>Dingle</em> by the <reg orig="sea side">seaside</reg>.</p>
<p>Some Aldermen of the City of London, have this Week made several Addresses to his Highness the Lord protector.</p>
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church over against the Stile that goes to Stepney, <unclear>in Trumpet</unclear> yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness</unclear> of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, all sorts of Agues [of which cure he never failed; and hath cured many that have been <unclear>thought <reg orig="uncurable">incurable</reg></unclear>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him. The History of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year, 1652.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, Febr. the First.</i></head>
<p>In my last, I gave you a brief <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of the Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> journey from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> to the <em>Swedish</em> Court at <em><reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg></em>, and certified you of his honourable entertainment; since which, her sacred Majesty hath been pleased to vouchsafe him audience; where his Lordship made an Excellent Oration in Latin, and it being translated into English I have inserted a copy of it, as it came to my hands.</p>
<head level="3"><i>His <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg> the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> speech to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em></i>.</head>
<p><em>Madam</em>, By command from my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg>, the Parliament of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, I do with all respect salute your Majesty, which had been sooner done, if by extraordinary accidents and engagements in the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of three Nations with no few <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> <reg orig="Divertions">Diversions</reg> it had not been retarded. And although the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> are not encouraged to send abroad, when they reflect upon the Barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places; yet your Majesty perceives that from your Government, neither our Masters nor their Servants have the least suspicion of any such entertainment: but we who are here present, do gratefully acknowledge our experience of the contrary, and of much Civility to our Nation.</p>
<p>My business is to communicate with your Majesty in matters relating to the common good, which is of so great weight that it admits of no hopes of <reg orig="successe">success</reg> without his special blessing, who by small means can bring great things to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>; the confidence whereof, with my submiss to the judgement and Commands of my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg> hath given me this Honour of being in your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence.</p>
<p>Whom, I shall not weary with many words or expressions beyond meaning; I am not sent hither for that cause, and it is different from my own <unclear>spirit</unclear>, as contrary to the practise and commands of my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg>, from whom, and from their servant, according to the <em>English</em> reality, your Majesty will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> all manner of <reg orig="plainnesse">plainness</reg> and truth in our transactions, Our deliverances and preservations, whereof we have been <reg orig="eye-witnesses">eyewitnesses</reg>, have been so near to miracles, and such monuments of infinite rich mercy and love from Heaven, that we should sin against them, if the least guile, or <reg orig="unfaithfulnesse">unfaithfulness</reg> should infect our conversation.</p>
<p>It is not my work to paint out my own <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, or to draw black lines upon any, though our adversaries; neither shall I take upon me to mention the excellencies of your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Person and Government, or of your people, and <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>, lest I should injure any merit; and because I speak to those whom God hath favoured with the enjoyment of great mercies, the increase and continuances whereof is heartily desired by my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg>, and by me their servant. The present happy Government under your Majesty remembers unto <pb n="6" /> us those blessed <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of our Virgin Queen <em><reg orig="Elisabeth">Elizabeth</reg></em>, under whom above 40 years the people enjoyed all protection and justice from their Prince, and she all obedience and affection from her people. May this and more be <unclear>the</unclear> portion of your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> and your <reg orig="Successours">Successors</reg>, nor had it been left in those who followed Queen <em><reg orig="Elisabeth">Elizabeth</reg></em>, though <reg orig="forreigners">foreigners</reg>, but through the extremity of their own Government. When attempts were made to ravish from us our highest interest, the Orthodox Religion and just liberty, the defence whereof undertaken by King <em>Gustavus Adolphus</em>, your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Royal Father of blessed memory, in his <em>German</em> Expedition, for the <reg orig="Protestants">Protestants'</reg> relief was in him most honourable and <reg orig="successfull">successful</reg>, and surely for us was most just and necessary, and alike crowned with gracious <reg orig="successe">success</reg> by the Almighty. For the extirpation of both which had long been endeavoured otherwise; the fire brake out, first in <em>Scotland</em>, afterward in <em>Ireland</em>, and lastly in all parts of <em>England</em>, and not a Family Free from the rage of our decennial, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> civil War, and yet after so much <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> powered forth, we <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God we live, who was pleased still to determine for the Parliament, and after these, and eight tenders and Treaties of peace, wherein we received the denial from our adversaries, it pleased the gracious and all disposing hand of God for the good of <em>England</em>, to change the Government thereof. We cannot <reg orig="finde">find</reg> that in any age there hath been a declared War between these two Nations, but a constant intercourse of friendship and Amity, with mutual Offices of kindness out of which great profit and <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg> hath redounded unto both. And your Majesty having by your late <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers to <em>England</em> signified your Royal inclination and willingness by all good means to conserve and <reg orig="encrease">increase</reg> the ancient good understanding between these States, upon these and other weighty considerations, and to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how acceptable the former overtures of your Majesty have been, the <em>Parliament</em> have thought fit by me to make tender unto your Majesty of the friendship of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and to let you know that they are not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> ready to renew and preserve inviolably that amity and good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> which hath hitherto been between the two Nations, but are farther willing to enter into a more strict Alliance and Union (then hath as yet been) for the good of both. And in such a way as shall he held requisite, I shall be ready more particularly to communicate what I have in charge for this purpose. <i>Thus far the speech.</i></p>
<p>The <em><reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg></em> most Excellent Majesty having seriously and attentively <unclear>audited</unclear> his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, returned a gracious answer, to the great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> of all that heard her. This ensuing Letter will further inform you.</p>
<p><i><em>SIR</em>, We are now at <em><reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg></em>, where the Queen resides by reason the <unclear>Plague at <em>Stockholm</em>. My Lord was entertained with very much respect, and on the 23 of December my Lord had Audience; and the Queen heard him with as much Gravity and Majesty, as to any apprehension</unclear> might be <pb n="6" /> composed in a Woman, if not in a man; and my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> having had twice private Audience since, commendeth her to be the acute Woman that ever he met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and to be admired for her knowledge in <reg orig="publike">public</reg> affairs, knowing the transactions of State far beyond his expectation. Here are several <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> come to reside from <em>Spain, France, Holland, Denmark</em> and <em>Russia</em>: And though they endeavour to obstruct my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> proceedings, there is very great hopes of effecting the business his Excellence came hither about, the Queen having declared such readiness and freedom to treat with my Lord about it. For the Queen told my Lord, that she esteemed it a great honour, that the Parliament had been pleased to send an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> to her, especially of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> condition, and that she <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> would take care, during his abode there, that not the least injury should be offered to him nor his company. And further said, that in the transaction she would manifest the affection she bore to the Commonwealth, and that she not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> desired to renew former <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between them, but to enter into a nearer Union <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore.</i></p>
<p><reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg>. Jan. 1654.</p>
<head level="3">Thursday, Febr. 2.<i></i></head>
<p>The last Letters from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, that a great Flemish ship put on shore at <em>Dartmouth</em>, having <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one dead man aboard her. Some Canary ships are safely arrived at Falmouth, and 4 ships from Malago are come into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>. The Wetwang and the <unclear>Newcastle</unclear> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, brought two Dutch Capers of 6 Guns apiece and 100 prisoners, into Newcastle And some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken two ships within the Haven of Brest. The <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg> with an unanimous <unclear>consent</unclear>, have presented a Declaration to his Highness, with an Address subscribed by the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the fleet. Wherein they acknowledge their thankfulness, that the Lord hath preserved his highness from many eminent dangers, and understanding he hath accepted of the protection of this Commonwealth, declare they will be faithful and obedient to his highness, in performance of their trust, and also that in the utmost hazard of their lives they will be <reg orig="service able">serviceable</reg> unto his highness in the station that the Lord hath placed him.</p>
<p>This day was published an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance appointing a Committee for the Army, and Treasures at War.</i></p>
<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
<p><em>LONDON</em>, Printed by R. WOOD, 1654.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>