<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout174">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 174
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The Return of the Messengers from <em>Holland</em>, and the Signing of the Ratification of the Articles of Peace by the States General; Together with a Copy of the Instrument sent over by them for his Highness the Lord Protector to subscribe unto. Also the King of <em>France</em> his desires, that the King of <em>Scots</em> and his Mother would depart his Territories, and their resolution thereupon; With a <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight between three English Merchants Ships returning richly laden from the Straits, and three French men of War, and the grievous <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> sustained by the English therein. Sundry notable Fights between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Highlanders</em>, with the routing of their parties in several places; Also the Rising of the <em>Scots</em> in the <em><reg orig="Low-lands">Lowlands</reg></em>, the killing and taking of many Officers and prisoners of quality, and General <em>Monk</em> appointed to be Commander in Chief of all the forces raised there <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England</i>.</p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 7. to <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 14. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>April</em> the 7</i>.</head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>When Nations have been long <reg orig="over-grown">overgrown</reg> with corruptions, there usually are but two sorts of Cures; the one is by <em>Force</em>, the other by <em>Policy</em>: the most <em>frequent</em> is <em>Force</em>, but the Best, <em>Policy</em>, which doth not make <unclear>such <em>deep incisions</em></unclear> as the other, because <em>many times <unclear>the Remedy is worse</unclear> <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <unclear>Disease</unclear></em>. He that <unclear>cured</unclear> by Force, is sometimes constrained by the <unclear>knottiness</unclear> or difficulty of the Work, to cut so deep as to <reg orig="kil">kill</reg>; but this is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> incident to those who observe not the temper of the Patients, and are ruled by (rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> rule) their own passion; which hath been one main Cause, <i>That many Victor, have lost the benefit of their Victories, for want of knowledge to make right use of them</i>.</p>
<p>Some Princes have been led out of the way by Flatterers, who have <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> them to govern by their Wills, and not to be <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> to Laws, <i>which are <reg orig="bnt">bent</reg> as Cobwebs to catch the smaller <reg orig="flyes">flies</reg></i>; those have made Force (which should be used <pb n="1" /> as <reg orig="Phisick">Physic</reg> to cure) to destroy, and by that means fomented War, to raise themselves to the <reg orig="pinacle">pinnacle</reg> of Riches.</p>
<p>But the greatest Wisdom and Art that can be <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> by those that govern, is, to avoid <unclear>Flatterers</unclear>, and those that aim at nothing but self-ends; and the <unclear>best</unclear> way to be sure not to be deceived, is to suspect all men, but not <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the <unclear>suspicion</unclear>; for Flatterers will for their own ends not value the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>. <em>Ludibrand</em> reporteth of <em>Leo</em> <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of the East, that he was glad to learn the truth from the mouth of poor <reg orig="Shepheards">Shepherds</reg> and Husbandmen, because his Courtiers were all Flatterers. <em>Flavius Vopiseus</em> in the life of <em>Aurelian</em>, <reg orig="sheweth">showeth</reg> sundry reasons why Princes and great men torment their inferiors; First (<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he) that they too much Liberty; secondly, they abound in all things; thirdly, their Minions and Flatterers do them no good; fourthly, their Guards are willing to execute all wicked and villainous Commissions; fifthly, that most <unclear>Ministers</unclear> of State are <unclear><reg orig="infariably">invariably</reg> covetous</unclear>; and lastly, that they are ignorant in State affairs. I hope none will <reg orig="mis construe">misconstrue</reg> my honest meaning, or think I <unclear>dart</unclear> forth beams to reflect on our present Government; my intention being <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to present you with those gleanings which I have and shall hereafter gather from a more worthy pen, who undertaketh to teach the <i>Art of just Preserving <reg orig="Politike">Politick</reg> Government; to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the causes of all changes in all Governments since the beginning, and rules to prevent such changes.</i> I shall ingenuously endeavour weekly to trace his steps, and hope that the present Power will rather give encouragement to the Work, <reg orig="then">than</reg> discourage it; I hereby promising, that nothing shall be herein inserted prejudicial to them; the most that shall be said, will be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to <reg orig="advice">advise</reg> <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Ministers of State to affect Justice, for they are not Gods Ministers, unless they impartially distribute Justice to each individual, which is the best policy; and agreeable to the Eternal Law of God, which teacheth all men to do as they would be done unto, and instructeth all men to be contented to be governed as well as to govern: Innumerable examples of this <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg>, may be found of this <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> in Roman Histories, where it is recorded, that <em>Marcus Fabius, Cajus Manlius, Quintus Fabius</em>, and many other Consuls, served as private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> in those Armies that they had formerly been Generals of. &mdash; But to Intelligence.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <em><reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg></em> below the <em>Church</em>, over against the Stile that goes to <em>Stepney</em>, in <em>Trumpet</em> <unclear>Yard</unclear>, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M</em> Student in Mathematical <reg orig="pysick">physic</reg>, who cureth the Tysick &amp; Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, &amp; deafness of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, and all sorts of Agues, of which cure he never failed; with other diseases <unclear>incident</unclear> to men.</i></p>
<p><i>Also, he cureth perfectly all diseases peculiar to women, or their <reg orig="Sexe">Sex</reg>, be they either <reg orig="chronical">chronic</reg> or Acute; and hath cured many that have been thought to be past cure. Also, he cureth those that are Deaf and thick of Hearing, and hath a present Remedy for the <reg orig="Tooth-Ache">Toothache</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him.</i></p>
<pb n="2" />
<p>Because many will not give credit to the Agreement of Peace between the Commonwealths of England and Holland, (though their <reg orig="Unbeleef">Disbelief</reg> proceeds from several causes, some <reg orig="prejudicately">prejudicially</reg> fearing the worst, and others wishing and desiring rather that the Fountain of <reg orig="Bloud">Blood</reg> may still be open) We can, and do assure you, That the Articles (as we said before) were signed and sealed by the Commissioners on both sides, on Wednesday last, and within 14 days are to be signed and sealed by the Lord Protector, and the States of Holland, and then to be <reg orig="publicky">publicly</reg> proclaimed and published, both in England and Holland in one day. The Agreement with Denmark is also taken in upon the Articles: And for satisfaction of the loss which our English Merchants sustained by that <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> command, whose demands amount to about 150000 l. it is <unclear>referred</unclear> to four Merchants, two whereof to be English, and the other two Dutch; which four Merchants shall have absolute power to determine those demands within the space of twenty days; the place where they are to <unclear>sign</unclear>, is Guild Hill. As touching the business of Amboyna, it is referred to eight Commissioners, who have six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> time to agree thereon, and in case they agree not, then Umpires are nominated to determine that business. <i>Let those that delight themselves in <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, have <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> to <reg orig="drinke">drink</reg>, for they are worthy.</i></p>
<p>From the Isle of Wight we hear, That a private man of War hath, about two days since, taken and brought in hither two French vessels, one of which is laden with Salt, the other hath but little in her except <unclear>ballast</unclear>; Our Fleet is for the most part at St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, and the rest at the <reg orig="Spits head">Spitshead</reg>, being in all near 100 sail, gallant ships, and bravely accommodated. One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> hath taken a Holland ship, and carried her to Portsmouth; she hath in her 8 Bales of Paper, and some small quantity of Indico. Many ships that were here, went away yesterday morning towards the Downs; and several Merchants ships are at present here in this road, being detained by contrary winds; they expect some favourable Easterly gales, that <unclear>so they</unclear> may proceed on their intended voyages.</p>
<p>From Deal we understand. That a man of War of ours is gone for Holland, to get the Ratification of the Peace made with them, and an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from the Dutch <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg>, touching the Agreement. Most part of the ships which remained in this <unclear>Road</unclear>, are gone up into the <unclear>River</unclear> of Thames; here is only some few left that are bound to the Southward. A Fleet consisting of about 40 or 50 sail of ships, great and small, passed by this place, which we suppose to be the Dunkirk fleet bound for London.</p>
<p>From Legorn, March 23. thus. This week in the fight of this City was a <unclear>sore</unclear> fight between two ships at Sea, the one a Dutchman of War of 32 guns, and the other an English ship called the Expedition, who came from Zant with Currans; the fight lasted 6 hours, but night having parted them, both ships sunk; most of the men were saved, but nothing else, thought the fight was near the shore.</p>
<p>It is advertised from Cullen, That the Treaty between the Elector and the Spanish Commissioners, is brought to perfection, and signed, which is, That both French and Spanish <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have free passage through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of Liege, not committing any acts of hostility upon each other; and the Spaniards in point of satisfaction for the losses received from them and the Lorrainers, shall pay to the said Elector 200000 <reg orig="Rixdollar">Rix-dollars</reg> <unclear>from <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorraine's</reg> estate.</unclear></p>
<!-- possible printing error here -->
<p>it would then be the better for himself.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 10.</i></head>
<p>This day came to my hand, The substance of the Peace agreed upon <unclear>between England and</unclear> Holland, which according to the best Intelligence that I <unclear>bring there is to this effect</unclear>; but somewhat larger in particulars, That there <unclear>shall be a closer</unclear> Alliance and Confederacy between the Commonwealths of England, and the State of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> was ever heretofore. That the Peace be <unclear>published by</unclear> both Commonwealths, upon one and the same day, after which, all Acts of <unclear>Hostility</unclear> to cease after six weeks, and to the Mediterranean after <unclear>ten</unclear> weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>; after which, all prizes to be <unclear>restored</unclear>. That all acts pasts be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither to act anything against the other. That all hostility cease between England and Denmark; none to assist the Rebels of either Nation with any supply, but <unclear>assist</unclear> each other against them; &amp; neither to receive those that are declared enemies, but cause them upon notice to depart within 28 days, on pain of death. That no <unclear>private</unclear> persons be <unclear>suffered</unclear> to assist the enemies of either, nor to pay to <unclear>either</unclear> greater <unclear>Impositions</unclear> <reg orig="then">than</reg> others. The <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships to strike their Flags to the English in the British Seas; no retreat to be given to <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of the Ports of either; each to comprehend the other in any Treaty with any <unclear>Nation,</unclear> if desired. That if any particular persons break the peace, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not <unclear>break</unclear> the National Confederacy, but those that <unclear>do it</unclear> to be punished. The <unclear>Subjects</unclear> of each to travel freely <unclear>through</unclear> all quarters of each, by Water or Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and <unclear>submitting</unclear> to the Laws where they are. That in storms each may have <unclear><!-- approx. 4 words -->, if they break not bulk</unclear>, without paying of <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>. The Merchants or <unclear>Mariners of either Commonwealth</unclear> not to be <unclear>pressed to serve under</unclear> the other, <unclear>but upon inevitable necessity</unclear>, and then to have satisfaction. That in each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> <unclear><reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg></unclear>, they pass between their Ships and Inns with lawful <unclear>weapons, offensive</unclear> and defensive. That all ships of both Commonwealth <unclear>defend</unclear> each other, against all whomsoever, <unclear>sailing their</unclear> course together. That if any other take any ships out of either of their Dominions, both parties to <unclear><reg orig="ingage">engage</reg></unclear> against them <unclear><reg orig="untill">until</reg> restitution</unclear> be made. The Searchers of both, to take no more of any of either, <unclear><reg orig="then">than</reg> their Instructions.</unclear> Letters of <unclear>Reprisal</unclear> not to be given for damage <unclear><!-- approx. 3 words -->three <reg orig="moneths">months'</reg> satisfaction</unclear> may be had. That such as have <unclear>Private Connections</unclear>, put in good security not to damage the Subjects <unclear>of either</unclear> Commonwealth, That not above 8 ships of War remain in any Port <unclear>of</unclear> the <unclear>others</unclear> Commonwealth, without consent. That Justice be done by the States <unclear>of those that</unclear> are alive, that <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in <em>Amboyna</em>. That there may be Commissioners on both sides to examine the differences of the inhabitants <unclear>of</unclear> both Nations in the East Indies, Greenland, Muscovy, Brazil, or other places, and <unclear>if</unclear> they cannot agree within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to refer it to be <unclear>determined</unclear> by the Protestant Switzers. Security is already given for payments of <pb n="4" /> the monies to the <unclear>Eastland</unclear> Company, upon the business of <unclear>Denmark</unclear>, and the <unclear><reg orig="summe">sum</reg></unclear> agreed upon.</p>
<p>Take here a Copy of a Letter from Scotland. SIR, The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> will inform you what kind of task the Horse are put upon in these <unclear>parts, to <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg></unclear> the Rebels and Mossers, who daily gather and are as often <unclear>scattered.</unclear> Besides what was done by Major General <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, commanded by Cornet Kennet, coming from <reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg>, with some <unclear>Sess</unclear> which they had collected, were set upon by 40 of the Enemy, received their charge, and then charged through the Rebels, <unclear>roused</unclear> them, killed 4 on the place, <unclear>took</unclear> 6 whereof 3 mortally wounded, and had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 4 of his party wounded. <unclear>Lieut.</unclear> Hickman with another party fell upon 60 of the Enemy under the command of Captain Campbel, took 6 above 20 horse; Captain Campbel was shot in the back, his horse taken, but he himself escaped <unclear>amongst the <!-- 1 word --></unclear> and <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear>. <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg> and <reg orig="Glencarry">Glengarry</reg> &amp;c. are gone over Taine into Sutherland to <unclear><reg orig="joyn">join</reg></unclear> with Middleton, and then they will be near 4000, yet I doubt not but Col. Morgan <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them <unclear>with his party. Montrose and the Lord <reg orig="Dodhoppe">Dudhope</reg> are raising men in the Bays of Angus, and <!-- 2 words --> speaks them 300 horse. Thus doth they <!-- approx. 6 words --> the Country miserable, having <!-- approx. 2 words --> the most cowardly enemy that ever we dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>. Upon <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> night last they had apart, returning from the South towards <!-- approx. 2 words --> to which <!-- approx. 5 characters --> another party of the enemy, of about 60 Horse and 60 Foot, commanded by Col. <!-- approx. 2 words -->; at which <!-- 1 word --> Cornet Kennet <!-- approx. 5 words --> and Lieutenant <!-- approx. 6 words --> Col. <reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg> Regiment, with 13 Horse, and 30 Foot <!-- approx. 2 words --> made after them; the Enemy got the <!-- approx. 8 words --> who killed one Captain, and 12 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, took Lieutenant Col George <!-- approx. 6 characters --> William <!-- approx. 10 words --> above 40 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> <!-- approx. 8 words --> with 16 Horse, and <!-- approx. 18 words --> horses killed. This is all the intelligence that <!-- approx. 12 words --> are abroad in these parts <!-- approx. 5 words --> in several parties in the Lowlands and <!-- approx. 2 words --> have been <!-- approx. 2 words --> in several parties, and divers of them killed and taken. And Gen. Monk is gone to take command of the <!-- 1 word --> in Scotland.</unclear></p>
<head level="3"><i><unclear>Dalkeith</unclear> April 16, 1654.</i></head>
<p><unclear>From Colchester  it is certified, That the Right Honourable Col. <!-- approx. 8 characters -->, High Steward of the aforesaid Town, was received with great solemnity, by the Major, Aldermen, Common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> men, Bishops, and other eminent Townsmen; who conducted him to the Town-Hall, where he was at the Sessions sworn free <reg orig="Burhgess">Burgess</reg>, and a Justice of Peace. After a Declaration was agreed on, and signed by them all, which he this day presented to his Highness the <!-- possible printing error here --> the Protestants in France; He made over that he was glad <!-- approx. 2 words --></unclear> it would then be the better for himself.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, April 11.</i></head>
<p>The Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, and <unclear>divers Certificates</unclear> were presented unto them <reg orig="in">on</reg> behalf of several particular persons, for <unclear>approbation; and in regard that none hereafter should</unclear> out of carelessness or partiality <unclear>at their hand, to a Certificate for any person</unclear> that hereafter may be found unworthy <unclear>to be admitted, and to become</unclear> prejudicial to the Church of Christ, and frustrate the <unclear>intentions of our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> which</unclear> made this Ordinance; the said Commissioners do <unclear>earnestly beseech all whom it</unclear> may concern (in the bowels of Christ) as they tender the <unclear>honour of the great God himself</unclear>, whose servants we all are, the prejudice of the <unclear>souls of his people <!-- 1 word --></unclear> by the <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> of his Son, the advancement and <reg orig="peopagation">propagation</reg> <unclear>of his Gospel, through all the parts</unclear> of this Land and Nation, where unto we <unclear>belong, so to lend the alliance</unclear> both of their fervent prayers, and due <unclear>informations</unclear>, that thereby the <unclear>weak may</unclear> be carried on more prosperously, and the Commissioners more <unclear>encouraged to amend it.</unclear></p>
<p><i>Signed in the name, and at the request of the Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers. By Francis Rouse. Io. Arrowsmith. William Gosse. Stephen Marshal.</i></p>
<p><unclear>Letter from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> speak</unclear> of another Engagement betwixt Col. Morgan, and the Enemy; but they <reg orig="tel">tell</reg> us not the particulars only they say, that the Enemy is once more <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear>, and driven <unclear>further</unclear> up into the mountains, with the loss of about 200 men.</p>
<p><unclear>The peace with Holland being concluded (as you heard before) our Merchants are <!-- approx. 2 words --> goods on ships and, as <!-- 1 word --> Lighters can be gotten to carry them where the <!-- approx. 3 words -->. We likewise heard the like preparations in Holland for transporting of goods of several sorts <!-- 1 word -->. And now all the rest of Europe are at a stand, <!-- approx. 5 words --> upon us, and begin to cast about with themselves, what action may be <!-- 1 word --> considerable enough for to be undertaken next by those great Heroes which are as ready for action as any opportunity can be to offer <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>Yesterday was</unclear> the Goal-delivery; three were hanged one whereof died <unclear>most desperately</unclear>, and going up the Cart, drank a health to the <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> Majesty: <unclear>One</unclear> was pressed last Saturday, and being afterwards heard to groan, was carried down to the Press-yard again to have the <unclear>execution <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg></unclear>.</p>
<p>Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> John <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg> is removed from the Tower to be prisoner in some more remote place.</p>
<head level="3">Wednesday April 12.</head>
<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for the Adjourning part of Easter Term, 1654.</i></head>
<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; Out of a <unclear>tender care and</unclear> desire that so necessary and good a work may at length <pb n="6" /> be brought to effect, it is held convenient that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, it is held convenient and necessary to adjourn part of the next Term of Easter; be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That part of the said Term of Easter now next <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> be adjourned, that is to say, from and after the first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, unto the last Return of the said Easter Term, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>; And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or <reg orig="commandement">commandment</reg> to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, may tarry at their dwellings, or where their business shall be, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, until the said last Return, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that <unclear>behalf</unclear>.</p>
<p>And be it also ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, and Barons of the Exchequer, giving them authority to adjourn the said part of the said Term of Easter, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the said first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the said last Return of the said Term, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, as before is said, and the said adjournment shall be made, as aforesaid. And be <unclear>it further</unclear> Ordained, That all Matters, Causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, as is aforesaid; and the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained, That a former Ordinance of the sixth day of this instant April, for the Adjourning of part of the said Term, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first Return of Trinity Term next, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em> be from henceforth Repealed and void. And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of London and Middlesex, and all other Sheriffs both in England and Wales, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the chief Market Towns and usual places within their several and respective Counties.</p>
<p>The  titular King of Scots is still at Paris, and of late something more merry <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary. The Deputies for Languedoc telling him, that if there were a Peace concluded with England, it would be well for all the Protestants in France; He made answer that he was glad of it, for it would then be the better for himself.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, April the 13.</i></head>
<p>The French Letters <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty hath sent to the little Queen, the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and the rest of her children, to desire them to remove out of his Territories, for that the English were <unclear>resolved</unclear> to send an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> reciprocally into <em>France</em>, and that their pensions should be paid to them where they should please to point to have it paid; whereupon they are making preparations for their departure out of <em>Paris</em>, the Queen goes to <reg orig="dwel">dwell</reg> at <em>Angers</em>, and <em>Charles Stuart</em> with his brothers and Prince <em>Rupert</em>, are bound for <em>Chantilly</em>, and they have had <reg orig="ferious">various</reg> consultations whether they should bend their course from thence to <em>Scotland</em>, or rather to <em>Germany</em>; the latter being supposed to be the safest way to keep their heads on their shoulders.</p>
<p>There are some Merchants have received Letters from Holland, that the States of the United Provinces have signed and ratified the <unclear>Instrument</unclear> of Peace, and the Messengers are upon their return with it, for his Highness the Lord Protector to do the like. And it is supposed that on Thursday next being the 20 of this instant, <em>Peace</em> will be generally proclaimed throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, a copy of the Instrument I have briefly in the precedent pages presented you with.</p>
<p>Three English Merchants ships returning very richly laden from <em>Smyrna</em>, were set upon by three French men of War near <em>Cape <unclear>Spart.verto</unclear></em>, and after a cruel and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight between them, they took one of the English, stranded another, and the third being nimble in sailing, escaped away by <em>Messina</em>. Also on the 25 of the last Month, a Mountain called <em>Vesure</em> in <em>Naples</em>, began to cast forth fire and <unclear>ashes</unclear>, to the great astonishment of thousands of people, who ran into the Churches, and caused the <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> to be rung, to give warning thereof to all the Country about.</p>
<p>The States of <em>Holland</em> have sent an express to the King of <em>Denmark</em> to <unclear><reg orig="certifie">certify</reg></unclear> him what agreement they have made with <em>England</em> concerning the Kingdom, and begin to cease their warlike preparations all generally being very willing to embrace <em>Peace</em>.</p>
<hr />
<p><i><unclear>Extracted out of the Original</unclear> Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register Book</unclear> of the Company of Stationers.</i></p>
<head level="3"><em>LONDON: Printed by</em> ROBERT WOOD, 1654.</head>
<head level="3">FINIS</head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>