<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout177">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 177
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p><i>A great Fight in Scotland between the English and the Highlanders, the storming of a Tower <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg> by Gen. <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> forces, the event and success thereof, the manner of the engagement, the particulars of the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> on both sides, the taking of cap. <em>Rogers</em>, Agent for the K. of Scots, the Sentence of Death <unclear><reg orig="denonnced">denounced</reg></unclear> against him, and his speech at the place of execution. The advancing of more forces from England &amp; Ireland, and Gen. <em>Monk's</em> Letter to his Officers, to repair with all speed to Scotland. The advance of the English <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> to the Coast of France, the taking of 42 sail of French-men, there <reg orig="inforcing">enforcing</reg> of two <em>Regiments</em> in the town of <em>Rochel</em>, the great Offers and Proposals of King <em><reg orig="Lewis">Louis</reg></em> for peace. The King of Scots, the D. of York, and the Queen of Sweden to meet at the Spaw. And a true copy of the Articles of the perpetual peace between England &amp; <reg orig="Holand">Holland</reg>.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 28. to <em>Friday</em> May <em>the</em> 5. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>April</em> the 28.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>In the time of <em>Germanicus</em>, it was moved in the Senate of <em>Rome</em>, that none should be admitted into the <unclear>Trusts</unclear> of the <em>Commonwealth</em>, but such that could rule their Families by prudence, and not by force, for there is a <reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg>, <i>That he that cannot rule a Family well, cannot rule a City; and he that cannot rule a City well, cannot rule a Principality</i>. Man is a free <em>Creature</em> by <em>Nature</em>, although there remaineth marks of slavery or servitude upon him, which are <reg orig="ingrafted">engrafted</reg> by the skill of the <em>Cunning</em>, and the force of the <em>Mighty</em>: By the one he is allured into slavery; by the other constrained to submit unto <pb n="1" /> slavery, in regard that he is <reg orig="over-awed">overawed</reg>. Obedience <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> is not a sign of love; <i>for people may be <reg orig="forc'd">forced</reg> to do that for fear, which they will do for love, but him for whom it is done, were better to have it undone.</i> <em>Plutarch</em> in the life of <em>Demetrius</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That Kings and Magistrates are not to measure their happiness by their Greatness, and he who doth receive Honours <reg orig="over-hastily">overhastily</reg>, doth but make haste to be in contempt. If a people will do the same for love, which they will do for fear; Why will not those that govern rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to rule by love <reg orig="then">than</reg> fear, and instead of <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> to be Lords of slaves, rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to be Rulers of free people, and maintain a <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> spirit, and not to deject or abase them. It was not so in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of old; for the <em>Persians</em> were as free a people as ever lived under a <em>Monarchy</em>; the <em>Macedonians</em> conducted by <em>Alexander</em> in his conquering of the world, were of the freest people in <em>Greece</em> in those days; and none more freer than the <em>Romans</em>, who accomplished excellent <reg orig="Atchievments">Achievements</reg>, by their lawful <reg orig="Undertakeings">Undertakings</reg>. We must not take him that commandeth in a <em><reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg></em> to be a Master, but a servant: It is true, his command is <reg orig="Master like">Masterlike</reg>, but the power by which they command, is the consent of the people, to convenient and good Laws; the which indeed is, or at least should be, the <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg> by which they should rule or govern by; and it is to be the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> limitation of those that are to govern, of what degree soever. Of this, more in our next: Therefore to Intelligence.</p>
<p><i>His Highness the Lord Protector has set forth a Proclamation concerning a cessation of all Acts of hostility between the Commonwealth of England, and that of the United Provinces, and their respective people, and the restitution of all things taken and seized upon by either party after the 4 of this instant May, 1654. This is to be published by both parties throughout their respective Territories.</i></p>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em>, the last <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, That the <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> party increaseth, and are very much exasperated; the which to confirm, we shall here present you with a Letter, wherein is comprised the full particulars, and exact Transactions on both sides.</p>
<head level="3">SIR,</head>
<p><i>Having so convenient an opportunity, I could no <reg orig="wayes">way</reg> possible omit writing to you by this Post, though notwithstanding it seems to be full Term here with us, since the <reg orig="adjorning">adjourning</reg> of yours at London; for, to speak truth, it is high time now to look about us, since that the enemy dares presume <pb n="2" /> to descent down upon the Lowlands, and (Lorain like) make great <unclear>devastations</unclear>, in plundering, pillaging, and unpeopling of the Countries; but some of them taking so long a leap, <reg orig="hopt">hopped</reg> short back; amongst the rest, two Captains, and some few private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, were lately <reg orig="truss'd">trussed</reg> up, as the <unclear>Falcon</unclear> does <reg orig="Wild-Ducks">Wild Ducks</reg>: Since which time, Gen. <em>Middleton</em> has drawn his Army in to <reg orig=" Southerland ">Sutherland</reg>, betwixt whom, and our forces, there is a Navigable River, not passable but by Boats, and those the enemy has drawn to their banks, and many desperate persons go in, and have recourse to them. They still continue in gathering up their new Levies, and have had a general <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, where a new Oath and Covenant was taken, to fight it out to the last man; and likewise Glencairn's Declaration was there published, <reg orig="stuff'd">stuffed</reg> up with many expressions that carry little consistency with their Course. I may <unclear>possibly</unclear> present you with a copy by the next: In the interim, we are drawn together our main strength to fight them: The great God of Hosts appear for us, and crown us with victory in the day of <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>.</i></p>
<head level="3">Dalkieth the 25 of April, 1654.</head>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday April 29.</i></head>
<p>From <em>Southampton</em> thus: Sir, <i>Mr. John <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg> (we hear) is committed to the old Castle in Jersey, where he deported himself with abundance of patience and humility, and has also declared, That he <reg orig="aymes">aims</reg> at nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the glory of God, the advancement of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the restoring of ever <reg orig="free born">freeborn</reg> man of England, to its ancient Rights and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, and the perfect purging of the Law from all abuses and corruptions.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>From the Navy, April 29.</i></head>
<p>We have entertained the <em>Proclamation of Peace</em> with the greatest solemnity that possibly can be: and Gen. <em>Pen</em> being once come aboard, I hope We shall then find what will be the Expedition which <em>Christendom</em> so much looks upon, whether we shall go to <em>Leghorn</em>, or the high Determinations of the Council so shall order it, as they shall call the <em>Turks</em> to an account at <em>Tunis</em>, or <em><reg orig="Algier">Algiers</reg></em>, for the wrongs they have done to our Nation. Indeed, we are so unanimous for Action and Enterprise, that each mans noble Spirit is ready to push him forward to <reg orig="atchieve">achieve</reg> something that may add more honour to his countries Fame.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 1.</i></head>
<p>This day his Highness <reg orig="solac'd">solaced</reg> himself in <reg orig="Hide-Park">Hyde Park</reg>, where 1100 <em>Cornish</em> Gentlemen <reg orig="toss'd">tossed</reg> a silver ball before him, and thousands of people were present to behold the same.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> May 2.</head>
<p>From <em>Hamborough</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the King of <em>Denmark</em> has been to visit the new Church of <em><reg orig="Altenaw">Altenau</reg></em>, &amp; the next day went back to <em>Gluckstadt</em>; upon whose <reg orig="arival">arrival</reg> came intelligence of Gen. <unclear><em><reg orig="Koningsmarks">Koningsmark's</reg></em></unclear> <reg orig="surprizing">surprising</reg> of the Town of <em>Bremerburgh</em>. Upon the Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> Demands to the Emperor of <em>Germany</em> for 135000 Rix-dollars, being so much left unpaid by the upper Rhine, it was granted.</p>
<p><em>Dover</em> the 24 of <em>April</em>, 1654. This evening came into this Road a private man of War being a <em>Marget</em> <unclear>Hoy</unclear> of 6 Guns, and about 50 men, who having found in the channel a Dutch ship coming from the <reg orig="West-Indies">West Indies</reg> that had been long at sea, and both ship and men much spent by the tediousness of the Voyage, did of a sudden clap Them aboard, and after a short (but sharp) dispute, became Masters of her, and brought her along with them: The ship is said to be of great value, for besides plate, whereof several Letters say there is a good quantity, the ship will be found full of other rich commodities, which will prove very beneficial to the Takers, when it comes to be judged prize.</p>
<p>From <em>France</em> it is certified, That there has been a great dispute between the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and P. <em>Rupert</em>, about the <em>Swallow</em> Guns; but <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> <reg orig="over-swaying">overswaying</reg> passion, Amity at last <reg orig="interveen'd">intervened</reg>, and the Gentlemen were both reconciled. It is said that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath resigned her Crown, and is expected this Summer at the <em>Spaw</em>, where young <em>Charles</em>, and his brother <em>James</em>, do intend to meet her Majesty, and divert themselves at the Season.</p>
<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 3,</head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has spent much time with his Council, about regulating the Law, the easing of the people, the redressing of Grievances, and the abating of Taxes, and it is hoped, we shall now have the enjoyment of our long looks for Liberties.</p>
<p>The next Term is like to be kept without any interruption, and a new Oath was lately <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> to the Judges, whereby impartial Justice may be equally executed.</p>
<p>There being lately published a copy of the <em>Articles of Peace</em>, without Order from the State, we shall hereby give you to understand, That by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Special command, there is a true copy in the Press; the effect whereof take as followeth:</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>The Articles of the perpetual peace, concluded between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, <unclear>&amp;c.</unclear> one the one part; and the high and mighty Lords, the States-General of the United Provinces of the Netherlands on the other part.</p>
<p><i>1. That from hence forward there shall be a firm <reg orig="unchangable">unchangeable</reg> Peace, sincere friendship, and a closer Alliance, and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of England, and the States of the United Provinces <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been ever heretofore, and of their respective Lands, Cities, and Countries, and of all under their obedience wheresoever, and of what condition soever.</i></p>
<p><i>2. That from henceforth all hostility shall cease.</i></p>
<p><i>3. That all wrongs and offences suffered by the one, or the other party shall be forgotten; and neither party shall pretend anything thereupon. All actions past shall be nulled, except those that shall be done in the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Seas after the time of 12 days, and from that Sea to the Cape of St. Vincent in the time of six weeks, and from thence in the Mediterranean Sea, as far as the line after the time of ten weeks, and at the other side of the line in the time of eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to be reckoned from the time of the publication of Peace, and all prizes taken after that time shall be restored.</i></p>
<p><i>4. That all the prisoners on both sides be released without ransom.</i></p>
<p><i>5. That both Commonwealths shall be confederate friends to defend one the other against whomsoever.</i></p>
<p><i>6. That neither of both shall act against the other either by Land or Sea.</i></p>
<p><i>7. That the States shall cause restitution to be made of all the ships and goods seized upon the English by the King of Denmark, that are set in being, as also a full compensation of the worth of those goods that may be sold already, and likewise that all damages and spoil of goods shall be made good to the Owners, by estimation, and when such satisfaction shall be done by the said King, then all hostility shall cease between England and Denmark.</i></p>
<p><i>8. That no Inhabitants of either Commonwealth shall assist any Rebel of either with moneys, ships, or victuals.</i></p>
<p><i>9. That both Commonwealths shall assist one the other at their proper charges against their Rebels.</i></p>
<p><i>10. That neither shall receive those that are, or shall be declared enemies of either Commonwealth.</i></p>
<p><i>11. That either Commonwealth having notice by the other that some of their enemies are in its Dominions, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give them warning to depart in 28 days upon pain of death.</i></p>
<p><i>12. That the English shall not <unclear><reg orig="pa">pay</reg></unclear> greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> other Nations.</i></p>
<p><i>13. That the States ships shall strike their Flag before the English in the British Seas.</i></p>
<p><i>14. That neither of the Commonwealths shall give retreat to any <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of their Ports.</i></p>
<p><i>15. That in case the English or the Dutch make any Treaty with any Prince, they shall therein comprehend each other reciprocally; if they desire it.</i></p>
<p><i>16. That in case some hostility should happen between the inhabitants of both <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, by one against the other; that the Alliance shall <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> hold and remain in full force; and the parties that shall be found guilty shall be punished.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<p><i>17. That the Subjects of the Commonwealth of England shall freely travel through all <unclear>quarters</unclear> of the United Provinces by water or by land, or into any Cities or <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> <reg orig="there of">thereof</reg>, armed or armed, provided they <unclear>are</unclear> not above 40 in a company, either with or without their <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>; and the Subjects of the Netherlands are to have the like <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> in England, and every, and all places under their subjection, carrying themselves submissively to the Laws of each Commonwealth.</i></p>
<p><i>18. That if it so fall out, that any ships of either State shall be storm or <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> be driven into any of the Havens of the one or the other State, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have liberty to go to sea again at their pleasure with their ships and goods, without paying any Custom or Impost provided that they break not the <unclear>bulke</unclear>, behaving themselves according to the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and <reg orig="customes">customs</reg> of the place where they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take harbour.</i></p>
<p><i>29. That no Merchants or Mariners of one or the other Commonwealth, shall have their goods, ships, or <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg> arrested in any of the havens or rivers of either Commonwealth to <unclear>serve</unclear> at War, or otherwise, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any general or particular command, except it be upon some inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction, not including herein, the Arrests by ordinary Courts of Justice.</i></p>
<p><i>20. That the Merchants, and their Factors, and servants, and the Mariners may travel and turn back <unclear>again</unclear> to their ships from the seas, waters, and havens of the one and the other Commonwealth and at their landing may use for defence of themselves, and their goods, all sorts of Arms, offensive and defensive, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, that being come to their <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg>, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> lay their Arms aside until the return into their ships again.</i></p>
<p><i>21. That men of War of both Commonwealths, or Merchants ships meeting together at sea, they shall defend each other against all whomsoever that shall offer to make any attempt upon either of them, so long <reg orig="is">as</reg> they sail on course.</i></p>
<p><i>22. That if any ship of either <reg orig="Republicke">Republic</reg>, or of a Neutrality shall by a third party be taken out of the havens or Dominions of either Commonwealth, both parties shall be <unclear>engaged</unclear> to follow the business for the <unclear>restitution</unclear> of the ships and goods to the owners.</i></p>
<p><i>23. That <unclear>Searchers</unclear> and other such Officers in the execution of their Office, that regulate themselves according to the Laws of each Country, and take no more of any <reg orig="then">than</reg> is <reg orig="permit">permitted</reg></i> them by their Instructions.</p>
<p><i>24.That if one party shall cause <unclear>some</unclear> damages to the other, there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be no Letters of Reprisal given: But if in <unclear>three</unclear> <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> time, no satisfaction is done, then the said Letters may be granted.</i></p>
<p><i>25. That all persons of either Commonwealth going to <unclear>Sea</unclear> with particular Commissions, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <unclear>obliged</unclear> by sufficient sureties, before the Judges of the Court where they receive their Commissions, That they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> do no damage to any subject of either Commonwealth.</i></p>
<p><i>26. That no more but <unclear>eight ships</unclear> of War <unclear><reg orig="shal">shall</reg></unclear> be suffered to come or remain in the Ports of each others Commonwealth at one time: And when there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be occasion for a greater number, then the consent must be first asked.</i></p>
<p><i>27. That the States <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> do Justice upon those that be found alive, that have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in <unclear>Amboyna.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>28. That there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be Commissioners established to examine the wrongs or injuries done or <reg orig="pretendedd">pretended</reg> to be done or suffered by the Inhabitants of either Commonwealth <pb n="6" /> in the <reg orig="East-Indies">East Indies</reg>, Greenland, Muscovy, Brazil, or other places. And if the Commissioners cannot agree <unclear>thereupon</unclear> within the time of three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, then the aforesaid differences to be referred to the Judgement of the Protestant Switzers.</i></p>
<p><i>29 And whereas formerly, some question and misunderstanding hath arisen between the Commonwealth of England, and the King of Denmark, by reason of the detaining of some ships and goods, it is agreed, and concluded on both sides, that satisfaction being given, all differences whatsoever shall be forgotten and buried in eternal Oblivion, so as the said King, his Kingdoms and Dominions, shall be received in this Treaty as a friend, in such manner, that he shall be <reg orig="re established">re-established</reg> in the amity of the Commonwealth, as he was formerly before the said detention, and his Deputies and Ambassadors shall be admitted with the like Honour, as the Deputies and other Ambassadors of other States being in amity.</i></p>
<p><i>30. It is further agreed that at the time when the ratification shall be delivered, four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides, who on the 18 May next ensuing, English <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, shall meet here in London to consider and moderate all injuries and damages, on either side from the year 1611 to the 18 of May, 1652. and in case of <reg orig="non agreement">non-agreement</reg>, to refer it to the judgement and <unclear><reg orig="umpioriage">umpirage</reg></unclear> of the Switzer Protestant Cantons.</i></p>
<p><i>31 Furthermore, it is agreed and concluded; That both parties shall truly and firmly keep and maintain <unclear><!-- approx. 3 words --> and all the</unclear> matters therein contained, and strictly take care that the same be observed and performed by either of their people.</i></p>
<p><i>32 <unclear>Item</unclear>, For further certainty and assurance that this peace and amity shall be uprightly, and in good faith observed, the States General do oblige and bind themselves, that all and every Officer both by Sea and land shall be <unclear>bound</unclear> to confirm this Treaty, and all the Articles thereof and promise sacredly upon Oath, that they shall, as far as is possible, religiously observe the same, and as far as to them belongeth shall perform the same, and take care that it be observed and performed by others.</i></p>
<p><i>33 Furthermore it is agreed, concluded, and accorded, that this present Treaty, and all that is <unclear>therein</unclear> comprised and expressed, shall be confirmed by the said Lord Protector, and the States General aforesaid, by open Letters on both sides, confirmed with the great Seal, in due and <reg orig="authentick">authentic</reg> form, within 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> next ensuing, or sooner if it can be done, and that within the said time, the Ratifications on both sides <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> exchanged, and that presently after the delivery and exchange of the Ratification, this Peace and <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> shall be published in such manner, and in such places as is usual, and from thence forwards all hostility on both sides shall cease.</i></p>
<head level="3">The Contents of the Commission.</head>
<p>For the assurance and witness of all this, we the Commissioners of his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> of the States General of the United Provinces, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> and force of the respective procurations of Our Commissions, have subscribed this present Treaty with our own Hands, and have confirmed it with our Seals. <i>Done in Westminster the 5 day of April, 1654.</i></p>
<p><i>H. Lawrence, P<unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear>. P. <unclear>Lisle,</unclear> H. Beverningh, J. Lambert, Gilb. Pickering, Wil. Nieuport, E. Montague, W. Strieklandt, Alb. P. <unclear>Fongestadt.</unclear></i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 4.</head>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, That Gen. Middleton having drawn most of his forces Northwards, some engagement <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg>, and a party of 40 horse commanded by an English Captain, advanced as far as Provost <em><reg orig="Marburnies">Marbunie's</reg></em> house near <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, which they <unclear><reg orig="fir'd">fired</reg></unclear>; but the Provost and his party maintained the Tower against them, and after a desperate storm and sharp dispute, two of the English were slain, divers wounded, and the castle being not feasible, the enemy made good their retreat, with little loss. col. <em>Morgan</em> <reg orig="remaines">remains</reg> still about <em>Dingwel</em>, unto whose assistance col. <em>Pride</em>, col. <em>Allured</em>, and divers other Regiments are designed from <em>England</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. Upon Gen. <em>Monk's</em> arrival, he sent for all his Officers at <em>London</em> to make all possible speed to engage suddenly. And the enemy are preparing to receive him, who have <reg orig="determinated">determined</reg> in Council, to <unclear>dispute</unclear> the field either to Death or Victory. In the late Engagement capt. <em>Rogers</em> (Agent for the K. of <em>Scots</em>) was taken, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to <em><reg orig="Dalkieth">Dalkeith</reg></em>, where he was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, condemned, and executed, and received his Sentence of Death with great humility and meekness of Spirit, making a copious Speech upon the Ladder, interwoven with sundry <reg orig="methodicall">methodical</reg> expressions, touching his life and conversation, and his integrity to the Trust reposed in him, saying <i>That he deemed it a singular mercy from the great Tribunal of <reg orig="Haven">Heaven</reg>, that Providence had decreed him worthy of laying down his life.</i></p>
<p>The K. of <em>France</em> is preparing large Offers to the <em>English</em> for peace; and among other things, <i>that the Protestants in that Kingdom shall enjoy their Liberties and freedom in <em>Religion</em>.</i></p>
<p>Gen. <em>Pen</em> is going from <em>London</em> to the Fleet; the design <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>; but the Instructions private. Of which, more in our next.</p>
<p>In the interim, some of the English <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> have <reg orig="allarm'd">alarmed</reg> the French, and <unclear>rides</unclear> <reg orig="tryumphantly">triumphantly</reg> upon the coast; but two Reg. Are sent to Rochel to <reg orig="re inforce">reinforce</reg> that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: from whence they write; <i>That the English have taken 42 of their ships laden with Wines, which doth very much trouble the King and Council; unto whom, a <em>Message</em> is come from his Holiness, for celebrating a <em>Marriage</em> between his <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, and K. <reg orig="Lewis">Louis</reg>: If you will have any more news at present, you must go to Pope <em>Innocent</em> the Tenth, who is now going to his grave; his death will make the <em>Janseninas</em> high in France, and will occasion some <unclear>Tumults</unclear>, it may be.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i><unclear>Extracted</unclear> out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>