<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout170">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 170
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>A Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council, concerning the continuation of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> and Excise, within this Commonwealth, and a perfect copy of the Rates set upon all <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> and <reg orig="Domestick">Domestic</reg> commodities Excisable. Also another Declaration of his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, inciting all people religiously to humble themselves before the Lord on Friday next, the 24 of this instant. Together with an Ordinance for the Approbation and Trial of Ministers, and a List of the Commissioners names. The Landing of more <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition in <em>Scotland</em> for the Rebels, their intentions to raise 30 Regiments, and expectation of the King of <em>Scots</em> or Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming to be their General. The general proceedings in the Treaty betwixt the English and Dutch Commissioners, and the advance of part of our Fleet to the <em>Texel</em>, and seizing on the Dutch Fishermen thereabouts, in sight of their Ships of War; With the coming of a great Fleet of Coal Ships into the River of <em>Thames</em> on the 19 instant.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> March 17, to <em>Friday</em> March <em>the</em> 24. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>March</em> the 17</i>.</head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The last Letters from Newcastle <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> us, that on the 16 instant there went from thence a great Fleet for London, with a good Convoy; and some small Ships lying in Sunderland neglecting that opportunity, were forced to adventure out without a Convoy, who were presently chased by six Capers that lay lurking thereabouts; the <unclear>Colliers</unclear> chose rather to run their Ships aground <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be taken; yet notwithstanding the Capers <reg orig="persued">pursued</reg> them, and <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> off five of them, the other five perished by the merciless fury of the tempestuous Waves, but the men were all saved. We have lost in a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time two and twenty Coal Ships. We are <reg orig="advertiz'd">advertised</reg> from <em>Dover</em>, that on the 19 instant the foresaid Fleet of Colliers arrived in the Downs, and are come into the River, so that the price of Coals is like to be very reasonable, if the Woodmongers dare be honest.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3">Saturday, March 18.</head>
<p>This day was ordered to be published by his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council, an Ordinance; That from after the 25 of this present <em>March</em>, the several Rates and charges hereafter set down, and every of them, and none other, in the right duty of Excise, shall be set, laid and imposed, and are hereby to be levied, demanded, collected, received, recovered and paid, in and <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> England and Wales, and Town and Port of <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg>, upon all and every the Commodities, Merchandizes and Manufactures Native and <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg>, <em>viz</em>.</p>
<head level="3">Rates of Excise and Commodities of <reg orig="In land">Inland</reg> making or growth.</head>
<p><i>For every barrel of Beer or Ale above six shillings, 2.s. for 6 shilling beer 6.d.</i></p>
<p><i>English <unclear><reg orig="Allum">Alum</reg></unclear> and <reg orig="Coper">Copper</reg>, the hundred <reg orig="conteining">containing</reg> 112 l. the maker to pay sixpence.</i></p>
<p><i>English Hops, the planter to pay two shilling the hundred.</i></p>
<p><i>English Saffron, for every 20.s. to be paid one, by the planter.</i></p>
<p><i>Tin, the buyer to pay <unclear>one</unclear> shilling for every 20.s. value.</i></p>
<p><i>English Iron, the maker to pay for every hundred containing 112 l. one shil. 6d.</i></p>
<p><i>All manner of Strong Waters <reg orig="distil'd">distilled</reg> here to be sold, the first maker is to pay 2.d. <unclear>a gal.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>For every barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made in this land, hard or soft proportionably, 4.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For every Ounce Troy of prepared Silver or Gold, to be paid where it is disgrossed, 2.d.</i></p>
<p><i>For every pound weight of Copper or other <reg orig="mettal">metal</reg>, to be paid where it is disgrossed, 1.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Whale <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, &amp;c. <unclear>made</unclear> here, to be paid upon every <reg orig="tun">tonne</reg>, 6.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For every fother of Lead containing a 2000 l. weight, 6.s.8.d.</i></p>
<p><i>For all Salt made or sold here, to be paid by the first buyer, a half <reg orig="peny">penny</reg> the Gallon.</i></p>
<p><i>All Salt made of Salt, to be paid by the maker thereof, one farthing upon the gallon.</i></p>
<p><i>For all <reg orig="Syder">Cider</reg> and Perry, made and sold by way of Retail, 2.s.6.d. the Hogshead.</i></p>
<p><i>Metheglin, <reg orig="Mede">Mead</reg>, and such like drinks, a penny upon every gallon.</i></p>
<p><i>For <unclear>Stareh</unclear>, upon every 20.s. value, to be paid by the <unclear>first maker, 1.s.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>For Glasses, upon every 20.s. the maker is to pay one.</i></p>
<head level="3">Rates of Excise of <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> Goods imported.</head>
<p><i>For every pound of <unclear>Tobacco</unclear> which is not of the English plantation, <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> already imported and remaining in the hands of the Merchant, to be paid by the first buyer, 1.s.</i></p>
<p><i>Every pound of Tobacco of the English plantation, 3.d.</i></p>
<p><i>For every <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg> of Wine already imported or to be imported, the first buyer to pay 6.l.</i></p>
<p><i>Every <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg> of Wine-Vinegar, imported or to be imported, to be paid by the <unclear>first buyer, 2 l.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>All Spirits of French, Rhenish, or other Wines, upon every gallon, 4.d.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Forrein">Foreign</reg> or <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Spirits sold for strong Waters, the <unclear>Utterer</unclear> to pay 1.s. on the gal.</i></p>
<p><i>Strong Waters perfectly made, imported &amp;c. the first buyer to pay for every gal, 1.<unclear>s.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>For all Beer or Ale imported by Sea, or brought in by Land, the Importer to pay 5.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For Pepper, Sugars, and other Grocery and Mercery Wares, wrought and <reg orig="gum'd">gummed</reg> Silks, <reg orig="Linnens">Linens</reg>, Upholstery, Haberdashery, Paper, and Leather, the first buyer to pay upon every pound, 1.s. For all manner of Drugs two shillings in the pound.</i></p>
<p><i>For every 112 pound of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> imported, &amp;c. 5.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For all Saltery Wares, the first buyer is to pay, upon every twenty shillings, 1.s.</i></p>
<p><i>The first buyer is to pay for every 112. l. of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> Hops, over &amp; <unclear>above Customs, 5.s.</unclear></i></p>
<pb n="2" />
<p><i>For Hemp, <unclear><reg orig="Flaxe">Flax</reg>, <reg orig="Towe">Tow</reg></unclear>, Tar, <unclear><reg orig="Rezen">Resin</reg></unclear>, Wax, <unclear><reg orig="Tullow">Tulle</reg>, Cable</unclear>, &amp;c. on every 20 shil. <unclear>6.</unclear>d.</i></p>
<p><i>For Glasses, and Earthenware, on every 20.s. the first buyer is to pay <unclear>2.</unclear>s.</i></p>
<p><i>For Woollen Cloth or <unclear><reg orig="Suffi">Sufi</reg> &amp;:.</unclear> the Importer is to pay <unclear>on every <!-- approx. 4 words --> 1s.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>For every 20.s. value of raw Silk imported. the first buyer is to pay, 6.d.</i></p>
<p><i>All <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> Salt imported, having not paid Excise, the buyer is to pay 3 half pence a gal.</i></p>
<p><i>For every 2.s. value of <unclear>bone-lace</unclear> imported, the first buyer is to pay 3. shil</i></p>
<p><i>For every 20.s. value of <reg orig="died">dyed</reg> <unclear>Silk</unclear> imported, the first buyer is to pay 5.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For every 20.s. value of Silk Lace imported, to be <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> by the first buyer, 3.s.</i></p>
<p><i>For all other goods or Merchandize whatsoever, imported or to be imported, upon which no Rates are set neither here or in the book of Rates for Customs (except <unclear>Bullion</unclear>, Corn, Victual, Arms, <unclear>Ammunition</unclear>, or Ordinance of Brass or Iron) upon every 20.s. value, to be paid by the first buyer, 1.s.</i></p>
<p>It is likewise Ordained, That from and after the 29 of March instant, <em>Thom. Allen</em> Alderman of the City of London, <em>Thomas Wood, Rich. Bury, Geo. Langham</em> Esquires, and <em>George <unclear>Fonecraft</unclear></em> Merchant, and none others, are and shall be, and are hereby declared, constituted and appointed, Commissioners and Governors of the Excise and new Import; who, or any three or more of them, are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and authorized to exercise and put in execution all and every the powers and authorities given or granted by, or contained in all or any the said Acts, Ordinances, or Orders of Parliament touching the Excise and New Import, as well for the collecting and <unclear>receiving</unclear> the several rates in this present Ordinances imposed and set, as the arrears upon any <unclear>former</unclear> <reg orig="Shedule">Schedule</reg> or Rates due, and concerning the Government and ordering of the Excise and New Import, as fully and amply as any Commissioners for Excise at the first of March aforesaid, might or ought to have done, and shall observe such Orders and directions as they shall from time to time receive from his Highness the L. Protector and his Council touching the same; And the Commissioners for their care, pains and service therein, shall have and pay themselves quarterly, in every twenty shillings raised and levied free and clear from all abatements and allowances for exportations or otherwise, two pence, and shall be liable according to the same rate, for all such exportations or otherwise, for one year after they shall be dismissed from this trust, and no longer.</p>
<p>And it is further Ordained by the Lord Protector, with the consent of His Council, That Sir <em>William Roberts</em> Knight, <em>John Stone, Henry Eising, Adam Bains</em>, and <em>John Bocket</em> Esquires, or any three of them, be and shall be hereby authorized to receive all appeals, and to <unclear>hear, decide and determine the same</unclear>, and to consider and Examine by each or otherwise, <unclear>what arrears</unclear> of Excise are not yet paid, and what hereafter may <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear>, either remaining in the hands of any Farmer, Commissioner, <reg orig="Sub commissioner">Sub-Commissioner</reg>, Collector, Importer, Seller, Buyer, Planter, <unclear>Grower</unclear> or <unclear>Maker</unclear>, or <unclear>of any Commodities</unclear> Excisable whatsoever, or in the hands of any person whatsoever, or for which any person whatsoever, by Bond, Bill, Entry, Promise or other engagement, hath been, may or shall <unclear>become obliged, and to <!-- 1 word --></unclear> for all persons, <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg>, articles, receipts, <pb n="3" /> bonds, or any writings concerning the Excise, or in any wise <unclear>relating</unclear> thereunto determine all differences concerning the Premises. And if any Sub-Commissioner, Collector, Farmer, or any their Deputies, or any <unclear><reg orig="Suraties">Sureties</reg></unclear> for them or any of them, or any Importer, Buyer, Seller, Carrier or conveyer of the excisable commodities, or any person engaged for them, or any of them, shall refuse or delay to pay into the Treasury of the Excise, any arrears, <unclear>fines</unclear>, forfeitures, or other sums of money, which by the said last recited Commissioners or any three of them, shall be adjudged due to the Commonwealth, and ordered to be paid; upon such default certified under the hand of the Treasurer, and from the last recited Commissioners or any three of them, unto the Commissioners for managing Estates now under sequestration, the said Commissioners for managing the Estates under sequestration, shall, and are hereby required to <unclear>sequester</unclear> the estates of all such persons, both personal and real; till such arrears, fines, forfeitures, and sums of money be fully paid with damages.</p>
<p>This Ordinance to commence from the five and twentieth day of March, one thousand six hundred fifty four, and to continue to the five and twentieth day of March which shall be in the year of our Lord, one thousand six hundred fifty five.</p>
<p><i>Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 19.</i></head>
<p>This day produced <i>An Ordinance for <unclear>Continuation</unclear> of an Act of Parliament</i>, <unclear><reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg></unclear>, <i>An Act for the Continuation of the Customs <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26th day of March in the year 1653</i></p>
<p>Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for continuation of the Customs, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 of March, 1653.</i> and all powers and <unclear>clauses</unclear> therein <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, be, and are hereby continued, and shall and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the six and twentieth day of March, in the year of the Lord, one thousand and six hundred fifty eight. And be if further Ordained that the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> shall not hereafter, <unclear>make payment</unclear> of the <unclear><!-- 4 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="Subsidue">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported, which <unclear>have been</unclear>, or hereafter shall be sold unto, or in the possession of any <reg orig="Shop-keeper">Shopkeeper</reg> or <unclear>retailer</unclear> of the same commodity, or for any such goods where the property, form or nature of the commodity once imported, is in any wise altered, mingled, amended, or <unclear>conscirnded</unclear>.</p>
<p>And be it hereby further Ordained, That the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> for the time being, shall have and receive upon <unclear>every twenty shillings</unclear> <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> clear unto the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> upon their account <unclear>such salary of</unclear> Poundage as is or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for <reg orig="Regulatihg">Regulating</reg> the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, or any other thereunto authorized by his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council.</p>
<p><i>Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>This day produced intelligence from <em><reg orig="Upsalah">Uppsala</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em>, which <unclear>certifies</unclear>; That the Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> Answer is delayed till they hear how the Treaty with us proceeds, that being the Wheels with which they intend to move. The <em>Queen</em> is desirous to live a <reg orig="retir'd">retired</reg> life, and surrender up the Government to her successor, and to that purpose summoned a Grand Council or Parliament to meet on the 12 of March, 1653.</p>
<p>From the <unclear>Texel</unclear> we received intelligence, The Freebooter Captain <em>Oomke</em> with another went to sea the 12 instant, and two other Freebooters <unclear>also</unclear> went to sea the next day. The said Captain <em>Oomke</em>, with Captain <em><unclear>Hogtenbeen</unclear></em> came home the 15 <unclear>with</unclear> such a good prize of a Flute laden with French Wines going for <em>London</em>, and from thence for <em><unclear><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></unclear></em>. It is here reported that 20 English ships have appeared before the wall, near the Texel, and that about 8 more are passed towards the North. And that they have taken about five fisher-boats within the sight of this land, two belonging unto this place, and three to <em><unclear>Huysdayn</unclear></em>. The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> are hasting the dispatch of an Ordinance for <reg orig="High Ways">Highways</reg> for mending them where need is, and for <unclear>prevention of breaking the ways by such</unclear> great Wanes and Carts have been by <unclear>six seven <reg orig="reign">rein</reg> Horses on a Team, not</unclear> for the future to exceed such a <unclear>number as shall be proportioned;</unclear> and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> were also <unclear>about some</unclear> other Ordinances which will <unclear>shortly</unclear> be dispatched.</p>
<p>A Petition Congratulatory hath been <unclear>presented from the Town of Newcastle</unclear> to his Highness the Lord Protector, professing much affection to his <unclear><reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg></unclear>, and the <unclear>late changes</unclear> of Government.</p>
<p><unclear>Also this day in the morning, the Lords <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> of the seven United Provinces of Holland, &amp;c. had audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, whither they were attended by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, Major Gen. <em>Lambert</em> <!-- approx. 3 words --> betwixt his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> person and the Park gate. The Lords <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> being now removed from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>, to Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg> at Ghannil Roe</em> near the <!-- 2 words -->. The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> appointed to confer with them, that met at the conference on Wednesday last at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>, were this day appointed to meet them at a Conference at Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> this night. There hath been much pains on both sides since the former conference to make <!-- 2 words --> <reg orig="forwardnesse">forwardness</reg> as <!-- approx. 6 characters -->. In the evening according <!-- approx. 3 words --> the Commissioners with Mr <em>Thurloe</em> Secretary of State, and Mr <em>Jesop</em> Clerk to the Council, in the L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches, and attendants, were carried to the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>; who when they came to the gate, were met by the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> who came and <!-- 1 word --> them and with great <!-- 1 word --> entertained them and went presently to conference in a chamber, fitted by the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> in Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> house where they treated <!-- approx. 8 characters --> at night, and they have almost fitted the Articles read to sign, which had been ready before this time</unclear>, had not the summoning up of the Danish <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg> took up much time.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 22.</i></head>
<p><i>A Declaration of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, inviting the people of England and Wales, to a Day of Solemn Fasting and Humiliation.</i></p>
<p>The common and notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised amongst us, notwithstanding all our Deliverances and Mercies, together with the present Rod of an Exceeding and Unusual Drought, which hath lain upon us for some years, and still continues and increaseth upon us, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Famine and Mortality, are no less than the Voice of God, calling aloud in our Ears to Fasting, and Mourning, and great Abasement of Soul before him.</p>
<p>And although the General end and Intendment of inviting to a day of <unclear>Fast</unclear> be, that all of every condition and quality whatever, do try and examine their heart and way more especially, according to their own Light, and in the use of such helps and means as the Lord in his Providence shall afford to each one, before and upon the said day of Meeting; yet finding some thoughts set seriously upon our heart, we judged it not amiss to <reg orig="recomend">recommend</reg> the same to Christian consideration, not to impose them upon any, or to confine any within the compass thereof; but leaving every man free to the grace of God, and to the work of his spirit, who works all things in the hearts of the <reg orig="sons">son's</reg> men, according to the Counsel and Good Pleasure of His own Will.</p>
<p>It cannot be denied but that God hath vouchsafed to appear very much in working the Deliverance of the Nation from their bondage and <reg orig="thraldome">thraldom</reg>, both Spiritual and Civil, and procuring for them a just Liberty by his own People.</p>
<p>Do we now walk worthy of our high calling in humbleness and lowliness of mind, holding forth the virtues of Christ in time of Peace, which was our strength, by the efficacy of which all our great things were accomplished in time of War? Have we a heart prepared as willingly to communicate the said Just Freedom and Liberty to one another, as we were industrious to get it? Do we thankfully <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> our mercy in the liberty of Worshipping God in Holiness and Righteousness without fear, being delivered but of the hands of our Enemies? Is brotherly love, and a healing spirit of that force and value amongst us that it ought? Do we own one another more for the grace of God and for the Spiritual Regeneration, and for the image of Christ in each other, or for our agreement with each other in this or that form, or opinion? Do we first search for the Kingdom of Christ within us, before we seek one without us? Or do we listen to them that say concerning the coming of Christ, lo here, and lo there? Do we not more contend for Saints having rule in the world, than <unclear>over</unclear> their own hearts? Are there not too many amongst us that cry up the spirit, with a neglect of love, joy, peace, <reg orig="meeknesse">meekness</reg>, patience, <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg>, temperance, long-suffering, forbearance, brotherly kindness, charity, which are the fruits of the Spirit? How do we carry <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the Churches <unclear>of God</unclear>, and the Saints, but towards them that are without? Do not some of <pb n="5" /> us affirm <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to be the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> true Ministry, and true Churches of Christ, and <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to have the Ordinances in purity, excluding our brethren, though of equal gifts, and having as large a seal of their Ministry, and desiring with as much fervour and zeal to <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> the Ordinances in their utmost purity? Do we remember old Puritan, or rather primitive simplicity, self-denial, mercy to the poor, <reg orig="uprighteousnesse">uprighteousness</reg>, and Justice? or are we not herein put to shame by those we easily call Antichristian or Carnal? Hath one that we judge to be without, equal justice with one we will call a brother? Do we contend for the <em>Faith once delivered unto the Saints</em>, as the things of faith ought to be contended for, with love, patience, tenderness, zeal, by <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>? Or rather imposingly, proudly, carnally, provokingly, sensually, thereby prejudicing the truth, and <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> we are calling aloud for the <reg orig="propogating">propagating</reg> of the Gospel, do we not put stumbling blocks in the way of the same, and too much <reg orig="indanger">endanger</reg> to make good the <unclear>slander</unclear> of the world in charging Profession with Faction? For want of circumspection and care herein, and a due regard to sincerity and uprightness, have not many <reg orig="apostatized">apostatised</reg>, running after <em>Fancies</em> and <em>Notions</em>, <reg orig="listning">listening</reg> to filthy <em>Dreams, worshipping of Angels</em>, and been carried by their Impulsions; and instead of contending for the faith, and holding forth the form of sound words, contended against <em>Magistracy</em>, against <em>Ministry</em>, against <em>Scriptures</em>, and against <em>Ordinances</em>, too much verifying the Prophesies of <em>Peter</em> and <em>Jude</em>, in these following words. 2 <em>Pet</em> 2. 1 2, 3, 10, 11, 12, 15. <em>Jude</em> ver. 4 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 16, 19.</p>
<p>And not <unclear>withstanding all these evils</unclear>, and worse, are upon, and in the midst of us, like <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> hair, here and there, and we <i>know it not, <unclear>our</unclear> pride testifying to our face, Hos 7.9, 10.</i> and we not return to the Lord our God, nor seek him for all this, but these things are contended for and <unclear>justified</unclear> under the notion of liberty, it being commonly said, that the Magistrate hath nothing to do either in repressing or remedying these things. We do hereby appeal to the hearts and consciences of all fearing the Lord, whether there be not as great cause as ever to lay our <em>Mouths in the dust, and to abhor <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg></em> before the Lord <em>for these <reg orig="abbominations">abominations</reg></em> whereby the eye of his <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> are provoked, and to seek pardon and remedy from himself of these things. Add we to these, the <unclear>resistance</unclear>, hatred and neglect of the Gospel by the <reg orig="generallity">generality</reg> of men, the contempt and despite done to the sincere professors of it, even for the image of Christ in them (although they have been instruments of many mercies, and of the obtaining a just freedom for the nation) The wickednesses, oaths, drunkennesses, revellings, and all manner of <reg orig="licenciousnesse">licentiousness</reg>, for which things the Scriptures have said, that the wrath of God undoubtedly overtake the children of disobedience.</p>
<p>And lastly the impunity of these things, through the neglect of the Magistracy, throughout the Nation, and then judge whether there be not cause that we be called upon, and do call upon each other seriously, to lay all these things to heart being greatly abased before the Lord for them. Upon the <unclear>serious consideration</unclear> of these things, we judge it not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> warrantable, but a duty, to call upon you, and <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, to set apart time to humble our souls before the Lord <pb n="6" /> to cry unto him for broken and penitent hearts, and that he would turn away his wrath and be reconciled to us; for the Lord he is <reg orig="mercifull">merciful</reg>, gracious, long-suffering, and abundant in <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> and truth, forgiving iniquity, transgression and sin, and will by no means clear the guilty, who are only such as go on in <unclear>their</unclear> <reg orig="hardned">hardened</reg> and impenitent hearts, refusing the grace offered by Jesus Christ. It is therefore hereby declared, That We, and our Council, do purpose (by the Grace of God) to set apart <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> <unclear>next</unclear>, being the 24 of this present <em>March</em>, for a day of Humiliation. And it is hereby Ordered that timely notice be given to the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em> who (together with the out-Parishes) we doubt not, will willingly keep the same day. And that like notice be given throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to have their several meetings upon the same day fortnight; And that copies hereof be printed and published to be sent to the several parts of the Nations, to invite them unto the performance of this duty. Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 20 of <em>March</em>, 1653.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Thursday, March the 23.</i></head>
<p>From <em>Scotland</em> our <em>Scout</em> is <reg orig="inform'd">informed</reg>, that <em>Middleton</em> hath summoned in all the Gentlemen of <em>Sutherland</em> and <em>Ross</em>, and prohibited the sheriffs to act <reg orig="any more">anymore</reg> in the name of the Lord Protector, saying he will give them a new commission to act by. He brought over above 60 Officers, the least of them a Captain; there is since another Vessel landed in <em>Caithness</em> with more arms and ammunition, and <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised 600 men and is upon his march to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him. He expects more provisions daily from <em>Holland</em>, and gives out, that as soon as the prepared parties are ready, and the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> sent the 160000 <reg orig="Rixdollars">Rix-dollars</reg> for the raising of 30 Regiments, that then their King, or the Duke of York will come to be their General. The Earl of <em><reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg></em> and Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg></em> have placed a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Isle of <em>Lough Tay</em>, where they intend to have a stock of Provisions.</p>
<p>This day was published the Ordinance for approbation of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Ministers of Gods Word, by which Ordinance is appointed 30 Commissioners, <em>viz.</em></p>
<p><i>Dr. <em>Arrowsmith</em>, M <em>Joseph Caryl</em>, M. <em>Obadiah Sedgwick</em>, M. <em>Owen</em>, M. <em>Greenhil</em>, Col. <em>Goff</em>, M. <em>Stephen Marshal</em>, M. <em>Hugh Peters</em>, M. <em>Strong</em>, M. <em>Goodwin</em>, M. <em>Nye</em>, M. <em>Campfield</em>, M. <em>Sydrach Sympson</em>, M <em>Nicholas Lockier</em>, M. <em>Manton</em>, M. <em>Tombs</em>, <em>Thomas St. Nicholas</em> Esq. And other able and godly Ministers and Gentlemen.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><i><em>Readers</em>, this Pamphlet <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> the <em>Faithful Scout</em> printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>, is <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in the Register Book of the Company of Stationers to him, peculiarly</i></p>
<head level="2">J. BURROUGHS, Cler.</head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>