<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout173">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 173
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">Scout:</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The Articles of <em>Peace</em> signed and sealed by the <em>Commissioners</em> of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> on Wednesday the fifth of <em>April</em>, and those <em>Articles</em> to be ratified within 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> by the Estates of both <em>Commonwealths</em>, and general Proclamation to be made thereof throughout all <em>England</em> and the <em>United Provinces</em>. The King of Scots commission to General <em>Middleton</em>, giving him power in all affairs both Ecclesiastical and civil, his besieging of <em><reg orig="Cinkeler">Sinclair</reg></em> castle, and surprising an English Vessel laden with arms and provisions, and the revolting of divers Knights and Gentlemen of quality, and going to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> with horse and arms. The taking of divers Ships belonging to <em>Bristol, Weymouth</em> and <em>Westchester</em>, by the <em>Brest</em> <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>; Together with the Transactions of His highness the Lord Protector and his <em>Council</em> at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the electing of commissioners of the Great Seal for the Chancery, and their debates concerning the adjourning of <em>Easter Term</em></i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> March 31, to <em>Friday</em> April <em>the</em> 7. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>March</em> the 31</i>.</head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>The Letters out of the West mention, that the Brest men of War are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, and that two of them took the <em>Charity</em> a ship of above 100 <reg orig="tuns">tonnes</reg>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> her port, and detain the Master for <em>Beech</em>; besides this of <em>Bristol</em>, they took another belonging to <unclear><em>Westchester</em></unclear>, and four Vessels of <em>Weymouth</em>, and thereabouts. Also the <em>Wilde Bore</em>, a ship of 24 guns, and 250 <reg orig="tuns">tonnes</reg>, taking in some lading at the <em><reg orig="Medera's">Madeiras</reg></em>, was forced by a storm to cut her cable and put to Sea, where meeting with a <em>Flushinger</em> of 22 guns, with those men that she had she fought gallantly, but being over-mastered they carried her into <em>Cadiz</em>, she's valued to be <unclear>worth</unclear> 5000l.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 4.</i></head>
<p>Yesterday was presented to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by Mr. <em>Dickeson</em>, and Sir <em>Thomas Withrington</em> Recorder of the City of <em>York</em>, the Declaration and Recognition of the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of that ancient City.</p>
<p>Letters from Mr. Feak, and Mr. John Simpson say to their Friends, that they are still the same men, and carried on under the same confidences.</p>
<p>This day the Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of State attended his Highness: the Lord Protector at the Cock-pit, after which they <unclear><reg orig="sate">sat</reg></unclear> in <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg> in <reg orig="White Hal">Whitehall</reg>, and several businesses of great consequence were transacted. The French <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> is removed from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> to his own lodgings in Covent Garden. And the Agent from the <unclear>Queen of Sweden had audience</unclear> by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, attended by Sir Oliver Flemming, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> divers Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and Mr. Secretary of State.</p>
<p>Sir Thomas Withrington, and the Lord Commissioner Lisle, were also this day sworn Commissioners of the Great <reg orig="Seil">Seal</reg> of England <unclear>for</unclear> the Court of Chancery by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, in the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> Chamber at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, the Lord <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> <unclear>Whitlock</unclear> who is now in Sweden, is also to be one with them. And there was published an Ordinance for continuing one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Probate of Wills and granting Administrations</i>, as followeth</p>
<p>Be it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations</i>, and all the Powers, Authorities, Matters and Things therein contained, shall be, and are hereby revived and continued in full power and force, to all intents and purposes, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further Order.</p>
<p>And it is hereby further Ordained, That <em>Richard Lucy, John <unclear>Hildeslay</unclear>, Nathaniel Barton, <unclear>Jervas</unclear> Bennet, Anthony <unclear>Rous, Joachim</unclear> Matthews, Edward Cludd, Thomas Wood</em>, <unclear>Esq</unclear>. and <em>Robert Titchbourn</em> Alderman of <em>London</em>, be added to the Judgesmen <unclear><reg orig="ioned">commissioned</reg></unclear> in the said Act, and that the said Judges named in the said Act, and in this present Ordinance; or any three of them, be, and are hereby authorized to put in execution all and every the Powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named might have done by force of the said Act.</p>
<p>An Ordinance was also this day published for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> and confirming of the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Framlingham and <unclear>Saxtead</unclear>, in the County of Suffolk, and the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments thereunto belonging, upon the Master, Fellows, and <reg orig="Schollers">Scholers</reg> of <reg orig="Pembrook">Pembroke</reg> Hall in the <reg orig="Vniversity">University</reg> of <reg orig="Cambridg">Cambridge</reg>, and their Successors <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, which were devised to certain charitable uses, by Sir Robert Hitcham Knight, late <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at Law, who did <reg orig="heretofoye">heretofore</reg> purchase of <em>Theophilus</em> late Earl of Suffolk, and his Feoffees, the Castle and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> <pb n="2" /> of Framlingham and Saxtead, and divers Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, with the <unclear>appurtenances</unclear>, lying and being in Framlingham and Saxtead in the County of Suffolk, which were by his direction <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear> and assured unto <em>Richard Keeble</em>, one of the Lords Commissioners for the great Seal of England, and to Francis Bacon <unclear>Esq.</unclear> and James River, William Buts, and Robert Buts Gentlemen, and their Heirs, who were persons <reg orig="onely"></reg> trusted by Sir Robert Hitcham.</p>
<p>And whereas afterwards, <em>viz</em>. the 8 of <em>August</em> 1636. the said Sir Robert Hitcham made his last Will and Testament in writing, and thereby did, amongst other things, will, limit, and appoint, That as touching the said Castle and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Framlingham and Saxtead, and all the Lands and Hereditaments which he and his <reg orig="Feoffes">Feoffees</reg> purchased of the said Theophilus <unclear>Earl</unclear> of Suffok, and his Feoffees, the said Robert Hitchams Feoffees and their Heirs, after his debts paid, should stand <unclear>seized</unclear> in trust to the uses of the Masters and Fellows of Pembroke Hall in Cambridge, and their Successors, and that upon request his Feoffees should make a good assurance unto them accordingly; of which, the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> <unclear>should</unclear> have to their own use, the Castle and <unclear>Royalties, and</unclear> Rents of Tenure, with the <unclear>Meat</unclear> and <reg orig="Fish-ponds">Fishponds</reg>, the Advowson of the Church, the <unclear>Hundred</unclear> of <unclear>Los</unclear>, the Fairs and Markets there; but the <unclear><!-- 1 word --></unclear> Lands of the said <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg>, and all the Hereditaments and Lands purchased of the Earl of Suffolk, as aforesaid the said <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> should have <unclear><reg orig="onely">only</reg> in trust to use</unclear>, to be by them converted to the uses following, <em>viz</em> That they should <unclear>pull</unclear> down all the Castle save the stone buildings, and therewith erect <unclear>at Framlingham one house</unclear> to set the poor on work, the poor and most needy <unclear>and impotent</unclear> of Framlingham, Debenham, and <unclear>Coxal, first</unclear>, and after them of other Towns if they see cause; and to provide a substantial <unclear>stock</unclear> to set them <unclear>on with</unclear>, and to allow such needy persons of them so much, as the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> should further think fit; And if they should build one or two <reg orig="Alms houses">Almshouses</reg> consisting of twelve persons (namely six a piece) for 12 of the poorest and <unclear><reg orig="decrepid">decrepit</reg></unclear> people there, which are to have each of them two shillings <em>per</em> Week during their lives, and forty shillings a piece for a Gown and <unclear>firing</unclear> every year: And that they should build a <unclear>School</unclear> house there at Framlingham, and appoint a <unclear>Master</unclear> who is to have forty <unclear>pounds</unclear> <em>per <unclear>annum</unclear></em> during his life, to teach thirty, forty, or more, of the poorest children of Framlingham, Debenham, and <unclear>Coxal</unclear>, to write, read, and cast<reg orig="accompt">account</reg>, as the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> shall think fit, and then they to have ten pounds a <unclear>piece</unclear> to <reg orig="binde">bind</reg> them Apprentices, at the direction of the four Senior <reg orig="Fellowes">Fellows</reg> of the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg>; and that they shall build the like <reg orig="Alms houses">Almshouses</reg> at Levington, which shall have the same allowance; and that there shall be <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> one to read prayers in the <unclear>Church of Framlingham</unclear> daily at the hours of eight in the forenoon, and four afternoon; who is to have <em>20 l. per annum</em>, and the Sexton five pounds. And whatsoever shall further come of that which the <unclear>Testa</unclear> or had formerly given in trust to the said <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg>, they to convert the same to the like use or <unclear>uses</unclear>, to continue as before <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, April 5.</i></head>
<p>Since the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> return from <em>Ireland</em>, we have received little of News from thence; save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that about 1200 <em>Tories</em> were shipped from Limbrick, and 1700 more are ready for transportation, which will render that Nation more free from Robbers than in times of the greatest peace.</p>
<p>We have also received farther intelligence from <em>Sweden</em>, that the <em>Queen</em> having <unclear>visited</unclear> her mother at <unclear><em>Nicop ng</em></unclear>, is again returned to <em><reg orig="Upsal">Uppsala</reg></em> to be present at the great Assembly of the Senators.</p>
<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, That the Commander in chief having issued forth a Proclamation, requiring all Burgesses and others to secure all <unclear>suspicious persons</unclear>, or otherwise to give intelligence of them to the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present government, and proceeded against accordingly: Several towns have been lately found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a <reg orig="Court-Marshal">Court martial</reg> for the same. The last week the Parish of <em>Liberton</em>, two miles from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, for harbouring 15 of the Enemy by the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving intelligence of them, and <unclear>the Tories</unclear> at their going away <unclear>stealing</unclear> 15 horses, the Parish was for that offence dined <unclear>200 <em>l.</em> </unclear> sterling, the person in whose house they were concealed, <unclear>sentenced</unclear> to imprisonment during pleasure, and the house where they were <unclear>harboured to be raised</unclear> to the ground, and a pair of <reg orig="Gallowes">Gallows</reg> to be built there. There are divers other <unclear>Parishes</unclear> who are summoned into Court <reg orig="Marshals">Martials</reg> upon the very same <unclear>account</unclear>, who will suffer for it. <unclear>It</unclear> is hoped this course will in time <unclear><reg orig="compell">compel</reg></unclear> the Scots not to give any Entertainment unto the Tories, but give notice of them, <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> they shall come, otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>
<p>The 21 instant Col. Cooper with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of Leven, where about <unclear>300</unclear> of the enemy quartered (about 4 in the <unclear>morning</unclear>) took <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg></em> <unclear>Trumpet</unclear>, and 35 other prisoners, and narrowly missed <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em> and <em>Newark</em>, who were both there; they killed 12, whereof one of them (as the enemy <unclear>confess</unclear>) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 Horse and some <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and totally scattered and routed the whole party, returning without any loss at.</p>
<p>Captain <unclear><em>Ortan</em></unclear> Commander of the Sun, and Captain <em><reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em> of the Union, came into Lieth Road from <em>Lewis</em> and <em>Orkney</em>, and brought three Companies of <unclear>Col <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em></unclear> Regiment, and therewith a particular relation of the late <unclear>infall</unclear> of the Earl of <reg orig="Seafort">Seaforth</reg> into <em>Lewis</em> Island.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>The Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath taken a Dutch man of war, being one of the four Capers that did so much infest the Northern seas. Our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> attended her 3 or 4 days before he could snap her; she carries 14 Guns, and is brought to Burlington Bay.</p>
<p>The Spaniard seems again to favour the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg>, the Arch Duke having ordered, that the Count <em>de Bussigni</em>, and the Abbot of <em>Mercy</em> shall be removed from the Castle of Antwerp to the Castle of Gant, on purpose to <reg orig="gratifie">gratify</reg> the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrain">Lorraine</reg>, who was very much offended that they should be imprisoned in the same prison with him. The Letters from Brussels do advertise That many <unclear>Irish</unclear> daily arrive there out of Ireland, who are all to go to the Pr. of Conde to be clothed &amp; armed: many of them die by the way through want. The Sentence of death is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> in the French Parl. against the Prince of Conde; they have also under consideration, some Propositions touching the disposing of the Crown Lands for the easing of the people of their taxes and oppressions.</p>
<p>The last Letters from <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the Commander of the <em>Sophire</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in thither a Dutch prize, laden <reg orig="onely">only</reg> with some few barrels of Pitch, Tar, &amp;c. And that the <em>Paul</em>, a ship in the States service, met with a man of War belonging to <em>Flushing</em> in <em>St. <reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> channel, which carried 15 Guns, with whom she fought continually for five hours together, yet thanks be to God, lost not a man, but sustained <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> in her Masts, sails, and rigging; the Enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and his ship was much torn; Yet our men made shift to <reg orig="towe">tow</reg> her into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>; she had aboard her some small quantity of Wines, and some silver, which our men easily <reg orig="pocketted">pocketed</reg> up, and well they <reg orig="deserv'd">deserved</reg> it, <em><unclear>Win</unclear> Gold and Wear it.</em></p>
<p>The Letters from <em>Scotland</em>, speak that the <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlander's</reg></em> Army is <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> into one Body, that since the landing of <em>Middleton</em>, there is likewise landed another Hoy with some few inconsiderable men and Arms, and that <reg orig="collonel">colonel</reg> <em>Robert <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em> is advancing toward them with a very considerable Army, resolving to fight them is they will keep together till his approach.</p>
<p><i>In <em><reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg></em> below the <em>Church</em>, over against the Stile that goes to <em>Stepney</em>, in <em>Trumpet</em> <unclear>Yard</unclear>, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M</em> <unclear>Student in Mathematical <reg orig="pysick">physic</reg></unclear>, who cureth the Tysick &amp; Cough of the Lungs, the <unclear>swelling of the Spleen, &amp; deafness of the ears</unclear>, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, and all sorts of Agues, of which cure he never <unclear>failed</unclear>; with other diseases <unclear>incident</unclear> to men.</i></p>
<p><i>Also, he cureth perfectly all diseases peculiar to <unclear>women, or</unclear> their <reg orig="Sexe">Sex</reg>, be they either <reg orig="Chronical">Chronic</reg> or Acute; and hath cured many that have been thought to be past cure. Also, he cureth those that are Deaf and <unclear>thick of Hearing</unclear>, and hath a present Remedy for the <reg orig="Tooth-Ache">Toothache</reg>. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><em>Thursday, April the 6.</em></head>
<p>The Mayor, Aldermen, Common council men, and other Inhabitants of the city of <em>Coventry</em>, have presented their humble Address and congratulation to his Highness the Lord Protector. And his Highness council are debating about the adjourning Easter-Term, or part of it.</p>
<p>The 5th. instant, about 6 or 7 of the clock in the Evening, the English commissioners went to the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> at Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevors">Trever's</reg></em> house, in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches, with Mr. Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council; and about nine a clock at night, totally finished the Ratification of the Articles of Peace, both between England, Holland and Denmark, which were then signed <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of the Commonwealth of England, by &mdash;</p>
<p>Major General <em>Lambert</em>. The Lord <em>Lisle</em>. Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>. Master <em>Lawrence</em>. Colonel <em>Montague</em>. Master <em>Strickland</em>.</p>
<p>And the Lord <em>Bevorning</em>, The Lord <em>Newport</em>, And the Lord <unclear><em>Yongstal</em></unclear>, signed <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of the States of Holland; who are to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> them within fifteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; and then <reg orig="publike">public</reg> proclamation is to be made there of throughout the Dominions of England, Scotland, Ireland, and all the United Provinces.</p>
<head level="2">Soli Deo Gloria.</head>
<p>This day produced farther intelligence from Scotland, certifying that <em>Middleton</em> hath brought over a very large commission from <em>Charles Stuart</em>, which <reg orig="impowers">empowers</reg> him in the disposal of all matters both <unclear>Ecclesiastical</unclear> and civil. They are still in <em>Sutherland</em> and <em>Caithness</em>, and the Lord <em>de la Banks</em> brothers, some Knights, and about 50 Gentlemen, with good horses, <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, &amp;c. are gone in to the Enemy, and <em>Middleton, <reg orig="Seafort">Seaforth</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Ragets">Raget's</reg></em> men <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> a Vessel of ours going to Lewis Island, by some <unclear>Boats</unclear> they sent out; she had in her 14 men, with Ammunition, provision and clothes for that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>; and hath also besieged <em><reg orig="Cinkeler">Sinclair</reg></em> castle in <em><reg orig="Kaithness">Caithness</reg></em>, being very cruel in burning and destroying all parts of the country that do not freely <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; whereupon Sir <em>James MacDonald</em>, and the captain of the <em>clan of Reynolds</em>, have ratified forces against him, for preservation of their <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <unclear>Register</unclear> Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></p>
<head level="3"><em>LONDON: Printed by</em> ROBERT WOOD, 1654.</head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>