<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScout166">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Faithful Scout, Issue 166
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">The Faithful</head> 
<head level="1">SCOUT.</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Containining">Containing</reg> these Particulars, viz.</head>
<p>&#x261e; <i>The apprehending of some more of the Conspirators against His Highness the Lord Protector, and the present Government. The wracking and breaking One upon the Wheel, with this Inscription written upon a Stake by it; <em>An Example to all those who will imitate such a Traitor.</em> Also, the <em>French <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg></em> sending over Mons. <em>Nieusville</em> to his Highness the Lord Protector, to desire that his Majesty and his Subjects may be comprehended in the Articles of Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>. A <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Fight between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Highlanders</em> near <em>Aberdeen</em>, and the routing of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Army consisting of 2000 men, and the <reg orig="persuing">pursuing</reg> of them seven miles; Also the advance of his Excellency the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> and divers other Noble Commanders for <em>Ireland</em>; Together with the <reg orig="dispiercing">dispersing</reg> of the Dutch Fleet of Fishermen, and taking of their <reg orig="Convoyes">Convoys</reg>: And an Order of the States of <em>Holland</em>, commanding all the Shipping in the Unites Provinces to be ready about the beginning of <em>March</em> next.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> Febr. 17, to <em>Friday</em> February <em>the</em> 24. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>London, Printed by <em>Robert Wood</em>; to prevent all false <unclear>Copies</unclear>.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning, Friday <em>February</em> 17.</i></head>
<img src="" alt="equestrian illustration encircled by phrase Scout the Faithful" />
<p>Her Majesty the <em>Queen</em> of <em>Sweden</em> having had news of the <em>Change</em> in <em>England</em>, received His <unclear><reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg></unclear> Credentials with all willingness; and His Excellence the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> hath had two meetings with the <em>Grand <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg></em>, and satisfied him concerning his power to conclude and determine things; they went over the Articles in general, and there was nothing seemed dubious or <reg orig="controversal">controversial</reg>, which His Excellency left unsatisfied; and we may confidently be assured, that after time hath ripened their debates, we shall receive an <unclear>an- <!-- approx. 2 words --> contentment</unclear> and good of this Nation.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>The last Week I gave you notice of a dangerous plot that was discovered against His Highness the Lord Protector, and this present Government; and how the Conspirators were apprehended at Master <em>Amp</em> a <unclear>Vintner</unclear> his House, dwelling at the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> of the Ship in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>; they have since been examined before the Lord Protector and his Honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, from whose Confessions may be gathered, that their Grand <reg orig="Designe">Design</reg> was;</p>
<p>1. That each Conspirator should take an Oath of <reg orig="Secresie">Secrecy</reg>, not to discover any part or parcel of their intended <reg orig="Designe">Design</reg>.</p> 
<p>2. That none should be trusted in this design, but such as should be adjudged absolute <reg orig="Royallists">Royalists</reg>, and true friends to their <unclear>titular</unclear> King.</p>
<p>3. That so many persons should be engaged for Officers to an Army as should undertake for the private <unclear>listing</unclear> of 30000 men to be ready to rise at a time appointed.</p>
<p>4. That this design should be <unclear>acted</unclear> in all the several Counties of England at once.</p>
<p>5. That one party at the time appointed should fall upon his Highness, and <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> him and his <reg orig="Life-guard">Lifeguard</reg> and others about him, as also the Garrison at St. James.</p>
<p>6. <unclear>Another</unclear> party were to seize upon the Tower of London.</p>
<p>7. That when all this should be acted, their <unclear>titular</unclear> King, <em>Charles Stuart</em>, should be in a private place in <unclear>the</unclear> City of London, and be brought forth and presently crowned, and proclaimed King, and Proclamation sent forth into all parts, <i>That Charles Stuart, eldest Son of the late King, was Crowned King,</i> &amp;c. offering pardon to <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> and all others that would come in.</p>
<p>8. That this design might be carried on with the better Judgement, and according to the Instructions they received from time to time from their titular King, they made choice of four persons of eminency, to carry on this trust. But it pleased God to touch the heart of one of those four who with a troubled spirit came and discovered this design to the Officers of the Army, and where some of them would be at such a time; whereupon Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Worsley, and other Officers went and apprehended these persons following at the Ship Tavern aforesaid:</p>
<p>M. Thomas Dutton,</p>
<p>Mr. Joseph Sawyer,</p>
<p>Mr. William Jenkins,</p>
<p>Mr. John Archer,</p>
<p>Mr. Thomas <unclear>Burce</unclear>.</p>
<p>Mr Joseph Parker,</p>
<p>Mr, Roger Lee,</p>
<p>Mr. <unclear>Thomas Rosse</unclear>,</p>
<p>Mr. Christopher Watkins.</p>
<p>Captain <unclear>Smith</unclear>,</p>
<p>Mr. Peter Middleton.</p>
<p>Mr Roger Cotes.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of such as are suspected to have a hand in this Plot, who are beyond the seas, and other remote places.</i></head>
<p>Charles Stuart,</p>
<p>The titular Duke of York,</p>
<p>Prince Rupert,</p>
<p>Major General Massey,</p>
<p>Major General Middleton,</p>
<p><unclear>Alderman Bruce</unclear>,</p>
<p>Lord Loughbrough.</p>
<p>Lord Byron,</p>
<p>Sir Thomas Sands,</p>
<p>Sir Thomas Armstrong, and many others.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<head level="3"><i>Saturday, Febr. 18.</i></head>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector and his Honourable Council considering that some things contained in the former Act for Treason, might appear dubious so some <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> Understandings, have caused an Ordinance to be published for the Explanation of Treasons: A true Copy whereof is here inserted.</p>
<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance declaring that the Offences therein mentioned, and no other, shall be adjudged High Treason within the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland</i>, it is, amongst other things, Ordained and Established, <i>That no Matter, Fact, Crime, or Offence whatsoever, other than such as are therein mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken, or adjudged High Treason</i>; and whereas some doubts and question may arise, whether that Clause in the said Ordinance doth not extend to the Offences mentioned in the instrument, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>The Government of the Commonwealth of England, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging,</i> and which are thereby declared to be High Treason; For clearing thereof, and removing all scruples thereupon, his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That neither the said Ordinance, nor thy Clause or thing therein contained, shall extend or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend unto all or any the Offences declared by the said Instrument to be high Treason, but that all and every the said Offences are hereby adjudged, <unclear>and</unclear> shall be adjudged, taken and deemed to be High Treason, and that all and every the said <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg> and <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> suffer the pains and penalties of High Treason, the said Ordinance, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein contained to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
<p>The last Letters from our fleet, speak about 80 sail to be upon the Coast of France, and besides them there be about 15 <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --> broad in squadrons, and as Scouts who have brought in 8 prizes. The main fleet of the Dutch is not yet heard of abroad, though we have intelligence they are very strong</unclear>, part of our Fleet are going Northward <unclear>yet not so but they can <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> again in</unclear> few hours if occasion be, but we are now for Peace, yet prepared for war.</p>
<p>From Newcastle they write, that <unclear>costs</unclear> are likely to be <reg orig="plentifull">plentiful</reg> at London, for they have <unclear>little</unclear> to do there, but dig and send them away as last as shipping comes thither for them. Three <unclear>English Regiments</unclear> are newly marched into Scotland (<unclear><!-- 1 or 2 words --></unclear> others went before them) and <unclear>shortly</unclear> you will hear the Highlanders have made the most of their game this winter, and <unclear>will</unclear> be forced to keep the Rocks and Hills in the summer, for all the brags of Middleton, and the aid they are permitted from the other side of the water.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Febr. 20.</head>
<p>The Lord Hastings hearing he was named to be suspected (as I have formerly mentioned in the precedent List) hath been with the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to clear himself. Some others are apprehended, and some Apprentices run away, and left Bills with their Masters for the moneys they have taken.</p>
<p>This day the two Deputies from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Amiland dined at his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg>, at the Cock-pit, with great entertainment.</p>
<p>This day we received intelligence, that on Thursday the 9 of Febr. Col. Morgan with a party of <unclear>1200</unclear> Horse, Foot, and Dragoons, engaged <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> and <reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg> Army (given out to be 2000) at a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> which they had that day at the head of Cromar 16 miles from Aberdeen; and though the Enemy had the advantage, after a little dispute they were totally routed, and pursued seven miles in the Hills. Kenmore had left a <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> in Kildrumming (the Earl of <reg orig="Mars">Mar's</reg> Castle) which our men were then marching against. Since this we have news of Captain <unclear>Motlows</unclear> marching out of the <reg orig="garisons">garrisons</reg> of <unclear><reg orig="Dunstafnage">Dunstaffnage</reg></unclear> and <unclear><reg orig="Dunolly">Dunnolly</reg></unclear> with a party out of those two <reg orig="garisons">garrisons</reg>, and that he <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> upon the house <unclear>Archchetton</unclear> in Lorn in <reg orig="Argilshire">Argyllshire</reg>, and took it with all the men, arms, and Ammunition in it: He killed three, and afterwards (that it might not harbour any more of those wild <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>) fired it. Since which Lieut. Col. Cotterel marched out of <unclear><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></unclear> to <unclear>reduce</unclear> the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Rosdew near Loch Lomond, and <unclear>before he came near it, the Enemy ran away, and left word they had no order to fight. We heard also yesterday, that Brokie Cap Lieut. to Col. Wogan, is dead <!-- 2-3 words -->; and the Earl of <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg> (that fires and burns <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> corn and houses) threatened to shoot Holland the <!-- approx. 10 characters --> to death, for not curing Wogan and Brokie. Some of these Blad <!-- approx. 4 words --> and tend to desire liberty to live peaceably, and no doubt <!-- 1 word --> long they will betray one another into our hand. Col. Cooper sent to <!-- 1 word -->, party of 100 foot, and about 100 horse and dragoons to Dunbarton, and on <!-- 2 words --> the advantage of this dry weather, they had a party of about <!-- 2 words --> and 100 horse in <!-- approx. 9 characters -->; but upon our approach they are fled without <!-- approx. 4 words --> <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, though they might have done it with great advantage, and out of great <!-- 1 word --> quit their <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, and carried away the iron gates of <!-- approx. 2 words --></unclear></p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of three Prizes <unclear>brought into the <!-- approx. 3 words --></unclear></i></head>
<p>1. <unclear><em>Jac b <!-- approx. 6 characters --></em> Mr of the <!-- 3 characters --> <em>St. David</em> <!-- half a line --> 2000 Holland <!-- approx. 6 characters -->, 800 <!-- approx. 6 words -->, 200 <!-- approx. 8 words -->, taken by Captain Francis <!-- approx. 5 characters --> Commander of the <!-- 5 characters --> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</unclear></p>
<p>2. <unclear><em>Jose</em> <!-- 2 lines --> taken by Capt. John <!-- 1 word --> Commander of the Nightingale <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>3. <!-- approx. 12 words --> 120 <reg orig="Tuns">Tonnes</reg>, <!-- approx. 6 words -->, taken by Capt. <!-- 2 words --> Commander of the Adventure <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear><!-- 1 word --> this from the Hague Feb 20. This day <!-- 2-3 words --> sent by the Protestant Cantons of Switzerland to mediate a Reconciliation</unclear>
<pb n="4" />
between the two Commonwealths of England and the United Provinces, who hath formerly resided long at London, is arrived here. The Freebooters <em>de Haen</em> hath brought in three ships taken upon the coasts of Scotland, two laden with coals, and a Flute laden with salted Salmon and other Goods. The last Sunday arrived here an express from London, with Letters from the Lord Beverling to the Lords States General. The Provinces of Zealand, Utrecht, Freezland, and <unclear><reg orig="Overvssel">Overijssel</reg></unclear>; first brought into the Lords States General their Resolution upon the Ratification of the Articles of Peace, and according to the resolution of the Lords States of Holland, approved of, and ratified them. The next day the same was done by the States of Gidlerland and <unclear>Gronning</unclear>. Insomuch that it is generally hoped that the Treaty shall very shortly be brought to a full conclusion, and some <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> go speedily for England, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> altering some things in the Articles proposed and signed by the Deputies of both sides in England.</p>
<p>One <em>Willebort Bosse</em> inhabitant of Flushing, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> lately from the <unclear>Caribde</unclear> Islands with a small vessel of six pieces of Ordnance laden with Tobacco and other like <unclear>commodities, and having about</unclear> the Canaries met with an English <unclear>vessel of 3 or 4 pieces <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, laden with Spanish Soap, and other Goods, esteemed to the value of 2000 <em>l.</em> Flemish, hath taken and brought her to Rochel. There was also 4 or five days ago by Captain Oliv. Danielle brought in a prize worth 20 or 24000 Gilders. And three days ago one Captain Lembrant, who hath taken five prizes with Coals, and amongst them a Flute called the Elephant, formerly taken by the English, Captain <em>John <!-- 1-2 words --></em> and another Freebooter had taken two prizes from the same Fleet, but they were parted by storm and misty weather, and so they lost them again.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>Letters from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that they begin to conceive great hopes of the Treaty between England, Holland, and are such rejoicing at the good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of that Negotiation. There are great preparations made by sea in Denmark. We hear from Frandenburgh that over against Leazer there <!-- 2 words --> in the <reg orig="skie">sky</reg> a star of an extraordinary <reg orig="brightnesse">brightness</reg> with <!-- 2 words --> streams round about. And from <!-- 1-2 words --> in the Country thereabouts there is so infinite a number of <!-- 1 word --> of all colours, and of other like <!-- 6 characters --> bred out of corruption, that it is feared they will eat up the fruits of the earth, spreading all that Country over even as <reg orig="farre">far</reg> as Brunswick.</unclear></p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, Febr. 21.</i></head>
<p>The Letters from <unclear>Ludow</unclear>, <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that Major Gen. Brown is discharged of his long imprisonment there, and is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up towards London, where <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> he will not be wanting of returning thanks to his Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for being more just and <reg orig="mercifull">merciful</reg> unto him <reg orig="then">than</reg> those that committed him.</p>
<p>From Dartmouth thus: Here are two ships <unclear>laden</unclear> and have hoisted sail this week for the Canaries and from thence to the Barbadoes, I pray God send them a prosperous voyage; we hear of more mischief done by the Brest men of War on these coasts, they have taken two English ships very lately and have driven another into a small harbour on the coast of <reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg>, which was in great danger to be taken.</p>
<p>It is advertised from Scotland, that several parties of the <reg orig="enemie">enemy</reg> falling <reg orig="downe">down</reg> into the Lowlands in several parties have been taken by our Forces; four of <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg> own Troop have been taken, and eight horse, his <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg>, whose name is Rutherford hardly escaped. There are a considerable party of the Highlanders not far from St Johnstons, who are very active since the drawing our horse Northwards, but upon the coming of two Regiments more from England, our Horse will be so disposed of, that the Highlanders will be met with in all places; it being impossible for them to move in the Lowlands, but we shall be at their heels to pursue them, or in the front to oppose them. But as the numbers of the Highlanders begin to decrease, so doth their courage, 10000 of the Arms, with other Ammunition and <unclear>utensils</unclear> of War, being sunk with the ship that brought them on the coasts of Scotland.</p>
<p>I am <unclear>informed</unclear> that the titular Scotch King sent lately unto Holland, <unclear>desiring the transportation</unclear> of some thousands of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and Officers which he had got together: and that from thence a Dispatch immediately was made to the King of Denmark, to see what assistance he could get there. The Scots continue that <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in parties, and oftentimes come short of home. <unclear>It is certified</unclear>, that it is impossible <unclear>for the Highlanders to have any considerable Body of Horse in the field until the middle of</unclear> May.</p>
<p>The long expected Ambassadors from Holland are not yet arrived. Our <unclear>fleet consisting</unclear> of fourscore and eight gallant ships are put forth to sea. The <unclear>Sovereign</unclear> is making ready with all possible speed at Portsmouth; so are the Rainbow, the Resolution, and the Andrew at <unclear>Chattau</unclear>. Several prizes are brought in, some belonging to France, and some to Holland.</p>
<p>Mr. <unclear>Feak</unclear> and Mr. Powel have made Addresses for their liberty. The Brother to the Portugal Ambassador is this Week to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>. More of the Conspirators were apprehended, of whom I shall shortly give you a further Account.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, Febr. 23.</i></head>
<p>Was published, <i>An Ordinance,</i> touching the Assessing, Levying, and Collecting of the latter three <reg orig="moneths">months'</reg> Assessment, appointed by an Act of the late parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>; <i>An act for an assessment at the rate of 120000 l. by the <reg orig="Moneth">Month</reg> <em>(for six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>)</em> from the 25. of December 1653, to the 24 of June then next casuing, towards the maintenance of the Armies and Navies of this Commonwealth.</i> Wherein, High Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council doth Declare and Ordain, that in case the way or manner of Assessing the said latter three <reg orig="Moneths">Months'</reg> Assessment by a pound rate, in such sort as is prescribed by the said Act, shall prove prejudicial, and obstructive to the bringing in the said <unclear>latter</unclear> three <reg orig="Moneths">Months'</reg> Assessment appointed by the said Act, by the time in the said Act for that purpose limited, That then, and in all such cases, the commissioners in any of the cities, counties, towns, and places in the said Act mentioned where such obstructions shall be or happen, shall appoint a general meeting together, and the major part of them meeting, may, and are thereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> (for the removal of such obstructions, and the more speedy and effectual execution of the said Act) to proceed according to the most just and equal way of Rates held in such places in the proportioning, levying and assessing the respective sums charged <unclear>upon</unclear> them; <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Act to the contrary thereof contained in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
<p>The <em>Tories</em> under <unclear><em>Morlagh O Brian</em></unclear>, who began to make a new bustling in Ireland, finding it impossible to subsist in their <reg orig="consumaciousness">contumaciousness</reg>, have submitted; and having laid down their Arms are to be transported into <em>Flanders</em>, for the service of the King of <em>Spain</em>.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>In <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg> below the Church, over against the Stile that goes to Stepney, in <unclear>Trumpet</unclear> yard, <reg orig="dwels">dwells</reg> <em>L.M.</em> Student in Mathematical <unclear><reg orig="Pysick">Physic</reg></unclear>, who cureth the Tysick and Cough of the Lungs, the swelling of the Spleen, and <unclear>deafness</unclear> of the ears, pestilent <reg orig="Feavers">Fevers</reg>, and all sorts of Agues, of which cure he never failed; with other diseases incident to men.</i></p>
<p><i>Also, he cureth perfectly all diseases peculiar to women, or their <reg orig="Sexe">Sex</reg>, be they either <reg orig="Chronical">Chronic</reg> or Acute; and hath cured many that have been thought to be past cure. If you <reg orig="inquire">enquire</reg> at the white Lyon in <reg orig="White-chappel">Whitechapel</reg>; or at the Angel in Cornhil <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Royal Exchange, they will direct you to him.</i></p>
<p><i>There is lately extant, The History of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628. until the year, 1652. Printed for <em>Nathaniel Brook</em>, and are to be sold at his shop at the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> of the <em>Angel</em> in <em>Cornhil</em>.</i></p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3"><i>Thursday February 23.</i></head>
<p>Captain <unclear>Foster</unclear>, and Captain <unclear>Pack</unclear>, Commanders of the <reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg> and Amity <unclear><reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, on the</unclear> 12 of Febr. fell amongst the Dutch Fishermen, and after a sharp conflict between them and their Convoys, took two Men of War that guarded them, and forced the Fishermen to draw up their nets, and leave their labour. We lost but one man, but the Dutch very many, and their ships so pitifully shattered, that nothing belonging will be of use except it be for firing, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> it be their Guns and Cables.</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> (with divers other well experienced Commanders) is <unclear>dispatched for Ireland</unclear>, with Recruits for filling up of the Regiments, and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> that Nation.</p>
<p>The French Letters <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the Duke de Longueville, is by his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> order arrived in Paris, and hath left his command in Normandy to be present at the Prince of Conde's Process. There is no doubt nor scruple made there of the agreement between the Commonwealth of England and the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces; and this Court would fain find some way to be comprehended in the Articles of Peace, and to that end his Majesty of France is sending over <unclear>Mons.</unclear> Nieuville <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> to the Lord Protector, to intimate unto his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, the desires of the French King, and the Peers of France, to enter into amity with the Commonwealth of England. The 15 instant old <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, the Prince of Conti was espoused to <unclear>Cardinal Mazarine's</unclear> Niece, which was celebrated with extraordinary Ceremony, <em>viz.</em> Balls, Masking, Prays, and the like Courtlike Pastimes. The Cardinal hath bestowed <unclear>upon them</unclear> one hundred thousand Escu's down, and the next year hath promised as much more. The Ambition of the Court <unclear>Ningles</unclear> is now to study who shall first win the favour of the Prince to feast with them, and then strive one to exceed the other to their own <reg orig="tuine">tune</reg> which hath constantly been the course of Flatterers, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to Princes, but their <reg orig="Favorites">Favourites</reg>. And to crown the <reg orig="Courtiers">Courtiers'</reg> <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg>, news was brought on the 17 instant, that <unclear>Beffort</unclear> was taken by the Marshal de Seneterre. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart with his Train are leaving of this place to try their fortunes in some other Countries. And Monsieur <unclear>Duresteste</unclear>, one of the chiefest Authors of the tumults of the City of <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, was <reg orig="crackt">cracked</reg> and broken upon the Wheel at <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>; and his head to be set upon a stake, and this Sentence written underneath;</p>
<p><i>An Example to all those who will imitate such a <reg orig="Traytor">Traitor</reg> in Rebellion.</i></p>
<p>The Hollanders are troubled, because the Lord Beverning hath not procured a Cessation of Arms; and some reason they have for it; For the last week we took nine ships laden with Wines near Ostend, and four going to <reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesbrough</reg> with Spice: Upon the hearing of which, the States ordered, That all the shipping that they could make, should be ready against the beginning of the next March.</p>
<hr />
<p><i><unclear><!-- approx. 3 words --> and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg></unclear> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>