<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton167">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scout, Issue 167</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Faithful</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>
<head level="3">COMMUNICATING,</head>

<p><i>A <em>Declaration</em> of his <em>Excellency</em> the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em> in <em>Ireland</em>, concerning his <em>Highness the Lord Protector</em>, and the present Government in England, with the <em>Remonstrance</em> and <em>Protestation</em> of <em>Mr. Wil: Lenthal</em> (Speaker of the late Parl.) and divers other Gentlemen at <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em> thereupon. The Discovery of a wicked Plot at <em>Windsor Castle</em> and the Sentence denounced against the betrayers of their trust. The Declaration, Papers and Commissions, intercepted and taken, <em>sent from the King of Scots</em>. The advancing of his brother Duke <em>James</em>, with an Army towards <em>Flanders</em>, and a Message sent from Prince <em>Leopold William</em> by the grace of God, <em><reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> of Austria</em>, and <em>Capt. Gen. Of the Low Countries</em>, to the <em>Lord Protector</em> on Wednesday last, a<em>nd his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> Order to the Lord Mayor of London</em>. With the coming up of the <em>Dutch Ambassadors</em> from <em>Gravesend</em> this present Friday, and the new Orders concerning <reg orig="Taylors">Tailors</reg>, Weavers, <reg orig="Shoomakers">Shoemakers</reg>, and Butchers, and divers other Trades both in City and Suburbs.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em>, Feb. 24. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em>, March 3.</p>
<hr />

<p>LONDON, Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1654.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday, Feb. 24.</i></head>

<p>The first thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view, is, a bloody Tragedy from sundry parts of the Nation; the Scene is Murder; but the Actors are called by the Name of Hectors, <em>alias</em> <reg orig="Highway men">Highwaymen</reg>; who have committed several notorious Robberies, and have <reg orig="dy'd">dyed</reg> the Earth with English blood; <reg orig="especiall">especially</reg> on Salisbury Plain, as appeareth by the sad and <reg orig="woful">woeful</reg> Story in the ensuing pages: Alas! this is not all; for in these our <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, we have the old Proverb verified, <i>That Beggars ride on horseback and Gentlemen go a foot</i>: More's the pity: But care is taken to prevent these <reg orig="insolencies">insolences</reg> for the future: so that I hope it will prove a brave World when every man <reg orig="enjoyes">enjoys</reg> their own.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>Whereas the great point of <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> and concernment to be safety and benefit of a Commonwealth, is the Electing and disposing of its own Magistrates, or the great Officers of State. And as for the <em>present Council</em>, and the election of them in the way it hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg>: It must be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg>, that we were in the beginning of a new Government, necessitated to create a little World out of a Chaos, and bring Form out of Confusion; so that there was an absolute necessity, that some who are known to be persons of integrity, and firm for the present Settlement, should at the same instant be taken in, to carry on the work: which can be no ground of just exception, especially seeing for the future, Elections shall run in the appointed channel, where their <reg orig="streames">streams</reg> are to flow from the People, and their original-Fountain. Yea, the high Office of Protectorship <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> is to be derived also from hence; and as in time it will appear, that the People in Parliament have the main choice of the Council, so they will likewise be <reg orig="Chusers">Choosers</reg> of the Lord Protector: For, it being left to the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> Him, and they hereafter coming to be chosen and trusted by the <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, it cannot otherwise be conceived, but that the Choice of Him takes its rise mediately from the People in <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>: because as whatsoever a <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> doth, is said and taken in a political sense to be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> act, because they are chosen and trusted by the people: so in like manner, and upon the same political account, when the Council comes to be chosen by <reg orig="Parlaments">Parliaments</reg>, as is before expressed, then the Act of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, must by a parity of Reason be reputed the Act of the people in <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>: And so you see, in effect, mediately or immediately, the election of all <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> (both high and low) are, or will at length, by this Constitution of Government, be in the hands of the People. Lastly, as to what concerns the Office of <em>Lord Protector</em>, it is to be observed, that he is not to be admitted to that dignity upon the Interest of Himself or Family, but <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> upon the account of his fitness for Government: it must pass, not by Inheritance, but Election. And certainly, it is a great advantage to a Nation, that the coming in and continuance of their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> depends only upon his own goodness, and the good will of the People, as it is in an <em>Elective Prince</em>, who standing upon terms of good <reg orig="behavior">behaviour</reg>, will be continually employed for the benefit and defence of the Community. And therefore if it shall please the Lord to bless this Commonwealth (as we trust he will) successively, with a choice of godly persons into that high Office, it is easily foreseen, what an advantage it will be to these 3. Nations, to have their whole strength and force combined thus under one head, for the safety of all: this Form being (without question) the fittest and most convenient for the Magistrate to put things in and in quick execution (as his proper work) for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good: as also what a comfort it will be to all the godly in the <em>Protestant Churches</em> abroad, who may have some more<pb n="2" /> sure and certain protection from <em>England</em> than heretofore, which as it is the greatest Body, being united with <em>Scotland</em>, so it will prove (we hope) the grand Bulwark of the <em>Reformed Religion</em>. Moreover, as touching the Person, whom the Lord hath now advanced and set over us to be out <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Magistrate, We shall not say much, because he seeks not the praise of men: only we believe even the enemies will confess, that he is every way worthy to Rule, whom God hath been pleased to use as his Instrument in that glorious Work of Redeeming the Liberties of his people: For, we are bold to say (weighing all circumstances together) that this Nation was never really Free, nor in any way of enjoying its Freedom so fully as now: so that there wants nothing but a cordial Close with the Government, to destroy all hopes of the common Enemy, and <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> our happiness. But if men shall yet proceed to lengthen their own <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg>, by hankering after that Family which God hath cast out before us, or by an unnatural seeking to <reg orig="imbroil">embroil</reg> their Country again in blood and misery, for the sake of that unfortunate Interest, as we are <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to suspect such a thing, and can hardly imagine that any should be so forlorn and desperate after so fair a Composure.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday Feb. 25.</i></head>

<p>The King of Scots is recovered of his late sickness; and his brother <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> is as merry as a Prince; but many of the Royal party goes with empty pockets (sometimes) as well as the Intelligencer: Alas poor <reg orig="Soules">Souls</reg> ! 'tis the chance of War: Therefore, patience in adversity, is a jewel worthy of acceptation in the deplorable <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Necessity. The little Queen is <reg orig="fill'd">filled</reg> with abundance of private and solid meditations; add on <reg orig="Ashwednesday">Ash Wednesday</reg> last she took her Ashes from the hands of Mr. Philips, who was sometimes her Confessor in England. Well! seeing it is so, I shall wind up all in this infallible <reg orig="Bottome">Bottom</reg>, <i><reg orig="Every one">Everyone</reg> <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> their Beginning; but no man <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> his ending.</i></p>

<p>His Excellency the Lord Whitlock having <reg orig="recceived">received</reg> plenipotentiary power to treat with her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, hath had several times audience, and upon insisting of all the Articles in general, there appeared nothing so difficult, which did not find an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> interpretation. And it is supposed after Time hath ripened the Debates, we shall receive an Answer by messengers, with glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> and Olive Branches: For the change of the Government in England, being arrived at the Swedish Court, her Majesty hath declared a great willingness to receive the new Credentials; so great an affection doth this bright star of Europe bear to his Highness the Lord Protector, that (if our Intelligence hath received the truth) she hath desired to<pb n="3" /> see his Picture, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> the picture of the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>, the Spark and glory of these Times.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding, the Letters from Swedeland to Holland do affirm, that our Ambassador having had several Audiences, and his <reg orig="perswading">persuading</reg> the Queen to an Amity; that her Majesty hath <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> very little inclination thereunto, and hath commanded her subjects to give her a List of all the losses sustained by the English. <i>'Tis something strange: therefore pick English out of the precedent passage.</i></p>

<p>The Ambassadors from the States of Holland are landed, with full power to conclude a peace. They are expected this day at <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, with all their gallant Retinue, consisting of one hundred in number, most excellently equipped; and divers eminent Gentlemen, and Officers are appointed to congratulate them from Gravesend to Westminster with the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Barges, and others, there being high and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> preparations at Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg> house in the Palace yard.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Feb. 27</i></head>

<p>Our <em>Scout</em> from Scotland advertiseth, that the English forces have fallen upon the Highlanders, and after an <reg orig="irresistable">irresistible</reg> and furious Onset, took above 120 Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, great store of Arms, Ammunition, Horses with plenty of provision, and afterwards blew up the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Dunkel. Col. Morgan hath also removed the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Kildrumny, and at Cromar put 120 to the sword, took 27 prisoners, 80 horse, &amp; all their Bag and Baggage.</p>

<p>The two Ambassadors from Holland, the L. Newport, and the L. Yongstal, that are come to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the L. Beverling, are now at Gravesend, and <reg orig="Rir">Sir</reg> Oliver Fleming, Master of the Ceremonies hath orders to receive them on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, March 3. at which time they are to come from Gravesend to Tower hill; and from thence, Coaches will be appointed to bring them and their attendants through the Cities of London and Westminster, to Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg> house in the Palace-yard which is trimmed up for their reception.</p>

<p>Mr. Wil. Lenthal, formerly Speaker of the Parl. and divers other Gentlemen, have sent a congratulatory Declaration from the City of <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, to his Highness the Lord Protector, blessing the Lord for this established Government and protesting much affection thereto.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Feb. 28.</i></head>

<p>Presents us with an Abstract of Scotland, intimating, That the E. of Athol hath drawn most of his forces together from Weems, and other places, and he with L. Bruce were the 14 at Glenshier, marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with Glencarn, Glengary, Kenmore, and the rest of the Royal party: Upon their conjunction, they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be at the least 4000. and then they intend to be revenged upon the English, if they can: but <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> foot are much discontented at the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their horse, and the English that came with Col. Wogan out of <reg orig="Francs">France</reg>, are much dejected at the death of their valiant Colonel. Col. Lilburn is sending Recruits to Col. Morgan; but somewhat inconsiderable, until such time that the new supplies are gone from England. The Scots are very high at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and <reg orig="breath">breathe</reg> forth Victories <reg orig="in stead">instead</reg> of Defeats, giving out, that the late blow given by Col. Morgan was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to some few <reg orig="Countreo men">Countrymen</reg>, when that it is evident, that G. Glencarn was there in person, and the valiant young Laird of Loughaber, who was one of the first that ran out of the field, and left his Commission from their King, signed C.R. behind him, together with the last Instructions of Lieu. Gen. Middleton, 5 Letters from C. the 2. to the Commander in chief of the Highlanders: All which Papers are to be sent up to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>There hath been lately some meetings of godly Ministers about London, to consider of a way of union and reconciliation of the differences that unhappily have crept in among the godly, and other excellent things in order to the progress of the Gospel. And this day Mr. Owen, Mr. Tho. Goodwin, M. Sydrack <reg orig="Simson">Simpson</reg>, Mr. Nie, and divers other reverend pious Ministers were with his Highness.</p>

<p>From Ireland our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, that the L. Deputy Fleetwood, and the Officers of the Army, have caused to be printed at Dublin their Declaration, to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with his Highness in the present change of Government: but indeed at first many there were that scrupled it; yet upon consideration they unanimously assented thereunto.</p>

<p>From Newcastle they write, that cap. <em>Wetang</em> hath scoured those coasts of the <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg>, and that he hath sunk and taken some. But alas! this doth not equalize our loss in the West, for true it is that the Brest men of war have taken the George of Bristol, being richly laden with Indigo, Sugar, and Tobacco.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 1.</i></head>

<p>The 27 of February last proved a fatal day to many; for, beside the Woman that burnt her child, 8 more having received Sentence of death were executed; amongst the rest, four of them were <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> at the lower end of <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet street</reg>, over against the Dog Tavern where they committed the Fact having not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="rob'd">robbed</reg> M. <em>Hancock</em> (Master of the said house, of great store of Plate; but likewise cut and wounded him in several places; for which, Mr. James Harrington (a <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg> of Middlesex) and the <reg orig="Meal-mans">Mealman's</reg> wife of Brainford, who served the said Mr. Hancock with meal, and knew the Orders of the house, and where the Plate lay, suffered the bitter pangs of death; a just reward for the Woman, but a pitiful Object to behold the man: for she was not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the grand <reg orig="Settor">Setter</reg>, and chief contriver of the Design, in drawing in of poor Mr. Harrington; but likewise the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> betrayer and Decoy of her Noble Hectors, who she so termed; as appears by the Speech and Confession of the said James Harrington under the Gallows, who spake to the people as followeth:</p>

<p><i>Gentlemen, and Christian friends</i>, You are this day come hither to behold a sad and pitiful Object, and a man to be taken off in the midst of his years: Nevertheless, although Providence hath decreed me such an untimely end, yet I doubt not, but that this ignominious and reproachful death, will to me prove a glorious and perpetual change; and I bless God I have a Conscience within speaks peace to my poor soul, fully assuring me, that this day shall I be in <reg orig="Paradice">Paradise</reg> with my blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; and that though my sins be as red as scarlet, yet <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> they be made as white as snow; for confident I am, I never was guilty of <reg orig="anyones">anyone's</reg> death, neither had I ever brought <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> to this untimely end, had it not <reg orig="bin">been</reg> for this woman (meaning the <reg orig="Meal-mans">Mealman's</reg> wife) <em><reg orig="Ioan">Joan</reg> West</em>, but God forgive her; for I do: And I bless God I am in peace with all men: Though many there are that calumn and brand me, that I have been an idle liver, and that I have committed several Facts and Crimes: I confess I have been a sinner, and a great company keeper, yet never <reg orig="wrongd">wronged</reg> any man whom I had society <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>: No, I appeal to the great <em>God</em> of Heaven whether I have or no: And though my cause be now thus unhappily <reg orig="ballanced">balanced</reg>, that the ignominious <reg orig="Skale">Scale</reg> of hard and cruel Destiny must even now be turned upon me; yet the penetracy of<pb n="6" /> my poor Soul hath taken away the bitter sting of Death; and there is not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> troubles me at this very instant (though I am here now ready to pass through the Vale of Death) but my poor wife, &amp; six languishing babes, whom I desire the Lord to bless, and to preserve keep and defend them with his glorious Guard of Angels, that so they may be shrouded under the Omnipotent Curtain of Providence, from the wicked Temptations of <reg orig="Sathan">Satan</reg> and his Instruments. Which that you may all do, is the desire of him, who implores the prayers of you, for the finishing of his last and final Work: And the blessed Spirit of the great God be amongst you all; to whom be all honour peace, and thanksgiving both now and for evermore, <em>Amen</em>. And so Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, sweet <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, receive my soul.</p>

<p>Having ended his speech, the Minister delivered an Exhortation to them all; and then <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> proceeded the execution, where the said Mr. <em><reg orig="Iames Harrington">James Harrington</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Ioan">Joan</reg> West</em>, hung from about eleven of the clock, till 4 in the afternoon at the one end of the <reg orig="Gallowes">Gallows</reg> next to the Tavern; and Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Sharp</em>, and Mr. <em>Robert Cadnor</em> at the other end. <i>A sad and <reg orig="woful">woeful</reg> Object to behold!</i></p>

<p>From the West our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, that there hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> a most barbarous and bloody Murder committed on Salisbury Plain, the manner thus: 8 or 9 Graziers being riding over the Plain, and having about 1500 pounds amongst them in their Port-mantles, they were set upon by about 18 or 20 Thieves, who demanded their monies, but being denied it, they fell <reg orig="pell-mel">pell-mell</reg> upon the Graziers, put every man to the sword, as they thought, with the loss of 5 of their own Hectors: yet is so pleased divine Providence, that one of the Graziers being not quite deprived of his Senses, heard what Inn they resolved to make to, and a company of Butchers coming by the next morning, fixing their eyes upon this sad and lamentable Object, rode up to them, which the Grazier perceiving, expressed himself, related the manner, and told em, they were gone to such an Inn at a Village <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Salisbury: Whereupon they left two to convey the said Grazier to a house, and the rest went, raised the tow, and beset the Inn where the Thieves were; but the <reg orig="high-way men">highwaymen</reg> opposed so far, that the True-men were constrained to fire the house and to batter and pull it down over their ears; so that some perished and consumed in the Dust and Flames: the rest were taken and <reg orig="commited">committed</reg> to Salisbury Gaol.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Thursday March 2.</head>

<p>From Windsor we have received intelligence, that there is a notable Plot or Conspiracy discovered, against some that should have betrayed their Trust in the castle; and one of them being taken <reg orig="imbezzelling">embezzling</reg> and carrying away the powder, was apprehended and <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> before the Governor, who received sentence to ride upon a Saker when it is shot off with an half charge. Mr <em>Feak</em>, and Mr. <em>Simpson</em>, are both there still, and in good health, blessed be God: But poor Judge Jenkins declines exceedingly.</p>

<p>Yesterday an Ambassador Extraordinary from the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> in Flanders, had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, where he did congratulate his Highness, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> him his Credentials, and presented him with a message from his master <em>Leopold William</em>, by the grace of God <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> of <em>Austria</em>, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em>, and Lieu. Gen. and Cap. Gen of the Low countries. After which he was conducted from thence by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, master of the Ceremonies. The said <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> hath set forth two Declarations against that famous old Thief <em>Charles</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, who hath filled a great part of Christendom with his rapines and cruelties, and now lies close prisoner at Antwerp; for the K. of Spain is resolved to set up <em>Francis</em> the younger brother in the elder <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> place, and that the said L. Duke <em>Francis</em> shall undertake the sole command of the Army, with all the <reg orig="Ensignes">Ensigns</reg> and Banners thereunto belonging.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> we have received advertisements, that Card. <em>Mazarine</em> has reduced both King, Princes, and that Gen. <em>Tureae</em> and the Duke of <em>York</em>, are preparing to take the field against the Spanish forces.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor of the city of London, and the Recorder of the said city, on the party of the city of London; and divers Magistrates of the city of Westminster, according to an Order sent to them came to attend his Highness and the Council, at the Council chamber in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>; and yesterday they were heard touching the business for a Corporation to be granted to the city of Westminster, and something <unclear>therein</unclear> it is probable will shortly be done. Several new Orders are drawing up by sundry eminent persons within the city for the regulating of abuses <unclear>in Trade</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> <unclear><reg orig="Shoomakers">Shoemakers</reg></unclear>, Silk-weavers, Tailors, Butchers, Carpenters, <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> for the suppressing of foreigners.</p>

<hr />

<p>Appointed to be printed; And extracted out of the original Papers, licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>