<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="FScoutHorton129">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Faithful Scout (printed by George Horton), Issue 129</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE FAITHFUL</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="SCOVT">SCOUT</reg>,</head>

<head level="3">Truly Representing,</head>

<p><i>The Declaration and Answer of her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden to the Speech of his Excellency the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, in the name and behalf of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England; and Her Propositions touching the peace and Government thereof. The new Desires and Proposals of the States of Holland, and their Message sent by the Lord Beverling to his Highness the Lord Protector, for a cessation of Arms. A Declaration thereupon; and a new Proclamation concerning the Scots King. The examination of Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Simpson</em>, at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, upon the Ordinance for high Treason, and their Declaration upon the committing of them to Windsor Castle. The revolting of divers of the Maj Gen. <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> Regiment in Scotland, and <unclear>big</unclear> Chaplain and others upon their march into England. The new Order to be published throughout all the Northern Counties, and the besieging of <em>Bury</em> <reg orig="Garisson">Garrison</reg> by the Highlanders.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Jan. 27. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> Feb. 3.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON. Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<p>The English fleet remain still about <em>Stoke</em> Bay in their old station; and divers of our Canary ships are come into Falmouth after long expectation; The Wetang and the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> have brought in 2 prizes to Newcastle, some Ordnance, and 100 prisoners: But the Brest men of war do much annoy us, and have taken some ships and Mariners. The Fairfax and the Swiftsure, with many others, are going to <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> the Coast of <reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg>.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Mr <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Goodwins">Goodwin's</reg> Queries</i></head>

<p>First may it not be queried, whether such persons, whether Ministers of the Gospel, or others, who <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> undertake or pretend to know, and predict unto people how long the present Government <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, and after how many months, or years, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> presently be dissolved and fall, do not impose a kind of wretched necessity upon themselves, to turn every stone for the raising of Tumults and Insurrections in the Land, and to enrage the people against the present Government and <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, thus to make a covering for their own shame, and to prevent the dishonour and reproach of <reg orig="fals">false</reg> Prophets from lighting upon their heads? Or did not the Wizard in France, having engaged the reputation of his Art in foretelling the death of Duke <em>Beron</em> by a <em>Bungurdian</em> on a certain day, and finding no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg>, the day now approaching, of the event otherwise, resolved to make himself a true Prophet by doing the execution himself, and accordingly <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> him? 2. Again, are not these passages ensuing (published in print and subscribed by Mr. <em>Simpson</em>, Mr. <em>Feak</em>, Mr. <em>Brooks</em>, M. <em><reg orig="Greenhil">Greenhill</reg></em>, M. <em>Knollys</em>, M. <em>Jesse</em>, M. <em>Woollaston</em>, M. <em>Harrison</em>, with several others, about two years since) worthy to be engraven in letters of Gold: If C&aelig;sar and Pagan Rulers under him Judea, and elsewhere, were to be honoured and submitted unto, as both Christ taught, and his Apostles; and yet they came in by the Sword, and kept <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Church in bondage, how much more should our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> be honoured by all people in our Nation? The same Authors soon after express themselves thus: In our days, wherein persons truly fearing God are of divers forms, dissenting in Church Government, &amp;c. some that are termed Presbyterians some Independents, some Anabaptists, and some that are not resolved with any of these; the power of <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> Rulers, or of being chosen, should not be limited to any of these forms or <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg>, to the excluding of others, excepting such who either deny propriety or Magistracy, or who assert carnal liberty, or Polygamy, whom we have witnessed against; or such as have opposed, or do not own this present Government.</p>

<p>And with one consent we do declare, as in the presence of the Almighty, who is the Searcher of all hearts, before whom the wicked and <reg orig="deceitfull">deceitful</reg> shall be confounded<pb n="2" /> at the day of Judgment, That all people in every Nation, as well members of Churches, as others, ought for conscience sake to honour such, as by the wise disposing providence of God, are their present Rulers, and are to submit to the civil commands, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of such Rulers as are faithful, but even to Infidels. If so, must not such men of necessity be <reg orig="fals">false</reg> Prophets, casting snares upon the people, and leading them out of the ways of truth and peace who are so far from honouring their present Governors (though no Infidels, nor keepers of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Church in bondage, but most zealous and faithful assertors of the entire liberties hereof) that with <reg orig="openmouth">open mouth</reg> they pour contempt upon them day after day.</p>

<p>Thirdly, Whether a <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> conscience bearing him witness the Holy Ghost, that his heart is upright with God, and that he unfeignedely purposeth, and desires to do all the good upon earth, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he abideth amongst men, which God <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> any <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> enable him unto; ought not such a person, even in conscience towards God, and out of love and geniusness of <reg orig="affectiun">affection</reg> to his generation, embrace and accept of all such opportunities and advantages of standing, for the promotion of his Work, which God <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> by any providence of his offer unto him? Or when God called Moses up to the top of the Mount, had it been meet for him to have answered, Nay; but I will serve thee faithfully beneath in the Valley? Or is it not a grand detriment or loss unto the world, when Princes, as <em>Solomon</em> speaketh, walk as servants on the earth, <em>i.e.</em> when men of noble principles, of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Spirits, whose hearts and <reg orig="foules">fouls</reg> are in travel with the wealth, peace, and prosperity of the world round about them, who are <reg orig="shap'd">shaped</reg> and <reg orig="form'd">formed</reg> as it were on purpose by God himself for Rule and Government, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> want a stage whereunto act like Princes, or be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> to enjoy themselves in privacy and retirement: Or in case the Sun should be <reg orig="over ruled">overruled</reg> to change place with the Moon, should not the world have cause in abundance to lament the change? Or had his Tabernacle been <reg orig="pitch'd">pitched</reg> in any inferior Orb beneath that, wherein it is now placed by God, could the earth have <reg orig="rejoyced">rejoiced</reg> in his light at that rate which now it doth? Or if a candle should creep under a bushel, when there is a candlestick provided and set on the table for it, <reg orig="shold">should</reg> not they in the house have much more reason to be offended at it, <reg orig="then">than</reg> well pleased?</p>

<head level="3">Saturday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 28.</head>

<p>From the North we have received intelligence, That a fleet of 80<pb n="3" /><reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of Dutch Merchants, with one man of war, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the <em>Sound</em> homeward, an English <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> <reg orig="weather-gag'd">weather-gauged</reg> them, and gave them five <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>; but <reg orig="afte">after</reg> half an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> dispute, the enemy <reg orig="tack'd">tacked</reg> about, leaving 5 or 6 as a sacrifice to the <reg orig="mercilesse">merciless</reg> waves; besides, seven of them were taken and <reg orig="caryed">carried</reg> to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have also taken 7 prizes in the West; so that the whole number, since the first riding of <em>Vantramp</em> paramount upon the Downs, amounts to 275. Yet not without some loss; for few days since the Hollander took 4 of ours, bound from Virginia and other parts.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 30.</head>

<p>The Declaration with the humble Address of the Generals, and the several Commanders in the fleet, was presented to his Highness the Lord Protector, wherein they declare their Resolution to live and die with him, in the station the Lord hath placed him, against his and the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> enemies.</p>

<p>The Citizens of <em>London</em> this day sent a message to his Highness, and <reg orig="addrest">addressed</reg> themselves by certain Aldermen; from whence, great Presents are preparing in a most rich and costly manner adorned with gold and silver.</p>

<p>The Commissioners of the Admiralty at <em>Amsterdam</em> have published a Declaration, intimating, That they conceive it not convenient that <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> in regard of the present Treaty think <reg orig="him self">himself</reg> secure, but to continue the former Hostility, until a cessation <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be proclaimed. An Order is appointed to be drawn up by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Council, for propagating the Gospel in the Northern Counties, and elsewhere. An Order likewise passed the Council, that M. <em>Feak</em>, and M. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Simpson</em> (<unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> upon the Act for Treason) should be committed prisoners to Windsor Castle. Whereupon they declared, that all powers whatsoever that were not of God, should not stand, but would suddenly be destroyed; A true <reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg> indeed; but little reason have they to infer any such thing upon our present Government which is the only Anvil of Christendom whereon all Antichristian Powers must be <reg orig="dash'd">dashed</reg> in pieces upon.</p>

<head level="3">Tuesday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 31.</head>

<p>By and Express from <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg> in France, it is certified, that Gen. <em>Brian</em> has gotten a body of 4000 foot and 1000 horse, and is fortifying the Castle of <em>Dingle</em> in <em>Ireland</em>. This proceeds from the Royal party, from whence we have likewise news, that Gen. <em>Glencarn</em> in Scotland,<pb n="4" /> has set forth a very high Proclamation against the English, resolving confiscation upon those that shall <reg orig="any ways">anyways</reg> assist them. They have <reg orig="beleagured">beleaguered</reg> <em>Burgy</em>, a garrison of ours, and have set guards upon the River Findern, to scour the passage from <reg orig="Inuerness">Inverness</reg>. But upon the 19 of <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. Col <em>Daniel</em>, Governor of St. <reg orig="Iohnstons">Johnstone</reg>, having intelligence that the enemy were in or about Dunkel, set out 100 horse and 100 dragoons under the command of cap. Lieu. <em>Ashby</em>, who came very near the town undiscovered, and the forlorn fell in with two of their Scouts, who made some resistance at the <reg orig="Baricado">Barricade</reg>; but our Dragoons charging up to their Breast-works, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> <reg orig="entred">entered</reg>, and killed 7 the Forlorn went in the mean time to the other end of the town, and pursued those that fled to the Hill, killing 7 or 8, and taking 25 prisoners, besides 50 horses, and some few Arms, with the loss of one of Col. <reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg> troop; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> capt. <reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg> Lieu. and cap. <reg orig="Ker">Kerr</reg> killed each other, both of them firing at one instant at more than 4 yards distance, with their <reg orig="Blunderbushes">Blunderbusses</reg>, and fell both from their horses at one time. A Lieu. of Gen. <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> Regiment, and some other Officers were taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Falkirk, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> Dens. And the Shallop built to secure trade in the River Clyde, is also <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by Col. <em>Harriet</em> and some Boats from the Loughs. Divers of Major General <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Regiment, together with the Chaplain, have deserted, and are coming for England. But the rest of the Regiments do well approve of the new Government in England.</p>

<p>From Holland it is certified, That the States of that Province have presented their Resolves to the States General, upon the Articles of Peace, which were approved of and the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Deputies had <reg orig="thankes">thanks</reg> returned them for their good services done in England, in behalf of their Country. The Assembly of the States of Holland and <reg orig="West-friezland">West Friezland</reg> are to be dissolved till the 20 of this instant Feb. And the Lord Beverling is returned for England to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to procure a cessation of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, till the other Provinces shall have time to bring in their Ratification to the Lords States General, and then a solemn Embassage to be sent to the Lord Protector, by the Lord Gen. <em>Brederode</em> to the Land forces, and the Lord <em>Updam</em> Admiral of the Navy, as is thought, to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the peace. We hear, that the States are gone from Zealand to the Hague, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in confirmation of the Peace; and that the Pope has sent to all the German Princes, &amp; others, to unite and comply against them.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3">Wednesday: Feb. 1.</head>

<p>The next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view, is, the Transcript of a Wormwood Lecture, from a Woman to her husband <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Billingsgate, upon the finding of him in company with another <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> wife; and thus he begins. Ha, ha, have I found you together <reg orig="ifaith">i' faith</reg>? <reg orig="heres">here's</reg> a goodly sight I promise you a knave and a quean together; is it possible goodman Rascal, that you should give me the slip so neatly, and sneak hither to your <reg orig="Trul">Trull</reg>? But I am glad that now at the last my good fortune has bought us together, <reg orig="we'l">we'll</reg> have a bout on't before we part: thou impudent Whore how darest thou keep company with my husband? What business have you together, none <reg orig="thats">that's</reg> honest I doubt, come out to me thou brazen faced lade, or <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> send the pot to thee with a wanion; let me come to her thou Rascal, or else give me the pot wont you ye rogue you wont you? By the mass <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> have my will if it cost my life; O you villain, such <reg orig="boldfac'd">boldfaced</reg> <reg orig="huswives">housewives</reg> as this makes me live such a life at home as I do: <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> be <reg orig="reveng'd">revenged</reg> on you both before <em>George</em>, or <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> want of my will, let me come to her thou slave, or <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> do that which I never thought of before: if thou wilt protect thy Minion from my fury, thou shall taste of it <reg orig="thy self">thyself</reg>. What, shall the proud Harlot thinkest thou <reg orig="out-brave">outbrave</reg> me to my face? 'tis best for you to let me have my <reg orig="peny worths">penny's worth</reg> of her, for by this light <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> give her a mark that thou shalt know her by another time, lest perhaps thou mayst forget her, <reg orig="ifaith">I' faith</reg>  Mrs. <em>Mink</em> it was a good deed to slit your nose, and spoil that tempting face of yours. Why dost <reg orig="noe">no</reg> thou let me come to her thou white <reg orig="liver'd">livered</reg> knave? prevent not my spleen upon her, lest thou urge it against <reg orig="thy self">thyself</reg>. But upon his importuning her, at last she was contented to bury all in a pot of ale and so the strife ended.</p>

<p>In me last I made mention of the Lord Ambassador <reg orig="Whitlockes">Whitlock's</reg> Speech to the Queen of Sweden, I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> now in this place you <reg orig="a Breviate">abbreviate</reg> thereof, to wit, His Excellency declared, That although the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England are not encouraged to send abroad, when they reflect upon the barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places, yea in her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Government they have not the <reg orig="lest">least</reg> <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>, but gracefully acknowledged their experience to the contrary. From thence he proceeded to the deliverance of the Armies of the Commonwealth, which have been wonderful; and touched upon<pb n="6" /> the excellencies of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> person and Government, making a comparison between her and Q. <em>Eliz</em>. He then made mention of the wars of her father for the true Protestant Religion and just liberties, which were also the occasions of the wars of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, in which God was pleased to determine for the Parl. He then made a similitude between the Nations of England and Sweden in Dispositions and language, and of the great desire to enter into a strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg>, for the renewing of former amity, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Simpson</em> have been examined before the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who denying to own the present power, stand both committed. But Mr. <em>Powel</em> has left the City: yet a little before he went, he declared at <reg orig="Christ church">Christchurch</reg>, and at <reg orig="Black fryers">Blackfriars</reg>, That may reigned now as Kings, without the <reg orig="advise">advice</reg> of the Saints, but the Lord would bring them down again; and that this power was not of God, and would shortly be destroyed: To prove it, he wrestled many sacred places of Scripture, <reg orig="sayes">says</reg> the Penman of the Hue-and-cry, upon his Anvil to frame his Engine to level Magistracy; O 'tis dangerous judging! I shall therefore insist no longer upon that particular; but present you with the said M. <em><reg orig="Powels">Powel's</reg></em> Hymn at <reg orig="Christ-church">Christchurch</reg> on the 18 day of Decemb. with an Antiphona thereunto.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Hymn</i></head>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>To Christ our King, let us <reg orig="prais">praise</reg> sing,</line>
<line>who is our Saviour dear,</line>
<line>Who is our Protector, and our Rock,</line>
<line>who will come and soon appear</line>
<line>To humble his and try their hearts,</line>
<line>and make them clean and pure,</line>
<line>To set his Kingdom upon Earth,</line>
<line>which ever <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="indure">endure</reg>:</line>
<line>His Saints <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> reign with him on earth,</line>
<line>and great ones they shall bow,</line>
<line>The Battle and the <reg orig="Battle-ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>and men of war shall know</line>
<line>That he will arise, and he will rule,</line>
<line>and their power will fall,</line>
<line>And Christ our great Commander, He</line>
<line>shall be our General</line>
<line><reg orig="Hast">Haste</reg> Lord, come quickly <reg orig="dowd">down</reg>,</line>
<line>thy Saints do wait and pray,</line><pb n="7" />
<line>And men would fain, if they knew how</line>
<line>thy Prophets kill and slay:</line>
<line>But they shall live, and eke stand up,</line>
<line>and give their Testimony</line>
<line>Against the Monarchs of the Earth,</line>
<line>that sit and reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<!-- The following "Antiphon" actually begins on the previous page of the newsbook, that is before the "pb 7" page break. It is written in a column along side the "Hymn" above and also carries on across the page break -->

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Antiphone">Antiphon</reg> </i></head>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>The <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> your king, his praise you</line>
<line>his Spirit leads you here</line>
<line>Who is your Protector, and your Rock,</line>
<line>and in you doth appear.</line>
<line>'Tis he exalts, and lifts your hearts,</line>
<line>to make you his most sure,</line>
<line>To set his Kingdom upon earth,</line>
<line>which shall not long <reg orig="indure">endure</reg>:</line>
<line>His Saints shall reign with him in Hell</line>
<line>and to him they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> bow,</line>
<line>The Battle, and the <reg orig="Battle-ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>and men of war do know,</line>
<line>Though he be up, and his doth rule,</line>
<line>yet his power will fall,</line>
<line>since <reg orig="Sathan">Satan</reg> your good Master, He is your General.</line>
<line>The Lord will come in his due time,</line>
<line>his Saints for to preserve,</line><!-- here corresponds to the place of the page break -->
<line>And all your lying Prophets slay,</line>
<line>who from his Word do swerve.</line>
<line>His Word <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, his Saints <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> live</line>
<line>to give their Testimony</line>
<line>Against false teachers of the Earth,</line>
<line>who strive to reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3">Thursday Feb. 2.</head>

<p>Having in the precedent pages presented you with the Speech if the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, I shall in the next place communicate her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Declaration and Answer to his Excellency: the true Copy whereof take as followeth.</p>

<p>That her Majesty esteemed it a very great honour that the Parliament had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> pleased to send an Ambassador to Her, especially a person of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> condition, and that she <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> would take care during his abode there, that not the least injury should be offered either to him or to his company; and that she hoped in her Government there should be no cause or doubt of the contrary; that as his person was very acceptable to her, so was the business which he had imparted; in the transaction whereof she should manifest the affection she bore to the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and her desire not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to renew former <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between them but to enter into a nearer union <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore, that she was glad of these blessings which the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> had received in their peace and settlement, and <reg orig="wisht">wished</reg> the continuance thereof to them. She thanked his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg> for his civilities to her &amp; for his acceptance of such entertainment as that place <reg orig="wold">would</reg> afford, and that she was <reg orig="sory">sorry</reg> it was not answerable to his quality and to the respect whom she bore to the Commonwealth whom he served, but desired him to take it in good part, for that he was very welcome to her Court. After she had done, his Excellency spake to her Majesty in French. That there were two of his Sons and other Gentlemen in his company, that much desired the honour of kissing her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> hand, if she pleased to permit it which she readily did to those which his Excellency appointed, which were 18. After that Ceremony passed, the Qu. spake to his Excellency in French desiring him to excuse the ill treatment by the way in his journey: but his Excellency returned thanks for the many favours received. She then excused her habit (being only in a plain grey Stuff made after this manner, a Coat down to the ground, and over that a close Jacket that came almost to her knees, buttoned down with great buttons, with a black Scarf about her neck <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> with a little black <reg orig="Ribbond">Ribbon</reg>.] saying she had been ill, which caused her to put <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> into the dress of her chamber, in which she chose to appear thus <reg orig="publiquely">publicly</reg>, rather than to disappoint his Excellency of audience; and that she hoped they should have time and opportunity enough to discourse together. His Excellency then took his leave of her Maj. but since has had private audience with the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> for three hours together.</p>

<hr />

<p>Appointed to be printed; and extracted out of the original Papers, licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>