<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="LIntell73">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Loyal Intelligencer, Issue 73</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Loyal Intelligencer:</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<head level="3">The Proceedings of his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>; the Transactions of Affairs from the States of Holland; the Designs now on foot in France, Denmark, Sweden, and Scotland; and other remarkable Occurrences from the K. of Scots, the Lord Craven, and Major Gen. Massey.</head>

<head level="3">Further comprising,</head>

<p><i>The Declaration of the Dutch Admirals at sea, published by sound of Trumpet aboard the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, and the Resolution of the Zealanders to dispute the quarrel against England by force of Arms: the setting forth another great Fleet by the Hollanders; and the routing, <reg orig="dispiercing">dispersing</reg>, and taking of fourscore <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of Merchants. The Declaration of the Officers and <reg orig="sea-men">seamen</reg> under the command of Gen. <em>Blake</em>, &amp; their Protestation touching the Lord Protector, and the present Government. The Proposals of Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Goodwin</em> thereupon, to be published throughout all Counties in England and Wales. Together with terrible and bloody <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from Scotland, and sad and lamentable News from <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan 23. to Monday <reg orig="Ian.">Jan.</reg> 30. 1653.</head>
<hr />

<p>The Scots grow numerous in the Highlands, and play REX upon the Lowlands; we have lately sustained some loss by them, but colonel Morgan has again paid them in their own <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg>, and taken some eminent prisoners; yet few of them worth 20 s. sterling: valiant captain <reg orig="Woogan">Wogan</reg> is said to be slain, who charged very desperately in the Van of the English.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Mr. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Goodwins">Goodwin's</reg> Queries.</i></head>

<p>First, May it not be queried, whether such persons, whether Ministers of the Gospel, or others, who <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> undertake or pretend to know, and predict unto the people how long the present Government <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, and after how many months, or years, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> presently be dissolved and fall, do not impose a kind of wretched necessity upon themselves, to turn every stone for the raising of Tumults and Insurrections in the Land, and to enrage the people against the present Government and <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, thus to make a covering for their own shame, and to prevent the dishonour and reproach of false Prophets from lighting upon their heads? Or did not the Wizard in France, having engaged the reputation of his Art in foretelling the death of Duke <unclear><em>Reren</em></unclear> by a <em><reg orig="Bungurdian">Burgundian</reg></em> on a certain day, &amp; finding no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg>, the day now approaching, of the event otherwise, resolved to make himself a true Prophet by doing the execution himself, and accordingly <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> him? 2 Again, are not these passages ensuing (published in print and subscribed by Mr.</p>

<!-- list laid out as two columns with dividing line -->

<p><i>John Simpson</i></p>
<p><i>Christopher Feak</i></p>
<p><i>William <reg orig="Greenhil">Greenhill</reg> </i></p>
<p><i>Thomas Brooks</i></p>
<p><i><unclear>Honsord Knollys</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>Thomas Harrison</i></p>
<p><i>Henry Jesse</i></p>
<p><i>Richard Wollaston.</i></p>

<p>with several others about two years since) worthy to be engraven with the point of a Diamond, and engraven in letters of Gold: If C&aelig;sar and Pagan Rulers under him Judea, and elsewhere, were to be honoured and submitted unto, as both Christ taught, and his Apostles; and yet they came in by the Sword, and kept <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Church in bondage, how much more should our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> be honoured by all people in our Nation? The same Authors soon after express themselves thus: In our days, wherein persons truly <pb n="2" />fearing God are of divers forms, dissenting in Church-Government, &amp;c. some that are termed Presbyterians, some Independents, some Anabaptists, and some that are not resolved with any of these; the power of <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> Rules, or of being chosen, should not be limited to any of these forms or <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg>, to the excluding of others, excepting such who deny propriety or Magistracy, or who assert carnal liberty, or Polygamy, whom we have witnessed against; or such as have opposed, or do not own this present Government.</p>

<p>And with one consent we do declare, as in the presence of the Almighty, who is the Searcher of all hearts, before whom the wicked and <reg orig="deceitfull">deceitful</reg> shall be confounded at the day of <reg orig="Judgment">Judgement</reg>, That all people in every Nation, as well members of Churches, as others, ought for conscience sake to honour such, as by the wise disposing providence of God, are their present Rulers, and are to submit to the civil commands, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to such Rulers as are faithful but even to Infidels.</p>

<p>If so, must not such men of necessity be <reg orig="fals">false</reg> Prophets, casting snares upon the people, and leading them out of the ways of truth and peace who are so far from honouring their present Governors (though no Infidels, nor keepers of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Church in bondage, but most zealous and faithful assertors of the entire liberties thereof) that with open mouth they pour contempt upon them day after day.</p>

<p>Thirdly, Whether a <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> conscience bearing him witness the Holy Ghost, that his heart is upright with God, and that he unfeignedly purposeth, and desires to do all the good upon earth, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he abideth upon men, which God <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> any <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> enable him unto; ought not such a person, even in conscience towards God, and out of love &amp; geniusness of <reg orig="affectiun">affection</reg> to his generation, embrace and accept of all such opportunities and advantages of standing, fro the promotion of his Work, which God <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> by any <pb n="3" />providence of his offer unto him? Or when God called Moses up to the top of the Mount, had it been meet for him to have answered, Nay; but I will serve thee faithfully beneath in the Valley? Or is it not a grand detriment or loss unto the world, when Princes, as <em>Solomon</em> speaketh, walk as servants on the earth <em>i.e.</em> when men of noble principles, of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Spirits, whose hearts and <reg orig="soules">souls</reg> are in travel with the wealth, peace, and prosperity of the world round about them, who are <reg orig="shap'd">shaped</reg> and <reg orig="form'd">formed</reg> as it were on purpose by God himself for Rule and Government, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> want a stage whereon to act like Princes, or be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> to enjoy themselves in privacy and retirement? Or in case the Sun should be <reg orig="over-ruled">overruled</reg> to change places with the Moon, should not the world have cause in abundance to lament the change? Or had his Tabernacle been <reg orig="pitch'd">pitched</reg> in any inferior Orb beneath that, wherein it is now placed by God, could the earth have <reg orig="rejoyced">rejoiced</reg> in his light a that which now it doth? Or if a candle should creep under a bushel, when there is a candlestick provided and set on the table for it, should not they in the house have much more reason to be offended at it, <reg orig="then">than</reg> well pleased?</p>

<p>From the North we have received intelligence, That a fleet of 80 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of Dutch Merchants, with one man of war, coming from the <em>Sound</em> homeward, an English <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> weather <reg orig="gag'd">gaged</reg> them, and gave them five broad sides; the Dutch answered her again; but after half an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> dispute, they <reg orig="tack'd">tacked</reg> about, leaving 5 or 6 as a sacrifice to the <reg orig="mercilesse">merciless</reg> waves; besides, seven of them were taken and <reg orig="caryed">carried</reg> to <em>Gottenburgh</em>. We have also taken 7 prizes in the West; so that the whole number, since the first riding of <em>Vantrump</em> paramount upon the Downs, amounts to 275. Yet not without some loss; for few days since the Hollander took 4 of ours, bound from Virginia and other parts.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector and his honourable Council have set forth an Ordinance, declaring, that if any person or persons shall compass or imagine the death of the Lord Protector, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <em>treason</em>.</p>

<p>Secondly, that if any person or persons shall maliciously or advisedly either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector and the people in Parliament assembled are not the <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Authority of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Common-wealth</reg>; or that the Exercise of the chief Magistracy and administration of the Government over the said Countries and Dominions, and the people thereof, is not in the Lord Protector, assisted with a Council, it shall be <em>treason</em>.</p>

<p>Thirdly, that if any person or persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> say that the present Government is tyrannical, usurped, or unlawful; or that there is nay Parliament now in being, or that have any continuance, or any Law in force for continuing the Parliament, which is declared to have been absolutely dissolved and determined upon the 20 day of April 1653. and shall be adjudged and taken so to be; or shall plot, contrive, or endeavour to stir up or raise force against the Protector or the present <reg orig="Covernment">Government</reg>, or for the subversion or alteration of the same, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> declare any such <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> or <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> by any open Deed, then every such offence shall be taken and adjudged to be <em>high treason</em>.</p>

<p>And whereas the Lord Protector and the Council, for the just &amp; lawful defence of this Commonwealth are at present necessitated, by reason of the manifold distractions within the same, and invasions <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> from abroad, so to continue armies and forces in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, which, under GOD, must be the <reg orig="intrumentall">instrumental</reg> means of preserving the good people of these Nations in <pb n="5" />peace and safety; Be it further ordained and established by the Authority aforesaid, That is any person, not being an Officer, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Member of the Army or Forces, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> plot, contrive, or endeavour to stir up any mutiny in the said Armies, or among the said Forces, or any of them; or to withdraw any <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> or Officers from their obedience to their superior Officers, or from the present Government as aforesaid; or if any person or persons whatsoever <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> procure, invite, aid or assist any Foreigners or strangers to invade England, Scotland, or Ireland, or any the Dominions thereunto belonging; or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> adhere unto any forces raised by the enemies of this Commonwealth; or if any person or person <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> plot, contrive or <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the betraying, <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> pr yielding up any City, Town, Fort, Magazine, ship, Vessel, or forces by Sea or Land belonging to this Commonwealth; or if any person or persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> counterfeit the Great Seal of England, Scotland, or Ireland, for the time being, used and appointed by Authority of Parl. or by the Lord Protector with the consent of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; or the Sign Manual, privy Signet, or privy Seal of the Lord Protector for the time being; or if any person or persons whatsoever <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> proclaim, declare, publish, or any way promote Charles Stuart eldest Son to the late King, or <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart another of his Sons, or any other the issue or posterity of the said late King; or any other person or person claiming by, from, or under him or them, or either or any of them, to be King or chief Magistrate of England, Scotland, or Ireland, or of either or any of them belonging; or if any person or persons shall give, keep, or hold any intelligence whatsoever by Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said Charles Stuart, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart, the late Queen their mother, or any of them; <pb n="6" />or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the <reg orig="mony">money</reg> of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, or shall bring any false money into this Land, either counterfeit or other, like to the money of this Commonwealth (knowing such money to be false) to the intent to Merchandize, or otherwise; or if any person or persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hereafter <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> forge or counterfeit any such kind of <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, either of Gold or Silver, which is not the proper <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg> of this Commonwealth, and yet is or shall be current within the same; or shall bring from the parts beyond the Seas into this Commonwealth, or into any the Dominions of the same, any such false or counterfeit <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg> of money being current within this Commonwealth as is abovesaid; or if any person or persons shall impair, diminish, <reg orig="falsifie">falsify</reg>, clip, wash round, file, scale, or lighten for wicked lucre or <reg orig="gains">gain's</reg> sake, any the monies of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, or of the Dominions thereof; then all and every the Offences abovementioned <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be and are hereby deemed, ordained and adjudged High Treason; And the Offenders therein, and their Counsellors, Procurers, Aiders, and Abetters, being convicted according to the Laws of this Nation, shall be and are here by deemed and adjudged to be <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg> against this Commonwealth, and shall suffer such pains of death, and incur such forfeitures, as in case of high treason is used and ordained. Provided <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg>, that neither this Ordinance, nor any thing therein contained as touching the <reg orig="moneyes">moneys</reg> and <reg orig="coyns">coins</reg> aforesaid, nor any Attainder of any person or persons for the future, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> in any wise be adjudged to make any corruption of blood to any of the <reg orig="heires">heirs</reg> of any such <reg orig="offendor">offender</reg> <reg orig="ot">or</reg> <reg orig="offendors">offenders</reg>, &amp;c. Provided nevertheless, and it is hereby declared to be the full intent of this Ordinance, that the Laws and Statutes made in the times of Q. Eliz. <pb n="7" />and K. <reg orig="Iames">James</reg>, against <reg orig="Iesuits">Jesuits</reg>, and popish Professors, should not be repealed, but stand in full force in every clause thereof.</p>

<p><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the 27. a Carpenter stood in the Pillory in Smithfield, for <reg orig="beatidg">beating</reg> and wounding his <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg>, and another for corrupt and wilful perjury, who had both his ears <reg orig="nail'd">nailed</reg>. The same day a great part of the South end of <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> took its fall, where about 40 children were playing, but not above 20 were seen to come forth at the door. Divers Gentlemen were walking there; but observing its sudden motion of rending about two yards asunder before it fell, escaped away timely without any harm.</p>

<p>From Holland we have received intelligence, that the States sit very close at the Hague, in order to an Answer to the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> message: but many conceive they will not condescend to a League Defensive, by reason they are so <reg orig="linkt">linked</reg> in Treaties with foreign Princes. The Zealanders are exceeding averse to a peace, and <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> rather to die gallantly with their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> in their hands, <reg orig="then">than</reg> be <reg orig="reproacht">reproached</reg> of having made an infamous peace with the English. And notwithstanding the fair Overtures for an agreement, yet they go on with all possible expedition in their Sea preparations, and intend to have a greater fleet out towards the latter end of Feb. <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever they had yet. The Dutch Admirals seem opposite to the Convention at the Hague, for concluding of a peace, and have published a declaration aboard the Navy, promising more in one hour to the <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> they can perform in ten. The Admiralty are making ready 20 new ships of war, of 150, and 136 foot long, and from 36 to 38 broad. They have taken 3 or 4 more prizes and carried them into the Uly, where 5 delicate East India ships are stranded: who left the whole fleet about Schagen, but are now said to be within the sight of the Land. Pure fish, if they were caught; but our silver hooks cannot yet take hold of them. Captain Cornelius Allard <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> the Devil upon Don's back, and has taken two sweet and delicate prizes from us, laden with Sugar, <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg>, and <reg orig="Bever-wool">Beaver-wool</reg>. But Gen. Pen has sent forth a Squadron to <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> the Channel. The <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> are unanimous, and have signed a Declaration to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in the present Government.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">London, Printed for <em>G. HORTON</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>