<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="LMess4">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
The Loyal Messenger, Issue 4
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" /> 

<head level="1">The Loyal Messenger,</head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="NEWES">NEWS</reg> FROM <reg orig="WHITE-HALL">WHITEHALL:</reg></head>
<head level="2"><em>COMPRISING</em></head>
<head level="3">The State and Martial <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> of, and in relation to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</head>
<head level="3">Further representing,</head>
<p><i>The Declaration and Resolution of his Highness the Lord Protector, &amp; his Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, concerning the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg>, Lawyers, and <reg orig="Attornies">Attorneys</reg>, the <reg orig="administring">administering</reg> of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> both in Law and Equity, the reforming of all Abuses and Corruptions, the writs to be issued forth by the Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal, and the Proclamation to be made throughout all England and Wales, by the Sheriffs of the respective Counties. The Authority of the Law disputed, the high Point of Habeas Corpus discussed, and the Opinions of the Reverend <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> touching the whole Matter of Mr. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg>, and Mr. Streater.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 3 of April, to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 10. of April, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p>It was the saying of the most illustrious and high-born Prince, <em>Gustavus Adolphus</em>, King of <em>Sweden</em>, that by all the German Wars he never got so much as one new pair of Boots; but exposed and laid himself open for the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> good of his Subjects and <unclear>Sould</unclear>: for by their <unclear>meriting</unclear> of Fame abroad, He desired that they might reap the honoured fruits thereof at home. <i>The Labourer is worthy of his Hire; and sweet is that Harmony that proceeds from the delightful String</i>, Do as you would be done unto.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council, upon mature Debate of redressing the grievances of poor prisoners, resolved, that an Ordinance for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>, should be forthwith printed and published. An Ordinance also passed for relief of persons that have acted in the service of the Parliament. There was another Ordinance likewise passed for prohibiting Cock-Matches, the exact Copy take as followeth:</p>
<p>Whereas the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Meetings and Assemblies of people together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cock-fighting, are by experience found to tend many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practices, to the dishonour of God, and do often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of persons and their families. For prevention thereof, Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publike">public</reg> or set meetings or Assemblies of any persons within England or Wales, upon matches made for Cock-fighting; And that every such meeting and assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an unlawful Assembly and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be, and punished; And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, Majors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, Constables, and Headboroughs, within their several Counties, Cities, Limits, and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such meetings and assemblies.</p>
<p><i>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>
<p>No news from Sea save that a Dutch man of war, called the <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Baptist</em>, bound from St. <em>Malos</em> to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and laden with Indico and Pepper, was taken by the Reserve <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>: the Capt. was a Frenchman, but the service being so <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hot, he was at last soundly <reg orig="pepper'd">peppered</reg>, and forced to surrender to cool himself. An Ostend man of war is brought into Plymouth by the Falmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and 3 Dutch prizes <pb n="2" /> laden with French Wines, Figs, and Raisins from St. Lucas. Alas! but to these sweet Fruits, we hear of very sharp and <reg orig="sowr">sour</reg> <reg orig="fawce">farce</reg>: for true it is, that the Brest men of War have taken the <em>Charity</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, and detain the Master for cap. <em>Beach</em>, whom they threaten to mete the same measure unto, as shall be inflicted upon the said <em>Beach</em>. They have also taken two Weymouth Vessels, another of Westchester, and most of the best ships belonging to Bristol. Nay, this is not all; but the Wild-Boar is <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by a Fleming, a delicate Vessel, and bravely fraught, and valued worth 5000 <em>li</em>. To this sad and <reg orig="dismall">dismal</reg> Scene ensues another fatal Act, that is, the <em>Expedition</em> of <em>Plymouth</em> coming from <em>Zant</em>, laden with <em>Currants</em>, was set upon by a Dutch-man of war, and after a long and sharp dispute both ships were sunk.</p>
<p>This day was presented to his Highness the Lord Protector a Declaration and Recognition by M. <em>Dickeson</em> Alderman, and Sir <em>Thomas Withrington</em> Recorder of the City of <em>York</em>: the true copy whereof take as followeth:</p>
<head level="3"><i>To his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c.</i></head>
<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord, whose eyes run to and fro through the earth, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself strong on the behalf of them whose hearts are perfect to him, to make bare his Arm, and bring salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, &amp; to break many yokes from off our necks, in accomplishment whereof, though humane Might and Power have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and <reg orig="over-ruled">overruled</reg> by the Spirit in the midst of the wheels, that we may justly say, We are not saved by <unclear>Bow</unclear>, or by Sword, but by the Lord our God; and therefore, in the first place we look upon it as our duty to acknowledge Salvation and blessing to him that sits upon the throne of Heaven judging the right, who hath done whatsoever it pleased him, both in Heaven, and in Earth, and in all deep places. Yet when we also consider how it hath seemed good in the eyes of God to single out your Highness as the man of his right hand, whom he hath made strong for himself, and through your <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg>, courage, and constancy, to do great and wonderful things in the <pb n="3" /> midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left. While, we bless the Lord, our heart is also to the Governors of <em>Israel</em>, who have <reg orig="jeoparded">jeopardised</reg> their lives in the high places of the field and are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> going on to second their valiant Acts by prudent Councils, that we may enjoy the end of every <reg orig="iust">just</reg> War, which is, a safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> peace. Unto your Highness therefore (as all the people of Israel to their Ruler) we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and peace be to thine helpers</i>.</p>
<p>For which congratulation, his Highness returned thanks to the City of <em>York</em>, and the Gentlemen that presented it.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 4.</i></head>
<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em> had this day audience by his Highness at the Cockpit, and the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> <unclear><em>Agent</em></unclear> had likewise audience, being attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his Highness divers Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of State.</p>
<p>The Committee for approbation of Ministers have met in <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>, chose their Register, and other Officers, and began to proceed in the business according to the Ordinance of his Highness. The place which they sit in, is at the end of the stone Gallery, at the corner of the Court, and their proceedings are such as promiseth much good to <unclear>this</unclear> Nation by the settling of an able, godly, and powerful Gospel <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>. They sit <reg orig="Mundayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg>, and <reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg>.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="Welch-men">Welshmen</reg> have sent a Declaration to his Highness, wherein they bless God for the late Change and present Government. And the like is come from <em>Norfolk</em>, and other places. <em>To God be all the glory.</em></p>
<p>The Commission of the great Seal being <reg orig="alter'd">altered</reg>, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, and Sir <em>Tho: Withrington</em> were this day sworn Commissioners for the custody of the great Seal of <em>England</em> for the Court of Chancery by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his Highness, and his Council, in the Council chamber at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>. The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> who is now in Sweden is also to be one with them.</p>

<p>From <em>Windsor</em> we have received intelligence, That Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Simpson</em> are still under restraint, and have sundry times declared, <pb n="4" /> That they <reg orig="aym">aim</reg> at nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the Glory of God, the good of his Church and people, the true propagation of his glorious Gospel, the safety and welfare of each County in particular, and the <reg orig="Common Wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in general, waiting in hope and expectation of a blessing and success accordingly.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 5.</i></head>
<p>And Mr. <em>Powel</em> in his Letter to Mr. <em><unclear><reg orig="Ienkin">Jenkin</reg></unclear> <reg orig="Iones">Jones</reg></em> in Wales, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That it is a very hard <em>Dilemma</em> when Ministers must be menaced for preaching, and being pressed as from pity to water the parched earth: Alas! alas! whither do his <reg orig="wandring">wandering</reg> passions lead him? Ay! even into a multitude of Vicissitudes. But, to the present Power, let Us humbly submit: <i>'tis good to be merry and wise.</i></p>
<p>This night between 6 and 7 <reg orig="a">o'</reg> clock the Lord <em>Lambert</em>, the L. <em>Lisle</em>, the L. <em>Strickland</em>, and the rest of the English Commissioners, went to the Dutch Ambassadors at Sir <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em>, in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches, with Mr <em><reg orig="Thurlo">Thurloe</reg></em> Secretary of State, and Mr. <em>Scobel</em> Clerk of the Council; and about 9 <reg orig="a">o'</reg> clock at night totally finished the Ratification of Peace, and the Articles were then signed and sealed by the Lord Ambassadors on the one side, with full power from the States, and the Lords commissioners with full power from the Lord Protector on the other side. And within 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> the Peace is to be ratified by the Principals on each part, and <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> proclaimed both in England and the Low-countries. Of which, more by the next: in the interim, be pleased to take notice, that one Article is, that the King of <em>Denmark</em> is to make satisfaction to the English Merchants for all the losses by them sustained and the Dutch are to be Security. Another is that both commonwealths are to assist each other, both offensive and defensive, &amp;c.</p>
<head level="3">Thursday April 6.</head>
<p>The next thing that we shall present you <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, is, the proceedings of the Royal Party in <em>Scotland</em>, which purports, that the Lord <em>De la <reg orig=" Banks ">Bank's</reg></em> Brothers, seven Knights, and 50 Gentlemen, are gone from the West to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, with special Horse and Arms, and that the <reg orig="heroical">heroic</reg> spirits <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, Kenmore, <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg>, <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg></em>, and divers other of the <pb n="5" /> mickle Lairds, are to also upon their march for a general conjunction with a Resolution to force all they can to rise with them. Hey toss, now the Game goes forwards: but confident I am, and with a candid Resolution I desire, that the success may <reg orig="center">centre</reg>, where the justness of the Cause most depends, and no otherwise. <em>Middleton</em> has a very large commission, and ordered by his Master <em>Charles</em> to dispose of all Affairs both Ecclesiastical and civil. He proceeds with fire and sword against all those that will not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, and hath besieged <em><reg orig="Cinkeler">Sinclair</reg></em> castle; besides, they have taken a Vessel of ours going to Lewis Island, laden with Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for that Garrison. In the Southern parts towards <em>Carlisle</em> they are very active in rising daily, which puts the English horse to extraordinary duty, even to <reg orig="tyring">tiring</reg> out.</p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> April 7.</head>
<p>Since our last, We have received intelligence, that the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> Army are all <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> into one body; but who <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> how soon they may be dispersed again: for the English are preparing to give them battle, and desire nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> sudden action. They speak high; but as yet dare not descend low: neither dare they interpose, unless with great advantage. The Broad Seal, we hear, is taken by order from his Highness, and disposed of, and the Commissioners for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners are not to proceed these 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. Sundry other excellent things are under Debate.</p>
<p>It is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that the King of Scots is yet in France, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty will produce betwixt England and France. He had a Present given him a little before Easter by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom. In the <reg orig="Holydayes">Holy days</reg> the little Queen his mother came to see him in the Palace Royal, and King <em><reg orig="Lewis">Louis</reg></em> vouchsafed him a visit in the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em>; After which, she returned to her Devotions in the Nunnery. But if there be a peace concluded between the Commonwealth of England, and the Crown of France, then they are to be excluded from the Court. Well! Patience is a Virtue: And I question not but <reg orig="e're">ere</reg> long to represent you with the glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of the Olive leaves under the happy Government of <em>Oliver</em> our Protector.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<p>There hath been a very sharp Dispute between the Paul <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and a Flushing man of War, the last Week; but after 5 hours Conflict, the Hollanders were forced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, and now <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the mercy of <reg orig="out">our</reg> States in Plymouth.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday April 8.</head>
<p>Presents us with an Ordinance for adjourning part of <em>Easter</em> Term, which take as followeth:</p>
<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained: Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to <reg orig="Adiourn">Adjourn</reg> part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>: Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness Lord Protector, by and with the consent of His <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> That part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em> now next coming to be <reg orig="Adiourned">Adjourned</reg>, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, unto the first Return of <em>Trinity</em> Term, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>: And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, and during the said Term, called <em>Easter</em> Term, may tarry at their dwellings, or where their business shall <reg orig="lye">lie</reg>, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, and without <reg orig="danges">danger</reg> or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf. And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg> shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, giving them authority to <reg orig="adiourn">adjourn</reg> the said part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&oelig;</em>, until the first Return of <em>Trinity</em> Term, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as before is said, and the said <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg> shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Matters, Causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, Depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg>, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as is aforesaid: And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the Chief Market Towns within their several and respective Counties.</p>
<p><em>Henry Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<p>The Ordinance for better amending and keeping in Repair the common <reg orig="High-wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation, was presented to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view.</p>
<p>Upon the arrival of the <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> at the Hague, touching the signing and sealing of the Articles of Peace between England and Holland, the Royal Party were much startled thereat, and Major Gen. Massey was pleased to make this construction upon the Ratification, That <unclear>sith</unclear> Providence had pleased to make up the Breach between the two <reg orig="Republiques">Republics</reg>, it was impossible that his Masters Game should go forward, and that he conceived it would redound most to the honour of the English Chevaliers, to engage mutually in the Christian service, against the Turks and Pagans. A most noble and <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Design, and I desire that it may prove effectual.</p>
<p>But on the contrary, the major part are exceedingly revived in spirit, and the Merchants on both sides have great cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>; for the <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> begin already to seek out for shelter, and to <reg orig="striffe">strive</reg> off from the Narrow Seas. <i>A fair riddance.</i> And the Navigable <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> appear somewhat <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg>, the Clouds of <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg> being gallantly expelled.</p>
<hr />
<p>There is lately published an excellent piece, exceeding useful for those who are detained in prison, and indeed worthy the perusal of all <reg orig="English-men">Englishmen</reg>, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>Clavis ad apriendum Carieris astia</i>; Or, the High Point of the Writ of <em>Habeas Corpus</em> discussed. And not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the several Branches of the said Writ, but also the Authorities of both Common and Statute Law (with divers ancient and obscure Records) produced and cleared. <reg orig="Shewing">Showing</reg> the Remedies against illegal and unjust Imprisonment. In being the Case of Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Streater</em>, and Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Lilburn">Lilburne</reg></em> in <em>Michaelmas</em> and <em>Hillary</em> Terms last past. With the Opinion of the Reverend Judges upon the whole Matter. With the Arguments of the Prisoners on the one part, and Mr. Attorney Gen. on the other. Printed for <em>R. Moon</em> at the seven Stars in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>, near the great North door.</p>
<p><i>Finis.</i></p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>





