<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MAul16542">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
Mercurius Aulicus, Issue 2
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="1">Mercurius Aulicus,</head>
<head level="2">COMMUNICATING</head>
<head level="2">The State and Martial <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> of, and in relation to</head>
<head level="3">the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 20 of March, to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 27. of March, 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>Summus locus bene regitur, quum is, qui pr&oelig;est, <unclear>Vitiis</unclear>, potius, quam <unclear>fi atribus</unclear> dominatur.</i></p>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>A <reg orig="LICENCER">LICENSER</reg>! thou piece of ignorance!</line>
<line>In my <reg orig="LORDs">LORD's</reg> Name <reg orig="fearles">fearless</reg>, my Book, advance.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>And would you have <em>Aulicus</em> again with <em>Sock</em> and <em>Buskin</em> enter the Stage? 'tis granted: but you require a <em>Courtier</em> to appear in Court language, in Scarlet and <reg orig="Sattin">Satin</reg> <reg orig="Phraises">Phrases</reg>, with gold and silver lace Complements; each Paragraph <reg orig="imbroidered">embroidered</reg> with many a rich Parenthesis; each <reg orig="Distick">Distich</reg> interwoven with ornamental Pointings. Alas! poor <em>Aulicus</em>! as some are mistaken to be <em>wise</em>; so art thou mistaken to be a <em>rich</em> and <em>gallant Courtier</em>, when thou art but a <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> <em>Orator</em>, a poor <em>Petitioner</em>, having waited, at times, not much less <reg orig="then">than</reg> seven years for thy <reg orig="Fathers">Father's</reg> sad and deplorable losses, and <reg orig="wer't">wert</reg> scarcely <reg orig="e're">ere</reg> <reg orig="incouraged">encouraged</reg> in thy Suits, promised redress, much less furthered by any, but his Highness, who (when he brought up the Rear of the Army, but the Van of their Virtues) at his house in <em>Drury</em> lane, when thou wert presented by his noble Son my Lord <em>Richard</em>, made an <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> mention of thy Father, to whom he seemed to be of recent memory, being pleased to honour him with the appellations of Patriot, faithful and well-deserving member in a <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; was further pleased to become instrumental to thy advancement (at <em>Putney</em>) when the <reg orig="villany">villainy</reg> (and too modest a word) of two persons (whose Names would pollute this innocent Paper, who scarcely ever, nay once did never discourse with <pb n="1" /> abused <em>Aulicus</em>) his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> noble <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg>. When Capt. General also, in the Gallery at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, he did graciously vouchsafe a reiteration of promises of redress, and thus may plead excuse for my assuming the Title of <em>Aulicus</em>, though I scarcely merit that of <em>Mercurius</em>, and my many many obligations to the illustrious family of the <reg orig="CROMWELS">CROMWELLS</reg>, as to the Lord <em>Henry</em>, who was pleased to say, I was worthy of the best <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> (though by my late imprisonment, notwithstanding my Pass) I lost that I had in <em>Ireland</em>, and am now destitute) and that I could in any <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> command a fortune. As the <reg orig="Phylosopher">Philosopher</reg> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, <i>Si ingratum dixeris, omnia dixisti</i>. But these things, sure, would loose the tongue of the dumb to speak, the hand that was lame and impotent nimbly to write their praises; yet my losses have been so <reg orig="aggrandiz'd">aggrandised</reg> by Salt, that it can scarcely be expected I should have any in my Writings; and now, you have heard <em>Aulicus</em> his Prologue, he humbly craves leave the <unclear><reg orig="newes">news</reg></unclear> of the <reg orig="sixe">six</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of the Week may be heard, and <em>exit</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 20 of March</i>.</head>
<p>Sith this day, or yester-night (and the evening and the morning were the first day) one <em>Foulcher</em> was <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to the <reg orig="Gate-house">Gatehouse</reg> in Westminster, upon suspicion of <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> half crowns of no true allay; and of a truth, <em>Aulicus</em> in this is a <em>Politicus</em>; for he would have such persons (who usually use Oaths, as bracelets to their Speech) to be stringed like Beads, if found guilty of such an <reg orig="inormous">enormous</reg> Crime.</p>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line><unclear>Why</unclear> tempt ye thus the Fates, ye Sons of wrong?</line>
<line>Ye have but half-crowns sure, that use this long,</line>
<line>Or once at all, why <reg orig="deifie">deify</reg> ye Dross?</line>
<line>The <em>Harp</em> ye find doth play you to the <em>Cross</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Uppsala</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em> thus: The Treaty goes on, but slowly; yet doubtless, if the Transactions between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> take effect, they will soon be <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> in new Councils; for her Maj. promiseth fair to the L. <em>Whitlock</em>; and hath revived her former Overtures of resigning up the Government to her Successor, and desires the liberty of retiring into privacy. The great Taxes upon the people is conceived <reg orig="wil">will</reg> push them forward to some notable design, which causeth the Senators to sit very close in <reg orig="councel">council</reg>. They are consulting what Answer to return to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proposals, for resigning up the Crown and <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>, to her Successor, or Lord Protector.</p>
<pb n="2" />
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>A wise King said, his life <reg orig="embraced">embraced</reg> ease,</line>
<line>'Twixt Constable, and Justice of the Peace,</line>
<line>That had his Orb; this <em>Amazon</em> doth see</line>
<line>Retirement hath the true felicity.</line>
<line>Danger is <reg orig="out-law'd">outlawed</reg> there, security</line>
<line><reg orig="Imbrac'd">Embraced</reg>, and freedom is in purity.</line>
<line>The Crown of Gold, is <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> a Crown of Thorn,</line>
<line>And as much painful, as it doth adorn.</line>
<line>O! how deficient are all mundane things,</line>
<line>I want five Crowns, Crowns sleighted are by Kings.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday March 21.</i></head>
<p>By a Letter from <em>Harwich</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that there is a Dutch ship of 400 <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts, and Iron, to a great value brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>
<p>The Lord Protector and his Council have set forth an Ordinance for the continuing of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>; and the Rates for every Barrel of Beer or Ale above 6 s. the barrel brewed by the common Brewer, or by any other person or persons who shall sell or tap out Beer or Ale <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> or privately, to be paid by the said Brewer or such other person or persons respectively is 2 s. For every Barrel of six shilling Beer of Ale, or above 4 shilling the Barrel 6 d. And so proportionably for a greater or lesser quantity of Beer or Ale above 4 s. the Barrel And no allowance to be made from henceforth for any Beer or Ale to be used in Fishing Vessels at sea, which is bought of the <reg orig="comon">common</reg> Brewer <reg orig="os">or</reg> <reg orig="Retaler">Retailer</reg> of Beer or Ale. Allum English the hundred weight, containing 112 pounds, to be paid by the maker 6 d. <reg orig="Coperas">Copperas</reg> English, the hundred weight 6 d. English Hops, the hundred weight, to be paid by the Planter 2 s. English Saffron, for every 20 s. value, to be paid by the Planter 1 s. Tin, for every 20 s. value, to be paid by the buyer 1 s. Iron English, for every hundred weight, to be paid by the maker 1 sh. 6 d. For all <reg orig="Aquavit&aelig;">Aquavitae</reg>; or strong water made or distilled within the Commonwealth whether of <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> or <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Spirits or materials to be sold upon every gallon, to be paid by the first maker or Seller thereof respectively two pence. For every barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within this Commonwealth of what sort <unclear>soever</unclear> to be paid by the maker, and so proportionably for hard <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> or soft <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within the Land 4 s. For every Ounce Troy of silver or gold prepared, melted down, or <pb n="3" /> disgrossed for Wyer, to be paid at the bar where the same shall be disgrossed 2 d. For every pound weight <reg orig="conteining">containing</reg> sixteen Ounces Averdupois, of any copper or other metal, that <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> prepared, and made fit or disgrossed, to be paid at the bar where the same <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> <reg orig="disgros'd">disgrossed</reg> one shilling. For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Whale <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Blubber <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Rape <reg orig="oyl">oyl</reg>, Pilchard <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, and all other <reg orig="oyls">oils</reg> made within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, upon every <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg>, to be paid by the maker six s. <em>per</em> <reg orig="Tun">Tonne</reg>, &amp;c.</p>
<head level="3">Wednesday the 22.</head>
<p>The Lord Protector set forth a Declaration, inviting the People of <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to a solemn day of fasting and humiliation, and ordered that <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the 24 instant should be set apart for the cities of London and Westminster; and the same day fortnight for all the Counties in general in England and Wales. The Causes are, first, the common notorious sins impenitently practised amongst us. Secondly, the present long drought, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> famine and mortality. The sins taken notice of by his Highness are, Nothwithstanding the just Liberty Spiritual and Civil, God hath procured by his own people, yet want of humble walking in the <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg> of Christ, or to communicate that liberty one to another. Or thankfully to acknowledge our liberty of worshipping God in holiness, want of brotherly love. Not owning one another for the grace of God more <reg orig="then">than</reg> form: Not seeking the Kingdom of Christ within us, before one without us. <reg orig="Listning">Listening</reg> to false Christs: Temporal Rule for Saints. A crying up of the Spirit; with a neglect of Love, and the other fruits of the Spirit: And an evil carriage towards them without: crying down Ministers that have a large seal of their Ministry, want of old Puritan <reg orig="self-deniall">self-denial</reg>; Mercy to the poor, uprightness, justice, and contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, as it ought to be <reg orig="apostatizings">apostatisings</reg> of many running after notions and fancies against Magistracy, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, Scriptures, and Ordinances, contempt of the Gospel, and sincere Professors of it, even for the Image of Christ in them. Oaths, Drunkenness, Revellings, and all manner of licentiousness. And the impunity of these things, through neglect of the Magistracy in several parts of the Nation. The Ordinance is also passed for approbation of Ministers, and about 30 Commissioners, Ministers, and other able and godly men, who are to sit where his Highness shall appoint for that purpose. Another <pb n="4" /> Ordinance for ejecting of scandalous and ignorant Ministers is under debate by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. &mdash;</p>
<p>This day there was no Audience, his Highness's time being solely taken up about <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Affairs, which occasioned <em>Aulicus</em> his Poetical Petition, which is here inserted.</p>
<head level="3"><i>To his Highness the Lord Protector.</i></head>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>How am I <reg orig="thunder-clapt">thunder-clapped</reg>! my <reg orig="palsy'd">palsied</reg> Pen</line>
<line>Fails in its Office to the best of Men,</line>
<line>In this our little World: and well I may</line>
<line>Have mine eyes <reg orig="dazled">dazzled</reg> by the illustrious Ray</line>
<line>Of so much <reg orig="luster">lustre</reg>, whose effecting Steel</line>
<line>Made Princes fall, and Opposites to reel,</line>
<line>And stagger from their greatness, whose known skill</line>
<line>Commands obedience from the proudest Will.</line>
<line>Your Highness hath <reg orig="perform'd">performed</reg> within these <reg orig="Iles">Isles</reg></line>
<line>What <em><reg orig="C&aelig;sar">Caesar</reg></em> did <reg orig="i'th">in the</reg> West by all his Wiles,</line>
<line>And Policies; or <em><reg orig="Philips">Philip's</reg></em> Son <reg orig="i'th">in the</reg> East:</line>
<line>This all do grant your Highness (at the least)</line> 
<line>But I boast more; they fought unarmed men,</line>
<line>And you magnanimous, and Gentlemen,</line>
<line>Of ripe experiences, haughty courages;</line>
<line>On whom the Turk could not force outrages,</line>
<line>If under your command, and conduct: who</line>
<line>A real <em>Perseus</em> seems; a <unclear><reg orig="Counel">Council</reg></unclear>; so</line>
<line>GOD's enemies have found: your <em>Sterling</em> worth</line>
<line><reg orig="Out-weighs">Outweighs</reg> Wars deepest Council; sally forth,</line>
<line>And conquer hearts, as much as you have men,</line>
<line>By righting of the long-oppressed, when</line>
<line>It doth arrive your ears. Oh! To this see!</line>
<line>And this your safest, best <reg orig="Life-guard">Lifeguard</reg> shall be,</line>
<line>Vouchsafe an ear unto the <reg orig="Orphans">Orphans'</reg> <reg orig="cryes">cries</reg>, <ptr target="N01"/></line>
<line><reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> up their tears, relieve their miseries;</line>
<line>He, whose Vice gerent you are, then will crown</line>
<line>Your pious Deeds, and mantle with renown</line>
<line>The Name of <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg>, which shall <reg orig="e'r">ever</reg> be</line>
<line><reg orig="Sign'd">Signed</reg> with affection, <reg orig="seal'd">sealed</reg> with <reg orig="memorie">memory</reg>,</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<note place="side" id="N01"><p>13000 <unclear><!-- 1 character --></unclear> Lost by the late King by the <reg orig="Authors">Author's</reg> Father.</p></note>
<p>By</p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> most humble, faithful, and obedient Servant,</i></p>
<p>AULICUS.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3">Thursday <em>March</em> 23.</head>
<p>From Dublin thus: The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, when he comes back to you will confuse those false Reports that were raised of us here, he having had a reception as a Prince, with 300 horse out of the City (most of them Citizens) with <reg orig="bone-fires">bonfires</reg> at night throughout the City.</p>
<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, have passed an Ordinance appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Preachers; and for prevention of all scandalous and popish intruders, it is ordained, That every person who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from and after the 25 of March instant be presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with Care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <unclear><reg orig="setled">settled</reg></unclear> Lecture in England or Wales, shall, before he be admitted into any such Benefice or Lecture, be adjudged and approved by the persons hereafter named, to be a person for the grace of God in him, his holy and <reg orig="unblamable">unblameable</reg> Conversation, as also for his knowledge and utterance, able and fit to preach the Gospel, and that after the said 25 of <em>March</em>, no person, but such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> upon such approbation be admitted, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Lecture or Benefice as aforesaid, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>
<head level="3"><i>The Names of the Commissioners.</i></head>
<p>Francis Rous Esq;</p>
<p>Dr. Tho. Goodwin,</p>
<p>Dr. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Owen</p>
<p>M. Thankful Owen,</p>
<p>Dr. Arrowsmith,</p>
<p>Dr. Tuckney,</p>
<p>Dr. Horton,</p>
<p>M. <reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg> Caryl</p>
<p>M. Philip Ny,</p>
<p>M. William Carter,</p>
<p>M. Sidrach Simpson,</p>
<p>M. William Greenhill,</p>
<p>M. William Strong,</p>
<p>M. Thomas Manton,</p>
<p>M. Samuel Slater,</p>
<p>M. Cooper</p>
<p>M. Marshal,</p>
<p>M. Tombes</p>
<p>M. Cradock,</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Faircloth,</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Hugh Peters,</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Sterrey</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Bamford</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Valentine</p>
<p><em>M. Jesse</em></p>
<p><em>M.</em> Obad ah Sedgwick,</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Nic. Lockier</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Dyke, <em>M.</em> Russel</p>
<p><em>M.</em> Campfield</p>
<p>Rob. Tichborn Alderman of London.</p>
<p><em>Mark</em> Hildesley,</p>
<p>Thomas Wood</p>
<p>John Sadler</p>
<p>Wil. Goff</p>
<p>Tho. St. Nicholas</p>
<p>Wil. Packer,</p>
<p>And Edw. <unclear>Cresset</unclear> Esquires.</p>
<p>One thing I cannot omit, that Tuesday last the English Commissioners, and the Dutch Ambassadors, after another audience before his Highness, had a large conference, and sundry papers were read by Mr. <em><reg orig="Iesop">Jesop</reg></em> Clerk to the Council and the Transactions of the Treaty debated by Mr. <em>Thurloe</em> Sec of State; upon the Result whereof, the Articles were even made ready to finish, and the <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> of <em>Denmark</em> took up much time.</p>
<head level="3"><i><em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> March 24.</i></head>
<p>No news, but that upon a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> invitation the City should so solemnly observe a Day of fasting and humiliation, and it is wished that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> this day fortnight <pb n="6" /> may keep it no worse: for we have great cause to bury our <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the dust for our notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised among us, and to consider the Rod of God upon us, in an universal Drought for some years, and still continued, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <reg orig="famin">famine</reg> and mortality: for, true it is, that in the North of England, and several other parts of this Nation, the Springs, River, and Brookes, are almost dry for 20 miles distant. O then consider!</p>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>To Fasting why should sensual flesh be <reg orig="loth">loath</reg>?</line>
<line>Fasting is good for soul and body both.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> we have received intelligence, That there are Articles of High-Treason exhibited against the famous <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> capt. <em>Beach</em>; who disputed the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the Seas in the Royal James with great Resolution: insomuch, that coming aboard the Warwick, he demanded of valiant cap. <em>Potter</em> the manner of performing his Articles, and said it was his promise to see him ashore in <em>France</em>; whereupon cap. <em>Potter</em> answered, That he never heard of any such Demand; but to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> him, proffered cap, <em>Beach</em> to go aboard his own ship again, and fight it out; but the captain refused it, retorting, <i>No Sir, 'tis good sleeping in a whole skin.</i></p>  
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Shall <em>Potter</em> in a fight not fear to <reg orig="dy">die</reg>,</line>
<line>And I not offer to his Victory</line>
<line>One <reg orig="Distick">Distich</reg>? sure my duty to it leads,</line>
<line>Poets are Trumpets of <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Deeds.</line>
<line>Then found a Charge, my <em>Muse</em>, and change some shot,</line>
<line>Frighten the Ocean, make the Welkin hot,</line>
<line><reg orig="Parboyl">Parboil</reg> the Fish, pickle in blood and dust</line>
<line>The braver <reg orig="soules">souls</reg>, who <reg orig="ne'r">ne'er</reg> with <reg orig="slothfull">slothful</reg> Rust</line>
<line>Would be <reg orig="consum'd">consumed</reg>. Hark! How Sea-Welkin roars</line>
<line>As if they had the <reg orig="Hichop">Hiccup</reg> <reg orig="o're">o'er</reg> and <reg orig="o're">o'er</reg>,</line>
<line>Ordnance, and Flames Thunder, <reg orig="Lightning">Lightening</reg> seem,</line>
<line>The Sea a Kettle <reg orig="boyling">boiling</reg>, by its <reg orig="steem">steam</reg></line>
<line>Appears, and <em>Thetis</em> hath the <reg orig="Chollick">Colick</reg> got,</line>
<line>Reverberated by incessant shot.</line>
<line>Death rides <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> on a furious Wave,</line>
<line>Which seems to threaten to each ship a Grave.</line>
<line>Now <em>Beach</em> hath Flood gates <reg orig="ope">open</reg> into his <reg orig="Hould">Hold</reg>,</line>
<line>'Tis madness now, not valour to be bold;</line>
<line>He craveth quarter, comes on board and then</line>
<line>Demandeth freedom for himself and men.</line>
<line>I gave them no such Articles <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he,</line>
<line>That proffered to fight it instantly,</line>
<pb n="7" />
<line>And repossess him of his ship: alas!</line>
<line>He would not tempt destruction by the Brass.</line>
<line>Thy worth let Canons with their wide mouth <reg orig="rore">roar</reg>,</line>
<line>While Earth has water, or the Main hath shore.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>This day about 100 Colliers came safe into the River of Thames, and it is already ordered by many of the honest Woodmongers to sell their Coals for eight pence <em>per</em> bushel.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday <em>March</em> 25.</head>
<p>Presents us with variety of strange <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from the Royal stamp, to wit, First, that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> has sent a fiery Summons, and a <unclear>flaming</unclear> Declaration to the <reg orig="whimsie-pated">whimsy-pated</reg> Jockies, to come in to his assistance, for the service of their King, and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: but <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> possible, but that they may be <unclear>soon stifled</unclear> with the <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> of our guns. 2 That there is a great army preparing in Germany to land suddenly: but when, and where, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>. And thirdly, that their <reg orig="gude">guide</reg> mickle Gentleman valiant <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em>, second son to the late King of Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>, was to command in chief, &amp;c. The truth of which we question: though many are pleased to whet their sharp appetites upon that ancient saying, <i>That there is never no smoke, but there is some fire</i>: and already begin to chew the Cud upon the Ordinance, this day extant, for continuing an Act for impressing of <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg>. There is also another Act this day published for continuation of an Act <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for laying an imposition upon <reg orig="Coles">Coals</reg>, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas.</p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Berries">Berry's</reg></em> Regiment of horse is designed to relieve the Lord <em><reg orig="Fleetwoods">Fleetwood's</reg></em> from the Guards at the <em><reg orig="Mewes">Mews</reg></em>, and <em>Roads</em>, &amp;c.</p>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Ye Sons of valour, and of abstinence</line>
<line>Are ruled by Reason, not by <reg orig="head-strong">headstrong</reg> <reg orig="Sence">Sense</reg>.</line>
<line><unclear>Rovents</unclear> the <reg orig="Catholicks">Catholics</reg> would not resent</line>
<line>If but acquainted with a Regiment,</line>
<line>Of this new <reg orig="model'd">modelled</reg> Army, where no Eye</line>
<line>Can see allowance of <unclear>impiety</unclear>.</line>
<line><reg orig="Here's">Here's</reg> <unclear>no Oath</unclear> <reg orig="Rhetorick">Rhetoric</reg>, no <reg orig="sayling">sailing</reg> on</line>
<line>In <unclear>liberal</unclear> Cups to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> affection.</line>
<line>No <em>Hectoring</em>; but <unclear>truer</unclear> valour here,</line>
<line>No spurious canting will arrive the Ear.</line>
<line>In sum: <em>Philosophers may Virtue</em> see,</line>
<line>And Christians view the power of <em><reg orig="Pietie">Piety</reg></em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<hr />
<p><i>The Declaration and Summons of General Middleton, published by sound of Trumpet in the North of Scotland, for and on behalf of <em>Charles Stuart</em>, Son to the late King of <em>Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg></em>. The proceedings of the English forces thereupon, and their great preparations for <reg orig="battel">battle</reg>. The raising of a mighty Army beyond the Seas, and their Resolution and Design. The Proposals of the Queen of Sweden, for resigning up her Crown. And the entertaining of the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> as a Prince. The Order of his Highness the Lord Protector touching the Navy, and impressing of <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg>, With the new Ordinance touching <reg orig="Coales">Coal</reg>.</i></p>
<p>Finis.</p>
<hr />
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>


