<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MAul16543">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
Mercurius Aulicus, Issue 3
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="1">Mercurius Aulicus:</head>
<head level="2">COMMUNICATING</head>
<head level="2">The State and Martial Affairs,</head>
<head level="3">of, and in relation to the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging:</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> March 27, to <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> April 3. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<p><i>What needs a Licence unto that book, where <unclear>His <!-- 1 word --></unclear> is, that <reg orig="impower'd">empowered</reg> a Licenser?</i></p>
<p>Excellently said <em>Phocion</em>, Temperance is a noble virtue, and chiefly appertaineth to the <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> state of Mankind, whereby the Princely government <em>Reason</em>, which reigneth as King in man, is known to bare sway in man, whereby it happily tempereth all his actions, and thereby <reg orig="hee">he</reg> differeth from the affects of Beasts. He <reg orig="onely">only</reg> is to be called a temperate and moderate person, which not only hath power over his wanton and corrupt affections, but so endeavoureth also himself, that he is to no man cruel or grievous, neither to any man dangerous; for he is tempered with the light of true heavenly grace, he is of nature affable, and familiar, he is <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> of <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> to men that <reg orig="wil">will</reg> come and speak with him, (considering his quality) whose house is <unclear>unlocked</unclear>, not shut, but open, where every man, as it were, in tempest and storms, may repair for their relief and succour. If I should aver this Cardinal <em>Virtue Temperance</em>, to <pb n="1" /> <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in this Court where <em>Aulicus</em> is a Poetical Courtier, (and Poets can be <unclear><reg orig="fantasie">fantasy</reg></unclear> create themselves not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Courtiers but Kings) and this temperate and moderate man to be his <em>Highness my Lord Protector</em>: I hope those not prejudiced by an inveterate antipathy to I is proceedings, <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not account me one of <em>Domitian's</em> flatterers, I having as <unclear>absolve</unclear> an abhorrency of that unmanlike vice, as any person living, and had my Reader a <reg orig="Christal">Crystal</reg> casement into my heart, he would apparently see and conclude, that my very <reg orig="thoughte">thought</reg> are <reg orig="antartick">antartic</reg> thereunto; for, as one said, <i>Quid est adulations unction, nisi domoram emunctio? Quid commendationis allusio, nisi pr&oelig;latorum delusie? Quid laudis arriso, nisi eorundum derisio?</i> I hope, I have still kept to my Text, for when a Courtier is not a Flatterer, it is news indeed, and as long as my Lord can be called <em>Justus</em>, I am <em>Aulicus</em>.</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 27.</i></head>
<p>This day the news of the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> safe arrival, arrived the ears of joyful <em>Aulicus</em>, though he came to Town on Saturday, and as his welcome was great from the City of <em>Dublin</em>, so <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> it be from me, his meanest, not menial, but most faithful Servant.</p>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Let flaming Loves in flaming <unclear><reg orig="firas">fires</reg></unclear> be seen,</line>
<line>Tell us herself be mantled all in green,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Poetrie">Poetry</reg> of Bells be added, here</line>
<line>Add too the Cannons breathing massacre,</line>
<line>The noble Trump rousing our inward parts,</line>
<line>Let all be <reg orig="showne">shown</reg> that can express our hearts</line>
<line>Unfeigned welcome: welcome as the child</line>
<line>unto the yearning Mother, long <reg orig="exil'd">exiled</reg>,</line>
<line>And but <reg orig="arriv'd">arrived</reg>; as to <em>Penelope</em></line>
<line>Was her <em><reg orig="Vlysses">Ulysses</reg></em>, whose hard <reg orig="destinie">destiny</reg></line>
<pb n="2" />
<line>Had <reg orig="caus'd">caused</reg> his absence twice ten years: Welcome,</line>
<line>As to the arms the Lady was at home.</line>
<line>My dearest Lord, as the approaching spring</line>
<line>Which gives new life to <reg orig="Vegitals">Vegetals</reg>, Birds sing</line>
<line>Their Roundelays, and with an artless art</line>
<line>With solitary Lovers do take part.</line>
<line>I am a plant my Lord, and shall re-live,</line>
<line>If planted by your noble hand, and thrive,</line>
<line>Though now I wither: Winter-want have thus</line>
<line>Robbed my leaves, I scarce am <em>Aulicus</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>This afternoon <em>Monsieur de <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> was received as the French Ambassador, who before was resident here as Agent, with many fair coaches, many with six horses a piece, the Ambassadors came in my Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> first coach, and had not the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of the Guard at the Tower interposed, it was probable <reg orig="som">some</reg> blood had been split at the <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> landing, for precedency of driving the coach in which he was, and the Portugal Ambassadors, for about forty swords of each side were drawn: Some conceive these proceedings to be <em>ta arreta</em>, secrets not to be uttered, and can not forget the disgust given to the whole English Nation in perpetrating a <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> upon the New Exchange, by which it appears animosities are epidemical to the Nation.</p>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>What means that clod of earth, weak man, so high</line>
<line>To aim, as if he <reg orig="wuld">would</reg> go <reg orig="deifie">deify</reg></line>
<line>Himself? Alas! each grave informs</line>
<line>Him, that Death renders his am Feast for <em>Worms</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday March 28.</i></head>
<p>By Letters from a good hand thus.</p>
<p><em>Sir</em>,</p>
<p>The sad spectacle, which I have generally beheld throughout most parts of Ireland, hath been a pressure long time upon my spirit, and now being at <em>Dublin</em>, I could not omit this opportunity, nor detain <pb n="3" /> it from your knowledge; the just hand of God hath been upon the Natives for many <reg orig="yeers">years</reg> past, which what by sword, plague and famine, they have been much depopulated, and thereby the famine is still the rifer among the poor sort, happily to get a dead cow, or horse to feed pon, adventuring their lives to steal Garrons in the night to eat in their Braches, having no other subsistence, but by getting Shamrigs and <reg orig="Sorrill">Sorrel</reg> until the Harvest comes, lingering and languishing about the places where they were born, looking like <reg orig="Negtoes">Negroes</reg> black in the faces, and with white teeth, dropping down dead in the <reg orig="high-wayes">highways</reg> and streets as they are going; yea, I have seen them <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in this place. God is just in all his <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, for you were an <reg orig="ear- witnesse">ear-witness</reg> what horrid massacres and inhumane butcheries were proved to have been perpetrated by that <reg orig="Arch-rebell">Arch-rebel</reg> Sir <em>Phelem O Neale</em> at his <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> here, and by his wicked accomplices. Flaming <reg orig="Oneal">O Neale</reg> indeed, for how many <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> Christians after quarter hath be burnt in Churches and houses? how unworthily did those sons of blood use the noble Ld. Caffield and his Lady? How did he drive naked Protestants like sheep to the slaughter, to a bridge, and then force them into the river? These things are so <reg orig="wel">well</reg> known to you, and to all Englishmen, as I need not dilate. I could wish there were Manufactories set up in this land, which would not only preserve, but be exceeding beneficial to the Commonwealth, besides in time there may be drawn from them a people, (and they will be as branes plucked out of the fire) which may serve God in a right way, which I leave to your consideration to <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> of, and remain,</p>
<p>Sir, Your humble servant, J.B.</p>
<pb n="4" />
<head level="3">By Letters from Plymouth thus:</head>
<p>Right <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>,</p>
<p>This day Cap. Featon commander of the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a Dutch prize, which hath only a few barrels of Pitch in her. This week the Paul, a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met a Flushing Man of war in the Channel of 15 guns, and after five hours fight took the Flushiner, and this day brought her into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>. Our Man of War lost not one man, but sustained some loss in Masts, <reg orig="Sayls">Sails</reg> and Rigging. The enemy lost thirteen or fourteen men, and the ship much torn, there was some silver in her, but it is said, the Sailors have shared that, as for any other lading, there are not any, save a <unclear>fect</unclear> Casks of wine, and the ships provision: There is in the <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, the Portsmouth, Constant Warwick, and Falmouth <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> and the Paul, which came in this day: The <reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesbrough</reg> went to Sea this day: I have no more to trouble your <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> with, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> humbly therefore take my leave and rest</p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> most humble and faithful Servant, J.B.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 29.</i></head>
<p><i>The Duke of <reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg>, occasioned by some expressions of passion, in breaking his windows, is in a manner immured having little light left him by casements, and these out of his reach, which at first <reg orig="sadded">saddened</reg> him, but now he triumphs over his captivity, which occasioned me to digest his noble resolution into verse.</i></p>
<pb n="5" />
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>My <unclear><reg orig="ofcsweld">of swelled</reg></unclear> <em>passions</em> I have now so <reg orig="tem'd">tamed</reg>,</line>
<line>That I can make <em>Adversity</em> <reg orig="asham'd">ashamed</reg></line>
<line>By Patience; nay, the Globe I here <reg orig="possesse">possess</reg>,</line>
<line>Make prisons proud of such <reg orig="contentednesse">contentedness</reg>.</line>
<line><em>Fame</em> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> but stammer what I here have done,</line>
<line>Although my foes, alas! think I me undone.</line>
<line><unclear>Be study</unclear> to be absolute; <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> see</line>
<line>I've been a doer, now a sufferer,</line>
<line><em>Virtue</em> before the world, here <reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> prefer.</line>
<line>Enforced misery <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be my mirth,</line>
<line><em>Afflictions</em> toys and jests; I scorn base earth.</line>
<line><unclear><reg orig="I'le">I'll</reg></unclear> be an object for each <reg orig="wond'ring">wondering</reg> <reg orig="ey">eye</reg>,</line>
<line>And gather strength to laugh at misery.</line>
<line>Whilst <reg orig="vertue's">virtue's</reg> in my heart in garrison,</line>
<line>Fools think this House a prison, it is none,</line>
<line>A brave <reg orig="raisd">raised</reg> patience I possess: be gone!</line>
<line>A willing man <reg orig="dyes">dies</reg> sleeping and all's done.</line>
<line>I am so <reg orig="cheared">cheered</reg> by a glorious glance,</line>
<line>Me thinks this house is my inheritance.</line>
<line>O foolish adversaries come and see!</line>
<line><reg orig="Ime">I'm</reg> wanton <reg orig="growne">grown</reg> with my <reg orig="captivitie">captivity</reg>.</line>
<line>This Castle is a Court, a <reg orig="galerie">gallery</reg>,</line>
<line>A <reg orig="choycer">choicer</reg> garden, <reg orig="Vniversitie">University</reg>.</line>
<line>Oppressors boast, and punish me still thus,</line>
<line><reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> tire you out, and be victorious.</line>
<line>The quintessence of <reg orig="contentation">contention</reg> shall</line>
<line>Adorn my dishes, cups, and chamber wall.</line>
<line>My Muse, and I <reg orig="wil">will</reg> revel it, and see</line>
<line>A greater <reg orig="fredome">freedom</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> poor <reg orig="Libertie">Liberty</reg>.</line>
<line><reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> teach my <reg orig="wel-used">well-used</reg> tongue tempests to tame,</line>
<line>Make <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> Rocks waton be in see with same</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>This afternoon the L. Ambassador of France, Monsieur <em>de <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> had audience by his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> my Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <pb n="6" /> <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> in great state, and it seems the French <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> gentlemen mistook that their <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> second coach ought to <reg orig="haue">have</reg> been driven before the first of the Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, which controversy is left to the <em>grandees</em> at Court to be decided by; for Aulicus is but a young Courtier though this was at his reception it was not so at his Audience.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 30.</i></head>
<p>A List of ships taken arrived my hands, &amp;c.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Friday March 31.</i></head>
<p>Friday M. Sadler one of the Masters of the Requests went towards Maudlin <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Cambridge, of which he is Master, and being so pious, conscientious and careful a gentleman in his office, I could not but applaud his sincerity, and <reg orig="grieue">grieve</reg> for his departure, though Mr Hatter is <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for the present, with the <em>Petitions</em> and <em>Reports</em> he hath so long and faithfully endeavoured an audience for, but through the pressing <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg> of State, that affair hath been much retarded, and he to his grief, hath found his <reg orig="labors">labours</reg> <reg orig="fruitlesse">fruitless</reg>: therefore my sentiments hereupon are in these ensuing English verse.</p>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Great faithful Servant of the British State,</line>
<line>Your Acts of Mercy do <reg orig="aproximate">approximate</reg></line>
<line>The Divine Majesty; then Oh, persist,</line>
<line>In seeking of the <reg orig="poors">poors'</reg> <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg>, desist</line>
<line>From <unclear><reg orig="'t">it</reg></unclear> never, but O, let your pious care</line>
<line>With <reg orig="irresistlesse">irresistless</reg> <reg orig="Rhet'rick">Rhetoric</reg> storm the ear</line>
<line>Of our great Lord Protector, let him know</line>
<line><reg orig="Th'">The</reg> oppressed wrongs, and as you have done, so</line>
<line>Resent the widows cries and orphans tears,</line>
<line>The last let move your eyes, the first your ears.</line>
<pb n="6" />
<line>But you must to the <reg orig="Vniversity">University</reg>,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Vniverse">Universe</reg> have scarce such miss, as I</line>
<line>Of your <unclear><reg orig="wisht">wished</reg></unclear> presence; their commons are short,</line>
<line>But mine are shorter <reg orig="then">than</reg> a snap at Court.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<head level="3"><i>Saturday April 1.</i></head>
<p>This day upon the Exchange there was a rumour that the King of Spain would render into the hands of the English, <em>Dunkirk</em> and the fort of <em>Mardike</em>, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> a peace should be concluded by us with the Lord Ambassadors of the <em>United Provinces</em>.</p>
<p>There is a Report that the Articles for peace were <reg orig="singned">signed</reg> and sealed on Friday late in the evening, between the English and the Dutch, which as it is said, was with much pains and great care on both sides, so that it is hoped the peace is now fully concluded.</p>
<p>Thus have you an account of</p>
<p><i>The signing and the Sealing of the Articles of Peace, between the English and the Dutch, with the taking of several ships by the English from the Dutch: And the report of the great <reg orig="profers">proffers</reg> of the King of Spain to the English, that they should not conclude a peace with the Dutch: The great <reg orig="murthers">murders</reg> committed by the bloody Rebels in Ireland, and many of them dying of the famine in the streets as they go. The great <reg orig="sadnesse">sadness</reg> of the Duke of <reg orig="Lorain">Lorraine</reg>: With other remarkable proceedings from several parts.</i></p>
<p><i>FINIS></i></p>
<p><em>London</em>: Printed for <em>F.N.</em> 1654.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>