<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MDem84">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Democritus, Issue 84</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Democritus</i></head>
<head level="2">OR</head>
<head level="2">A TRUE AND PERFECT</head>
<head level="1">NOCTURNALL,</head>
<head level="3"><i>Communicating many strange Wonders</i></head>
<head level="2">Out of the World in the Moon.</head>
<head level="3"><em>The Antipodes, Maggy-land, Tenebris, <reg orig="Fary-land">Fairyland</reg>, Green land</em>, and other adjacent Countries.</head>
<p>Published for the right understanding of all the Mad-merry-People of <em>Great-Bedlam</em>.</p> 
<hr />
<p><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> Febr. 1. to <em>Wednesday</em> February 8. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Fall back, fall edge, through thin and thick,</line>
<line>swift <em>Pegasus</em> <reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> <reg orig="trott">trot</reg>,</line>
<line>And if the <em>Jade</em> do wince or kick,</line>
<line>fill in the other <reg orig="Pott">Pot</reg>.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Stir up the Fire, my <em>Muse</em> is dull,</line>
<line>the Baggage will not <reg orig="flie">fly</reg>,</line>
<line>My <em><reg orig="Fancie">Fancy</reg></em> is not in the Full,</line>
<line>there is good reason why,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>But hang ill Luck, in flight of <em>Chance</em>,</line>
<line>by help of winged <em>Fame</em>,</line>
<line>My <reg orig="Witts">Wits</reg> shall the <em>Canaries</em> dance,</line>
<line>though <reg orig="leggs">legs</reg> and Verse run lame.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Call in the <em>Taber</em> and the <em>Pipe</em>,</line>
<line><em>Tobacco's</em> but a <reg orig="vaper">vapour</reg>,</line>
<line>And if the Boy bring <em>Ale</em> and <em>Light</em>,</line>
<line><reg orig="you'l">you'll</reg> see a Cripple caper.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A Pox on all ill luck, no matter, No chance, nor ill Fortune can dismay a <reg orig="Couragious">Courageous</reg> <reg orig="Minde">Mind</reg>, <reg orig="hee's">he's</reg> wretched that thinks himself to be so; I can <reg orig="indure">endure</reg> with<pb n="1" /> Patience, and that's a <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>; when the storm is over, there may be as great a Calm, if the cursed Hag <em><reg orig="Melancholly">Melancholy</reg></em> bring she not into a <em>Consumption</em>, I care not:</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line><reg orig="Maugre">Meagre</reg> her force, and so make envious Elves,</line>
<line>Punishing me, do mischief to themselves.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>This day (being Shrove Tuesday) a hardy Lad <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> <em>Barbican</em>, and seeing a Cock set down to be flung at, presently unbuttoned his Cloak, and giving it to one that stood by to hold, after flinging away two shillings and never touching the Cock, <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg> his Cloak, but the fellow that held it giving him the <reg orig="bagg">bag</reg>, his scratching of his Noddle perceived a <reg orig="Cox-combe">Coxcomb</reg> stuck in his Hatband, it is thought, by him that had his Cloak, which <em><reg orig="Cox-combe">Coxcomb</reg></em> (being a <reg orig="Gentlemans">Gentleman's</reg> son) is hereafter to be added to his Arms, to dub him a <em>New-made Gentleman</em>; As he went, away, a <reg orig="Brokers">Broker's</reg> Boy, crying at his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> door, <i><reg orig="Doe">Do</reg> ye want a Cloak or a Suit?</i> Yes sirrah, that I do, quoth the coxcomb, and you had best to restore it, or else <reg orig="ile">I'll</reg> charge ye with flat <reg orig="Fellony">Felony</reg>; so the <reg orig="Boyes">Boy's</reg> whooting after him, he went home a <reg orig="veryer">verier</reg> <reg orig="Cocks-combe">Cockscomb</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> he came out.</p>

<img src="" alt="two hens, crouched and facing each other in horizontally longer oval border" />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>And having lost his Witt, Money, and <reg orig="Cloake">Cloak</reg>,</line>
<line>The <em><reg orig="Cocks-combe">Cockscomb</reg></em> Gull, is by a Cock quite <reg orig="broake">broke</reg>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>An old Woman in <em>Corn-hill</em> being the same day making of <em>Fritters</em>, and not sending up her Apprentices any, that<pb n="2" /> were at work above in the <reg orig="Garrat">Garret</reg>, and smelling the scent of the <em>Fritters</em>, an unhappy Crack amongst them, slipping from the rest, got himself up into the Gutter, &amp; very <reg orig="mannerdly">mannerly</reg> surreverenc'd down the Chimney into a <reg orig="Kittle">Kettle</reg> of <em>Batter</em>, that hung over the Fire, three or four of her Kinsmen, with a neighbour or two, being invited to the eating thereof, they being <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> <reg orig="serv'd">served</reg> in to the Table, without the least mistrust, but in eating them, one having a better taste <reg orig="then">than</reg> the rest, <reg orig="relish'd">relished</reg> it something <reg orig="unsavery">unsavoury</reg> on the Palate, and told the good Woman, That surely her <i>Flour was grown</i>; no truly Neighbour, quoth she, <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> when I buy <reg orig="floure">flour</reg>, I knead it in my hand, and taste of it; sure quoth another, <i>It must needs be either Grown or Musty, for <reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> assure you it hath an <reg orig="odde">odd</reg> Taste;</i> with that the Old Woman putting a little <em>Fritter</em> into her mouth to taste, by accident happened on a Piece that the boy had <reg orig="dropt">dropped</reg> from the top of the Chimney, and chewing it in her mouth, presently spit it out again, Crying, <reg orig="gods">god's</reg> body Neighbours, It is surely grown indeed, How did this Knavish Meal-man deceive me? come <reg orig="Maide">Maid</reg> take them away, and carry them up to the Servants, <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> make no bones of them He warrant you.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>So they (like hungry <reg orig="Doggs">Dogs</reg> ) fell <reg orig="too">to</reg> in haste,</line>
<line>Whilst <em>Jack</em>, the <reg orig="Wagge">Wag</reg> would not so much as taste.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The young man that was like to have been ravished by the Lady that saw him Draw against the <em>Standard</em> in <em>Cheapside</em> the last week, is since contracted to the said Lady, who rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> she will marry the new <em>Way</em>, she is resolved to take his word for the first three Quarters, by which time she will try whether his Courage be answerable to his Weapon.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>If <em>Cupid's</em> Love-Dart want string, force, or might,</line>
<line><reg orig="Ther's">There's</reg> few Ladies, that in it take delight.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>The news from <em>Tripolo</em> is as followeth.</i></head>

<p>That the <em>Spaniards</em> are removing both the <em>Indies</em> into <em>Madrid</em> in <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> for fear of the <em>Dutch</em> and <em>French</em> <reg orig="Picroons">Picaroons</reg> that lie in the <em>Narrow-seas</em> expecting their <em>Plate-Fleet</em>, some report, they have hired a Magician to do it by Necromancy, as the stones were removed from <em>Ireland</em> to <em>Salisbury <reg orig="Plaine">Plane</reg></em>; If the News hold true, <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> is like to be the richest Country in <em>Europe</em>; and Gold and silver as <reg orig="plentifull">plentiful</reg> as <em>Chalk</em> is in <em>Malborow</em>: A Letter was lately intercepted in the Endimion, a ship sailing out of the Ocean of the Moon, signifying, how Prince <em>Mautico</em> with six <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of Ships was driven by a great <em><reg orig="Hurrycane">Hurricane</reg></em> into the Ocean of the <em>Moon</em>, where he was entertained in great state, by the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of the Moon, and feasted in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal in a Canopy bedecked with <reg orig="Starrs">Stars</reg>, the thunders were discharged round the Sky for joy, and great <reg orig="Bon-fires">Bonfires</reg> were made quite through the streets of the 12. Houses of the Heavens; after supper, came in the young <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg>, eldest Daughter to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, attended a Troop of <em>Synthian</em> Ladies, followed by many young Lords and Gentlemen, who all in order after the <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg>, saluted P. <em>Maurice</em>; after which began a <reg orig="Maske">Mask</reg>, with such variety of sweet <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg> and Dances, That the like was never heard by any Mortal ear before; his Brother the Prince of Plunderland hearing this <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>, is rigging a new fleet of ships to see if he can by the favour of next <em><reg orig="Hurrycane">Hurricane</reg></em>, sail up into <em>Cape Luna</em>, to see if he can <reg orig="repaire">repair</reg> his <reg orig="crak'd">cracked</reg> Fortune by marrying one of the <em>Phebean</em> Ladies; now the Taverns in <em>France</em> are become so incredulous, That they will of late hardly trust him with a Flap-<reg orig="Draggon">Dragon</reg>, or a Bottle of <em>Paris</em> Wine.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>This Outlandish <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> few think it true,</line>
<line>No matter so it sells, New, new, new, new.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="4" />

<head level="2">Oh the sad News out of Spittlefields; alas, alas for my old acquaintance <em>Nic. Culpepper. Mortus est</em>,</head>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>A man that thought all things came by Nature,</line>
<line><reg orig="Dy'd">Died</reg> even like any other Creature.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>Nay, he shall not want an <em><reg orig="Elegie">Elegy</reg></em> so long as <em>Dem</em>. Can hold a Pen, <em>Crast</em> and <em>Hay</em>, I see <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are all <reg orig="Mortall">Mortal</reg>, Who would have thought that Learned <em>Culpepper</em>, that could foretell whatever to poor <reg orig="Mortall">Mortal</reg> Wights befell, and every season of this young Infant Year, and all Events therein Declare, yet his own Death in's <reg orig="Scheam">Scheme</reg> did not appear, and though, and though in <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, more <reg orig="subtill">subtle</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> a <em>Quack</em>, yet <reg orig="dy'de">died</reg> before his yearly <reg orig="Almanack">Almanac</reg>.</p>

<p>But since he is dead, <reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> do so much for my <reg orig="disceased">deceased</reg> friend, as to invite the Guests, First for the Bearers, <em>Aries</em> shall carry his Head <reg orig="branch'd">branched</reg>, the <reg orig="studds">studs</reg> double gilt, Or, <reg orig="impal'd">impaled</reg> with Sables, on the <reg orig="upermost">uppermost</reg> of which shall be hung his Coat of Arms by the <reg orig="Herauld">Herald</reg> that <reg orig="blazon'd">blazoned</reg> them, <em>viz. Petricius Tenebrosus</em>, Governor of <em>Maggy-land</em>, <em>Taurus</em> shall carry his neck and throat, <em>Cancer</em> his breast and <reg orig="stomack">stomach</reg>; <em>Gemini</em> his Arms and shoulders, <em>Leo</em> his heart and Back, <em>Virgo</em> his <reg orig="Bowells">Bowels</reg> and Belly. <em>Libra</em> Reins and <reg orig="Loyns">Loins</reg>. <em>Scorpio</em> shall carry his <em>secret members</em>, <em><reg orig="Sagitarius">Sagittarius</reg></em> his Thighs, <em>Capricorn</em> his Knees, <em>Aquarias</em> his <reg orig="Leggs">Legs</reg>, and <em>Pisces</em> his feet; <em>Saturn</em> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> go next the Course in close mourning, with an heavy Aspect, <em>Mars, Jupiter</em> and <em>Luna</em> following in the like equipage, before him <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> go <em>fire</em>, carrying in one hand a flaming Torch, in the other the snuff of a Candle, in token of <em><reg orig="Mortallity">Mortality</reg></em>, <em><reg orig="AIRE">AIR</reg></em> shall come after, breathing out <reg orig="sighes">sighs</reg> and Groans, <em>Water</em> shall follow weeping, till she deliver<pb n="5" /> his Body safe to <em>Earth</em>, which shall be no sooner done, but the four <reg orig="Windes">Winds</reg>, namely <em>Favonius, Auster, Eurus</em> and <em>Aquillo</em> shall sing his <reg orig="funerall">funeral</reg> Dirge set to the tune of a new <em>Septentricnall</em> ligge; after these shall come the 4 <em>Ages</em>, viz. <em>Juventus, Adolesoentia, Virgens <unclear>&aelig;ras</unclear>, Senectus</em>, in their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> habits, bewailing his loss, after which shall follow the 4 <reg orig="Complections">Complexions</reg>, exercising their different <reg orig="Quallities">Qualities</reg>; after all this shall come all the Spirits of each region between heaven and hell, to convoy his soul to the <em><reg orig="Elizian">Elysian</reg> Shades</em>, and there to place him amongst the Ancients, <em><reg orig="Ptolme">Ptolemy</reg>, Tyobrache Gallen, Hippocrates</em>, &amp;c. <em>Rud, Booker</em>, and <em>Lilly</em>, are to take charge to see the 12 houses of the <em>Heavens</em> hung in mourning, for their care in seeing this <reg orig="perform'd">performed</reg>, they are to have New mourning suits of Celestial <reg orig="Broad-cloath">Broadcloth</reg> cut out of the <em>terebrosian Clouds</em>, and Belts <reg orig="imboss'd">embossed</reg> with black <reg orig="starrs">stars</reg>; His <reg orig="Liberary">Library</reg> are to be disposed to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Persons of note as his Learned Volume of the <em>Dispensatory</em> to the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg>, of <reg orig="Physitians">Physicians</reg>, and his translation of <em>Albertus Magnus</em> to each Student of the Black Art a <em>Book</em>, to teach them to Conjure up the Devil:</p>

<head level="2">His Epitaph.</head>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Here lies <em>Nick Culpepper</em> for want of breath</line>
<line>To drink of's <em>Sack</em>, was <reg orig="sack'd">sacked</reg> by Death,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Plannets">Planets</reg>, signs and stars in sable mourn,</line>
<line>To see their <em>Prophet</em> <reg orig="clos'd">closed</reg> in this sad <reg orig="Urne">Urn</reg>.</line>
<line><em>Fortune</em> did favour him, though he were wise,</line>
<line>And did supply his wants, even from the Skies;</line>
<line>Yet envious Death, cause <em><reg orig="Nicks">Nick's</reg></em> skill oft dies save;</line>
<line><reg orig="Strook">Struck</reg> him a <em>blow</em>, soon sent him to his grave.</line>
<line>Where rest in Patience; and <em>Patients</em> rest content,</line>
<line><em><reg orig="Nicks">Nick's</reg></em> Life like ours, alas a thing but lent,</line>
<line>When payable we know not, nor how soon,</line>
<line><em>Nick's</em> here <reg orig="ecclips'd">eclipsed</reg>, and changed like the Man:</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="6" />

<p>A little before the Death of this <em>Astrologer</em>, was seen by a blind Philosopher in Hounds-ditch, who described the sight he saw in the <reg orig="Ayre">Air</reg> to a Deaf <em>Tankard-bearer</em>, who relating it to a dumb <em>Oyster-woman</em>, she presently told it <em>Democritus</em>, who describes it after this Figure following;</p>

<img src="" alt="Image of a town, above it is a river or sea with a single ship on it, and above that a cloudy sky with canons and swords in it. Two figures stand on the right, one with a telescope pointed at the sky" />

<p>Also on Thursday last, the Rivers of <em>Thames</em> ebbing and flowing thrice in one Day, together with the <em>Blazing Star</em> seen over the <em>Thames</em> on Friday morning last, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Winsor">Windsor</reg></em> Castle, and <em>Democritus</em> straining his leg the day before, must needs portend the fall of some Learned man; But mum&mdash; for that, as Mr. <em><reg orig="Politique">Politic</reg> POST</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> pag. 1296. <i>'Tis good To be merry and wise, and very dangerous <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with <reg orig="edg'd">edged</reg> <reg orig="Tooles">Tools</reg>.</i></p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from <em>Wopping</em> is,</i></head>

<p>That on Wednesday come seven-night, in the halfway House on the <em>Thames</em> between <em>Black-wall</em> and <em><reg orig="Cuckolds">Cuckolds'</reg> Haven</em>, there was a great Dispute between the Spinsters of <em>Horsey-down</em>, and the <em>Linsy woolsey</em> Weavers of <em>Spittle fields</em>, The sum of the Dispute was,</p>

<p><i>Whether Cuckolds <reg orig="weare">wear</reg> <reg orig="Perriwiggs">Periwigs</reg>, or no?</i></p>

<p>The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> being put to the Vote, was by the <reg orig="Maior">Major</reg> part carried in the affirmative; till a Party of <reg orig="Sea-mens">Seamen's</reg> Wives from <em><reg orig="Ratcliff-high-way">Ratcliff highway</reg></em> stood up for the Negative, and quite carried it from the rest, and so passed an Edict, <i>That no Female hereafter should vent any such <reg orig="Herysies">Heresies</reg></i> against the <em>Cornucopians</em>, upon pain of being <reg orig="dsfranchized">disfranchised</reg> of her or their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Occupations.</p>

<p>A great Duel was fought <reg orig="latelly">lately</reg> in an Hand on the <em>Thames</em> between <em>London bridge</em> and <em>Lambeth</em>, between two armless <em>Watermen</em>; as soon as they had drew, and one wounded the other; the People came to part them, which they had no sooner done, but they asked the <reg orig="Water man">Waterman</reg> that was hurt, How they fell out? Who <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, He knew not, having never seen the other in all his Life. Then they <reg orig="ask'd">asked</reg> the other, How he came to draw upon one he never saw before, and so consequently could have no reason to be offended by him: To which the <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, That he had a <unclear>Quarrel</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 30 characters --></unclear> since the other <reg orig="Water-mans">Waterman's</reg> Boat had taken the Wall of his on the Thames.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>If <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg> do once fight for the Wall,</line>
<line>No wonder Land-men for less matters <reg orig="brall">brawl</reg>,</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

<p>London, printed by <em>J. <reg orig="Crowch">Crouch</reg></em>, and <em>T. W.</em> dwelling at the <em>3 Foxes</em> in <em>Long-Lane</em>. 1653.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>