<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MDem82">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Democritus, Issue 82</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Democritus</i></head>
<head level="2">OR</head>
<head level="2">A TRUE AND PERFECT</head>
<head level="1">NOCTURNAL,</head>
<head level="3">Communicating many strange Wonders</head>
<head level="2">Out of the WORLD in the MOON.</head>
<head level="3"><em>The Antipodes, Maggy-land, Tenebris, <reg orig="Fary-land">Fairyland</reg>, Green land</em>, and other adjacent Countries.</head>
<p><i>Published for the right understanding of all the Mad-merry People of <em>Great-Bedlam</em>.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> Novemb. 9. to <em>Wednesday</em> <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 25. 1653.</i></p>
<hr />

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line><i>Out from the Deep <em>Abyss</em> I come,</i></line>
<line><i>where <em>souls</em> in torments dwell</i></line>
<line><i>From <em>Prison</em>, as from living <reg orig="Tombe">Tomb</reg>,</i></line>
<line><i>An <em>Emblem</em> sure of Hell.</i></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line><i>Where <em>Cerberus</em> at Gate doth <reg orig="waite">wait</reg>,</i></line>
<line><i>to lock poor <reg orig="Mortalls">Mortals</reg> in,</i></line>
<line><i>But cursed <em>Money</em> is their <reg orig="Bayte">Bait</reg>,</i></line>
<line><i>when we come out <reg orig="agin">again</reg>.</i></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line><i>But oh! The torments of the <em>Hole</em>,</i></line>
<line><i>no <em><reg orig="Devills">Devils</reg></em> like their <em>Lice</em>,</i></line>
<line><i>Instead of <em>Brimstone</em> they burn <em><reg orig="Coale">Coal</reg></em>,</i></line>
<line><i>and of <em><reg orig="Mens">Men's</reg></em> bones <em>make Dice</em>.</i></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Heav'n keep me out, and grant my Pen,</line>
<line>no <reg orig="winceing">wincing</reg> Beast offend,</line>
<line>I lash at <em>Vice</em>, and not at men,</line>
<line>and so my Verses <em>End</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>What! A Hue-and-cry after Democritus? in the name of <em>Robin Hood</em> and <em>Little <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg></em> what art thou? I<pb n="1" /> charge thee by the golden Locks of <em>Apollo</em>, and the <em><reg orig="Scriech">Screech</reg> <reg orig="Owls">Owl's</reg></em> hoarse hollow, or fourth leg of a Swallow; by the eyes of a Mole, or a dead <reg orig="Witches">Witch's</reg> soul, appear in thy likeness, and answer me why thou makest all this cry, din, and <reg orig="clamor">clamour</reg> in the streets after me: if thou art the Ghost of the Aquarian Poet <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Taylor</em>, by <em><reg orig="Charons">Charon's</reg></em> Oar I charge thee speak, or <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> after hold thy tongue. Cannot a man sing Counter-<reg orig="tennor">tenor</reg> a little study <em>Lachrim&aelig;</em>, or view the inside of a prison, but he must be <reg orig="cry'd">cried</reg> all over the World? A pretty conceit I promise you, and very worth the laughter; but since you dare me to appear, here I am in my own likeness, being never more merry, nor having less cause: And therefore stand <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg>, for I will begin with the whipping of the blind Bear; I fear none but those lades that are <reg orig="gall'd">galled</reg> or guilty, and for them my invincible <reg orig="Gooses">Goose's</reg> Quill dares to the encounter, as long as I can buy a pen and ink, paper or vinegar, <reg orig="wyer">wire</reg> or whipcord, Wormwood or Gall, have at ye blind Harpers, I doubt not either of a Muse or Genius to administer them, without scandal, sedition, or danger of the Law, or blemish to any honest or true <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Reputation: A Poet can easily revenge the greatest injury; and <reg orig="leysurely">leisurely</reg> pull out of the <reg orig="poysonous">poisonous</reg> teeth of those of <em>Envies Whelps</em>, that <reg orig="maligne">malign</reg> his free and inoffensive mirth; but I am too merciful: For those Gentlemen (his friends) lovers of Wit, Mirth, or Ingenuity, to such he owes all grateful respects, not doubting again of their favourable entertainment and acceptance.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>I study mirth, and yet (dear friends) 'tis <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg>,</line>
<line><reg orig="Buyes">Buys</reg> paper, ink, or the rich sparkling wine.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="2" />

<p>Two Ladies of the Night walking the Rounds <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Cuckolds">Cuckold's</reg> Pound, were Planet struck in their Tutchholes, and presently by an old Quack, that formerly had been a Prigger of <reg orig="hookes">hooks</reg>, <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> into a Toping school, where they were no sooner <reg orig="entred">entered</reg>, but the Ladies were strongly taken one after the other with Fits of the Falling-sickness; for whose Cure a merry Drawer in the house prescribed this Remedy.</p>

<p>Truly Gentlemen, quoth he, if you are ever hereafter troubled with the Falling-sickness, it will not be amiss for you to forbear <reg orig="physick">physic</reg>; especially Suppositories and Glisters: Neither is it good for you to travel Westward Ho, because of avoiding the Isle of Man. And for that doubtless it is an evil Spirit <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into you, you must for a Charm have <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> your Legs a cross when you are not walking; and that perhaps in time may chance to cure you. After this came in the Merry Drawer with a Cup of Wine in his hand, a blind <reg orig="Fidler">Fiddler</reg> and his Boy, and presented them with this Song:</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Ladies of Chamber, Closet, <reg orig="Kitchin">Kitchen</reg>,</line>
<line>Troubled with cold or itching,</line>
<line>Come give but me a kiss or two,</line>
<line>And here's that shall cure you:</line>
<line>Not <em>Gallen</em> but <em><reg orig="Hypocrates">Hippocrates</reg></em></line> 
<line>Can <reg orig="e're">e'er</reg> perform such cures as these.</line><pb n="3" />
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Here's <em>Siss</em> that cannot hold her Water,</line>
<line>And <em>Sue</em> that cracks <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg> with laughter,</line>
<line>Here's <em>Nan</em> with Barn, <em><reg orig="Iones">Joan's</reg></em> placket torn,</line>
<line>A Citt that wants cure for his Horn.</line>
<line><em>Not Gallen; but <reg orig="Hyppocrates">Hippocrates</reg>, &amp;c.</em></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Here's <em>Meg, Moll, Kate</em>, Maids of the <reg orig="Dayrie">Dairy</reg>,</line>
<line>But last night blew-<reg orig="nipt">nipped</reg> by a <reg orig="Fayrie">Fairy</reg>,</line>
<line>For making Butter with their <reg orig="tailes">tails</reg>,</line>
<line>Green-sickness Bess for what she <reg orig="ailes">ails</reg>,</line>
<line><em>Not Gallen; but <reg orig="Hyppocrates">Hippocrates</reg>, &amp;c.</em></line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Here's <em>Peg</em> hath had a touch too much,</line>
<line>And <em>Jane</em> and <em><reg orig="Megg">Meg</reg></em>, and twenty such</line>
<line><reg orig="Oth'">O'th'</reg> Falling-sickness that complain,</line>
<line>this Glass holds care for all their <reg orig="paine">pain</reg>.</line>
<line><em>Not Gallen; but <reg orig="Hyppocrates">Hippocrates</reg>, &amp;c.</em></line>
<line><em>Could <reg orig="ere">e'er</reg> perform such cures as these.</em></line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The old Lecherous Culle, perceiving himself <reg orig="smoak'd">smoked</reg> by the Whidling Drawer, that, as he conceived, had <reg orig="stowted">stouted</reg> him in this Song, suddenly removed his brace of <em><reg orig="Mobbs">Mobs</reg></em> to fresh Quarters in <em>Pasty-nook</em>, where after he had victualled his <em><reg orig="Mobbs">Mobs</reg></em>, he <reg orig="Intrenched">Entrenched</reg> himself for that Night, without being any whit molested in beating up their Quarters; but early in the morning the <reg orig="sorded">sordid</reg> Cullee being in a deep sleep, the <em><reg orig="Mobbs">Mobs</reg></em> very honestly <reg orig="pick'd">picked</reg> his Pockets, nipping him of a good round sum, and so <reg orig="slipt">slipped</reg> <reg orig="down staires">downstairs</reg>, and left him (like an <em>Old <reg orig="Boobee">Booby</reg></em>) in the lurch; he hath since been in <em>Thieving-lane</em> to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> out the Wenches, but to no purpose.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>I wish all Lecherous K----s were <reg orig="serv'd">served</reg> no worse,</line>
<line>That for their Lust, regard not soul, nor Purse.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="4" />

<p>A musty Citt. <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> not long since well Toppyfi'd from hunting in the Purleys of <em>Bun hill</em>, chanced in his way home to take up a fine little <reg orig="foysting">foisting</reg>-hound, which he thought to carry home, to present to the Cuck-q&mdash; his Wife, but <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> homeward through <em>Cole-man-street</em>, to <em>Lawrence Lane</em>, (being an old Gamester) he bethought himself of the Bowling-Alley; yet his <reg orig="braines">brains</reg> running a long <reg orig="byas">bias</reg>, he conceiving himself <reg orig="uncapable">incapable</reg> of Play, thought to <reg orig="Bett">Bet</reg> a shilling or two, to recover some part of that <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> charges, yet his <reg orig="Dogg">Dog</reg> troubling him, he at last bethought him to put him up in his <reg orig="Cod-piece">Codpiece</reg>, but being overcharged with liquor, yet very <reg orig="intentive">attentive</reg> in looking after the Bowls, he turning to the wall to make Water, mistaking his hold, pulled out the <reg orig="Doggs">Dog's</reg> <reg orig="tayle">tail</reg> out of his <reg orig="Cod-piece">Codpiece</reg>, and so holding it to the Wall, plentifully bewatered his defiled garments which run out at his knees all about the Ally; two Bowls were drowned thereby, the rest run the <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> above four <reg orig="yeards">yards</reg> from the <em>Jack</em> for fear; which caused great laughter in all the Company.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Had the poor Dog had so much <reg orig="witt">wit</reg>,</line>
<line>When he had <reg orig="pist">pissed</reg>, he would have shit.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg> and a <reg orig="Wolfe">Wolf</reg> not long since set upon <em><reg orig="Demecritus">Democritus</reg></em>, and had devoured both him and his Family, had he not been relieved by <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>, the conflict was very sore, and had not relief come, he had ended his mirth in <em>Lachrym&aelig;</em>; the Wolf is to be hanged in <reg orig="Satirick">Satiric</reg> <reg orig="Iambiqe">Iambic</reg> line, made of juice of <em><reg orig="Hounds">Hound's</reg> foot</em>, the Lion to be cut in pieces with a <reg orig="woodden">wooden</reg> Chopping-knife, whilst <em>Democritus</em> is quietly permitted to go on with his honest labours.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>Some I suppose may have a fancy of desire to hear some News out of the Counter-hole before I begin <em>Hinc Lachryme</em>, ----- Here might you see DEMOCRITUS turned into HERACLITUS, ------ the Remembrance of it is so grievous, that my Pen bleeds to think of it, seeming <reg orig="in stead">instead</reg> of ink to shed tears; I may well compare it to three Emblems: the first is a Bawdy-house, or a Bawdy house of it, wherein is nothing to be seen but a few <reg orig="lowsie">lousy</reg> Beds, and bare walls, and some <reg orig="banckrout">bankrupt</reg> Unthrifts, <reg orig="scribling">scribbling</reg> to their friends for money to redeem them from their large Reckonings. Next, I might well compare that prison to a ship, the Master-side being the Upper-Deck; the Hole being the place for <reg orig="Balast">Ballast</reg>, or Under-hatches: they have <reg orig="Cabbins">Cabins</reg> indeed; but from lodging in them, Lord deliver poor DEMOCRITUS, and all his Friends; and for his Enemies, God grant they may never have a worse punishment betide them: intricate Cases are the Tacklings, Executions the Anchors, <reg orig="Capiasses">Capiases</reg> the Cables, Chancery Bills the huge <reg orig="Sayls">Sails</reg>, a long Term the Mast, Law the Helm, a Judge the <reg orig="Pylot">Pilot</reg>, a <reg orig="Councellor">Councillor</reg> the Purser, an Attorney the <reg orig="Boat-swain">Boatswain</reg>, his steering Clerk the Swabber, Bonds the Waves, <reg orig="Outlaries">Outlawries</reg><pb n="6" /> Gusts, the Verdicts of Juries rough Winds, Extents the Rocks that split all to pieces: All the difference between a ship and a prison being this; the one is a moving misery; and the other a standing one. That it is a Hell, who can imagine otherwise, when he shall hear the hideous <reg orig="ratling">rattling</reg> of chains, <reg orig="hand-cuffs">handcuffs</reg>, bolts, Guives and fetters, entered, you shall meet with persons of all conditions; one wringing his hands; another laughing; another swearing and cursing; one blaming Destiny; another, Luck; another, Fortune that brought him thither: one crying out of his <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> wife: another of his false friend; another of his hard Creditor, that all like the Devil, and the seven deadly sins, laboured to bring him to that place of horror, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> Lawyers and <reg orig="Jaylors">Jailers</reg> like <reg orig="promethian">promethean</reg> Vultures gnaw asunder the very <reg orig="heart-strings">heartstrings</reg> of the poor persecuted prisoners; being admitted into the Society or Fraternity of these Prison-patients, infected with the City pestilence, you may perceive the Plague Sores of the Law to be the offending and disturbent Diseases that infects the place.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Vexing, grieving, plaguing prisoners worse,</line>
<line><reg orig="Then">Than</reg> all Diseases, or their <reg orig="Makers">Maker's</reg> curse,</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="7" />

<p>Being once <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> in this Trojan-Horse, you must expect the <em>Nullum Vacuum</em> in your guts, that though you be never such a Coward when you come in, yet in three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> you will have an admirable <reg orig="stomack">stomach</reg>; besides, like Hell, it is very <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to come in thither, but very rare and never to get out again. But oh! The Torments of the Hole! There might you see poor <em><reg orig="Democrutus">Democritus</reg></em> turned <em>Heraclitus</em>, beholding the poor souls lie grovelling on the bare <reg orig="boords">boards</reg>, tormented with Racabites and Moabites: the one being bit with these Hellish Vermin, kicking his heels unto his <reg orig="bed-fellows">bedfellow's</reg> mouth; a fire indeed they have which torments them the more, because they have not enough fitting, as if they had none at all: when I saw this I seriously conceived the sight thereof was more sad <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other object in the world, and Democritus had been suddenly translated into Melancholicus, had not a fellow sat sleeping before the small fire, and another <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> a pot of water of about 3 pints and after three motions, offering it towards him, slung it in his face, which caused me to return to my merry Cue of laughter, to see how like a <reg orig="drown'd">drowned</reg> Rat the fellow rose, shook his <reg orig="eares">ears</reg>, looked about him, and answered not a word.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>I asked him what it meant, he told me <em>Owling</em>,</line>
<line>If so, quoth I, the Devil's here a <em>fowling</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The last letters from Leaden-Hall street make mention of one Margery May, a Sowce-woman, <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> to <reg orig="Gyllian">Gillian</reg> a Brainford, that this last Christmas was apprehended by a blind leather-<reg orig="ear'd">eared</reg> Constable for selling Bag-puddings, <reg orig="in stead">instead</reg> of Collars of Brawn; the deceit <reg orig="shee">she</reg> used was (as my intelligence gives it) to get the largest sprig of Rosemary she could provide, and to sprinkle the same over with <reg orig="flowr">flower</reg> or white salt finely beat, by which trick, she hath deceived many purblind Cits, that having something hanging in their light could not distinguish the pudding from the brawn: the Sowce-woman pleads innocence, <reg orig="aleaging">alleging</reg> she brought her Ware into the open Market, and there sold it; and if it were the ignorance of any to buy it, mistaking one thing for another, the fault was in them, and not in <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>: she is committed to <em>Barcardo</em> by Justice <em>Humkin</em>, and is to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> next Christmas by a Jury of Pudding-wives. Of this more hereafter.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Your Mothers (Sirs) going a gooding,</line>
<line>if you had not been dull,</line>
<line>Had taught you to know Brawn from Pudding,</line>
<line>or an Ox from a Bull.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<hr />

<p>London, Printed for <em>G. HORTON</em>, 1653.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>