<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MDem86">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Democritus, Issue 86</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Democritus,</i></head>
<head level="2"><i>OR,</i></head>
<head level="2">A TRUE AND PERFECT</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="NOCTURNALL">NOCTURNAL</reg>,</head>
<head level="3"><i>Communicating many strange Wonders</i></head>
<head level="2">Out of the World in the Moon.</head>
<head level="3"><em>The Antipodes, Maggy-land, Tenebris, <reg orig="Fary-land">Fairyland</reg>, Green land</em>, and other adjacent Countries.</head>
<p>Published for the right understanding of all the Mad-merry-People of <em>Great-Bedlam</em>.</p> 
<hr />
<p><em>From</em> Wednesday <em>Febr</em>. 15. to Wednesday <em>February</em>. 22. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>When <em>Moles</em> do fly, and mount the Skies,</line>
<line>and <em>Eagles</em> build in Earth,</line>
<line>When th' <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> in the water dies,</line>
<line>her Ashes gives new birth.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>A Poor man may in <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> be rich,</line>
<line>the rich in <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> poor,</line>
<line>Some that are <reg orig="blinde">blind</reg>, fear not the Ditch,</line>
<line>a K&mdash; will love a Whore.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>The <em>Bedlam</em> World is sure <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> Witch,</line>
<line>and <em>Money</em> is her Imp,</line>
<line>And many men fat, fine and rich,</line>
<line>do to her <em>folly's</em> Pimp.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Give me on humble, merry heart,</line>
<line>to suffer any ill,</line>
<line>And from good <em>Conscience</em> not to start,</line>
<line>till <em>Death</em> my Body kill.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>This Week Gentlemen, a <em>Man</em> or a <em>Mouse</em>; Either <em>exit Democritus</em>, or Enter <em>Hiraclitus</em>; No matter, cheer up, as long as thy <em>Cause</em> is honest, and Conscience <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg>, the<pb n="1" /> threats of <reg orig="brain-sick">brainsick</reg> enemies cannot daunt thee; so long as <em>Justice</em> and <em>Equity</em> takes my part, I fear none but God and his Substitutes, and <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> avoid <em>D&aelig;mon</em>, I <reg orig="uterly">utterly</reg> <reg orig="defie">defy</reg> thee and all thy Works.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>And in my <reg orig="Mirthfull">Mirthful</reg> harmless <em>Cue</em></line>
<line>Base <em><reg orig="Spight">Spite</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Envie">Envy</reg></em> will subdue.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>There is a Physician lately come out of <em>Tenebris</em> that helps any <em>Gentleman Usher</em> of the Consumption in the legs this <em>Lent</em> by eating of Veal, which will wonderfully increase their <em>Calves</em> in one <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>; Or if any Virgin be sick of <em>Cupid</em>, that her Disease grow to a <em>Tympanie</em>, let her with all speed possible remove <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, changing the <reg orig="Aire">Air</reg> for 40. Weeks after, keeping very spare <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg> when she travels, ever after using <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> <reg orig="Exercizes">Exercises</reg>, till the Party be married, and then she is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> danger. If any Lady be sick of the <em>Sullens</em>, she knows not where, let her take a <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> of <em>Simples</em>, I know not what, and use them I know not how, applying them to the place grieved, I know not which, and she shall be cured I know not when. If any <em><reg orig="Scholler">Scholar</reg></em> be troubled with an <em>Itch</em> or breaking out, which in short time may prove the <em><reg orig="Skurvy">Scurvy</reg></em>; let him forbear <em>clawing</em> or fretting meats, especially eating Eggs with <em>Chickens</em> in them; and so after dinner <reg orig="stroak">stroke</reg> his temples with <em>fasting-<reg orig="Spittell">Spittle</reg></em>, and so purge <em><reg orig="Choller">Choler</reg></em>, but by any means upwards. If any be troubled with the <em>Tentigo</em>, he must <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> to <em>Japan</em>, or because the <em>Coven-Garden</em> is of the same altitude and Elevation of the Pole, and a shorter Voyage, let him but <em>hunt</em> there one afternoon for his Recreation, and it shall be done in an instant; the readiest way to <em>start</em> the <em>Game</em>, is to have an eye up to the Bell-<reg orig="conyes">conies</reg>, where a Knight of micckle same the other day courted a Brace of <em>Drury-lane</em> Ladies, making them <reg orig="shew">show</reg> their fine <em><reg orig="imbroider'd">embroidered</reg> toes</em> <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the <reg orig="railes">rails</reg>, to <reg orig="spight">spite</reg> and vex his poor distressed Wife, who (poor Lady) works hard for a Groat or Six-pence a day to keep her alive; Oh <reg orig="shamelesse">shameless</reg> impudence of men and Women in these inconstant times.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> be <reg orig="troudled">troubled</reg> with a <em><reg orig="Fellon">Felon</reg></em> on his finger, whereby he hath lost the <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> use of his Hand; let him but once use the <reg orig="exercize">exercise</reg> of swinging, and stretch but himself upon the <reg orig="Soveraigne">Sovereign</reg> Tree on <em>Paddington <reg orig="Faire">Fair</reg></em> Day, It will certainly kill the <reg orig="Fellon">Felon</reg>. If any Lady be married, and cannot have a <reg orig="Childe">Child</reg> in 3 quarters after, if she have but a longing Desire to be a Mother, let her eat to her Breakfast a <em>new-laid <reg orig="Egge">Egg</reg></em> in a <reg orig="spoonfull">spoonful</reg> of <em><reg orig="Goats">Goat's</reg> Milk</em>, with a scruple of <em>Amber-<reg orig="greece">grease</reg></em>, and at supper feed on a <em>Hen</em> <reg orig="traoden">trodden</reg> but by one Cock, and above all things, to <reg orig="avoide">avoid</reg> hurrying in <em>Hackney Coaches</em>, especially on the <em>Stones</em>, or thinketh by Paintings, Patches, Frizzlings, <reg orig="Powdrings">Powderings</reg> or Perfumings to mend what Nature made; and no doubt she shall increase and <reg orig="fructifie">fructify</reg>, suddenly after. If any <em>Lapland</em> Merchant be burst, or troubled with a Rupture in his Estate, so that he cannot go abroad to make <em>Water</em>, let him decoct Gold from a Pound to a Noble; taking the Broth thereof from 6 <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg> to six <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg>, and he shall afterwards be assured at the <em>Assurance</em> Office, in a short time after, to be as Able a Man as ever he was. If any be <reg orig="Deafe">Deaf</reg>, Lame, <reg orig="Blinde">Blind</reg>, or any <em>bound</em>, or <em>loose <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg></em>, if Ladies <reg orig="foule">foul</reg>, would be made fair, have new Powder, or new <reg orig="Haire">Hair</reg>, if any dream or walk by Night, are troubled with the Mare or <reg orig="Spright">Sprite</reg>, be <reg orig="Drumms">Drums</reg>, or Rattles in thy head, are not thy Brains well tempered, Do's &AElig;olus thy <reg orig="stomack">stomach</reg> gnaw, hast Worms or Vermin in thy Maw, dost thou desire young Maids to please, here's the best <em>Cantharides</em>, all Diseases that arise from ill-disposed Crudities, of <reg orig="lazie">lazy</reg> <reg orig="Gowt">Gout</reg>, I Cure the rich, and rid the <reg orig="Begger">Beggar</reg> of the Itch, I <reg orig="steame">steam</reg> avoid both thick &amp; thin, I dislocated <reg orig="joynts">joints</reg> put in, I can lost <em><reg orig="Maiden-heads">Maidenheads</reg></em> restore, and do ten Thousand Cures more.</p>

<head level="2">Probatum est.</head>

<p><i>I lie at the <em>Flying <reg orig="Horse-shooe">Horseshoe</reg></em> in <em>Honesty</em> street, and am constantly at home between Twelve and 16. in the <reg orig="fore-noon">forenoon</reg>; You may inquire for <em>Doctor Fumigosus</em> the English Italian, who will at those hours be ready to attend you.</i></p><pb n="3" />

<p>The last News from <em>Westminster, Feb. 13.</em> make mention of a terrible bloody <reg orig="Battell">Battle</reg> between the Watermen and Hackney-Coachmen, who fell out in the <reg orig="Palace-yard">Palace yard</reg>, which should carry a <em>Fair</em> to <em>Lambeth</em> cheapest; from words they fell to blows, and so began the <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>; a Waterman gave the onset with his <em>Stretcher</em>, and <em><reg orig="plyed">plied</reg></em> it home so roundly, that his Noddle saluted his <em><reg orig="Coach-horses">Coach-horse's</reg></em> heels; with that the rest of the <em><reg orig="Hackny">Hackney</reg>-men</em> began to shoot brickbats from the <em>Mortar-pieces</em> in their Coach-boxes so thick that two <reg orig="Sculls">Skulls</reg> were broke, and such streams of blood issued there from them, that the <em>Fountain</em> in the <em><reg orig="Pallace-Yeard">Palace yard</reg></em> was drowned therewith; They kept such a bawling, that if the <em>Lawyers</em> had not formerly been acquainted with it, an <em>Order</em> doubtless would have been taken with them; but the <em><reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg></em> being more <em>fair-conditioned</em> <reg orig="then">than</reg> the Coachmen, at last yielded to a Treaty; <em>The first man</em> being an <em><reg orig="Oare">Oar</reg></em> just come <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg>, <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> the great and insufferable injuries they sustained by the multitudes of <em>Hackney-Coaches</em>, next to <em>London-bridge</em> a great <em>Frost</em>, and a <em>Press</em> of <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg>, the most grievous <reg orig="eye-sore">eyesore</reg> to them as could be; The Coachman made but a round Reply to the business, <em>driving</em> very home for the usefulness of Coaches, <reg orig="alledging">alleging</reg> in these faithless times, <i>Men had rather trust themselves five miles by Land, <reg orig="then">than</reg> half a mile by Water,</i> by reason of <em>sudden</em> storms and dangers that very often and unexpectedly, whereby many had been formerly drowned; whereupon they put the case between both parties to Arbitration, binding themselves by an <em>Assumsit</em> to stand to the <em>Arbitrament</em> of two men that were neither <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg> nor <reg orig="Coach-men">Coachmen</reg>, who in short time gave up the Result, That the <reg orig="Coach-men">Coachmen</reg> should drive by Water, and the <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg> row by Land; and so both parties rest well content, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that <em>London-bridge</em> and great <em>Frosts</em> should not molest <em>Coaches</em> nor <em><reg orig="Coach-men">Coachmen</reg></em> as they had formerly done <em><reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg></em>.</p><pb n="4" />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>And so this <reg orig="Quarrell">Quarrel</reg> was soon taken up,</line>
<line>And they made friends, did end all in a Cup</line>
<line>Of Rich <em>Canary</em>, that brave <em><reg orig="Fancie">Fancy</reg></em> can</line>
<line>Carry <em>swifter</em> <reg orig="then">than</reg> Coach or Waterman.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>At the closing up of this difference, a Letter was brought to a <reg orig="Water-man">Waterman</reg>, that a servant of his that was formerly <reg orig="Prest">Pressed</reg>, was drowned by an accident, whereupon reading the same he <reg orig="fetch'd">fetched</reg> a great sigh, saying, <i>Alas, Alas, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> is gone the way of all Flesh:</i> You had said true; quoth a Coachman, if he had miscarried on Land, but miscarrying by water, I rather think your servant <i>is gone the way of <reg orig="al">all</reg> Fish</i>; At which answer all the Company laughed, and so the <reg orig="Coach-men">Coachmen</reg> took their way <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the <em>Thames</em>, and the <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg> rowed home <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the streets well elevated with good Liquor, much peace and amity having been between them ever since.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>All parties so I hope will soon agree,</line>
<line>And then for <em>France</em>, brave Lads, away go we.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A <reg orig="sorrowfull">sorrowful</reg>, but loving Son of the <em>Muses</em>, for the untimely fall of his dear Father, penned this mournful <em>Dirge</em> or <em>Ditty</em> in the <em>Antipodes</em>, which being very pithy, I have here exposed to the view of all those that love their <reg orig="Fathers">Father's</reg> <em>Money</em> better <reg orig="then">than</reg> his <em>Person</em> or <em>Life</em>:</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>In sad and Ashy weeds,</line>
<line>I sigh, I sob, I pine, I mourn,</line>
<line>My Oat and yellowed Reeds,</line>
<line>I know to Jett and Ebon turn,</line>
<line>My wretched eyes,</line>
<line>Like Winter Skies,</line>
<line>My sorrows, cheeks <reg orig="o're flow">o'erflow</reg>,</line>
<line>All Heavens knows why,</line>
<line>Men mourn as I,</line>
<line>And who can blame my <reg orig="wo">woe</reg>.</line>
</stanza><pb n="5" />
<stanza>
<line>In fable Robes of Night,</line>
<line>my <reg orig="Dayes">Days</reg> of joy <reg orig="apparell'd">apparelled</reg> be,</line>
<line>My sorrow sees no Light,</line>
<line>My Eyes through sorrow nothing see.</line>
<line>For why my <em>Sun</em>,</line>
<line>His <reg orig="daies">days</reg> hath run,</line>
<line>And from his <em>Sphere</em> doth <reg orig="goe">go</reg>,</line>
<line>To endless Bed,</line>
<line>Of folded Lead,</line>
<line>And who can blame my Woe?,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>My Flock I now forsake,</line>
<line>That <reg orig="senceless">senseless</reg> <em>sheep</em> my grief may know,</line>
<line>And <em><reg orig="Lillies">Lilies</reg></em> loath to take,</line>
<line>That since his fall, presume to grow,</line>
<line>I hate the <reg orig="Aire">Air</reg>,</line>
<line>Because it dare,</line>
<line>To breath, and He not so,</line>
<line>A vault now doth,</line>
<line><reg orig="Intombe">Entomb</reg> his worth.</line>
<line>And who can blame my woe?,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Aye me, poor Lad, alone,</line>
<line>Alone how can such sorrow be,</line>
<line>Not only men make <reg orig="moane">moan</reg>,</line>
<line>But more <reg orig="then">than</reg> men make <reg orig="moane">moan</reg> for thee;</line>
<line>The gods of green,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Mountains">Mountain's</reg> Queen,</line>
<line>The fair and sacred Row,</line>
<line>The <em><reg orig="Nimphs">Nymphs</reg></em> <reg orig="devine">divine</reg>,</line>
<line>The <em>Muses</em> nine</line>
<line>Do all condole my woe.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Thou awful guider of the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg>,</line>
<line>(If Shepherd may the question thus)</line>
<line>What Death could supply,</line>
<line>To take away his gentle breath from us?</line><pb n="6" />
<line>Is <em>Hermes</em> fled,</line>
<line>Is <em>Cupid</em> dead,</line>
<line>Doth <em>Sol</em> his Sphere <reg orig="forgoe">forgo</reg>,</line>
<line>Or <em>Jove</em> his joy,</line>
<line>Is <reg orig="stol'n">stolen</reg> from <em>Troy</em>;</line>
<line>O who can blame my Woe.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Did not mine Eyes, O heaven,</line>
<line>Adore your worth as much before,</line>
<line>As now unto your seven,</line>
<line>You added have one <em><reg orig="Plannet">Planet</reg></em> more:</line>
<line>Well may you raise</line>
<line>Now double <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>,</line>
<line>And your black shine <reg orig="bestowe">bestow</reg>,</line>
<line>Your powers have won,</line>
<line>Another SUN,</line>
<line>And who can blame my woe.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Yet at your hands I <reg orig="aske">ask</reg>,</line>
<line>This boon, which you may easily grant,</line>
<line>That I in endless Mask,</line>
<line>Of sorrow may condole His want;</line>
<line>Sure <em>His</em> Devine</line>
<line>Parts with you shine,</line>
<line>Too good for us below,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Earths">Earth's</reg> black breast,</line>
<line>His <reg orig="bodies">body's</reg> rest,</line>
<line>Can I <reg orig="intombe">entomb</reg> him so?</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>Bless me! what a strange Dream have had <reg orig="to Night">tonight</reg>? Methought I see the World <reg orig="dash'd">dashed</reg> into a second <em>Chaos</em>, the <em><reg orig="Axeltree">Axletree</reg></em> of Heaven gave such a <em>Crack</em> it <reg orig="fear'd">feared</reg> me! Oh my <reg orig="desceased">deceased</reg> FATHER! Oh his distempered Son! I cannot speak for <em>Weeping</em>.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Oh heavenly Powers, let it not be thus</line>
<line>Another <em>Night</em> with poor <em>Democritus</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="7" />

<p><i>The last Letter from <em>Constantinople</em>, make mention of a <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> accident, That happened there the last moon-shiny-Night; The Letter speaks as followeth,</i></p>

<p><i>SIR,</i></p>

<p>I presume you have heard the News in the <em>Antipodes</em> of the unexpected fall of <em><reg orig="Mahumets">Mahomet's</reg> <reg orig="Tombe">Tomb</reg></em>, but the reason of the fall being hid from our eyes, is since miraculously discovered to be thus; The <em>Man in the Moon</em> wearing <em>Hobnails</em> on his <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, just when the <em>Moon</em> passing over in the <reg orig="Equanoctiall">Equinoctial</reg> of that Country, being in an <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> Conjunction with <em>Mars</em>, caused so great a heat in the Sun, that the <em><reg orig="Hobnailes">Hobnails</reg></em> in the Man in the <em><reg orig="Moons">Moon's</reg></em> <!-- "shooen" alt. Plrl for shoe?-->shun melting the Leads of the <em>Church</em> where he hung, the <em><reg orig="Load-stone">Loadstone</reg></em> fixed thereto had violently drawn the <em>Man</em> quite out of the <em>Moon</em>, had he not by great accident caught hold of his <reg orig="Doggs">Dog's</reg> <reg orig="taile">tail</reg>, who to save his Master, clasped his <reg orig="fore-feet">forefeet</reg> on the horns of the <em>Moon</em>, and so held his Master up fast, till the <em><reg orig="Load-stone">Loadstone</reg></em> had <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to his <em><reg orig="Hob-nailes">Hobnails</reg></em>, at which instant of time <em><reg orig="Mahumets">Mahomet's</reg></em> <reg orig="Tombe">Tomb</reg>, that had hung up so many hundred years, fell on the sudden to the ground, which caused such great astonishment in the People, that they run all mad, being so <reg orig="lunatick">lunatic</reg>, That they could never be brought to their <reg orig="witts">wits</reg> since; but what is most strange, the <em><reg orig="Load-stone">Loadstone</reg></em> hanging at the <em>Man</em> in the <em><reg orig="Moons">Moon's</reg></em> <reg orig="shooe">shoe</reg>, hath since that time drawn up <reg orig="in to">into</reg> the Clouds the great <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> of <em>Constantinople</em>, and many other Cities in the <em><reg orig="Turks">Turks'</reg></em> Dominions; which lament the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of their goodly buildings,</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Now deeming <em><reg orig="Mahumet">Mahomet</reg></em> a Fable,</line>
<line>They once <reg orig="ador'd">adored</reg> as Venerable.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

<p>London, printed by <em>J. <reg orig="Crowch">Crouch</reg></em>, and <em>T.W.</em> dwelling at the <em>3 Foxes</em> in <em><reg orig="Long-Lane">Long Lane</reg></em>. 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>