<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MDem85">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Democritus, Issue 85</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Democritus,</i></head>
<head level="2"><i>OR,</i></head>
<head level="2">A TRUE AND PERFECT</head>
<head level="1">NOCTURNALL,</head>
<head level="3"><i>Communicating many strange Wonders</i></head>
<head level="2">Out of the World in the Moon.</head>
<head level="3"><em>The Antipodes, Maggy-land, Tenebris, <reg orig="Fary-land">Fairyland</reg>, Green land</em>, and other adjacent Countries.</head>
<p><i>Published for the right understanding of all the Mad-merry-People of <em>Great-Bedlam</em>.</i></p> 
<hr />
<p><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> Febr. 8. to <em>Wednesday</em> February. 15. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Of <em>Green-Land</em> Rights, and dismal Sights,</line>
<line>in Water, Earth and Skies,</line>
<line>Of <em>Blazing <reg orig="Starrs">Stars</reg></em>, Meteors, and <em>Lights</em>,</line>
<line>old Women can't tell Lies.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Of sixteen <em>Tides</em>, and fourteen Ebbs,</line>
<line>of <reg orig="raineing">raining</reg> Blood, Salt, <reg orig="Wheate">Wheat</reg>,</line>
<line>Of <em><reg orig="Froggs">Frogs</reg></em> that do <reg orig="spie">spy</reg> <reg orig="Spiders">Spider's</reg> <reg orig="Webbs">Webs</reg>,</line>
<line>and Wonders far more great.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line><reg orig="Colechester">Colchester</reg> <reg orig="Doggs">Dogs</reg> <unclear>him</unclear> they did fight,</line>
<line>must needs Presage a Change,</line>
<line>When Day is past, then <reg orig="commeth">cometh</reg> Night,</line>
<line>oh this is very strange.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Of Tales and Stories past belief,</line>
<line>of <em>Springs</em> that late are dry,</line>
<line>And of a Wood that <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> a Thief</line>
<line>four Miles above the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The Last Letters from <em>Holburn-Hill</em>, make mention of two Old Women, being in a Trance, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Graies-Inn-Lane">Gray's Inn Lane</reg>, that saw a <em>Blazing <reg orig="Starr">Star</reg></em>, about 16 <em>German</em> miles<pb n="1" /> up in the <reg orig="Aire">Air</reg>; they describe it to be of a terrible Aspect, the Star being very bright &amp; sparkling, circled about it as it were with two <em>Half-<reg orig="Moones">Moons</reg></em>, very bright and clear, from the <reg orig="hornes">horns</reg> of which <em><reg orig="Moones">Moons</reg></em> issued <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> <reg orig="streames">streams</reg> of inflamed <reg orig="Aire">Air</reg>, which <reg orig="dazled">dazzled</reg> the eyes of all that beheld the same, insomuch that they that <reg orig="look'd">looked</reg> <reg orig="stedfastly">steadfastly</reg> on it, are <em><reg orig="Moon-blinde">Moonblind</reg></em>, and very <em><reg orig="Lunnatick">Lunatic</reg></em> ever since.</p>

<head level="2">This certainly (if true) foretelleth some sad or grievous accident.</head>

<p>But in these <reg orig="Distemper'd">Distempered</reg> times, if but an idle pated Woman stare up in the Skies, and fancieth she seeth any thing, presently another, and another comes staring up, &amp; so perhaps half a street; One <reg orig="saies">says</reg> it looks like a <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, and another like an <em>Elephant</em>, another <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> it is like a <em>Dragon</em>, another <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, it looketh like a flaming <em>Sword</em>, and another comes, and he <reg orig="sware">swear</reg> he sees a Castle <reg orig="beleagured">beleaguered</reg>, and the <reg orig="Cannon">Canon</reg> playing, Swords clashing, Muskets discharging, pushing of Pikes, horses and men <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> <reg orig="weltring">weltering</reg> in Blood, all this being at first but the <reg orig="Frenzie">Frenzy</reg>, or conceit of some intoxicated <em>Moon Calf</em>, and <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Imaginations of distempered Brains, who <reg orig="fancie">fancy</reg> they see, what indeed they see not; as a <reg orig="Tooper">Trooper</reg> lately in <em>Pulchers</em>, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> <reg orig="homward">homeward</reg> well elevated, or <reg orig="Alevated">Alleviated</reg>, swore to his Wife and Servants that St. <em>Pulchers</em> Church was sunk underground, because as he came by in a <em>Moon-shiny Night</em>, he beheld the shadow of that Church in the <reg orig="Kennell">Kennel</reg>; which made many of the <em>mad</em> merry People of Great <em>Bedlam</em> run out to see this <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> Sight: but returned back as wise as they went.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>These <em><reg orig="Lunacismes">Lunacisms</reg></em> reigning in our Age,</line>
<line>More <reg orig="then">than</reg> the Skies our madness doth Presage.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="2" />

<p>There is a great report of a <reg orig="Ghoast">Ghost</reg> that <reg orig="walkes">walks</reg> every Night amongst the Butchers at <em>Smithfield <reg orig="Barrs">Bars</reg></em>, the <em>Shambles, <reg orig="White-chappell">Whitechapel</reg></em> and <em>Eastcheap</em>, in the <reg orig="habite">habit</reg> of <em>Mallet</em> the Lawyer, pulling the Meat off the <reg orig="Butchers">Butcher's</reg> Tainters; many have adventured to strike at him with Cleavers and Chopping-Knives, but cannot feel <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> but <reg orig="Ayre">Air</reg>, every Saturday at Night between 9 and 12. he <reg orig="walkes">walks</reg> his stations in this very Habit as you see, doing more mischief to the <em>Butchers</em> <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever <em><reg orig="Robbin">Robin</reg> Goodfellow</em> did to the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> <reg orig="Hindes">Hinds</reg>.</p>

<img src="" alt="picture of Robin Goodfellow, with his arms spread and something in his left hand, possibly a scroll" />

<p>A young maid meeting him on <em><reg orig="Valentines">Valentine's</reg></em> Day in the morning in <em>Moor-fields</em>, made him a low Cursey, bidding him <em>Good morrow Valentine</em>, whereupon he saluting of her, <reg orig="eat">ate</reg> her up alive; the same day a cunning Constable took up a Wench in the <reg orig="Walkes">Walks</reg>, but more of this hereafter.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>The News from Smock-Alley <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <unclear>Ham-street</unclear>, is, of a sad Accident that <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> on Thursday night last, of a <em>Light Gentlewoman</em> of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, that for love of her Husband, after drinking of six single pots of <em>blessed Lull</em>, <reg orig="yclipsed">eclipsed</reg> <em>Ale</em>, or <em>Plush</em>, very desperately <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> in a Tobacco-pipe, her Husband missing her about three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after, and could by no means find her, till he <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> home late, and filling a Pipe of Tobacco, by the light whereof found his wife hanging in the Tobacco-pipe, which made him <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> in great fury till his rage went out in snuff with his Pipe; after some small deliberation, thinking she had yet been alive, calling <em>Bess, Bess, Bess</em>, three or four times, and seeing she made no answer, he cut her down, and lapping her up in a sheet of <reg orig="Smoak">Smoke</reg>, <reg orig="incoffin'd">incoffined</reg> her in a Coffin <reg orig="squar'd">squared</reg> out of Tobacco-pipe Clay; she is to be buried next <em>Shrove-Tuesday</em>, and all the old <reg orig="Smoakers">Smokers</reg> in the City of <em>Bedlan</em> are invited to her <reg orig="Buriall">Burial</reg>, instead of Naples-Bicker, they are to be <reg orig="serv'd">served</reg> with each a pipe of the best <em>Spanish</em> Tobacco called <em>Tare-nose</em>, or by some <em>Trinedads</em>; instead of Burnt Claret the men and women are to be <reg orig="serv'd">served</reg> with Strong-waters; when she goes into the ground, a noise of <em>Bedlan Flutes</em> are to pipe her <em><reg orig="Requium">Requiem</reg></em>, that her soul (if ever she had any) may ascend up in a fume to the Clouds, where the god of Thunder is to make Salt-peter of her Bum, and to cut out her Tongue into <reg orig="Thunder-bolts">Thunderbolts</reg>, her eyes are to be made Lightning, her brains formed into Clouds, her skull made a Jorden for <em>Vulcan</em> and his Cyclops; her Jaws are to be sent to <em>Prosperine</em>, and hung as a <reg orig="Trophee">Trophy</reg> over the Gates of her <reg orig="infernall">infernal</reg> Court; her neck, shoulders, and arms are to be presented to Pluto for a New-<reg orig="Years">Year's</reg> Gift; her hands being his Lime-<reg orig="twiggs">twigs</reg>, are to made two <em><reg orig="Engins">Engines</reg></em> for <em><reg orig="Belzeebub">Beelzebub</reg></em> to work mischief on too credulous <reg orig="Mankinde">Mankind</reg>; Her <reg orig="Brests">Breasts</reg> are one to be placed upon <em>Cockney-Hill</em> and the other on the <em><reg orig="Devill's">Devil's</reg> Anse-ic-Peak</em>, on her <em>Nipples</em> are to be placed two <em><reg orig="Beakons">Beacons</reg></em>, to give warning when <reg orig="Cupids">Cupid's</reg> <reg orig="skorehing">scoring</reg> Dart enters flaming hearts of young <em>Amorists</em> that burn with love,<pb n="4" /> and cannot be quenched till they come to <em><reg orig="Sluts">Slut's</reg> Well</em>, <reg orig="scituate">situate</reg> in a Mossey Valley between the two Hams; her belly is to be made a new <em>Mint</em> to Coin <em>Prigs</em> and Pads against next <em>Paddington Faire</em>; her Thighs are to be made <em>Supporters</em> whereon to hang the New Pictures without <em>Temple-<reg orig="Barre">Bar</reg></em>; her Feet to be <reg orig="bequeath'd">bequeathed</reg> to the lame <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> in <em>Covent-Garden</em>, to walk to <em>Piaza</em> without Crutches.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Thus all her body I do well dispose,</line>
<line>One thing forgot the <em>Pox</em> shall have her <em>Nose</em>,</line>
<line>And for her <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg> that none ever knew,</line>
<line>Take them, good Devil, for they are thy due,</line>
<line>If any ask who this vile Dame should be,</line>
<line><reg orig="Tis">'Tis</reg> <em><reg orig="Judas">Judas'</reg></em> Mother that once <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> on Tree,</line>
<line><reg orig="Nam'd">Named</reg> <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg> Money, Aunt to Mrs. <em>Juncto</em>,</line>
<line>That lately was, but now is quite <em>defuncto</em>,</line>
<line>Which makes my Pockets to shed tears,</line>
<line>And sets my Guts together by the ears;</line>
<line>If any want her cursed company,</line>
<line>I am most sure 'tis poor bewitched I;</line>
<line>(The want of her made Old <em>J. <reg orig="Tailor">Taylor</reg></em> dies,)</line>
<line>The want of her (vile Witch) makes poor men curse,</line>
<line>Who like a <em>Jade</em> flies to the rich <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Purse,</line>
<line>But if she <reg orig="ere">e'er</reg> be <reg orig="rais'd">raised</reg> again from ground,</line>
<line><reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg> punish her, a Penny to a Pound.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A <reg orig="Quire">Choir</reg> of <reg orig="Meremaids">Mermaids</reg> were (the same day that 3 Tides <reg orig="flow'd">flowed</reg> in the <em>New River</em> together) heard by <em>Jack Adams</em> of the Parish of <em>James Clarken-well</em>, to sing <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> sweetly in the little <em>Ducking-Pond</em>; the same Night, the <em>Dromedary</em> took his journey towards <em>Cambridge</em>, where he is to take his <em>Degrees</em> and Commence Master of <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>; Two <em>Dolphins</em> likewise were seen dancing over the <em>Thames</em> with a pair of <reg orig="Bagg-pipes">Bagpipes</reg> before them; and a blind Woman that went to <em><reg orig="Hide">Hyde</reg> Park</em> to steal <reg orig="Veneson">Venison</reg> in the Night, affirmeth that she saw at the bottom of a Pond, two <em>Half Suns</em> in one <reg orig="Horison">Horizon</reg>; the meaning of these presaging, and portending<pb n="5" /> <reg orig="Cometts">Comets</reg>, <em>Time</em> it is thought will <reg orig="duely">duly</reg> unfold, and suddenly make an <reg orig="appeare">appear</reg>.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>How many wish for Change, and yet change not</line>
<line>Their Course of Life, till Death doth change their Lot!</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A young <em>Cock Pheasant</em> in <em>Pasty-nook</em> hath a rare faculty in composing of <em>Characters</em>, and variable <reg orig="kindes">kinds</reg> of Letters, both Vowels and Consonants, and is able to give each Letter his <reg orig="propper">proper</reg> sound; yet this Bird being by some of his own <em>feather</em> enticed on <em>Shrove-Tuesday</em> last towards <em><reg orig="Lambs">Lamb's</reg> Conduit</em>, when he was there, took his flight amongst the rest of his Company to <em>New-Market Heath</em>, where after a Day or two, he was sprung by two <em>Gentlemen</em> that were a <em>Hawking</em>, he to shun the <em>Hawk</em>, betook himself under a Bed for shelter, <reg orig="wher">where</reg> one <reg orig="pooking">poking</reg> him in the <reg orig="Taile">Tail</reg> with his <em>baking staff</em>, the poor <em>Pheasant</em> came out, ready to moult his feathers for fear, yet the Gentlemen compassionating him (being <em><reg orig="decoy'd">decoyed</reg></em> out by other <em>Birds</em>) did him no injury, but passing by his offence, committed him to the tuition of Sir <em>John <reg orig="Old Castle">Oldcastle</reg></em>, who upon the next default in the same <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg>, is to <i>pluck a feather with him</i>, and afterwards to have him <reg orig="press'd">pressed</reg> to his <em>good behaviour</em> in the New-<em><reg orig="Cuckoos">Cuckoo's</reg> Nest</em> in <em>Hosier Lane</em>,</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Where Fools in Venus Lime-<reg orig="twiggs">twigs</reg> may be caught,</line>
<line>Too late repenting that they <reg orig="follow'd">followed</reg> naught.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The last Monday, a <reg orig="Heard">Herd</reg> of Swine driving <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> <em>Long-lane</em>, 600 Jews were suddenly converted by them, some think it was for fear those <em>Rumford</em> <reg orig="Cattell">Cattle</reg> should serve them as they served the <em><reg orig="Devill">Devil</reg></em> in the Country of the <em>Gergesens</em>, when they carried him headlong into the Sea.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>A <em>Scot</em>, a <reg orig="Broaker">Broker</reg>, a JEW, a Whore,</line>
<line>As <em>Usurer</em>, a Lawyer, and some more,</line><pb n="6" />
<line>Take them good Devil, as the <em>Swine</em> did thee,</line>
<line>And <reg orig="drownd">drowned</reg> them underneath the &mdash;low Tree.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A mad <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Parson <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> riding up to <em>London</em>, between <em>Islington</em> and the <em>Red Bull</em> met with a <em>Small-<unclear>coabe</unclear> Man</em>, very black, with the Sack of <em>Small-wale</em> at his back; The <reg orig="pittifull">pitiful</reg> Parson, minding to put a jeer on the Small-coal-man, made a sudden stop with his Horse, saying with a loud <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg>, that those that rid after him, might <reg orig="pertake">partake</reg> of the <reg orig="jeast">jest</reg>; Fellow, fellow (quoth he) I <reg orig="prethee">prithee</reg> tell's some News from Hell, I see thou hast a whole Sack full at thy back; Truly quoth the Small-coal-man, I can tell you but very little News from Hell, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the <reg orig="Devill">Devil</reg> wants a <reg orig="Chaplaine">Chaplain</reg>, and you ride but a little faster you may perchance have the Place.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>His Company did burst with very laughter,</line>
<line>Calling him <em>Pluto's</em> Chaplain ever after.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>A young Gentlewoman casting her Apron over her face, because she would see no body till she came to her <reg orig="Sweet-hearts">Sweetheart's</reg> <reg orig="Bed-side">Bedside</reg>, on <em><reg orig="Valentines">Valentine's</reg></em> morning, was met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> in the street by another youngster, who claiming her for his Valentine, and offering to salute her, she denied to uncover her Lips, whereupon he finding the Passage to her <reg orig="Wickett">Wicket</reg> Door, <reg orig="enter'd">entered</reg> one of his hands, clasping the other about her neck, kissed her Apron, which another seeing, and laughing at him, He told him, he was but a fool to laugh at him, for the <reg orig="Gentlewomans">Gentlewoman's</reg> <reg orig="Lipps">Lips</reg> tasted sweetest when her Kisses were <reg orig="strain'd">strained</reg> <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> her Apron. Two Citizens, walking in a Garden the other <em>Moon-shiny Night</em>, one asked his Companion what he took it to be a Clock, Faith, quoth the simple <em>Citt</em>, I have a <em><reg orig="Sun-diall">Sundial</reg></em> in my other pockets, stay till I go but in and fetch it, and I will resolve you presently.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>What <reg orig="pitty">pity</reg> 'tis a learned Citt,</line>
<line>Should from the Schools bring no more Wit.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="7" />

<p>The last News out of <em>Greenland</em> make mention of a terrible fight between two great flocks of Birds, the one <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the North of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and the other from the South, That flock from the North were all <em>Greenland Cuckoos</em>, to the number of 1654200 or thereabouts, the other Flock were <em>Swallows</em>, that met in a green Plain on the top of a high mountain of Ice, where (as in a <reg orig="pitch'd">pitched</reg> field) they began the fight; the first charge was given by the Cuckoos who with much fury charged the left wing of the Swallows <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> and <reg orig="thorow">through</reg>, leaving many of them dead upon the place; but the <em>Swallows</em> being <reg orig="inraged">enraged</reg> with fury, rallying their <reg orig="scatter'd">scattered</reg> Forces, in a <em>swift</em> motion wheeled about into the rear of the <em>Cuckoos</em>, and so charging them in the <reg orig="tailes">tails</reg>, put them to the row, doing execution them about twenty miles together, leaving many thousands of them stark dead lying on the <reg orig="Ayer">Air</reg> as thick as Motes in the Sun; In this last Action there was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one <em>Swallow</em> wounded in the great toe, but by the help of the King of <em><reg orig="Greenlands">Greenland's</reg></em> <reg orig="Dogs-Leach">Dogs Leash</reg>, being as <reg orig="skilfull">skilful</reg> an <em><reg orig="Augre">Auger</reg></em>, as <em><reg orig="Chyrurgeon">Surgeon</reg></em>, cured the same perfectly in three quarters of the fifth part of a Minute; But the People of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> (being very <reg orig="unsetled">unsettled</reg> in their <reg orig="mindes">minds</reg>) begin to <reg orig="speake">speak</reg> some words at random; as to say, that this strange and unusual sight of those Birds, that still frequent the hottest <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>, was an assured sight of the fall of some great <reg orig="Heroe">Hero</reg> or Worthy of that Country, and most probably the King himself, who should be invaded by the Mores, who should prevail against him; and either <em>swallow</em> him up, or drive him out of his out of his cold Climate, into a warmer, Since this great fight, the <em>Feather-makers</em> are sending out as new <em>Green-land</em> Fleet to trade for <em><reg orig="Cockoos">Cuckoo's</reg></em> <reg orig="tailes">tails</reg>, which is a richer <reg orig="Commoditie">Commodity</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> Whales.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Whose heads are heavy, <em><reg orig="Cockoos">Cuckoo's</reg></em> Feathers will</line>
<line>Make light their <reg orig="Witts">Wits</reg>, and brains with <reg orig="Whimseys">Whimsies</reg> fill.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

<p>London, Printed by <em>J. <reg orig="Crowch">Crouch</reg></em>, and <em>T. W.</em> dwelling at the 3 <em>Foxes</em> in <em>Long-Lane</em>. 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>