<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MNullus02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Nullus, Issue 2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><em>Mercurius</em> NULLUS</head>
<head level="2">OR</head>
<head level="2">The invisible NUNCIUS:</head>
<head level="3">Most Partially</head>
<head level="2">Comprising the Sum of all Intelligence between</head>
<head level="3">Well-close and Westminster</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> morning, <em>March</em> 20. till yesterday in the Afternoon, <em>March</em> 19.</head>
<hr />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Behold! once more to you I come,</line>
<line>My Name is <em>nullus, nulla, nullum</em>.</line>
<line>My nature is to bite not gore,</line>
<line>At none that bit not me before:</line>
<line>But if they bite or strike me then</line>
<line>My Nature is to strike <reg orig="agen">again</reg>.</line>
<line>Poor <reg orig="Mortals">Mortals'</reg> wounds I love to heal,</line>
<line>I feed on <reg orig="sighes">sighs</reg> at every meal.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>Hah Rogues! Did I not tell you of this before? Did I not <reg orig="prophecie">prophecy</reg> of your implacability? Did not I delineate your vast <reg orig="stomacks">stomachs</reg> ? I told ye I thought <reg orig="newes">news</reg> would not please you, and I think I spake very true: I gave ye the properties of news, yet still ye <reg orig="sleight">slight</reg> me: I unfolded the Word to you, but yet ye regarded it not; neither (as I hear) are ye content with my expressions, but deem them too too mean for your mounting <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> forsooth: No wonder but ye must look so high; sure did ye but reflect on your Peacock feet ye would be more reasonable in your conjectures. But why do I speak of <em>Reason</em>? both you and your thoughts are <reg orig="canker'd">cankered</reg> with sensuality:<pb n="1" /> But the best is, I an not bound to <reg orig="humor">humour</reg> you: if ye like not my lines, either mend or meddle not with them: I <reg orig="liv'd">lived</reg> before you saw them; and no doubt but I shall live after your whining at them. Ye are the true <em>Zoyli</em> and <em>Momi</em>, which are disturbed at <em>Venus</em> Love slippers, or <em>Minerva's</em> house, because it was not moveable like the foolish whimsies in your <reg orig="Butter-fly">Butterfly</reg> Noddles. Can I <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> words for you? What do ye want? I told ye, to tell you were knaves, were no <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, perhaps ye are angry because I told you not how, and wherein you were so, which I would quickly do; but I will not, my expressions shall not rise so high: I had rather dabble my fancy-wings in the dirt, by flying low, <reg orig="then">than</reg> fly high, and so dash <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> in pieces by a fall. I had rather you should say my Muse is heavy, then I should cry <em>Peccavie</em>. Besides, I will be cautious, by reason of the bad success of a good friend of mine. I will take heed lest I be liable to the Lash of his supposed merit: he is an honest acquaintance of my Godfather <em>Apollo</em>; ah poor sons of the Muses! into what a sad position are ye involved? by reason of the malignancy of some, who scarce <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> how many new Moons there is in a month; nay not when their own horns bud. Ah poor Wretches! were it not for the freedom of your minds, what might become of your shackled bodies? But <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>, it is better to be passive for a good conscience, then active in the Courts of iniquity. But I <reg orig="wil">will</reg> proceed to intelligence: here Secretary bring me my packet of Letters. The first thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> worthy your observation is, The other day an English <em>Hellena</em> discovers one of the sons of <em>Venus</em>, being a younger brother, but a second <em>Adonis</em> for his beauty, she made at him <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg>, and (by the usual posture) <reg orig="intices">entices</reg> him into a blind <reg orig="Ale:house">Alehouse</reg>, where she fell down backwards before him, confessing<pb n="2" /> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> cast by the power of his beauty. The young man being <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> drawn in, <reg orig="fals">false</reg> upon her, where she neatly <reg orig="nipt">nipped</reg> him of 30 good shillings, and so I leave them: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> this I say to thee, O thou <em>Helena</em>, thou art both a Whore and a <reg orig="Traytoress">Traitoress</reg>; a Whore to <em>Paris</em>, and a <reg orig="Traytoress">Traitoress</reg> to <em>Diephobus</em>; and to thee oh comely <em>Hiacinthus</em>! I say, O <em>formose puer! nimium ne crede Colori</em>. Now Sirs, if I conceived weeping would do any good, my tears should not be wanting: but sure, should I <reg orig="metamorphise">metamorphose</reg> my merry self into whining <em>Heraclitus</em>, I should not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> allay the dust of your stupidity, but bring a deluge to destroy you all. O Heavens! Do not you blush at three things? <em>Aurora</em> art not thou ashamed of us? prethe, in stead of riding with old <em>Tithon</em> in the Southern chambers to beget more Mernnons, stay in the East to stop thy brother <em><reg orig="Titons">Titon's</reg></em> motion. Let him not run round in our Hemisphere, since we desire to <reg orig="invellop">envelop</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> in the dark Dungeon of damnable Errors. Let us be illuminated by the <reg orig="Suns">Sun's</reg> absence, to be sensible of our own madness. Here's <em>Arminians</em> and <em>Socinians</em>. Here's <em><reg orig="Iesuites">Jesuits</reg></em> and <em>Rahabites</em>. Here's <em>Adamites</em> and <em>Moabites</em>. Here's <em>Arians</em> and <em>Antiscriptarians</em>. Here's Wakers and soul sleepers, &amp;c. is not here a brave company? are not we pretty well accommodated with variety of Religions. Nay if here be not enough, here's <em>knockers</em> and <em>Ranters</em> too. O fine sport! pray who can <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> but laugh at it? Nay, but to speak with solid Reason, what eye can refrain from weeping at it? But alas! tears will avail no more, nor reclaim any more, <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em>Aristeus</em> his constant motion can reduce <em>Euridice</em>: it is not sad that these things should be, and no injunction, no prohibition laid upon them. What are we, and from whence did we spring? are not <reg orig="soules">souls</reg> sparks of Heaven? if then there be but one Root, why<pb n="3" /> should the Branches insurrect and quarrel among themselves? Sirs, if ye are men, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> so. Here Boy, bring out my <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, <reg orig="bils">bills</reg>, hatchets, <reg orig="halberts">halberds</reg>, tongues, fire-shovels, knives, <reg orig="scissers">scissors</reg>, bodkins, and needles; yea even all the edge and pointed tools ye have: stand up for the defence of <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg>, and offence of others: keep off the Devil if you can, for he fights like strong-<reg orig="breste">breasted</reg> ANT&AElig;US against you in the flesh. O Hercules, Hercules, where art thou? Come crush him in pieces in thy arms, as he used to crush his friends. Let every man sweep his own door: let every man wash his own hands and heart from the guilt of Error. Here's one Dog barks madness from the pulpit, enough to infect all the Audience. Another like Melancheres (the curst Cur of Acteon) bites (by reason of advantage) his Master by the back. Another insinuates himself into his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> <reg orig="bosome">bosom</reg> (like the fawning <!--Asse?-->Asle in <reg orig="&AElig;sops">&AElig;sop's</reg> Fables) Another wanting power answerable to his <reg orig="envie">envy</reg>, like a perfidious Hermit, newly sprung from his adulterate Cave, goes secretly and <reg orig="stigmatizes">stigmatises</reg> his next <reg orig="Neighbor">Neighbour</reg>, and by clandestine policy renders him odious and contemptible to all his friends. O horrid Villain; pish, <!--tis??-->'ti: no matter<pb n="4" />: but <unclear>prethet</unclear> friend have a care, that when thy back is <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> thou art not <reg orig="serv'd">served</reg> as Ixion would once have done to Jupiter, to give him the brow antlers, Say, sirs, is this honestly? No sure, it is the first greatest magnitude of Knavery; but their tongues and hearts look two <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> like double-faced Janus: these are they that will not swear but lie: pray mark therefore this following Poem, taken in part verbatim by an honest fellow from the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of a zealous brother and sister, meeting on a <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> day in the fields.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Sirs, I can neither sing nor dance,</line>
<line>Yet I have learnt a Song by chance:</line>
<line>indeed it is a harmless Song,</line>
<line>As void of Reason as of wrong:</line>
<line>And yet it is as full (<reg orig="i'le">I'll</reg> tell you]</line>
<line>Of matter, as our sisters <reg orig="bellie">belie</reg>.</line>
<line>The other day a holy Lass</line>
<line>Stark naked in the Waves there was,</line>
<line>And as she in the streams did <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> </line>
<line>A zealous brother he came by,</line>
<line>And (as the Spirit had <reg orig="inclin'd">inclined</reg> him)</line>
<line>He <reg orig="chanc't">chanced</reg> to cast his eyes behind him,</line>
<line>Where bare and naked in the place</line>
<line>He did espy this babe of Grace:</line>
<line>And then to her he spake as <reg orig="followes">follows</reg>,</line>
<line>Do you belong to great <unclear><reg orig="Allhollowes">Allhallows</reg></unclear></line>
<line>She answers, I'm a member there:</line>
<line>But pray, <reg orig="sayes">says</reg> he, what do you here?</line>
<line>Why brother I must bathe herein</line>
<line>To wash me from my deadly sin,</line>
<line>And make my flesh fit to inherit</line>
<line>Tho holy and blessed Spirit,</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="5" />

<p>But, Gentlemen, though my Pen chance to spew out here and there a strange Tale, yet I desire you not to give credit to any matter that seems hyperbolical, because such are presented for <reg orig="Lyes">Lies</reg>, and you desired so to take them: We shall therefore descend to <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> Transactions, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>News from the Sea, or the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg> of Megellam.</i></head>

<p>It is credibly certified for an untruth, that the last Saturday come sevennight a very strange and wonderful fire (an <em>ignis fatuus</em> sure it was) <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in these parts, which hath burnt up 33 Acre of Ground in the main Ocean, together with all the Cities, <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>, Houses, Trees, Tenements, &amp;c. there <reg orig="scituate">situate</reg>, and hat made the <reg orig="soyl">soil</reg> altogether unarable: so that <reg orig="its">it's</reg> to be feared that the Plain which formerly did <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> such plenty of almost all sorts of Fish, will now scarce furnish us with bread-corn.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from ROME</i></head>

<p>It is certified that <em>Remus</em> and <em>Romulus</em> met both in the Market-place, last Market-day, resolving to fight a Duel: they <reg orig="slipt">slipped</reg> out of their <reg orig="Tombes">Tombs</reg>, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> their <em>Manes</em> slept: but they awakening, and finding them not there, sent out speedy <em>Hu-and-Cry</em> after them; so that they were <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> apprehended by <reg orig="C&aelig;sars">C&aelig;sar's</reg> Officers, and guarded again into their Shrines, where they <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> bound hand and foot, and are to answer at the Tribunal Bar next Sessions.</p>

<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Newes">News</reg></em> from Shinar</head>

<p>The Pigmean people are now re-edifying and fortifying the Tower of Babel, which is to be their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, wherein they may have a League offensive and defensive against the Cranes, the greatest Foes they have.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from <em>Wales</em>.</i></head>

<p>Her was a Leaden Pear-tree in her Orchard was beer leaden pairs last <!--faux-Welsh accent??--><reg orig="Chrishmash">Christmas</reg>, and her Coose was tread her <reg orig="Neighbor">Neighbour</reg> (like a Cander) treading her wise (like a Coose) in her bed. These are strange variations of the Season.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from London.</i></head>

<p>Our proceedings are all at a standing motion, Religion (both true and false) by some is <reg orig="gobled">gobbled</reg> up as Dogs <reg orig="goble">gobble</reg> puddings. Others lap a little, then sneer away having burnt their chops. Others utterly detest and shun it, as a Mouse may do a Rat. These are Atheists worse <reg orig="then">than</reg> the very Devils, who fear and tremble at the <reg orig="Diety">Deity</reg>. Others pursue poor Religion, and seek to devour it and Learning also. These are Papists, Jesuits, and Ranters. Oh! how they labour to turn Temples and <reg orig="Colledges">Colleges</reg> into their Pockets. Some Expectants stay to see whether the <!--Market???-->Manket will fall, Religion is not cheap enough yet for them; but in the mean time they bring up their children in the Schools of Vice very learnedly, which indeed they need not do, we are apt to run headlong to the Devil without help: it is as natural to us, as it is for a Dog to run, a Bird to fly, or a Fish to swim: is there not a propensity to do it without Art. O yes yes, there is more need of prohibition, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a propagation to evil. Alas! where is some body to stand in the gap, who can conquer these things? Ah pity, pity; while the poor Fishes wanton in the pleasant streams they are <reg orig="caried">carried</reg> into <em>Mare Mortuum</em>. Here's every man a <em>Phaeton</em>, and an Incendiary to burn all things; and yet this <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on so <reg orig="subtilty">subtlety</reg>, that its almost inapprehensible.</p><pb n="7" />

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>This man has <reg orig="vow'd">vowed</reg> <reg orig="hee'l">he'll</reg> drink no Wine,</line>
<line>But is resolved to <reg orig="resigne">resign</reg> </line>
<line>His appetites unto his friend,</line>
<line>He thinks <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> time to make an end:</line>
<line>But hence it is that he retires,</line>
<line><!--his? Typo/reg?-->Pis purse performs not his desires.</line>
<line><reg orig="Heres">Here's</reg> noble Whiskin <reg orig="vowes">vows</reg> that be</line>
<line>Has not quite <reg orig="renounc'd">renounced</reg> adultery;</line>
<line>And reason too, for <em>Age</em> <reg orig="essayes">essays</reg> </line>
<line>Upon his Crown, and gently <reg orig="layes">lays</reg> </line>
<line>His Spirit down, 'tis <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <em>Age</em></line>
<line>Not graces that doth the man <reg orig="asswage">assuage</reg>.</line>
<line>But where's the man that doth forsake</line>
<line>His wife, even for his <reg orig="Virtues">Virtue's</reg> sake?</line>
<line>O these as hardly may be found</line>
<line>As <em>Incubus</em> on holy ground.</line>
<line>Some from their Vices do dissent,</line>
<line>Because th'are inconvenient:</line>
<line>Which argues not at all they be</line>
<line>The true-born sons of <reg orig="Sancity">Sanctity</reg>:</line>
<line>But it declares to all men, rather,</line>
<line>Such sons have <em>Pluto</em> to their father.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>