<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MNullus01">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Nullus, Issue 1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><em>Mercurius</em> NULLUS</head>
<head level="2">OR</head>
<head level="2">The invisible NUNCIUS:</head>
<head level="3">Most Partially</head>
<head level="2">Comprising the Sum of all Intelligence between</head>
<head level="3">Well-Close and Westminster</head>
<hr />
<head level="3">From <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> morning, till yesterday at Noon, 1654.</head>
<hr />

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Here's <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's false, and <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's true,</line>
<line>Here's <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's old, and <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's new,</line>
<line>Here's <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's good and <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that's bad,</line>
<line>Here's merry News, and News that's sad:</line>
<line>And here's presented to your view</line>
<line><reg orig="Newes">News</reg> lawful, and unlawful too:</line>
<line>What shall I say? I've here in store,</line>
<line>Such <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> as <reg orig="ne're">ne'er</reg> was heard before.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>Now I come that never came before, and perhaps will never come more. I am very importunate to have free access to the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="Theater">Theatre</reg>, <reg orig="becaus">because</reg> my Occupations are of great <reg orig="importancy">importance</reg>. Sirs, pray be not angry with me, I come to salute your Leathern, Vellum, &amp; Athenian Ears, with a <reg orig="Hop-sack">Hopsack</reg> full of <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>, and indeed I hope it will please you: if not, pray send me word to the sign of the <reg orig="Flying-horse-shoee">Flying Horseshoe</reg> on Addle-hill, <reg orig="scituate">situate</reg> on the shoulders of him, whose Anagram is, <i>Bad at the best</i>, and I shall coin from the Mintage of my Muse some better for you, that may please you, if possible: but I think your vast <reg orig="stomacks">stomachs</reg> are implacable, especially with <reg orig="newes">news</reg>: It may be if I should invite you all to meet me at the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Treasury <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> morning, promising to give you 1000 l.a. man, then ye would run thither more nimbly <reg orig="then">than</reg><pb n="1" /> the Cripple that <reg orig="out-stript">outstripped</reg> all the <reg orig="boyes">boys</reg> in the Bear-Garden, throwing aside his Crutches) when the Bear was remitted from the stake. But, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> Sirs, it would argue as much folly in you to expect it, as there's impossibility in me to effect it. For I am scarce able to buy every <reg orig="Dissentor">Dissenter</reg> a Hempen <reg orig="Coller">Collar</reg> to hold them up when their sensibility of the flourishing estate of true Religion (which I doubt will never be in my <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>) shall sink them into the deep Deluges of damnable Despair. But before I come to my <reg orig="Theam">Theme</reg>, pray give me leave to play the Logician, and make a brief Apology, as the custom is, which shall be as broad as long; yea, even four square.</p>

<p>First, then for the words; <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>, it comes from <em>nosco</em>, to know: or rather from <em>dico</em> to tell, because we seldom have <reg orig="newes">news</reg> till it is told Us; and you must note, it is continually attended with the <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg> of the subsequent properties, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>Either {<em>True</em> or <em>False</em> {<em>New</em> or <em>Old</em> {<em>Good</em> or <em>Bad</em> {<em><reg orig="Legall">Legal</reg></em> or <em>Illegal</em>.</p>

<p>If it be true, 'tis contrary to falsity: if false, it varies from verity: if it be new it opposes Antiquity: if old it favours not of novelty: if it be good, it is not <reg orig="blemisht">blemished</reg> with malignancy: if bad, its the antipode to prosperity: if lawful, it is not shackled up in the Chains of Silence: if unlawful, it must not be communicable from man to man. But lest some of your sudden Coxcombs, unsanctified Noddles or <reg orig="cobling">cobbling</reg> Capacities, should not be able to apprehend <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> in its genuine sense, I will lead you one step further into this <em>Thesaurum auream</em>, by affixing an example to two properties.</p>

<p>First, true <reg orig="newes">news</reg> is such, as is <reg orig="reveal'd">revealed</reg> by one, disproved<pb n="2" /> by none, and <reg orig="confirm'd">confirmed</reg> by thousands. Secondly, false <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> is such, as is declared by one confirmed by none, and disapproved by thousands. But lest I should make too large an Exordium, and thereby seem to throw my small house out at the great <reg orig="Windowes">Windows</reg>, I shall proceed to the <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, <em>viz</em>. Upon a time going into Tower-street to drink a cup of merry Ale, in the next room to mine, I saw a zealous Stocking-seller (having a bundle of stockings by him) drawing a silk <reg orig="stockin">stocking</reg> on the Ablaster leg of a verian Lady; and having drawn it on, he demanded if it were fit; she <reg orig="answer'd">answered</reg> it was too short. Why, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, it will retch into a longer fix by and by, if you please to touch it with your soft hand. I but, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> she, I tie my stockings above the knee. O, why there's the thing Madam, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, I doubt not but to fit it by and by with such Wares as will come on without drawing. She then, by a silent Language of smiles and glances, expressed her kind acceptance of his wares: he <reg orig="fals">falls</reg> to work and while they were <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about their Occupations I took my <reg orig="Gentlemans">Gentleman's</reg> <reg orig="stockins">stockings</reg>, and <reg orig="dipt">dipped</reg> them for 40 shillings, remembering that <i>Falere ta lem non est Fraus</i>, and left him these lines.</p>

<p><em>Sir</em>, For the redemption of your Wares, you must pay 40 s. and it is but just you should do so, because you <reg orig="pierct">pierced</reg> your sting with such <reg orig="advantane">advantage</reg> into the sort thing of your choice Paragon. Sir, pray refuse not to pay the Coin, and I will abuse you not: but if you are refractory, then I think the more you stir, my friend, the more you'll stink.</p>

<p>I past from thence into <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>, and there meeting with one of my acquaintances, I <reg orig="askt">asked</reg> him what news: Why, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, good news; I have found a brass farthing <reg orig="wrapt">wrapped</reg> up in a paper, with this inscription, <i>My whole estate.</i> Now I thought sure Heaven <reg orig="smil'd">smiled</reg> on me, because<pb n="3" /> I should so easily purchase the estate of another. But I demanded of him how his Confidence <reg orig="brookt">brooked</reg> this; Conscience <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, and <reg orig="smil'd">smiled</reg>, Truly the power of money, [which ever hath <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> of Religion) hath sentenced that to remain in exile, till at <reg orig="Dooms-day">Doomsday</reg> it <reg orig="returnes">returns</reg> to be an Evidence against me: nor could I conveniently have <reg orig="contain'd">contained</reg> it in the small circumference of my breast, it being of so large a size: nor is it my case <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, but thousands more. Oh this <reg orig="Devillish">Devilish</reg> <em>Pacunia!</em> it was this that slew <em>Hobson</em> the <reg orig="Fidler">Fiddler</reg>; who for <reg orig="Lucres">Lucre's</reg> sake, <reg orig="skrewd">screwed</reg> up his Pegs so high, that he <reg orig="crackt">cracked</reg> his Twatling-strings, and <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> of his singing Melancholy. Nay, <reg orig="i'le">I'll</reg> tell you more, As I <reg orig="past">passed</reg> through Ludgate, I <reg orig="spyed">spied</reg> the green man at <em>London</em> stone, shoving so fiercely against the chief Pillars of Ludgate that you would think he would have <reg orig="over turned">overturned</reg> it <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg>. Why how now friend said I, what the Devil is this for? O <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, I am newly <reg orig="slipt">slipped</reg> out of Newgate, being invited thither for Theft; and for <reg orig="Credits">Credit's</reg> sake, I dare not return, till <em>I</em> have penetrated the Walls of this Wardrobe, and <reg orig="rob'd">robbed</reg> the inhabitants for money to pay my fees. 'Twas money that save Pimp H. from the Lashes of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Reproach when he was taken napping with J.W. this also cured him of the Pimp <em>H</em>. from the Lashes of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Reproach when he was taken napping with J.W. this also cured him of the P &mdash; x, redeemed his Pillory, and saved him that he <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> not of a Hempen Fever, as it was decreed. 'Twas this that rent and <reg orig="repair'd">repaired</reg> <em><reg orig="Iones">Jones's</reg></em> Placket: 'Twas this that erected the famous three <reg orig="corner'd">cornered</reg> Swingle-tree, <em>viz</em>. Tyburn, and brings custom thither monthly. 'twas this that founded the never dying Order of <em>Kn(ights) aves</em> of the Post. Nay, it will even turn Post into men. 'Twas this that <reg orig="caus'd">caused</reg> my <reg orig="cole">coal</reg>-black Dog to be <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg>, whose skin I adjudged to be worth three pence. 'Twas money that bit me by the shins (the curst Cur being so called that did<pb n="4" /> it. 'Twas this that <reg orig="caus'd">caused</reg> Sir <em>T.K.</em> to put the remainder of the candle, which he borrowed, into his Pocket, when he had sealed his Letter. 'Twas this that invited a Wooden-pated Custard-eater to descend from his horse, passing over the Water, and to catch at the shadow of his Gold chain (which he thought had been real) in the water. But <reg orig="its">it's</reg> no wonder, if he acted the <unclear><!-- approx 5 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="&AElig;sops">&AElig;sop's</reg> Fables, seeing he hath no more brains <reg orig="then">than</reg> a <unclear>Goon</unclear> &mdash; But leaving the Power of Money, let us behold the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of Vice, how vigorous it is in the Element of ignorance, or in the <reg orig="Joult-logger head">Jolt loggerhead</reg> of a Leathern-cheek Lawyer, who meeting with a <reg orig="Damozel">Damsel</reg> in <reg orig="Fleet-street">Fleet Street</reg>, ushers her to the Devil Tavern, where they sate very civilly a great while; at length a Client knocks at the door of his breast: Whose there? <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> the Lawyer, <reg orig="i'me">I'm</reg> your <reg orig="Clyent">Client</reg> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he. Pray what's your name, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> the Lawyer? My name, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, is Lust. O pray come in Sir, <reg orig="sayes">says</reg> the Lawyer, you are he <em>I</em> have <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> so long for. Whereupon the Lawyer binds Reason as fast to the Peace, as he uses to bind his Conscience when he pleads for money, and boldly salutes his Lady thus: I have a Jewel large in the measure, and the same I fain would set within the curious hairy Treasure of thy own carnal Cabinet.</p>

<p><i>Her Answer</i></p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>To set it there, it is no sin;</line>
<line>The door is open put it in</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>Then in it went; but ere they could finish in comes M. Constable, who redeemed them from the <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> Paw, and guards them to the Poultrey Palace, allowing them a <reg orig="nights">night's</reg> lodging there; and in the morning they were attended with great pomp and solemnity before a Justice, where I leave them.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>As I went along the Strand, I thought infallibly I had seen <em>Parnassus</em> hill; for I beheld a Virgin, or one so habited at the least, newly fallen down from the step going up to <em><reg orig="Merlins">Merlin's</reg></em> door (by which it appears she went to know her fortune, but saw it before) she so lay that her legs pointed towards heaven, which caused me to think it was the forked top of <em>Parnassus</em>; and this the more willing I believed, by reason a Spring was transparent; which Spring I thought to be <em><reg orig="Hellicon">Helicon</reg></em>. Besides, the English <em>Merlin</em> then present, &amp; the flocking of Virgins thither, gave me to think that M&oelig;c&oelig;nas or Apollo, and the Muses had been there. She went to have her figure cast, but she cast it <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the Sun, Moon and Stars, more apparently <reg orig="then">than</reg> any Artist can do. Some say there is a secret meaning in this; for, 'tis thought if the Wench had not fallen in the <reg orig="enterprize">enterprise</reg>, but got safe up into <em><reg orig="Merlins">Merlin's</reg></em> Closet, he would have <reg orig="crained">craned</reg> her up to heaven, and have <reg orig="stillified">stultified</reg> and planted her next door to <em>Perseiss</em>, or <em>Caput Medus&aelig;</em>, who should have been as a faithful Scout to him, who intends to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> <reg orig="Replers">Repler's</reg> words, which are, That no new thing should be done in heaven without his knowledge; And for the better conveying down of intelligence, there should have been a stiff paper Trunk (cut out of the old <reg orig="Almanacks">Almanacs</reg>) <reg orig="fixt">fixed</reg> to the top of the Chimney, not to her hands, for then the whirling about of the <em>primum mobil&oelig;</em> would have caused it to have <reg orig="gather'd">gathered</reg> wind, or drawn it from the mouth of the Chimney: it should have just <reg orig="reacht">reached</reg> up to her sphere, so that each day when she was perpendicular she should have delivered her mind: But this Plot failed, and the poor fellow, I doubt, will procure a supernatural assistance.</p>

<p>But passing to the next, I had scarce gone three steps, but<pb n="6" /> I saw a Blade whose eyes were so <reg orig="fixt">fixed</reg> to the fancies at his <reg orig="Codpiss">Codpiece</reg>, that he could not cast up his eyes to Heaven; which <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> him to be more Beast <reg orig="then">than</reg> Man. For the Creator.</p>

<p><i>&mdash; Os homini sublime dedit c&oelig;lumque iueri.</i></p>

<p>But he was well requited presently for by the immediate descending of a <unclear>Jordan</unclear> upon his pate, full of hasty pudding, he was <reg orig="crown'd">crowned</reg> and <reg orig="annointed">anointed</reg> for an absolute Coxcomb.</p>

<p>The next man <em>I</em> met with was a friend of mine, who, after a long preamble to little purpose, <reg orig="tels">tells</reg> me that he catched his honest <reg orig="neighbor">neighbour</reg> in bed with his wife but that very morning. Ha, ha, let them laugh that wins; this is bad news for him, though not for others.</p>

<p>At the next Fleet, my Genius conducted me into an Alley hard by <reg orig="Chearing-cross">Charing Cross</reg>, where <reg orig="Cuitezans">Citizens</reg> are lapidable for two pence a dozen, and there my dull <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> were awakened with such a Curfew, such a clear <reg orig="eccho">echo</reg> as <em>Pilemel</em> could <reg orig="neer">near</reg> parallel. Whereupon <em>I</em> <reg orig="stept">stepped</reg> into the Covent, and who should there be but a <reg orig="Taylors">Tailor's</reg> bride standing like <em>Diana</em> among the <reg orig="Nimphs">Nymphs</reg>, displaying his Doctrine of Saint <em>Dominica</em>, and measuring out Divinity by her <reg orig="husbands">husband's</reg> yard, giving to every Woman a competent measure: As for men, there was none there; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the ninth part of a wan was present, for the Taylor himself was there, whose yard was common to every sister: And as for their Precepts, <em>I</em> have <reg orig="squar'd">squared</reg> some of them out in this following Poem.</p><pb n="7" />

<p><i>The Poem</i></p>
<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>ALL of you that do desire to be</line>
<line>Of our divine Society,</line>
<line>You must be armed sure and strong</line>
<line>To do no right, no take no wrong:</line>
<line>And <reg orig="whatsoe're">whatsoe'er</reg> you take in hand,</line>
<line>Be sure you make Religion stand</line>
<line>As a Palladium in defence</line>
<line>Of your <reg orig="adorn'd">adorned</reg> and guilt pretence:</line>
<line>Use fine and gentle words <reg orig="untill">until</reg> </line>
<line>Ye work the Hearers to your Will:</line>
<line>And if (by <em>Hocus Pocus</em>) ye</line>
<line>Can (close and unexpected lye)</line>
<line>Steal tools of silver gold, or rings,</line>
<line>Or such like necessary things,</line>
<line>And not debouch the tribe with shame,</line>
<line>Do it in <em><reg orig="Proserpina's">Proserpine's</reg> Name</em>:</line>
<line>And when your husbands shall be ill,</line>
<line>Go ye to bed to whom ye will:</line>
<line>Or whom ye can procure: but make</line>
<line>No scruple for your Conscience sake.</line>
<line>If ye are Virgins, then indeed</line>
<line>Take man, for ye have greatest need;</line>
<line>But doubt not in the least disgrace;</line>
<line>For when you are in such a case,</line>
<line>as that your bellies puff and mount,</line>
<line>and ye have not a day to count,</line>
<line>Then come to us, and you shall see</line>
<line><reg orig="We'l">We'll</reg> give you safe Delivery.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>