<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell170">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 170</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate <reg orig="Inteligencer">Intelligencer</reg>,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Speech of his <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg> the Lord Ambassador from the most illustrious and high-born Prince, <em>Lewis King of France and Navar</em>, and his Message and Letters Credential, presented to his highness the Lord Protector, yesterday, being the <em>28</em> of this instant March, upon his receiving Audience. The dividing of the English <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> into four <em>Squadrons</em>, the <reg orig="cleering">clearing</reg> of the narrow seas of the <em>French, Dutch</em>, and <em>Irish <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg></em>, and the number of ships taken. The violent proceedings of the <em>Highlanders</em>, and the manner of their descending and <reg orig="faling">falling</reg> in amongst the Lowlanders.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday March 22. to Wednesday March 29. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>The English Fleet are divided into four Squadrons, the better to scour and secure the Narrow Seas, they are excellently well equipped, and as bravely <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>: Nothing wanting, but a resolute Enemy to fight then; which neither curled Waves, nor Weltick Ocean can bear in case the <reg orig="Belgick">Belgic</reg> <reg orig="Canons">Cannons</reg> be <reg orig="silenc'd">silenced</reg>. They have already forced the <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, Rovers, and Irish <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg>, from Brest to Toulon in France, where they have now time enough to sing the second part to the same tune, <i>O bone, O bone</i>. We have taken another of their men of War, and a Dutch Merchant laden with extraordinary good commodities. And Fame reports, that they have taken another of ours, <em>In skits</em>.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Ferries">Ferry's</reg></em> Regiment of horse is designed to relieve the Lord <em><reg orig="Fleetwoods">Fleetwood's</reg></em> from the Guards at the <em>Mewes</em>, the <em>Roads</em>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>This day about 100 Colliers came safe into the River of Thames, and it is already ordered by many of the honest Woodmongers to sell their Coals for eight pence <em>per</em> bushel.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday <em>March</em> 25.</head>

<p>Presents us with variety of strange <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from the Royal stamp, to wit, First, that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> has sent a fiery Summons, and a flaming Declaration to the <reg orig="whimsie-pated">whimsy-pated</reg> Jockies, to come in to his assistance, for the service of their King and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: but <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> possible, but that they may be soon stifled with the <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> of our guns. 2 That there is a great army preparing in Germany to land suddenly: but when, and where, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>. And thirdly, that their <reg orig="gude">good</reg> mickle Gentleman valiant <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em>, second son to the late King of Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>, was to command in chief, &amp;c. The truth of which we question: though many are pleased to whet their sharp appetites upon that ancient saying, <i>That there is never no smoke, but there is some fire</i>: and already begin to chew the Cud upon the Ordinance, this day extant, for continuing an Act for impressing of <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg>, <em>viz.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuation of an Act, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for laying an imposition upon Coles, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas.</i></head>

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg> <i>An Act for laying an imposition upon Coles, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas</i>; And all powers and clauses therein contained be, and are hereby continued, and shall and do stand in full force, until the 26. day of <em>March</em>, 1655.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuing an Act for the impressing of <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> <i>an Act for impressing of <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg></i>, And all powers and clauses therein <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, be, and are hereby revives, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> continue and stand in full force, until the first day of <em>Novemb</em>. 1654.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for passing Custodies of <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg> and <reg orig="Ideots">Idiots</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Act of the late Parl. on the behalf of Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, it was, among other things, enacted, That the <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> for passing of the Custodies of the said Idiots &amp; <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, should be signed by the Council of State before the Commissioners <pb n="2" />of the great Seal of <em>England</em>, should pass the same <unclear>under</unclear> the said Seal; And whereas that <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> is since dissolved, Be it Ordained by his highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal for the time being, do not pass the said Subsidier under the Great Seal, before the same be signed by his Highness the Lord Protector, and that the same so signed by his Highness, shall be a sufficient Warrant for passing the same under the said Great Seal, any Law, Statute, Act, Ordinance, or <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>The great Fleet of colliers from Newcastle are now come safe into the River of Thames; and the price is already ordered by many, to sell them for eight pence a bushel: in pursuance whereof Proclamation hath been made at Westminster, and the said price is stated &amp; put in execution. Twelve of this fleet were stranded by the Hollander, who have taken a Vessel belonging to Yarmouth laden with Wine, coming from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>; but they purchased her at a <reg orig="deer">deer</reg> rate: for having taken excess of the <reg orig="juyce">juice</reg> of Grapes, they steered <reg orig="head-long">headlong</reg> among the Rocks at Hartlepool, where they all received <reg orig="ship-wrack">shipwreck</reg>, and the Vessel was torn in pieces.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Gouncil">Council</reg>, have passed an Ordinance appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Preachers; and for prevention of all scandalous and popish intruders it is ordained, That every person who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from and after the 25 of March instant be presented, nominated, chosen or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with Care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Lecture in England or Wales, shall, before he be admitted into any such Benefice or Lecture, be adjudged and approved by the persons hereafter named, to be a person for the grace of God in him, his holy and <reg orig="unblamable">unblameable</reg> Conversation as also for his knowledge an utterance, able and fit to preach the <reg orig="Gosspel">Gospel</reg> and that after the said 25 of <em>March</em>, no person, but such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> upon such approbation be admitted <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Lecture or Benefice as aforesaid <em>&amp;c.</em> Francis Rous Esq; Dr. Tho. Goodwin Dr. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Owen, M. Thankful Owen, Dr. Arrowsmith, Dr. <unclear>Muckney</unclear>, Dr. Horton, M. <reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg>, Caryl M. <unclear>Pinlip</unclear> Nyl William Carter, M. Sidrach Simpson, M. William Greenhill, M. William Strong, M. Thomas <unclear>Manton</unclear>, M. Samuel Slater M. Cooper M. Marshal, M. Tombes, M. Cradock, <em>M</em>. <unclear>Fairclogh</unclear>, <em>M.</em> Hugh Peters, <em>M.</em> Sterrey, <em>M.</em> Bamford, <em>M. Valentine</em>, <em>M.</em> Jeffee, <em>M.</em> Obadiah Sedgwick, <em>M.</em> Nic Lockie, <em>M.</em> Russel <em>M.</em> Dyke, <em>M.</em> Campfield, Rob. Tichborn Alderman of London <unclear>Mark Hltley</unclear> Thomas Wood, John <pb n="3" />Sadler, Wil. Goff, Tho. St. Nicholas, Wil. Packer, and Edw. Cresset Esquires.</p>

<p>These, or any five of them, are appointed commissioners for such approbation and admission as is abovesaid, and upon death or removal of any of them, others <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from time to time be nominated in their places by the Lord Protector and his Successors, by advice of his Council, in the <reg orig="intervale">interval</reg> of Parliaments; and sitting the Parliament, by the Protector and Parliament: And the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, met together in some certain plan of the city of <em>London</em> or <em>Westminster</em>, as his Highness shall appoint, are hereby authorized to judge and take knowledge of the ability and fitness of any person so presented, chosen, or appointed, according to the qualification <reg orig="abov-mentioned">above-mentioned</reg>; &amp; upon their approbation of such his ability and fitness, to grant unto such person admission to such Benefice or Lecture by an Instrument in Writing, under a common Seal to be appointed by his Highness, and under the hand of the Register or Registers for the time being, and to be also nominated by the Lord Protector and his Successors; which Instrument the said Register or Registers <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> cause to be entered in a book for that purpose, and kept upon Record.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Uppsala</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em> thus: The Treaty goes on, but slowly; yet doubtless, if the Transactions between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> take effect, they will soon be <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> in new Councils; for her Maj. promiseth fair to the L. <em>Whitlock</em>; and hath revived her former Overtures of resigning up the Government to her Successor, and desires the liberty of retiring into privacy. The great Taxes upon the people is conceived <reg orig="wil">will</reg> push them forward to some notable design, which causeth the Senators to sit very close in <reg orig="councel">council</reg>. They are consulting what Answer to return to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proposals, for resigning up the Crown and <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>, to her Successor, or Lord Protector. But by another Abstract we are given to understand, that the Marriage between the King of Scots, and her Royal Majesty is, ratified and agreed upon by the Princes and Peers of the General Assembly at the Dyet, <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, that the great Duke of <em>Holstein</em> is to marry the Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> Princess of <em>Orange</em>. Alas! alas! too high fortunes, to be interwoven with so fatal and deplorable conditions: For, the Post Letters of a later date, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> inclination is to merit the King of <pb n="4" />the Romans, eldest Son to the Emperor of Germany; but that business being <reg orig="deter'd">deterred</reg> by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, 'tis probable she will again renew her former Proposals for to <reg orig="center">centre</reg> in Solitudes. Notwithstanding, the hearts of her Subjects are exceeding averse to the change of Government, and with great acclamations of joy sounds forth her praises with a cordial and loyal <reg orig="Eccho">Echo</reg>,</p>

<head level="1">Long Live THE QUEEN,</head>

<p>Indeed, <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> comes a better; for Changes and Mutations, are the <reg orig="Fore-runners">Forerunners</reg> of a fatal Catastrophe and Depopu8lations. &mdash; but mum! not a word more, O it would vex a Dog to see a <reg orig="Puddin">Pudding</reg> creep.</p>

<p>Hi Highness the Lord Protector being not very well, takes the morning <reg orig="Ayr">Air</reg> often: he lies again at the Cock-pit, but intends <reg orig="e're">ere</reg> long, for his new Palace, so soon as all things can be made ready for his accommodation. The old Trade still goes on, and a Brew-house is erecting.</p>

<p>The Dutch Letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning last about 3 of the clock, was seized and broke open by 5 Hectorian Knights of Fortune, within a mile of S. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> Church; but finding no <reg orig="moneyes">moneys</reg> in the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg>, broke open the Letters, cast them upon the ground, and turned the Messenger back again, with a <reg orig="Belgick">Belgic</reg> Flea in his ear. Some of these Letters made mention of a final Agreement between the two Republics of England and Holland. And Monsieur <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> Neusuille</em>, Ambassador from the King of France, was brought in state through the City on the 27 instant, to Sir Abraham <reg orig="Wiliiams">Williams</reg> in the Palace-yard: He is to receive audience on the 28 instant.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From Dublin thus: The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, when he comes back to you will confute those false Reports that were raised of us here, he having had a reception as a Prince, with 300 horse out of the City (most of them Citizens) with <reg orig="bone-fires">bonfires</reg> at night throughout the City.</p>

<head level="3"><em>March</em> the 24.</head>

<p>No news, but that upon a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> invitation the City should so solemnly observe a Day of fasting and humiliation, and it is wished that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> this day fortnight may keep it no worse: for we have great cause to bury our <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the dust for our notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised among us, and to consider the Rod of God upon us, in an universal Drought for some years, and still continued <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <reg orig="famin">famine</reg> and mortality: for, true it is, that in the North of England, and several other parts of this Nation, the Springs, River, and <reg orig="Brookes">Brookes</reg>, are almost dry for 20 miles distant. O then consider!</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>To Fasting why should sensual flesh be <reg orig="loth">loath</reg>?</line>
<line>Fasting is good for soul and body both.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>By a Letter from <em>Harwich</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that there is a Dutch ship, of 400 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts, and Iron, to a great value brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March the 21.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Protector set forth a Declaration, inviting the People of <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to a solemn day of fasting and humiliation, and ordered that <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the 24 instant should be set apart for the cities of London and Westminster; and the same day fortnight for all the Counties in general in England and Wales. The Causes are, first, the common notorious sins impenitently practised amongst us. Secondly, the present long drought, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> famine and mortality. The sins taken notice of by his Highness are, Notwithstanding the just Liberty Spiritual and Civil, God hath procured by his own people, yet want of humble walking in the <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of Christ, or to communicate that liberty one to another. Or thankfully to acknowledge our liberty of worshipping God in <unclear>hotness</unclear>, want of brotherly love Not owning one another for the grace of God more <reg orig="then">than</reg> form: Not seeking the Kingdom of Christ within us, before one without us. <reg orig="Listning">Listening</reg> to false Christs: Temporal Rule for Saints. A crying up of the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, and the other fruits of the Spirit: And an evil carriage towards them without: crying down Ministers that have a large <unclear>seal</unclear> of their Ministry, want of old Puritan self <reg orig="deniall">denial</reg>; <pb n="6" />Mercy to the poor, uprightness, justice, and contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, as it ought to be apostasizings of many running after notions and fancies against Magistracy, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, Scriptures, and Ordinances, contempt of the gospel, and sincere Professors of it, even for the Image of Christ in them. Oaths, Drunkenness, Revellings, and all manner of licentiousness. And the impunity of these things, through neglect of the Magistracy in several parts of the Nation.</p>

<p>On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, being the 27 of this instant <em>March</em>, there came a <em>Post</em> from Scotland, intimating, That the Royal part increaseth, and that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise <em>Southerland, Caithness</em>, and the county of <em>Ross</em>, and so to drain the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, even as a <reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> sucketh in Water, of all the able, stout, and resolute hearts, that are able to bear Arms from sixteen to sixty; with a Resolution to descend down into the Lowlands: for indeed, they grow numerous, and swell up as a Snow-Ball doth in its rolling; but may as soon dissolve again in the like Element. The <reg orig="Lor">Lord</reg> <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to seven hundred, the Earl of <em>Athol</em> five hundred, Co. <em>Forbs</em> five hundred, and the last general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> seven thousand horse and foot they spake themselves to be <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> armed, but have not obtained as yet the silver Instrument, which is the life of the Cause, and the very sinew of War: but their expectation is great from <em>Germany</em>, and for <reg orig="ought">aught</reg> I know, long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for may come at last: in the interim, they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march. And the Names of the chief Commanders are as followeth, <em>viz.</em></p>

<!-- list laid out in two columns -->
<p>Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, commander in chief.</p>
<p><em><unclear>Saundy</unclear> Glencarn</em>, General of the Horse.</p>
<p>The Earl of <em>Athol</em> <reg orig="Ceneral">General</reg> of the Foot.</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Kenmore</em>, Lieutenant General.</p>
<p>Sir <em>George Monroe</em>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Major.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Ordnance.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Hinderson</em>, commander in chief of the <reg orig="Bow-men">Bow-men</reg>.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Dyler</em>, commander in chief of the <reg orig="Bow-men">Bow-men</reg>.</p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Sinclare">Sinclair</reg></em>, Engineer.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Crawford</em>.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Hume</em>,</p>
<p>And divers other eminent Officers.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>From Scotland it is further advertized, That Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath sent a Letter to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, declaring, That it was not unknown what amicable <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> they had <reg orig="us'd">used</reg>, to avoid the effusion of Christian blood since they came into those parts, which though hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they should <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the same; <em><reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> further</em>, That their Arms were still <reg orig="stretcht">stretched</reg> out ready to embrace them, <reg orig="when ever">whenever</reg> God should incline them to come in; and that they sought not domination over them, to enslave them, nor to depress them in any lawful way, but to carry on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Work: And that if they would still be blinded, and persist in the <reg orig="gain-saying">gainsaying</reg> and opposing, then what further misery befell their Nation by famine or sword, would <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> heavy upon them. This Letter (though favouring so much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adversaries; for immediately thereupon, an Answer was returned; which being briefly contracted, the genuine sense take as followeth; That in case they were not in a capacity against the unjust proceedings of the English, yet were they in a capacity to suffer, and should submit to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Will, either by doing or suffering, until the time of their deliverance come; and that if it were their happiness to perish in their Duty and Loyalty, it would be a sufficient mercy to them: and when the persecution had arrived to its height, their captivity should be returned. But doubtless, but that in time we shall be able to put a Hook into the Nostrils, and a Bridle into the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of these high and mighty Youngsters, who threaten nothing but fire and sword to all that shall oppose them. There has been a Summons sent to the castle of Lough by col. <em>Morgan</em>, in the name of the Lord Protector, demanding a rendition. But the Governor returned Answer, That as for the castle it stood upon a Rock, and as for the Lord Protector he knew no such man: in consideration whereof, he was resolved to dispute the Walls by Inches and to fight it out to the last man.</p>

<p>The 28 instant, the French Ambassador had Audience before his Highness the Lord Protector, at which time, upon presenting of his Letters Credential from his Master the King, he made a very learned and excellent Oration, touching his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, and the renewing of a more stricter League and Union between both Nations. Of which, more in our next.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>