<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell176">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 176</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer.</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING,</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> now on foot in <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and other parts of <em>Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these Particulars, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector, concerning the two great and potent Fleets of England, and the new Orders and Instructions sent to the Judges of the Admiralty, touching the Navy, with the strict charge and command concerning all ships and men of war, both at sea and in Port, and the Resolution of <unclear>these men touching</unclear> the famous Expedition to be determinated in the behalf of all Christendom. The proceedings of the Hollanders thereupon. The advancing of the English towards Brest, the Remonstrance of Mr. John Lilburn, and the proceedings of both Armies in Scotland.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> April <em>the</em> 26, to <em>Wednesday</em> May <em>the</em> 3.</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>Geo: Horton for information of the People.</em></head>
<hr />

<p>By an Express from <em>Scotland</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That Gen. <em><reg orig="Midleton">Midleton</reg></em>, who knows well enough how to manage the War, at the first <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>  of the approach of the English Forces, drew off his men from all places of disadvantage, and marched into the lower <reg orig="pats">parts</reg> of <em>Southerland</em>, having got the River of <em>Forth</em> to favour his Intentions, by seating himself where the River is most spacious; as also by taking all the Boats that made the River passable, and by <reg orig="fastning">fastening</reg> and mooring the Boats on his side. Our forces are all drawing to a Head, and many supplied are going from <em>Ireland</em>, to assist their Brethren in <em>Scotland</em>; for, indeed, <pb n="1" />some letters represent, that by reason of the access and recourse of many discontented parties, the enemy is much exasperated: Yes notwithstanding, many there are which have abandoned this desperate service, that to any Rational Eye seems to promise nothing but Death and Famine to the adverse party.</p>

<p>By another Express, thus: we have received very remarkable intelligence, intimating, That the Royal party increase, and have taken some few prisoners from the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills, the Lord <em>Forrester</em>, and the Lord <em>Dudhop</em> are in <em>Athol</em>, and very active in attending the motion of General <em>Middleton</em>. The rest of their forces in <em>Caithness</em> have left no means unassayed for raising of the whole <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>; but the people being <reg orig="timerous">timorous</reg> of rising, <reg orig="feariny">fearing</reg> <reg orig="least">lest</reg> the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Sinclair</em>, commanded by cap. <em>Langrish</em> of col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Regiment should punish them for their Loyalty, after <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> march from thence: wherefore for their encouragement, Maj. Gen. <em>Dyal</em> with a strong party of foot, and 100 stout horse, is ordered to sit down before it for the reducing of it, which is conceived to be a work of great difficulty, the place being situated on a very high <em>Rock</em>, yet if they prove successful in this <reg orig="Atchievement">Achievement</reg>, they intend then to attempt <em>Ruthin</em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>; but cap. <em>Hill</em> (the Governor) has reinforced it with provisions, and is well provided for a siege.</p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em>, the last <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, That the <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> party increaseth, and are very much exasperated; the which to confirm, we shall here present you with a Letter, wherein is comprised the full particulars, and exact Transactions on both sides.</p>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>Having so convenient an opportunity, I could no <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> possible omit writing to you by this Post; though notwithstanding it seems to be full Term here with us, since the adjourning of yours at London; for, to speak truth, it is high time now to look about us, since that the enemy dares presume to descend down upon the Lowlands, and (Lorain like) make great devastations, in plundering, pillaging, and unpeopling of the Countries; but some of them taking so long a leap, <reg orig="hopt">hopped</reg> shot back; amongst the rest, two Captains, and some few private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, were lately <reg orig="truss'd">trussed</reg> up, as the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> does Wild ducks: Since which time, Gen. <em>Middleton</em> has drawn his Army into Southerland, betwixt whom, and our forces, there is a Navigable River, not passable but by <unclear>Boats all those</unclear> the enemy has drawn to their banks, and many desperate persons go in any have recourse to them. They still continue in <pb n="2" />gathering up their new Levies, and have had a general <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, where a new Oath and Covenant was taken, to fight it out to the last man; and likewise Glencairn's Declaration was there published, <reg orig="stuff'd">stuffed</reg> up with many expressions that carry little consistency with their Course. I may possibly present you with a copy by the next: In the interim, we are drawn together our main strength to fight them: The great God of Hosts appear for us, and crown us with victory in the day of <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Dolkeith the 25. of April, 1654.</p>

<p>By an Express from <em>Newcastle</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Monk</em>, after some congratulation from the Mayor and Aldermen, by three sorts of Wine, Loaf-sugar, Cakes, and <reg orig="Lemmons">Lemons</reg>, took his leave, and immediately journeyed for <em>Scotland</em>; upon whose departure a ship bound from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> was sunk near the Bar of <em>Tinmouth</em>, and another <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Holy Island, which was richly frught, and bound for <em>Yarmouth</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> April 26.</i></head>

<p>This day the Peace between England and the United Provinces, was by 12 Trumpets, and 4 Heralds at Arms solemnly proclaimed; first, in <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> in presence of his highness and the Council, and afterwards received at Temple-bar by the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen, and thence conducted to the Royal Exchange.</p>

<p>The 27. His highness sent an Invitation to the Dutch Ambassadors Resident in London, and a stately and magnificent Feast was prepared, with <unclear>delicate</unclear> Entertainment in this Princely Palace.</p>

<p>The Articles of Union between England and Sweden have been debated by the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, and Count Erick, who has delivered in certain Articles on behalf of that Crown, but his Excellency has delivered in his Exceptions to the Queen, and the Reasons of non-admittance. So that the accord as yet seems dubious; in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, be pleased to take a view of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proposals to P. <em>Charles</em>, to <unclear>wit</unclear>; 1 She will retain the best part of the Kingdom and Customs to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>. 2 She will be no subject, but free of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> without control. 3 She will travel where she pleaseth. 4 She will not revoke those Gifts of hers, which are <em>Pr&aelig;dia Corone</em> and were by her given out of favour to Courtiers. <i>The <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Answer.</i> 1 He will not be a King without a Kingdom or <unclear>at</unclear> least without the better part of it. 2 he will have no Rival, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> she a Superior. 3 He will not hazard himself about her designs abroad. 4 He will not be without a sufficient Revenue both for peace and war.</p>

<p>By the last Intelligence from the Navy we are <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That divers Prizes have been this week taken; amongst the rest, a Dutch ship bound for the East Indies; the rest, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> where, for I do <pb n="3" />not: <reg orig="Onely">Only</reg> thus much be assured of, that the English Assurance hath taken the non-Assurance belonging to France, laden with 25 <unclear>Lasts</unclear>of Tar and pitch, and likewise the <em>Confidence</em> of <em>Amsterdam</em>, gallantly fraught with Pitch, Linseed, and Deal, was <reg orig="constrain'd">constrained</reg> to yield, after a fair salute from the precious <em>Pearl</em>; <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, a French ship likewise; i which service, the captain, and one M. <em>Spilman</em>, deported <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> with singular courage: And after this honourable <reg orig="Atchievment">Achievement</reg>, as a testimony of their cordial affection and love to their <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, bare up with the nimble <em>Drake</em>, and boarded two stately <em><reg orig="Flemmings">Flemings</reg></em> sweetly laden with Wines from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>: but alas! to these sweet comforts, we cannot <unclear>on</unclear> it, but present you with certain tart crudities, that is, the <em>Fox</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> striking <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> with the <em>Royal James</em> of <em>Brest</em>, an exchanging two <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, was so puissantly received, that after many dry <reg orig="blowes">blows</reg> on both sides, and coming to <reg orig="grapling">grappling</reg>, they sunk each other; but by the <unclear>series</unclear> of <em>Providence</em> many of the men were miraculously saved, by plunging through the raging Billows upon the top of empty hogsheads.</p>

<p>From <em>Portsmouth</em> they write, That two Squadrons of the English are still riding in <em>Stokes-Bay</em>, but expect to weigh Anchor about the fifth of <em>May</em>: The rest are gone out, and upon the arrival of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Pen</em> from <em>London</em>, expects to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon some honourable design against the Enemies of <em>Christendom</em>, and to release those deplorable <em>Captives</em> at <em>Argier</em>, and <reg orig="else where">elsewhere</reg>. We hear that the Knights of <em>Malta</em>, and <em>Venetians</em>, are also designed against the Turk, and to that end, 40 Galleys are preparing for the service.</p>

<p>By an Express from <em>Falmouth</em> it is certified, That the English <em><reg orig="Grayhound">Greyhound</reg></em> chasing two <em>Brest</em> men of War, they proved so subtle in the <reg orig="persuit">pursuit</reg>, that bearing up amongst the Rocks, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> their own Doors, she was forced to strike off, and durst not venture to attempt the Game any further.</p>

<p>There are about 100 ships bound Southward to several parts, and stay <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for a fair wind <i>A prosperous Gale attend them.</i></p>

<p>From <em>France</em> they write, That immediately upon the departure of <em>Henrietta Maria</em> late Queen of <em>England</em>) from <em>Paris</em>, there appeared a great Eclipse of the sun, which continued for the space of 7 <reg orig="houres">hours</reg>; But so soon as its radiant Beams <reg orig="brake">broke</reg> forth again in its glorious lustre, there was then seen strange Apparitions in the <reg orig="Ayr">Air</reg>; as two great Armies in a Warlike posture, the black and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> <reg orig="Ensignes">Ensigns</reg>, <pb n="4" />the beating of Drums, and sounding of Trumpets, the depolutations of Cities, and sacking of Towns, with sundry other dreadful <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> wonderful to behold: which certainly presageth some mighty <em>Change</em> and <em>Catastrophe</em>. But from the Devouring Sword, the Lord preserve Us, and grant that it may no longer be drunk in the <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> chosen people.</p>

<p>Cardinal <em>de Rets</em> is removed to the castle of <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em>, where he hath been complemented by the Duke of <em>Brissac</em>, and most of the Nobility and Gentry thereabouts; the <em>Parisians </em> are very much troubled at the monstrous Imposts and Taxes laid upon them; <i>can ye blame them?</i> and threaten to ease themselves, by Revenge upon <em>Mazarine</em>, who has unjustly <reg orig="usurpt">usurped</reg> so vast a revenue, by degrading others, and setting up himself, <i>An Epidemical Disease, I could wish we might cease from so great an <unclear>incision</unclear></i>: Therefore, to remove the Cause (in part) of their present Maladies, he has Ordered (by his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> special <reg orig="Commandement">Commandment</reg>) that the Impost upon all <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> shall be taken off, and has promised to redress all other grievances, so soon as the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Affairs of the Crown and Kingdom will admit, <i>Better once <reg orig="then">than</reg> never, I wish it universal.</i></p>

<p>His Majesty has sent two <reg orig="Councellors">Councillors</reg> of the <em>Parliament</em> to <unclear><em>Chantroi</em></unclear> and <em>Montmorencie</em>, take possession of the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> <em>Revenues</em> and <em>Castles</em>, and to <reg orig="re-unite">reunite</reg> them to the <em>Crown of France</em>, which accordingly they did, and there proclaimed him <reg orig="Traytor">Traitor</reg> by <em>Act</em> of <em>Parliament</em>; <i>that's no <reg orig="newes">news</reg>.</i></p>

<p>But his Highness is resolved to prosecute the Cause notwithstanding, and since the denouncing of that <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Sentence against Him, he has made a vigorous progress in the same Colours, and hung up some of the Effigies of the Nobility at his <reg orig="head-quarters">headquarters</reg>.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Scots</em> is upon his removal; but the Duke of York is very much solicited to continue his command in the Army, being in high esteem with the King and Court, and <em>Achilles</em> like striketh Terror where He comes.</p>

<p><i>His Highness the Lord Protector has set forth a Proclamation concerning a cessation of all Acts of hostility between the Commonwealth of England, and that of the United Provinces, and their respective people, and the restitution of all things taken and seized upon by either party after the 4 of this instant May 1654. This is to be published by both parties throughout their respective Territories.</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From <em>Leghorn</em> the 2 of <em>April</em>, 1654. The last <reg orig="newes">news</reg> we have in these parts, is, that by a Vessel come hither with silks from Messina we hear, that there hath been of late a great <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> upon that coast, where 16 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> have been cast away, and above 1300 men; besides, about 30 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> upon these seas, and 2500 men.</p>

<p>By another Express from Alicant we hear, That a great Army is raising in the Kingdoms of <reg orig="Valentia">Valencia</reg> and Aragon, which are to be sent for the Dukedom of <em>Milan</em>, and partly for <em>Catalonia</em>; The Vice-King of Naples <reg orig="playes">playes</reg> <em>Rex</em> upon the coast of <em>Apuglia</em>, and has beaten most of the <em>French</em> towards <em>Sicily</em>. The Pestilence is again broken out at <em>Malaga</em> and <em>Barcelona</em>. </p>

<p><em>Dover</em> the 24 of April, 1654. This evening came into this Road a private man of War being a <em>Marget</em> Hoy of 6 guns, and about 50 men, who having found in the channel a Dutch ship coming from the West-Indies that have been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent by the tediousness of the Voyage, did of a sudden clap Them aboard, and after a short (but sharp) dispute, became Masters of her, and brought her along with them: the ship is said to be of great value, for besides plate, whereof several Letters say there is a good quantity, the ship will be found full of other rich commodities, which will prove very beneficial to the Takers, when it comes to be judged prize.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em> they write, That the Senate having received the <em>news</em> of the Defeat of some of their forces in <em>Dalmatia</em>, which was done by a part of 5000 Turks, who lying in an Ambuscado took them at an advantage, but with this moderation, that the <em>Morlacks</em> and the <em>Venetians</em> <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> themselves so gallantly, that <reg orig="neer">near</reg> upon 2000 of the Turks were slain on the place, and many wounded, but not without the loss of 250 mean.</p>

<p>The Declaration and Petition of the Mayor and Inhabitants of the Town of <unclear><em>Guilford</em></unclear> being presented to his Highness, blessing god for taking upon his shoulders that great and ponderous <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of the Government of the three Nations, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> desiring a godly and learned minister to supply the Benefice of <em>Trinity</em> and <em>Maries</em>-Parishes in the behalf of him lately deceased. &amp;c. This being presented, his Highness standing uncovered, vouchsafed this gracious Answer,</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p><i><em>Gentlemen</em>, I have read your paper, <reg orig="wherin">wherein</reg>, what you there express touching my taking of the Government upon me, you say what is truth, I did not desire it, nor have I (I am sure) told you so; I believe god put it into your hearts, I shall desire your prayers, that I may do as you have expressed, for God is my Bottom, and in him <reg orig="onely">only</reg> do I trust: As for your desire of a Minister, I think I have not granted the Living away; and upon your making choice of such a one as your paper mentions, I shall take Order that you shall have your suit.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Hide-Park">Hyde Park</reg>, May 1.</i></head>

<p>this day there was the hurling of a great Ball, by 50 <em>Cornish</em> Gentlemen on the one side, and 50 on the other: one party played in red caps, and the other in white: there was present his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, many of his privy Council, and divers eminent Gentlemen, to whose view was presented great agility of body,, &amp; most neat and exquisite <reg orig="wrastling">wrestling</reg>, at every meeting of one with the other, which was ordered with such dexterity, that it was to show more the strength, vigour and nimbleness of their bodies, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to <reg orig="indanger">endanger</reg> their persons. The Ball they <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> was silver, and <reg orig="design'd">designed</reg> for that party which did win the Goal.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg> April 28.</i></head>

<p>The Armies on both sides are preparing to receive each other, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> has <reg orig="drain'd">drained</reg> <em>Innerness</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those forces which he brought from <em>Aberdeen</em>, so that he lies with about 1200 Horse and Dragoons, and 2000 Foot, betwixt the enemy and the passes they must needs march though, if they intend to move out of the North corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, and 'tis said, they are resolved, there being no way left them to avoid it, but through such inaccessible bounds, as 'tis impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their foot, it being exceeding mountainous, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> they are in will not <pb n="7" />long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an account of some action betwixt him and <em>Middleton</em>; what the success will be, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>; for, to speak truth, we have a very stout and stubborn enemy to deal withal.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Navy, April 29.</i></head>

<p>We have entertained the <em>Proclamation of Peace</em> with the greatest solemnity that possibly can be; and Gen. <em>Pen</em> being once come aboard, I hope We shall then find what will be the Expedition which <em>Christendom</em> so much looks upon, whether we shall go to <em>Leghorn</em>, or the high Determinations of the council so shall order it, as they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> call the <em>Turks</em> to an account at <em>Tunis</em>, or <em>Algier</em>, for the wrongs they have done to our Nation. Indeed, we are so unanimous for Action and Enterprise, that each <reg orig="mans">mans</reg> noble Spirit is ready to push him forward to <reg orig="atchieve">achieve</reg> something that may add more honour to his <reg orig="countries">country's</reg> Fame.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>O glorious <em>Heroes</em>, that despise your own,</line>
<line>For <reg orig="others">others'</reg> safeties, purchasing the frown</line>
<line>Of praise immortal, <reg orig="Virtues">Virtue's</reg> Throne do claim</line>
<line>By steep ascents, and <reg orig="tryumph">triumph</reg> over Time.</line>
<line>Labour and sweat by purchasing honour here,</line>
<line>Is more <reg orig="then">than</reg> staying of a <reg orig="murth'rous">murderous</reg> Bear:</line>
<line>He that would land at joy must <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> through woes,</line>
<line>And sleight the silken mean, and base repose;</line>
<line>but <reg orig="imbrace">embrace</reg> labour, and with gallant mind</line>
<line>B' as restless as the Sun, as nimble as wind:</line>
<line>And brave <em>Alcides</em> like, slay the fierce <em>Bore</em>,</line>
<line>(we may do now as he did heretofore)</line>
<line>And Honour, thought it be a small reward</line>
<line>For those our Seas, that valiantly do guard,</line>
<line>If as the warbling <em>Lark</em>, I do not raise,</line>
<line>I'm in a Cage; she, mounting, sees <em>Sol's</em> <reg orig="Rayes">Rays</reg>,</line>
<line>And cherished with warmth and freedom sings</line>
<line>A melody, fit for <reg orig="Eares">Ears</reg> of Kings.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>From <em>Southampton</em> thus: Sir, <i>Mr. John Lilburn (we hear) is committed to the Castle in Jersey, where he deports himself with abundance of patience and humility, and has also declared, that he <reg orig="aymes">aims</reg> at nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the glory of God, the advancement of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the restoring of every free born man of England, to its ancient Rights and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, and the perfect purging of the Law from all abuses and corruptions</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>