<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell177">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 177</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer.</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING,</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> now on foot in <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and other parts of <em>Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these Particulars, viz.</head>

<p><i>Strange and wonderful News from the Isle of Jersey, concerning Mr. John Lilburn, late prisoner in the Tower of London; and a Narrative of several particulars touching the State Affairs. With a Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector to the People, and the Debates of the Committee, touching the Equity and Lenity of the Law, and that the Justice thereof allots no pardon to the Wicked. The King of <reg orig="Denmarks">Denmark's</reg> Message to the Lord Protector, A Declaration of the Christian Princes touching the present Government, and the Inscription of the Papers affixed and set up touching his Highness. The proceedings of the two Armies in Scotland, and the taking of Brazil from the States of Holland.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> May <em>the</em> 263 to <em>Wednesday</em> May <em>the</em> 10.</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>Geo: Horton for information of the people.</em></head>
<hr />

<p>The concluding of a peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, causeth new <em>counsels</em> in almost all the Courts of <em>Christendom</em>; and so radiant a lustre doth it cast among the Princes, that many of them have been pleased to set forth a <em>congratulatory Declaration</em>, owning the Government which is invested in Him: And <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, sundry papers have been set up at the most eminent places in several parts, with this Inscription,</p>

<head level="2">Let OLIVER live, so long as He rules well.</head>

<pb n="1" />

<p>his Highness the Lord Protector, and her Highness Protectress, are gone to <em>Hampton Court</em>. The Yeomen of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Guard wait by turns Monthly, and Mr. <em>Ingoldsby</em> (brother to col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>) is made captain of the Guard. Their coats are grey cloth with black Velvet <reg orig="collers">collars</reg>, and black Velvet and silver lace and trimming. col. <em>Nathaniel Fiennes</em> is added a member to the council.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador makes many applications to his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, by way of negotiating a peace between <em>England</em> and his Majesty (who is now of years to be crowned very suddenly) if he propound terms safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, he need not doubt of his Errand, <i>For it is a sign of godliness to be at peace with all men; yet peace cannot <reg orig="tryumph">triumph</reg>, except Reason ruleth.</i></p>

<p>The Ambassador from the King of <em>Denmark</em> has presented his Letters credential from the King his Master, and on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> last he had audience before his Highness, where he congratulated him in his place of Government, and seemed to acknowledge it a <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> that so much of the differences were taken up by the Treaty with the Dutch, and hoped all would conduce to a happy peace, to the advancement of the Protestant Religion, and stopping the effusion of innocent <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>. This appears very fair; but he had something more of State Affairs, which he imparted in writing unto his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg>, and will afterwards be taken into consideration.</p>

<p>There is to be a general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs by the <em>English</em> fleet very suddenly; and Rear-Admiral <em>Lawson</em> is already gone towards the Northern parts with 20 men of war; the <em>Fairfax</em> is Admiral; and 'tis said he hath landed 6 or 7000 men near the Isles of <em>Orkney</em>, who intend to make up suddenly towards Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, who has sent the Lord <em>Glengary</em> into the West with 500 resolute men of fortune to raise the people ingeneral.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched to <em>Tain</em>, where he saw the enemy, but could not come at them for want of boats, the water being broad and very impetuous, which <reg orig="constrain'd">constrained</reg> him to return back to <em>Dingwel</em>.</p>

<p>From Ireland they write, That the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em>, and his <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of Officers, have ordered that 5000 horse and foot be sent to the North of <em>Scotland</em> and col. <em>Venables</em> is taking care to transport 'em, <i>good shipping attend them</i>. The General <reg orig="councel">council</reg> hath cast Lots for the Provinces, for satisfying the Arrears of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, and the Lot of the General Officers is fallen in <em>Munster</em>. The standing Army from <pb n="2" /><em>June</em> 1649 are content to take two Thirds at present. The Officers of the Army have <reg orig="joyntly">jointly</reg> subscribed a Letter to his Highness, owning the Government which is invested in Him.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the King of <em>Denmark</em> has been to visit the new Church of Altenaw, &amp; the next day went back to <em>Gluckstadt</em>; upon whose arrival came intelligence of Gen. <em><reg orig="Koningsmarks">Koningsmark's</reg></em> <reg orig="surprizing">surprising</reg> of the Town of <em>Bremerburgh</em>. Upon the Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> Demands to the Emperor of <em>Germany</em> for 13500 Rix-dollars, being so much left unpaid by the upper Rhine, it was granted.</p>

<p>Gen. <em>Pen</em> is going from <em>London</em> to the Fleet; the design <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, but the Instructions private. Of which, more in our next.</p>

<p>In the interim, some of the English <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> have <reg orig="allarm'd">alarmed</reg> the French, and rides <reg orig="tryumphantly">triumphantly</reg> upon that coast; but two Reg. are sent to Rochel to <reg orig="re inforce">reinforce</reg> that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: from whence they write, <i>That the English have taken 42 of their ships laden with Wines, which doth very much trouble the King and Council; unto whom, a <em>Message</em> is come from his holiness, for celebrating a <em>Marriage</em> between his <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, and K. Lewis: If you will have any more news at present, you must go to Pope <em>Innocent</em> the Tenth, who is now going to his grave; his death will make the <em>Janseninas</em> high in France, and will occasion some Tumults, it may be.</i></p>

<p>The K. of <em>France</em> is preparing large Offers to the <em>English</em> for peace; and among other things, <i>that the Protestants in that Kingdom shall enjoy their Liberties and freedom in <em>Religion</em>.</i></p>

<p><em>Dover</em> the 24 of April, 1654. This evening came into this Road a private man of War being a <em>Marget</em> Hoy of 6 guns, and about 50 men, who having found in the channel a Dutch ship coming from the West-Indies that have been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent by the tediousness of the Voyage, did of a sudden clap Them aboard, and after a short (but sharp) dispute, became Masters of her, and brought her along with them: the ship is said to be of great value, for besides plate, whereof several Letters say there is a good quantity, the ship will be found full of other rich commodities, which will prove very beneficial to the Takers, when it comes to be judged prize.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has spent much time with his Council, about regulating the Law, the easing of the people, the redressing of Grievances, and the abating of Taxes, and it is hoped, we shall now have the enjoyment of our long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for Liberties.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>The Lord Protector and his council have set forth an additional Ordinance for the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>; a copy whereof take as followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance of the 17 of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for continuing the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg></i>, it is next after the Rates therein specified, generally declared and provided, <i>That all other goods and merchandizes (except Bolloin, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron; imported, or to be imported) not specified, or therein rated, should pay after the rate of <em>5 l. per centum</em>, according as the same are charged by the book of Rates, for the custom to be paid by the first buyer one shilling.</i></p>

<p>Be it ordained, and it is hereby ordained and declared by his Highness, with the advice and consent of his Council, That the said clause be null and void; and instead thereof, Be it hereby ordained and declared, That all other goods and merchandizes, mentioned in the said book of Rates for the Customs, (except Bulloin, Corn, Victual, arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of <em>Brass</em> or Iron, and Wools of sheep) imported, or to be imported, which are not in the said Rates of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> before or otherwise charged, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hereafter pay <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, after the rate of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant or Importer, and the same is to be collected accordingly. And to the end, the whole Receipts of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> may be the better reduced into one Cash, and the charge and number of Officers thereby retrenched, It is hereby ordained by Authority aforesaid, That from and after the 25 day of <em>March</em> last, the Revenue of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> shall be <!-- repetition over a line break --><reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> shall be but one Receipt, and so accounted for; and that all Receipts and <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> heretofore taken or kept of any payment of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> or new Import, be <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any additional Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, and designed to separate use or uses whatsoever, shall from thenceforth cease and be void, and be brought and reduced to one general Cash and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Revenue. Provided nevertheless, that the <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg> of all fines and forfeitures, imposed and received since the 25 of <em>March</em> last, or that hereafter shall be imposed and received, shall be still kept in an <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg> apart, and be paid out towards the maintenance of widows and maimed <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, according to the Ordinance of Parliament of the 13 of <em>July</em>, 1647.</p>

<p>And it is hereby for the further Relief of the said <reg orig="Widowes">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, ordained, That from and after the said 25 day of <pb n="4" /><em>March</em> last, there shall be, out of the general Cash and Revenue of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, allowed the certain yearly sum of 26260 pounds, to be paid weekly by equal portions out of the said <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Receipt, unto such person or persons as is, are, or shall be appointed thereunto by his Highness and his Council, and be <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for <reg orig="imploying">employing</reg> and disposing thereof to the use aforesaid. Which said yearly <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of 26260 pounds is to be in lieu of all and every sum and sums of money assigned by any Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, out of any the Receipts of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, for the relief of the said <reg orig="Widowes">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="souidiers">soldiers</reg>, other <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg> of fines and forfeitures before excepted; And the present Commissioners of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, or any three of them, shall have power from time to time to issue out all moneys, either delivered over unto them, by the commissioners preceding them, or which hath, or shall be received by them since the 25 of <em>March</em> last, according as they are, or shall be directed by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, or by Authority thereof. And the said Commissioners for <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, and their Sub commissioners, are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to make repayment of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> to any person whatsoever, for any goods imported upon the Exportation <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, in such sort as the late commissioners might have done before the 25 day of <em>March</em> last, It appearing unto them that the duty of the said Goods have been fully paid; any former Clause, Article, or provision to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p><i>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>The Committee have spent some time in order to the regulating of the Law, and many gallant things are in agitation for the ease of the people, and the due administration of Equity and Justice: in pursuance whereof, these particulars are laid before them, <em>viz.</em></p>

<p>1 <i>That Justice is the mother of <reg orig="Vertues">Virtues</reg>, the right Spouse of Fortitude, for which Governors are created; and by whose <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> they rule.</i></p>

<p>2 <i>Justice allots not pardon to the Wicked, which might bring the hazard of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</i></p>

<p>3 <i>Justice requireth Equity, Equity judgeth with Lenity, Lenity produceth Laws, which sometimes must extend to extremity.</i></p>

<p>There is great hopes of a universal Redemption from slavery, and the enjoyment of true Liberty and Freedom is now arriving at the Haven of <em>England</em>, where 'tis hoped, the free born people in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>, will now suddenly anchor: <i>The Lord grant it; 'tis high time.</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The next Term is like to be kept without any interruption, and a new Oath was lately <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> to the Judges whereby impartial Justice may be equally executed.</p>

<p>From <em>Southampton</em> thus: Sir, <i>Mr, John Lilburn (we hear) is committed to the old Castle in Jersey, where he deports himself with abundance of patience and humility, and has also declared, That he <reg orig="aymes">aims</reg> at nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the glory of God, the advancement of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the restoring of every free-born man of England, to its ancient Rights and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, and the perfect purging of the Law from all abuses and corruptions</i></p>

<p>He sent a Letter to his very much afflicted wife; but it was intercepted, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to his Highness.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A <em>Letter</em> from <em>Sweden</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>I sent unto you about a fortnight since; but having very little news in that letter I was <reg orig="resolv'd">resolved</reg> to make you amends in this, (though in a few words) by acquainting you that our Treaty with the queen is concluded, and the Articles of Agreement are signed, which are, 1 That from henceforward there shall be a firm and perpetual peace. 2 That they shall assist each other against any enemy whatsoever. 3 That there shall be free Trade and Commerce. The rest are very honourable on both sides. And my Lord intends for England suddenly.</i></p>

<p>Upsal, April 8. 1654.</p>

<p><i>The last letters from Holland say, That the Royal party give out, that there hath been a great fight in Scotland, and that Gen. Middleton hath obtained a great Victory, and killed col. Morgan; yes, <em>in skits</em>: but I conceive this to be <reg orig="coyn'd">coined</reg> with a false stamp; so that probably we may chance them in time for their fictitious and <reg orig="vain-glorious">vainglorious</reg> Reports.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, That Gen. Middleton having drawn most of his forces Northwards, some engagement <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg>, and a part of 40 horse commanded by an English Captain, advanced as far as Provost <em><reg orig="Marburnies">Marburnie's</reg></em> house near <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, which they <reg orig="fir'd">fired</reg>; but the Provost and his party maintained the Tower against them, and after a desperate storm, and sharp dispute, two of the English were slain, divers wounded, and the castle being not feasible, the enemy made good their retreat, with little loss. col. <em>Morgan</em> <reg orig="remaines">remains</reg> still about <em>Dingwal</em>, unto whose assistance col. <em>Pride</em>, col. <unclear><em>Allared</em></unclear>, and divers other Regiments are designed from <em>England</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. Upon <pb n="6" />Gen. <em>Monk's</em> arrival, he sent for all his Officers at <em>London</em> to make all possible speed to their Charge, being resolved to proceed with all expedition, and to engage suddenly. And the enemy are preparing to receive him, who have determinated in Council, to dispute the field either to Death or Victory. In the late Engagement capt. <em>Rogers</em> (Agent for the K. of <em>Scots</em>) was taken, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to <em>Dalkieth</em>, where he was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, condemned, and executed, and received his Sentence of Death with great humility and meekness of Spirit, making a copious Speech upon the Ladder, interwoven with sundry <reg orig="methodicall">methodical</reg> expressions, touching his life and conversation, and his integrity to the Trust reposed in him, saying, <i>That he deemed it a singular mercy from the great Tribunal of <reg orig="Haven">Heaven</reg>, that Providence had decreed him worthy of laying down his life</i>.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> it is certified, That there has been a great dispute between the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and P. <em>Rupert</em>, about the <em>Swallow</em> guns; but <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> over-swaying passion, Amity at last <reg orig="interveen'ed">intervened</reg>, and the Gentlemen were both reconciled. It is said that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath resigned her Crown, and is expected this Summer at the <em>Spaw</em>, where young <em>Charles</em>, and his brother <em>James</em>, do intend to meet her Majesty, and divert themselves at the season.</p>

<p>His Majesty has sent two <reg orig="Councellors">Councillors</reg> of the <em>Parliament</em> to <em>Chantilli</em> and <em>Montmorencie</em>, to take possession of the Prince of <em>Conde's Revenues</em> and <em>Castles</em>, and to <reg orig="re-unite">reunite</reg> them to the <em>Crown of France</em>, which accordingly they did, and there proclaimed him <reg orig="Traytor">Traitor</reg> by <em>Act of Parliament</em>; <i>that's no <reg orig="newes">news</reg>.</i></p>

<p>but his Highness is resolved to prosecute the Cause notwithstanding, and since the denouncing of that <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Sentence against Him, he has made a vigorous progress in the same Colours, and hung up some of the Effigies of the Nobility at his <reg orig="head-quarters">headquarters</reg>.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Scots</em> is upon his removal; but the Duke of York is very much solicited to continue his command in the Army, being in high esteem with the King and Court, and <em>Achilles</em> like striketh Terror where He comes.</p>

<p>There has been seen over the city of <em>Paris</em> a blazing <em>Comet</em>, which shot her <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Train towards the North: some interpret, that it pretends great miseries; and, to speak the truth, 400 of the <reg orig="malecontents">malcontents</reg> murmuring themselves into a conspiracy, and crying out in the streets, No <em>Mazarin</em>, no <em>Tillier</em>, no <em>Servient</em>, the Provost with a <pb n="7" />strong guard came to suppress them, and falling immediately to blows, divers were killed and wounded on both sides.</p>

<p>by the last Express from <em>Scotland</em>, thus: We conceive the Enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagues with their inroads upon the Lowlands, where they burnt and destroyed all that stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reasons of their mischiefs and our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is want of intelligence from amongst them; for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce <reg orig="squeez">squeeze</reg> ten true words out of them. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> we hear hath made his way out of <em>Southerland</em>, where col. <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> his horse, but it proved not feasible; for indeed we have an enemy as subtle as resolute, and they play fast and loose with us in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming to them, and their thoughts extend so far, that there will then be a general Rising of the people: <i>But alas (poor Gentlemen) 'tis dubious whether he will <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> in the Holy War, as the Scots calls it; or draw his Sword against those which are sanctified, as the Saints term it</i>.</p>

<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That the States are sending out a considerable number of men of War to <em>Brazil</em>: <i>'tis time, for true it is, that they have almost lost all which they formerly got: <em>Ha, ha, </em>mark this Gentlemen, that ill-gotten Goods will waste and dissolve as a Snow-ball in the radiant Sun.</i></p>

<p>Strange and various are the Reports from the Isle of <em>Jersey</em>, touching Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em>; so that I shall <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to reduce my <em>Pen</em> from inserting any Thing that may prove obnoxious, or disconsonant from the Rules of Verity; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, that by Tradition of Circumstances, 'tis made out, that he is <em>mortus est</em>; but whether it be under the notion of feeling the pulses of the people, or alienating the minds of their affections form the present Government, I cannot administer any <em>Antidote</em>; thought preventing <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg> be ever held more safe <reg orig="then">than</reg> removing. &mdash; But from all sudden and untimely Deaths,</p>

<head level="2">Good Lord deliver Us.</head>

<p>Gen. <em>Monk</em> is upon his march from <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> towards <em>Aberdeen</em>, and most of the Additional forces are drawing up to the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg>.</p>


<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>