<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell169">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 169</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate <reg orig="Inteligencer">Intelligencer</reg> ,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> concerning the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> of Beer, Ale, Wine, Strong-water, Salt, <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg>, Hops, Iron, Tin, Gold and silver, and divers other Commodities. With the the several Rates and Impost, to be observed and kept throughout all Cities, Towns and Corporations within the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England the Dominion of Wales, and the town of Berwick. Likewise the further Transactions of the Treaty between the English and the Dutch, the reading of the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> Letter, signed <em>C. R.</em> and the several Results and Proceedings thereupon.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday March 15. to Wednesday March 22. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>Since our last, the Lord Protector has received an account of nine millions of money which is due upon the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> faith, the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers'</reg> Arrears, and Debentors, and care is taken to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> them all ingeneral. His Highness 'tis said, hath demanded restitution of the crown of France for the injuries sustained by the English. Since the landing of Gen. <em>Middleton</em> in Scotland, divers are come in to him, and he has already secured the castle of Skeibo, wherein he hath put 300 barrels of powder, and hath likewise brought over with him 1000 Snaphance fire locks, and as many Pikes, Muskets, &amp; Pistols, as made in all 5000 Arms, besides some pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>.</p>

<p>The Lord Seafort hath gotten six hundred men together, and Gen: Glencarn, the Earl of Athol, and col. Forbs intends a general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Aberdeen.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> the 14 of <em>March</em>.</head>

<p>This day Major <em>Bourn</em> and others were robbed at Shooters Hill, <em>an injury not to be <reg orig="born">borne</reg> with:</em> many that had been before robbed were bound, and laid by in a Wood <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="adjoyning">adjoining</reg>: the same Thieves assaulted a Coach coming from <em>Canterbury</em>, wherein was one Gentleman, and two Ladies, with a Gentleman on horseback appertaining to the Coach, who with <reg orig="undanted">undaunted</reg> valour charging them, which were 5 in number, was in the Conflict slain, thought assisted by him in the Coach, who received a shot, and fought with such gallantry, that he wounded one of the Thieves: Notwithstanding whose valour, the Coach at last was robbed of 30 <em>l.</em> but the Thieves, through haste and fear, did <reg orig="over-see">oversee</reg> 50 <em>l.</em> which was in <reg orig="Portmantle">Portmanteau</reg>. The <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> was raised, and Col. <em>Blount</em> made <reg orig="Hu-and">Hue and</reg> Cry after them, but to no effect. The Gentleman slain in the Combat was buried at <em>Greenwich</em>, and, as it is credibly reported, the Thief that was wounded coming to Mr. <em>Moloines</em>, a <reg orig="Chyrurgeon">Chirurgeon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe lane</reg>, to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>; and having laid down his Cloak, being desired to stay till a Gentleman wounded at Shooters hill was <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to tempt his Destiny, made use of his heels, but not his Cloak; and being pursued with full cry, was (as 'tis <reg orig="rumour'd">rumoured</reg> ) taken in Cheapside, and is like to make his Will at Tyburn.</p>

<p>The treaty between the Dutch Ambassadors, and our Commissioners, had some furtherance this day.</p>

<p>From on board the <em>Taunton</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> the 17 of <em>March</em> then at <em>Portsmouth</em>; and by a Letter of a later date, thus: This day we came from Sea; but know not how soon we shall out again to meet with the Armado of <em>Holland</em>: their number, as we have received intelligence, consists of one hundred and forty men of War.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Upsal">Upsala</reg> in Sweden Jan. 20. thus: The treaty goes on between the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, and her Majesty, by her grand Chancellor, who treats <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in the <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg> Tongue. <i>Then who but blind men would put out <em>England's</em> Eyes, the <em>Universities</em>? Like the Fox in the Fable, <reg orig="contemning">condemning</reg> the Grapes they cannot reach.</i></p>

<p>It was a saying of <em>Scipio</em>, that excellent Commanders, Statesmen, and Philosophers, that he loved not a City, <em><unclear>frantibus m&aelig;nibus</unclear>, ruentibus moribus</em>. Let those Sons of Ignorance interpret the former by this saying of <em>Senecus</em>. <i>O! <!-- next sentence in Latin is badly printed --><unclear>Vuinam vertutis adversarij, nota alia 
<!-- next four words are just a guess, very hard to read -->ratsone puneruntur, qui ut ipsam virtutem videanteademq; relicti, intoteicant.</unclear></i> The two Ordinances touching Ministers and touching the law is before a Committee, whereof Justice Hales in the Chair.</p>

<p>This day the Commissioners from the Lord Protector went from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in two Coaches with the Secretary of State and the Clerk of the Council, and their attendants to the Dutch Ambassadors, at Sir Abraham Williams; from whence they are not yet removed to Sir John Trevers: they were met at the gate by the Lords Ambassadors, where the Lord Beverling made a speech to them, and they received them with great respect and love on both sides. Being come into the house and into a chamber appointed for their Conference; they spent much time in order to the finishing of the peace. The business this day, was, to confer their Papers of the agreement, for though they have agreed, yet it is <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> by each side, and on Wednesday last they compared their papers; which when both compared together, do in all particulars agree; then they are to sign on both sides. And what they sign, the Dutch Ambassadors do in the name of the States General. But to confirm it the more, it is to be sent to the States, who are also to give their assent after the Ratification, and then they deliver the Articles on both sides, which <reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived will be done within the space of three weeks.</p>

<p>This Certificate I have here inserted at the desire of Mr. <em>Edmund Felton</em>, an ancient, experienced, and approved Engineer.</p>

<p>Whereas <em>Edmund Felton</em> Gent. hath of late discovered unto the Committee of Fortification of the City of <em>London</em>, how an Engine of his Invention will secure the foot from the horse, and the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> from musket shot; one Engine to supply the room of 24 Pike-men, or more, which said Engine two men may manage at pleasure: for the seeing of which, we appointed some of the said <reg orig="Comittee">Committee</reg> to see and try the said Engine, which hath hanging <reg orig="Brest-works">Breastworks</reg>, and was shot at about 40 paces distant, the <reg orig="musquetiers">musketeers</reg> <reg orig="raming">ramming</reg> in powder and bullet, yet could not the shot piece <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the said <reg orig="Breast-work">Breastwork</reg>, which we who were appointed did see, and so reported to the rest of the Committee; And being requested by the said <em>Ed. Felton</em> so to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> under our hands of the truth of what we saw and reported of, we have done accordingly. Witness our Hands the 14 of March, 1653.</p>

<p><i>Rich. Bateman, Tho. Nowel, Christopher Pack, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Story, P. Miles.</i></p>

<p><i>Vera Copia Ex.</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>Vanity at this day opens all her <reg orig="doores">doors</reg> to manifest divers persons to the World, who would otherwise have been <reg orig="buryed">buried</reg> in obscurity: such a person some judged one <em>I</em> met with at Court this week, who has long waited to obtain and Order, that there may be a Hearing of each <reg orig="mans">mans</reg> Cause within 40 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Petition is exhibited: for, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, <i>where there is no Law, there is no transgression</i>; And this would mind Committees and persons <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with the business of this Nature to be very <reg orig="cautelous">cautious</reg> how they eat up the Poor by tedious <reg orig="delayes">delays</reg>, when a Petitioner many times dines <reg orig="onely">only</reg> upon <em>Air</em>, though perhaps an <em>Heir</em> to a considerable estate. I demanded what benefit this Gentleman would have by obtaining this, he said it would be a general good, and that was sufficient <reg orig="recompence">recompense</reg>. I <reg orig="ask'd">asked</reg> him what he was? He <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, <i>A Master of Arts</i>. I retorted, that if he could effect this, he would be Master of his Art indeed: His name is Mr. <em>Thomas Philpot</em>, but his countenance promises him to be not such Patriot, nor Politician: but if there be such a man living, that <reg orig="layes">lays</reg> himself out <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> good, I think it is rare <reg orig="newes">news</reg> indeed. Honest <em>Tom</em>! thy Design, if it arrives to perfection, (for we use to judge by events) will render thee as famous, as was <em>Drake, Forbisher, Raleigh</em>, or any, whose nobler Spirits <reg orig="pusht">pushed</reg> them forward to brave <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>.</p>

<p>By a Letter from <em>Lyn</em> in <em>Norfolk</em>, that came this day it was thus certified, That Mr. <em>Robert Autforth</em> of the same town has lost his ship being taken by a man of War upon the Coast of <em>Scotland</em>. Twelve more were forced ashore by the <em><reg orig="Belgick">Belgic</reg> <unclear>Bores</unclear></em>.</p>

<p>Every <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day there preacheth two Orthodox Divines before his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Lady Protectoress in <em>Whitehall</em>: the privy Rooms are terminated, and the several Tables of Diet appointed.</p>

<p>The next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view, is, the King of <em><reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg></em> Letter to the Lord Gen. <em>Glencarn</em>; a Transcript whereof take as <unclear>followeth</unclear>:</p>

<p>After Our hearty commendations, <em>&amp;c</em> We cannot but give you thanks for your activeness, in doing of Us and Our <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdome</reg> service; And we do hereby give you further to understand, that We do highly value and approve of your <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> in a service that doth so much import Us; and to the end you may receive some <pb n="4" />other encouragement from <reg orig="Our Self">Ourself</reg>, We have given special Order to <em>Middleton</em> to hasten unto you: He hath provided in <em>Holland</em> a considerable number of able Commanders, every way fit for Our Service. The <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> which we sent from <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em> may happily be with you before this Letter. We wish that the late differences between <em>Seafort</em> and you, may not be prejudicial to our Affairs, we bid you right heartily <reg orig="farewel">farewell</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Signed <em>C. Rex.</em></i></p>

<p>We received further Advertisement, that the great ship called formerly the <em>Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em>, now the <em><reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg></em>, is put forth to Sea.</p>

<p>The council at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> have taken into consideration the abuse of farthings, and have debated the allowance of tokens to be made by one that will make them of intrinsical value. The Queen of Sweden is sending a message to the Lord Protector <reg orig="Gromwel">Cromwell</reg>, by way of congratulation; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> has set down her Resolution for War against the Emperor, having in readiness 39000 horse and foot.</p>

<p>By letters this day received from <em>Ireland</em> it is certified that the Lord <em>Hen. <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> (by the permission of the Almighty) will return hither in a fortnight, nothing of disturbance being there: Adjutant Gen. <em>Allen</em>, and one <em>Standich</em> come over with him.</p>

<p><i>To his most excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> by the Divine Providence, <em>Lord Protector</em> of the three Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></p>

<p>The Cordial Declaration and humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of the ancient and renowned City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, by the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg> and COMMON <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> thereof, Signed and signified under the Common Seal of the said City, at a Common <reg orig="Councie">Council</reg> there holden.</p>

<p>Desert and Praise should <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> go together as Twins, where the one precedes it is an injury to <reg orig="with-hold">withhold</reg> the sequence of the other; So great hath been the desert of your most Excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> (through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God in the eyes of all these Nations for divers years past, that we humbly conceive we should make <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> a scorn in the <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> of Foreigners for our ingratitude, if we should not make our Praises in some measure commensurable to Your <reg orig="vaste">vast</reg> Achievements.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> sincerely in what we Declare, <unclear>and do</unclear> hope that <unclear>Adulation will not by any good men be interpreted t <reg orig="lye">lee</reg> couchant in</unclear> our Expressions, for we shall speak the words of Truth and <reg orig="Sobernesse">Soberness</reg>. &amp;c.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>This day his Highness the Lord Protector took up his Lodgings at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and <unclear>thereby hath made it a Court; for <reg orig="Princes">Princes'</reg> presences make Courts</unclear>, and not the Princes. See! What a <reg orig="Prophetick">Prophetic</reg> Spirit <em>Aulicus</em> had, that he began to write on this very week, wherein his Highness vouchsafed to honour <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>As welcome as is the green-mantled Spring</line>
<line><reg orig="Vnto">Unto</reg> the plumed Quire, who joyfully sing</line>
<line>And Carol welcomes, as the Plants we see</line>
<line>Now revelling in Summer <reg orig="Liverie">Livery</reg>:</line>
<line>Indeed, my Lord, <reg orig="you'r">you're</reg> mightier <reg orig="then">than</reg> a King,</line>
<line>He brings in glittering <unclear>rains</unclear>, but you the Spring.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> March 17.</head>

<p>The Highlanders increase in Scotland, and Gen. Middleton begins to play <em>Rex</em> again: they had a <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the 11 instant, and are now marching towards the Lord <reg orig="Reaffs">Reaff's</reg> Bounds. There hath lately happened a great disaster between Cap. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> troop and Cap. <reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg>, the manner thus: Cap. Palmer having pursued the enemy, at last met with a party of horse, which he took to be the enemy, whereupon he charged them desperately, but were as gallantly repulsed by Cap. Mason, who charged them though and through, and for the space of half an hour the business was very disputable, in which unhappy engagement 6 were slain on both sides and 8 wounded, whereof Cap. Palmer is one.</p>

<p>From Plymouth <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have certain intelligence, that the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath sent in 9 ships, which was taken upon the French Coast, and the <reg orig="Non-such">Nonesuch</reg> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath taken three delicate Vessels laden with Wine, Beans, and Salt. Nine more taken on the Coast of Scotland, and Cap. Wilkins hath taken another, bravely fraught with rich Merchandizes. The Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> is now put forth to sea, and rides in Stoke bay. Two <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships that were coming from Ipswich toward London, were taken by a Dutch man of war, they <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the English of both under the Decks of one of them, on the 4 of March, and then left them, sending them homeward; but the next day the English at a seasonable time lifted up the decks, relieved themselves, took the Dutch, and <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> them under the deck where they were, and brought away both their ships to the Downs, which are now <unclear>safe in the River</unclear>, with the prisoners.</p>

<p>The Queen of <em>Bohemia</em> (sister to the late King of Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>) is going to <em>Frankendale</em>, which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place, and of great frequentation, it being the mid-way betwixt <em>Wormes</em> and <em>Spiers</em>, where she will do the best she can to entertain young <em>Charles</em>, and to accommodate him in the present juncture of <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg>. His brother JAMES (second Son to his late Majesty) is as valiant as Hector <pb n="6" />in the King of France's Army; but the little Queen (his Mother) is of a sudden struck very solentary. The Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> do with much importunity press upon the loyal breasts of the English in several places to support the weak distressed Estate of their Prince; especially at the city of Hamborough, where the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> did <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="solicite">solicit</reg> and importune the Treasurer of the English company, who fearing his power, and loath to part with those monies which belonged to all the English Merchants who <reg orig="traffick">traffic</reg> in those parts, acquainted the President of the English Companies with it, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> the inconveniences that would arise, if he <reg orig="shold">should</reg> deliver such <reg orig="moneyes">monies</reg> to him. Whereupon the President weighing the truth of the Reasons, made his complaint to the Senate, who <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> the Lord Wentworth not to exact any sums of money of the Treasurer, unless he was able to put in good security for the re-disbursing of them.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> we have received intelligence, that the Constant Warwick, and the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> being together, met with the great <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> Cap. <em>Beach</em>, who had newly taken two prizes; but perceiving that our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the Prizes, and was afterward secured by the night coming on. The same night the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> and the constant Warwick chanced to part company, and it so fell out about midnight that <em>Beach</em> roving about, lighted on the <em>Constant Warwick</em> all alone, which before he came near, he took to be a Merchant man, and went on with an intent to board him; but the <em>Warwick</em> demanding who he was, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> he was the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and for <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>. But the <em>Warwick</em> suspecting him, bade him round off. Then <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake, and seeing the <em>Warwick</em> to be a man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, he presently made away; but the <em>Warwick</em> being a good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg>, made after him, and kept company with him all night. About 6 in the morning, <em>Beach</em> began the fight, firing 3. Guns, which were answered by the <em>Warwick</em>. The encounter lasted till two in the afternoon, at which time <em>Beach</em> and his men called for Quarter, and had it. He had five foot water in the hold when he yielded; he had 200 men, 20 whereof were killed; his <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> is a gallant new Vessel, of 42 guns, whereof but thirty eight were mounted. There are taken aboard with him <pb n="7" />nine Captains besides himself, and divers Gentlemen, who are all prisoners. This is that <em>Beach</em>, the <reg orig="Ring-leader">Ringleader</reg> Pirate, who hath done our merchants so much mischief this winter, that he lived like a Prince at <em>Brest</em>; for which 'tis like he will receive his reward, being brought in hither, with the rest of his companions.</p>

<p>The Lord Protector and his Council have set forth an Ordinance for the continuing of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>; and the Rates for every Barrel of Beer or Ale above 6s. the barrel brewed by the common Brewer, or by any other person or persons who shall sell or tap out Beer or Ale <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> or privately, to be paid by the said Brewer or such other person or persons respectively is 2 s. For every Barrel of six shilling Beer or Ale, or above 4 shilling the Barrel 6d. And so proportionably for a greater or lesser quantity of Beer or Ale above 4 s. the Barrel. And no allowance to be made from henceforth for any Beer or Ale to be used in Fishing Vessels at sea, which is bought of the <reg orig="comon">common</reg> Brewer or <reg orig="Retaler">Retailer</reg> of Beer or Ale. A <unclear>Run</unclear> English the <reg orig="hundred weight">hundredweight</reg>, containing <unclear>112</unclear> pounds, to be paid by the maker 6 d. Coperas English, the <reg orig="hundred weight">hundredweight</reg> 6 d. English Hops, the <reg orig="hundred weight">hundredweight</reg>, to be paid by the Planter 2 s. English Saffron, for every 20 s value, to be paid by the Planter 1 s. Tim, for every 20s. value, to be paid by the buyer 1 s. Iron English, for every <reg orig="hundred weight">hundredweight</reg>, to be paid by the maker <unclear>2 sh.</unclear> 6d. For all Aquavit&aelig; or strong water made or distilled within this Commonwealth whether of <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> or <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Spirits or materials to be sold upon every gallon, to be paid by he first maker or Seller thereof respectively two pence. For every barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within this Commonwealth of what sort soever to be paid by the maker, and so proportionably for hard <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within the Land 4 s. For every Ounce <unclear>Troy</unclear> of silver or gold <unclear>prepared</unclear> melted down, or disgrossed for <reg orig="Wyer">Wire</reg>, to be paid at the bar where the same shall be disgrossed 2 d. For every pound weight <reg orig="conteining">containing</reg> sixteen Ounces Averdupois, of any copper or other metal, that <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> prepared, and made fit or disgrossed, to be paid at the bar where the same <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> <reg orig="disgros'd">disgrossed</reg> one shilling. For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Whale <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Blubber <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, <unclear>Rape</unclear> <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, Pilchard <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, and all other <reg orig="oyls">oils</reg> made within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, upon every Tun to be paid by the maker six s. per Tun, &amp;c.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>