<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell167">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 167</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Demands of his Highness the Lord Protector, to their Excellencies the Lord Ambassadors from the States of Holland; the number of Town required to be delivered up to the English, and the further proceedings of the Treaty at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, in order to the signing, sealing and confirming of the Articles for Pease: With a List of those Princes, Dukes, <reg orig="Earles">Earls</reg>, Lords and Gentlemen, that are to be excluded from the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of England and Holland. Together with strange and wonderful Visions from <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, presented to Col. Bingham, Col. West, Col. Bennet, the <unclear>Lady Dercy</unclear>, the Lady Vermuden, and divers other honourable persons, touching the strange Revolutions, and various Contingencies of these times.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday Feb. 28. to Wednesday March 8. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>The English Fleet rideth not far from the Isle of Wight: some Squadrons are at the Spits-head, and others at Saint <reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg> point: they are ready to put forth to Sea in the most gallant equipage that may be. For we have now in one body the bravest Fleet that ever was put forth since the Wars began, and the <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> are very unanimous, Divers foot <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> are gone down to their assistance, no less <reg orig="then">then</reg> 30 out of a company were drawn forth on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last, and divers others are to follow: <i>a prosperous Gale attend them.</i></p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The Ambassadors landed with their Attendants at Tower Wharf, where were <unclear>Coaches</unclear> provided for them, their Lordships were in one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coaches, and the Master of the Ceremonies with them, drawn by <reg orig="sixe">six</reg> horses: Next followed the French and the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassadors'</reg> Coaches, with above 20 more all with 6 horses, besides above 40 Coaches most with 4 horses <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>; they rode in a stately equipage through the City from Aldgate by the Royal Exchange, and so to the Palace yard Westminster to Sir Abraham Williams's, where they are to be entertained, with their Retinue, at the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> charge for some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. And on Saturday in the afternoon they had audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector in the Banqueting house at <reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg>, the room was richly hung with hangings, and a rich chair of State set for the Lord Protector, and Chairs on the one side for the Ambassadors, the entertainment was stately, and gallant, and the subject of this Audience was partly congratulatory to his Highness, and to declare the business of their coming to make and settle a firm peace, and to renew their old friendship which hath been for many years between the two Nations.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Advertisements.</i></head>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> from Scotland advertiseth, that the English forces have fallen upon the Highlande4rs, and after an irresistible and furious Onset, took above 120 Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, great store of Arms, Ammunition, Horses with plenty of provision, and afterwards blew up the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Dunkel. Col. Morgan hath also removed the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemies</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Kildrumay, and at Cromar put 120 to the sword, took 27 prisoners, 80 horse, &amp; all their Bag and Baggage.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>The English Fleet remains still about St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em> point by the Isle of Wight, and the Merchant men are all gone from <em>Dover</em> road toward <em>France</em>, and other parts. Our men of War <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> the Rex upon the Narrow seas; but the Hectors in <em>Kent</em> proceed on most inhumanely killing, robbing, and destroying all that comes <reg orig="neer">near</reg> them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Further Advertisements from the North.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, that the enemy are divided into divers parties to raise their assigned Levies, and the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, having a considerable party of horse and Foot, hath sent forth the fiery Cresses, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> fire and sword to all that <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> comply with the English. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> is marched toward <em><reg orig="Lenox">Lennox</reg></em> with several Troops, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived in design for the South. Divers of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em> Regiment are revolted to the enemy, but some of them were taken, and rewarded with a Rope. Others were <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> up to the Gallows at <em>Dunkel</em>, and <reg orig="Marshal">Martial</reg> Law is <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> executed upon all those who incur the penalty thereof. The Tories are somewhat high in <em>Ireland</em>, and some distempers are brake forth; but the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is safely arrived to put a period to those Distractions.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Advertisements from Sea.</i></head>

<p>From Yarmouth our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, that the Lord <em>Williamson</em> is landed, as Ambassador Extraordinary from the King of <em>Denmark</em>, whose Majesty hath sent a Message to his Highness, making application upon the success of the Dutch Treaty. And the Lord Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> have presented their Credenti8akls, wherein they desire to include his Majesty. In order whereunto, the States of the 7 United Provinces do all of them agree and consent to the Agreement of Peace, and the said Ambassadors are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same, desiring a speedy cessation of Arms, and that all Acts of Hostility may cease on both sides. Their Lordships are to have Audience again on Tuesday, being the 7 of this instant <pb n="3" />March, so that undoubtedly some few circumstances being considered on, all will be concluded, and a Peace fully <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>.</p>

<p>The King of Scots (we hear) is going for <em>Germany</em>, being invited by the Princes, and his brother <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em> is designed for <em>Flanders</em> where the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold William</em> (General for the King of <em>Spain</em>) is very potent. The Lord <em>Digby</em> is said to go along with him as Lieut. Gen. and Sir Lewis Dives as Maj. Gen. Marshal Thurene is preparing likewise to take the field. The Lord Inchiquin has received great command from the King, and divers Irish Gentlemen are to command under Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>. The Lord Jermin is excluded from the Count, but the Lord <unclear><em>Traff</em></unclear> is taken in.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Strange and wonderful Visions from <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>.</em></i></head>

<p>Upon the 7 day of the 11 month called <em><reg orig="Ianu.">Janu.</reg></em>, being the 6 day of the week, or <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Mr. <em>Powel</em> Minister of the Gospel in <em>Wales</em>, being brought before the Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, to give an account of some things by him delivered in his <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Exercises: Among many other friend who came to see what would be done with him, there came a maid, Mrs. <em>Anna Trapnel</em> by name, who waiting in a little room <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Council door, where there was a fire; amongst many others she <reg orig="staid">staid</reg> for Mr. <em><reg orig="Powels">Powel's</reg></em> coming forth, and then intending to return home, she was beyond <reg orig="yer">her</reg> own thoughts or intentions, having much trouble in her thoughts; and being as it were seized by the Lord, she was <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> forth in a Spirit of prayer and singing from noon till night, and went down into Mr. <em><reg orig="Roberts">Robert's</reg></em> Lodging, who kept the Ordinary in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and finding her natural strength going from her, she took her bed about eleven of the clock in the night, where she lay from that day being the 7 day of the month, to the 19 day of the same month, in all 12 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> together: the first five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> she neither eat nor drank: and the rest of the time, once in 24 ho: sometimes a very little toast in small beer; sometimes <reg orig="onely">only</reg> chewed it, and took down the <reg orig="moysture">moisture</reg>; sometimes she drank of the small beer, and sometimes <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="washt">washed</reg> her mouth therewith, and then cast it forth, lying in bed with her eyes shut, and her hands seldom seen to move: She delivered in that time many and various things, speaking <pb n="4" />every day 3 or 4 hours, and sometimes praying both night and day and singing spiritual songs; which many eminent persons hearing of, among the rest, came Col. <em>Sydenham</em> (a member of the Council) Col. <em>West</em>, Col. <em>Bennet</em>, with his wide, Col. <em>Bingham</em>, the Lady <em>Dercy</em>, the Lady <em>Vermuden</em>, and divers others; who heard her declare as followeth, to wit, That 7 years since she being sick of a <reg orig="Feaver">Fever</reg>, and given over by all her friends as one not like to live, the Lord then gave her faith to believe from that Scripture, After two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> I will revive thee, and the 30 day I will raise thee up, and thou shalt live in my sight; which two days I understood to be two weeks that I <reg orig="shold">should</reg> <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in that <reg orig="Feaver">Fever</reg>; and at that very time and hour that it took her, that very hour it left her, and accordingly from which time, the Lord made use of her for refreshing of afflicted ones, and such as were under temptation: and when that time was ended, she being in her chamber, desired of the Lord to know whether she had done that which was <!--??--><reg orig="off">of</reg>, and from himself, Reply was made to her, That she should approve her heart to God, and for that she had been faithful in a little, she should be made an instrument of much more; so particular <reg orig="soules">souls</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> have benefit by her, but the Universality of Saints <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have discoveries of God through her: whereupon <reg orig="shee">she</reg> prayed that he might be led by the still waters, and honour God secretly, being conscious to herself of the deceitfulness of her own heart, looking upon herself as the worst amongst <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> flock: whereupon the Lord told her, that out of the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of babes and sucklings he would perfect his praise. After which she had many Visions, and Revelations touching the Government of the Nation, the Parl. Army, and Ministry, and having fasted nine days, nothing coming within her lips, she had a most strange Vision of horns; she saw fair Horns which were 4 Powers: the first was that of the Bishops, which first Horn she saw broken in two, and thrown aside: then appeared the second Horn, and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to it an head, and although it seemed to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> more white <reg orig="then">then</reg> the first, yet it endeavouring to get aloft it was suddenly pulled down, and broken to pieces. The third Horn had many splinters <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to it like to the <reg orig="skales">scales</reg> of a fish, and this was <unclear>presented</unclear> to be a Parl. consisting of many men, having very fain and plausible <unclear>pretences</unclear>, but this was also broke. And as for her Vision touching the Lord Protector, we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> refer you to the general Relation itself, extent <reg orig="to-morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The Lord Mayor of the city of <em>London</em>, and the Recorder of the said city, on the party of the city of London; and divers Magistrates of the city of Westminster, according to an Order sent to them came to attend his Highness and the Council, at the Council chamber in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>; and yesterday they were heard touching the business for a Corporation to be granted to the city of Westminster, and something therein, it is probable will shortly be done. Several new Orders are drawing up by sundry eminent persons within the city, for the regulating of abuses in Trades <em>viz.</em> <reg orig="8hoo makers">Shoemakers</reg>, Silk-weavers, Tailors, Butchers, Carpenters, and <reg orig="Joyners">Joiners</reg>, and for the suppressing of <reg orig="foreiners">foreigners</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> we have received advertisements, that Card. <em>Mazarine</em> has reduced both King, Princes, and that Gen. <em>Tureue</em> and the Duke of <em>York</em>, are preparing to take the field against the Spanish forces.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday March 2.</head>

<p>From Windsor we have received intelligence, that there is a notable Plot or Conspiracy discovered, against some that should have betrayed their Trust in the castle; and one of them being taken <reg orig="imbezelling">embezzling</reg> and carrying away the powder, was apprehended and <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> before the Governor, who received sentence to ride upon a Saker <unclear>when it is shot off</unclear> with an half charge. Mr. <em>Feak</em>, and Mr. <em>Simpson</em>, are both there still, and in good health, blessed be God: But poor Judge Jenkins declines exceedingly.</p>

<p>Yesterday an Ambassador Extraordinary from the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> in Flanders, had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, where he did congratulate his highness, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> him his Credentials, and presented him with a message from his master <em>Leopold William</em>, by the grace of God <reg orig="Arch duke">Archduke</reg> of <em>Austria</em>, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em>, and Lieu. Gen. and Cap. Gen. of the Low countries. After which, he was conducted from thence by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, master of the Ceremonies. The said <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> hath sent forth two Declarations against that famous old Thief <em>Charles</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, who hath filled a great part of Christendom with his rapines and cruelties, and now like close prisoner at Antwerp; for the K. of Spain is resolved to set up <em>Francis</em> the younger brother in the elder <reg orig="brothers">brothers</reg> place, and that the said L. Duke <em>Francis</em> shall undertake the sole command of the Army, with all the <reg orig="Ensignes">Ensigns</reg> and Banners thereunto belonging.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Feb. 28.</i></head>

<p>Presents us with an Abstract of Scotland, intimating, That the E. of Athol hath drawn most of his forces together from Weems, and other places, and he with the L. Bruce were the 14 at Glenshier, marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with Glencarn, Glengary, Kenmore, and the rest of the Royal party; upon their conjunction they will be at the least 4000. and then they intend to be revenged upon the English, if they can: but <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> foot are much discontented at the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their horse, and the <reg orig="Rnglish">English</reg> that came with Col. Wogan out of <reg orig="Francs">France</reg>, are much dejected at the death of their valiant Colonel. Col. Lilburn is sending recruits to Col. Morgan, but somewhat inconsiderable, until such time that the new supplies are gone from England. The Scots are very high at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and breath forth Victories instead of Defeats, giving out, that the late blow given by Col;. Morgan was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to some few <reg orig="Countreo men">Countrymen</reg>, when it is evident, that G. Glencarn was there in person, and the valiant young Laird of <reg orig="Loughaber">Lochaber</reg>, who was one of the first that ran out of the field, and left his Commission from their King, signed C. R. behind him, together with the last Instructions of Lieu. Gen. Middleton, 5 Letters from C. the 2. to the Commander in chief of the Highlanders: All which Papers are to be sent up to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>There hath been lately some meetings of godly Ministers about London, to consider of a way of union and reconciliation of the differences that unhappily have crept in among the godly, and other excellent things in order to the progress of the Gospel. And this day Mr. Owen, Mr. Tho. Goodwin, M. Sydrack Simson, Mr. Nie and divers other reverend pious Ministers were with his Highness.</p>

<p>From Ireland our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, that the L. Deputy Fleetwood, and the Officers of the Army, have caused to be printed at Dublin their Declaration, to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with his Highness in the present change of Government: but indeed at first many there were that scrupled it; yet upon consideration they unanimously assented thereunto.</p>

<p>From Newcastle they write, that cap. <em>Wetang</em> hath scoured those coasts of the <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg>, and that he hath sunk and taken some. But alas! this doth not equalize our loss in the West, for true it is that the Brest men of war have taken the George of Bristol, being richly laden with Indigo, Sugar, and Tobacco.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> <!--?--><reg orig="Ian.">Jan.</reg> 7. His highness the Lord Protector was <reg orig="usher'd">ushered</reg> in with a high and magnificent Train; and all things being prepared and in readiness, He is to keep his Court in that stately Palace. As touching the further proceedings of the Treaty, the Opinions of men are various, touching a conclusion; and 'tis said, that four of the chief Towns in Holland are demanded to be delivered up to the English for Security: which if true, then <reg orig="farewel">farewell</reg> </p>

<p>The King of Scots,</p>
<p>The Princess his Sister,</p>
<p>James the second Son,</p>
<p>Henry the third Son,</p>
<p>The Prince of Orange,</p>
<p>The Lord Craven,</p>
<p>The Lord Digby,</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. Massey,</p>
<p>The Lord Wilmot,</p>
<p>The Lord Culpepper,</p>
<p>The Lord Wentworth,</p>

<p>And all other Gentlemen whatsoever, that shall be found enemies against the two States, are to depart and be <reg orig="banisht">banished</reg> after certain <reg orig="days">days'</reg> warning. Well! few words are best at present; but of this more hereafter: in the interim I shall evade some particulars, by reason many things seem dubious, and I have often times been told, that truth must not be spake at all times; which certainly can prove no otherwise <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Paradox: But I must not <reg orig="center">centre</reg> too much upon the present Revolutions, various Contingencies, and wonderful Transmigrations, that have, and may happen in this little corner of the Earth, since that we have beheld the Fall of one of the mightiest monarchs in Europe, and in Him of Monarchy <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, with the several designs and transactions that were set on foot for the instating of his son in the Throne, and the fruitless events thereof. The Dissolution of the (commonly called) everlasting Parl. the calling of another, and the dissolution, the Lord Gen. made Lord Protector, &amp;c. And seeing that I have drawn a conclusion from the end of one Monarchy, to the beginning of another, I desire (if it please the wise Disposer of all things, as well as persons, to grant us peace, both at home and abroad) that we may live to spin out the <reg orig="thred">thread</reg> of our life in a mutual and happy conversation.</p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>