<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell171">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 171</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate <reg orig="Inteligencer">Intelligencer</reg>,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The gracious Resolution of his Highness the Lord Protector, concerning the languishing and deplorable conditions of the poor Prisoners in <em>Ludgate, Newgate, the Fleet, Gate-house, Upper-Bench</em>, and all other Gaols and Prisons whatsoever both in City and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. With the proceedings of his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council thereupon; and a Declaration for the relief of all those that have acted in the service of the Parliament. The taking and disposing of the Broad Seal of England, and the Ordinances to be published throughout England and Wales. The <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> of the Highlanders into one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> Body, and the preparations of both Armies to give <reg orig="battel">battle</reg> unto each other.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday March 29. to Wednesday April 5. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>Since our last, We have received intelligence, that the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> Army are all <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together into one body; but who <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> how soon they may be <reg orig="dispierced">dispersed</reg> again: for the English are preparing to give 'em battle, and desire nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> sudden action. They speak high; but as yet dare not descend low: neither dare they interpose, unless with great advantage. The Broad Seal, we hear, is taken and disposed of, and the Commissioners for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners are not to proceed these 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. Sundry other excellent things are under Debate.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The 27 instant, the French Ambassador had Audience before his highness the Lord Protector, at which time, upon the presenting of his Letters Credential from his Master the King, he made a very learned and excellent Oration, touching his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, and the renewing of a more stricter League and Union between both Nations. Of which, more in our next.</p>

<p>The 29. the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Burdeux">Bordeaux</reg></em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Audience in the Banqueting house in <em>Whitehall</em>, which was richly hung with stately Hangings, and thousands of people present. Being carried in the L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and with him some of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, &amp; Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, attended by divers Noble persons, being in all above forty Coaches, more with six horses <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>. Where he was received by his Highness the Lord Protector, his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> being with his Highness at the upper end of the Banqueting house, where after several Congies each to other, the L. Ambassador made a speech to his Highness, and after his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> answer and salutings, he returned back again. The sum of the L. <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech was to declare that he came from the K. of <em>France</em> his Master to treat in order to a firm peace to be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> with <em>England</em>. Touching which he has a <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> answer.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of 18. Prizes taken by the Ph&oelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance, and <reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a Galliot Hoy, whose Mast being shot by the Board she was burnt. 2. Taken by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the Hope of <reg orig="Hous-down">Housdown</reg>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50. <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 3. Taken by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em>, the Claus of Housdown <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 4. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaids">Mermaid's</reg></em> Boat, the Fortune of Mazeland Sluys, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 32 Tons, wherein were many <unclear>barrels</unclear> of Fish, and 6. of Salt, with about 40 empty Cask. 5. Taken by the same day by the <em><reg orig="Newcastles">Newcastle's</reg></em> Boat, the Skell-fish of Mazeland Sluys, with Fish, Salt, &amp; empty Cask. 6. Taken by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat, the Plumpart of Mazeland Sluys, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 30 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise. 7. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the Providence of Mazeland Sluys, 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading. 8. Taken likewise the Fortune of Delfs-haven, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Brandywine, French wine, Prunes &amp;c. 9. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 10. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, two Scotch vessels, laden with Beef, <reg orig="Flower">Flour</reg>, <reg orig="Train-oyl">Train-oil</reg>, <reg orig="Deer-skins">Deerskins</reg> and Sugars. 11. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the Waking Boy of <unclear>Enchuvsn</unclear> a private man of War, of 8. Guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable. 12 Pikes, 10. Muskets, eight Pistols, and a boat with four Oars. 12. A Merchant ship brought in prize into <em>Rye</em>. 13. A Denmark ship brought into <em>Scarborough</em>. 14. A rich prize, laden with Sugar, and other Merchandizes, taken by a private man of War worth <pb n="2" />150000 l. A private man of War belonging to <em>Zealand</em>, taken by the <em>Paul</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> with 15. piece of Ordnance and 60 men, after six hours dispute, she is brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is returned from <em>Ireland</em>, and is (blessed be God) safely arrived at the Cock-pit. All is quiet and in a good condition in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>From Leghorn our Post hath brought intelligence, that the French <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> have taken two English Merchant ships bound for London, but purchased them with the loss of much blood.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Upsal">Uppsala</reg> in Sweden thus: All the actions of our great Queen are so many wonders, and continual effects of her <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg>, and of the greatness of her incomparable courage; but some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since in special she did give such proof thereof, that the same may be called the Crown of all her other actions, seeing it doth manifest to the World how this admirable Princess hath set <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> above the Crowns, under which man commonly do seek their satisfaction and glory. The 23 of Feb. she having summoned all the Senators of the Land, they all made their appearance except 9 who were out of the Land upon <reg orig="publike">public</reg> employment: her Majesty declared unto them the design she had to leave the charge of the Kingdom, and to that end she was resolved to go to Nicoping to confer with the Prince Palatine of Sweden her Cousin, having sent him Letters to invite him thither, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to accept the charge of the Kingdom, and the managing of the State Affairs: This Prince is the same who was heretofore Generalissimo of the Swedish Armies in Germany, concluded first a peace with the Duke Picolomini and in the year 1650 at the Coronation of the Queen, was then declared apparent Heir to the Crown of Sweden, and by the States and Commonality acknowledged so, having made their Oath of Allegiance to him, as unto their future King, after the <reg orig="Queens">Queens</reg> death; we are expecting with great impatience the event of that generous and unthought of Resolution. The 26 of Feb. her Majesty had a <reg orig="mask">masque</reg> danced in the behalf of the Earl <em>de Montecuculli</em>, Gen. of the horse to the Emperor, where were present the English and Spanish Ambassadors, with many of our Senators: the beginning of this <reg orig="Mask">Masque</reg> was of an exquisite harmony of voices and instruments to sing some <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Poems, composed first by an Italian called <em>Albertus Vemino</em>, in honour of the Emperor: in the midst of it was made a splendid and Royal Collation <pb n="3" />of <reg orig="Sweet-meats">Sweetmeats</reg>, and other Rarities, and at the end of the <reg orig="Mask">Masque</reg> was brought by the Earl of <em>Todta</em> a rich Collar, and being laid <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Queen, there was a Cushion laid at her feet: then having called to her the Earl of <em>Montecuculli</em>, and with her own hands invested him of that new Order of Knighthood called of <em>Amarantha</em>, and first instituted by her Majesty, who holding both his hands, did make him promise that he would truly and faithfully keep and observe all the statutes of that Order: During all this Ceremony the <reg orig="musick">music</reg> both vocal and instrumental, and among other rare pieces then sung, was one made in Italian, whereof all the verses ended thus, <i>Long may live Aramantha</i>.</p>

<p>his Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council, upon mature Debate of redressing the grievances of poor prisoners, resolved, that an Ordinance for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>, should be forthwith printed and published. An Ordinance also passed for relief of persons that have acted in the service of the Parliament. There was another Ordinance likewise passed for prohibiting Cock-Matches, the exact Copy take as followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Meetings and Assemblies of people together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cock-fighting, are by experience found to tend many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practice, to the dishonour of God, and do often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of persons and their families. For prevention thereof, Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his council, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publike">public</reg> or set meetings or Assemblies of any persons within England or Wales, upon matches made for Cock-fighting; And that every such meeting and assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an unlawful Assembly and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be, and punished; And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, Majors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, constables, and Headboroughs, within their several Counties, Cities, Limits and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such meetings and assemblies.</p>

<p><i>Hen. Scobel. Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>Another Ordinance is likewise passed, for continuing one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations, viz.</p>

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations, and all the powers, authorities, matters, and things therein contained, shall be, and are hereby revived and continued, in full power and force, to all intents and purposes, until further Order. And it is hereby further ordained that Rich. Lucy, John Hildesley, Nathanial Barton, Jervas Bennet, Anthony Rous, Joachym Mathews, Edward Clud, Thomas Wood, Esquires, &amp; Robert Tichburn Alderman of London, be added to the Judges mentioned in the said Act, and that the said Judges named in the said Act, and in this present Ordinance, or any three of them, be, and are hereby authorized to put in execution all and every the Powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named might have done by force of the said Act</p>
<p>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>The Newcastle <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg> hath taken a Dutch man of war of 14 guns, and sent her into Bridlington Bay: this was one of the four Capers that did much annoy us on the Northern Coast. Sundry other Vessels are taken; but the lading of some are scarce worth mentioning.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The great expectations of Peace and union between the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of England and Holland is now arrived our Ears, insomuch, that we can certainly assure you, that the Articles both in relation to them and Denmark, are absolutely concluded on, and the Commissioners are even now ready to sign and seal on both sides.</p>

<p>Paris April the first. All the discourse at present is concerning that which was acted in Parliament on Saturday last, when all the Chambers being assembled, and every member in their scarlet <reg orig="gownes">gowns</reg>, the King then came, and being sat in his bed of Justice, they proceeded in the business of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and immediately read the sentence, which is, That for being found guilty of high Treason and Rebellion against the King his Lord and liege <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, he was to be put to death, and that so soon as he should be apprehended, his Sentence to be executed, his lands and goods all forfeited to the Crown; in regard of his quality he is not to be executed in <reg orig="Effigie">Effigy</reg>, &amp; as touching the manner of his death the Parliament would not determine but left it to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is much troubled at this cruel Sentence against his brother, and has left the Court.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg> our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, That the Commander in chief hath issued forth a Proclamation, requiring all <reg orig="Burroughs">Boroughs</reg> and Parishes to secure all <reg orig="suspitious">suspicious</reg> persons, and enemies to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: Several Towns have been found guilty of the breach hereof, the persons confined, and their houses <reg orig="level'd">levelled</reg> with the ground, and a pair of Gallows erected in the same place. The 21 instant Col. Cooper with a party of Horse and Dragoons from Glascow, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of <em>Leven</em>, where about 300 of the enemy quartered [about 4 in the morning]) took <reg orig="Mac-Naughtons">Mac-Naughton's</reg> Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, but Col. Newark escaped. In this Conflict many a stout Spirit saluted the ground, and the whole part was totally routed, with very little.</p>

<p>There hath been a very sharp Dispute between the Paul <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and a Flushing man of War, the last Week; but after 5 hours Conflict, the Hollanders were forced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, and now <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the mercy of our States in Plymouth.</p>

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, being the 27 of this instant <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, there came a <em>Post</em> from Scotland, intimating, That the Royal part increaseth, and that <pb n="5" />Gen. <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise <em>Southerland, Caithness</em>, and the county of <em>Ross</em>, and so to drain the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, even as a <reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> sucketh in Water, of all the able, stout, and resolute hearts, that are able to bear Arms from sixteen to sixty; with a Resolution to descend down into the Lowlands: for indeed, they grow numerous, and swell up as a Snow-Ball doth in its rolling; but may as soon dissolve again in the like Element. The <reg orig="Lor">Lord</reg> <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to seven hundred, the Earl of <em>Athol</em> five hundred, Co. <em>Forbs</em> five hundred, and the last general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> seven thousand horse and foot they spake themselves to be <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> armed, but have not obtained as yet the silver Instrument, which is the life of the Cause, and the very sinew of War: but their expectation is great from <em>Germany</em>, and for <reg orig="ought">aught</reg> I know, long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for may come at last: in the interim, they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p>

<p>From Scotland it is further advertized, That Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath sent a Letter to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, declaring, That it was not unknown what amicable <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> they had <reg orig="us'd">used</reg>, to avoid the effusion of Christian blood since they came into those parts, which though hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they should <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the same; <em><reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> further</em>, That their Arms were still <reg orig="stretcht">stretched</reg> out ready to embrace them, <reg orig="when ever">whenever</reg> God should incline them to come in; and that they sought not domination over them, to enslave them, nor to depress them in any lawful way, but to carry on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Work: And that if they would still be blinded, and persist in the <reg orig="gain-saying">gainsaying</reg> and opposing, then what further misery befell their Nation by famine or sword, would <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> heavy upon them. This Letter (though favouring so much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adversaries; for immediately thereupon, an Answer was returned; which being briefly contracted, the genuine sense take as followeth; That in case they were not in a capacity against the unjust proceedings of the English, yet were they in a capacity to suffer, and should submit to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Will, either by doing or suffering, until the time of their deliverance come; and that if it were their happiness to perish in their Duty and Loyalty, it would be a sufficient mercy to them: and when the persecution had arrived to its height, their captivity should be returned. <pb n="7" />But doubtless, but that in time we shall be able to put a Hook into the Nostrils, and a Bridle into the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of these high and mighty Youngsters, who threaten nothing but fire and sword to all that shall oppose them. There has been a Summons sent to the castle of Lough by col. <em>Morgan</em>, in the name of the Lord Protector, demanding a rendition. But the Governor returned Answer, That as for the castle it stood upon a Rock, and as for the Lord Protector he knew no such man: in consideration whereof, he was resolved to dispute the Walls by Inches and to fight it out to the last man.</p>

<p>The Dutch fleet are in a formidable posture, and new Orders issued forth to Vice-Admiral <em>Ruiter</em>. The King of Spain looks with a notable <reg orig="sheeps">sheep's</reg> eye upon the <reg orig="Belgick">Belgic</reg> <reg orig="Lyons">Lions</reg> and 'tis conceived <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> may probably be attempted.</p>

<p>It is advertized, that the King of Scots is yet in France, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty will produce betwixt England and France. He had a Present given him a little before Easter by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom. In the <reg orig="Holydayes">Holidays</reg> the little Queen his mother came to see him in the Palace Royal, and King <em>Lewis</em> vouchsafed him a visit in the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em>; After which, she returned to her Devotions in the Nunnery. But if there be a peace concluded between the Commonwealth of England, and the Crown of France, then they are to be excluded from the Court. Well! Patience is a Virtue: And I question not but <reg orig="e're">ere</reg> long to represent you with the glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of the Olive leaves under the happy Government of <em>Oliver</em> our Protector.</p>

<p>There is still listing of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> in several places; and valiant Co. <em>Goff</em> (that faithful, prudent, and pious Assertor of <em>England's</em> Liberties) is very vigilant in preventing of Distempers, and careful to preserve the Peace and <reg orig="Tranquility">Tranquillity</reg> of these Nations.</p>

<p>It is reported, that when the Articles are signed between the English and Dutch, that then certain Squadrons of these two incomparable Fleets are to spread their <reg orig="Canvass">Canvas</reg> upon the Turkish Dominions; which will be a Work of singular excellency, and much tending to the never-dying Honour and Fame of his highness the Lord Protector throughout all Christendom.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>