<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell175">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 175</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer.</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING,</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> now on foot in <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and other parts of <em>Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these Particulars, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Declaration of his most excellent Highness, <em>OLIVER</em> Lord Protector of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging: with his Act of Pardon and Grace to the people of the Scottish Nation; and the Names of the Princes, Dukes, <reg orig="Marquesses">Marquises</reg>, <reg orig="Earles">Earls</reg>, Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, that are excepted from any benefit thereof: Together with a <em>List</em> of the Nobility, Colonels, and Officers, now fined by his <em>Highness</em> for adhering to the Royal part, and the mighty sums of money imposed, with the time prefixed for the payment. Also, the new Order concerning the white Cross of St. <em>Andrew</em>, the <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> of it with the <em>Red </em>cross, and the golden <em>Harp</em>, and the speech of the <em>Lord Ambassador</em> from the most high and mighty Prince <em>Lewis</em>, to his <em>Highness</em> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and his Answer thereunto.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> April <em>the</em> 19, to <em>Wednesday</em> April <em>the</em> 26.</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Robert Wood, for information of the People.</em></head>
<hr />

<p>By an Express from <em>Paris</em>, thus: In answer to yours concerning the little Q. and her Son the K. of <em>Scots</em>, thus much at present; On the 22 of April she went from hence, having two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before taken her leave of the King and Court, there went with her, her two <unclear>sons</unclear> <em>Charles</em> and <em>James</em>, Prince <em>Rupert</em>, the Lord <em>Digby</em>, sir <em>Lewis Dives</em>, and divers other Gentlemen, in all about 12 Coaches; some say she intends for <em>Orleans</em>: others, to the Duke her brother, at his house near <em>Blois</em>.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The Articles of peace are delivered to his Highness the Lord protector in a silver box, signed and sealed by the States of the United provinces, all concurring; and his Highness hath appointed the like to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> here, and to pass the Great Seal of England; and then he will sign it by his sign <em>Manual</em>, which is them to be put into a silver box, and be sent to the <em>Hague</em>; and after signification of the States General receiving thereof, it will be published in both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, that the grand design of Rising doth appear every day more universal, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Scots flying out, but divers English; and amongst the rest three Clerks, belonging to the Court of Justice at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, divers <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> out of Lieth, and about 50 from Sterling are gone t the Hills; from whence they descend down <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> into the Lowlands, and amongst others, the E. of Salkirk, second son to the Marq. of <em>Douglas</em>, started out the other day, and took from Boggehal 60 horse. Nay, this is not all, but divers other <reg orig="English-men">Englishmen</reg> are got to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> under the command of an <reg orig="Irish-man">Irish-man</reg> so that <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Army consists of at least 800 horse &amp; 3000 foot, and are resolved to engage us. Whereupon col. <em>Morgan</em> with 850 horse, &amp; 1600 foot is advanced against them, and a sudden engagement is expected.</p>

<p>Cap. Staner, and Cap. Smith, Commanders of the Tonnington and Plymouth <reg orig="frigots">frigates</reg>, have taken an Holland East-India ship outward bound of 800 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with 350 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of goods, and 4 Chests of silver. The Constant Warwick hath brought in Prize a Brest man of war with 8 guns, and 50 men into Plymouth.</p>

<p>Ay! But to this welcome <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, we have received very sad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg>, that is, on Tuesday last Cap. Southwood, commander of the White-Raven, going from Lieth Road towards Newcastle, was set upon by a 11 Dutch men of war, boarded and taken, and the 13 instant a private man of war of ours, was accidentally blown up in the Lieth Road, and 6 men killed.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Warsow">Warsaw</reg></em> they write, that the <em>Muscovites</em> before they would grant the <em>Cossacks</em> their protection, obliges them to renounce the Amity of the <em>Tartarians</em>, that they should never acknowledge their old Polish Lords, nor wear any habit after the polish mode, or wear any red or yellow boots, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> black ones; and that they shall drink no strong waters, play at cards, or take tobacco &amp;c.</p>

<p>The French in <em>Bruxel</em> are in a <reg orig="pannick">panic</reg> fear that the K. of Spain will deliver into the hands of the Lord protector of England, the town of Dunkirk for security of forces which they fear shall be sent over to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, for the service of the K. of Spain, against the Crown of France.</p>

<p>The Q. of Sweden hath written a letter to the French Ambassador, concerning her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Resolution of surrendering Her Crown and Kingdom to Pr. <em>Charles</em>, which is conceived to be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for promoting of the princess of <em>Orange</em> and the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> sister.</p>

<p>From Holland they write, That the States General have sent to all Provinces, and considerable cities to bring in their opinions and consents <pb n="2" />concerning the House of <em>Orange</em>, and the <em>Stuarts</em> Family; <i>'tis hoped all things will prove for the best</i>. And 'tis conceived the Q of Sweden hath a good intention for the <em>Low-Countries</em>: Unto which confines, valiant Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> is said to prosecute his journey with a stately Train. Their great Armado, far bigger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, is designed to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth into the Deep about the merry month of <em>May</em>: at which time they intend to play strange pranks, <i>over the left shoulder</i>.</p>

<p>The States have had several meetings for preventing of the Designs which may be intended against the <em>Sound</em>, and to preserve the <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> right to the K. of <em>Denmark</em>; and upon the Result, sent Orders to the Admiralty of <em>Amsterdam</em>, to carry on the Naval <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> with expedition.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> it is certified, That capt <em>Potter</em> Commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em> (who not long since brought in that famous <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> cap. <em>Beach</em>) hath again disputed the <reg orig="soveraignty">sovereignty</reg> of the seas with another Brest man of War, called the <em>Bridget</em>, and after a sharp and cruel conflict, came to <reg orig="grapling">grappling</reg>, and at last boarded her, and brought her into the aforesaid Port: she is one of the neatest things and best <reg orig="saylor">sailor</reg> that ever spread her <reg orig="canvass">canvas</reg> upon the curled Waves.</p>

<p>From <em>Truro</em> in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, That Mrs. <em>Hannah Trapnel</em>, who lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, hath for some time <reg orig="bin">been</reg> in those parts, where she passed from Town to Town, to vent her <reg orig="Prophesies">Prophecies</reg>, and alienate the hearts of the people from the present Government: There are in her company one Mr. <em>Langdon</em>, and M. <em>Bauden</em>, two members of the late short-lived <em>Parliament</em>: But the Justices having taking notice of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and practices, she was apprehended; and M. <em>Lobb</em> giving the Charge in the last Sessions, willed the Jury to inquire, 1 concerning <em>Vagrants</em>, 2 such as occasioned unlawful meetings, 3 such as speak against the present Government. There were two Indictments drawn against her; but M. <em>Langdon</em>, and M. <em>Bauden</em>, endeavoured to make a learned Defence, and could not be suffered: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they entered into Bonds of 300 <em>l.</em> for her good <reg orig="behavior">behaviour</reg>, and appearance at the next Assizes. This passage reminds me of the old story of <em>Eliz. Barton</em>, the Holy Maid of <em>Kent</em> (as she was called) in the days of H. 8. who was made use of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests, by <reg orig="feined">feigned</reg> Miracles &amp; Trances, to raise admiration in the multitude, and foment seditious Humours against the Government; for which she and her accomplices were all executed.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, has set forth an Ordinance, declaring, That all persons of the Scottish Nation of what degree of quality soever (except the persons hereafter named) shall, from and after the 1 day of <em>May</em>, 1654. be freed, acquitted, &amp; discharged, from all Forfeitures, fines, Sequestrations, pains, penalties, imprisonments, or punishments whatsoever, for any matter or thing by them <reg orig="commited">committed</reg> by sea or land, in relation to the late war, or any preceding war between the two Nations; And that after the said 1 day of <em>May</em>, no sequestration fine, or punishment, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be imposed, but the same to be put in perpetual Oblivion.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Names of those exempted from Pardon and Grace.</i></head>

<!-- list organised as two columns-->
<p><em>Henrietta Maria</em>, the Queen of the late King <em>Charles</em> deceased.</p>
<p><em>Charles Stuart</em>, their eldest son,</p>
<p><em>James Stuart</em>, their second son.</p>
<p><em>James</em> late duke of <em>Hamilton</em>, deceased.</p>
<p><em>William</em> late Duke of <em>Hamilton</em> deceased.</p>
<p><em>John</em> Earl of <em>Crawford Lindsey</em>,</p>
<p><em>James</em> Earl of <em>Kalender</em>,</p>
<p><em>John</em> Earl of <em>Lawderdail</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Kelley</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Lowdon</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Athol</em>,</p>
<p>Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Lorn</em>, eldest son of the Marquess of <em><reg orig="Arguile">Argyll</reg></em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Machlin</em>, eldest son of the L. <em>Lowdon</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Montgomery</em>, eldest son of the Earl of <em>Egglingtoun</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Spynie</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Cranston</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Sinclare</em>,</p>
<p><em>Thomas Dalyel</em>, late Maj. Gen. of the foot in the Scottish Army.</p>
<p><em>John Middleton</em>, late Lieu. Gen. of the Horse in the Scottish army.</p>
<p>Viscount <em>Newburgh</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Bargany</em>,</p>
<p>Sir <em>Thomas Tompson</em>,</p>
<p>Lord <em>Napier</em>,</p>
<p>Laird <em>Domeston</em> of <em>Womar</em>,</p>
<p>Earl of <em>Glencarn</em>,</p>

<p>And it is further ordained, that the several persons hereafter named, do pay unto his Highness the Lord Protector his <reg orig="publike">public</reg> receipt the several respective sums of money hereafter mentioned and expressed, as a fine and fines for and in respect of his or their estates, to be paid in such manner, and at such times, as is hereafter expressed, that is to say,</p>
<!-- list organised as two columns-->
<!-- names left-justified, sums of money right-justified -->

<p><em>David Lesley</em>, late Lieu. Cen. of the Scotch Army 4000 <em>li. sterling.</em></p>
<p>Marq. of <em>Douglas</em> 1000 <em>li. sterling.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Angus</em> 1000 <em>l. ster.</em></p>
<pb n="4" />
<p>Earl of <em>Selcrig</em> 1000 <em>l. ster.</em></p>
<p>The Heirs of Francis late Earl of Bucleuch deceased, 15000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Galloway</em> 4000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Roxburgh</em> 6000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Cockeram</em> 5000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Forrester</em> 2500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Armstruther</em> 1000 marks <em>ster</em>.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Archibald Sterling</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Drummond</em> 500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p><em>Henry Mawl</em>, son to the E. of <em>Panmure</em>, 2500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>James Levingston</em> of <em>Kilsith</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Murrey</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Buchane</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Viscount <em>Dudhop</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Preston of <unclear><em>Cragmeller</em></unclear> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Andrew Flesher</em> 5000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>John <unclear>Wnuchab</unclear></em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Prith</em>, and Lord <em>Drumond</em> his eldest son, 5000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Winton</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Findlater</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Murry</em> 3500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Quinsburgh</em> 4000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <unclear><em>Eith</em></unclear> 6000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Duffus</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Grey</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Panmure</em> 10000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Arrol</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Tullibardine</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Sowthesk</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <unclear><em>Dalbensie</em></unclear> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Hartfield</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Ross</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Sample</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Elphinstone</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Boide</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Cooper</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Balwaird</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Rollock</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Kinghorn</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Kinkardine</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Bamfe</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Medrum</em> of <em>Tylliebody</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Robert Graham</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>William Scot</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Arnot</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Hay</em> of <em>Bowset</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Francis Reven</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Scot</em> of <em>Montrose</em> 3000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Laird of <em>Rothemegordon</em> 500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>John Scot</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Laird of <unclear><em>Gossid</em></unclear> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Laird of <em>Bachilton</em> 1500 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Rothes</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Lewis Stuart</em> 1000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>James Carmighil</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>
<p>Laird of <em>Stanhop</em> 2000 <em>l.</em></p>

<p>All and every which sum and sums of money, shall be paid unto <em>George Bilton</em> Deputy Treasurer at <unclear><em>Lieth</em></unclear>; one <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> thereof, on, or by the 2 day of <em>August</em>, 1654; and the other <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> on, or by the 2. day of <em>Decemb.</em> Then next ensuing; and in default of such payment, all and every the real and personal estate of every person and persons so making default, shall from thenceforth be absolutely confiscate; and the Commissioners for Sequestrations, are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to seize the same accordingly.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>By an Express from <em>Naples</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Delfino</em> having besieged the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Clim</em>, found so cold a welcome, by the host and desperate sallying out of the Turks, that after a lamentable and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> conflict, he was totally routed, and left behind him above a thousand gallant men, and all his Bag and Baggage, besides some pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, April 18.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Lodowich de Gand</em>, Lord of <em>Brachey</em>, and Resident here in <em>England</em> in behalf of the high and mighty Prince <em>Lewis</em>, Duke of <em>Guelders</em> and <em>Julters</em>, Conte of <em>Egmont</em> and <em>Zutphon</em>, &amp;c was this day, with many Gentlemen of quality accompanying him in coaches, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, unto his Highness the Lord Protector; The Lord President <em>Laurence</em>, and some other Lords of the Council, with the Secretary of State, being present in his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> chamber, where the said Lord Resident had audience, and made a congratulatory Speech, which was answered with abundance of respect from his Highness.</p>

<head level="2">By the Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</head>

<p><i>Whereas a peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the States General of the united Provinces of the Low countries. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be made on both parts on <em>Wednesday</em> next, being the 26 of this instant <em>April</em>; from which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after 12 days, within these seas; and in all other places on this side the cape of St <em>Vincent</em>; and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> sea, and to the &AElig;quinoctial Line, after ten weeks; and beyond the &AElig;quinoctial, after the space of 8 months: which several spaces were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this Commonwealth, and to all others whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof, to the end, they may have warning to provide for their own safety, and not expose their ships to danger within the several and respective times aforesaid.</i></p>

<p><em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em>, <em>April</em> 21. thus: This Afternoon arrived here the Express, who doth return into <em>Holland </em>to carry to the States General the ratification of the peace, signed and sealed by his Highness the L. <pb n="6" />Protector, which upon signification of their receiving, will suddenly be proclaimed both in <em>England</em> and<em> Wales</em>.</p>

<p>There are brought into this Road three Dutch prizes, whereof one was a ship bound for the East Indies, and the other two of great value. There are also brought into <em>Harwich</em> two Dutch prizes which came from <em>Norway</em>; and some Busses are taken by a private man of war, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> into <em>Yarmouth</em>, laden with fish.</p>

<p>By an Express from aboard the <em>Pearl</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> it is certified, That about 50 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of English men of War, and as many Dutch, are designed for the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, the <em>Indies</em>, and <em>Levant</em> seas; and that Gen. <em>Pen</em> is to be commissionated for this famous Expedition. The Fleet rides as yet in <em>Stokes-Bay</em>; but expects daily command to weigh anchor.</p>

<p>By an Express from <em>Scotland</em>, we have received very remarkable intelligence, intimating, That the Royal party increase, and have taken some few prisoners from the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills, the Lord <em>Forrester</em>, and the Lord <em>Dudhop</em> are in <em>Athol</em>, and very active in attending the motion of General <em>Middleton</em>. The rest of their forces in <em>Caithness</em> have left no means unassayed for raising of the whole <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>; but the people being <reg orig="timerous">timorous</reg> of rising, <reg orig="feariny">fearing</reg> <reg orig="least">lest</reg> the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Sinclair</em>, commanded by cap. <em>Langrish</em> of col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Regiment should punish them for their Loyalty, after <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> march from thence: wherefore for their encouragement, Maj. Gen. <em>Dyal</em> with a strong party of foot, and 100 stout horse, is ordered to sit down before it for the reducing of it, which is conceived to be a work of great difficulty, the place being situated on a very high <em>Rock</em>, yet if they prove successful in this <reg orig="Atchievement">Achievement</reg>, they intend then to attempt <em>Ruthin</em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>; but cap. <em>Hill</em> (the Governor) has reinforced it with provisions, and is well provided for a siege.</p>

<p>The Armies on both sides are preparing to receive each other, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> has <reg orig="drain'd">drained</reg> <em>Innerness</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those forces which he brought form <em>Aberdeen</em>, so that he lies with about 1200 Horse and Dragoons, and 2000 Foot, betwixt the enemy and the passes they must needs march though, if they intend to move out of the North corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, and 'tis said, they are resolved, there being no way left them to avoid it, but through such inaccessible bounds, as 'tis impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their foot, it being exceeding mountainous, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> they are in will not <pb n="7" />long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an account of some action betwixt him and <em>Middleton</em>; what the success will be, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>; for, to speak truth, we have a very stout and stubborn enemy to deal <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and as potent they speak themselves to be as valiant, saying they scorn to prove perfidious (in the least) to so great a Cause wherein the interest of their King so much depends; but will rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to sacrifice their lives in the field, and dispute the mountainous passes by inches.</p>

<p>The two Armies continue now at an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> distance from each other for some days past, and 'tis conceived that the English have <reg orig="som">some</reg> advantage of them in respect of ground, and will endeavour by all means to engage them, though their number far exceeds ours. But alas! during the time of their declining engagement, many of our <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> run from several parts to the enemy, which do much exasperate them, and annoy Us. We expect a sudden Engagement, and many desperate onsets there hath already been; yet not much cause to laugh on either side as yet: Therefore, for the success, we must refer it unto Him in whose hands are all the Corners of the Earth.</p>

<p>But some letters of a later date <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That col. <em>Morgan</em> hath <reg orig="dispierced">dispersed</reg> some of them, killed divers, and took many prisoners, which seems to be of the same complexion, as certain stories derived from the Fame of Tradition.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has also ordained, That all the people of <em>Scotland</em>, shall be incorporated into one <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> with <em>England</em>; and in every Parl. to be held successively, 30 persons to be called from thence. And that this Union may take its more full effect and intent, It is further ordained, That the Arms of <em>Scotland</em>, viz a Cross, commonly called the Saint <em><reg orig="Andrews">Andrew's</reg></em> Cross, be received into, and <reg orig="born">borne</reg> from henceforth in the Arms of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>Whosoever can give notice of two black stoned horses, strayed away, or otherwise conveyed away from <unclear><em>Hyan ferries</em></unclear> in <em>Northamptonshire</em>, on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> night the 14 of April 1654. both long <reg orig="Mayns">Manes</reg> and <reg orig="Tayles">Tails</reg>; the bigger horse four white feet, and a knot in the fetlock of the <reg orig="neer">near</reg> leg behind: The other, which is the lesser horse, a scar in the <reg orig="fore-head">forehead</reg>, and a white foot behind, an the fashions in the further Leg behind, and a little hole in one of his ears. If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> can bring <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of them to <em>Rich. Burton</em> at the <reg orig="Horse shooe">Horseshoe</reg> in <em>Smithfield</em>, they shall have 40 shillings for their pains.</i></p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>