<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell172">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 172</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate <reg orig="Inteligencer">Intelligencer</reg>,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The <reg orig="Lettters">Letters</reg> and Papers taken in the tower of London, concerning the proceedings of State Affairs, and Mr. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Lilburn, and the removing of him from thence to the Isle of <reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg>. A Declaration and Narrative touching the Change of Government, and the happiness of those people who live under such a Government, and the happiness of those people who live under such a Government, where it is the duty of their Governors to rule by Law, and content to be governed as well as to govern; <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> representing the never to be forgotten <reg orig="Presidents">Precedents</reg> of the Roman Consuls, and worthy to be written in letters of Gold with the point of a Diamond, how gallantly they served as private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> in those <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> Armies which formerly they had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> Generals of. With variety of intelligence from Denmark, France, Scotland &amp; Holland.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday April 5. to Wednesday April 12. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>The K. of Denmark hath sent forth his Royal Mandates to raise forces to send aboard his Navy to secure the <em>Sound</em>: and the Low counties make great preparations to defend themselves. At the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg>, last Saturday, a man was sentenced to be <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg> to death, and being afterwards heard to groan, was carried down to the Press-yard again to have the execution <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg>. Another that was <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> <reg orig="dy'd">died</reg> most desperately smiling as he rode along in the Cart, and drinking a health to the Devil in Sack.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3">Mr <em>Tho. Lewis</em>, Mr. <em>Tho. Powel</em>, and Mr. <em>Griffith Harley</em>, <i>their Letter to Master <em>Jenk. Jones</em>.</i></head>

<p>Mr Hones, We desire to be resolved by you, whether the elected Ministers of this Country, who have been silenced and suspended, how this long time, <i>ab officio, &amp; beneficio</i> may at last have the door of utterance opened, and be permitted to preach the Gospel freely among those that do much want it, <unclear>and do as earnestly</unclear> call for it, as the parched Earth after the dew and rain of Heaven. The reason why we put this business to the question is: because about the last spring, some of our fellow Ministers, taking the boldness to preach the word of God, were some of them, sent prisoners to <em><reg orig="Chepsto">Chepstow</reg></em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, others pulled out of the Pulpit, and all the rest were <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> to have the same measure meted unto them, if they should make the same attempts: and therefore we desire to know whether we are under the same restraint still, or are at liberty: we doubt not but that you can resolve us herein, as well as any other in this County, and we hope you will be pleased to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> our civil request herein, and vouchsafe us a line of answer, which you may direct to either of the subscribers, who are</p>
<p>Your friends, as far as you are a friend to Christ and his ways</p>
<p><i>Tho. Lewis, Tho. Powell, Griffith Harley</i></p>
<p>Feb. 6. 1643.</p>

<head level="3">Mr. Jenk. <reg orig="Jones">Jones'</reg> letter in Answer to the former.</head>

<p><i>Gentlemen,</i></p>
<p>Your letter dated <em>Feb.</em> 6. 1653. I received the 1. of <em>March</em>. And in Answer to what you propose therein I shall only put you in <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> that you are still, and more than line t be in the same condition, with those in the last Spring: and tell you that you are to expect the same measure from the present Power, whose connivance you seem, at least, to <reg orig="fancie">fancy</reg> to <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg>, as your brethren has the last Spring from the then powers. And also that you need not <unclear>pretend your being</unclear> pressed as from <reg orig="pitty">pity</reg> to water the parched earth, there being more Sermons preached now in one <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, <reg orig="then">then</reg> were formerly in twelve, and with very much, though I dare not say with a greater blessing: consider the restraint-fearing Spirit <unclear><reg orig="thats">that's</reg> in</unclear> you,</p>
<p>Your friend, and servant,</p>
<p><i>Jen. Jones.</i></p>
<p><em>March</em> 2. 1653.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em> the 7. instant: The Ships, which were in this Road are now <unclear>gone</unclear> Southward. The English Fleet are an 100. sail, lie at St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point</em>, and the rest at <em>Spits head</em>.</p>

<p>No news from Sea, save that a Dutch man of war, called the <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg></em> <pb n="2" /><em>Baptist</em>, bound from St. <em><reg orig="Malos">Malo's</reg></em> to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and laden with <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg> and Pepper, was taken by the Reserve <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>: the Capt. Was a Frenchman, but the service being so <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hot, he was at last soundly <reg orig="pepper'd">peppered</reg>, and force to surrender to cool himself. An Ostend man of war <unclear>was</unclear> brought into Plymouth by the Falmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and 3 Dutch prizes laden with French Wines, <unclear>Figs</unclear>, and Raisons from St. Lucas. Alas! But to these sweet Fruits, we hear of very sharp and <reg orig="sowr">sour</reg> <reg orig="sawce">sauce</reg>: for true it is, that the Brest men of War have taken the <em>Charity</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, and detain the Master for cap. <em>Beach</em>, whom they threaten to mete the same measure unto, as shall be inflicted upon the said <em>Beach</em>. They have also taken two Weymouth Vessels, another of Westchester, and most of the best ships belonging to Bristol. Nay, this is not all; but the Wild Boar is <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by a Fleming, a delicate Vessel, and bravely fraught, and valued worth 5000 <em>li</em>. To this sad and <reg orig="dismall">dismal</reg> Scene ensues another fatal Act that is, the <em>Expedition</em> of <em>Plymouth</em> coming from <unclear><em>Zant</em></unclear>, laden with <em>Currants</em>, was set upon y A Dutch man of war, and after a long and sharp dispute both ships were sunk.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 4.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em> had this day audience by his highness at the Cockpit, and the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> <em>Agent</em> had likewise audience, being attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his Highness divers Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of state.</p>

<p>The Committee for approbation of Ministers have met in <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>, chose their Register, and other Officers, and began to proceed in the business according to the Ordinance of his Highness. The place which they sit in, is at the end of the stone Gallery, at the corner of the Court, and their proceedings are such as promiseth much good to this Nation by the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of an able, godly and powerful Gospel <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>. They sit <reg orig="Mundayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg>, and <reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Welch men">Welshmen</reg> have sent a Declaration to his Highness, wherein they bless God for the late Change and present Government. And the like is come from <em>Norfolk</em>, and other places. <i>To God be all the glory.</i></p>

<p>The Commission of the great Seal being <reg orig="alter'd">altered</reg>, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, and Sir <em>Tho. <unclear>Withrington</unclear></em> were this day sworn Commissioners for the <pb n="3" />custody of the great Seal of <em>England</em> for the Court of Chancery by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his Highness and his Council, in the Council chamber at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>. The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is added to them.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em> we have received intelligence, That the French men of war upon the Coast of <unclear><em>Apulia</em></unclear> have done much harm, and taken many prizes, among whom is an English ship worth fifty thousand pounds taken at <em>Cape Spativente</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> the 3. instant.</head>

<p>This day was presented to his highness the Lord Protector a Declaration and Recognition by M. <em>Dickeson</em> Alderman, and Sir <em>Thomas Withrington</em> Recorder of the City of <em>York</em>: the true copy whereof take as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord, whose eyes run to and fro through the earth, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself strong on the behalf of them whose hearts are perfect to him, to make bare his Arm, and bring salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, &amp; to break many yokes from off our necks, in accomplishment <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg>, though humane Might and Power have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and over-ruled by the Spirit in the midst of the wheels, that we may justly say, We are not saved by Bow, or by sword, but by the Lord our God; and therefore, in the first place we look upon it as our duty to acknowledge Salvation and blessing to him that sits upon the throne of Heaven judging the right, who hath done whatsoever it pleased him, both in Heaven, and in Earth, and in all deep places. Yet when we also consider how it hath seemed good in the eyes of God to single out your Highness as the man of his right hand, whom he hath made strong for himself, and through your vigilancy, courage, and constancy, to do great and wonderful things in the midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left. While we bless the Lord, our heart is also to the Governors of <em>Israel</em>, who have jeoparded their lives in the high places of the field and are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> going on to second their valiant Acts <pb n="4" />by prudent Councils, that we may enjoy the end of every just War, which is, a safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> peace. Unto your highness therefore (as all the people of Israel to their Ruler) we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and peace be to thine helpers.</i></p>

<p>For which congratulation, his Highness returned thanks to the City of <em>York</em>, and the Gentlemen that presented it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Westminster April 5.</i></head>

<p>This night between 6 and 7 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> the Lord <em>Lambert</em>, the L. <em>Lisle</em>, the L. <em>Strickland</em>, and the rest of the English Commissioners, went to the Dutch Ambassadors at Sir <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Trevers</em>, in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches, with Mr. <em>Thurlo</em> Secretary of state, and Mr. <em>Scobel</em> Clerk of the Council; and about 9 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night totally finished the Ratification of Peace, and the Articles were then signed and sealed by the Lord Ambassadors on the one side, with full power from the States, and the Lords commissioners with full power from the Lord Protector on the other side. And within 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> the Peace is to be ratified by the Principals on each part, and <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> proclaimed in both England and the <reg orig="Low-countries">Low Countries</reg>. Of which, more by the next: in the interim, be pleased to take notice, that one Article is, that the King of <em>Denmark</em> is to make satisfaction to the English Merchants for all the losses by them sustained and the Dutch are to be Security. Another is that both commonwealths are to assist each other, both offensive and defensive, &amp;c.</p>

<p>the next thing that we shall present you <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, is, the proceedings of the Royal Party in <em>Scotland</em>, which purports, that the Lord <em>De la<unclear><reg orig="Banks">Bank's</reg></unclear></em> Brothers, seven Knights, and 50 Gentlemen, are gone from the West to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, with special Horse and Arms, and that the heroical spirits <em>Glencarn, Kenmore, Athol, Forbs</em> and divers other of the mickle Lairds are very plausible, by which means they work <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> upon the affections of the Lowlanders, and expects the access of more forces very suddenly.</p>

<p>The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is come to <em>Glencarne</em> with about 700. horse and foot, <em>Seafort</em> and some new raised forces by him, are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. <em>Glencairn</em> being 2000, horse and foot, is at <em>Dingwel</em>, and it is thought we may engage them there.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>There hath been a very sharp Dispute between the Paul <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and a Flushing man of War, the last Week; but after 5 hours <unclear>Conflict</unclear>, the Hollanders were forced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, and now <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the mercy of our States in Plymouth.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday April 8.</head>

<p>Presents us with an Ordinance for adjourning part of <em>Easter</em> Term, which take as followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained: Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to <reg orig="Adiourn">Adjourn</reg> part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>: Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> That part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em> now next coming to be <reg orig="Adiourned">Adjourned</reg>, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, unto the first return of <em>Trinity</em> Term, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>: And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, and during the said Term, called <em>Easter</em> Term, may <unclear>carry<!--tarry??--></unclear> at their dwellings, or where their business shall <reg orig="lye">lie</reg>, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, and <unclear>without charges</unclear> or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf. And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg> shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, giving them authority to <reg orig="adiourn">adjourn</reg> the said Term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, until the first return of <em>Trinity</em> Term, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as before is said, and the said <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg> shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Matters, Causes, and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, Depending in any of the said Courts shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said <reg orig="Adiournment">Adjournment</reg>, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as is aforesaid: And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em> do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the Chief Market Towns within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobel</em> Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors have sent an <unclear>Express</unclear> to their Masters the States of the united Provinces, giving them an Account of the Ratification <pb n="6" />for Peace, which is to be signed and sealed by the Lord Protector within 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and then to be <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> proclaimed both in England and Holland in one day. The Agreement with Denmark is also taken in upon the Articles; and for the loss sustained by the English Merchants, whose Demands amount to about one hundred and fifty thousand pounds, it is referred to two English and two Dutch Merchants absolutely to determine those Demands within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and their place of sitting appointed at Guild <reg orig="Hal">Hal</reg>. Also the business of <unclear><em>Amboyna</em></unclear> is referred to eight <unclear><reg orig="Commssioners">Commissioners</reg></unclear>, who have six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> time to determine thereof, and in case they agree not, Umpires are nominated.</p>

<p>Upon the arrival of the <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> at the Hague, touching the signing and sealing of the Articles of Peace between England and Holland, the Royal Party were much startled thereat, and Major Gen. Massey was pleased to make this construction upon the Ratification, That sith Providence had pleased to make up the Breach between the two <reg orig="Republiques">Republics</reg>, it was impossible that his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> Game should go forwards and that he conceived it would redound most to the honour of the English Chevaliers, to engage mutually in the Christian service, against the Turks and Pagans. A most noble and <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Design, and I desire that it may prove effectual.</p>

<p>But on the contrary, the major part are exceedingly revived in spirit, and the Merchants on both sides have great cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>; for the <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> begin already to seek out for shelter, and to striffe off from the Narrow Seas. <i>A fair riddance.</i> And the Navigable <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> appear somewhat <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> the Clouds of <reg orig="Pickroons">Picaroons</reg> being gallantly expelled The Ordinance for better amending and keeping in Repair the common <reg orig="High-wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation, was presented to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have received further intelligence, that the mickle Lairds, are also upon their march for a general conjunction with a Resolution to force all they can to rise with them. Hey toss, how the Game goes forwards: but confident I am, and with a candid Resolution I desire, <unclear>this</unclear> the success may <reg orig="center">centre</reg>, where the justness of <pb n="7" />the Cause most depends, an no otherwise. <em>Middleton</em> has a very large commission, and ordered by his Master <em>Charles</em> to dispose of all Affairs both Ecclesiastical and civil. He proceeds with fire and sword against all those that will not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, and hath besieged <unclear><em>Cinkeler</em></unclear> castle; besides, they have taken a Vessel of ours going to Lewis Island, laden with Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for that Garrison. In the Southern parts towards <em>Carlisle</em> they are very active in <unclear>rising</unclear> daily, which puts the English horse to extraordinary duty, even to <reg orig="tyring">tiring</reg> out. They are drawing together all into one body, and action is suddenly expected. As for the proceedings of Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, they are <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on with abundance of dexterity.</p>

<p>Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Lilburn</em> is removed from the tower of <em>London</em> to some remoter place, 'tis said to Isle of Jersey; the cause is reported to be for attempting again something against the State: and moreover, that he had writ certain Letters, which Papers were seized on in the Tower, and from thence conveyed to his highness. Under whose Government, the Lord grant that we may enjoy peaceably both the Law of God, and the Law of Man in their brightest <reg orig="Rayes">Rays</reg>, and glorious lustre, it being the Oath that he hath sworn unto, and great is the happiness of those people who live under such a Government, where it is the duty of their Governors to rule by Law. O it is an excellent thing to be contented to be governed, as well as to govern; for, to speak ingenuously, innumerable examples of this kind may be found amongst the Romans, as <em><reg orig="Cajus">Caius</reg> Manlius</em>, and divers other Consuls, served as private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> in those Armies that they had formerly been Generals, which indeed is according to the Law of Nature.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> we have received intelligence, That the King of Scots is still at <em>Paris</em>, and of late as merry as a Prince; for upon the Deputies of <em><reg orig="Longuedoc">Languedoc</reg></em> telling him, that if there were a peace with <em>England</em>, it would be well for all the Protestants in <em>France</em>: He made answer that he was glad of it, for then it would be the better for <reg orig="him self">himself</reg>. His brother <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em> hath taken the field against the Prince of <em>Conde</em> and with five thousand horse and foot has taken in sundry strong <unclear>Hods</unclear>.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>