<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell166">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 166</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Declaration of her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, concerning his Highness the Lord Protector, and the present Change of government in England. With her gracious Desires touching the young Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>. Likewise, the landing of the Dutch ambassadors, and the going down of divers eminent Gentlemen, and Officers, with the States Barges, to congratulate them up from Gravesend to the City of Westminster. Together with variety of other intelligence from the King of Scots, his brother <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em>; and a full and perfect Relation of that great and bloody Murder committed on Salisbury Plain, by 20 <reg orig="High-way men">Highwaymen</reg>, upon eight Graziers, who fought it out to the last man, <reg orig="dying">dyeing</reg> the very ground with blood; the like never heard of since the Reign of blessed Queen <em>Elizabeth</em> of happy Memory.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday Feb. 23. to Wednesday Feb. 29. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>The King of Denmark is sending an Ambassador over to his Highness the Lord Protector, desiring to be included within the Articles of the two Commonwealths of England and Holland. The King of France is doing the like; and most Christian Princes in Europe are bringing up the Rear to congratulate his Highness: O brave England! what? shall all these stately Monarchs and Princely Flowers now <reg orig="center">centre</reg> upon the Territories of they little Island: <reg orig="Ay">Aye</reg>, 'tis time, seeing that Royal Cedars were constrained to stoop to its magnificent and flourishing Branches.</p>
<pb n="1" />

<p>Whereas the great point of <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> and concernment to the safety and benefit of a Commonwealth, is the Electing and disposing of its own Magistrates, or the great Officers of State. And as for the <em>present Council</em>, and the election of them in the way it hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg>: It must be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg>, that we were in the beginning of a new Government, necessitated to create a little World out of a Chaos and bring Form out of Confusion; so that there was an absolute necessity, that some who are known to be persons of integrity, and firm for the present Settlement, should at the same instant be taken in, to carry on the work: which can be no ground of just exception, especially seeing for the future, Elections shall run in the appointed channel, where their <reg orig="streames">streams</reg> are to flow from the People, and their original-Fountain. Yea, the high Office of Protectorship <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> is to be derived also from hence; and as in time it will appear, that the People in Parliament have the main choice of the Council, so they will likewise be <reg orig="Chusers">Choosers</reg> of the Lord Protector: For, it being left tot he <reg orig="Counsel">Counsel</reg> to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> Him, and they hereafter coming to be chosen and trusted by the <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, it cannot otherwise be conceived, but that the Choice of Him takes its rise mediately from the People in <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>: because as whatsoever a <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> doth, is said and taken in a political sense to be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> act, because they are chosen and trusted by the people: so in like manner, and upon the same political account, when the Council comes to be chosen by <reg orig="Parlaments">Parliaments</reg>, as is before expressed, then the Act of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, must by a parity of Reason be reputed the Act of the people in <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>: And so you see, in effect, mediately or immediately, the election of all <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> (both high and low) are, or will at length, by this Constitution of Government, be in the hands of the People. Lastly, as to what concerns the Office of <em>Lord Protector</em>, it is to be observed, that he is not to be admitted to that dignity upon the Interest of Himself or Family, but <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> upon the account of his fitness for Government: it must pass, not by Inheritance, but election. And certainly, it is a great advantage to a Nation, that the coming in and continuance of their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> depends only upon his own goodness, and the <reg orig="good will">goodwill</reg> of the People, as it is in an <em>elective Prince</em>, who standing upon terms of good behaviour, will be continually employed for the benefit and defence of the Community. And therefore if it shall please the Lord to bless this Commonwealth (as we trust he will) successively, with a choice of godly persons into that high Office, it is easily foreseen, what an advantage it will be to these 3. Nations, to have their whole strength and force combined thus under one head, for the safety of all: this Form being (without question) the fittest and most convenient for the Magistrate to put things on, and in quick execution (as his proper work) for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good; as also what a comfort it will be to all the godly in the <em>Protestant Churches</em> abroad, who may have some more <pb n="2" />sure and certain protection from <em>England</em> than heretofore; which <unclear>as it is the greatest</unclear> Body, being united with <em>Scotland</em>, to it will prove (we hope) the grand Bulwark of the <em>Reformed Religion</em>. Moreover, as touching the Person, whom the Lord hath now advanced and let over us to be our <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Magistrate, We shall not say much, because he seeks not the praise of men: only we believe even the enemies will confess, that he is every way worthy to Rule, whom God hath been pleased to use as his Instrument in that glorious Work of Redeeming the Liberties of his people: For, we are bold to say (weighing all circumstances together) that this Nation was never really Free, nor in a way of enjoying its Freedom so fully as now: so that there wants nothing but a cordial Close with the Government, to destroy all hopes of the common Enemy, and <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> our happiness. But if men shall yet proceed to lengthen their own <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg>, by hankering after that Family which God hath cast out before us, or by an unnatural seeking to <reg orig="imbroil">embroil</reg> their Country again in blood and misery, for the sake of that unfortunate Interest, as we are <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to suspect such a thing, and can hardly imagine that any should be so forlorn and desperate after so fair a Composure.</p>

<p>At the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg> on Thursday, <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, and Saturday last was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> one <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg> <em>Beard</em>, who upon Evidence, was cast, for bewitching a child: the manner thus: About fifteen weeks ago, the child was struck lame on the left leg, then in the right Arm, and afterwards struck in a most lamentable and fearful manner, sometimes lying raging and speechless, and at other times foaming at the mouth, with her hand closed up: And having continued thus for many weeks together, at last the said <em>Beard</em> came by, which the child perceiving, immediately fell a raving, by making of <reg orig="signes">signs</reg>, and the like: Whereupon the Parents suspecting her to be the Woman that had <reg orig="bewitcht">bewitched</reg> their child, <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> a Warrant, and had her before a Justice; and after examination, she was committed to Newgate, &amp; from thence, brought down to the Sessions in Old <reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg>, where she was arraigned for her life; and upon the Examing of witnesses, and searching of her, it appeared that she had three long Tears <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to her <reg orig="privie">privy</reg> Parts, which she said was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the <reg orig="Pyles">Piles</reg>: But upon the giving in of Evidence, she was cast, and divers others, who suffered death on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last.</p>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> from <em>Holland</em> intimates, that the Difference grows great between the Royal Party, and the Netherlanders, and that they have already disputed the Quarrel touching <em>England</em>. But sure it is, that their Ambassadors are now come with full power to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Articles of Peace. Of which, more by the next.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 27 instant, proved a fatal day to many; for, besides the Witch before-mentioned, eight more having received Sentence of death were executed; amongst the rest, four of them were <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> at the lower end of <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>, over against the Dog Tavern where they committed the Fact, having not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="rob'd">robbed</reg> M. <em>Hancock</em> (Master of the said house) of great store of Plate; but likewise cut and wounded him in several places; for which, Mr. James Harrington (a <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg> of Middlesex) and the <reg orig="Meal-mans">Meal-man's</reg> wife of Brainford, who served the said Mr. Hancock with meal, and knew the Orders of the house, and where the Plate lay, suffered the bitter pangs of death; a just reward for the Woman, but a pitiful Object to behold the man: for she was not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the grand <reg orig="Settor">Setter</reg>, and chief contriver of the Design, in drawing in of poor Mr. Harrington; but likewise the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> betrayer and Decoy of her Noble Hectors, whom she so termed; as appears by the Speech and Confession of the said James Harrington under the Gallows, who spake to the people as followeth:</p>

<p><i>Gentlemen, and Christian friends</i>, You are this day come hither to behold a sad and pitiful Object, and a man to be taken off in the midst of his years: Nevertheless, although Providence hath decreed me such an untimely end, yet I doubt not, but that this ignominious and reproachful death, will to me prove a glorious and perpetual change; and I bless God I have a Conscience within speaks peace to my poor soul, fully assuring me, that this day shall I be in <reg orig="Paradice">Paradise</reg> with my blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; and that though my sins be red as scarlet, yet <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> they be made as white as snow; for confident I am, I never was guilty of <reg orig="any ones">anyone's</reg> death, neither had I ever brought <reg orig="my self">my self</reg> to this untimely end, had it not <reg orig="bin">been</reg> for this woman (meaning the <reg orig="Meal-mans">Meal-man's</reg> wife) <em><reg orig="Ioan">Joan</reg> West</em>, but God forgive her; for I do: And I bless God I am, in peace with all men: Though many there are that calumn and brand me, that I have been an idle liver, and that I have committed several Facts and Crimes: I confess I have been a sinner, and a great company keeper, yet never wronged any man whom I had society <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>: No, I appeal to the great <em>God</em> of Heaven whether I have or no: And though my cause be now thus unhappily <reg orig="ballanced">balanced</reg>, that the ignominious <reg orig="Skale">Scale</reg> of hard and cruel Destiny must even now be turned upon me; yet the penetracy of <pb n="4" />my poor Soul hath taken away the bitter sting of Death; and there is not any thing troubles me at this very instant (though I am here now ready to pass through the Vale of Death) but my poor wife, &amp; six languishing babes, whom I desire the Lord to bless, and to preserve keep and defend them with his glorious Guard of Angels, that so they may be shrouded under the Omnipotent Curtain of Providence, from the wicked Temptations of <reg orig="Sathan">Satan</reg> and his Instruments. Which that you may all do, is the desire of him, who implores the prayers of you, for the finishing of his last and final Work: And the blessed Spirit of the great God be amongst you all; to whom be all honour peace, and thanksgiving both now and for evermore, <em>Amen</em>. And so Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, sweet <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, receive my soul.</p>

<p>Having thus ended his speech, the Minister delivered an Exhortation to them all; and then immediately proceeded the execution, where the said Mr. <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Harrington</em>, and <em><reg orig="Ioan">Joan</reg> West</em>, hung from about eleven of the clock, till 4 in the afternoon at the one end of the <reg orig="Gallowes">Gallows</reg> nest to the Tavern; and Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Sharp</em>, and Mr. <em>Robert</em> <unclear><em>Cudnor</em></unclear> at the other end. <i>A sad and woeful Object to behold!</i></p>

<p>From the West our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, that there hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> a most barbarous and bloody Murder committed on Salisbury Plain, the manner thus: 8 or 9 Graziers being riding over the Plain, and having about 1500 pounds amongst them in their <reg orig="Port-mantles">Portmanteaus</reg>, they were set upon by 18 or 20 Thieves, who demanded their monies, but being denied it, they fell <reg orig="pell-mel">pell-mell</reg> upon the Graziers, put every man to the sword, as they thought, with the loss of 5 of their own Hectors: yet it so pleased divine Providence, that one of the Graziers being not quite deprived of his Senses, heard what Inn they resolved to make to, and a company of Butchers coming by the next morning, fixing their eyes upon this sad and lamentable Object, rode up to them, which the Grazier perceiving, expressed himself, related the manner, and told <reg orig="em">'em</reg>, they were gone to such an Inn at a Village <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Salisbury: Whereupon they left two to convey the said Grazier to a house, and the rest went, raised the town, and beset the Inn where the Thieves were; but the <reg orig="high-way men">highwaymen</reg> opposed so far, that the True-men were constrained to fire the house, and to batter and pull it down over their ears; so that some perished and consumed in the Dust and Flames: the rest were taken and committed to Salisbury Gaol.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Febr. <unclear>20</unclear>.</i></head>

<p>This day came Letters from <em>Scotland</em> touching the proceedings of the Highlanders, and the setting forth of a Proclamation by General <em>Glencarn</em>, a Copy whereof followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the <reg orig="Kindom">Kingdom</reg> of <em>Scotland</em> for opposing the common Enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his Justice hath permitted to overcome and to be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we could turn to him by <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> repentance. And to the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that none of <reg orig="hir">his</reg> faithful Subjects may pretend ignorance, and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires and Parishes, and Head Burghs by open <em>Proclamation</em>, that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> may make his several proportions ready to be delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under our hand wheresoever the foresaid Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of honour, will not move to their duty, may be proceeded against with fire and sword, unworthy to be looked upon as Scotchmen, to the <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> of all false-hearted <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>, who by their treacheries and rebellions against their lawful King and his just Power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of Gods wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</p>

<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses had been brought forth from any well-affected person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said horses has been taken, that they shall <!--??-->mere and stent themselves equally, for bearing equal burden, and <reg orig="refound">refund</reg> the persons from whom any horses has been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of horses now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries, forth of <pb n="6" />every thousand pound of Rent: And the proportion of Foot, every third man; and what <em>Dragoons</em> are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one <em>Dragoon</em>. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes, where no Burghs are, the Provost and Bailies of Burghs to proclaim this at the <reg orig="Merkat">Market</reg> <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as they will answer the contrary upon their highest peril. Given under our hand the first of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p>

<p><i>Sic subscribitur Glencarne.</i></p>

<head level="3">God save King <em>Charles</em> the second.</head>

<head level="3"><i><em>Colonel <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Letter of the routing of the Highlanders in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>I marched out of Aberdeen on Wednesday last with 5 Companies of Col. <em><reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg></em>, three of the late Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg></em>, four Troops of Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> horse, and two of Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em>, and the party that came from the <em>Merns</em> and <em>Angus</em>, with three Troops of my own <em>Dragoons</em>. And upon Thursday about two <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> we came to the <em><reg orig="Lough">Loch</reg></em> at the head of <em>Cromar</em>, where <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> where after a <reg orig="littls">little</reg> dispute we totally routed their Army, but being so near the Hills we could do no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> take and kill about 140, having pursued them seven miles into the Hills, their General hardly escaping with about <reg orig="fourty">forty</reg> horse. All the rest being quite dispersed, Maj. <em>Knight</em> came up even when we were going to engage; we are now upon our march towards their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Kildrumy</em>, which we hope to give you a good account of, I shall give you the particulars in my next: no more but that I am</p>

<p><i>Lowrie, 10 Febru. 1653 at 6. in the morning.</i></p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> humble Servant, <em>Tho. Morgan.</em></i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>His Excellency the Lord Whitlock having <reg orig="recceived">received</reg> plenipotentiary power to treat with her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, hath had several times audience, and upon insisting of all the Articles in general, there appeared nothing so difficult, which did not find an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> interpretation. And it is supposed after Time hath ripened the Debates, we shall receive an Answer by messengers, with glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> and Olive Branches: For the change of the Government in England, being arrived at the Swedish Court, her Majesty hath declared a great willingness to receive the new Credentials; so great an affection doth this bright Star of Europe bear to his Highness the Lord Protector, that (if our Intelligence hath received the truth) she hath desired to see his picture, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> the picture of the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>; the Spark and glory of these Times.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding, the Letters from Swedeland to Holland do affirm, that our Ambassador having had several Audiences, and his <reg orig="perswading">persuading</reg> the Queen to an Amity; that her Majesty hath <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> very little inclination thereunto, and hath commanded her subjects to give her a List of all the losses sustained by the English. <i><unclear>'Tis</unclear> something strange: therefore pick English out of the precedent <unclear>passage</unclear>.</i></p>

<p>The Ambassadors from the states of Holland are landed, with full power to conclude a peace. They are expected this day at <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, with all their gallant Retinue, consisting of one hundred in number, most excellently equipped; and divers eminent Gentlemen, and Officers are appointed to congratulate them from Gravesend to Westminster with the States Barges and others, there being high and honourable preparations at Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg> house in the Palace yard.</p>

<p>The King of Scots is recovered of his late sickness; and his brother <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> is as merry as a Prince; but many of the Royal party goes with empty pockets (sometimes) as well as the Intelligencer: Alas poor <reg orig="Soules">Souls</reg> ! 'tis the chance of War: Therefore, patience in adversity is a jewel worthy of acceptation in the deplorable <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Necessity. The little Queen is <reg orig="fill'd">filled</reg> with abundance of private and solid meditations; add<!--sic. Typo for "and"??--> on <reg orig="Ashwednesday">Ash Wednesday</reg> last she took her Ashes from the hand of Mr. Philips, who was sometimes her Confessor in England. Well! seeing it is so, I shall wind up all in this infallible <reg orig="Bottome">Bottom</reg>, <i><reg orig="Every one">Every one</reg> <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> their Beginning; but no man <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> his ending.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>