<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell174">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 174</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer.</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING,</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> now on foot in <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and other parts of <em>Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these Particulars, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Proclamation for Peace, agreed upon by the States of England &amp; Holland the <reg orig="Prophesie">Prophecy</reg> of Mr. William <unclear>Lillie</unclear> concerning the great and <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> Changes, and Revolutions of the Times; his observations touching the Government, and his Predictions to all Europe, denoting and setting forth the time and manner of the Turn of Times, and the great things that shall happen <unclear>thereupon</unclear>, worthy of diligent perusal. The new Design of the English and Dutch fleets, the rising of the French, and standing upon their own Guard all along the Coast of Brittany, the taking of the field by the King; the Proclamation of the Hollanders; and a <reg orig="TRAGIDY">TRAGEDY</reg> performed in the presence of Charles, James, and Henry, first, second and third sons, to the late King of Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>From <em>Wednesday</em> April <em>the</em> 12. to <em>Wednesday</em> April <em>the</em> 19.</i></head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Robert Wood, for information of the People.</em></head>
<hr />

<p>Great and <reg orig="Wonderfull">Wonderful</reg> Apparitions have been lately seen in the Firmament in many places; and such strange and unusual Objects, that they have even caused as much admiration, as affluence of people; for certain it is, that there has <reg orig="appear'd">appeared</reg> obvious, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Warlike Horse, but <unclear>armed</unclear> men also, with presageth a Turn of times, and sundry Mutations and Revolutions, amongst Christian Princes: Alas! Innumerable of these dreadful <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> have be discerned here in <em>England</em>; as the raining of blood in the year 1653 &amp;c. But of these <em>Revolutions</em>, more anon.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>From <em>Ireland</em> we have received intelligence, that there is scarce any thing wanting in that <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> but people to manure the <em>ground</em>, and a good conference to hold forth their infallible practices, which indeed has been too much eclipsed in these our <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The plague is well <reg orig="appeas'd">appeased</reg> in many parts; yet notwithstanding the pestilence rageth too too much amongst many: From which, <i>Good Lord deliver us</i>.</p>

<p>From <em>Minhead</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the <em>Brest</em> men of war do much harm in that channel, having of late taken several Vessels, whereof some of considerable value which belonged to <em>Bristol</em>: others, of no great esteem, yet too good to be lost. Nay, they are grown to such a height, that they dare presume to come even into the very mouth of <em>Severn</em> where they beat us with our own Weapons, by employing our own Vessels against Us.</p>

<p>The last Post from <em>Rochel</em> in <em>France</em> <reg orig="advertizeth">advertiseth</reg>, That the Report of the conclusion of the Treaty between <em>England</em>, and the <em>United Provinces</em>, and that nevertheless there was a mighty Fleet ready to go to Sea, riding <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Portsmouth</em>, the same hath given a strong <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg> along the Coast of <em>Brittany</em>, in these parts, as far as the River of <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> each Governor and Commander of Castles standing much upon their guards, and not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> so, but they have likewise sent letters to the Court, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to demand assistance, but also to know his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure therein.</p>

<p>The Governor of the castle of <em>Falkenstein</em> having in a most <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> manner plundered a <reg orig="Ministers">Minister's</reg> house, turned him and his Family out of doors; but it so moved the <reg orig="Countreyes">Countries</reg> adjacent, that watching their opportunity when one half of the Garrison was absent, resolved to make a retaliation thereof and most unanimously as one man) marched up to the Walls, assaulted the Defendants, and as many as were found in opposition were all put to the sword, and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> (for his cruelty) let blood in the Neck <reg orig="vain">vein</reg>, and so he departed this life.</p>

<p>The States of <em>Holland</em> have sent an express to the King of <em>Denmark</em> to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> him that agreement they have made with <em>England</em> concerning that Kingdom and begin to cease their warlike preparations <unclear>all</unclear> generally being very willing to embrace <em>Peace</em>.</p>

<p>The last Letters from <em>Germany</em> <reg orig="advertize">advertise</reg>, That the new Levies are <pb n="2" />almost finished, and that great is the expectation of the <reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg> playing a new Game with certain Christian Princes. They have reinforced the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <unclear><em>Casal</em></unclear>, and the Dukes of <em>Florence</em>, <em>Parma</em> and <em>Modena</em> are also raising of divers <em>Military forces</em>.</p>

<p>But what their Design is, we cannot as yet give you an Account of; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, that there is a bloody war to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on vigorously this Summer. Indeed, all <em>Europe</em> seems to be in a Chaos of confusion; and nothing but war and <reg orig="Rumors">Rumours</reg> of war throughout most of the <em>Christian Territories</em>: The Vice-King of <em>Naples</em> threatens destruction to <em>Catalonia</em>, and the King of <em>Spain</em> is determined to take field suddenly. The Prince of <em>Conde</em> begins to move, and has received new Instructions from the Council of <em>Spain</em>, which has given so great an <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> to the King of <em>France</em>, that no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> fifty thousand <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> and foot are designed to impede their march, and Gen. <unclear><em>Thurone</em></unclear> is to advance forthwith into <em>Picardy</em>, and take a view of the <unclear>Army</unclear>, and to set it in a posture fit for a march: he has received Commission from his Master King <em>Lewis</em> as chief Generalissimo, and his Majesty and the great Court Favourite Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, are both resolved to honour him with their own persons in the field, and to take a view of all the <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> Towns and Castles.</p>

<p>The French Letters <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty hath sent to the little Queen, the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and the rest of her children, to desire them to remove out of his Territories, for that the English were resolved to send an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> reciprocally into <em>France</em>, and that their pensions should be paid to them where they should please to point to have it paid; whereupon they are making preparations for their departure out of <em>Paris</em>, the Queen goes to <reg orig="dwel">dwell</reg> at <em>Angers</em>, and <em>Charles Stuart</em> with his brothers and Prince <em>Rupert</em>, are bound for <em>Chantilly</em>, and they have had serious consultations whether they should bend their course from thence to <em>Scotland</em>, or rather to <em>Germany</em>; the latter being supposed to be the safest way to keep their heads on their shoulders.</p>

<p>There are some Merchants have received Letters from Holland, that the States of the United Provinces have signed and ratified the Instrument of Peace, and the Messengers are upon their return with it, for his Highness the Lord Protector to do the like. And it is supposed that on Thursday next being the 20 of this instant, <em>Peace</em> will be generally proclaimed throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Mr <em><reg orig="Lillies">Lillie's</reg></em> <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg>, concerning the Change of Government.</i></head>

<p>As the <em>Genius</em> of <em>England</em> <reg orig="sores">soars</reg> high, so great will the Changes and Mutations be. The Scottish Nation naturally unquiet; and about the year 1657, or 1658 the <em>Hollander</em> is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg>, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in relation to that He hath in the East Indies, but more properly to the West Indies, or Sea voyages to both places; and indeed some miraculous Changes will be about the Years 1660 1661, and will manifest themselves in the <em>West Indies</em>, but especially in the <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, where the Pole is not more elevated <reg orig="then">than</reg> 24, and no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 12 or 14.</p>

<p><em>Zealand</em> and <em>Holland</em>, and the rest of the United Provinces, especially <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <unclear>he Brul</unclear>, and the Texel, or that part of the Province which <reg orig="lyeth">lieth</reg> North East from Yarmouth; part of Flanders, much of France bordering on the South or <reg orig="South-Eeast">South-East</reg> of England, is lamentably to suffer. The Hollanders by decay of Trade, Divisions, Tumults, mortality of people, <reg orig="irruptions">eruptions</reg> of Sea Banks, and without a present amendment, a Foreigner shall enter into the Hague, Amsterdam, and other places before 1672.</p>

<p>France shall suffer by Famine, Pestilence, and the Sword: the Southern and South-East parts of Spain will be many Sea-fights <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Gulf of Venice, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to the Isle of Candia, or the Mediterranean sea; and wonderful Seditions and Risings in that part of Greece <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Archipelago: as also, some very high Rebellion against the Ottoman Family, in the lesser Asia, or <reg orig="Natolia">Anatolia</reg>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Lilly">Lily</reg> will again <reg orig="blossome">blossom</reg> to the Northern Counties, if they do not destroy it with the <unclear>Sectarian Contentions</unclear> of the Times; for it will grow to be a very <unclear>flourishing</unclear> or great Tree among you: but if you <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to contend, dispute, and <unclear><!--whole word--></unclear>, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to know the true God, and the glorious Prince of Peace, the <unclear><!--whole word--></unclear> and influence will pass over you, and touch but some few; and then afterwards you will be forced to stretch water from strangers for the thirst of your <unclear><reg orig="soules">souls</reg></unclear>.</p>

<p>Yes through civil Wars, devastations of <reg orig="Countreyes">Countries</reg>, levelling of Cities, Mutations of the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and Customs of Nations and <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall intervene; as also Rebellions, Famine and Plagues, deposing Kings, and murdering or <reg orig="poysoning">poisoning</reg> of Popes, and <reg orig="over throwing">overthrowing</reg> many in great places of Authority: yet all these put together, shall but make way for the <reg orig="glorius">glorious</reg> <unclear><reg orig="Lampes">Lamps</reg></unclear> of the Son, who within these 20 years next succeeding shall either wholly, or in part, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> themselves in Europe: so that after many sad years, a Chair of rest is promised unto Us: yea, a firm peace, and all earthly <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>, according to the appearing of a Comet with the South Latitude: from whence I infer, that a man, a Prince, or men appear in Europe under the notion of</p>

<head level="2">Pure Honesty,</head>

<pb n="4" />

<p>or born of a mean Progeny, or Progenies: or with small or no forces, or with much Humility at first cloud his or their <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>, or begin to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself, or themselves, at first with much humanity and Religion: but afterwards when mounted to the top of the <reg orig="pinacle">pinnacle</reg> of Greatness and preferment, then like a furious Jehu he shall march through the most parts of Europe with an invincible Army; and in every Nation where he comes, with the assistance of Clubs, <em>viz.</em> Common-people; and if his Army pervert, destroy or change the King, Prince, Magistrate, or Authority then ruling, or having then dominion, then shall He level Mountains, and settle Europe in peace; and be an occasion likewise to settle an Uniformity in Religion, and shall cut off the Hydra heads of Heresies and strange Opinions amongst the Clergy and others, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> he shall restore the loss or forfeited <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> of Nations and people; and in his Banners these words shall be engraven,</p> 

<head level="2">Fear GOD,</head>
<head level="2">Obey KING JESUS,</head>
<head level="2">Submit to the TRUTH,</head>
<head level="2">And do violence to no MAN.</head>

<p>The Kingdom of France shall be subdued, and wholly conquered by this man, though Italy will endeavour to support the French wheat they can, we in England shall most certainly know when these things are <reg orig="neer">near</reg> at hand, by observing when France is subdued; for then again we English shall enter upon the Stage of Providence, our <unclear><!--entire word--></unclear> being next; and our danger then approaching, and till then we shall have a position of inland peace and <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>.</p>

<p>Take here the copy of a Letter from Scotland. SIR, The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> will inform you what kind of task the Horse <unclear>are put</unclear> upon in these parts, to <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg> the Revels and Mossers, who daily gather and are as often <unclear><!--entire word--></unclear>. Besides what was done by Major General <reg orig="Harisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, commanded by <unclear>Cornet Kennet</unclear>, coming from <reg orig="Dunfriez">Dumfries</reg>, with some <unclear><!--whole word, starts in S--></unclear>which they had collected, were set upon by 40 of the Enemy, received their charge, and then charged through the Rebels, routed them, killed 4 on the place, took 6 whereof 3 mortally wounded, and had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 4 of his party wounded. <unclear>Lieu.</unclear> Hickman with another party fell upon 60 of the Enemy under the command of Captain Camphel, took 6 above 20 horse: Captain Camphel was shot in the back, his horse taken, but he himself escaped amongst the <unclear>Walaas</unclear> and bogs.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>Three English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships returning very richly laden from <em>Smyrna</em>, were set upon by three French men of War near <em>Cape Spartiverto</em>, and after a cruel and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Fight between them, they took one of the English, stranded another, and the third being nimble in sailing, escaped away by <em>Messina</em>. Also on the 25 of the last Month, a Mountain called <em>Vesure</em> in <em>Naples</em>, began to cast forth fire and ashes, to the great astonishment of thousands of people, who ran into the Churches, and caused the <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> to be runs, to give warning thereof to all the Country about.</p>

<p>Since the Prince of <em>Conti's</em> coming in to the King, and taking the <em>Oath of <reg orig="Allegeance">Allegiance</reg></em>, his Majesty hath created him Vice King of <em>Naples</em>; and a very sumptuous and admirable Equipage is making ready for solemnizing the Journey.</p>

<p>The 14 instant, was acted at the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em> the stately Italian <em>Comedy</em>, called, the Nuptials of <em>Peleus</em> and <unclear><em>Theiss</em></unclear>, being a thing of incomparable invention, and no less costly. There was a mighty affluence of people, amongst the rest, came the disconsolate Queen, her three Sons, <em>Charles, James</em>, and <em>Henry</em>, and the Princess her Daughter.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> doth still remain at <em>Antwerp</em> close prisoner, and there is a strong Report that he is to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> prisoner into <em>Spain</em>, which is <em>malum omen</em>, for the obtaining that liberty which he was promised, when he was apprehended. <i>Ha! ha! This is as like to prove as bad to him, as is already the disposing of all his estate that hath already been found in that estate.</i></p>

<p>The 14 instant, his highness came to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, where He dined with many of the Lords of his Council; their Reception was performed magnificently; and a great affluence of People; but many returned unsatisfied, be reason that a guard of <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> were put upon duty, upon the solemnizing of the Feast.</p>

<p>It is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em> is to have the <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> of a <em>Habeas Corpus</em> at the Return of the next Term; and 'tis hoped his <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> will suddenly follow. The same measure I could wish might be meted to <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> under restraint.</p>

<p>By Letters further from <em>Holland</em> it is certified, That the States have fully ratified the Agreement for Peace with great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> and alacrity of Spirit, and that they have sent a Return of the Instrument to his highness the Lord Protector; insomuch, that 'tis given out, that the Articles are to be proclaimed on Thursday next.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>All which particulars, appears to be evident; for that the English Fleet hath weighed anchor from S. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em> Point, and now rides with their white Flags and Streamers in Stokes Bay. A great part of the Fleet are designed for a new Expedition, and some are ready to hoist <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> for the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>, and other places.</p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, that on the first instant General <em>Middleton</em> had a general <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Skiibo</em> in <em>Southerland</em>; and after the receipt of Orders from this experienced Generalissimo, part of the Army marched for the South Highlands, the rest were to continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. Commissions are gone forth in the Name of their Master <em>Charles</em>, to <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> the Army.</p>

<p>And so proportionably in every county where they have command. The Lord <em>Seaford</em>, and <em>Mackoldwie</em> are suddenly expected with their Levies also, which are not a few; and this Son of <em>Mars</em> Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> gives out, that he hath brought great store of Spanish Gold, lent by his Master the Emperor, from whom is expected a great Loan &amp; many men, with plenty of the Lord knows what, which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother-in-law, which he had <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends, for his often failing in his promised coming amongst them. Sometimes they make desperate incursions, but pay often for their bold attempts. Nay, this is not all, but 'tis said they have more Arms and Ammunition landed. Of which more in due time.</p>

<p>In the interim, true it is, that many horse and foot are expediting down, and Lieu. Col. <em>Mitchil</em> is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> with 9 Companies of Foot, six Troops of Horse, and a gallant party of resolute Dragoons, which are to march tomorrow to <unclear><em>Braben</em></unclear>; to which are added 4 Troops of horse and 3 companies of foot, all which, are to keep a pass at Dinghil, and to engage the enemy, if possible.</p>

<p>The next thing that we shall present, is, the motion of the grand Wheels in <em>Sweden</em>, <reg orig="betweend">between</reg> her Royal Majesty Queen <em>Christiana</em>, and his Excellency the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>; whose industrious Negotiation has received a candid <unclear>occupation</unclear>; for indeed the Queen has so great an affection for <em>England</em>, and in particular to His Highness the Lord Protector, that she is very inclinable to make up this <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> before she acquits the Government, which will be a <pb n="7" />very fair and specious conclusion of her Reign, that she has gained to Sweden so considerable an <reg orig="Allie">Ally</reg> as the State of <em>England</em>. </p>

<p>The German Princes are more and more astonished at the immediate Transactions between the two <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg> of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, and threaten an incursion upon the United Provinces with fire and sword. But the States General have set forth a <em>Placact</em>, or <em>Proclamation</em>, commanding all <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> whatsoever to repair to their respective colours, <i>upon pain of death</i>; and that every Colonel do repair forthwith to their respective Duties.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Regiments belonging to the Netherlands.</i></head>

<!-- list laid out as two columns-->
<p>The Lord <em>Brederode's</em>, Lieut. General.</p>
<p>Count <em>William</em> of <em>Nassaw</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Craven</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Goring</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Legg</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Welch</em>,</p>
<p>And about 18 other Regiments of Horse and foot.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, That Gen. Monk is arrived, and hath dispatched an Express to the Commander in chief colonel <em>Robert Lilburn</em>, and tot he rest of the Officers, for a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Council, whereby they may debate and <unclear>terminate</unclear> on such things as may prove most <unclear>feasible</unclear> for carrying on so great a Work, wherein the safety and welfare of the three Nations doth chiefly depend. We expect sudden action, for the English are now <reg orig="imbodied">embodied</reg>, and there is <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> skirmishing betwixt the flying parties in the remote parts. Indeed, we have a sturdy enemy to deal <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and men of desperate fortunes, <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather to expose themselves to the hazard of the field, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to purchase captivity by a timorous Spirit.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, we hear, that there is an Act of Oblivion to come forth (<i>sure I am, 'tis not yet out</i>) by his Highness, and he council, acquitting all person whatsoever now in <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> of their several <unclear>Acts</unclear> and crimes, in case they shall come in and submit.</p>

<p>The 5 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of new Dutch ships, never yet at sea, will now soon be ready to spread their <reg orig="canvass">canvass</reg> upon <reg orig="Neptunes">Neptune's</reg> Dominion, and the English are most excellent well equipped for some gallant Design, <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> expecting when they shall <em>attempt</em> the same. <i>Beware the Turk and Pope!</i></p>

<p><i>The Proclamation for peace is now in the <em>Press</em>, and will suddenly be proclaimed.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>