<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ModIntell165">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Moderate Intelligencer, Issue 165</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Moderate Intelligencer,</head>
<head level="2">COMPRISING</head>

<head level="2">The several proceedings of State Affairs, in England, Scotland, and Ireland: With the Affairs and Designs now on foot <em>Holland, Denmark, France, Sweden</em> and <em>other parts of Europe</em>.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <em>Particulars</em>, viz.</head>

<p><i>The Declaration and Message of Mr. Feak, and Mr. Simpson, <unclear>sent</unclear> to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Remonstrance of Mr. <unclear>Rogers</unclear> touching the present proceedings and Occurrences of the times; together with a Declaration of the People touching the relieving of the oppressed and delivering the Captive. With a Narrative touching the further proceedings between England and Holland, the putting forth of Gen. Blake to sea with fourscore and eight gallant man of war, and the going of the <em>Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em>, the <em>Resolution</em>, the <em>James</em>, and the <em>George with above 500 pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>, Arms and Ammunition after them</em>. Likewise the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> Letter to the states of <em>Holland</em> And their Answer thereunto. With his Message to the K. of <em>Denmark</em>, And his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Resolution thereupon.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3">From Wednesday Feb. 16. to Wednesday Feb. 22. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton, for information of the People.</em></head>

<p>Having a fair and noble way of Administration provided, under which men may live in a plenary enjoyment of their Liberty as Christians, and their Rights as Men; we do not, <unclear>neither<!--could be "never"--></unclear> can we in any measure doubt but that we shall <reg orig="finde">find</reg> a ready and cheerful concurrence from all sober persons; and have ground chiefly to expect it from all the people of God, though of different judgments, seeing equal Liberty is given to them all (without just offence to any) and the principal care is for preventing true Religion, and the countenance of its Professors. We, for our parts, have done <pb n="1" />our duty, in declaring the grounds of our judgment. For, when we look back upon what is done, we find nothing that stares in our faces; and if there could have been imagined any better way of Settlement, we should have <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg> it with the same spirit of submission. But here we see, our Friends have taken in the good of all the three sorts of Government, and bound them all in one. If War be, here is the Unitive <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> (but nothing else) of Monarchy to encounter it; and here is the admirable Counsel of <reg orig="Aristocracie">Aristocracy</reg> to manage it: If Peace be, here is the industry and courage of <reg orig="Democracie">Democracy</reg> to improve it. And whereas in the present Constitution, the Legislative and Executive Powers are separated: the former being vested in a constant succession of Parliaments elective by the people; the latter in an elective Lord Protector, and his Successors, assisted by a Council; we conceive the State of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> is thereby reduced to so just a <unclear>ten <!-- one word --></unclear> the Ills either of <reg orig="seccessive">successive</reg> Parliaments <unclear>furnished <!-- one word --></unclear> power both of executing and making Laws, or of a perpetual Parliament (which are <unclear>Division, Faction and Confusion)</unclear> being avoided on the one side, and the inconveniences of absolute Lordly power on the other; the frame of government appears so well bounded on both sides against Anarchy and Tyranny, that we hope it may now (through the blessing of God) prove a seasonable Mean (as for the better defending of these Dominions against Enemies abroad, and promoting our interest in foreign parts, so also) of peace and settlement to this distracted Nation; and be <pb n="2" />of a durable continuance to succeeding Ages, for the glory of the most high GOD, the advancement of his gospel, the protection of this people, and the benefit of Posterity.</p>

<p>From Holland it is further certified, that the United Provinces have brought in their Ratification onto the Articles for Peace, and that they have both signed and sealed ingeneral; and are preparing of an Ambassador to be sent unto his Highness the Lord Protector, for the confirming thereof: It is said the Lord Updam is the man elected: But of this, more in my next.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Judges appointed for the several Circuits in <em>England</em>, for this winter Assizes.</i></head>

<p>1. For the Western Circuit, The Lord Chief Justice <em>Roll</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Serjeant</reg> <em>Glyn</em>. 2 For <em>Berks, Oxford</em>, &amp;c. Lord Chief <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>St. John</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Atkins</em> 3 For <em>Sussex, Kent, &amp;c.</em> Mr <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Ask</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Peapis</em>. 5 For <em>Bucks, &amp;c.</em> Mr Baron <em>Nicholas</em>, and Mr. <em><reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> Conyers</em>. 6 For the Northern Circuit, Mr. <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Hayle</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Windham</em>. </p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Assizes held by the Judges this winder in the several Counties, in their Circuits.</i></head>

<head level="3">1 <i>For the Western Circuit.</i></head>

<p>1 For <em>Hampshire</em>: <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 27 <em>Febr.</em> at the Castle at <em>Winchester</em>. 2 <em>Wiltshire</em>, Wednesday 1 <em>March</em> at <em>New Sarum</em>, 3 <em>Dorsetshire</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> <em>6 March</em> at <em>Dorchester</em>. 4 <em><reg orig="Summersetshire">Somersetshire</reg></em>, Wednes. 8 <em>March</em> at <em>Chard</em>. City of Exeter, 13 March. <em>Devonshire</em> the same day, at the Goal <!--Gaol?--> Garden near the City of Exeter. <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, 20 <em>March</em> at <em>Launceston</em>.</p>

<head level="3">2 <i>for the Circuit of <em>Berkshire, &amp;c.</em></i></head>

<p>For <em>Berkshire</em>, 28 <em>Febr.</em> at <em><reg orig="Redding">Reading</reg></em>. <em>Oxfordsh.</em> 3 March at <em>Oxford</em>. <em><reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg></em>, 8 <em>March</em> at <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, &amp;c. <em><reg orig="Stafford shire">Staffordshire</reg></em> 24 <em>March</em> at <em>Stafford</em>, 25 at <em>Lichfield</em>. <em>Worcestersh</em>. 29 <em>March</em> at <em>Worcester</em>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>The King of Scots is now going for Germany: from whence our Scout bringeth intelligence, that the Emperor is coming down by land against the Hollander, requiring restitution for several injuries by them committed.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>Ma. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> is gone for the North of Scotland with about two hundred Cavaliers, he was transported by 7 ships from Holland, and <reg orig="caryed">carried</reg> some Arms and Ammunition. Ha, ha, ha! I smell a Rat: pick <reg orig="Duch">Dutch</reg> spregne out of that.</p>

<p>His highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council have set forth an Ordinance of explanation touching Treason; a Copy whereof followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance declaring that the offences therein mentioned, and no other, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be adjudged high treason within the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland</i>, it is amongst other things ordained and established, that no matter, fact, crime, or offence whatsoever, other than such as are therein mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken or adjudged to be <reg orig="high-treason">high treason</reg>; And whereas some doubts and questions may arise, whether that clause in the said Ordinance doth not extend to the offences mentioned in the Instrument, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, The Government of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and which are thereby declared to be high Treason; For clearing thereof, and removing all scruples thereupon, his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his Council, doth declare and ordain, that neither the said Ordinance, nor any clause or thing therein contained, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> extend or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend unto all or any f the offences declared by the said Instrument to be high treason, but that all and every the said Offences are hereby adjudged to be high treason, and that all and every the <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> shall suffer the penalties of <reg orig="High-treason">High treason</reg>, the said Ordinance, or any thing therein contained to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p><i>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has appointed certain <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> every week to receive Reports from the Masters of Requests of Petitions presented to them, and to give Answers.</p>

<p>the Highlanders grow numerous in Scotland; and the Tories are too potent in Ireland. they have had several <reg orig="Randevouzes">Rendezvouses</reg>; and sundry times made incursions upon the Lowlanders. But care is taken to prevent the like for the future, if we can. The King of Scots has sent Letters to them, promising aid and assistance. But alas! fair words butter no Parsnips.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>Since which time, we have received intelligence, that young <em>Charles</em> hath sent a message unto the States of Holland, desiring the transportation of some horse and foot raised for this service; but the States returned Answer, that in this juncture of time with England, they neither could nor durst expose their shipping to any other service, but what might redound to the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> good of the United Provinces: Whereupon a Dispatch was made to the King of Denmark, imploring <reg orig="Ayd">Aid</reg> and Assistance from thence: but alas! the emergent and weighty Affairs of that Kingdom being so great, his Majesty can no <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> possible answer his expectation. For we have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> taken certain Prizes from the Dane, but some likewise from France &amp; Holland, notwithstanding the present Overtures for peace from the Netherlands; which cannot be (as yet) <reg orig="avoyded">avoided</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the expected Ambassadors are come over, to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> their Articles, and to confirm and establish a perfect peace, and a firm League and Union; Which Ambassadors are expected within few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, if they do no (as formerly they have one) derogate from anything that hath been formerly agreed on. But if they prove so apostate, then let England judge things rightly, and take heed how they make Leagues and Union with such a people: how they forbear to mind what the <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> of Providence <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> to them, or neglect to take the opportunities that such a signal hand of God (as hath lately appeared) hath put before them, to secure themselves, do justice to their people, and maintain the Reputation of that Cause amongst them, which God hath written his name upon both at Sea and Land, in such <reg orig="unparallel'd">unparalleled</reg> and glorious Characters. And let every man take heed how he seeks to bind the Hand of God, when he is shaking his Rod over a people, especially when they have upon them the symptoms of Displeasure; and how they stand in the way of <reg orig="Gods">Gods</reg> Design in the World, and how they express more tenderness to such a people, <reg orig="then">then</reg> to the security, Blood, and Right of their <reg orig="Countrey-men">Countrymen</reg>, and the Will of God, which We ought to pray is done in earth as it is in Heaven. For when the Lord is moved from his Throne, to do his great work in the world, in routing Antichrist, making of his name glorious, in relieving the oppressed, delivering the Captive, and throwing down the unrighteous powers on Earth.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>The most exact and perfect relation of the great Plot and bloody Conspiracy of divers Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, and Citizens, against his Highness the Lord Protector, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>On Tuesday last, being the 13 of this instant Feb. a company of Gentlemen met at Mr. Amps at the Ship-Tavern in the <reg orig="Old-Bayley">Old Bailey</reg>, and being drinking two pair of stairs high, and having called for as much Sack as came to eight shillings and six pence, before they had put a period to their quaffing Glasses, in came Lieu. colonel Woosley, and divers other Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> (having notice of their Design and Meeting by one of the four appointed to receive instructions from the King of Scots) with their Swords and Pistols <reg orig="cockt">cocked</reg>, and went immediately <reg orig="up staires">upstairs</reg>, where they demanded the Names of the Person, their Residence, and their present business; which they answered: But it being not <em>satisfactory</em>: the Officers told them, they has an Order form his Highness to apprehend them, and commit them to custody, during the pleasure of his Highness: Whereupon the <em>Drawers</em> were all called up, and examined, <i>Whether or no, they knew those Gentlemen</i>, they answered, <i>They knew not one face there, except M. <em>Dutton's</em>.</i> Whereupon they secured them all, and conducted them to <em><reg orig="Iames's">James's</reg></em>, upon the <em>Ordinance</em> for <em>Treason</em>, for contriving and conspiring against his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector. And <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, took away Mr. <em>Amps</em> the Master of the house; but upon examination, he was acquitted. And upon Thursday last they were all brought to their <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> before the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, where <reg orig="som">some</reg> of them confessed, and laid open the whole Design: the manner whereof was as followeth: 1 That an Oath of <reg orig="Secresid">Secrecy</reg> should be given to all to whom it should be revealed, which accordingly was done; and none was made privy to any thing of it, before he first took the Oath. 2 That the design should be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on in the management thereof, by such as should be faithful friends to their King. 3 That so many persons should be engaged for Officers to an Army, as should undertake for the private lifting of 30000 men to be ready to rise at a time appointed. 4. That at the said time wherein they should so rise, that they should fall on to act what was designed in all the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties, and parts of England at once. 5 That one party should fall <pb n="6" />at that time the Lord Protector, to murder him and his Life-guard, and those Officers and others that should be about him: And they had two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> debate, whether they should fall upon his Highness at that time when he dined in the city of London, and murder him, and those him with then; but it was resolved in the Negative, because <em>Ch. Stuart</em> was not in England, nor their forces ready in other parts of England. 6 That at the same time another party <reg orig="shold">should</reg> have seized on the Council at Whitehall, and have murdered them and their Attendants. 7 That the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at <reg orig="Iameses">James's</reg> should be also at the same time seized on, and the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> surprised in their quarters there, and at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and all put to the sword that opposed. 8 That a strong party <reg orig="shold">should</reg> at the same time <reg orig="seiz">seize</reg> upon the Lieutenant of the Tower, the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, take possession, and let out the prisoners. 9 That at this time their King should be ready private in a place of the city of London, and be brought forth, and presently crowned, and proclaimed King, and have the Government put into their hands by them, and all that should oppose, to <reg orig="dye">die</reg> without mercy. 10 That at the same time parties should <reg orig="seiz">seize</reg> upon all the several Guards and <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> in England. 11 That Proclamations should have been sent out to all parts of England, that <em>Ch. Stuart</em> was crowned King, and received into the city, offering pardon unto all that would come in, and comply with them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A list of the names of those that were examined and sent to the Tower.</i></head>

<!-- List laid out as two columns -->
<p>M. <em>Dutton</em>,</p>
<p>Captain <em>Smith</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em><reg orig="Ienkins">Jenkins</reg></em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Sawyer</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Archer</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Parker</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Bunch</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Lee</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Ross</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Cotes</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Middleton</em>,</p>
<p>M. <em>Watkins</em>,</p>

<p>Since which time, divers are apprehended by Warrant form the Lord Mayor, and committed to Newgate.</p>

<p>The English fleet rides still about St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> Point; but the Dutch are not yet forth. There has been a great <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> upon the Coast of France, and divers men drowned. The English fleet from the Straits, Spain, Portugal, and <unclear>Biscain</unclear>, are come safe into the River of Thames, and several Dutch Prizes also. Ten more are expected every Tide. the last Post from France advertiseth, that King Lewis and his Council have agreed to send an Ambassador Extraordinary <unclear>unto</unclear> his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>The last intelligence from Portsmouth advertizeth, that Gen. <em>Blake</em> <unclear>is put</unclear> forth too sea with fourscore and eight gallant ships; a List of the rest that are suddenly to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth, take as followeth:</p>

<!-- list laid out as two columns -->
<p>The <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>,</p>
<p>The Resolution,</p>
<p>The Rainbow,</p>
<p>The Andrew,</p>
<p>The George,</p>
<p>The James,</p>
<p>The <reg orig="Non such">Nonesuch</reg>,</p>
<p>The Ruby,</p>
<p>The <reg orig="Saphyr">Sapphire</reg>,</p>
<p>The <reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg>,</p>
<p>The Victory,</p>
<p>The Golden Cock,</p>
<p>The Mary,</p>
<p>The Fairfax,</p>
<p>The Assurance,</p>
<p>The Frederick,</p>

<p>From Windsor we have received intelligence, that <em>Mr. Feak</em>, and <em>Mr. Simpson</em> have sent up a Declaration and Letter to his Highness, (by way of Address) wherein they implore their liberty. This, to me, seems something strange: therefore, by my next, I shall make a further enquiry into the truth thereof.</p>

<p>This day came piping hot <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from tower hill, that the King of Scots was landed in the North of Scotland; which to me seems as true as his Residence in London, at the time when the aforesaid Conspirators were apprehended in the <reg orig="Old-Bayley">Old Bailey</reg>.</p>

<p>Major Gen. Harrison is going for Stafford-shire, and intends to betake himself to a private course of life. Alas poor Gentleman! I wish all men would rather expose themselves to the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> <reg orig="Ayr">Air</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be restrained (by their contempt of magistracy) either in a prison or tower: though notwithstanding Mr. Feak, and Mr. Simpson remains still at Windsor Castle; and not long since declared, that they never found more inward comforts, and spiritual solacings, in the time of their freedom, <reg orig="then">than</reg> now do in their tribulation. And Mr. Rogers declares it a part of his duty, as touching his Ministry, to speak concerning the Revolutions and present Occurrences of the times.</p>

<p>From France our Occurrences advertiseth, That the Prince of Conde has taken the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Dinan, and ransacked the famous town for their loyalty to the King and Crown.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>