<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPoet02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Poeticus, Issue 02</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Poeticus:</i></head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Comprizing">Comprising</reg> the sum of all intelligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, and SCOTLAND,</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>

<p>&mdash; <em>Ita vertere Seria</em>{ Horat.de Ar. Poet</p>

<head level="3">Also <reg orig="comprizing">comprising</reg>,</head>

<p><i>The Addresses and Proposals of the Lords the Ambassadors of Holland concerning the confirming of a peace, with the Articles of Agreement; The setting forth of the fiery Crosses, and <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg> <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> fire and sword to all that are disobedient. The great strength of the Tories in Ireland. And the advancing of the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> and five hundred men there. Also the coming in of 50 <reg orig="Colliars">Colliers</reg> with <reg orig="coles">coals</reg>. With the Speech of the Lord <em>Yongstal</em> to his Highness the Lord Protector for a <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> peace betwixt both Nations, and his answer thereunto.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em>, March 1. to <em>Wednesday</em>, March 8. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 1.</head>

<p>This day Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Vavasor Powel</em> made their Addresses to his Highness the Lord Protector for their liberty, some Ministers have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> with them, and adviseth them to be sensible of their mistakes.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 2.</i></head>

<p>By the last Post from the West we received intelligence, that there hath been a most <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> and inhuman Murder committed on Salisbury Plain: The manner thus; Eight or nine Graziers being riding over the Plain, and having about 1500 pounds amongst them, in their portmantles, they were set upon by 18 or 20 <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg>, who demanded their moneys, but being denied it, they fell <reg orig="pel mel">pell-mell</reg> upon the Graziers, and put every man to the sword, as they thought, with the loss of five of their own Hectors; yet is so pleased divine Providence, that one of the Graziers, being not quite deprived of his <reg orig="Sences">Senses</reg>, heard what <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg> they resolved to make to, and a company of Butchers coming by the next morning, fixing their eyes upon this sad object, rode up to them, which the Grazier perceiving, expressed himself, related the manner and told them they were gone to such an Inn at a Village <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Salisbury. Whereupon they left two to convey the said Grazier to a house, and the rest went and raised the Town and beset the Inn where the Thieves were, but the <reg orig="highway men">highwaymen</reg> opposed so <reg orig="farre">far</reg>, that the honest men were constrained to fire the house, and to batter and pull it down over the ears; so that some perished and consumed in the dust and flames, the rest were taken and committed to Salisbury <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>.</p>

<p>This day also we received information by letters from Paris thus: The Cardinal <em>Retz</em> doth still remain a close prisoner, but <reg orig="som">some</reg> means are used by Mediators for his enlargement, by means of a Marriage between the L. <em>Mancini</em>, who is Nephew to Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, one of the Cardinal <em>de <reg orig="Rhetz">Rhetz'</reg></em> Nieces.</p>

<p>By Letters from Lieth thus <i>Since the late rout given to Glencarn and Kenmore <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Aberdeen, we hear that Glencarn is <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those broken Forces<pb n="2" /> which were left, with Athol and Seafort. We hear that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> hath taken the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> Garrison of Kildrummy.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, March 3.</i></head>

<p>An Ambassador from the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> had this day audience, who did congratulate his Highness, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> his Letters of credence confirm the sincerity, as well as the authority of his gratulation.</p>

<p>By Letters from Rome we are advertised, That the Lord <em>Messino</em> the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg>, hath order to go into Spain to negotiate, and hasten the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> peace, according to the Instructions given him by his Holiness, being charged to do the same afterward with his Majesty of <em>France</em>. The Pope hath also by his Letters given charge to the Cardinal of <em>Este</em>, and to that of <em>Trivultio</em>, Protectors of <em>France</em> and of <em>Spain</em>, to contribute their most earnest <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to make the design to take effect, for the advancement of the Romish Religion.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Paris</em> we are advertised, that Mr. <em>Beverling</em> hath a large Commission sent him to treat with <em>England</em>; and that honest <em>Mr: Du-Rantisi</em> is put to death in <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, he was put on the wheel, and his head set on a Pole.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Dalkeith</em>, Feb. 16: we received intelligence, That the party that <em><reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. Col. Cotterel</em> sent from <em>Dunbarton</em> to have seized on the Shallop we lately lost in <em><reg orig="Clide">Clyde</reg></em>, went up into the Highlands into a Lough where it was, but upon their coming she was set on fire by them. Kenmore came privately with a small party into Dunkel presently after the engagement with Col. <em>Morgan</em> from whom I have received no further intelligence as yet.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday March 4.</i></head> 

<p>This day there came to my hands a more fuller account of the taking in of the Garrison of Kildrummy by Col. Morgan, which for your better satisfaction take these ensuing Letters.</p>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>I received <reg orig="yurs">yours</reg>, and <reg orig="finde">find</reg> your propositions very hard without order from my Lord General, Sir, if you will be pleased to suffer me to send one to my Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and upon his return we shall render the <reg orig="Hous">House</reg> if they come not <reg orig="againe">again</reg> <reg orig="munday">Monday</reg> at night for our relief we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> march with our <reg orig="Hors">Horse</reg> and arms to <reg orig="anie">any</reg> part of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> <reg orig="Armie">Army</reg> in Scotland, and withal the place be made <reg orig="useles">useless</reg> for <reg orig="anie">any</reg> <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>: and for the effusion of blood, We take god to Witness, yours <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be the Fault, no more, but</i></p>

<p>Kildrummy Feb. 28.</p>
<p><i>Yours as time <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> serve, <em>Wil Drummond</em>.</i></p><pb n="4" />

<p>SIR,</p> 

<p>I have considered your Answer, and cannot grant your desires, yet so tender am I of shedding of blood in case you be not satisfied with the terms I <reg orig="offred">offered</reg>, if you please to send 1 or 2 Officers fully authorized to treat in order to your sudden surrender, I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> rather deal <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> use cruelty, I expect your answer by this Bearer, and am</p>
<p><i>Yours as occasion shall offer, <em>Tho: Morgan.</em></i></p>
<p><i>For major <em>Drummond</em> Officer in Chief in the House of Kildrummy</i></p>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>I have received yours, and am as loath to shed blood at this time as any shall be; Sir, I thought you would have <reg orig="suffred">suffered</reg> me to have sent to my Lord General, because I being put here by him, and on such a sudden to surrender, I believe no man of Honour, but might esteem me the basest of men, but however for the matter of Treaty, if you please to send <reg orig="downe">down</reg> to the Gate one or two, I shall wait on them there to hear your will; no more but that I am</p> 
<p><i>Yours as before, <em>W: Drummond</em></i></p>

<p><i>For <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> Commander in chief of the English Forces in the North of Scotland.</i></p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March 6.</i></head>

<p>This day we received intelligence, That his Excellency the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> having received plenipotentiary power to treat with her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, hath had several times audience, and upon insisting of all the Articles in general, there appeared nothing so difficult, which did not find an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> interpretation. And it is further supposed, that after time hath ripened the debates and conferences, we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> receive a gracious answer by Messengers, with <reg orig="joyfull">joyful</reg> tidings. For the Change of the Government in <em>England</em>, being arrived at the Swedish Court, her Majesty hath declared a great <reg orig="deale">deal</reg> of willingness to receive the new Credentials.</p>

<p>The Ambassadors from the States of Holland are landed with full power to conclude a peace. They are come to <em>Whitehall</em>, with all their gallant Retinue, most gallantly equipped; and divers eminent Gentlemen and Officers came along with them to congratulate them from Gravesend to Westminster, they were met with six coaches, belonging to his Highness the Lord Protector, and about 20 more <reg orig="drawne">drawn</reg> all with six horses, and after them followed 40 coaches drawn with 4 horses, and about 60 coaches <reg orig="drawne">drawn</reg> with two horses: Many of the last were of the Nobility of England, according as the violence of the late war had disposed of their fortunes. In one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches was the Master of the Ceremonies, who with accustomed complements received the Dutch Ambassadors, and brought them to their lodgings at Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his house in the Palace yard, where they are to be <reg orig="maintaind">maintained</reg> at the charge of the Commonwealth for certain days.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>By Letters from the West we received intelligence of the taking of two of the Brest Men of War, and a Merchant ship by the English.</p>

<p>Our fleet is still plying up and down in the Channel, and many prizes are daily brought in. The fleet greatly increaseth daily by the coming in of other ships, and are in a very good condition.</p>

<p><reg orig="Vpon">Upon</reg> Addresses made to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his council, by the Magistrates of the City of <em>Westminster</em>, in relation to the Government thereof; there have been several Debates, and because the City of <em>London</em> is concerned in it, the said City of <em>London</em> hath had notice of it, that so a dispatch may be made of the whole, to the union and content of both Cities. It was therefore ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, that the chief Magistrates of the City of <em>London</em>, and the City of <em>Westminster</em> should be both sent for, and heard together. The Magistrates of the City of <em>Westminster</em> desire a Corporation, and have long sued for it.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Addresses have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> made to the Lord Protector by <em>William Lenthal</em> Esquire, sometimes Speaker of <em>Parliament, Thomas Pury</em> Esquire, sometimes a Member of <em>Parliament</em>, and divers other Gentlemen from the City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, who in the name, and under the Seal of the said City signed by the Magistrates thereof, hath presented to his Highness a Declaration congratulatory, blessing the Lord for this established Government, and protesting much affection thereto.</p>

<p>It is confirmed by Letters from <em>Scotland</em>, that whilst our horse were in the more <reg orig="Northerne">Northern</reg> parts of that Nation, Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, who is again recovered of his wounds, is marched Southwards, to see what parties he can find <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg>, or what booty he can get at <em>Lenox</em> or <em>Tivisdale</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday March 7.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we received this day intelligence, that the Enemy are divided into divers parties to raise their assigned Levies, and the Earl of <em>Athol</em> having a considerable party of horse and Foot, hath sent forth the fiery Cresses, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> fire and sword to the disobedient.</p>

<p>Several Regiments of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Daniels, is revolted to the enemy, but <reg orig="som">some</reg> of them, we hear, are taken again, and rewarded with a rope. Others of them were tied up to the Gallows at Dunkel, and <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> Law is executed daily upon all those who incur the penalty of the same.</p>

<p>The Tories in Ireland are grown somewhat high, and new distempers are broke forth; but the Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> is safely arrived to put a period to those distractions.</p>

<p>From <em>Yarmouth</em> we are advertised, that the Lord Williamson is landed as Ambassador Extraordinary from the King of Denmark, whose Majesty hath sent a Message to his Highness, making application upon the <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of the Dutch Treaty: And the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors from Holland have presented their Credentials, wherein they desire to include His Majesty. In order whereunto the States of the seven united Provinces do all of them agree and consent to the Agreement of Peace, and the said <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same, desiring a speedy cessation of Arms, and that all acts of hostility may cease on both sides.</p>

<p>Their Lordships are to have audience on Tuesday again, being the seventh of this instant, so that undoubtedly some few circumstances being considered on, all will be concluded, and a firm peace <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>