<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol192">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 192</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> February 9. to <em>Thursday</em> Febr. 16. 1654</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Feb.6</i></head>

<p>The Enemy at their late being Badgenoth, got three men from every four Ploughs in that Country, (except one near the water) but many of them returned back; the Lauhabec men, did plunder much when the Enemy was in Murriland, and then left them: the greatest part of <reg orig="Lelentarnes">Lelentarne's</reg> forces are at Strathspey near the Land of <reg orig="Gyants">Giants</reg>, who will (as is said) keep out his house against them, having taken in men and provisions to that end.</p>

<p>The 28. Instant, about 36 Horse came into the Coast of Gowry, to Sir <em>Peter <reg orig="Hayes">Haye's</reg></em> House called Meginch, they did break his outer Court, and demanded his Horses, threatening to burn his Corn otherwise; but he firing at them, they ran away, but two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after a great party came and burnt about 6001: sterling in Corn: also the Earl of <em><reg orig="Lnihtgowes"><!--Linlithgow?-->Lnihtgowe's</reg></em> <pb n="1" />Corn for not delivering his Horses.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Deal the 9. of February.</i></head>

<p>There hath passed through this Road several ships this week, which came from the Southward, and are all bound for London: there hath been high winds lately, which have made some wrack upon the Coast of France about <reg orig="Callice">Calais</reg>, <reg orig="Bullein">Boulogne</reg> and those parts, among others a Dutchman of War, of good strength, who rid in <reg orig="Calice">Calais</reg> Road, was beaten upon the shore, broken in pieces, many of the men drowned, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a few saved: there are very few ships at present in this Road, this North and Easterly winds having carried them away.</p>

<p>These ships aforementioned are all safely arrived in the River of Thames. Also several prize ships, whereof five <reg orig="Dutches">Dutch</reg> prizes with French wines, one ship with Currants and about ten other Dutch prizes are expected every Tide.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Falmouth 16 thus.</i></head>

<p>Here are still many ships here, who are bound for London and <reg orig="othe">other</reg> parts to the Eastward of this place; all those that were here, being gone some for Ireland, and others for Portugal, Spain and West Indies, we have not heard lately any news from Ireland, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> by way of Barnstable, we hear that the Irish Rebels would again be stirring, and to that end are gathered into small bodies: with the which they have lately done us some mischief, this winter season being very <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> to them, and is a means that those Rogues cannot be <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg> so soon as it is to be wished.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Cows">Cowes</reg>, in the Isle of Wight Feb. 8.</i></head>

<p>Our Fleet doth still ride near St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point. Upon Monday last, there passed by this island near 30 sail ships, which come all from the <reg orig="Strieghts">Straits</reg>, Spain and Portugal, and are for the most part bound for London, as we are informed by a small Vessel, who came along the Channel in their Company, that a private man of War hath brought in two prizes, the one a Dutch ship, of considerable bigness, and the other a French Vessel, which rides between this place and Yarmouth.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>Last week you had a brief account of some passages touching the late entertainment of his Highness in the City. Among which we omitted this that the <em>Lord Mayor</em> was Knighted by his Highness. This following Speech was delivered also by the <em>Recorder</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Mr. <reg orig="Recorders">Recorder's</reg> Speech to the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>May it please your Highness, my Lord Protector, it hath been observed by some, That when <em>Samuel</em> offered Sacrifice, he therefore reserved the Shoulders for <em>Saul</em>, that he might know what was the weight of Government: The consideration of which made <em>Maximilian</em> affirm, that none who knew how heavy Diadems were, would stoop to take them up. <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> are like the heavenly bodies, much in veneration, but never in rest; and how can it be otherwise expected, when they are not made for themselves, or their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> glory, but for the safety and good of <reg orig="mankinde">mankind</reg>? so in the civil world, great things being ordained to serve the less: We see the Sun by its Beams, serving the eye of the meanest <reg orig="Flye">Fly</reg>, as well as of the greatest Potentate. The supremacy of <em>Salus Populi</em>, was the conclusion of the Twelve Tables, and will be a Prevalent <reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the end of the world.</p>

<p>By thus much, My Lord, you may perceive the dark side of this Leading Cloud of Government; but if God vouchsafe assistance from those Shoulders, upon which the Government is laid, and put under his everlasting Arms, you will see the bright side also, and thence Encouragement. This Support he is pleased to give, by letting Rulers know he is the Author of their Power, and that from him they are to expect their Rule. The Designation of government, as to forms and persons, is an humane institution, and mutable, as things that are made; but Government itself, abstractively<!--abstractly--> considered in its pure Original is of a Divine Off-spring, and can with no less difficulty be shaken, <reg orig="then">than</reg> those <reg orig="Vestigias">Vestiges</reg> which being as Relations tell us, upon the tops of some Mountains, above the Clouds, can <pb n="3" />be disordered by wind and Tempest. And for the rule, the word, or reason of God in the Divine understanding, is the Eternal law of all things. But this being too deep a well for <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Bucket to draw out of, it pleased his infinite goodness to let fall a <reg orig="Rivolet">Rivulet</reg> from this Source into the Creature; which leaving an impression in <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> understanding, we call the law of nature: But man having this <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, presently became of no understanding; his mind being clouded with passions and sins, had soon need of superadded helps, which God gave him, by those other laws fit for Government, and still gives a Spirit for the framing of such Municipal Laws, as are according to his Will, and suitable to the good of the people. But when this was done, the best Laws without a Government, were no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> as the Sword behind the Ephod; and therefore <em>Moses</em> in his time, and other <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> in their time, must be as walking Laws and administrators of Justice.</p>

<p>We may conclude, My Lord, Your Highness hath experimented both these encouragements, as being the Spectator of some, and the subject of other great revolutions which have happened in this Age, and Land of Wonders: And not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> know, that the Most High rules in the Kingdom of men, disposing them to whom he pleaseth; but also, that its not sufficient with the Princes of the Nations, to exercise dominion which is the common Image of God, except there be so a share in the peculiar Image of his righteousness and holiness; they being <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> indeed and after a peculiar manner, to whom the reason, or Word of God so comes.</p>

<p>My Lord, There is one help more in Government, which God is pleased often to add to the rest, which is the giving in of the Affections of the People. The solemnity of this day, wherein the Citizens of this great City appear in their several Companies, as so many Cities within the City, speaks much to this; they leave it to other Nations to salute their Rulers and victorious Commanders with the names of <unclear><em>Caesares</em></unclear> and <em>Imperatores</em>; and after triumphs, <pb n="4" />to erect for them their <em>Arcus Triumphales</em>: but if I mistake not, their end, this day, is not any such outward Pomp or Glory, but that those who have been delivered together, might rejoice together; and to express their Desires, That the Civil Sword might be as prosperous for <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Ends, in the Hand where it is placed, as the Military Sword hath been in the same hand.</p>

<p>This City <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> goes alone in <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> Actions: it was anciently called by <em>Stephanides</em>, The Heart of the Nation; and if the Heart be in a <reg orig="Politique">Politic</reg> consideration, as it is in the <reg orig="Naturall">Natural</reg>, it will communicate Life and Spirits into the other Members, by which means the whole Body may unanimously contribute their desires and endeavours to oppose the common Enemy, and after all our Distractions, see the Nation established upon the firm Basis of Peace and Righteousness, which is the end of Government and shall be the end of my further troubling your Highness.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall, Jan. 11. S. N.</i></head>

<p>Our Negotiation hath not as yet made any progress, by reason of the absence of most of the Senate. But now that the Grand Chancellor is come to Town, I suppose we shall in a short time see what their intentions are as to an intimate Alliance with us. The Chancellor speaks very much love and affection to the Commonwealth of England, and since his coming hither he hath performed a visit unto my Lord Ambassador, demonstrating much civility and respect to him. I hope there will be a good account of this affair. <pb n="5" />Her Majesty intends to take a Progress for about a <reg orig="Fornight">Fortnight</reg>, to see the <reg orig="Coppermines">Copper mines</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <unclear>Regensburgh</unclear> the 29 dito, S.N</i></head>

<p>The Estates of the Empire are hitherto come no farther concerning the Capitulation, <em>viz.</em> whether or no the same should be taken in hand <em>in pleno</em>, or <em>per Deputatos</em>; and that in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the point of Justice should be taken in hand. The Introduction of the new Princes is now (on certain conditions) permitted, and will shortly go forward. A Keeper in <em>Silesia</em> who by his own <reg orig="consession">concession</reg> has committed 182 <reg orig="Murthers">Murders</reg> among others; two little Children, whom he affirms to have gotten by his own Sister, whose hearts having cut out, he had devoured, is imprisoned, and will shortly receive his reward.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg> 28 dito S.N.</i></head>

<p>From hence there is little, we being shut up with Ice. The peace in Poland holds, if the ensuing Parliament approves thereof. The King demanded Eighteen Subsides for the defraying of charges, and disbanding of the Army; but <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> supposed the Parliament will not be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> to grant any before they have an account of what hath been raised these two years, which is near 50 Subsides, and yet the Soldiery has wanted their pay, which has caused them much to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and destroy the Country by plundering and taking Free quarter; so that upon the examination <pb n="6" />of these things, there is likely to be great Troubles, the Gentry venting themselves with much eagerness against some <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, and likewise against the Queen herself, charging her with the Transportation of his Treasure, whereby <reg orig="shee">she</reg> hath provided a Bank for <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> and Favourites.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague, February 4 S.N.</i></head>

<p>There is a flying Report in Town, that the English <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> which went to carry Monsieur <em>Beverning</em> back to England, should be cast away and Beverning drowned; but there is no certainty of it; I hope the contrary. This day I saw a Copy of a very sharp Letter from the Emperor to the States, concerning the <reg orig="Restauration">Restoration</reg> of all Goods and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> belonging to the Order of <em>St Jean</em>, which doth import very much, it may perchance bring a War between Them and the Emperor, which would prove very <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> to these Counties. I presume this is the work of the Brandenburgher, and the House of Nassaw.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg>, <em>February 6.</em></i></head>

<p>We have little here since my last. A <reg orig="Brest-man">Brest man</reg> of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> of Twenty two <reg orig="Gunns">Guns</reg> <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> in our <reg orig="Channells">Channels</reg>; whereby the residue of our <em>Cadiz</em>-ships that lie in Ireland, are in some danger:</p>

<p>This day I am informed of a Truth that now in <reg orig="Monmouth-shire">Monmouthshire</reg>, near Ragland, in an Orchard, an Apple tree hath had green Leaves, <reg orig="Budds">Buds</reg> and young Apples. These are strange variations of the Seasons.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">This Latin <em>Epigram</em> was made upon his <reg orig="Highnesse's">Highness's</reg> entertainment in the City.</head>

<p><i>In Augustalia Serenissimi Domini &amp; Principis, OLIVARII D. Protectoris Reipub. <em>Angli&aelig;, Scoti&aelig;, &amp; Hiberni&aelig;, &amp;c.</em> Summ acum magnificentis celebrata <em>Londini</em>; Auspiciis Dom. Pr&aelig;toris, Senatus, &amp; totius Civitatis Londinensis, Februarii 8 1654.</i></p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Barbara C&aelig;sare&aelig; sileant Magnalia <em>Rom&aelig;</em>,</line>
<line><em>C&aelig;sar</em> adest melior. Sidus ut orbe novum</line>
<line><em>C&aelig;sare</em> major adest, quia noluit esse: Coronam</line>
<line>Arripiant alii; Se potuisse sat est.</line>
<line><em>C&aelig;sar</em> at alter erit, si quid pr&aelig;sagia possint,</line>
<line>Cum petet igne tuos, <em>Roma</em> profana, deos:</line>
<line>Hinc mihi &amp; omen erit, tua jam capitolia posse</line>
<line>Scandere, &amp; hinc <em>Britico</em> subdere colla jugo,</line>
<line>Quod sic tricipites potuit cicurare Tyrannos;</line>
<line>Dein tremit <em>Italici</em> trina corona <em>Jovis.</em></line>
<line>Erige te nostro, Regina <em>Britannia</em>, ponto,</line>
<line>Auspice CROMWELLO, ponito jura mari;</line>
<line>C&aelig;ruleos accerse deos, &amp; <em>Naiadas</em> omnes</line>
<line>In <em>Thamesin</em>, totus concinat inde chorus.</line>
<line>T&uacute;que agesis, NOVA TROIA, novos simul indue vultus,</line>
<line>Serta struas tanto Principe digna volo.</line>
<line>Corda hominum qu&aelig;rit qui tot Diademata sprevit,</line>
<line>VOS, &amp; non media pegmata celsa vi&acirc;</line>
<line>Secum adsert Laurus, spoliat&aacute;q; sceptra Tyranni,</line>
<line>Et <em>Libertatis</em> magna troph&aelig;a dedit.</line>
<line>Nunc prim&ugrave;m Cives estis, qi Regibus olim</line>
<line>Servi, ut Concives discite fr&aelig;na pati:</line>
<line>Non audit victor Miles, sed Fascibus arma,</line>
<line>Legibus &amp; mutat, sumit &amp; inde Togam,</line>
<line>Sic qu&aelig; nuper erat rudis indigest&aacute;que moles,</line>
<line>Quam dixere <em>Chaos</em>, jam novus orbis erit;</line>
<line>Protin&ugrave;s ad primum remeabunt omnia punctum,</line>
<line>Sanctus eritque <em>Plato</em> magnus Apollo mihi;</line>
<line>Aurea Saturni refer&eacute;tque <em>Platonicus Annus</em></line>
<line>Secula; cum &aelig;ternis silibus <em>Annus</em> eat!</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>From Bristol, February. 7.</i></head>

<p>Since the last, some of our <em>Cadiz</em> ships are arrived, and bring notice that the rest are in <em>Ireland</em>, having made our land a month since, but by contrary winds forced and kept there, which is very good news to our Merchants, who had almost given them up for lost, it being 8 weeks since they set sail from <em>Cadiz</em>. Some of them have brought a Dutch man of about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Salt which they took a little off that part as they put homeward.</p>

<p>The <em>Brest</em> men of war have since taken two Vessels of <em>Milford</em>, of which we had notice this day; and about the time of the taking of the former, took 3 ships one of 18 guns, another of 12 laden with lead and red herrings, who pretended themselves of <em>Amsterdam</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, being <em>Dutch-men</em>, but had Cockets from <em>North-Yarmouth</em>, the Seamen being <em>Dutch</em>, and indeed the commodities English. It is a shame, that those Rogues should be permitted thus to rob upon our Seas, and that such Cow-ships are employed <em>Westward</em>, which way all ships make that are bound for <em>England</em>. One of our <em>Bristol</em>-ships was taken half a league from <em>Scilly.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris Febr.15.1654</i></head>

<p>We expect shortly in Court the <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> <em>de Mercoeur</em>, coming from Provence to see one of the Cardinals sisters married to <em>Mr. Harpaion</em>. The Receiver of the <reg orig="Vniversity">University</reg> of <em>Paris,</em> has obtained from the King last <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, that no impositions shall be paid for Papers, having <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> many good reasons for it; that <reg orig="Youngmen">Young men</reg> could not prevail in their studies, nor the Printers <reg orig="liue">live</reg> by their Trade.</p>

<p>Last Saturday, arrived here Deputies from the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> of Melun, complaining of their Lieutenant to the Parliament; that he made them pay so much moneys, without any order from the King; upon which the Parliament sent Mr. <em>Baron</em> a <reg orig="Counsellour">Counsellor</reg> of the great Chamber, to bring them the information of such business. The marriage of the <em>Duke de Nemours</em>, with <em>Mademoiselle de Longueville</em> is renewed, she being hitherto in love with the Duke <pb n="9" /><em>of York</em>; but the Queen of France hindered that; and told her the Duke of York was too high a person for her, being son to a King, and a <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> brother, so she is now contented to marry <em>de Nemours</em>.</p>

<p>Last week the King sent for Mr. Marshal <em>de Shambert</em> to come to Court, to which he obeyed; but when he was to depart, the Inhabitants of that Town, and those of <em>Metz</em>, told him plainly, if he left them out, that they would lock the Gates after him, and never admit him again, and that they would <reg orig="shew">show</reg> him and the Cardinal, that they were able to defend themselves: upon which he stayed and sent his excuse to the King, he being <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of both those places.</p>

<p>The Prince <em>Francis de Loraine</em>, <reg orig="Cozen">Cousin</reg> to the Duke of <em>Loraine</em>, and Bishop of Verdun, parted hence yesterday to Verdun; his Majesty having given him that <reg orig="Bishopprick">Bishopric</reg> to be his.</p>

<p>We hear of a great plot discovered in Flanders; that some People were to murder the Arch-Duke, and Prince <em>de Conde</em>, and that twelve men were committed for it, and that the Arch-Duke, have sent their informations and sentence of death to the King of Spain, to be confirmed and sent to the Parliament of Malines back, to be put in execution, we expect the confirmation of it by the next.</p>

<p>Its reported Prince <em>Conde</em> his forces have taken Dinan, a place in <em>Payes de Liege</em>, and pillaged it for having received Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em>, when he was banished hence; others say, the Inhabitants gave them <unclear>60. In</unclear> livers, not to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> them wholly.</p>

<p>We hear the <em>Emperor</em> sent several <reg orig="Troopes">Troops</reg> of Horse to the Elector of Collen, and Duke <em>De Loraine</em> to oppose <em>Conde</em> his violence there. Its written hither from <em>Holland</em>, that the Princess <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> with her son, goes to keep their Court in Breda; by reason she sees the Provinces of <em>Holland, Zealand</em>, and <em><reg orig="Frizland">Friesland</reg></em>, assembling, and <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> together, for to conclude the peace with the Commonwealth of England.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<head level="3"><i>From Chester, February 4.</i></head>

<p>By the late Letters from <em>Dublin</em> we hear, that things thereabout at present are very quiet. The Irish of late have had a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Fast; the occasion is not known, but to themselves. Some few desperate Tories are yet doing mischief in Munster; and some <reg orig="sculking">skulking</reg> in Wicklow, <reg orig="snap'd">snapped</reg> about a dozen of our Surveyors.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Sears-Castle,</i> February 5.</head>

<p>the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> brought into Bridlington bay a small Dutch Pirate of 6 Guns, and 50 Men, which had taken some <reg orig="Collyers">Colliers</reg> upon this Coast, about 12 days since. The Captain and Men are sent to York <reg orig="Gaole">Gaol</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, February 9.</i></head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector hath appointed certain <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> every week, to receive Reports from the Master of Requests, concerning such Petitions as are presented to them, and to give Answers.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Mackworth</em> <reg orig="Governer">Governor</reg> of Shrewsbury, is by his Highness added to the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</p>

<p>Mr Recorder <em>Steel</em>, Mr <em>Nudigate</em>, Mr <em>Twisden</em>, Mr <em>Maynard</em>, and Mr <em>Hugh Windham</em>, are made <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at Law. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Hales</em> is made a <reg orig="Judg">Judge</reg> of the Common-pleas; and its conceived other new Judges will be made.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, February 5.</i></head>

<p>After the Enemies departure out of Bagenoth, we had this Account of their proceedings there, That they got 3 men from every 4 <reg orig="Ploughes">Ploughs</reg> in the Country, except those near the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <unclear><em>Ruthuen</em></unclear>, but many of them are since come back, <pb n="11" />the People going according to the <reg orig="Ministers">Minister's</reg> <unclear>Exhortation</unclear> given them <em>To give the <reg orig="Devill">Devil</reg> a Bone in <unclear>his mouth</unclear>, and put him to the Dove</em>: however many of them have suffered much by the Enemy, <reg orig="especialy">especially</reg> such as fled the Country at their approach. Things have of late been pretty quiet, and some of the Enemies seem to desire Passes to live quietly at home. Col. <em>Wogan</em> is for certain dead of those wounds he got near <em>Drummond</em>, and buried in the Highlands. His Capt. <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> also is irrecoverable, which discourages the whole party of English, and I am told they are upon dissolving. Their cruel Acts of burning their <reg orig="Countrymens">Countrymen's</reg> houses and Corn, makes them stink in their Nostrils, and I am apt to believe they are not so much of one party, as was supposed, nor their <reg orig="designe">design</reg> so <reg orig="universall">universal</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall in Sweden, January 11.</i></head>

<p>The absence of the great <reg orig="Chancelor">Chancellor</reg> of Sweden was one cause why my Lord Ambassador has for <reg orig="som">some</reg> few days been at a stand. Now things will be put to an issue; and so much the rather, because of the late change that hath fallen out in England, which we hope will prove for the honour of God, and the good of our Native country. It is extraordinary well resented here by the Queen and her Servants, who were much pleased, that the Credentials came so soon from his Highness the Lord Protector, to my Lord Ambassador; and the Queen hath received them with all satisfaction</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>From Mylor, in <reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg>, Feb. 6.</i></head>

<p>Last week we had three <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> here, the Falmouth-<reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, which brought a prize into Lea; the Warwick, which brought another into Foy; and the Portsmouth-<reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, which (as I hear) fought 4 French Merchant-men, two of 24 guns <reg orig="apeece">apiece</reg>, a third of 16. and the fourth of 14 guns. She suffered much from the two great ones, but at length, they stood away, and left the other two to her, which now are in Plymouth. We have had here several ships from <reg orig="Alicant">Alicante</reg>; Malaga, and the Canaries, which came in without any Convoy.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris February 18 stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The Duke of Longueville, though lately lifted at, is by the King's good grace, gone back to his Government of Normandy, having first taken his leave if his Majesty, the Queen, Duke <em>d'Anjou</em>, and the Cardinal, who for <reg orig="honors">honour's</reg> sake, and to lay a farther obligation upon him, conducted him in person, to the gate of Richelieu.</p>

<p>Beffort in Alsatia is at length taken by the Marshall <em>de la Ferte Seneterre</em>, in which service was the Duke of <reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg> Regiment.</p>

<p>Here hath lately been an Assembly of the Clergy, intended to oppose a Bull of the Pope's obtained by the Jesuits, whereby they had gotten power, the first Sunday in every month, by <reg orig="publick">public</reg> prayers, to fetch souls out of Purgatory, and so were in a fairway to have carried away the main Trade from the rest of the Clergy, The other occasion of their meeting was, to oppose the Impositions and Taxes laid upon them by the King and his Council; to the payment whereof our Parisian Clergymen are very averse, because of the hard usage and continued imprisonment of their Patron, the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em>, who hath been <reg orig="sollicited">solicited</reg> by divers messengers from his Majesty, to make a surrender of the Coadjutorship of this City; and upon condition he do it; he hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> promised his Liberty. But it will not be; the said Cardinal <reg orig="returnes">returns</reg> nothing but excuses, and modest denials, yet sufficiently resolute.</p>

<pb n="13" />

<p>On Friday, an arrest was verified in Parliament; that all Strangers shall be obliged to pay two Sols out of every pound of Merchandise that they import into this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>.</p>

<p>The fifteenth instant his Majesty, the Queen the Duke <em>d'Anjou</em> and the Cardinal were at the Fair of St <reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg>.</p>

<p>This Court is much taken up with Joviality, Balls Ballets, and Masques, and Weddings. Here was married lately the Marquis of Baden, a German, to Prince <em>Thomas</em> his daughter, called the <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of Caignan.</p>

<p>But the great marriage now to be celebrated is between the Prince of Conti, brother to the Prince of Conde, and one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces. He arrived here on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> in the afternoon, having been met first by the Cardinal at Fontaine-belleaure, fourteen leagues from this City. They <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> here both in one Coach; the Prince in the hinder-part, and the Cardinal in the fore-part, a Troop of Horse of the Cardinal's guard on each side of them, with about 30 Coaches, and 6 Horses in their company. It is said the marriage will be completed tomorrow.</p>

<p>The Prince sent his brother <em>Conde</em> a Letter <unclear>touching</unclear> his resolution of marriage, which its said he would not vouchsafe to read, but threw it in the fire; such is the height of his Spirit. Nevertheless, such is the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> indulgence toward him, that the process of confiscation against his Estate, is forborne to be put in execution. This marriage will salve that. Reports are made here by the Messenger that lately was in England, how nobly he had been received there by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, which hath been so resented here, that it is conceived they will suddenly send away an extraordinary Ambassador for England. Hereupon it is given out, that <em>Charles Stuart</em> is for a sudden remove out of this Kingdom, and that he resolves for <em>Germany</em>. This Court will be glad to be rid of him, a special regard being had of <em>English</em> friendship, upon the <em>Dutch</em> pacification; and upon condition he depart, they will be <unclear>inclinable</unclear> enough to continue his Pension.</p>

<pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg> February 16. stilo novo</i></head>

<p>Many Arguings here have been to and fro, about the business of Peace; yet the Interest of our Country is like at length to <reg orig="prevaile">prevail</reg> against the corruption of the adverse party; and our necessities &amp; losses have taken off the high <reg orig="humor">humour</reg> of the common sort; so that Peace will be very <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg>, and its generally believed that it <reg orig="wilbe">will be</reg> concluded. Zealand, on whom the brunt of the War hath chiefly <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg>, stands very much inclined if not more than Holland, though at first they were most eager and forward to the Breach. It is foreseen, what difficulties would befall all sorts of people, should we venture the <reg orig="Inconveniencies">Inconveniences</reg> of another <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> conflict; for, another Years loss of Free Trade and Fishing were a thing not to be endure, the multitude here not being so easily kept in order, under hardships, as in other Countries. It is said that 4, or 5 of the Provinces are willing to end the War, and those that are most considerable; which will draw on the rest in a little time. By the next we hope that we may give some more full Account.</p>

<p>This is certain, the English Royalists in this Country <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not like the present Transactions, and many of them are upon removing. The whole Family of Orange is much discontented, and all their Party. The Princess <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> and her son the young Prince, are removing to the Town of Breda, there to manifest a dislike by keeping at a distance.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<p><em>Middleton</em> is departed with about <unclear>120</unclear> Cavaliers, for the Highlands, having 5 or 6 small Vessels to transport his followers and Necessaries. This State is sending an Extraordinary to his Majesty of <em>France</em>. The thought of Peace makes our Merchants very pleasant, it being a manner taken for granted.</p>

<p><em>Dublin Jan. </em>31. We are now going to Proclaim the Lord Protector <em>Mortagh O Brian</em> hath laid down Arms upon Terms too good for him; <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> thought out of design to correspond with <reg orig="som">some</reg> <reg orig="forein">foreign</reg> aid, as they say themselves. Several Rogues go out daily. The natives <reg orig="sel">sell</reg> all they to get <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, supposing they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> get again the Commodities they sell at easier Rates. But an eye will be had upon them.</p>

<p><em>Febr. 12.</em> There arrived in the Evening a Servant of the Heer <em>Beverning</em> from the <em>Hague,</em> who brought <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of the inclination of the Provinces to a Peace; that 5 of the 7 Provinces had signed the Articles, and that the other 2 would suddenly accord. The next day it was said, that the 2 Provinces had also signed, and that Ambassadors would shortly be here to make a final Confirmation. Since that, it is given out here likewise, by some of the <em>Dutch</em> themselves, That the Heer <em>Beverning</em>, who resides at present in the Strand, hath as Plenipotentiary, received full Power and Instructions to conclude; with Advertisement, that 3 Extraordinary Ambassadors will be here in few days, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in a confirmation of the whole; and that this Power hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> sent him in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, to <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> the reality of Intentions of his Superiors to a <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> Agreement. Thus much out of the mouths of some of the <em>Dutch</em>. Wednesday night the 15. February, the Heer <em>Beverning</em> had Audience given by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>. What the Issue of these things may be, a few days time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">&#x261e; <em>The continuation of</em> Artamenes, or, <em>The</em> Grand Cyrus</head>

<p>That Excellent new Romance; Written by that famous Wit of <em>France</em> Monsieur <em>de Studery</em>, Governor of <em>Notre-Dame</em>; and now Englished by <unclear>Fl G:Esq</unclear>; To be sold by <em>Humphrey Moseley</em> at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Arms in St. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard, and <em>Thomas Dring</em> at the <em>George</em> in Fleet Street.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">Conjectura Cabbalistica, <em>or, A <reg orig="conjecturall">conjectural</reg> Essay</em></head>

<p>Of interpreting the Mind of <em>Moses</em> according to a threefold <em>Cabbala: viz.</em> Literal, Philosophical, Mystical, or Divinely Moral. By <em>Henry More F</em>: of C:C: <em>Cambridge</em>. To be sold by <em>Samuel Thompson</em> at <!--large space--><em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>