<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol199">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 199</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> March 30. to <em>Thursday</em> April 6. 1654.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3">Dalkeith, March 25.</head>

<p>Col. Cooper having notice about 30 of the enemy under Mac-Naughton, and the young Laird of Newark who lay in the Isle of Leven beyond Dumbarton, appointed several horse from our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> at Kilcrooch, Cardrasse, and Buhannan to fall into that Island at a Pass near Buhannan, about four of the clock on the 21 instant in the morning, and accordingly that night himself marched from Glasgow with a party of horse and Dragoons by the way of Dumbarton, and fell into the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, took Mac-Naughton's <pb n="1" />Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, narrowly missed Mac-Naughton and Newark, killed 12, whereof one (as the enemies confess) was a Lieutenant of horse, took between 50 and 60 horse (some good ones) and some Arms, put a perfect rout upon their whole party, and returned the same day back without any loss.</p>

<head level="3">From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, March 20.</head>

<p>No news will be more <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> here than peace; and now all conclude, the next Letters will tell the issue of the Treaty between you and the Dutch, on which so much depends.</p>

<p>The English Resident, Monsieur Bradshaw is now received here as Resident for his Highness the Lord Protector; and in testimony that this Senate desire to preserve the good will of his Highness, they have done more now upon the first demand by the Resident in the name of his Highness than heretofore.</p>

<p>You may perhaps have heard formerly of one Waites, a revolted Merchant of the English Company, who, as the King of Denmark <reg orig="past">passed</reg> this way yesterday, was laid hold on, is now laid by the heels by the Resident, to answer his <reg orig="perfideousness">perfidiousness</reg>. He was notably instrumental, while the Resident was in Denmark heretofore, to harden the King and his Court by vile reports, so that he was looked on as one of <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg> Agents, and now deserves to be dealt with accordingly. The mad Malignants, both English and Dutch, swear and stare at this here, but the Resident is a known man, and is one that values them not at the rate of a rush.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Whithall">Whitehall</reg>, March 20.</i></head>

<p>It was ordered that the following Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance declaring, that the Proceedings in the Case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> in <em>Ireland</em>, shall be as formerly.</i></p>

<p>Whereas by the Laws of <em>Ireland</em>, the proceedings in Case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, and against <reg orig="Murtherers">Murderers</reg>, hath been used to be as in Case of Treason and against Traitors; whereupon a doubt hath arisen, whether by the Ordinance <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance, declaring that the offences therein mentioned, and none other, shall be adjudged high Treason, within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland, </em>and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging</i>, the same be not taken away and repealed; for clearing whereof, be it Declared, Ordained, and established by his Highness the <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em>, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the offence, proceedings, and punishment in case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, and of <reg orig="Murtherers">Murderers</reg> in <em>Ireland</em>, and all Commanders, aiders, or abettors: in or unto any such fact, or person, shall remain, continue and be the same to all intents and purposes, as the same was or were before the making of the said Ordinance, and as if the said Ordinance had not been made, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, or any Law, or Statute to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p><i>March 23</i> the like Order passed for publishing another Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for Relief of persons that have acted in the Service of the Parliament.</i></p>

<p>Whereas many good and necessary Acts, <pb n="3" />Ordinances and Orders of Parliament have heretofore been made for the encouragement, <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg> and saving harmless of such persons as have in any sort by Sea or Land Engaged or Acted, or commanded to be done, any matter or thing whatsoever by Authority, or for the service or benefit of the Parliament; and Committees having been appointed to take care therein, And that Justice should be done accordingly, the Power of which Committees being determined, and so no course settled for parties grieved. His Highness having a continued and lively sense of such <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> undertakings and hazards for the service of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> in times of eminent danger and extremity, And being willing that full remedy should be provided for their safety, Doth, by and with the consent and advice of his Council, Declare, Establish, and Ordain, That all and every the said Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament, and every Article, Clause and Sentence in them, or any of them contained, shall stand, remain, and be in full force, effect and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, and be put in practice and execution, and be pleadable and made use of in all Courts of Justice, as fully and absolutely, to all intents and purposes, as if the same had been now particularly made for such purpose.</p>

<p>And it is further Declared, Established and Ordained, That the words, Clauses and sentences, in all and every the said Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament, shall be adjudged, expounded, and taken in all Courts and proceedings <pb n="4" />of Justice; and elsewhere, most beneficial and available, to all and singular the persons that have so acted or done by Authority, or for the service or benefit of the Parliament; And if, upon any Trial or Proceedings, in any Court of Justice, it shall appear unto the Judge, or Judges, before whom such Trial or Proceeding shall be had or made, That the Party that hath acted by the Authority, or for the service or benefit of the Parliament, hath not had, or cannot have such full and just relief therein, as by the said Acts, Ordinances or Orders of Parliament was intended or provided, Then such Judge, or Judges shall, and are hereby required to make certificate thereof to the Barons of the Exchequer, upon which Certificate the said Barons, or any two of them, shall have Authority, and are hereby <reg orig="Impowred">Empowered</reg>, <reg orig="Authorized">Authorised</reg>, and Required, upon such Certificate and complaint of the party grieved, to proceed, and do therein to all intents and purposes; And they have hereby given unto them the same and like Powers, Authorities, Jurisdiction, and course of proceeding, in all Causes for relief of such party or parties grieved in the <reg orig="Premisses">Premises</reg>, as any Committee or Commissioners of or for <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, appointed by Authority of Parliament, had, or lawfully might have exercised.</p>

<p>And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That where any person, that ought to have been <reg orig="Indempnified">Indemnified</reg>, by the true meaning of the said Acts and Orders of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, hath any Judgement or Verdict already obtained <pb n="5" />against him at Law, for any matter or thing for which he ought so to have been <reg orig="indempnified">indemnified</reg>, by reason whereof he is disabled to plead his matter of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg> before the said Judges, before mentioned, that then in every such case, upon complaint exhibited before the said Barons of the Exchequer, setting forth his case, and <reg orig="alledging">alleging</reg> such matter for his <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, as that Court shall judge sufficient; and also give in such security, as the said Barons shall approve of, to pay Costs unto the party molested or drawn so in question before the said Barons, in case he shall not prove the suggestion of his said Complaint, the said Barons, in such special case, also may proceed to do therein, for <reg orig="Indempnifying">Indemnifying</reg> the said party grieved, as hereby they are <reg orig="Authorized">Authorised</reg> to do, upon the Certificate of the Judges before mentioned.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That nothing in this Ordinance be construed or understood to revive the power of the said Commissioners in any the former Ordinances or Acts of Parliament named, so as to enable the said Committees to intermeddle in the execution of any of the said Acts or Ordinances,</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Plymouth</em> Fort, <em>March</em> 24.</head>

<p>The news this place affords is, the Commander of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a Dutch prize, which hath no loading, only some few Barrels of Pitch, &amp;c. This week the <em>Paul</em>, a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met with a <em>Flushing</em> man of War in the Channel, of 15 guns, who after 5 hours fight took her, and this day brought her <pb n="6" />in hither; we lost not any man in the fight, but sustained some damage in Masts, Sails, and Rigging; the enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and the ship much torn, she hath some Silver in her, and some small quantity of Wines.</p>

<p>Great have been the expectations and hopes of a Peace and Union between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> upon this Treaty, which we have several weeks mentioned, and we can now safely assure you, that the Articles of Peace, both in relation to them and <em>Denmark</em>, are absolutely concluded on, and for a full confirmation (undoubtedly) will be signed and sealed by Commissioners on both sides before the publication of our next.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Upsal, March 3.</i> S.V.</head>

<p>The Queen came from <em>Westraas</em> on Sunday last, and it is reported that the Prince Palatine hath accepted of her Propositions, since which Summons are issued for the calling together the States of this Nation by the second of <em>May</em> next, before which time we shall hardly hear <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> more of this great and strange business. <em>Don Piemontel</em> the Spanish Resident is remanded home by his Master, who intends to take his journey over land within this fortnight or thereabouts. We are not likely to receive any answer <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the certainty of our Treaty with the Dutch is known; and I believe, when that is understood we shall be dispatched, and that to our contentment.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Copenhagen, March</i> 22. S.N.</head>

<p>In the absence of this King and Court, there <pb n="7" />is little news of here, only an Ambassador from the Duke of <em>Muscovia</em> is lately come hither from <em>Stockholm</em>, as is said, under pretence of buying up some Ammunition of War for the use of his Master against the King of <em>Polonia</em>. This people through their jealousies are yet <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> of the the<!--the is repeated, it appears at the end of a line then the beginning of the next--> issue of the Treaty with <em>England</em>, yet hoping there will be peace, they do not <reg orig="to">too</reg> much fear their neighbour the Swede, or any of their private Transactions with <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg></em> the 21 dito, S. N.</head>

<p>Last Harvest divers Arms were sent from hence for <em>Lubeck</em> by a Gentleman of this Country, and some say for the service of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, but cannot affirm the certainty. In my last I wrote you of the Conjunction the Muscovites had made with the Cossacks, which some say is not yet completed. Indeed all reports out of <em>Poland</em> are so various, that little can be credited. The difference between this King and Crown about the balances of <em>Poland</em> and <em>Littow</em> is not yet ended. It's reported the King will repose himself after <em>Easter</em> here in <em>Paussia</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, March 31.</i></head>

<p>These two Ordinances following were <reg orig="Order'd">Ordered</reg> to be printed; the one <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for suspending the Proceeding of the Judges</i> named in the Act, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>. The other is <i>An Ordinance prohibiting Cock Matches</i>.</p>

<p>Whereas upon perusal and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors <pb n="8" />and poor Prisoners</i>; many doubts and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an explanation of the said Act, for the better enabling the Judges in the said Act named and <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> for sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges, <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> in and by the said Act, <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="inconveniencies">inconveniences</reg> and mischiefs would grow, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the said Creditors and Prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles and suits in Law and Equity For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: And whereas many of the said Prisoners have <reg orig="offred">offered</reg> really to <reg orig="endevor">endeavour</reg> the satisfaction of the said Creditors, if some further time may be given for that purpose; Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the said <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any the Estates Real or personal, of any of the said Prisoners, or of any other person or persons whatsoever mentioned or intended in or by the said Act; nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any the powers or authorities given by the same, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 20. day of <em>April</em> next. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Acts or things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or by any of them, by <reg orig="vertu">virtue</reg>, <reg orig="color">colour</reg>, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said 20 day of <em>April</em>, shall be utterly void, null, and of none effect; saving only that it shall and may be <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> for the said several amp; respective Judges that have bailed or let out any Prisoners upon Sureties or otherwise, out of Prison (which Prisoners are to appear again at a certain day before the said Judges, and are not absolutely discharged by any Order of the said Judges) to sit <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the remanding and <reg orig="recomitting">recommitting</reg> of the said Prisoners into their former Prisoners and <reg orig="Goals">Gaols</reg>, where they formerly were detained in Prison, there to remain in safe custody, and to continue and be in the same condition as formerly they were at the time of their Bailing or letting out as aforesaid.</p>

<p><i>Hen: Scobell, Clerk of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance prohibiting</i> Cock <unclear>Matches</unclear>.</head>

<p><i>Whereas the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Meetings and <unclear>Assemblies</unclear> of people together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cockfighting, are by experience <unclear>found to tend</unclear> many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Peace and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practices, to the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of <pb n="9" />God, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of Persons and their Families. For prevention thereof be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by, and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publique">public</reg> or set meeting or Assemblies of any persons within <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, upon Matches made for Cock fighting, And that every such meeting, and Assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid; is hereby declared to be an <reg orig="unlawfull">unlawful</reg> Assembly, and shall be adjudged, deemed and taken to be punished. And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, <reg orig="Maiors">Mayors</reg>, Bailiffs, Constables, and Headboroughs within their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties, Cities, Limits and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such Meetings and Assemblies.</i></p>

<p><i>Hen: Scobell Clerk of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3">To his Highness OLIVER Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland,</head>

<p><i>The humble Address and congratulation of the <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg>, Recorder, Aldermen Ministers, <reg orig="Sherrifs">Sheriffs</reg>, Common <reg orig="councill">council</reg>, and other Inhabitants of the City of Coventry.</i></p>

<p>As we bless <em>God</em> for, so we <reg orig="canot">cannot</reg> but with glad hearts, represent to your Highness, how clearly we have of late beheld, that holy Proverb <reg orig="fulfild">fulfilled</reg> (<i>In the Mount of the Lord it <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> seen</i>) for when we feared the life of Religion, Magistracy, Ministry, Laws &amp; Liberties (the dear concernments of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people) would have expired, and <reg orig="bin">been</reg> found by Posterity covered with Ashes, through the inadvertency of some Men, it pleased the Lord above and beyond our foresight and provision, <reg orig="hapily">happily</reg> to repose, and to make your Highness eminently a mean to prevent the danger; and as Divine Providence hath signally pointed you out, and raised you up to save us from those our fears; so we cannot but expect, that the same will also make you instrumental to accomplish these our hopes; that religion and all ordinances of Christ are moving towards purity and power; that the building of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> house may now rise to the top-stone, and all his people cry <em>Grace, Grace</em> unto it: That Magistracy and Ministry will be secured from the violation of <reg orig="prophane">profane</reg> and irregular, pens and tongues; and that henceforth men fitly qualified may be set apart for both callings: that the laws will receive life, &amp; common liberties <reg orig="toeir">to their</reg> maintenance, and that we shall have no self advantage, solemnly t bless the Lord for your Highness protecting of us, and our affairs civil, then we of this City have had for the fruit of your power whilst it was martial. These are our hopes, which under God have their foundation in your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> constancy, to contend for, &amp; <reg orig="adhear">adhere</reg> to the <reg orig="knowne">known</reg> and undoubted interest of God and this Nation, so well of late secured in the provision made for the future parliaments. Now that your Highness may be the hand of the Lord to do all <reg orig="thesethings">these things</reg>, and fulfil his good pleasure; we shall not be wanting <pb n="10" />,or neglect any duty incumbent on us, which may conduce to the <reg orig="Nations">Nation's</reg> protection and your Highness, or your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> protection under God, and we shall ever pray and remain,</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> most humble servants</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, April 6. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The French Troops being <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> out of the Country of <em>Liege</em>, upon the Parole of the Prince Elector, that the Spaniards, Lorainers, or the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Forces should not attempt anything against them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Peace that is made, whereof I made mention in my foregoing; they took their march directly towards <em>Malmedy, Stanelo,</em> and <em>Tionville</em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> (as is said) with the Marshal <em>de la Ferte Senterre</em> in <em>Alsatia</em>, there to attend the motions of the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em>, who is said to have made his peace with the King of <em>France</em>, upon reasonable terms granted to his person, whereupon he hath delivered <em>Brisack</em> and some other places up to the King of <em>France</em>. The said Prince of <em>Collen</em> is come with his Court to <em>Fleurn</em> (between <em>Brussels</em> and <em>Namur</em>) to speak with his Highness, the Archduke <em>Leopold William</em>; and for this purpose he sent the Baron of <em>Petersen</em> hither to this Court, to give notice thereof to his said Highness.</p>

<p><em>Francis</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em> is upon the way with his two sons to come to this Court, where they are making ready his Lodgings, to entertain him according to his quality; he is to have the supreme command of his <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> Armies, who hath given his consent unto it upon certain conditions.</p>

<head level="3">From the <i>Hague, March</i> 30.</head>

<p>Last Wednesday here arrived Letters from the Lords Ambassadors in <em>England</em>, being dated the 20 of this month, sent over in a ship called the <em>Pincq</em>, wherein they <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> to the Lords States that the Peace was not yet quite concluded, and that they made in <em>England</em> great preparation for the Sea in great haste; the occasion thereof being unknown; it doth seem to cause some <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> amongst the Lords States; whereupon Orders were presently sent to <em>de Ruyter</em> and young <em>Tromp</em> to go for North <em>Holland</em> to hasten on the equipage of the ships; and several Messages are also sent to the <reg orig="Colledges">Colleges</reg> of the Admiralty to hasten out the Fleet. It is said likewise that they have sent for the Lord Admiral <em>Opdam</em> out of <em>Flanders</em>, where he is at present. Since that a neighbour Nation makes such great preparations, it is no wonder that the like is done here.</p>

<p>Last night the Lords States sent a Pink with Letters from <em>Scheveling</em> for <em>England</em>, to hasten on (as is said) the ratification of the Peace, which we do here much long for, and make no doubt now again, but that same will be speedily effected; since we hear there is now great hopes again that all will be accommodated between us.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Denmark</em> hath notice sent him from hence that 70 Englishmen of War had steered their course Northwards, in all likelihood <pb n="11" /><reg orig="design'd">designed</reg> against the <em>Sound</em>, which by the assistance of the Swedes might be <unclear>surprised</unclear>, if not timely prevented.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> by order of the Lords, the said States, they are raising of men for their ships, to set forth their Fleet in all haste.</p>

<p>The Rhyngrave hath been to congratulate the Prince Elector of <em>Cullen</em>, about the peace that hath been concluded at <em>Tierlemont</em>.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Denmark</em> came yesterday to <em>Altenaw</em>, and was entertained in one of his <reg orig="Agents">Agent's</reg> Country Houses. The Senate hearing of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> being so near their City, caused all the Guns on that side of their Walls divers times to be fired, and sent a stately present unto him, by two of their Senators, but it was refused by the King, by reason as is said, the Burgomaster came not himself with it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, April 3. An Ordinance for continuing one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, an <unclear>Act for Probate</unclear> of Wills, and granting Administrations.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations</i>, and all the Powers, Authorities, Matters and things therein contained, shall be, and are hereby revived and continued, in full power and force, to all intents and purposes, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further Order. And it is hereby further Ordained, That <em>Richard Lucy, John Hildesley, Nathaniel Barton, Jarvas Bennet, Anthony Rous, Joachym Mathews, <unclear>Edward Cludd</unclear>, Thomas Wood, Esqs</em>; and <em>Robert Hitchburn</em> Alderman of <em>London</em>, be added to the Judges mentioned in the said Act, and that the said Judges named in the said Act, and in this present Ordinance, or ay three of them, be, and are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to put in execution all and every the Powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named might have done by force of the said Act.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris, April 8. 1654. S.N.</i></head>

<p>Since my last I have but little news worthy of your lecture.</p>

<p>The Letters which came the same day from <em>Bordeaux</em>, inform us that the Partisans of this Court did very much suspect the English arming.</p>

<p>The next day news came from <em>Champagne</em>, that Mr. <em>Faber</em> had at last <reg orig="repassed">re-passed</reg> the <em>Meuse</em> without meeting Mr <em>le Prince</em>, But that some of the said <em>Prince's</em> Troops having met the French Regiment <em>de la <unclear>Nieuville</unclear></em> of about four hundred <reg orig="hors">horse</reg>, they had wholly defeated it, and taken the Lieutenant Colonel named <em>Lundy</em>, which commanded it.</p>

<p>This Court hath also received notice that Prince <em>Francis de Lorain</em>, notwithstanding all the intrigues this Court and the Guysards have made use of to draw him in their side, hath ranged himself to the Spanish, and taken Oath to Command his <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> Troops for the service of that King, leading to <em>Brussels</em> the most dear Hostages the Archduke can desire of him, which were to receive there exceeding great and sumptuous honour.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<p>The Lord <em>Peter Mazarin</em> his father hath been <reg orig="naturalized">naturalised</reg> French in the Register of this Parliament; and I am informed the King hath also sent him a Commission of <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> to reside at <em>Rome</em> during six months.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris, April 8. S. N.</i></head>

<p>The King is gone to St. <em>Germain en laye</em>, and his Eminency which forsakes him not, is also gone with him, although his Majesty had told him that he might stay if he pleased; his said Majesty will be back again <reg orig="to night">tonight</reg> to exercise <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> a new Mask which is shortly to be danced in the <em>Louvre</em>.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean while">meanwhile</reg> the Deputies from the Reformed Churches are still delayed, and notwithstanding the brave promises which are made them, they now refuse to hear them under a pretence (say they) that in this Conjuncture of affairs with the Cardinal of <em>Retz</em> they cannot disoblige the Pope, so that as yet they could not receive Audience from the King nor from the Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>.</p>

<p>The said Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> has been carried to <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em>, and they have fed him with hopes that he shall there be in liberty under the <reg orig="Baile">Bail</reg> of Marshal <em>de la Milleray</em>; but it is credible he will at last find himself deceived.</p>

<p>This Court sent last week, the Duke of <em>Ampville</em> unto the Duke of <em>Orleance</em>, to flatter and offer him the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Estate by marrying the Duke of <em>Enguien, Conde's</em> heir, to one of his Royal Highness his daughters.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging.</i></head>

<p>The Recognition of the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the ancient City of <em>York</em>.</p>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord to run to and fro through the earth to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself strong on the behalf of them whose hearts are perfect toward him, to make bare his arm, and bring salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, and to break many <reg orig="yoaks">yokes</reg> from off our necks; in accomplishment whereof, though humane power and might have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and overruled by the Spirit in the midst of the Wheels, that we may justly say, we are not saved by Bow or Sword, but by the Lord our God. And therefore in the first place we look upon it as our duty, to <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> salvation and blessing to him that sits upon the Throne of heaven judging Right, who hath done whatsoever it pleaseth him in heaven and in earth, and in all the deep places.</p>

<p>Yet when we also consider, how it seemeth good in the eyes of God to single out your Highness as the man of his right hand, whom he hath made strong for himself, and through your <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg>, courage and constancy to do great and wonderful things in the midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left; while we bless the Lord, our heart is also to the Governors of <em>Israel</em> who have <reg orig="jeoparded">jeopardised</reg> their lives in the high places of the Field, and are daily going on to second their valiant <pb n="13" />acts by prudent <reg orig="councels">counsels</reg>, if we may enjoy the end of every just War, which is a safe and honourable Peace. Unto your Highness therefore, as once the people of <em>Israel</em> to their Ruler, we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and peace be to thine helpers.</i></p>

<p>If we should promise to ourselves too much concerning your Highness, or any of the sons of men, especially in this day wherein the Lord <unclear>hath</unclear> so much received our confidences, and proclaimed to us by the <unclear>voice</unclear> of manifold providences, <i>Cease from man whose breath is in his nostrils</i>, we should not only <reg orig="intrench">entrench</reg> upon the honour of God and our own peace, but be injurious to your Highness, who are better able to bear the burden of much trouble, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a little of that trust which we owe to him alone, in whom there is everlasting strength, who turns every Staff into a Reed, when it is rested on. Yet we cannot but declare our great hopes, that the Lord will still delight to use your Highness as a blessed Instrument of much honour to his great Name, and happiness to this Commonwealth; That as <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath <reg orig="helpt">helped</reg> you to build the Wall of <em>Jerusalem</em>, the defence and safety of his People even in troublous times, so he will also engage your heart and enable your hands, according to your eminent station, to further the spiritual Work and welfare of his Church and Temple, which waits for a season of more <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="adde">add</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the declaration of our satisfaction in the present Government administered by your Highness, and our cheerful submission unto it, which we shall be ready to second with our prayers and endeavours for your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> prosperity, and the people of God who fit under your shadow. Humbly begging your favourable aspect and influence upon the honour and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> of this ancient City, whose strength is much decayed, though their burdens be increased, which yet they are more willing though unable to undergo, till a just and reasonable remedy be procured. Our lot is fallen something remote from the great scene of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affairs, which hath been prejudicial to us; but we trust, though we enjoy not, so much warmth of the Sun as the Southern parts: yet the beams of your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness'</reg> goodness and justice, whom God hath set up in the midst of us, shall comfortably reach this place, which though in many outward advantages, it may come behind others, yet will strive to an equality with the best, in their affection and faithfulness to your Highness and this Commonwealth.</p>

<p><i>Signed by the Mayor, in the name and by the appointment of the Aldermen and Commonalty of the City of York, <em>John Geldert Maj.</em></i></p>

<p>To his Highness OLIVER CROMWELL, Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland, </em>and <em>Ireland</em>, and the dominions thereunto belonging.</p>

<p><i>The humble Petition and Representation of the Grand Juries, at the Assizes held at York, <em>March 1653.</em> in the behalf of themselves and of the Nobility, Justices, Gentry, and Freeholders, with the other Inhabitants of the County of York.</i></p>

<p>Whereas, it seemed good unto the Almighty and wise disposer <pb n="14" />of all things, by many great and admirable Steps of Providence, to advance your Highness to the present and peaceable administration of the Government of this Nation, in which we trust that all friends to true Religion and <reg orig="publick">public</reg> liberty shall have cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>. We your Petitioners, do humbly and cheerfully <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> our thankfulness to your Highness, for your great care in preserving us from those evils of Tyranny and <unclear><!--8 characters--></unclear>, which we have very lately apprehended <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> in eminent danger of; as also our satisfaction and acquiescence in the Government now established; which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> shall in our places and stations be ready with all faithfulness to preserve and maintain.</p>

<p><i>Further representing and desiring,</i></p>

<p>That countenance may be given to godly and able Ministers of the Gospel, such as have or shall give Testimony of their good affections to the State, as it is now constituted; and that for their encouragement, some timely Provision may be made for a competent and comfortable <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, and that they may be vindicated from oppressions and affronts arising from Principle, of <reg orig="Prophaneness">Profaneness</reg> and Superstition, and other more specious pretexts, alike dangerous to the propagation of the Gospel, and in opposition to government. That scandalous Ministers may be removed, and fornications, superstitions, and corruptions still tenaciously retained by many, to the hurt of ignorant persons, and prejudice of such Ministers as desire to be faithful, may be <reg orig="reform'd">reformed</reg>; and that those disorders and disturbances as <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> break out in matters of religion may be rectified.</p>

<p>That the augmentations of Ministers already made, may be more equally and impartially <reg orig="destributed">distributed</reg>.</p>

<p>And for all these ends, that some faithful and godly men may be <reg orig="empowred">empowered</reg> in this Country, so as we may not be necessitated upon every occasion to <reg orig="repaire">repair</reg> to <em>London</em>, where many necessary things are not prosecuted by reason of the tediousness and great <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of such <reg orig="journeyes">journeys</reg>.</p>

<p>That Courts of Judicature may be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in this great <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, it having been under consideration, and a great progress made therein in Parliament, upon the Petitions of the People in these parts, for the perverting of excessive <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> and other <reg orig="Inconveniencies">Inconveniences</reg> in Law suits, occasioned by the remoteness of this County from the City of <em>London</em>,</p>

<p>That some way may withal <reg orig="conveniencie">convenience</reg> <reg orig="bee">be</reg> directed and <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> for Probate of Wills within this Country: and that these Courts may be without unnecessary appeals to <em>London</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Bristol, April 1.</i></head>

<p>We have little news here, but of continued <reg orig="loses">losses</reg>. The <em>Charity</em> of above 100 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, taken by two Brest men of War, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> her Port in France; the Master whereof they detain for that <reg orig="villane">villain</reg> <em>Beach</em>; besides this Ship of Bristol, they took a Vessel of Westchester, and a day or two before four Vessels of Weymouth, and the western Parts: <pb n="15" />The <reg orig="wildboare">Wild Boar</reg> also of above 250 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> 14 guns, taking in some lading at the Mederas, and so <reg orig="in tending">intending</reg> for <reg orig="Barbadas">Barbados</reg>, was forced by a storm to cut Cable and to Sea, where he met with a Flushing of 22 guns, whom with those men she had fought stoutly, till being overmastered, she was brought into Cadiz. The Ship and goods worth 5000.l. belonging to honest men, as Mr. <em>Speed</em>, who hath lost 280l. <em>ster<!--possibly a printers error, intended to be master?--> James Powel</em>, Capt <em>Beal, Jeremy Holwey</em>, and several Families, who usually trade to the Western Islands: most of the best Ships of this Port are lately taken, especially by the Brest men. This City by reason of it is full of murmurings.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Plymouth, March</i> 13. 1654.</head>

<p>Yesterday, here passed to the Eastward forty sail of English ships, come from Spain and Portugal, &amp;c. The Expedition of this <reg orig="towne">town</reg>, Mr. <em>Mathews</em> Master coning from <em>Zant</em>, laden with <unclear>Currants</unclear>, was set upon by a Dutch man of war of thirty guns, off the <em>Burlings</em>, and after a long dispute, night parted them, the man of war, fired some guns to the Leeward for help, and presently after was seen to sink in the sea; And the Expedition having received an <reg orig="unfortunat">unfortunate</reg> shot sunk also the next morning. But all the men were saved by the care of this place, who together with some others are safely arrived here.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, March 28.</i></head>

<p>The last intelligence from the North is, that the enemy still keep Skelko Castle, and have cast up some works about it, to secure themselves and the pass; the also continue a Garrison in Skelko, upon that Ferry which is upon Tain River Sir <em>James Macdonald</em> and the Captain of Clanrannoid are in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> to defend their Country against <unclear><em><reg orig="Glengaries">Glengary's</reg></em></unclear> parties: the enemy are yet in Sutherland and Caithness, gathering what men they can there. In these and the Southern parts towards Carlisle, they are very active in rising <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, which put the Horse here to extraordinary duty, even to <unclear>tiring</unclear> out, and yet we cannot meet with any of them in bodies, though prisoners are brought in <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>. <em>Middleton</em> hath brought a very large Commission from <em>Charles Stuart</em>, and hath the disposal of all affairs, both Ecclesiastical and Civil.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, April 3</i></head>

<p>The Commission of the great Seal being <reg orig="alter'd">altered</reg>, the Lord <em>Whitelock</em>, Lord <em>Lisle</em>, and Sir <em>Thomas <unclear>Widdrington</unclear></em>, were appointed Lords Commissioners for the custody of the great Seal of England.</p>

<p>No news, from sea, save that a Dutch man of 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, bound from S. Malos to Amsterdam, most part of her lading being <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg> and Pepper was taken by the Reserve, and brought since into Plymouth.</p>

<p><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg> April 5. The Commissioners of the Council had a meeting with the Dutch Ambassadors, and about nine <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at Night the Articles of PEACE between England and the United Provinces were <unclear>signed</unclear> and sealed on both sides. The Commissioners having proceeded thus far, the Peace is, within fifteen <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, to be ratified by the <unclear>Principal</unclear> on each part, and <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> proclaimed both in England and the Low Countries; of which more by the next.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>