<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol189">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 189</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> January 19. to <em>Thursday</em> January 26. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3">From <em>Ruthen</em> Castle. January 2.</head>

<p>I Had given you account of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> first advance in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, but (through the baseness of some of the people) my Bearer was discovered to the enemy, and taken by them, but not my Letters, and <em>Kenmore</em> caused him to be burned both hands and feet in a most barbarous and <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> manner, to cause him to confess what he had done with my Letters, which notwithstanding he refuse to do; and yesterday being appointed for his execution within sight of this Garrison, a deep sleep fell upon his Guard, so that he escaped their hands, and came back to me. <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glengary</em> with their Forces marched by the wasy of <em>Strathspey</em>, and <em>Glencarne, Lorn, Mac Heldny</em>, and some of <em>Mac <reg orig="Griggers">Grigger's</reg></em> men, with the rest of that Gang, <em>Atholl</em> being left behind, marched in by the head of this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> their forces within three miles of this Garrison, where <em>Glencairne</em> now quarters. At their approach to this place, <pb n="1" /><em>Glencairne</em> sent me a letter stuffed with <em>Scotch</em> complements, the Copy whereof, with my answer, as also his letter to the Country Gent are <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>. There hath <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> out some discontent between <em>Glencairne</em> and <em>Lorn</em> about the men of this <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, <em>Lorn</em> saying, that by reason they were his men, he ought as well to have the ordering and disposal of them, as the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Athol</em> had had of his: But <em>Glecairne</em> told him, that although his father took up the rents of the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, the men were the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg></em>, and that <em>Lorn</em> should have nothing to do with them, but he would use them as he pleased; whereupon high words arose between them, and <em>Glencairne</em> offered to draw his sword, and <em>Lorn</em> went away in great rage, swearing, that rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> he would see his own people abused by <em>Glencairne</em> he would lose his life; and thereupon drew to the other side of the water from <em>Glencairne</em>, and <em>MacKeldny</em> with some of the <em><reg orig="Macgriggers">Macgrigger's</reg></em> men, and about sixty horse with him, and sent the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> in all haste to the Gentry of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: but some of them fearing it might be some plot, did not answer his desires. I sent a letter, the copy <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> is also <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>, to some that went to him, knowing that they <reg orig="shew">show</reg> what ever Letters to them. Yesterday <em>Glencairn</em> had <reg orig="rendezvouz">rendezvous</reg> about 4 miles off on the north side of the river, and <em>Lorn</em> with <em>MacKeldny</em>, and what others he had with him, were drawn up on the South side of the River, <reg orig="welnigh">well nigh</reg> in opposition, and the whole of their number was not above 1600 horse and foot. The last night <em>Lorn</em>, and Col. <em>Meynes</em>, with 6 horse, left all and fled, and <em>Glencairne</em> presently sent a party of horse after him to apprehend him. Had <em>Lorn </em>stayed and concurred with them, this <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> for the most part would have gone his way but this difference hath put most of them to a stand, and some of them are fled to <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> amp; other parts, to secure themselves. Parties of horse and Posts are directed every way for the apprehending of <em>Lorn</em>, the enemy take up all horses they can find, and except <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear>few Troopers, they are work-horses, and <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> <pb n="2" /><reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> beasts without <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, and their Foot <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> starven fellows, many of them having no other Arms <reg orig="then">than</reg> cudgels, and those that have Arms have no Ammunition, and they are full of fears, so that had we but six hundred horse and foot at this time, we might in all probability put them to their best shifts to escape our hands. They use this <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> somewhat hardly, and especially since <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> departure. And that same night the difference was between them, <em>Glencairne</em> in a <reg orig="despitefull">despiteful</reg> manner, removed his quarters to <em>Ballathrone</em>, where the <em><reg orig="Bailiffes">Bailiff's</reg></em> interest lies, and I <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> hath left little there that could either be eaten or carried away. I am informed that the Lord of <em>Grant</em> although he hath not personally appeared with them hath sent divers letter unto them. And further my Intelligence <reg orig="sayes">says</reg> that the enemy intend when they have eaten up this <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, which will not be long at the rate they devour, to separate to wit, <em>Glencairn</em> to march North, towards <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>, Ross</em> and <em>Caithness</em>, and <em>Kenmore</em> towards <em>Aberdeen </em>Shire. What is become of <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> men, I cannot yet certainly learn, but the flying report is, that they are dispersed. The enemy keep Guards on the other side of the water at the Kirk-town, within less <reg orig="then">than</reg> twice musket shot of the Castle, but never <reg orig="appeare">appear</reg> on this side of the water within sight of the Castle, and where I cannot over to them by reason of the Ice. Since I began to write, my Intelligence assures me, that the occasion of <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> so sudden flight was, that after he had <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> out with <em>Glencairn</em>, that same night he sent a Letter to me, to advise me where to fall on <em><reg orig="Glencairnes">Glencairne's</reg></em> men with the best advantage, but his Bearer proving false, carried his Letter to <em>Kenmore</em>, whereupon they drew up part of the Army that way, thinking to take him that night, and so fled, as aforesaid: they have imprisoned 7 or 8 of the <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> Gentlemen that were with him. It is also said, that <em>Lorn</em> posted away a letter to his Father acquainting him with his condition, and that he was <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in to him. The <em>Braymen</em> of this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> close with the enemy.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, January 8.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> from <em>Upsahla</em> of the <unclear>22</unclear> of December, S.V. I understand his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg>, and very honourable Reception there, having been (to use his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> own expression) more <reg orig="then">than</reg> is usually given to Extraordinary Ambassadors, whereby the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Majesty is pleased to testify her great respect to the Commonwealth of England. By another Letter from thence of the 24 of December S.V. information is come, That on the next precedent day, his Lordship received Audience by her Majesty with no less Honour and Solemnity; but the particulars thereof were then not known.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen, January 11. S.N.</i></head>

<p>We understand here of the <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Reception of the English extraordinary Ambassador at <em>Upsahla</em>, which is affirmed to have been extraordinary for stateliness and solemnity. A Fleet of <reg orig="som">some</reg> 80 Sail of Dutch Merchantmen, with one Convoyer, being lately departed out of the Sound, and intending homeward, on this side the <em>Scaw</em>, met with an English <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> coming from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, who sent the Convoyer soundly <reg orig="batter'd">battered</reg> and basted, with a great many of the said Fleet back again; and having taken <reg orig="som">some</reg>, brought them up into <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>. This people, especially the Dutch, are so <reg orig="madd">mad</reg> thereat, that they say, <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> ere long will be a worse <reg orig="Pirates">Pirate's</reg> nest, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever <em>Dunkirk</em> was. This Court stands as yet in expectation what the issue <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be of the Treaty with England, not knowing whether they will be <pb n="4" />included or excluded out of the same; but if they be excluded, their fears will render their poor people unserviceable, for their own defence.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam, January 14. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The last storm hath caused much damage in these Parts by Sea and Land. In <em>Texell</em> are cast away 5, or 6 ships, one of whom was an East Indy man outward bound, and about 200 men lost in her. Another East-Indy ship lost all her Masts, &amp; consequently her Voyage; many others were forced on shore. In a Dorp of North Holland, <reg orig="cald">called</reg> <em>Rype</em>, 600 houses, &amp; 5000 Bundles of Hemp were consumed with Fire; a remarkable stroke of God, if they were but sensible of it. A Friend writes me from the <em><reg orig="Haghe">Hague</reg></em>, that he saw the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> private Letter from their Deputies, who wrote that on Friday last was <reg orig="sevenight">sevennight</reg> they had made a <reg orig="finall">final</reg> end, whereof they should receive a large account per next.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg> January 4. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The Messenger that came on here from <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em>, hath brought a good Resolution from his Minister. Yesterday the Ambassadors were again conducted to the Assembly, where the Introduction of the new Dukes of <em>, Picolomini, &amp; Aversberg</em>, as also the admission of the City of <em>Bremen</em>, and satisfaction of <em>Lorain</em> were propounded, but nothing concluded upon.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> January 10. S.V.</i></head>

<p>There departed out of this River <reg orig="som">some</reg> few days ago a Fleet of 70, or 80 Merchantmen, bound for <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Ports and Places. 2 Dutch Capers, and 2 other <reg orig="States">State's</reg> men of war which lay purposely at <pb n="5" /><em>Gluckstads</em> to wait for them, departed with them out of the River; so that it is thought they are all carried into <em>Holland</em>, and will be examined there it being suspected that a great many of them are bound for <em>England</em>. Although this City did <reg orig="busle">bustle</reg> a little to maintain the Neutrality of this River, yet have the Capers and men of War free liberty to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> and come upon the same at their own pleasure, being likewise permitted and suffered to go out with the Merchant-men the very same Tide, whereas at other places they are bound to stay 2, or at least one Tide after their departure.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Here follow some Passages betwixt the Earl of <em>Glencarn</em>, and one Captain <em>Hill</em>, a Commander of ours in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>For my honoured Friend Captain <em>John Hill</em>, Governor of the Castle of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>I have seen a Letter of your directed to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>, wherein you have expressed so much fidelity to your unjust Masters from whom you are trusted, that it makes me conceive, if those principles of yours were rightly founded upon the warrantable grounds of Legality, you might yet redeem your former failings, and those principles of <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg> and <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> which now <reg orig="darkned">darkened</reg> in you, being out of their true Channel may shine eminently, when unclouded, from under those <reg orig="fatall">fatal</reg> <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and snares wherein many <reg orig="galant">gallant</reg> spirits in this Age are <reg orig="insnared">ensnared</reg>. Thus much I have conceived it fit to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> you, that I might undeceive you in some Opinions, upon which I find you ground your <pb n="6" />Arguments in your Letter to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>: As first, you look upon your Commonwealth (as you call it) as one firm and <reg orig="fixt">fixed</reg> Government, whilst the Lord knows there is at this instant no such thing in <em>England</em>; that Power <reg orig="wch">which</reg> was lately called a Parliament, being by the Trustees again <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> in <em><reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> hands, &amp; now none knows what Government he will pitch on; Another ground you <reg orig="goe">go</reg> upon in your Letter, that this Army now on foot by his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Command, for his and his long oppressed Peoples delivery, will soon vanish. It seems the distance you are at in this remote place, admits you not right information; you may indeed look upon this as the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> work, returning the abused spirits of all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Subjects to their duty to their King and Country; for now most of all <em>Scotland</em> are in Arms, and many <reg orig="galant">gallant</reg> English are already in Arms, and have marched through the greatest part of <em>England</em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces in this Kingdom; besides what is doing in <em>Ireland</em>, all Christian Princes are arming against those you now serve, and ere long will bring a flood of Strangers upon them, if the Lord <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not bring them to prevent their <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> by a timely submission to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> just command. I have given you this right view of the present condition of Affairs, because I have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> informed of your gallantry, that when you reckon betwixt God and you alone, and <reg orig="deales">deals</reg> impartially with <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg>, you may <reg orig="doe">do</reg> <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> that right to <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> that <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> God hath given you in the most approven way by him, wherein if <pb n="7" />you <reg orig="finde">find</reg> I can serve, you may freely command your Friend and Servant GLENCAIRN.</p>

<p><i>December 30.1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>For the Earl of Glencairn.</i></head>

<p><i>My Lord</i></p>

<p>Yours I received by your Trumpeter, wherein you may have put your self to much <reg orig="labor">labour</reg> to convince me of the erroneousness of my Principles, and of my blindness for want of Information; the truth is, I see not so far as I desire, but the more I see, the more I discover of the unwarrantableness of your Proceedings, going about to disquiet the Peace of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and to devour that little which the poor People have left them upon the pretence of a King, which I assure you I have disowned, and will still disclaim: And <reg orig="wheras">whereas</reg> you are pleased to inform me of the greatness of your Army, and of many who daily appear for you in <em>England</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, I am apt to believe that were you so <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> as you speak, your Lordship might have had far better Quarters in the Lowlands; but were you ten times the number which you are, it should not cause me to own that power which you call Kingly, or to betray that Trust committed to me by my just Masters, the deliverers under God of the poor oppressed and <reg orig="inslaved">enslaved</reg> People of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, from the <reg orig="Regall">Regal</reg> Tyranny and Bondage, but shall through the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> assistance approve <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to them, while <reg orig="cal'd">called</reg> by the name of JOHN HILL.</p>

<p><i>Butkven Castle, December 30. 1653.</i></p>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall in Sweden, Decmb. 22.</i></head>

<p>I shall give you an account of our journey from <em><reg orig="Gottenburg">Gothenburg</reg></em> to <em>Upsall</em>, which hath been very long and difficult, yet our God hath brought us safely the last night. We went out of <em><reg orig="Gottenburg">Gothenburg</reg></em> on Wednesday the 29 of November. The Magistrates came <reg orig="solemly">solemnly</reg> to take their leaves, the Citizens were in arms in the Market-place, and the Garrison <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> upon the works. As we passed them, they gave us <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="vollies">volleys</reg> of great and small shot. We could reach but two leagues that day, and yet came to our quarters an hour within night, where most of our wearied company must be contented to lie upon fresh straw, as in many other places where we lodged. The first night my Lord <em>Lagerfields</em> Secretary met us from the Court, whither he posted to give the Queen notice of our <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg>, and she sent him back to attend my Lord in his journey, and to see that we had accommodation, who with the <em><reg orig="Syndick">Syndic</reg></em> from from <!--repeated presumably a printers error--> <em><reg orig="Gottenberg">Gothenburg</reg></em> (whom the Town sent with us) gave us great assistance in our journey, and without whom we should not have <reg orig="perform'd">performed</reg> it in many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> longer. Our Train consisted of 83 saddle-horses, two Coaches, and about threescore <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>, few of them not carrying above one Trunk apiece, being very small, and drawn with one horse, and were brought in by the Country at every stage. For five or six days journey the ways were very rocky, but very passable throughout all our journey, and much the better because by command from the Queen, the Governors of Provinces had caused the <reg orig="high-ways">highways</reg> and bridges to be mended. The fifth <reg orig="days">day's</reg> journey we came to a City called <em>Scazez</em>, which is a <reg orig="Bishops">Bishop's</reg> See, a very old Town, and a large Church in it. The tenth <reg orig="days">day's</reg> journey Mr. <em>Andrew Potley</em> met us by the way, whom my Lord sent to the Court, with letters to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> them of our <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg>: with him came one Mr. <em>Lilly Chrone</em>, a servant of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, who was sent to visit my Lord in his journey, and to see that his Excellency should want no <reg orig="Accomodations">Accommodations</reg>, he brought with him letters from Prince <em>Adolph</em> the grand <pb n="9" />Master. The eleventh <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> journey we came to a <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> called <em>Erbrow</em>, where we met with letters from <em>England</em>, dated the 11 of November, whom my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em> left with <em>Dewy</em> (whom my Lord sent before) my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em> being got but a <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> journey before us, notwithstanding our stay at <em><reg orig="Gottenberg">Gothenburg</reg></em>. From this place the <em><reg orig="Syndick">Syndic</reg></em> of <em><reg orig="Gottenberg">Gothenburg</reg></em> posted to Court, to acquaint them with our being come so <reg orig="farre">far</reg>. The 14. <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> journey we came to a City called <em>Westraaz</em>: in this town, as in divers others, were quartered <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Companys">Companies</reg> of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Guards, and of them Guards were set at my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Lodging for security. At that City of <em>Erbrow</em> (where one Company was quartered) <em>Salmafius</em> his son was Captain. Here and at <em>Westraaz</em> I perceived that the Swedish Gentlemen who accompanied us, were desirous that we would stay for some time, but did not give any plain reason for it: whereupon his Excellency being resolved not to delay, went forward on his journey, the next day being Thursday, to a Town called <em>Encopin</em>, within 4 leagues of <em>Upsall</em>; Mt Lord asked the Swedish Gentlemen, if it were the <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> for him to send a letter to the <em>Master of the Ceremonies</em>, or any other Officer, to give them notice of his coming, they answered, It was not, but that they had sent before of themselves. This night a <reg orig="Poste">Post</reg> came with Letters from the <em>Grand Master</em> to Mr. <em>Lilly Chrone</em>, the contents whereof he signified to my Lord to be to this effect, That the Queen and her Court were astonished at his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> being advanced so <reg orig="farre">far</reg> in his journey in so short a time, which was much beyond their expectation; that her Majesty was resolved to receive him with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary respect and <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, for the which preparation could not be made in so short a time as we might come from <em>Encopin</em> to <em>Upsall</em>. It was therefore her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desire that his Excellency should repose himself <reg orig="untill">until</reg> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> at <em>Encopin</em>, and then to come 2 leagues to a <reg orig="Gentlemans">Gentleman's</reg> house, which the <em>Grand Master</em> had commanded to be provided for him. And from thence upon Thursday to come to <em>Upsall</em>. My Lord knew no other answer to this desire, and in <pb n="10" />this place; but to submit, to it the rather <reg orig="becaus">because</reg> our Baggage was not come up to us, for want of horses, with which Mr Stapylton continued, and took extraordinary pains and care, and endured many hardships in his attendance upon that charge.</p>

<p>Tuesday morning we went from thence towards Upsall, the weather continuing <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hard; half a league before we came to Town, the Master of the Ceremonies met his Excellency, and told him that the Queen had sent him to congratulate his safe arrival, and to conduct him to Upsall: about a quarter of a League from the Town, two Senators met his Excellency, that is, two of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State, they <reg orig="spake">spoke</reg> to him in the Swedish Tongue to the same effect that the Master of the Ceremonies had done, as I understood by their <reg orig="Interprether">Interpreter</reg>; My Lord answered them in English, that the respect which her Majesty did bear to the Commonwealth of England, appeared in her honourable reception of him their Servant, which he desired to <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> with thanks to her Majesty: they then brought his Excellency into a rich Coach of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, where the two Senators and Master of the Ceremonies <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> with him. There were divers other Coaches of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, with the Spanish Agents, and many Noble <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> Coaches, in all eighteen, every one with six horses, and a great many of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> servants on horse-back, they brought my Lord to my Lodging, and then left him: the Rooms of Entertainment, and four of five Bed-Chambers were furnished with the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Hangings and Beds: the Bed in his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Chamber richly Embroidered with Gold; about half an hour after, came in a Gentleman of the Bed-Chamber to my Lord, and told his Excellency that the Queen had sent to see how he did after his journey, to bid him <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg>, and my Lord returned his thanks to her Majesty: a little after him, Mr. Lagerfieldt came to see my Lord, and told him the Queen commanded him to come to his Excellency, and to take care that if he wanted any accommodation we might be <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg>.</p>

<pb n="11" />

<p>Then the Master of the Ceremonies desired of his Excellency a copy of his Credentials, which he had ready, and gave to him, who <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> them presently to the Queen, and left them with her, and returned back to accompany his Lordship to Supper. In a Lobby next to the withdrawing Room, is a constant guard of the Qa: <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, beyond that is a very fair Room, which was very well furnished, with a great deal of Plate, and many wax-Candles in it; two Tables were plentifully <reg orig="furnisht">furnished</reg>, the one for my Lord, the other for his Steward; over his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> seat was a Canopy of State; About the middle of Supper, the Master of the Ceremonies rose from his seat, and came to his Excellency, and with a great glass of Wine begun to him a health to the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>; my Lord told him, That it was neither agreeable to his <reg orig="Judgment">Judgement</reg>, nor to the practice of those whom he served in <em>England,</em> to drink or pledge any health. He pressed it earnestly upon my Lord, and his Lordship as earnestly refused it; and some words of a little heat passed betwixt them, but being in French, <reg orig="every body">everybody</reg> did not take notice of it; he then began a health to Capt. <em>James Whitlock</em>, who likewise refused it. Then he began a health to Dr <em>Whistler</em>, who refusing it, the Master of the Ceremonies in a slighting way desired him to give it some other name; the Dr. answered, That if he pleased he might call it a Eating a health; When the Master of the Ceremonies saw himself thus resisted, he was quiet, and seemed much displeased; and my Lord no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg>. After Supper, Mr <em>Lagerieldt</em> came to us again, to whom his Excellency related this passage at Supper, and desired that our Liberty, and the <reg orig="maner">manner</reg> of our Country might be reserved to himself and company; which he said was most fitting, and he would take care that the like should not be done hereafter. Then his Excellency desired my Lord <em>Lagerfieldt</em> to move the Queen, that if she pleased he might have his Audience before the Holidays, which he very willingly undertook to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, and it sped well, for the next say my Lord <em>Lagerfieldt</em> brought my Lord word that the Queen was very ready to <reg orig="gratifie">gratify</reg> his Request, and had appointed him audience upon Friday, till which time our Entertainment will be her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> charge: We are put to <unclear>great</unclear> inconvenience at this place for want of Beds, most of our company lying upon Straw; but the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Officers have sent into the Country, and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are in hopes to have some brought in here shortly. The Plague continues still at <em>Stockholm</em>, and there is no Speech of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> removing thither. My Lord is <reg orig="extreame">extreme</reg> weary of our long and great Feasting:</p>

<p>Yesterday the Queen was not well, but kept her bed, but this day she was abroad again. We shall prove Frenchmen; that Language is more spoken at the Court, <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other. By this time I presume you are weary of my long Letter; I shall reserve <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> after my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Audience, when you may look to be troubled again. The Audience is to be <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> afternoon.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, January 25. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>In my last I gave you an account of the Treasons discovered here, contrived through the pernicious practices of Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em>, since which his Highness the Archduke hath caused a strict Guard to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> kept in all the <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, and hath caused the Earl of <em>Bassigny</em> to be apprehended at Court, he was Governor of the Country of <em>Arthois</em>, and of the family of the Horns (who was formerly beheaded in the company of the Earl of Egmont, by order of the Duke of Alva at Brussels) <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as he was apprehended, he was sent prisoner to the Citadel of <em>Antwerp</em>, under a very strong guard, and presently some Commissioners were sent by the <reg orig="Privie">Privy</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to visit his Castle, called <em>Over-Ische</em>, two or three leagues from this City, where they found all his papers and writings, with a good round sum of money, which they brought away with them, and afterwards laid up in a place till further order, and till such time as he had been examined; which the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Privie">Privy</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and of the Parliament of <em>Malines</em> do intend to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> very suddenly in the said Castle of <em>Antwerp</em>: And <reg orig="becaus">because</reg> that this Lord is <reg orig="allyed">allied</reg> to the chiefest Families of this Country, they will not suffer men to say, His Imprisonment proceeds from Treason; but that he hath <reg orig="opprest">oppressed</reg> the people of his Government, and hath extorted from them <reg orig="severall">several</reg> contributions to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> his own ambition. His Mayor, Secretary, &amp; some other of his <reg orig="Domesticks">Domestics</reg>, are also taken after much trouble, and imprisoned. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Marquis of <em>Trasignie</em> is sent to his Government. As for the affairs of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em>, they still grow worse and worse, and they are like to be made the seat of war; for the French troops are marching thither to quarter there, in opposition to the rest: for it is said that the Marquis <em>Faber</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em>, doth conduct them, consisting of a hundred <reg orig="Troopes">Troops</reg> of Horse, and three thousand Foot, who do give out that at their arrival; they will drive out the <em>Lorainers</em>, and the Prince of <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> Forces, and afterwards settle those of Liege in their ancient Liberties. His Highness the Archduke rides now and then a hunting with the chief of the Court, the season of the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> affording no manner of action, and good order being taken to secure the garrisons round about him.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></i>, January 19.</head>

<p>His <em>Highness</em>, and his Council, having passed two Ordinances, they were this day ordered to be printed: The one is <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for repealing several Acts, and <reg orig="Resolvs">Resolves</reg> of Parliament, made for or touching the subscribing or taking the <em>Engagement</em></i>. Which stands repealed from the aforesaid nineteenth day of <em>January</em>. 1653. and is now printed and published.</p>

<p>The other is <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance declaring the offences herein mentioned, and no other, shall be adjudged <em>High Treason</em>, within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland, and Ireland</em>, and the dominions <pb n="13" />thereunto belonging.</i> Whereof I shall here set <reg orig="downe">down</reg> a <reg orig="briefe">brief</reg> extract, for caution to the People, and such of them, to whose sight (perhaps) the printed Ordinance <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> may not come.</p>

<p>The offences are these; <i>1. If any compass or imagine the of the <em>Lord Protector</em> for the tome being. 2. If any shall write, print, openly declare, preach, teach, or otherwise publish, that the <em>Lord Protector</em> and the people assembled in Parliament, are not the <reg orig="suprem">supreme</reg> Authority of this Commonwealth.</i> 3. If any shall declare (as aforesaid) <i>that the exercise of the chief Magistracy, in these dominions, is not in the <em>Lord Protector</em> <reg orig="asisted">assisted</reg> with his Council. 4. Or that the said Authority or <reg orig="Goverment">Government</reg> is Tyrannical, usurped, or unlawful. 5. Or that there is any Parliament now in being, or that hath any continuance, or any Law in force for continuing the Parliament, which is hereby declared to have been dissolved 20. <em>April. 1653.</em> and shall be adjudged, and taken so to be. 6. Or if any shall in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> endeavour to stir up or raise force against the Lord Protector, or present Government, for subversion or alteration thereof, and shall declare such endeavour by any open deed.</i> These offences shall be adjudged High Treason.</p>

<p>Moreover these following offenders and offences are (according to this Ordinance) to be adjudged within the compass of <em>Treason viz.</em> All endeavours of any mutiny (not being a member or members of any of the Armies) and to make <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, disobedient in any of the forces. All Inviters and procurers of Invasion from abroad upon any of these Dominions. All adherers to any forces of the common Enemies. All Plotters for surrender of any City, Town, Fort, <reg orig="Magazin">Magazine</reg> Ship, &amp;c. All counterfeiters of the great Seal, or of the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> Manual, Privy Signet, or privy Seal of the <em>Lord Protector</em> for the time being. All proclaimers or promoters of the pretended right of <em>Charles Stuart</em>, or any of that family, to the government of this Commonwealth, or any of the dominions thereto belonging. All Corresponders and Intelligencers with him, his mother, his brother <em>James Stuart</em>, or any of them. All Counterfeiters, Clippers, Diminishers, Falsifiers of <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, for gains sake. All Importers of false <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, &amp;c. together with their Counsellors, Aiders, and <reg orig="Abetters">Abettors</reg>, are to be taken, adjudged and executed as Traitors. <i>Provided, that nothing in this Ordinance as touching the monies and <reg orig="coyns">coins</reg> aforesaid, shall extend to make any corruption of blood, to any <reg orig="heire">heir</reg> of any offender, or to the prejudice of any wife of such offender. Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, that no person shall be prosecuted for any offence here mentioned, unless the prosecution be within one year after the offence committed.</i></p>

<p>Now the offences afore-named, and no other, are to be adjudged <em>High Treason</em>, notwithstanding any former Act or Statute, &amp; Provided nevertheless, and it is declared to be the true intent and <pb n="14" />purpose of this Ordinance, that the laws made in the reigns of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, and King <em>James</em>, against the Pope and See of <em>Rome, Jesuits, seminary Priests, and professors of the Romish Religion,</em> shall stand in full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>. All <reg orig="Abetters">Abettors</reg> of the Pope's Jurisdiction in <em>England</em>, all procurers &amp; promoters of <unclear>Balls</unclear> from the Pope to absolve people from their obedience to this Government, or to move any to promise obedience to any other Prince or power whatsoever.</p>

<p>Lastly, All <em>Jesuits, Priests</em>, &amp;c. borne in any of these Dominions, who have taken or shall take orders by authority derived from the See of <em>Rome</em>, and shall afterwards be found within this Commonwealth; These offenders <reg orig="afore-mentioned">aforementioned</reg> shall be adjudged and executed as Traitors.</p>

<p><i>And here I cannot let pass this last Proviso, without this remark thereupon; That the People of God in these dominions have abundant cause to bless the Lord, who hath put it into the hearts of our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, to make such provision against the faction (called Religion) of Popery, and those desperate engineers, the Popish Priests, who seek the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of us, our Country, and of the Gospel of Christ, which is above all other considerations. And truly, there was never more need <reg orig="then">than</reg> now of such a Law; seeing Popery is become the great interest of that family which the Lord hath cast out before us. If ever they procure any force or power again, it must be upon a Popish account. And that their endeavours <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> wholly upon that foot, is evident by <em>Charles <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> many application to the Court of <em>Rome</em>, which are commonly known; and to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, besides his Alliance and combination, to and with other Popish Princes: so that the grand security of the reformed Religion is absolutely involved in this present form of Government, and the utter exclusion of that family of <em>Stuarts</em> <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>.</i></p>

<p>The above cited Ordinance you may have more at large from his <reg orig="highness">highness'</reg> Printers.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg> January 23. stilo novo</i></head>

<p>Our Commissioners are arrived at last out of <em>England</em>, and have brought us great hopes of a Peace as we hear. They have made report to the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Convention is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> called to accomplish the business: God give good success for a happy conclusion. There are <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Merchantmen arrived in <em>Zealand</em>, from <em>Bordeaux, Rochel, Nantes</em>, and other parts; two private men of War have brought in there two English Prizes, richly laden, one of 180 Lasts, and the other 200 Lasts. Notwithstanding our great hopes of Peace with <em>England</em>: we shall in no wise slacken our hands in our Sea preparations, and we do hope to have a greater Fleet out at Sea, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever we had yet, at the beginning of March next.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<p>In <em>Zealand</em> they will not <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of the peace, but do persist for a war; they there, that the English will not have a peace unless they buy it at a dear rate, and with ready money; which the <em>Zelanders</em> look upon as a Peace that will be dishonourable, troublesome, disadvantageous, and not lasting: and therefore they think that the other Provinces ought not to second them, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> they had rather die gallantly with their arms in their hands, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be <reg orig="reproacht">reproached</reg> of having made an infamous peace with the <em>English</em>, but these are only the discourses of the people, and of those that get by the <reg orig="ruines">ruins</reg> of others: but we that are Merchants must pray and desire peace, for if these miserable wars continue, we shall be quite undone for want of Trade, which is the only support of these Countries.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dalkeith</em> January 17.</head>

<p>The Enemy are part in <em>Badgenoth</em>, and part in the Laird of <em><reg orig="Grants">Grant's</reg></em> Bounds. The <reg orig="partie">party</reg> that Colonel <em>Morgan</em> drew from <em>Aberdeen</em> towards <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> could not get over <em>Spey</em>, the waters so high. The <em>Boggy-geith</em> is a very useful Garrison, the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Huntlies">Huntley's</reg></em> Lady being removed to <em>Strathbogie</em>: The Enemy are much startled at <em><reg orig="Argiles">Argyle's</reg></em> son <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> revolt, and think there is a greater design in the same than is presently apparent. There is to be a great meeting in <em><reg orig="Argile">Argyle</reg></em> of all <em>Clan-<reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em>; it is said to offer some proposals to the Commander in Chief. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> yet lies wounded in some part of <em>Monteith</em>.</p>

<p>Om Thursday last <em>Athol</em> and <em>Lorn</em> were at the house of <em>Ballock</em> <reg orig="nere">near</reg> <em>Lough Tay</em>, since which <em>Athol</em> is very sick, and in <em><reg orig="Weems">Weems'</reg></em> Garrison; and <em>Lorn</em> pretends his father is not <reg orig="reconcileable">reconcilable</reg> to him, whereupon he goes not home. The 14 instant the Captain Lieutenant to Colonel <em>Okey</em> with a party from S. <em>Johnstons</em>, fell Into the Quarters of about 40 of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse about <em>Strabaughan</em> near <reg orig="litte">little</reg> <em><reg orig="Dunkel">Dunkeld</reg></em> under Lieutenant <em>Ramsey</em>, took 10 Prisoners, and 16 Horses, and killed two on the place. But Captain <em><reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg></em> Troop from <em>Drummond</em> had not so good success, for the Lieutenant being sent out with a <reg orig="partie">party</reg> of 30 Horse to rescue some sheep taken by the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg> near the Garrison, pursued so far as to rout them; but another <reg orig="partie">party</reg> of 60 Horse, and 100 or 200 Foot lying in Ambuscado, our men had a very difficult retreat, yet 20 of them charged through, the Lieutenant was killed, the Cornet, one Corporal, two Trumpeters, and 7 Troopers taken, and the Quartermaster wounded. Divers of the Enemy were killed, and amongst the rest (is supposed) <em>Wogan</em>, for he and the English with him gave the first charge.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Plymouth</em>, January 20.</head>

<p>Since the writing of my Letter, Captain <em>Godfrey</em> in the <em>Middleburgh</em> is come in, and hath brought with him two ships laden with Wine and <reg orig="Brandie">Brandy</reg>, the one of which I suppose will prove a very good prize, she is about 300 tons, and the other is more questionable.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is lately published a most excellent Treatise, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg></p>

<p>&#x261e; Z&Omega;OTOMIA, or Observations on the present manners of the English, briefly <reg orig="anatomizing">anatomising</reg> the Living by the Dead, with an useful <reg orig="derection">direction</reg> of the Mountebanks of both Sexes, by <em>Richard Whitlock</em> Doctor in <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, late Fellow of <em>All Souls</em> <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in <em>Oxford</em>. Printed for <em>Humphrey Moseley</em> at the <em><reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Arms</em> in S. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>PARTHENISSA, that most <reg orig="fam'd">famed</reg> Romance,</i></head>

<p>Composed by the Lord <em>Broghill</em>, and dedicated to the Lady <em>Northumberland</em>. Printed for <em>Richard Lownds</em> at the <em>White Lion</em> in S. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>