<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol205">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 205</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, May 11. to <em>Thursday</em>, May 18. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, May 4.</i></head>

<p>The coming of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monck</em> to this Town is a welcome business, and he was received with all demonstrations of affection. At his <reg orig="arivall">arrival</reg>, he went first to <em>Dalkeith</em>, to give Order about the Forces, and receive an Account of things from him who had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> Commander in chief. After that, his Resolution being known to come hither, the Magistrates of the Town provided to receive him with such <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> as became them in duty to Express. He and his Officers, were met at the <reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg> end, by the Provost and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and the English Judges in their Formalities; with whom he and his Officers, having alighted from their horses, walked along the <pb n="1" />High-street up to the Cross, which was set forth with hangings and other Ornaments, as it was wont to be when they used to proclaim their Kings; and there they first proclaimed his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c. by sound of Trumpet and Drums beating. After that was done, the General and his Officers were conducted to a dinner that had been prepared at the charge of the Town, where nothing was wanting that might <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> the good will and fair respects of the Inhabitants. At night they ended all with <reg orig="Fire-works">Fireworks</reg>; so that <reg orig="its">it's</reg> to be believed this place will continue faithful to his Highness upon all occasions.</p> 

<head level="3">From Paris, May 16. S.N.</head>

<p>The 24 of this Month is the day designed here for the Coronation of the King at Rhemes, and all things are in preparation, and the Nobility ordered to give attendance according to the <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> Custom. The Duke of Orleans, which founds not well, and may (if the Cardinal continue his Reign) turn very much to his prejudice. Many men wonder what the reason should be, why he should continue thus resolute and obstinate against the Court, and all the Importunities used with him from time to time, by Message from the King; but others say, this ought to be imputed to his daughter <reg orig="Madamoiselle">Mademoiselle</reg>, who is a great votary to the Prince of Conde and his Interest, and having a great power over her father, doth by her <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> keep him at this <pb n="2" /> distance. Others again there are that say, the Princes of the blood of <reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg> party, do look to have a day once more, wherein they may lift out the Cardinal, and that they want not a sufficient party, even here in Paris, that would seen <reg orig="shew">show</reg> themselves, were there an opportunity. Yea, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> talked as if <reg orig="farr">far</reg> the major part would be inclined that way, because since the late Exile, and return of the Cardinal with the King, all things have been worse <reg orig="then">than</reg> before; the Parliament hath been baffled, and the people oppressed more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, whereas they thought by letting in the King they should have shut out all their miseries: But now seeing themselves deceived, the name of Conde is again in some reputation among them, and they <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> out openly enough in expressions against the Cardinal and his Government, whom they look upon as ruling both King and Kingdom, and therefore he and the rest of the prime Ministers of States that are his Creatures, bear all the blame. Murmur and Mutiny is here the very genius of the people: so that they do not carry such Countenance; of joy and satisfaction as were wont to <reg orig="fore-run">forerun</reg> a day of Coronation.</p>

<p>That which I writ you in my last concerning his yielding up of Brisack and Alsatia by Count Harcourt to the Spaniard, proves to be a <reg orig="mis-information">misinformation</reg>; for, we find the contrary now, and Letters give assurance of his good inclination to continue faithful to France, and that to that purpose all things are in a manner accorded betwixt him and his Majesty:</p> <pb n="3" /> 

<p>Preparations are making with all speed, that his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Armies may take the Field especially that which is to contest with Flanders under the Command of Marchal Turein, because there lies the <reg orig="eye-sore">eyesore</reg> of France, and most need of Action, in regard the Spaniard will be in the field, and appear very considerable, with his own Forces, and the Duke of <reg orig="Lorains">Lorain's</reg> Army (more at his devotion now <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever) and the Forces of the Prince of Conde; by which means it is like to prove an active Summer between both the Crowns. But assure <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> much of the Affairs of this Nation depends upon a Peace with England, which if they can get by their Ambassadors treating at London, will prove a welcome business; but what to think of it as yet they know not.</p>

<p><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and his Retinue are always talking of a departure, and preparing for it. <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> is that which (when it can be had) must set them packing: in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> they <reg orig="loyter">loiter</reg> up and down betwixt City and Country, to see what the event of things will be, and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> steer their course accordingly. The Highlanders in Scotland are much talked of again, and they promise mountains, are again presented to the French Court, as a considerable Body.</p>

<head level="3">By the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of his Highness, setting apart Tuesday the 23. Of this present May for a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> day of Thanksgiving, for the Peace concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Provinces, and for the late seasonable Rain.</i></p> <pb n="4" /> 

<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the outstretched arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment, and wonder, Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter and they will <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, and indeed the dispensations of the Lord have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> as if he had said, England thou art my first-born, my delight amongst the Nation, under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us.</p>

<p>The Lord having added another Link to this golden Chain of his loving kindness by giving us a Peace with our <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> the United Provinces, (whereby he hath not only stopped a great issue of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, but we trust also given us hearts to unite our <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> and strength for the mutual defence of each other) calls for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>

<p>It is therefore thought fit to set apart Tuesday being the 23 of this present May, as a day for Praise and for the thankful <reg orig="acknowledgment">acknowledgement</reg> of this blessing of Peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other blessings.</p>

<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up, that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> Famine, and did cause the Beasts of the field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into the expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord <pb n="5" />imparted this mercy to us, did any amongst us, foreknow it was coming, was it not by stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that immediately before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy? And doth not this bespeak? 1. That the manner of conveying this mercy is the best part of the mercy.</p>

<p>2. That the Lord has not cast us off, that his Spirit yet strives with us, that he hath a People of his love among us, and loves the Nation so far as to provoke it to be in love will calling upon the name of the Lord for better things than Corn and Wine.</p>

<p>3. That he knows best how and when to answer the expectation of the Husbandman, and when to hear, even the mourning of the brute Beast, who <reg orig="wil">will</reg> yet much more hear the desires of them that fear him, and that in the fittest season.</p>

<p>4. That the Heavens having thus declared the glory of God, and the Earth answering thereunto in its fruitfulness, Why should not we be melted and <reg orig="softned">softened</reg>, humbling <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> under the so marvellous kindnesses, and abounding unto all fruitfulness in every good word and work of love; And if every place hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> made partaker of his showers, Why should not we (laying aside our differences) be <reg orig="inlarged">enlarged</reg> also each to other?</p>

<p>5. That seeing the Lord hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> thus universal in this Mercy, Why should we not universally turn from the National Evils and vain practices which are yet too superstitiously and customarily exercised amongst us, which we need not repeat here, because they are too well known, and we <pb n="6" /> trust <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg> by those godly Ministers who shall be called to Preach unto the People upon this occasion? Conclude we with the words of David, <em>Psalm</em> 107. V.</p>

<p>30. <i>Then they are glad, because they be quiet, so he bringeth them unto their desired Haven.</i></p>

<p>31. <i>O that men would prefer the Lord for his goodness and for his <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> works to the children of men.</i></p>

<p>32. <i>Let them exalt him also in the Congregation of the people, and praise him in the assembly of the Elders.</i></p>

<p>33. <i>He turneth Rivers into a wilderness, and the water springs into dry ground.</i></p>

<p>34. <i>A <reg orig="fruitfull">fruitful</reg> Land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell in it.</i></p>

<p>35. <i>He turneth the Wilderness into a standing water, and dry ground into water springs.</i></p>

<p>36. <i>And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a city for habitation.</i></p>

<p>37. <i>And sow the Fields, and plant Vineyards, which may yield fruits of increase.</i></p>

<p>38. <i>He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly, and suffers not their cattle to decrease.</i></p>

<p><i>O that Men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> works to the children of Men.</i></p>

<head level="3">Given at Whitehall this 9th of May, 1654.</head>

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen May 3.</i> S. N.</head>

<p>It is certainly believed here, that the Peace between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> is fully concluded and ratified; which causeth great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> among this people. This day Don <em>Antonio Piemontelli</em>, late Spanish Ambassador by the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> arrived here; It is said he will pass through <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em> in his return homewards to his Master.</p> <pb n="7" /> 

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Regensborgh">Regensburg</reg>, May 2.</i> S.N.</head>

<p>Some of his <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Court give forth, as if he were resolved to continue here yet some four weeks: In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the States labour almost day and night for the perfection of some of the most necessary business; amongst others, the capitulation made with the Roman King at his Coronation, and the like things of great importance.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick April 29.</i> S.N.</head>

<p>Here passeth nothing worthy of Intelligence, only the Treasurer of <em>Poland</em> is daily expected, his Message is Moneys, for which he will engage the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> part of the Pound-chamber, or <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg>-house; his Negotiation I believe will find but slight entertainment; yet by reason of the differences among themselves, they must <reg orig="doe">do</reg> something to <reg orig="gratifie">gratify</reg> the King, lest he take part with the Protestant against them.</p>

<p><em>May</em> 11. An Ordinance was published for further Doubling upon, and finishing the Sale of Deans, <reg orig="Deans">Deans'</reg> and <reg orig="Chapters">Chapters'</reg> lands, and of Manors of Rectories, Glebe-lands, &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels May 15. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The publication of the Peace in <em>England</em>, doth beget new life in the Merchants of these parts; only the Town of <em>Dunkirk</em> doth lose very much by it; for the <em>Holland</em> Factors that have driven the Trade there during the wars, for their Masters, are now returned back from whence they came.</p>

<p>The Imperial City of <em>Bremen</em>, <reg orig="scituated">situated</reg> upon the River of <em>Weser</em>, doth suffer very much; for the Swedish <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Koningsmark</em> doth hold it <pb n="8" /> <reg orig="blockt">blocked</reg> up, having beset all the chief passages to it; which the Towns of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Lubeck, <reg orig="Luxenbourgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, and others, having seriously considered how <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> it may happen to them for the future, they have sent their Commissioners to the Court of Sweden, to mediate in the behalf of the said City, as their <reg orig="Neighbor">Neighbour</reg> and <reg orig="Allie">Ally</reg>, being one of the Hans Towns.</p>

<p>These Countries here receive great benefit by the lying of the English Fleet continually in the Channel, or in sight of the French Coasts, whereby the French are fain to keep their Army upon their own Territories, to guard their Coasts, and reinforce their <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> and strong Holds for fear of some <reg orig="surprisall">surprisal</reg> by the English; so that these Parts are all quiet at present, but it is not likely they will continue long so; for there is a <reg orig="Rumor">Rumour</reg> that the French Army under the Command of the <reg orig="Mareschall">Marshal</reg> of <em>Turenne</em>, is already on their march towards these <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>: And because they may be ready likewise to oppose the French. The Archduke hath given order for the speedy marching of the whole Spanish Army to a <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> <em>Francis</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em> with his two Sons is gone from hence to take upon him the Command of the <em>Lorain</em> Forces, &amp; to conduct them also to the <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>; He hath taken a good <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of Money with him to pay his <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and to have them sworn, that they will be <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> unto him.</p>

<p>The Archduke hath given possession of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> </em>Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorains">Lorain's</reg></em> whole estate to his Brother <em>Francis</em>: This hath made him, the more enraged <pb n="9" />against his Brother, whom he did sufficiently hate before; but he not being in a condition by reason of his Imprisonment to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> him any mischief, the other doth not much value the weapon of his tongue, and whose words are now taken by all in <reg orig="generall">general</reg> for no slander: They looking upon Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> for a <reg orig="vertuous">virtuous</reg>, affable, and courageous Prince.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris May 20. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Mareshall">Marshal</reg> of <em>Turenne</em>, who goes to <reg orig="comand">command</reg> his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Army, intends to depart <!--typo or reg??-->hince this week or the next to his charge. And the Court (some suppose) will <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>Rheims</em> this day <reg orig="sevennight">seven nights</reg> to the Coronation of the King; in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, they have given order to every frontier for the safeguard of their Country; and have sent an Express into the County of <em>Franche counte</em> to the end to frustrate the design, whereof they have advice, that the Spaniard is hatching there, to break the neutrality of that Province. Yesterday an Answer was given to the complaints of the Protestants of <em>Montpelier</em>, concerning the business of the Consulship, which shall be divided according to their desire; but with this Restriction, That the nomination of the Protestant Consuls shall be ratified by his Majesty: and that they shall give the precedence to the <reg orig="Catholicks">Catholics</reg>. Wherewith the Protestant Commissioners are not altogether satisfied.</p>

<p>The Ambassador of <em>Holland</em> is said to be in dispute with him of <em>Savoy</em> about the <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> at the ceremony of the Coronation of the King. He likewise complains that the French have <pb n="10" />taken and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> still take many of their ships, and make no restitution nor satisfaction for injuries and damages done them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></i> May 6.</head>

<p>About the 3 instant, Major-general <em>Drummond</em> came from <em>Middleton</em> to <em>Lough-Tay</em>, and <em>Glencairn</em> with about 100 Horse; and one <em>Murray</em> with the like number of Foot, came into <em>Athol</em>, about the 4 instant. They give out they passed by Colonel <em>Morgan</em> in a Mist; but its supposed they came by <em>Loughaber</em>. They intend to hasten their Levies, and speed to the North to surround Col. <em>Morgan</em>, if they can.</p>

<p><!--Montrose??? Typo/blurred??--><em>Monirose</em> is raising his Levies at <em>Branar</em>, and some small parties sent by <em>Middleton</em> are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with him. They give out that they expect <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, when their Affairs are a little<em> </em>more ripe. Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> five Companies are come up: Gen. <em>Monck</em> will be at <em>Sterling</em> next week. The Ministers in this City prayed for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, the very next day after the Lord Protector was proclaimed, and the Union published.</p>

<p>The Enemy have received Provisions contrary to expectation lately by two ships from <em>Dunkirk</em>, laden with Men, Arms, and Ammunition.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rye,</i> May 12.</head>

<p>The little <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> of <em>Ostend</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> much vex and torment the Fishermen upon this coast, under pretence of seeking after French Vessels. This week, a Barque being on her way between <em>Diepe</em> and this place, with 4 <unclear>small guns</unclear>, attempted to take her; but the Barque having many Passengers, as well English as French, defended <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> so <pb n="11" />gallantly, that in a little dispute the <em>Ostender</em> lost seven men, and had some wounded. It is probable the Barque might have got away, had it not <reg orig="bin">been</reg> for a shot between wind and water that sunk her down immediately; but most of the Passengers were saved.</p>

<head level="3">Whitehall May 16.</head>

<p><i>An Ordinance for continuing an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act of Parliament <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners, until the <em>31</em> of <em>May</em> instant.</i></p>

<p>BE it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, that one Ordinance of the Eighteenth of April 1654. <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance so further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an act <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An act for the relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>, be continued, and shall stand in force until the 31 day of May instant; and that the several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any the Estates <reg orig="reall">real</reg> or <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> of any of the prisoners, or other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in, or by the said Act, nor shall otherwise <reg orig="intermedle">interfere</reg> in the execution of the said act, or of any the powers or authorities given by the same, until the said 31 day of may instant, otherwise then as in the said Ordinance is limited, and that all other Acts or things to be done by the said respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the said Act from <pb n="12" />henceforth until the one and thirtieth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, shall be and are hereby declared to be utterly null and void.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Upsal</em> April 15.</i></head>

<p>You cannot but by this time understand that which will please you; that (blessed be God) my Lord Ambassador is <reg orig="com">come</reg> to a good conclusion of his business here: For, when by Letters from <em>England</em> he understood the state of your treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>, it being in such condition that the affair in this place could have no reflection upon it, it was then high time for his Lordship to rouse up his Spirits, and put on the business more than formerly; which took so good effect, that in Fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after this beginning we were come to a full agreement; and now there remains nothing but the signing and sealing of the Articles, which I presume will be done upon the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> return hither; she is gone to see her Mother, and to meet with the Prince Royal, her Successor, to <reg orig="conferr">confer</reg> about the great business of her Resignation of the Government; we look for her to be back again the next week, in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> my Lord Ambassador is forced to make another halt.</p>

<p>All the great Ones, Officers, Senators, and Courtiers are likewise gone out of Town, and have left the <unclear>Muses</unclear> very desolate in this Academy, which at the best is no Paradise, so that I suppose my Lord Ambassador will, as soon as the business is completed, remove from this place, and be drawing homeward.</p> <pb n="13" /> 

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></i> May 12. <em>stilo novo.</em></head>

<p>We had no Letter last week from England; the <reg orig="Pacquet">Packet</reg> was Robbed about Brussels, and most Letters opened: Some State-Thieves (I believe) met with it.</p> 

<p>As I wrote in my last, my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> hath now finished the Affair at <em>Upsall</em>. We expect him here within a Fortnight, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> coming over the <reg orig="Baltick">Baltic</reg> Sea to Lubeck in a ship of Thirty six <reg orig="Gunns">Guns</reg> appointed by the Queen of Sweden.</p> 

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith</i> May 6.</head>

<p>The <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> forces <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not now increase, and I hope they will shortly diminish very much, a great part of them having more mind to come in, than to stay out in Arms.</p>

<p><em>Glencairn</em> is come into Athol with about Two hundred Horse and Foot to assist Montross in his Levies; and now to help a little their dying hopes, they give out that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart </em>will be here shortly. I have nothing further at this time, but refer you to the ensuing Declaration; a Copy whereof followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in Chief of all the Forces in SCOTLAND</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness and affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the Liberties and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="Expence">Expense</reg> of so much Blood and Treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more <reg orig="then">then</reg> there equal proportion with <em>England</em>) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace; Yet divers lewd persons broken in their Fortunes, and <pb n="14" /> dissolute in their Lives, are run into Rebellion, and being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Brethren, Tutors, Masters, and People among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable People of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in Peace. And to the end that no Peaceable means might be left <reg orig="unattempted">not attempted</reg>, for the prevention thereof, I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, do Declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are accepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next <em>English</em> Garrison, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned, for any Offence, Spoil or Plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion, (the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.) And I do Declare, That if any Parents, Brethren, or Tutors, who have assisted and connived at any their Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publications hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, to tender themselves, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are hereby freely pardoned; But if otherwise, then the said Parents, Brethren and Tutors, who have so offended, shall be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion. And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion, without the knowledge or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth; I do therefore hereby Declare, That if the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth, to render him or themselves, within twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after publication hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the said Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned; But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said Parish and Presbytery, Two shillings six pence a day for each <reg orig="Horsman">Horseman</reg>, and Ten pence a day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their ordinary Sess<!--Unable to find meaning or replacement for sess - possibly slang for Assessment?-->, out of the said Presbytery, which the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English Garrison is hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> and receive monthly, during the time the said persons shall so continue in Rebellion. And I do likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into Rebellion, or attempt so to do, and safely to deliver him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next <em>English</em> Garrison; and in case of resistance, to take such weapons as they can get, and to fight the said person or persons; and if they shall kill any of the said persons <pb n="15" />so resisting, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive as a reward of their good service, all such Moneys, Goods, Horses, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, as the said Rebellious Persons are then possessed of, besides full satisfaction for their pains and travel therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seafirth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>,<em> Donald Mac-Donald</em> Laird of <em>Glengary</em>, and Major General <em>Dayel</em>; I do hereby therefore declare, That what person or persons soever of this Nation, (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal Contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any <em>English</em> Garrison, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only be pardoned for any thing he or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but also shall receive as a Reward of his good service, the sum of Two hundred pounds sterling, for every person so killed or brought prisoner, as aforesaid. And lastly, for the encouragement of all <reg orig="peacable">peaceable</reg> and well affected People, both <em>English</em> and <em>Scots</em>, I do hereby Declare, That what <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> shall be done to their Persons, Goods or <reg orig="Geer">Gear</reg>, for their good affection to the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>, the same shall be again repaired out of the Estates of such as have done the <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, or out of the Estates of the Friends and harbourers of such <reg orig="wrong doers">wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the Parish, presbytery, or Shire, where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, or give the <em>English</em> Forces such timely notice thereof, that the said <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> may be apprehended by them. And I do hereby require all Provosts, Bailiffs, and Chief Officers of Head Burghs, in their several Burghs, to cause these presents to be duly Published and Posted up, according to the usual form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me, in writing, under his or their hands.</p>

<p><i>Given under my Hand at <em>Dalkeith</em> this 4. Day of May 1654.</i> George Monck.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, May 16.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Major of <em>London </em>and some of the Aldermen dined with His Highness.</p>

<p>No News by the last Post from <em>Scotland</em>, not from <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">&#x261e; <i>The FRENCH COOK</i></head>

<p>Prescribing the way of <unclear>making</unclear> ready all sorts of Meats, Fish, and Flesh, with the proper sauces: together with the whole skill of Pastry Work, and a <unclear>Treatise</unclear> of Conserves both Dry and Liquid. The second Edition <unclear>Concocted</unclear> and enlarged; Sold by <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Adams</em> at the <em><unclear>Tallotynnar St.</unclear> <reg orig="Dunstans">Dunstan's</reg></em> Church in <em>Fleet Street.</em></p>
 <hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>