<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol201">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 201</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, April 13. to <em>Thursday</em>, April 20. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<p>Whereas there is a Letter directed by the <em>Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers</em>, under the following Title, which is of serious and universal concernment, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought meet here to make it <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>

<p><i>To all the faithful Servants of Jesus Christ, Especially to such as labour in the Words and Doctrine, through <em>England </em>and <em>Wales</em></i>.</p>

<p><i>Dear Brethren,</i></p>

<p>There being nothing under Heaven of greater importance, then the preaching of the glorious Gospel of Jesus Christ, you cannot but be very sensible of what weight and concernment it <pb n="1" />is to take a right estimate of all that offer themselves, and to pass a due approbation of such only, as Christ himself would have admitted to that great <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>. A great part of which service in this Nation, the Lord by his Providence hath cast upon us, and is by us undertaken, as with much fear and trembling, so with a deep sense, that the effectual accomplishment thereof will much depend upon the Testimonials exhibited to us, concerning the holy and good Conversation of such as seek for approbation from us. Wherefore considering how easily and frequently abuses creep into businesses of this nature, partly through the <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> of those who are ill-deserving, and partly through the non attendance of others, who are better minded. For the prevention of any such miscarriage, we have thought it our duty, hereby humbly and earnestly to beseech all the people of God throughout the Land, who shall send any Certificate to us, that they would not take things upon the opinion and report of others, but (according to the good provision made in the Ordinance, designing us to this Service) to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their own personal knowledge and experience, so as neither any, whom God accepteth, may want the testimony of his servants, nor any be recommended by them whom he disalloweth; lest guilt be contracted by you, to whose testimonials so much is referred, as that through carelessness or partiality therein, very unworthy men may unawares be admitted, to the dishonour of God, the prejudice of his Church, and the utter <pb n="2" />frustrating of the pious intentions of our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, and we also be accounted blame-worthy, if through your misinformation, way being made for our mistakes, we should at any time act amiss. This we are, and shall be more liable to, by reason of the difficulty of our making discovery in a short time of several <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> graces and gifts, in so full and ample a manner s would be desired for just satisfaction, without the faithful help of such as having been observers of them, and conversant with them, do more fully know, not only the tenor of their doctrine, but the constant course of their lives. It being a much more <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> thing to be able to describe what a godly man should be, then to be one indeed. Nor may we doubt, but there are some men, who having first willingly deceived themselves by a false apprehension and persuasion of their own condition and estate in grace, will think it <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to deceive us, by giving a false account of that condition. But as such shall do well to consider, that he who <reg orig="trieth">tryeth</reg> the Spirit is not mocked, neither can any thing be hid from his eyes and that this must undergo another kind of Test then this slender scrutiny of ours, when the secret of all hearts shall be laid open, and brought to light. So our Brethren may likewise please to consider what opportunity is put into their hand by this Address made unto them for the avoiding of such mistakes, and the inconveniences which may follow upon them through their neglect; besides the blot which will deservedly stick to them, not only for the present, but with <pb n="3" />posterity and succeeding times, forasmuch as the Certificates now exhibited will appear upon Record. For the prevention whereof, we humbly conceive and hope, that this friendly and <em>brotherly intimation</em> will be accounted seasonable, and by the blessing of God, be found useful for the successful carrying on that work which we have in hand. And therefore, <em>Dear friends, and much beloved in the Lord</em>, give us leave again, earnestly to beseech you in the bowels of Jesus Christ, as you tender the Honour of the great God himself, whose servants we all are, the precious souls of his people, purchased by the <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> of his Son, the advancement and propagation of his Gospel through all the parts of this Land and Nation, whereunto we belong, so to lend us the joint assistance both of your servant prayers and due informations, that hereby the Work may be carried on more prosperously, and we more encouraged to attend it.</p>

<p><i>Signed in the Name, and at the Request of the Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, by</i></p>

<p>Francis Rons.</p>
<p>John Arrowsmith.</p>
<p>William Goff.</p>
<p>Stephen Marshall.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></i> 24 S.N.</head>

<p>The English Fleet which keeps in the <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg> doth give us <reg orig="continuall">continual</reg> Alarms here, and the more, because they write from <em>Rochell</em>, that they <pb n="4" /><reg orig="doe">do</reg> see <reg orig="severall">several</reg> great ships to appear on that side as if they had <reg orig="som">some</reg> design upon the coast on <em>Xaintongne</em> or <em>Bretagne</em>, and this men do firmly believe by reason of a report they have there of my Lo: Protectors dismissing of the French Ambassador to return into <em>France</em>; so that they have given order to all in <reg orig="generall">general</reg> to stand upon their guards, and the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshall</reg> of <em>Milleray</em> hath placed <reg orig="severall">several</reg> of his <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> up and down the coasts of <em>Britain</em>, and fortified the Fort of <em>Louis</em>, in order to the security of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, in case of landing. But we hope here there is no such design in hand intended against this Country, but rather a firm Peace with us as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as <em>Holland</em>, we being as much for it to the Protector. <reg orig="Yesterdays">Yesterday's</reg> Post brought us the certain news of the signing and sealing of the Treaty between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p>All honest men here are glad of it; only <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his party take it to heart; he is still in expectation of his money to carry him from hence, he would fain be gone, and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> would <reg orig="dispence">dispense</reg> with some of his Pistols, which are very scarce with him at this time. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> being come safe to <em>Nantes</em>, where it was said he should have his liberty, notwithstanding all those fair promises, is secured in the Castle, and not <reg orig="suffred">suffered</reg> to stir abroad, nor any of his friends to come to visit him. The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazarin</em> hath given order for the making of a very fine Garden and Orchard to the <em>Bois de Vincennes</em>, a house about a mile from this city, where the said Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> was lately imprisoned, and <pb n="5" />which hath been made use of for that purpose, is now <reg orig="design'd">designed</reg> for a <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>; where he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he will keep all manner of beasts and Deer for the Game, that so he need not go far from Paris, when he intends to take his pleasure. The <reg orig="Curat">Curate</reg> that thought to have gotten great matters by complaining of the Priest for preaching in his Sermon, That is was <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> for any of the Parish to make confession to what Priest they pleased, whereof I mentioned in my last, is ordered to be <reg orig="banish'd">banished</reg> for making such a disturbance when the Priest was a preaching, and the Priest to be <reg orig="resto'd">restored</reg> to his Office again.</p>

<p>The Protestant Commissioners have had Audience lately, at which time they remonstrated to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Council the sad consequences of their not doing of them Justice according to the Edicts; whereupon they returned then answer in very fair words, and that shortly they would effectually answer their desires. The <reg orig="Hang-man">Hangman</reg> is this day to deface and pull down the Arms and <reg orig="Scutcheons">Escutcheons</reg> of the House of the Pr: of <em>Conde </em>in this City.</p>

<p>The King still delights himself with dancing of his Ball, where the last time he <reg orig="danc'd">danced</reg> it, one of the workmen of the Machines, fell down not two steps from the King, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> himself. The Pope we hear is still alive; upon his <reg orig="swouning">swooning</reg> away, they reported him to be dead. It is said the Venetians have received lately a notable defeat in <em>Dalmatia</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rysell April</i> 5.</head>

<p>The Lorainers conducted by the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em><pb n="6" />, are now quartered between <em>Douay</em> and this City, take all the Cattle they can meet withal in those places where they come; Men, Women &amp; Children are made prisoners by them, and made to pay them <reg orig="Ransomes">Ransoms</reg> according to their discretion, or for want of <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> are plundered and violated. And where they meet with any Churches Castles, or strong houses, where the poor people are fled with their Goods; it so be they cannot take them by force of Arms, they set them on fire, as <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> no longer ago than yesterday, where we saw on fire a Village called <em>Gamen</em>, a mile and a half from this City, lying upon the Road towards<em> Douay</em>. It seems that the Country is given to the Lorainer for plunder, for they live worse with the Inhabitants than any Enemy would do. <reg orig="Wherfore">Wherefore</reg> the poor people dare not stay any longer in their houses, when they <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> of their approach, but fly to the next Cities, and there sell their Cattle and <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> for a small value; and when that little money is spent, they are ready to perish in the streets for want of <reg orig="substistance">subsistence</reg>. In short, the Miseries which the People suffer by the Lorainers, are not to be <reg orig="express">expressed</reg>, nor indeed fit to be <reg orig="publisht">published</reg> to the world; tending so much to the shame and disparagement of Christians; their Actions <reg orig="farr">far</reg> exceeding the cruelties of the worst of Infidels.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, April</i> 12.</head>

<p>An Ordinance passed touching the Surveyors of the <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg> for this present year, 1654. as followeth: Whereas in an Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair <pb n="7" />the Highways within this Nation, it is ordained, among other things, that two or more able and sufficient <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg>, as in that Ordinance is expressed, should be elected and chosen upon the first <reg orig="Tuesdaynext">Tuesday next</reg> ensuing the five and twentieth day of March yearly, to be Surveyors of the Highways within their respective Parishes for the year ensuing: And whereas by reason of the publishing of the said Ordinance, the time aforesaid for such election for this year was elapsed, so as such election could not be made on that day in pursuance of the said Ordinance, whereby the benefit intended to the People is thereby obstructed; It is Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the persons which are already chosen or shall be chosen before the first day of May, 1654. to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> which Election is hereby <reg orig="enjoyn'd">enjoined</reg> to be made in every Place and Parish by the time aforesaid, under the penalties in that Ordinance expressed, in case no election hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> already made, shall undertake the said Office, and be sworn, on, or before the 6 day of May aforesaid, under the said penalties in the said Ordinance set down in that behalf, and shall be Surveyors for this present year, as if such Election had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> made on the said first Tuesday after the said 25 day of March, anything in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding; And the said Surveyors so sworn, and all others authorized by the said Ordinance, shall be, and are hereby <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to proceed in and put in execution, all the Direction, Powers <pb n="8" />and Authorities in the said Ordinance contained, as fully to all intents and purposes, as if the Election had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> made on the day <reg orig="therin">therein</reg> appointed.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance <reg orig="impowering">empowering</reg> Commissioners to put in execution an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco in England</em>. That upon consideration had of the great prejudice arising to the English Plantations in Foreign parts, and the great Damage and <reg orig="Losse">Loss</reg> to Trade at home, by the planting of Tobacco in this Nation; It is Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That Sir <em>William Rovert, John Stone, Gervas Bennet, Henry E. Syng, Adam Bains</em>, and <unclear><em>Io.</em></unclear><em> Bocket</em>, Esquires; or any 3. or more of them, be, and are appointed Commissioners, and are <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg>, authorized and required, by all fit and <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> ways and means, to put in executing an Act of Parliament, dated the first of April, 1652. <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <em>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco in England</em>; and every clause, article matter and thing therein contained, and Act or Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding; and all Officers Civil and Military, and all other persons are required to be <reg orig="ayding">aiding</reg> and assisting unto the said Commissioners, or any person or persons <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by them in this service, for the <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> execution, by the said Act, or this Ordinance, granted and <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> to the said Commissioners.</p> <pb n="9" />

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsall">Upsala</reg>, March</i> 7. S.V.</head>

<p>The Grand Chancellor being infirm and indisposed, the Queen hath authorized his second Son Count <em>Erick</em>, to Treat with my Lord Ambassador, and on Monday last he gave his Lordship a Meeting, and they had a very large Debate upon the Articles, but they came to no result; only he said he would acquaint the Queen with the effect of the Discourse. Her Majesty is still resolved for privacy, and some say that the Senators have <reg orig="complyed">complied</reg> with her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desires in that particular: But an Affair of that nature <reg orig="canot">cannot</reg> be fully determined but in <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> which is now shortly to meet, only they speak here, as if all things would be done, and great expectations are of the Coronation of her Successor, who is expected here in this Town.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick, April</i> 4. S.N.</head>

<p>A Trooper of this city is come on here with Letters from <em>Warsaw</em>, relating, that on the 28, of <em>March</em> the Polish <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> was dissolved fruitless, by reason his Majesty would in no way <reg orig="resolv">resolve</reg> to dispose of the <reg orig="Generelat">General</reg> of the crown &amp; Dukedom of <em>Littaw</em>, wherefore they would proceed no farther, but were presently dispersed. All what hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> said concerning the <reg orig="Muscovits">Muscovites</reg> amounts to nothing. Against the second of June, another convocation is determined, and published a Decree, promising therein, that the <reg orig="Souldiary">Soldiery</reg> should be duly paid.</p><pb n="10" />

<head level="3"><i>From Regensburgh</i>, March. 23. S.N.</head>

<p>The <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> departure stands yet appointed on the 28. of April next precisely. His <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> was resolved to have washed the feet of the poor this day, but his indisposition (being troubled with the gout) <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> him of his purpose, forcing him to keep his bed. Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> is come on here from <em>Wien</em> with a stately Train: it is said he will prosecute his Journey for the Low-Countries presently after the Holy-<reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. This <!--??--><reg orig="Ryxday">Rex day</reg> is like shortly to be transformed <reg orig="in">into</reg> a Deputations day, which I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> will be appointed at <em>Regensburgh</em> or <em>Frankfurt</em>, by reason of the great number of considerable difficulties, which the short time and soon departure of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, will not suffer to be determined here. Friday last there was a great quarrel between the Swedish Ambassadors and the Agents of the City <em>Bremen</em> in the Assembly, the Ambassadors protesting against the others presence, desiring that they might be sent out of the Convent. But this was plainly denied and the quarrel taken up between them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague</i>, April. 8. S.N.</head>

<p>We conceive here the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath a good intention for these Countries, because she concludes not with <em>England</em>. The States General have written to all Provinces and considerable Cities of this Commonwealth to bring in their opinions and consents concerning the house of <em>Orange</em> and <em><reg orig="Steuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> <reg orig="Familie">Family</reg>. Our Fleet is now fitting for the Sea, with all haste, and is far better than ever we had any, but I believe will not be quite ready within less than a <reg orig="months">month's</reg> time.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Minehead</i>, April 10.</head>

<p>Here is little news in these parts, only that the <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> of <em>Brest</em> do much harm in this Channel, having if late taken several vessels, whereof some of a considerable value, which belonged to <em><reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg></em>, some of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which were appointed to keep these Seas, being gone towards <em>Dublin</em>, and so to the Westward of Scotland, giveth more <reg orig="libertie">liberty</reg> to these Rogues to commit their <reg orig="Villanies">Villainies</reg> without any opposition, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> into the very mouth of <em>Severn</em>; there is lately come some <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> from <em>Ireland</em>, who bringeth news, that the Plague is well appeased in most parts of that Country, and all things quiet, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a great want of people to manure the ground in many parts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Innerness</i>, April 2.</head>

<p>Yesterday the Enemy had a general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> in <em>Sutherland</em> near <em>Skilbo</em>, they were about 1200 Foot, and 800 Horse, (500 little better then baggage Horses, and many wanting Pistols) and after the receipt of Orders from Lieut. Generalissimo <em>Middleton</em>, most were to march for the South <em>Highlands</em>, and the rest to continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to join in the South. <em>Middleton</em> added to their number at the <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about 200 Horse and Foot, and hath ordered to be levied out of <em>Ross</em> <pb n="11" /> <i>Two hundred and fifty Sutherland 300, Cathness 600, and Stranavar 300. He expects hourly <em>Seaford</em> with 500 and <em>Mackholdwy</em> to be ready with his Levies; He gives out that he hath brought great store of Spanish gold lent his Master by the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, from whom is expected a great Loan, and many men, which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother-in-law, which he had <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends for his often failing in his promises to them. This day Lieut. Col. <em>Mitchil</em>, <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> hither with 9 Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of <reg orig="Hors">Horse</reg>, and a commanded party of 180, with 5 Troops of Dragoons, which are to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to Brahan, to which are added 4 Troops of Horse, and 3 Companies of Foot. The use of the march is to keep a Pass at Dinghill, which by a numerous concurrence of knowing men of the Country, will force them to fight us, stay where they are, or hazard the loss of their horse, by length, badness of way, and want of provisions, if they march to the South by the North-west hills, they having no other way to march otherwise.</i></p>

<head level="3">From Rotterdam, the 13 April S.N.</head>

<p><i>The satisfaction for the restrained ships in the Sound, was no sooner demanded here, but consented to as we hear; for that being the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> obstacle in the way which was said to hinder the conclusion of the <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg>, and now removed, we doubt not but this next post will bring us the certain news of a good agreement, and that the Articles are signed by the Principals on both sides; the delay whereof hath caused many apprehensions, and jealousies, and <reg orig="biassed">biased</reg> discourses, that this drilling of the <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg> is like to breed no good, and your being so strong at sea, renders it the more suspected.</i></p>

<p><i>In the <reg orig="mean time ">meantime</reg> the United Provinces have been exhorted to furnish without delay, the money which hath been demanded of them extraordinarily, for the equipage of the Seas: and several meetings have been held for the preventing of the designs, which may be intended against the Sound and preserve the entire right to the King of Denmark; whereupon the States General have sent their orders to the admiralties of <reg orig="Austerdam">Amsterdam</reg>.</i></p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall, March 17.</i></head>

<p>The Grand Chancellor being sickly, the <reg orig="Qu:">Queen</reg> has given order to count <em>Erick</em>, his second Son, and a person of very great accomplishments, to Treat with my L: Ambassador: And on Monday last they both had a meeting to debate upon the Articles. Our being here hath not <reg orig="bin">been</reg> without its use and advantage to England in several respects: Not long since, a Senator here, and He not one of the least ability, was pleased to say, That my Lords being here had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> of greater fruit to our Commonwealth, then if we had sent an Army of 10000 into <em>Holland</em>. And, I suppose, the Issue <reg orig="wil">will</reg> abundantly countervail the charges of the <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg>, should they be never so great. The Queen is yet resolved for privacy; And <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said, That the Senators have <reg orig="comply'd">complied</reg> with Her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desires in that particular. But an affair of this nature cannot be actually determined but in Parliament; which will now meet shortly. The Prince Royal, to whom the Qu: resigns, is expected here very speedily; and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed, for no other end but to treat with the Senators about that affair. The Qu: proposes to have the lands in <em>Pomerania</em>, as part of her maintenance; &amp; some say, That the Senate have agreed thereunto; and that the cattle of <em>Stetin</em> is making ready for her Majesty, where she intends to reside. Others are bold to think, that this pretence of resigning, and the coronation of the Prince, is but to usher in their <reg orig="Mariage">Marriage</reg> together with more Pomp and Solemnity. But a matter of this weight, so blinded, and so hidden in its circumstances, may be censured, and guessed at by all, but can be apprehended by very few.</p><pb n="13" />

<head level="3">For his Highness the Lord Protector for the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging.</head>

<p><i>May it please your Highness</i></p>

<p>Many of the precious servants of God in there Nations (over which the Lord hath set your Highness> have gotten upon their watch Tower, to see if they can discover what hath been the eminent design of the Lord in these latter days. For the All-wise God hath of late visibly <reg orig="bin">been</reg> out of his common-Road of Providences his paths have been in tempests and thick darkness, plucking up by the roots the greatest of men, and the highest of Powers, like Cedars in Lebanon, that he might make way for the glorious bringing forth of Truth and Righteousness. And we question not but the Lord is fulfilling that great <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg>, <em>Isa: 60.17.</em> I will make thine Officers peace, and thine Exactors righteousness. For when we consider how the Lord hath eminently made your Highness <reg orig="instrumentall">instrumental</reg> for the breaking off the Iron <reg orig="yoak">yoke</reg> from off the necks of the three Nations, and likewise hath invested you with the Supreme Power of this Commonwealth, whereby you may be exceedingly <reg orig="instrumentall">instrumental</reg> to the Lord Jesus, in the advancement of his Kingdom in Righteousness our spirits, have judged it our duty to process our great Resentment of this signal mercy from the hands of our God, &amp; do solemnly bless the Lord for setting up your Highness over this great people, &amp; shall <reg orig="endevor">endeavour</reg> through the strength of Christ to live in all humble Obedience to your Highness, as becometh those who are under your Government and Protection.</p>

<p>Febr: Signed in the Name, and by order of the Common-council of Newcastle upon Tyne,</p>

<p><i>Will: Johnson Major.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith,</i> April 11.</head>

<p>Notwithstanding the hand of God is so eminently seen in destroying these rude people, and that they are no sooner gathered together, but they are scattered, yet they are still breaking forth in the Lowlands, and amongst others, the Earl of <em>Salkirk</em>, second son to the Marquis of <em>Douglas</em>, started out the other day, and went away from about <em>Boggehall</em> with 60 Horse, and this week about 40 Englishmen are got to the Hills under the command of an Irishman. Col. <em>Daniel</em>, Capt. <em>Elsmare</em>, and others have lately met with divers of the Rebels, so that the prisoners begin now to fill the only way to case the Commonwealth of their Charge will be to send these Idle people to Burbadoes and other parts, to work for their living, which would be done soon, and without respect of persons. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> main body as yet continues in <em>Sutherland</em>, <em>Mac Aldow</em>, and <em>Mac Cloud</em>, lately marched to them with 400 foot, and the Earl of <em>Seafort</em> expected with 700. The Earl of <em>Sutherland</em> leaving his house and Country, and declining from joining with the Enemy hath suffered very much <pb n="14" />together with his people, and if Col<em> Morgan</em> had not come into <em>Ross</em>, they threatened to fire it, in case the people had not risen generally with them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> will be (by a supply from <em><reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg></em>) 850 Horse and Dragoons, and 1500 Foot, with which he will endeavour to engage the Enemy who are about 800 Horse, and 3000 Foot, who give out, they will rather engage with us then hazard the going through the Hills, they being so <reg orig="mountanous">mountainous</reg> and impassable, knowing that it <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of their horses, &amp; most of their Foot.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement, concerning the Commissioners appointed for Approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers sitting at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</i></head> 

<p>The Commissioners for <em>Approbation</em> <em>of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Preachers</em> sit on <em><reg orig="Mondayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg>,</em> and <em><reg orig="Fridayes">Fridays</reg></em>; of which <em><reg orig="Fridayes">Fridays</reg></em> for <em>Augmentations</em>, much as grace in <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> hearts, some University men, for defect thereof, have been laid by, and some who never were University men, yet furnished with Gifts and Graces, have been received and welcomed.</p>

<p>No difference at all among the Commissioners themselves, though they be of divers Judgements about Church matters, all minding the advancement of the Gospel.</p>

<p>They being 38 in number are severed into three divisions, each division fitting their Month, so that the Work will <reg orig="goe">go</reg> constantly on.</p>

<p>No partiality used in their Trials. Testimonies and Certificates are narrowly looked into, because much depends upon them.</p>

<p>If Patrons would present good men, it would much help on this work.</p>

<p>Some of the men who have been already tried, have preached at <em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em> and <reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable others will hereafter be put upon this way of exercising their Gifts.</p>

<p>If the carriage of this business were in the view of the Nation, the Censures of men would be <reg orig="forborn">forborne</reg>; and whereas some are of opinion, that these Triers ought to have been sent from Churches, men are to know, that the Magistrate only looks to the sending forth Preachers, and takes not upon him to set down Church-Officers; but out of the number of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, Church-Officers may afterwards be chosen, if Congregations see Cause.</p>

<p>An extraordinary number of Preachers are continually attending upon these Commissioners to receive their Trial; and yet there will be want of Thousands. They usually sit upon the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before mentioned, from 8 till 12 in the morning; and sometimes every day, because of the abundance of business pressing upon them.</p>

<p>No Certificates are approved but such as come subscribed under the hands of such persons as are known to the Commissioners, or to some of them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Truro in Cornwall</i>, by the last.</head>

<p>Mrs. <em>Hannah Trapnel</em>, she that lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, hath for some time been in these parts. <pb n="15" />There seem to be two convincing Reasons against her Spirit; <reg orig="eth">the first</reg> one is that it withdraws from Ordinances, and the other is, that it is <reg orig="Non-sensical">Nonsensical</reg>. There are in her Company one Mr. <em>Langdon</em>, and Mr. <em>Bauden</em>, two Members of the late short-lived Parliament. The Justices of this County have taken notice of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and practices; and Mr. <em>Lobb</em> giving the charge here this last Sessions, willed the Jury to enquire, 1 concerning Vagrants, 2 such as occasioned unlawful meetings, 3 such as speak against the present Government. There were two Indictments drawn against her: <em>Langdon</em> and <em>Baudon</em>, her Compeers and Abettors, <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> to make a learned Defence for her, but it was not suffered; only they entered into Bonds of three hundred pounds for her good behaviour and appearance at the next Assizes. If you had inquired better into her business, when she tranced it at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, it might have prevented the staggering of many a spirit in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>. The design intended to be made use of by means of this woman is (it seems) to compass <em>England</em>, and pass from one good Town to another to vent her Prophesies, and thereby disaffect the people to the present Authority. It calls to mind the old story of <em>Elizabeth Barton</em>, the holy maid of <em>Kent</em> (as she was called) in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of<em> Henry </em>the 8. who was made use of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests, by <reg orig="fained">feigned</reg> Miracles and Trances, to raise admiration in the multitude, and foment seditious <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> against the Government; for which she and her accomplices had in the end their reward.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, April 13. The <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of rising here does appear every day more universal, not only the Scots flying out, but divers English; and amongst the rest three Clerks, belonging to the Court of Justice at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>. Divers <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> out of Leith, and about 50 from Sterling, are gone to the hills.</p>

<p><em>Whitehall</em> April 17. This day in the morning Information was given That the Ratification of the Peace was come over from the <reg orig="States-Generall">States-General</reg> to their Ambassadors here, it having <reg orig="bin">been</reg> <reg orig="don">done</reg> in the Hague the Thursday before, and the People of these Provinces not a little rejoiced at it. All things are now preparing here for a final Ratification to be made also by his Highness the Lord Protector; of which you may hear more ere a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> more be over.</p>

<p>From Sea, the only news is, that a fleet of about 40 sail of French Merchant-men were met with off of Ushant, by the Portsmouth and Middleburgh <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>; who assailed them, and <reg orig="maintain'd">maintained</reg> a Fight, in which they sunk the Admiral of the French, and took 5. It was foul weather, so that our 2 <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> were parted in the fight; otherwise the best part of the French might have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> taken.</p>

<p>A Report comes of our taking a Dutch Merchant-man also, new built, an Early-Indy-man, of about 800 <reg orig="Tonns">Tonnes</reg>, well fitted for that <reg orig="Voiage">Voyage</reg>, with a convenient store of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, and other Necessaries, being newly set forth toward the Indies. But this I cannot yet ascertain, because no Express is come concerning it.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>