<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol194">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 194</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> February 23. to <em>Thursday</em> March 2. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, February 18.</i></head>

<p>About four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, Col. <em>Daniel</em> with a party of Horse, Foot, and Dragoons, together with the conjunction of another party from <em>Dundee</em>, in all about 1000. <reg orig="march'd">marched</reg> towards <em>Dunkel</em>, where the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> most considerable Quarters was, and where they had newly established a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Lord <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> house near the Church. And upon Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em> approach (the Lord <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em>, and Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> having intelligence retreated to the Hills, &amp; left only the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and some few to defend the Church) those in the Church durst<!--reg to dared?--> not stand, <reg orig="busled">bustled</reg> to the House, which our men attempted <pb n="1" />likewise, and got under the <reg orig="Wals">Walls</reg> with Pickaxes and other Instruments that were in readiness, and in no short time gotten to a part of the House without the loss of one Man; and having slain only 3 of the Enemy, the rest <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> Quarter and had it granted, yet notwithstanding unworthily began to resist a little, which <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> our men the more; and then they <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out Quarter <reg orig="amain">again</reg>. In the House we took 2 Lieutenants, one <reg orig="Ensigne">Ensign</reg> with blue Colours, Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs'</reg></em> own Quartermaster, 2 <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg>, 2 Cornets, and 119 private Rogues, together with 80 <reg orig="Musquets">Muskets</reg> and <reg orig="Bandeliers">Bandoleers</reg>, some Firelocks and Swords, about 16 pound of Powder, as also 25 Troop-horses, and 14, or 15 case of Pistols, with much Meal, Malt, Oats, which not having convenience to carry away, we set fire to a <reg orig="Barrell">Barrel</reg> of powder, and those Provisions, and blew up them and the <reg orig="Hous">House</reg> together. About 5 days ago one of the late Col. <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> men, with 3 of his best horses, got his Landlord to help him water them, and <reg orig="runn">run</reg> away with them to <reg orig="Blaire-castle">Blaire castle</reg>, one of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>; which makes the English less trusted by <em>Athol</em> and the Tories. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath also removed the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at <em>Kildrummy</em>; and many of those <reg orig="Horsmen">Horsemen</reg> he routed at his <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> with <em>Glencairn</em> (the great Patron, or rather spoiler of his Country) running to <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em> <reg orig="neare">near</reg> <em>Dunkiel</em>, <unclear><!--12 characters possibly 2 words--></unclear> them to foot. Col. <em>Morgan</em> at his late Engagement with the Enemy at <em>Cromar</em>, killed 120. and took 27 prisoners, with all their Ammunition, and most of their Arms, and <reg orig="abou">about</reg> 80 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg>, which we lost not one man.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, March 1. stilo novo</i></head>

<p>The 25 of the last Month the Duke of Lorain was here taken Prisoner by order of the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em>, and the next day he was sent Prisoner with a strong Guard to the Castle of Antwerp, which is reinforced with 500 Spaniards, for his better <unclear>Security</unclear>, of the Regiment of Don <em>Gaspar Bonifacy</em>, Madam <em>Beatrice</em> his second Wife by promise, was also arrested at <em>Allost</em>, and conducted to Brussels, there to be examined, and to know of her where they may find his Papers &amp; Money; whereof it is thought he has a good store in his bank, which is a commodity that is now in these parts very scarce, and much wanted for the speedy recruiting of the Army of his said Highness the Archduke. There are also warrants given out for the apprehending the Lieutenant of his Guard, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other his <reg orig="Domesticks">Domestics</reg>. Thus the crafty Fox is taken and secured from devouring any more of the poor <reg orig="Peoples">People's</reg> Poultry, who are glad at their hearts to hear this good news, which made them to make Bonfires for joy, as if they had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> delivered out of the hand of a cruel Enemy: presently after he was taken Prisoner, the Earl of <unclear><em>Fuensoldagne</em></unclear> went immediately towards his Army, with good store of <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> to content his Soldiers, and to take the command thereof 'till such time as his Brother <em>Francis</em> of Lorain can come to command the same in chief himself. And likewise since the Imprisonment of the said Duke, the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em> has put forth a Declaration, giving to understand to all Head-Officers, Masters of the Camp, <pb n="3" />Colonels, &amp; Men of war in the service of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> Duke of Lorain, that he having secured for <reg orig="som">some</reg> time, the person of said Duke, by <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Order and command of the King his Lord, for the proper good of the house of Lorain, and other high considerations, tending in order to the welfare of the State, and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="Tranquility">Tranquillity</reg>; the intention of his Majesty and mine is that the body of said Troops <reg orig="doe">do</reg> remain under the command of the E. of <em>Ligneville</em>, in the same service they stand at present, till such time that his brother <em>Francis</em> Duke of Lorain <reg orig="doe">do</reg> take the command thereof, to preserve the Rights of the Lord his Brother, and the house of Lorain.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg></i></head>

<p>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, the Government of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland by a Lord Protector and successive <reg orig="Trienniall">Triennial</reg> Parliaments is now established; And whereas <em>Oliver Cromwell</em> Captain <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of all the Forces of this Commonwealth, is declared Lord Protector of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it necessary (as <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hereby do) to make publication of the Premises, and strictly to charge and command all, and every person and persons, of what quality and condition soever in any of the said three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers and Officers, whom this may <pb n="4" />concern, are required to cause this Proclamation to be forthwith published in their respective counties, cities, corporations and Market Towns; to the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</p>

<p>Given at Whitehall this sixteenth day of December 1653.</p>

<head level="2">IRELAND</head>

<p>By the commissioners of the commonwealth of England for the Affairs of Ireland</p>

<p>The Proclamation above mentioned lately coming to our knowledge, we held it our duty for prevention of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> disturbances and interruptions in the administration of Justice, to publish the same: To the end that all Sheriffs, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg>, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Officers and Ministers in this Nation, whom the same doth concern, may take notice thereof; Requiring all Officers and Soldiers of the Army, and all Sheriffs, Judges, Justices of the Peace, commissioners for Administration of Justice, and all others who are entrusted with the management of any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Affairs, to be vigilant in their respective charges and Trusts, That the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Service may be carried on, and that the common Enemy, upon this change of Government, may not take any advantage to contrive or act new disturbances against the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace. Dated at Dublin the <reg orig="thirtyeth">thirtieth</reg> day of January, 1653.</p>

<p>Signed by Order and command of the said commissioners,</p>
<p>JO: HUGHES Sec'.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3">From Paris, February 28. stilo novo.</head>

<p>Severe resolutions are taken against the Prince of Conde, and there seems to be a greater eagerness in the prosecution, since his brother the Prince of Conti hath been married to the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece. It seems the Cardinal intends to crush the other brother, that a way that may be laid to put this into possession of his <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> honours and fortunes. Thus the Cardinal hath outwitted and overreached Conde. His place of Major Domo, or Master of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Household, is now disposed to Prince Thomas of Savoy.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> labours likewise to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> himself by another match that he propounds for his Nephew, and it is to one of the Nieces of Cardinal de Retz, a man that he knows not how <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, nor much longer to detain in prison, and therefore he would fain oblige him (if possible) by an alliance. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the said Cardinal is kept close.</p>

<p>Another match hath been propounded between the Duke of Nemours, and <reg orig="Madamoiselle">Mademoiselle</reg>,, daughter to the Duke of Longueville. But as yet little can be said of it.</p>

<p>Beffort having been taken in by the Marshal de la Ferte, the said Marshal hath made very earnest application to Count Harcourt, that he would yield up Brisack, and other places under his Government in Alsatia, to be disposed of by his Majesty; for which purpose he hath renewed to him the former Tenders, according to such Propositions as were made heretofore, <pb n="6" />for his indemnity, in case of surrender.</p>

<p>The resolution of sending a new person into England having been waved, it was agreed that Monsieur de Bordeaux Neufville (who hath for some time past resided at London) should be <reg orig="impower'd">empowered</reg> as Ambassador.</p>

<p>The news being arrived here, that two Ambassadors <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> from the United Provinces to England, it is taken as if the Peace were already concluded; and therefore this Crown will <reg orig="doe">do</reg> nothing farther to disoblige the English Lord Protector. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, foreseeing what is like to follow, <reg orig="chuseth">chooseth</reg> rather to depart of himself, 'tis talked everywhere that he will be gone out of hand; and (as the <reg orig="crie">cry</reg> goes) for Germany.</p>

<head level="3">From Dalkeith, February 20.</head>

<p>Upon Tuesday last Col. Daniel marched out of St. Johnstons with a party of foot and dragoons, and met with some other forces from Dundee, with which he fell the next morning with Dunkell (the chief quarter of the enemy) the enemy quit the Town, and betook themselves to the great House (and the Kirk) which they endeavoured to keep, but <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as our foot came under the house, and with pickaxes made holes, and got into the house, and killed three men, thereupon the enemy betook themselves to one room and desired quarter, which was granted for their lives; we took two Captains, two Lieutenants, one <reg orig="Ensigne">Ensign</reg>, and Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbes">Forbes'</reg> Quartermaster and 9 prisoners; we only had one man hurt with a stone, <pb n="7" />but not much. Atholl and Forbes were gone from that place into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> not above two hours before. We took one blew<!--blue?--> Colours in the house, which we have since made untenable: we now have in several about 400 prisoners, and it were to be wished that some Instructions were given by his Highness for the disposal of them, most of them being idle rogues, which it would be a work of charity as well as policy to rid the Country of, by sending them to some <reg orig="foraign">foreign</reg> Plantations, where they might be in an incapacity if returning, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> some service in their generation, by being made to work for their livings; for here they will do nothing, but rob, burn, and <reg orig="murther">murder</reg>, as oft as they get liberty, and while they are kept as prisoners, are a charge to the Commonwealth, and a weakening to our forces by putting them upon extraordinary duty for guards for them, and often attempt to make escapes. Some of them, one a notorious <reg orig="murtherer">murderer</reg>, lately gagged the <reg orig="Marshals">Marshal's</reg> man at Sterling, in order to their escape, but were discovered, and laid in irons. A party of four of Major General <reg orig="Harisons">Harison's</reg> late Regiment (which we now hear is to be the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwells">Cromwell's</reg> going from Cardross towards Sterling to convoy a prisoner of ours that lately escaped from the enemy) were met with by one Captain Buhannan, and nine more, and taken.</p>

<p>About 4 or 5 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since, one of Col <reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg> men with 3 of their best horses, got his Landlord to help him to water them, and ran with <pb n="8" />them to Blaire Castle, which makes the Earl of Athol not to trust Englishmen so much. Athol dismounted very many <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that ran from Glencairn upon the defeat at Cromar, the particulars which Engagement we had this evening thus, Their number was about fourteen or fifteen hundred horse and foot, at a very strong Pass, which was a mile in length, and we could march but one man <reg orig="abrest">abreast</reg> the enemy had 30 foot at the top of the Glen, but Lieut. Symonds being commanded out with a party of foot, and Capt. Lisle with a party of horse to the top of the Hill, so amazed them, that their game was spoiled, for after a short dispute we routed them, and pursued them 7 miles over the Hills, such way as they did not expect we could follow them. We killed about 120, took 27 prisoners, with all their Ammunition, <reg orig="bagg">bag</reg>, baggage, and most of their Arms, and about 20 horse, Glencairn and Kenmore hardly escaping. These mercies were very seasonable, for the enemy were very high, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> nothing but fire and sword, if all did not rise with them presently. Upon the 10 instant Col. Morgan <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> to Kildrummy, where they had a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of 40 foot, ad 30 horse, which being summoned, the Governor was <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>; at last (the third day) he came to a Treaty, and <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> the House upon Articles, to march away with Arms, Ammunition, <reg orig="bagg">bag</reg>, and baggage, which was not much; The House being strong, and not to be taken without great guns, which we had not, neither could our Forces have lain <pb n="9" />there above one night longer; and indeed, <em>Glencairn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> had left that house as a bait, thinking we would besiege it before we fell upon them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> left a Garrison of foot and horse in it, and returned to Aberdeen. In all this business we lost not one man <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one was lost accidentally by one of our <reg orig="owne">own</reg> men, neither had we any man wounded, but two Horses shot.</p>

<p>Sir you have here my <reg orig="piecemeal'd">piecemealed</reg> relations, which in regard of time and intelligence, coming many times after I have begun my Letters; I hope you will pick <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> out of my lines.</p>

<p>Since the writing of this, I have a more particular relation of the business at Dunkel, but have not time to acquaint you with the whole. The names of the Officers taken are. Captain <em>Nicholson</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, Capt. <em>Fiffe</em>, Lt. <em>Charles Watson</em>, Lieut. <em>William Rosse</em>, Ensi. <em>Broughy</em>, and <em>Patrick Gray</em>, quartermaster to Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>. Arms taken, 80 Muskets with <reg orig="Bandaleers">Bandoleers</reg>, and Swords, some few firelocks 14 pound of powder, but what was in their <reg orig="Bandaleers">Bandoleers</reg>. A great quantity of Meal, Malt and Oats provided for the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> forces; which we not being provided to carry away, blew it up with the house. 25. Troop horses taken, with 15 [air of pistols. <em>Athol</em> and <em>Forbes</em> came into Dunkel the night after we were gone, <reg orig="withall">with all</reg> the force they could make: According to the old proverb, when the Fryer is beaten then came <em>James</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Chester, Febr. 26.</i></head>

<p>On Wednesday last, the Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> took ship for Ireland, at the point of Aire; we hope he is well over, though <reg orig="their">there</reg> fell out very violent storms, immediately after his <reg orig="imbarquing">embarking</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, by the last.</i></head>

<p>That you may understand the reasons and manner of the Arch-Duke <em>Leopold's</em> proceedings against that famous <reg orig="Thiefe">Thief</reg> the Duke of <em>Lorraine</em>, who hath filled a good part of <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg> with his rapines and cruelties. I have here <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> two Translates of those two Declarations; <pb n="10" />which have been set out here by his Highness; the one directed to the Soldiery of the <em>Lorain</em> Army; the other to all men in general; where you will <reg orig="finde">find</reg>, that <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em>, the younger brother, is set up by the Spaniard in the elders <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> place, as the younger brother of the house of <em>Conde</em> is by the Cardinal in France.</p>

<p>Leopold William, <i>by the grace of God Arch-Duke of Austria, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em> &amp;c. Lieut. <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and Capt. General of the Low Countries, and of <em>Burgonie</em>, &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>To all high Officers, Masters de Camp, Colonels, Captains, and Soldiers bearing Arms under the <reg orig="Ensignes">Ensigns</reg> and Banners of the Lord Duke of <em>Loraine, Charles: Health</em>. We give you to understand, that having this day secured for some time, the person of the said Duke of <em>Loraine Charles</em>, in <reg orig="persuance">pursuance</reg> of a special order and command, which we have received from the King my Lord; for the good of the house of <em>Loraine</em> in particular, and other high and weighty considerations, relating to the welfare of the State and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace: His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> and our intention is that the whole body of his Troops do continue in the same service as they are now upon under the command of <em>Count de Ligneville</em>, until the L.Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Loraine</em> shall arrive here, (which will be in a few days) to undertake the command of this Army, to the preservation of the rights of the said Duke, and the house of <em>Loraine</em>, under the Protection of his Majesty, Declaring that no Officers, <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, or others belonging to the said Army shall be brought to a <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>, or questioned for any riots, or <reg orig="misdeanours">misdemeanours</reg> whatsoever, which they may have committed under the said Lord Duke. Hereby also strictly and <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> forbidding them to go to the service of any other neighbour Princes or States, either friends or enemies, upon pain of forfeiture of both body and goods, as well in respect to the vassals and natural subjects of his Majesty, as those heretofore lifted and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in the <reg orig="Musterrolls">Muster rolls</reg> of that Army; and as to other strangers, upon <pb n="11" />pain of being punished as deserters of their Colours. Provided notwithstanding that any formerly listed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in the Service of his Majesty, and that have gone from their Colours although without leave, may return and repair to them without danger of being questioned in any <reg orig="waies">ways</reg>, or proceeded against for the same. As to the rest, We refer Our self to that which the Count of <em>Guensaldagne</em> Commander in Chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Armies, shall more particularly acquaint them with, in relation to the advantages which shall be speedily procured and effected for them.</p>

<p>Given at <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em>, the 25 of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p>

<p>Leopold William, <i>by the grace of God Arch-Duke of <em>Austria</em>, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em> &amp;c. Lieutenant Governor, and Captain General of the <em>Low Countries</em>, and of <em>Burgonie</em>, &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>As no man can be ignorant what duty and respect our Cousin the Lord Duke of <em>Lorain <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, hath been obliged to bear to the King my Lord, and all his Allies, Friends, and good Subjects, since the time that he hath in these parts of his Dominions, been sheltered from the violences, oppressions, and usurpations that have been practised by <em>France</em> against his person and State; where he hath been received by his Majesty and his Lieutenant General with all friendship and good confidence, and under a special protection, not only to the espousing of all his interests in the Solemn Assembly for <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg> of Peace, but also furnishing him with Pay, and <reg orig="maintainance">maintenance</reg> for his Troops, and admitting him to our Resolutions and Councils of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> against the common enemy: So it's no less known to all the world how contrary to the said Lord Duke hath acted to what was due from a Prince of his birth so entertained, treated, and gratified, as is before mentioned, and so strictly bound to the Interest and Service of his Majesty, and the good of his Kingdom. For, besides the tears groanings, and general exclamations of the people that bore <reg orig="publick">public</reg> testimony of the Thefts, Robberies, <reg orig="Sacriledges">Sacrileges</reg> Rapes both of married women and maids, and other abominable and detestable Riots committed under the Conduct of his Army, the wracks of which destructions and devastations, he himself gathered up; His Majesty and his Lieutenant General have from time to time been well informed of the secret intelligences of the said Lord Duke, and of his several <reg orig="designes">designs</reg>, as <reg orig="farr">far</reg> different from the common good, and service to which the conjunction of Forces ought to tend, and also of his inconstancies, and pretended change of judgement in Resolves of matters of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, and the alterations and affected <reg orig="delaies">delays</reg> that he gave in things already debated, and that even at the very point of executing most important services, which might have been the overthrow of many and high enterprises, which in all <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg>, and according to humane reason, could not but have had a happy issue; These practices were at length grown so notorious, and to such a <pb n="12" /><reg orig="hight">height</reg>, that not only the Lieutenant General, Commanders of Armies, Masters de Camp, and all other Officers were eye-witnesses of his tricks and artifices, and could point at them, but even the meanest <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg>, and the whole people seemed astonished to see things thus pass on without any remedy provided against them. 'Tis true, the King my Lord, through his accustomed goodness, and singular affection which he doth and ever will bear to the House of <em>Lorrain</em>, hath as far as possibly he could, connived at, and passed it by, in hopes that the said Duke moved with the courteous usage and benignity his Majesty hath treated <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, might become sensible of his Interest, and in conclusion return to his duty; but on the contrary, his exorbitant proceedings arrive to such a height, that not only all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Subjects and Vassals do abhor and detest him, that it was apparent that these Countries, for perfecting their misery, might have felt the effects of the vengeance which they <reg orig="design'd">designed</reg> to take of him, the King my Lord, lest he should provoke the anger of God against him and his people, could not defer any longer to stop the course of this evil, and therefore it is, upon consideration of these <reg orig="publick">public</reg> and manifest truths, that his Majesty for a speedy and effectual remedy thereunto, hath Commanded us to secure the person of said Lord Duke, in which he hath acted according to the Law of Nature and Nations, which allows all <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Princes to remove off their State and People, Oppressions and violence, be it who it will be that opposes them, and to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> all Justice to themselves, their people, and neighbour Potentates, States, and Friends, when all other <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> have been attempted in vain and without success, of which the ages past want not examples, in cases less fortified by circumstances, and justified <reg orig="then">than</reg> this. This proceeds not from any avetsation of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> to the house of <em>Lorrain</em>, but he protests ever to protect them, and to adhere to their Interests. In witness whereof his Majesty hath provided that the Command of the Armies and Troops of the said Lord Duke shall pass to, and remain <reg orig="sequestred">sequestered</reg> in the hands of the Lord Prince <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em>, his brother, from whose natural good inclinations, and sincere intention, his Majesty is assured he shall reap the fruits, and receive the true effects of a conjunction of Forces. And <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the said Duke <em>Francis</em> shall arrive, his <reg orig="Majestie's">Majesty's</reg> and Our intention is, that the Count <em>de Ligneville</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> continue in the execution of the Charge, and Office of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>.</p> 

<p>We therefore in the Name, and on the behalf of the King my Lord, do Command all his Subjects and Vassals, and request all neighbour Princes and States to rest satisfied, and have a good opinion of this order and resolution of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg>, expecting that another time and conjecture of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affairs may calm these <pb n="13" />motions and changes, and that God restoring <reg orig="quietnesse">quietness</reg>; by <reg orig="softning">softening</reg> the obstinate Spirit of <em>France</em> to Peace, the People may be again established in <reg orig="Tranquility">Tranquillity</reg> and a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Repose, and every one readmitted to that which is his Right. <i>Given at <reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels the 25 of Febr. 1654.</reg></i></p>

<p>LEOPOLD WILLIAM</p>
<p><i>Signed by Order of his Highness</i></p>
<p>VERREYKEN</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Bristol February 24.</i></head>

<p>We have little here, only the Brest men of War play Rex on our coast. The little George of this Port, bound from <em>Mevis</em>, was taken on our coasts by one of them. After <reg orig="som">some</reg> hours fight, the Brest man putting out English <reg orig="Colors">Colours</reg>, and speaking in English, that they should be hanged for firing against the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ship, and repeating it often between each <reg orig="broad side">broadside</reg>, the Passengers and some Seamen threw down their Arms, and would fight no longer; <reg orig="least">lest</reg> when they came home they should be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>; so two of their men being <reg orig="kild">killed</reg>, and many more of the <reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg>, they delivered up; but the same ship is re-taken by the Ostenders; <reg orig="shee">she</reg> had made a very good Voyage, being laden with <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg>, Sugar and Tobacco. The <em>Samaritan</em> of <em>Bristol</em> bound for Biscay, was taken lately by Cap. <em>Beach</em> of <em>Brest</em>; but is since retaken by the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, and brought into <em>Plymouth</em>; why should our poor Merchants pay Salvage in such cases after plunderings. The Ostender set the men of the George on shore at <em>Lyme</em>; but the ship is prize, because first taken by the French.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, February 28.</i></head>

<p>Our Provinces have at length unanimously agreed to the Peace, and Ambassadors are very suddenly to be dispatched away with their <reg orig="joynt">joint</reg> assents. When the Ratification is once passed, then woe to the Pitch, <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, and Faggots, and the Wine tuns not to be excluded. Doubtless the joy will be more than ordinary. They have here printed the Articles of the Treaty, but supposed not to be the true ones. We hear also that France is upon the point of <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with you, and that you intend to make peace with all your <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg>, the better to cement at home.</p>

<pb n="14" />

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, the Spaniards have made bold to take up quarters in our land of Overmase, thought they are now dislodged; <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said they are designed to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Lorainers, to hinder the French advancing. The <reg orig="Germain">German</reg> <reg orig="supplyes">supplies</reg> are not yet come, though much <reg orig="talkt">talked</reg> of; and there are those that affirm 7 or 8000 Swedes to be upon their march to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Spanish; which is strange, though like enough to be true, <em>Monsieur Interest</em>, being the only mover of all affairs. We are very sorry to heat that the Lord Commissioner <em>Beverning</em> in England cannot prevail, for a cessation of Arms with the Lord Protector, in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> that the rest of the Provinces can approve and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Articles of the Treaty, agreed on between the Commissioners of both States. We are also informed here, that the Spanish Ambassador is often in conference with the Lord Protector, and that he hath offered to make a League, offensive and defensive with his Highness: And likewise it doth cause much admiration amongst us here, <reg orig="mot">not</reg> knowing what <reg orig="designe">design</reg> the English have in hand, by setting forth such mighty Fleets to sea, when there is no doubt made here of an accommodation between both States; the incertitude whereof doth cause us to hasten out our Fleet, and to make greater preparations <reg orig="then">than</reg> was intended by this State. But all honest men hope that the arrival of our <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> will clear up all doubts, and jealousies that may arise from hence.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal in Sweden, January 27.</i></head>

<p>Our affairs here have had a little pause; the Lord Chancellor having been indisposed in his health, but now he is abroad <reg orig="againe">again</reg>. The Treaty goes on, and this afternoon my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, and he have a meeting concerning it; we cannot but believe, but we shall have a very desired issue; yet they are a little stumbled here at our detention of their ships, and at the dilatoriness of the proceedings of the Court of Admiralty concerning them. There are report here of an Extraordinary coming from France, and another from Russia; this Virgin Lady is much courted in this juncture.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris, by the last.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="onely">only</reg> considerable here is; the intelligence being given of the Preparations that are forwarding in Flanders, that the Spanish forces may be ready to take the field with the <reg orig="ftrsi">first</reg> of the spring, the like order is taking here by Marshal <em>Tureine</em>, if possible, to prevent them.</p>

<p>The Cardinal (it seems) intends to stock France with his Alliances; and for that end having sent for the remainders of his <reg orig="kindree">kindred</reg> out of Italy, two of his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> sisters, and more of his Nieces (as they are called) are <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>, and now not many Leagues from hence. The <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Secretary is gone with a little Regiment of <reg orig="Tailers">Tailors</reg>, <reg orig="Milenors">Milliners</reg>, and Perfumers, to set them forth in habit <em>a la mode de Paris</em>, before they come on any further; which being done, the King, Duke <em>de <reg orig="Aniou">Anjou</reg>, Cardinal</em>, and the great <pb n="15" />ones of the Court, intend to meet them at <em>Fontain-Bleau</em>, and so conduct them hither. One of the girls is so <reg orig="handsom">handsome</reg>, that it is presumed the King (at least) will be <reg orig="inamored">enamoured</reg> of her. Really, this Cardinal is a gallant man, who can not only quell his opposites, but reduce both King, Princes, and Kingdom to be at his own devotion.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Dalkeith, February 21.</i></head>

<p>The Earl of <em>Atholl</em> hath drawn all the Forces he can together from <em>Weems</em> and other places, and he with the Lord Bruce were the 14 instant at <em>Glenshier</em>, marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Glencairn, Glengary, Kenmore, &amp;c.</em> upon their conjunction they will be between 3 and 4000. and then they intend to be revenged of Col. <em>Morgan</em> for their late rout; but (through divine assistance) he may make them amends with such another beating: yet <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> foot are much discontented, and leave him daily out of a sense of their declining, dangerous, and desperate condition by their daily losses in all parts, and complain much of the cowardice of their horse: The English that came with <em>Wogan</em>, are much dejected at his death, and lament their leaving <em>France</em>, and being in so wretched and barbarous a place as the Highlands. We are daily sending what supply we can to Col. <em>Morgan</em>, but cannot much <reg orig="adde">add</reg> to his strength <reg orig="till">'till</reg> the two Regiments come out of <em>England</em>. The Scots at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> are very high, and have so great a spirit of Malignancy and unbelief, as to give out that the late defeat given by Col. <em>Morgan</em> to the enemy at <em>Cromar</em>, was only to some Country-men met there, though it is unquestionable that <em>Glencairn, Kenmore</em>, and most of their great fighters were there in person, and that the valiant <em>Mac-alding</em> Laird of <em>Loughaber</em> was one of the first that ran out of the field, and left his Commission from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, directed to Col. <em>Hum. Cameran</em>, dated <em>Decemb. 10. 1652.</em> Behind him, Lieut. Gen. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> last Instructions, several Letters from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, &amp;c. to the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Glencairn</em>, and other papers of consequence were taken, which it's not to be doubted that they would send with a company of Countrymen; but these kind of <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> are so like the old English <reg orig="Cavaliers">Cavalier's</reg> confident evasions, that I do but beat the fire to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to drive these people out of them, who will not be convinced by anything but a good sword subduing and cutting down those broken reeds upon which they lean &amp;c.</p>

<p><i>February 26.</i> The Lord <em>Newport</em> and <em>Tongstall</em>, Ambassadors extraordinary from the States General of the <em>United Provinces</em>, arrived at <em>Dover</em>, with full power (as is supposed) to conclude a Peace, being attended by a Retinue of about 80 persons. The Master of the Ceremonies is to receive them at <em>Gravesend</em>, and conduct them by water to <em>London</em>, Friday the third of <em>March</em> instant.</p>

<p><i>March 1.</i> Audience was given by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, to a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister sent from the Arch-Duke, out of <em>Flanders.</em></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>