<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol193">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 193</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> February 16. to <em>Thursday</em> Febr. 23. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Sterling, Febr. 6.</i></head>

<p>There was a party here <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> high flown before the late change; but they are at present a little milder <reg orig="then">than</reg> formerly; they were so forward, that they thought to carry all before them. they were ready to pick the left hole in any <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Coat, which was not of their judgement; and to <unclear>article</unclear> against him, though it were for things done two or 3 years ago. The enemies body is yet in the North, they increase <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, and now persons of quality goes into them. It is full time to raise all we can for our own security.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, February 11.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> is the greatest part of the News here at present; <em>Kenmore</em> with his body of about 2000 of those wild people, is now at <em>Kildrunning</em>, an house of the Earl of <em>Mar's</em> in <em>Murrayland</em>: they have been very quiet of <pb n="1" />late, and if peace with the 7 Provinces be concluded; they are not like to be very troublesome: Most of <em>Wogan's</em> party (now he is gone the way of all flesh) are contriving to get as well out of <em>Scotland</em> as they came into it.</p>

<p>We do <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> snap divers of the enemy in small <unclear>parties</unclear>; a Lieutenant of Col. <em>Fairfax's</em> Regiment with twelve <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg>, took four of <em><reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> <reg orig="owne">own</reg> Troop, and eight Horse, and one Lieutenant <em>Rutherford</em> who commanded them, narrowly escaped; <em>Glencairn</em> hath set out a Proclamation, threatening Fire and Sword to all those that do not comply with him in sending their Levies. Mr. <em>Jo. Goodwin's</em> 17 Queries are reprinted at Leith.</p>

<p>On Sunday last, 4 of Col. <em><reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg></em> and two of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em>, going from <em>Drummond</em> Castle for St. <em>Johnstons</em>, were set upon by about 50 of the Remains of Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs's</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> horse, who took 3 of them, killed 2 and the other escaped, There is a considerable party of the Enemy on those parts, about Contrie<!--I guess that this is a place rather than 'country'--> who are very active, since the drawing of the horse Northwards, but upon the coming in of the two Regiments from England, our horse will be placed so as to meet with them at all turns. Col. <em>Drummond</em> is certainly got, to the Enemy with further Instruction from <em>Charles Stuart</em>, from whom he is sent to see in what posture they are, and whether so considerable as to protect him, in case he should come to them this Summer. He tells them, that his Majesty strained hard to send them over a ship with ten thousand arms, which is cast away upon the coasts of Ireland though I am apt to think it is the same ship that was driven from the coasts of Loughaber to Killebiggs. There is nothing come since my last from the North.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels the 22 Febru. Stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>They do write from Paris that Beffort is taken, but we give no credit to it; for they say here, that it is still besieged by the Marshal of Senterre; who hath refused to receive the place upon Articles; conceiving he ought to have it at discretion, by reason of the obstinacy of those <pb n="2" />of the same Garrison, who are resolved not to yield the place but upon Articles of war, unless the Town be taken from them by storm. The Marquis of Faber, with his French army, doth yet keep the field, and gives out that he will come and drive the Duke of <em>Loraine</em> out of the Country of Liege, together with the Troops of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>. But on the contrary, the <em>Lorrainers</em> and the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> forces have agreed together, to go and find out the said Marquis in the <reg orig="Dukedome">Dukedom</reg> of Bouillon<!--Boulogne?-->, where they are quartered: for which purpose the said <em>Lorrainers</em> are building a bridge of boats, to pass the River of Meuse, there being no <reg orig="otherway">other way</reg> to get into the <reg orig="Dukedome">Dukedom</reg> this Winter time: so that they are like to drive away the said Marquis, who thought himself strong enough to have mastered the <em>Lorrainers</em>, and the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> forces. Thus between them both the strongest party is like to carry it right or wrong; both place would be glad to be rid of either party, the Countries being wholly exhausted and ruined between them. Great sums of moneys are raising here, for the speedy bringing the Army into the field, for this next Summers expedition.</p>

<p><em>Dublin</em> Castle February 1. We have here little, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Articles have lately been made with Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, in the behalf of all the Tories in Munster, for their transportation into Flanders, a Copy whereof I send you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>. The Lord Protector hath been proclaimed in <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg>, Clonmeil, and Tredagh, and this day, after a long Pause, in this place, but now the Bells are ringing, Cannons, and small sh<unclear><!--approx. 5 characters possibly split between two words-->ring</unclear>, and the acclamations of the people speak <reg orig="alowd">aloud</reg> their satisfaction of the present Government.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Articles of Agreement made <reg orig="end">and</reg> concluded on between Major <em>Peter Wallis,</em> and Capt. <em>Tho. Coakely</em>, on the one party; and Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, in the other behalf of himself and party on the other side.</i></head>

<p>That Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, with all such of his party as will adhere unto, and will <pb n="3" />engage with him to be transported into <em>Flanders</em>, for the service of the K of Spain, in that Army whereof the Prince of <em>Conde</em> is <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, do lay down their Arms, with such stores of Ammunition, and such other habiliments pf war, without <reg orig="imbezlement">embezzlement</reg>, as is hereafter expressed in this Article, by Wednesday the 25 of this instant January; <em>viz.</em> those of the county of <em>Cork</em> at <em>Moyallow</em>, and <em>Mackrompe</em>; those of the county of <em>Kerry</em> <em><reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg>, &amp;c.</em> in the respective Counties where they are, except what is hereafter excepted; to Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em> one case of Pistols, and to all other Commissioned Officers their Swords only.</p>

<p>2. That license be granted to the said Col. to transport himself, and as many of his party, as well of the Clergy, as others that do adhere unto him, and will engage with him for the service aforesaid; and also of all others protected persons, with such others as have been in Arms, as are willing to engage with the said Col. to be transported as aforesaid, submitting themselves to the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, according to the instructions of the Authority of this Nation; allowing the persons so submitting the benefit of the explanation of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, as is set down and annexed to the Articles made with the Lord <em><unclear>Muskery</unclear></em>.</p>

<p>3. That the said Col. be allowed Commissions for such numbers as he shall produce at the Waterside, according to the Establishment of the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Army, and likewise to <pb n="4" />every private Soldier six shillings each man at their going on shipboard, or twelve shillings each man when they are arrived in <em>Flanders</em>.</p>

<p>4. That the said Col. do produce at the Waterside at the Harbour of <em>Kingsale</em>, to be shipped in order to their transportation, upon or before the 14 day of <em>February</em> next ensuing, as many of his party as are now in arms in the County of <em>Cork, <reg orig="Kerr">Kerry</reg>, <reg orig="Limrick">Limerick</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Waterfoord">Waterford</reg></em>, as do adhere unto him, and will engage with him in the aforesaid service; and also of all such other persons as do adhere unto him, and engage with him as aforesaid.</p>

<p>5. That Free quarter be allowed the said Col. and all such of his party as do adhere unto him, and engage with him, and lay down their arms as aforesaid, from the time so laying down arms, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the time of their transportation, according to direction from their Col. <unclear><em>Pheir</em></unclear> or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, or of any other Governor <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> thereunto. And the benefit of quarter to be allowed to all such of the Clergy, and other protected, and such as have formerly been in arms, that do adhere unto the said Col, and engage with him from the time of their so adhering and engaging as aforesaid, provided that they, and every of them, content themselves with such ordinary diet as the Country usually allows themselves.</p>

<p>6. That eight <reg orig="daies">days</reg> time be allowed to rally and draw together all such of his said party now in the County of <em>Cork, Kerry, <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg>,</em> and <em>Waterford</em>, as do adhere unto him, and will engage <pb n="5" />with him for the service aforesaid without molestation or prejudice from any forces or <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> under the pay of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>; and likewise Free-quarter to all such of the said party in the respective Counties if they desire it where they now are, and their <reg orig="thorowfare">thoroughfare</reg> from County to county, in order to their laying down of Arms, as is before appointed; provided the said <reg orig="colonell">colonel</reg>, and every of the said party forbear all Act and Acts of hostility against the commonwealth of England their Forces and Garrisons; And all persons whatsoever under the protection of the commonwealth, provided also that the said colonel, or any of his party take not any prey or preys, or offer any violence to the protected People in the respective counties, after the date of these Articles, and the knowledge thereof communicated to them: An in case any prey be taken by the said col. or party after the date of these articles, before the <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg> be communicated as aforesaid, in that case the prey or preys so taken to be returned to the Owners, all but what is disposed of to the necessary relief of party or parties so taking the said prey or preys; the like restitution to be made for any other violence or injury done or committed by any of the said party after the aforesaid date of the said Articles.</p>

<p>7. That the said col. and all such other of his party as do adhere unto him, and engage with him as aforesaid, be freed and acquitted from all personal arrears for debt, or claims of that nature, and from all manner of molestation, for any <pb n="6" />prey or preys taken, or any other act or acts <reg orig="don">done</reg>, or committed by him, or every of them since the year 1640. but as is expected and provided for in the Article; provided also this extend not to the exempting of any of the Goods and chattels of any of the aforesaid persons so adhering and engaging, as aforesaid from making satisfaction for any just debts for which any of the said persons may be convicted by the due course of law.</p>

<p>8. That the said col. and all others of his party as do adhere unto him, as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> the clergy, as those that have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> in Arms, with such other protected persons as shall so adhere and <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him, as aforesaid, as also all such of his party as shall lay down their Arms as aforesaid, be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and admitted to dispose of their Goods and chattels to their best advantage within the aforesaid time of their Transportation.</p>

<p>9. That all such of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> party as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere and engage to transport themselves, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not, be forgiven the forfeitures of their Bonds, to themselves and their Sureties: and also that none of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> party now under his command be admitted to stay in this Nation, or to dispose of themselves without his license.</p>

<p>10. That the said Col. or any of his party so adhering and engaging, as aforesaid be admitted to recover any of his or their goods left in custody of any protected persons, which said persons have not discovered the said goods to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next adjacent Garrison before the signing hereof.</p>

<p>11. That the said Col be admitted to transport himself into Flanders as aforesaid, with fifteen hundred Irish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and in case the said Col. cannot produce at the Water-side the whole number by the time appointed, <pb n="7" />the said Col. then to be allowed to depute an Officer to stay behind, who shall be qualified with power to <reg orig="rallie">rally</reg> and raise so many as may make up the said number, which number so raised, to be transported as aforesaid, be allowed the benefit of these conditions in all particular, provided the said Officer or Deputy produce the said number of men at such Ports, and at such times as he shall be thereunto appointed by Col. <em>Phair</em>, or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them after the <unclear><!--blank approx. 4 characters--></unclear> of <unclear><!--blank approx. 9 characters--></unclear> next ensuing.</p>

<p>Provided also that the said Col. or Officer enter sufficient security to the said Col. <em>Phair</em> or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, that the said Officer, or any such as shall be raised or rallied in order to their transportation, as aforesaid, Act not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> during before the time of their transportation, to the prejudice of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, their Forces or Garrisons.</p>

<p>12. That the wives of all such of the said <reg orig="Colls.">Cols.</reg> party be allowed to enjoy the benefit of the act of Qualification equally with the Wives of others in protection.</p>

<p>13. That all such of the said <reg orig="Colls.">Cols.</reg> party to whom the charges of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> may extend be allowed 16 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time to state their cases in writing, and receive the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers thereupon and allow eight and forty hours after the knowledge of the opinion of the said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> is communicated unto the party so concerning, to dispose themselves for their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> security (if they desire it.)</p>

<p>14. That the Articles be confirmed and allowed of by his Excellency the Lord General.</p>

<p>15. That for the performance of these articles sufficient Hostages shall be given upon signing hereof.</p>

<p>16. In testimony whereof, we do hereunto <reg orig="interchangbly">interchangeably</reg> set our hands and seals, the 12th of <em>January</em> 1653.</p>
<p><i>Signed sealed and delivered in the presence of us, Tho. Mosse, Fr. Cartret, Nathaniel Child. Mortogh O Brien.</i></p>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen, Febru. 7. S.N.</i></head>

<p>Mr. <em>Williamson</em>, one of the late residents for this Crown in England, is departed hence few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> ago, with Commission from the King, to congratulate his Highness the Lord Protector of that Commonwealth; the King being <reg orig="overjoyd">overjoyed</reg> that he is included in the Dutch Treaty, thinking that his satisfying the Merchants is all that will be required at his hands.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Regensburgh </i>the 2 of<i> February S.N.</i></head>

<p>The States of the Empire, being now for the second time <em>per decretum</em> <reg orig="admonish'd">admonished</reg> by his <reg orig="emperial">imperial</reg> Majesty, to absolve the major part of the chief difficulties within the space of three months or less, (his said Majesty, being resolved at the ends of the said three months to move hence) meet <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, and are very earnest in the dispatch of their business. A very considerable sum of money, is come to the <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> Court out of Bohemia, as also great quantities of wine, whereof a good part was presented to his Highness the Prince Elector of Bayern.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg>, Febru.4. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The <em>Tartars</em>, withdrawing their forces out of this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>, have, contrary to their promise (and notwithstanding 150000 Guilders were given them only for that purpose) spread themselves far abroad in the Country, <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> and <reg orig="spoyling">spoiling</reg> the same all over, and taking away many thousands of men and beast; which the 1500 <reg orig="Polnish">Polish</reg> horsemen, that were given them for their convoy, had not been able to hinder, if another party of three thousand horse were not in all haste sent to their succour, who having overtaken them, <reg orig="beate">beat</reg> some parties of the <em>Tartars</em>, and relieved a great many thousands. Notwithstanding all this, it is given forth here, that the peace will hold, and be confined on the at-standing Ryxday, but there is small hopes of it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> the 7. dito S.V.<!--S.N.?--></i></head>

<p>There is a Dutch Agent come here from the Hague to reside in this City (as is thought) to oppose the Trade <pb n="9" />of the English, if the peace succeed not. Mr. <em>Williamson</em>, late Danish Resident in England, is also come to <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg>, who, as he gives forth, is going again for England, to congratulate the Lord Protector; he takes the Hague in his way to see the issue of the Treaty.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall February 17.</i></head>

<p>His Highness and his Council ordered the publication of two Ordinances. The one an Ordinance touching the assessing, levying and collection of the later 3 Months assessment, appointed by an Act of the late Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for an Assessment at the rate of an 120000 l by the Month, for 6 Months, from the 25 of December 1653. to the 24 of June then next ensuing, towards the maintenance of the Armies and Navies of this Commonwealth.</p>

<p>The other is <em>an Ordinance of Explanation touching Treasons</em>; as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Ordinance declaring that the Offences therein mentioned, and no other, shall be adjudged high Treason within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, it is, among other things Ordained and established; That no <reg orig="Mater">Matter</reg>, Fact, crime, or Offence whatsoever, other than such as are therein mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken, or adjudged to be high Treason; And whereas some Doubts and Questions may arise, whether that clause in the said Ordinances doth not extend to the offences mentioned in the Instrument, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, the Government of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and which are thereby declared to be <pb n="10" />High Treason; For clearing thereof, and removing all scruples thereupon, His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That neither the said Ordinance, nor any <reg orig="claus">clause</reg> or thing therein contained, shall extend or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend unto all or any the Offences declared by the said Instrument to be High Treason, but that all and every the said Offences are hereby adjudged, and shall be adjudged, taken and deemed to be high Treason; and that all and every the Offender and Offenders shall suffer the pains and penalties of High Treason, the said Ordinance, or anything therein contained to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Hen Scobell <em>Clerk of the Council.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris </i>Febr. 25. <i>stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>This Court hath at last resolved to congratulate his Highness the Lord Protector by their Ambassador Mr <em>Neufville</em>, to whom they have sent <reg orig="Authentique">Authentic</reg> Commission of Ambassador, who is to make know to his Highness the great desire the King hath to enter into amity with the commonwealth of England. On Sunday last the Marriage of the Prince of <em>Conti</em> with the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece was celebrated with much ceremony. The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> hath bestowed upon him his Palace, and given him One hundred thousand Escus in ready money down, and a Year hence he is to receive as much more: Since, he hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> continually feasted by the great ones of the Court. On the 17 of this Month, news was brought of the taking of Beffort by the Marshall of <em>Seneterre</em>, upon Articles of War.</p>

<pb n="11" />

<p>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is shortly to be beheaded <em>in effigies</em>, for not appearing according to Summons. <em>Charles Stuart</em> with his Train are leaving of this place, to try their fortunes in some other Country. One of the chiefest Authors of the tumults of the City of <em>Bordeaux</em>, called <em>Duresteste</em>, was lately apprehended and brought to <em>Raole</em>, where he was condemned to be broken upon the Wheel, and was since executed accordingly at <unclear><em>Bordeaux</em></unclear>; his head is to be set upon a stake, and his sentence written underneath, for an example to all those who will imitate him in his rebellion.</p>

<p>This last week several persons were apprehended in <em>London</em>, upon discovery of a Plot against the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and the present Government, whereupon they have been examined, <em>Feb.18.</em> Eleven of them were sent close prisoners to the Tower.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Rotterdam</em> Feb 20. <em>stilo novo.</em></head>

<p>We do not yet hear whether the Lord <em>Beverning</em>, who was sent into <em>England</em>, there to make known that the States of <em>Holland</em> did approve of the Articles of Peace agreed on at <em>Gravesend</em>, and that the other Provinces would soon declare the same, had obtained a Cessation of Arms, which was also given him in charge to demand. Which doth trouble us the more, because the English have taken the 3. of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> before <em>Ostend</em> nine of our ships coming from <em>Nantes</em> laden with wines, and four other ships going from <em>Middleburgh</em> to <em>Roan</em> with spice: So that we begin to mistrust very much the success of his Negotiation, or at least that no cessation of Arms is to be had. which hath caused our States to give order to the Admiralties to advance with all speed the equipage of the Sea, which is to be ready against the beginning of next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, Those of the Province of <em>Zealand</em> have also agreed to the Treaty made with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Our Resident in <em>Sweden</em> doth write, that the English Ambassador hath had several audiences since he came, and doth all what he can to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them of the force of his <pb n="12" />Superiors, and to dispose the Queen to unity with them. To which the Queen hath yet <reg orig="shewn">shown</reg> very little inclination, but hath commanded her Subjects to give her a list of all their losses and damages sustained by the <em>English</em>. The loss of our Merchant-men hath also caused our Admiralties to prohibit all Masters of ships to go to sea, upon the penalty of two thousand gilders, <reg orig="till">'till</reg> such time that the Lord <em>Beverning</em> be returned from <em>London</em> with the suspension of Arms, which he is to propose to the <em>Lord Protector</em>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> we are making all the haste we can to send over Extraordinary Ambassadors to sign the Treaty of Peace, who we believe will be going from hence about a fortnight hence; the more haste will be made to dispatch, since we do doubt very much that we shall not be able to obtain a Cessation of Arms so much desired for by all in general. Here is no doubt made but the rest of the Provinces will also <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, since <em>Holland</em> and <em>Zealand</em> have done the same.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Upsall</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, Jan 20.</head>

<p>We have no visible obstacle lies in our way, that may give us a distrust of accomplishing what we are come about. My <em>Lord Ambassador</em> and the <em>Grand Chancellor</em> have had two meetings to discuss our affairs; and they have not produced any such differences, but that we may well hope for a successful issue. At their meetings the Chancellor being satisfied by his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Commission, that he had power to conclude and determine of things, they went over all the articles in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>, and there did not seem to be started any such knotty <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg>, which did not receive its satisfactory answer. I suppose they will not break but after time has ripened the debates, we shall receive an answer to our full contentment. We have had news of the Change in <em>England</em>, and the Queen has <reg orig="receiv'd">received</reg> the new Credentials with all willingness, she having a great respect to my <em>Lord Protector</em>. You shall hear from hence as we make our progress.</p>

<pb n="13" />

<head level="3">From <em> Glencairn's</em> Proclamation</head>

<p><i>Whereas it hath pleased his Majesty to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> for opposing the common Enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his justice hath permitted to overcome and to be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove, and consume in his wrath, if we could turn to him by <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> repentance. And to the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that none of his faithful subjects may pretend ignorance, and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires and Parishes and head Burghs by open Proclamation, that every one may make his <reg orig="severall">several</reg> proportions ready to be delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under out hand wheresoever the <reg orig="foresaid">aforesaid</reg>  Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do <reg orig="remaia">remain</reg> disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of honour, will move to their duty, may be proceeded against with fire and sword, unworthy to be looked upon as Scotchmen, to the terror of all <reg orig="falsehearted">false-hearted</reg> Traitors, who by their treacheries and rebellions against their <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> King and his just Power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</i></p>

<p><i>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses has been brought forth from any well affected person or persons beyond their due preparation, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said horses has been taken, that they shall mete and stent themselves equally, for bearing equal burden, and <reg orig="refound">refund</reg> the persons from who any horses has been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of horses now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries, forth of every thousand pound of Rent: and the proportion of foot, every third man; and what Dragoons are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted <pb n="14" />for one Dragoon. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes; where no Burghs are, the Provost and Bailies of Burghs to Proclaim this at the <reg orig="Mercat">Market</reg> Cross of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as they will answer the contrary upon their highest peril. Given under our hand the first of <em>February, <reg orig="1954">1654</reg>. Sic subscribitur Glencarne.</em></i></p>

<p><i>God save King <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> the second.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith 14 Febr. 1653.</i></head>

<p>On Wednesday last, Col. <em>Morgan</em>, with 8 companies of Foot, 6 Troops of horse, and three Troops of dragoons, with a party of commanded horse out of the Mearnes of Angus, marched from <reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg>; and upon Thursday about two of the clock came to the Lough, at the head of Cromar, where <em>Glencarne</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at Rendezvous, and (after a little dispute) he totally routed their army; but being so near the hills he could do no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> to take and kill about 140: having pursued them 7 miles into the field. Their General hardly escaping with about 40 horse. After this engagement, Col. <em>Morgan</em> marched towards Kildrummy.</p>

<p>Nor was Capt. <em>Mutloe</em> in the Western Highlands idle, for hearing that the Laird of <em>Archaton</em> (being one of the chief Malignants in Lorne) had Garrisoned his house for the Enemy; he drew forth a party out of Dunstaffenage and Dunnely, fell upon the house, and after some dispute, having killed three of the enemy, <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> the house, and took a Lieutenant with other prisoners, and store of Ammunition and Arms. The Gent. And Heritors of the Shire of <em>Argyle</em> had lately a meeting, with the Marquis thereof at Innerara, where they resolved not to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those people now in Arms; but to be ready at 24 hours warning to oppose them. The business of Lewis was thus; <em>Norman mac Cloud</em> with 4 or 500 men landed in Lewis-Island, and after 3 or 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> staying in some inaccessible places of the Isle, fell upon our <reg orig="Souldiea">Soldiers</reg>, who lay at Sternway out of the Fort, and killed 12 of them; but a party out of the fort beat them thence, relieved the remainder <pb n="15" />of the men, removed the goods into the Fort and burnt the houses. The last week <reg orig="Leiut.">Lieut.</reg> Col, <em>Cottrel</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> out of Glasgow to reduce the Garrison of Rosdew near <em><reg orig="Loughlamond">Loch Lomond</reg></em>, and before he came near it, the Enemy ran away, and left word that they had no orders to fight. We hear also that <em>Brockie</em>, Capt. <reg orig="Leiut.">Lieut.</reg> to the late Col. <em>Wogan</em>, is dead of his wounds; and the Earl of <em>Athol</em> that fires and burns <reg orig="folks">folk's</reg> corn, and horses, threatened to shoot <em>Holland</em> the <reg orig="Chyrurgeon">Surgeon</reg> unto death, for not curing <em>Wogan</em> and <em>Brockie</em>. <reg orig="Som">Some</reg> of those blades begin to cry <em>Peccavi</em>, and sends to desire liberty to live peaceably; and no doubt ere long they will betray one another into our hands. This day the Lord <em>Calender</em> is apprehended upon an information against him of Correspondency.</p>

<p>I have <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> you one of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> Proclamations for the bringing in of Levies.</p>

<p>The Persons who stand committed to the Tower for the late treasonable Conspiracy, are these Eleven: Mr <em>Thomas Bunce</em>, Mr <em>Roger Cotes</em>, Mr <em>Thomas Dutton</em>, Mr <em>Joseph Sawyer</em>, Mr <em>Joseph Barker</em>, Mr <em>John Archer</em>, Mr <em>William Jenkins</em>, Mr <em>Roger Lee</em>, Captain <em>Smith</em>, Mr <em>Christopher Watkins</em>, Mr <em>Thomas Rosse</em>. Of the extent of their Conspiracy, and the Particulars you may hear hereafter.</p>

<head level="3">From Dalkeith February 16.</head>

<p>I have nothing of news since my last. The party that Lieut. Col. <em>Cotterel</em> sent from <reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg> to have <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> on the Shallop we lately lost in Clyde, went into the Highlands, to a Lough where it was, but upon their coming, <reg orig="shee">she</reg> was set on fire by them. Kenmore came privately with a small party into Dunkell on Friday last, which was the day after the Engagement with Col. morgan; from whom there is nothing since my last.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement.</i></head>

<p>As concerning the Peace with the Dutch, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed their Intentions are <reg orig="reall">real</reg>. For there are Ambassadors to come out of Holland, and their Friends here <reg orig="doe">do</reg> say, their business is to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> an Agreement, according to the late Treaty. They were looked for by the Heer Beverning every day this week, and are still expected so that its conceived, it cannot be long ere they arrive in England.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">A brief Exposition of the Prophecies of</head>
<p>&#x261e; <em>Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, Habbakkuk &amp; Zephaniah</em></p>

<p>By Mr <em>George Hutcheon</em>, Minister at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Recommended unto the reader by Mr <em>David Dickson</em> and Mr <em>Edmund</em> <unclear><em><!--7 characters--></em></unclear>. Sold by <em>Ralph Smith</em> at the Bible in Cornhill.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>