<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol186">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 186</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> December 29. to <em>Thursday</em> January 5. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Mylor in Cornwall, December 26.</i></head>

<p>We have had a French wine <reg orig="prises">prizes</reg> brought in by the <em>Non-such</em> and <em>Assistance</em> <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, last week. They <reg orig="belong'd">belonged</reg> to the Dutch, who forsook their ships and fled ashore in their Boats, but left a Match and Train to blow up our men, which was near the Act. Only, one Match did burn, which was <reg orig="spyd">spied</reg> and valiantly repulsed by ours.</p>

<p><i>From Dalkeith December 16.</i> The broken people under <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em>, are now <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> towards the North by the Bray of <em>Mar</em>, Report speaks them 5000 Horse and Foot, and by a joint concurrence of Intelligence they cannot be less than 3000. <reg orig="Assoon">As soon</reg> as the Marq. Of <em>Huntley</em> was dead, divers of his Followers went to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and being met by 8 Troopers of Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment, who questioned them for Riding with Arms; they pleaded they were allowed them by the capitulation, but at last fell to blows, in which one of them and two of ours were slain, and at last a party of the Enemy came up and overpowered our men, took 4 more, and the other 2 narrowly escaping. Whether they intend for <em><reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg></em>, or to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in <em>Murray</em> land for <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> of Quarters, is <pb n="1" />not certain; but our Forces are <unclear>ready to oppose them with what</unclear> strength we have in <unclear><!--approx. 23 characters, more than 1 word--></unclear> lately taken and imprisoned some <unclear><!--approx 13 characters probably more than 1 word--></unclear> <em>Blackford</em> in <em>Perthshire</em>, for denying their Levies, and give out they will proceed in like manner <unclear>others</unclear>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels January 4. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The Packet-boat from <em>England</em> is not come this week, which maketh us to surmise that there hath happened some new alteration in the Government amongst you: We discourse here strangely, though we know nothing of it: Only we hear that all your Ports are shut, and that you will not suffer a Boat to go out to bring any news as yet of your transactions. But we hear by a Ketch that is lately arrived, who bringeth news that you have dissolved your new Parliament, and that the Army is divided about it: we expect every hour to hear the certainty thereof.</p>

<p>Here is a <reg orig="rumor">rumour</reg> as if the King of <em>Scots</em> should be <reg orig="past">passed</reg> through this Town <em>Incognito</em> in aCoach of six horses towards <em>Holland</em>. But our last Letters from <em>France</em> mention him to be still at <em>Paris</em>; and therefore this is not to be believed; but here are those that will not be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> of the contrary. Here is lately come from <em>London</em>, General <em>Marsin</em>, and goeth hence within this day or two to find out the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, to give an account of his Negotiation in <em>Spain</em>. The said Prince wageth with his Troops a little new War in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em> to get their Winter-quarters. The Inhabitants having <reg orig="everywhere">every where</reg> put themselves in a posture of defence, and standing on their guard, to maintain their <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> and freedom: So that those of the Prince of <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> Forces have taken from them by force of arms, the little Town if <em>Fosses</em>, <reg orig="scituated">situated</reg> between Sambre and the <em>Meuse</em> two Rivers so called in that Country; But not being content with this one place they are <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> against the Town of <em>Chastelet</em>, upon the said River <em>Sambre</em>, which without doubt they will be master of in a short time. They have also a design to take <em>Dinant &amp; Chinai</em>, which places are to serve the said Prince of <em>Conde</em> for a Principality, and <em>Rocroy</em> is intended for his capital City: whereof his son the Duke of <em>Anguien</em> is Governor, and the Earl of <em>Bouteville</em> his Lieutenant, having within that place a very strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of his own Troop, which doth force the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> round about to pay Contribution to him towards their <reg orig="maintainance">maintenance</reg>. According to his Majesty the King of <em><reg orig="Spains">Spain's</reg></em> command, his Highness the Archduke hath caused the Lord <em>Charles de Hovines</em> to be declared Chief and President of the Privy <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, to the great content of <reg orig="som">some</reg>, and discontent of others.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3">From <em>Paris</em> January 3. <i>stilo novo.</i></head>

<p><i>This whole Town is filled now with the discourse of the dissolution of the Parliament <unclear><!--a big space here "in" seems likely--></unclear> England, whereupon men spend their judgements, according to their various tempers and disposition of <reg orig="minde">mind</reg>. But the ill-willers were not so jocund when they heard of the manner of the dissolution; that it was a voluntary act of their own grounded upon many serious and weighty considerations of the major and more sober part of the members of Parliament, to prevent the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of Religion and Liberty, both like to be swallowed up by a licentious party among them. I am confident, had your Ministers been <reg orig="pull'd">pulled</reg> down (as was here expected by all the Doctors) an Act could not have been done in all the world more grateful to the Pope and his Emissaries the <em>Jesuits</em>, throughout <em>Europe</em>: So that by this alteration of yours, the Protestant interest seems raised again from the dead, and we trust will once again <reg orig="finde">find</reg> protection in <em>England</em>; upon which Account, the Churches of God do hope, that they may have cause to bless God for your new made Election</i></p>

<p><i>Here is news come, that the Garrison of <em>Philipsbourg</em> is yielded up to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> party. It is said likewise, that <em>Befford</em> is surrendered to the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> of <em>Uxelles</em>. This will give Count <em>Harcourt</em> occasion to look about him.</i></p>

<p><i>Advice in arrived here, that some of the Prince of <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> party have made an inroad into <reg orig="Champaigne">Champagne</reg>, where they seized great store of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>; and that he himself; having by a vomit rid away his Quartane-Ague, is departed from <em>Rocroy</em>, by way of <em>Namur</em> to <em>Brussels</em>, there to take the <reg orig="Aire">Air</reg>; but principally, to take away all jealousies from the <reg orig="Spanyards">Spaniards</reg>, that they may not suspect of any underhand treaty with the Court of <em>France</em>; of which there hath been some talk of late.</i></p>

<p><i>On Thursday, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and his small Court, met the King and Queen at the Jesuits <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in <em>St. <reg orig="Anthonies">Anthony's</reg></em> street, whether their Majesties had retired to Even-Service; which was performed with great solemnity, by the <reg orig="musick">music</reg> of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> own Chapel, After their Devotions the King and Queen entertained <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, with his two brothers, the pretended Dukes of <em>York</em> and <em>Gloucester</em>, at a sumptuous Collation. Their mother is immured at <em>Chaliot</em>, to exercise her devotion there, this Festival, among the Nuns. They are very <reg orig="frolick">frolic</reg> with the two hundred thousand Crowns that they got of <em>Germany</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the dominions thereto belonging. As it was <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> declared at Westminster, the 16 day of December, 1653. &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>I. That the Supreme Legislative Authority of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, shall be, and reside in one person, and the People assembled in Parliament; The style of which person shall, <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em> of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</p>

<p>II. That the exercise of the chief magistracy and administration of the government over the said Countries and dominions, and <pb n="3" />the people thereof, shall be in the <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em>, assisted with a Council; the number whereof shall not exceed twenty one, nor be less <reg orig="then">than</reg> thirteen.</p>

<p>III. That all Writs, Processes, Commissions, Patents, Grants, and other things, which now run in the name and <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of the Keepers of the liberty of England by the Authority of Parliament, shall run in the name and <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of the <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em> from whom, for the future, shall be derived all Magistracy and <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> in these three Nations; and shall have the power of pardons, (except in case of Murder and Treason) and benefit of <reg orig="al">all</reg> forfeitures for the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> use. And shall <reg orig="governe">govern</reg> the said Countries and Dominions in all things by the advice of the Council; and according to these presents, and the laws.</p>

<p>IV That the <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em>, the Parliament <reg orig="siting">sitting</reg>, shall dispose and order the Militia and Forces, both by Sea and Land, for the peace and good of the three Nations, by consent of Parliament; and that the <em>Lord PROTECTOR</em>, with the advice and consent of the major part of the Council, shall dispose and order the Militia for the ends aforesaid in the intervals of Parliament.</p> 

<p>V. That the <em>Lord Protector</em> by the advice aforesaid shall direct, in all things, concerning the keeping and holding of a good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Kings, Princes and States; and also with the consent the major part of the Council have the power of war and peace.</p>

<p>VI. That the Laws shall not be <reg orig="altred">altered</reg>, suspended, abrogated, or repealed, nor any new Law made, nor any Tax, Charge, or Imposition laid upon the people, but by common consent in Parliament, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as is expressed in the 30 Article.</p>

<p>VII. That there shall be a Parliament summoned to meet at Westminster upon the third day of <em>September</em> 1654. and that successively, a Parliament shall be summoned once every third year, to be accounted from the dissolution of the preceding Parliament.</p>

<p>VIII. That neither the Parliament to be next summoned, nor any successive Parliaments, shall, during the time of five months, to be accounted from the day of their first meeting, be adjourned, prorogued, or dissolved without their own consent.</p>

<p>IX. That as well the next, as all other successive Parliaments, shall be summoned, and elected in manner hereafter <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; That is to say, the persons chosen in within England, Wales, the Isle of Jersey and Guernsey, and the town of Berwick upon Tweed to sit and serve in Parliament, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, and not exceed, the number of 400. The persons to be chosen within Scotland, to sit in Parliament, shall be, and not exceed, the number of 30. And the Persons to be chosen to sit in Parliament for Ireland, shall be, and not exceed the number 30.</p>

<p>X. That the Persons to be elected to sit in Parliament from time to time for the several Counties of England, Wales, the Isles of Jersey <pb n="4" />and Guernsey, and the town of Berwick upon Tweed, and all places within the same respectively, shall be according to the proportion and numbers hereafter <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>.</p>

<p><i>But for these numbers, I will (for want of room) refer you to next week.</i></p>

<p>The distribution of the Persons to be chosen for <em>Scotland</em>, and the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties, Cities, and places within the same, shall be according to such proportions and number, as shall be agreed upon, and declared by the <em>Lord Protector</em> and the major part of the Council, before the sending forth of Writs of Summons for the next Parliament, The distribution of the persons to be chosen for <em>Ireland</em>, and the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties, Cities, and places within the same, shall be according to such Propositions and number, as shall be agreed upon, and declared by the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and the major part of the Council, before the sending forth Writs of Summons for the next Parliament.</p>

<p>XI. That the summons to Parliament shall be writ under the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, directed to the Sheriffs of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Counties, with such alteration as may suit with the present Government, to be made by the <em>Lord Protector</em> and his Council, which the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great Seal, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> seal, issue, and send abroad by Warrant from the Lord <em>Protector</em>. If the Lord <em>Protector</em> shall not give Warrant for issuing of Writs of Summons for the next Parliament, before the first day of <em>June</em>, 1654. or for the Triennial Parliaments before the first day of <em>August</em> in the third year, to be accounted as aforesaid, That then the <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg>, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great Seal for the time being, shall, without any Warrant or direction, within seven <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the said first day of <em>June</em>, 1654. Seal, Issue, and send abroad Writs of Summons (changing therein what is to be changed as aforesaid) to the several and respective <reg orig="Sherrifs">Sheriffs</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, for summoning the Parliament to meet at <em>Westminster</em>, the third of <unclear><em>September</em></unclear> next; and shall likewise within seven <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the said first day of <unclear><em>August</em></unclear>, in every third year; to be accounted from the dissolution of the precedent Parliament, Seal, Issue, and send abroad several Writs of Summons changing therein what is to be changed, as aforesaid, for summoning the Parliament to meet at <em>Westminster</em> the <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> of <em>November</em> in <unclear>that</unclear> third year. That the said <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Sheriffs shall, within ten days after the Receipt of such Writs as aforesaid, cause the same to be proclaimed and published in every Market-town within his county, upon the Market days <unclear>thereof</unclear> between Twelve and Three of the clock; and shall then also publish and declare the certain day of the week and month for <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> Members <pb n="5" />to serve in Parliament for the Body of the said County, according to the tenor of the said Writ, which <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> upon Wednesday five weeks after the date of the Writ &amp; shall likewise declare the place where the Election shall be made; for which purpose he shall appoint the most convenient place for the county to meet in and shall send Precepts for Elections to be made in all and every City, Town, Borough, or place within his County, where Elections are to be made by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of these Presents, to the Mayor, Sheriff, or other head Officer of such City, Town, Borough, or place, within 3 days after the Receipt of such Writ and Writs, which the said Mayor, Sheriffs, and Officers respectively are to make publication of, and of the certain day for such Elections to be made in the said City, Town or place aforesaid, and to cause Election to be made accordingly.</p>

<p>12. That the day and place of Elections, the Sheriff of each County, and the said Mayors, Sheriffs, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other Head Officers within their Cities, Towns, Boroughs and places respectively, shall take view of the said Elections, and shall make return into the <em>Chancery</em> within Twenty days after the said Elections of the persons elected by the greater number of Electors, under their Hands and Seals, between him on the one part, and the Electors on the other part; wherein shall be contained, That the Persons elected <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not have power to alter the Government as it is hereby <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in one single Person and a Parliament.</p>

<p>13. That a Sheriff who shall willingly make any false Return, or neglect his duty, shall incur the penalty of Two thousand Marks of <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> English <reg orig="mony">money</reg>; the one Moiety to the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and the other moiety to such person as will sue for the same.</p>

<p>14 That all and every person and persons who have aided, advised, assisted, or abetted in any War against the Parliament, since the first of <em>January</em>, <unclear>1641</unclear> (unless they have been since in the service of the Parliament, and given signal testimony of their good Affections thereunto) shall be disabled, and be uncapable to be elected, or to give any Vote in the Election of any Members to serve in the next Parliament, or in the three succeeding Triennial Parliaments.</p>

<p>15 That all such, who have advised, assisted, or abetted the Rebellion of <em>Ireland</em>, shall be disabled and uncapable <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> to be elected, or to give any Vote in the Election of any Member to serve in Parliament; as also all such who do or shall <unclear>profess</unclear> the Roman <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</p>

<p>16 That all Votes and Elections given or made contrary or not according to these Qualifications, shall be null and void: And if any person who is hereby made uncapable, shall give his Vote for Election <pb n="6" />of Members to serve in Parliament, such person shall lose <!--3-4 character space here, possibly "and" missing-->forfeit one full <reg orig="yeers">year's</reg> value of his real estate; and one full third <unclear>part</unclear> of his personal estate; one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the Lord Protector, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to him, or them who shall sue for the same.</p>

<p>17 That the persons who shall be elected to serve in Parliament, shall be such (and no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> such) as are persons of known Integrity, fearing God, and of good conversation, and being of the age of 21 years.</p>

<p>18 That all and every person and persons seized or possessed to his own use, of any estate real or personal, to the value of 200l. and not within the aforesaid Exceptions, shall be capable to elect members to serve in Parliament for Counties.</p>

<p>19 That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great Seal, shall be sworn before they enter into their Offices, <reg orig="truely">truly</reg> and faithfully to issue forth and send abroad Writs of Summons to Parliaments at the times, and in manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; And in case of neglect or <reg orig="failer">failure</reg>, to issue &amp; send abroad Writs accordingly, he or they shall for every such offence be guilty of High Treason, and suffer the pains and penalties thereof.</p>

<p>20 That in case of Writs be not issued out, as is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, but that there be a neglect therein, fifteen days after the time wherein the same ought to be issued out by the Chancellor, Keeper of Commissioners of the Great Seal, that then the Parliament shall, as often as such <reg orig="failer">failure</reg> shall happen, assemble and be held at <em>Westminster</em>, in the usual place, at the times <reg orig="prefixt">prefixed</reg>, in manner and by the means hereafter expressed; That is to say, That the Sheriffs of the several and respective Counties, Shrievedoms, Cities, Boroughs and places aforesaid, within <em>England, Wales, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, the Chancellor, Masters and Scholars of the Universities of <em>Oxford</em> and <em>Cambridge</em>, and the Major and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of the Borough of <em>Berwick</em> upon <em>Tweed</em>, and other the places aforesaid respectively shall at the several Courts and places to be appointed as aforesaid, within 30 days after the said 15 days, cause such Members to be chosen for their said several and respective Counties, Shrievedoms, Universities, Cities, Boroughs and places aforesaid, by such persons and in such manner, as if several and respective Writs of Summons to Parliament under the Great Seal had issued and been awarded according to the Tenor aforesaid: That if the Sheriff or other persons <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> shall neglect his or their duty herein; That all and every such Sheriff and person <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> as aforesaid, so neglecting his or their duty, shall, for every such offence, be guilty of High Treason, and shall suffer the pains and penalties thereof.</p>

<p><!--not numbered but should presumably be 21--><i>That the Clerk, called <em>The Clerk of the Commonwealth</em>, in Chancery for the time being, and all others, who shall afterwards execute that Office, to whom the Returns shall be made, shall for the next Parliament, and the two succeeding Triennial Parliaments, the next day after such Return, <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> the Names of the several persons so returned, and of the places <pb n="7" />for which he and they were chosen respectively, unto the Council, who shall peruse the said Returns, and examine whether the persons so Elected and Returned be such as is agreeable to the Qualifications, and not disabled to be elected. And that every such person or persons being so <reg orig="duely">duly</reg> Elected, and being approved of by the major part of the Council to be persons not disabled, but qualified as aforesaid, shall be esteemed a Member of Parliament, and be admitted to sit in Parliament, and not otherwise.</i></p>

<p><i>22 That the persons chosen and assembled in manner aforesaid, or any 60 of them, shall be, and be deemed the Parliament of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; and the supreme Legislative power to be and reside in the Lord Protector and such Parliament, in manner herein <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>23 That the Lord Protector, with the advice of the major part of the Council, shall at any other time <reg orig="then">than</reg> is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, when the necessities of the State shall require it, summon Parliaments in manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, which shall not be adjourned, prorogued, or dissolved without their own consent, during the first three months of their sitting, and in case of future War with any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> State, a Parliament shall be forthwith summoned for their advice concerning the same.</i></p>

<p><i>24 That all Bills agreed unto by the Parliament, shall be presented to the Lord Protector for his consent; and in case he shall not give his consent thereto, within 20 days after they shall be presented to him, or give satisfaction to the Parliament within the time limited; that then, upon Declaration of the Parliament, that the Lord Protector hath not consented nor given satisfaction, such Bills shall pass into, and <unclear><!--approx. 11 characters--></unclear>laws, although he shall not give his consent thereunto; provided such Bills contain nothing in them nothing contrary to the matters contained in these Presents.</i></p>

<p>25 That <em>Philip</em> Lord Viscount <em>Lisle, Charles Fleetwood</em> Esquire, <em>John Lambert</em> Esquire, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em> <reg orig="Barronet">Baronet</reg>, Sir <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Wolsley</em> Baronet, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em> Bar. <em>Edward Montague</em>, Esq. <em>John Desborow</em> Esq;<em> Walter Strickland</em> Esq; <em>Henry Lawrence</em> Esq; <em>William Sydenham</em> Esq; <em>Philip Jones</em> Esq; <em>Richard Major</em> Esq; <em>Francis Rous Phil. Skippon</em>, Esqs, or any seven of them, shall be a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for purposes <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in this Writing; and upon the death or other removal of any of them, the Parliament shall nominate six persons of ability, integrity, and fearing God, for every one that is dead or removed, out of which the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> shall elect two and present them to the Lord Protector, of which he shall elect one:</p>

<p>And in case the Parliament shall not nominate within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after notice given to them thereof, the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> shall nominate three as aforesaid to the Lord Protector, who out of them shall supply the vacancy; and until this choice be made, the remaining part of the Council shall execute as fully in all things, as if their number were full: And in case of corruption, or other miscarriage in any of the Council in their trust, the Parliament shall appoint seven of their numbers, and the Council six, who, together with the Lord Chancellor, Lord Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal for the time being, shall have power to hear and determine <pb n="8" />such corruption and miscarriage, and to award and inflict punishment, as the nature of the Offence shall deserve; which punishment shall not be pardoned nor remitted by the Lord Protector: And in the interval of Parliaments, the major of the Council, with the consent of the Lord Protector, may, for Corruption, or other miscarriage as aforesaid, suspend any of their number from the exercise of their Trust, if they shall <reg orig="finde">find</reg> it just, until the matter shall be heard and examined as aforesaid.</p>

<p>XXVI. That the Lord Protector and the major part of the Council aforesaid, may at any time before the meeting of the next Parliament, add to the Council such persons as they shall think fit; provided the number of the Council be not made thereby to exceed 21. And that the <em>Quorum</em> to be proportioned accordingly by the Lord Protector and the major part of the Council.</p>

<p>XXVII. That a constant yearly revenue shall be raised, <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and <reg orig="establisht">established</reg> for maintaining of 10000 Horse and Dragoons, and 20000 Foot, in England, Scotland and Ireland, for the defence and security thereof, and also for a convenient number of Ships for guarding of the Seas; besides 200000 <em>per annum</em> for defraying the other necessary charges for administration of Justice, and other <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government: which revenue shall be raised by the Customs, and such other <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and means as shall be agreed upon by the Lord Protector and Council, and shall not be taken away or diminished, nor the way agreed upon for raising the same altered, but by the consent of the Lord Protector and the Parliament.</p>

<p>XXVIII. That the said yearly revenue shall be paid into the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Treasury, and shall be issued out for the uses aforesaid.</p>

<p>XXIX. That in case there not be cause hereafter to keep up so great a defence at land or sea, but that there be an abatement made thereof; the money which will be saved thereby, shall remain in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service, and not be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to any other use but by consent of Parliament, or in the intervals of Parliament, by the Lord Protector and major part of the Council.</p>

<p>XXX. That the raising of money for defraying the charge of present extraordinary forces both at Land and Sea, in respect of the present wars, shall be by consent in Parliament and not otherwise; save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Lord Protector, with the consent of the major part of the Council, for preventing the disorders and dangers which may otherwise fall out both at sea and land, shall have power, until the meeting of the first parliament, to raise money for the purposes aforesaid, and also to make laws and ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force, until order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same.</p>

<p>XXXI. That the Lands, Tenements, Rents, Royalties, Jurisdictions and Hereditaments which <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> yet unfold or undisposed of by Act or Ordinance of Parliament, belonging to the Commonwealth, <pb n="9" />(except the Forests and Chases, and the <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> and Manors belonging to the same; the Lands of the Rebels in <em>Ireland</em>, lying in the four Counties of <em>Dublin, Cork, Kildare</em> and <em>Katerlaugh</em>; the Lands forfeited by the people of <em>Scotland</em> in the late Wars: and also the Lands of Papists and Delinquents in <em>England</em>, who have not yet compounded) shall be vested in the Lord Protector; To hold to him and his Successors, Lord Protectors of these Nations, and shall not be alienated, but by consent in Parliament: And all Debts, Fines, Issues, <unclear>Amerciaments</unclear>, Penalties and Profits, certain and casual, due to the Keep<!--hyphenated at the line break, "Keeper"?--> of the Liberties of <em>England</em> by Authority of Parliament, shall be due to the Lord Protect, and be payable into his <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Receipt, and shall be recovered and prosecuted in his Name.</p>

<p>32 That the Office of the Lord Protector over these Nations, shall Elective, and not Hereditary; and upon the death of the Lord Protector, <reg orig="an other">another</reg> fit person shall be forthwith elected to succeed him in the Government, which Election shall be by the Council; who immediately upon the death of the Lord Protector, shall assemble in the Chamber where they usually sit in Council, and having given notice to all their number, of the cause of their assembling, shall, being thirteen at least present, proceed to the Election; and before they depart out of the said Chamber, shall elect a fit person to succeed in the Government, and forthwith cause Proclamation thereof to be made in all the three Nations as shall be requisite: And the person that they or the major part of them shall elect, as aforesaid, shall be, and shall be taken to be Lord Protector over these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging: Provided that none of the children of the late King, nor any of his Line or Family be elected to be Lord Protector or other chief Magistrate over these Nations, or any the Dominions thereunto belonging. And until the aforesaid Election be past, the Council shall take care of the government, and administer in all things as fully as the Lord Protector, or the Lord Protector and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> are enabled to do.</p>

<p>33 That <em>Oliver Cromwell</em> Captain General of the Forces of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, shall be, and is hereby declared to be Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, for his life.</p>

<p>34 That the Chancellor, Keeper or Commissioners of the Great Seal, Treasurer, Admiral, chief Governors of <em>Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, and the chief Justices of both the Benches, shall be chosen by the approbation of Parliament; and in the intervals of Parliament, by the approbation approbation<!--this repetition is presumably a printers error--> of the major part of the Council, to be afterwards approved by the Parliament.</p>

<p>35 That the Christian Religion, contained in the Scriptures, be held forth and recommended as the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Profession of these Nations; &amp; that as soon as may be, a provision less subject to scruple and contention, and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present, be made for the encouragement and maintenance of able and painful Teachers, for instructing <pb n="10" />the People, and for discovery and confutation of error, <reg orig="Heresie">Heresy</reg>, and whatever is contrary to sound Doctrine: And that, until such Provision be made, the present Maintenance shall not be taken away or impeached.</p>

<p>XXXVI. To the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> profession held forth, <reg orig="non">none</reg> shall be compelled by penalties or otherwise, but that endeavours be used to win them by sound Doctrine, and the example of a good conversation.</p>

<p>XXXVII. That such as profess faith in God by Jesus Christ (though differing in judgement from the doctrine, worship or discipline <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth) shall not be restrained from, but shall be protected in the profession of the faith, and exercise of their religion; so as they abuse not this liberty, to the civil injury of others, and to the actual disturbance of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> peace on their parts: provided this liberty be not extended to Popery or Prelacy, nor to such as, under the protection of Christ, hold forth and practice licentiousness.</p>

<p>XXXVIII. That all Laws, Statutes, and Ordinances and Clauses in any Law, Statute and Ordinance to the contrary of the aforesaid liberty, shall be esteemed as null and void.</p>

<p>XXXIX. That the Acts &amp; Ordinances of Parliament, made for the sale or other disposition of the Lands, Rents and Hereditaments of the late King, Queen and Prince, of <reg orig="Arch-Bishops">Archbishops</reg> and Bishops, &amp;c. Deans and Chapters, the Lands of Delinquents, and Forest Lands, or any of them; or of any other Lands, Tenements, Rents and Hereditaments belonging to the Commonwealth, shall no way be impeached or made invalid; but shall remain good and firm: And that the Securities given by Act and Ordinance of Parliament for any sum or sums of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, by any of the said Lands, the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, or by any other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Revenue; and also the securities given by the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith of the Nation; and the engagement of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> faith for satisfaction of debts and damages, shall remain firm and good, and not be made void and invalid upon any pretence whatsoever.</p>

<p>XL. That the Articles given to, or made with the Enemy, and afterwards confirmed by Parliament, shall be performed and made good to the persons concerned therein. And that such appeals, as were depending in the last Parliament, for relief concerning Bills of Sale of <reg orig="Delinquents">Delinquent's</reg> Estates, may be heard and determined the next Parliament, <reg orig="Any thing">Anything</reg> in this writing, or otherwise to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>XLI. That every successive Lord Protector over these Nations shall take and subscribe a solemn Oath, in the presence of the Council, and such others as they shall call to them, That he will seek the peace, quiet, and welfare of these Nations, cause law and justice be equally administered, and that he will not violate or infringe the matters and things contained in this writing and in all other things <pb n="11" />will to his power, and to the best of his understanding, <reg orig="governe">govern</reg> these Nations, according to the Law, Statute, and Customs.</p>

<p>XLII. That each person of the Council shall, before they enter upon their trust, take, and subscribe an Oath, that they will be true and faithful in their trust, according to the best of their knowledge; and, that in the election of every successive Lord Protector, they shall proceed therein impartially, and do nothing therein for any promise, fear, <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> or reward.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Oath taken by his Highness <em>OLIVER CROMWELL</em>, Lord PROTECTOR.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Wheras">Whereas</reg> the major part of the last Parliament (judging that their sitting any longer, as then constituted, would not be for the good of this Commonwealth) did dissolve the same, and by a writing under their hands, dated the twelfth day of this instant <em>December</em>, resigned unto me their powers and authorities; And whereas it was necessary thereupon, that some speedy course should be taken for the settlement of these Nations upon such a basis and foundation, as by the blessing of God, might be lasting, secure property, and answer those great ends, of religion and liberty, so long contended for; and upon full and mature consideration had of the form of government hereunto annexed, being satisfied that the same, through divine assistance, may answer the ends aforementioned; and having also been desired, and advised, as well by several persons of interest and fidelity in this Commonwealth, as the Officers of the Army, to take upon me the Protection and government of these Nations in the manner expressed in the said form of government, I have accepted thereof, and do hereby declare my acceptance accordingly, And do promise in the presence of God, that I will not violate, or infringe the matters and things contained therein, but to my power, observe the same, and cause them to be observed. And shall in all other things, to the best of my understanding, govern these Nations according to the <pb n="12" />Laws, Statutes and Customs, seeking their peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally administered.</p>

<p>O.CROMWELL</p>

<p><i><em>Oliver Cromwell</em>, Captain <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of all the Forces of this Commonwealth, and now declared <em>Lord Protector</em> thereof, did this 6 of December 1653. sign this Writing, and solemnly promise, as is therein contained, in presence of the Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, who administered the same Oath, and of the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of London, divers of the Judges of the Land, the Officers of State and Army, and many other persons of Quality.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> December 20.</i></head>

<p>The last Letters from Holland speak that People generally for Peace, and the Dane begins to doubt they will lurch him. He knows them, and hath had a feeling of their practices upon him heretofore.</p>

<p>The lofty Terms propounded by the French Ambassador at the Hague, are looked on here as <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Court <reg orig="ginns">gins</reg>, which will not take the costive <em>Hollander</em>, who know the odds twixt a French promise and performance; nor is it imaginable, that this interposition of the Monsieur there, should work <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> at all upon the Queen of Sweden. Its supposed, the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> will have a stronger influence on that Horizon. The <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> that convoyed his Lordship, did (as we hear) <reg orig="met">meet</reg> with 4 Dutch Merchantmen, bound homeward from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> well laden.</p>

<p>The last Letters from <em>Stockholm</em> report the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> on his way to <em>Upsabla</em>, within two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> Journey of the Court. Two of his Gentlemen were already <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> there, at the coming away of the Post, which is all the news we have here of his Lordship at present. Doubtless, he had a bad journey of it, this being the worst season of the year for <reg orig="Travail">Travel</reg> in that Country, there having been as yet no bearing Frosts: But the Letters speak of great Preparations to receive the Ambassador most <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg>. It will be well if they prove as <reg orig="reall">real</reg> and ready in the main of the Negotiation, as doubtless they will be splendid in the ceremonial <reg orig="paat">part</reg>; that noble Lady affecting gallantry.</p>

<p>This week brings nothing of moment from the <em><reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg></em> Court. And from the Dane is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> said, they talk of equipping a great Fleet against Spring. I suppose their Fears put them upon large thoughts: but the Dutch, their Confederates having failed them in Money, they will be to seek of that. This is certain, the Danes are vehemently jealous, that the Dutch will lurch them in <pb n="13" />the Treaty. The loftiest Prince in <em>Christendom</em>, would hardly have ventured to give <em>England</em> such an Affront, as that bold <em>Bayard</em> did.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris the</i> 28 Decem.</head>

<p>The happy establishment of your Commonwealth, doth still more and more perplex the Royal party here at the <em>Lovure</em>, where their opinions are divided; some do hope that this will cause the Army to divide in regard <em>Harrison</em> and his party are laid aside, which may make for their advantage in the end. Others more solid in judgement, look upon this way of settlement as a means to unite all interests, and to settle the Nation in peace and quietness with <reg orig="its">it's</reg> neighbour Nations so that these men have no courage to hope that <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> will accrue hereby to their advantage. Yesterday the Marquis of <em>D'eras</em>, the Earl of d' <unclear><em>Arbioux</em></unclear> and two other Lords, whose names I will give to you in my next; came to the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal by eight of the clock in the morning in a Hackney Coach, and fought a Duel with short swords, and so much rage, that on a sudden two were killed upon the place, and the other two fled immediately, and have not been heard of since. His Majesty the King of <em>France</em> doth intend to make a journey shortly into <em>Normandy</em>, where it is said, that the Cardinal hath a design to establish the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> in the place of Monsieur de <em>Longueville</em>. His said Majesty hath laid a new Impost of fifteen pence upon <pb n="14" />every Ream of Paper that shall be brought in 5 which is no pleasing news to the people. They do now for certain intend to go about the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>. I hear they have already made a choice of a place for their sitting.</p>

<p>There is no certainty yet of the revolt of <em>Philipsbourg</em>, as I told you in my last; the Letters that came lately from thence makes no mention of it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Rotterdam</em>, the 2 of January</i>, stilo novo.</head>

<p>There is little news to write at present, there being no Post come this week, which doth cause us to suspect that you have once more dissolved the Parliament. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, we <reg orig="onely">only</reg> expect the resolutions of your Commonwealth, to make peace or war, being equally disposed to one or the other, for our rest, or for our reputation; and as there is more likelihood for us to continue the war, seeing you do not answer our good intentions, by showing yourselves so high in your demands, there is a general willingness to contribute sufficiently, <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> according to his estate and means, towards the maintaining of necessary <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> for the defence of our Provinces. And for this purpose we are building of ships in all our Ports, where do arrive several ships from all parts richly laden to support our Trade; and some of them have brought us Guns, Bullets, <reg orig="Salt-peter">Saltpetre</reg> and other Ammunition of war, which we stood in great need of, notwithstanding all this, we should be glad of a peace upon any reasonable terms: For, if the war continue we must expect to have our Trade quite ruined by it, which consequently will be the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of this Country: and although we do please ourselves with fine words, how that the King of <em><reg orig="Scots">Scot's</reg></em> affairs thrive in <em>Scotland</em>, and that many of the Nobility begin to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Highlanders, to whom there hath been sent from hence 6, or 7000 Arms and Ammunition of all sorts, which are said to be safely arrived in those parts. Yet the wise and sober minded men amongst us look upon them as a company of plunderers that are got together to rob and steal, and so to return to their holes again when the season of the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> will permit to pursue them; and do conclude that this <reg orig="Countries">Country's</reg> safest way and chiefest good will be to conclude a peace with <em>England</em>, though it be upon disadvantageous terms to us, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to continue in so chargeable a war as it hath proved to be ever since we entered into it.</p>

<p>I hear there are some <em>English</em> prizes brought in lately into <em>Zealand</em>, taken by some of their private men of war; that Province is <pb n="15" /> generally more inclined to war <reg orig="then">than</reg> any of the rest; though they have thriven no better by it <reg orig="then">than</reg> their confederates.</p>

<p><em>France</em> and we are yet at a distance; their Ambassador hath had no Audience of late, he is waiting to see what will be the issue of the Treaty in <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Pembrook</em> Decem. 23, 1653.</i></head>

<p>On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last we had here the fearfullest Thunder, Lightning and Rain, as hath been heard of, and some <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> destroyed thereby. The Lord speak peace to his people, many constructions poor people make.</p>

<head level="3"><i>January 4. 1653.</i></head>

<p>The Trustees for the sale of Forrest-Lands have appointed upon <em>Tuesday</em> next, the tenth of this instant <em>January</em> in the forenoon to sit for allowance of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Faith Bills to be doubled upon security of the said Lands, and thenceforth weekly every <em>Tuesday</em> in the forenoon, till the sum to be doubled be full.</p>

<p><em>William Tayleure</em>, Secretary to the said Trustees.</p>

<p>No news from Sea, save that our Fleet rides about the <em>Channel</em>: And that we have lost two ships of 18 Guns, and 400 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>, laden with Masts and some other Commodities: which were taken by certain Dutch men of war this last week, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> into <em>Flushing</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Whitehall</em> January 2.</head>

<p>The <em>Dutch Deputies</em> had their last Conference, and spent the whole day therein; but came to no conclusion. The next News we hear of them is; That <em>January</em> 3. they departed from their house, sent their Goods a shipboard, and themselves went after about nine <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> the same night. Whether they have set sail; or whether the wind sit yet right for them; or which way the <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> will turn; or whether it may bring them about again, is as yet unknown: But if the just and reasonable condescensions of <em>England</em> take not effect, it must and will appear, that the <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> never sat yet in a right corner at the <em>Hague</em>, for a fair Accommodation. Of which (perhaps) more hereafter.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>