<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol197">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 197</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> March 16. to <em>Thursday</em> March 23.1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3">From <i>Sterling, March 7.</i></head>

<p>Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em>, with some horse, is about the head of this River, and by night makes In-<reg orig="fals">falls</reg> into the Country, to plunder those who are disobedient to his Warrants. Now he demands 23l. Scotch for every horse and arms. His and his <reg orig="Officers">Officer's</reg> Trade is only to fill their pockets, and oppress the Country. They <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>-people are as malignant as ever to our Interest.</p>

<p>I acquainted you last week of Major <em>Bridges</em> his going out this day sennight<!--sic-->, and taking of 26 prisoners, with 18, or 20. horse.</p>

<p>Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em>, yesterday morning, came <pb n="1" />with a considerable party of horse, near a Garrison of ours, to get in his Levies. The Officers of the Garrison having notice of it, marched out. But the enemy lying in <em>Ambuscado</em>, fell unawares upon our men, took 9 of them prisoners, and 7 of our horse. The enemy also had some loss, two slain, and divers wounded.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Upsal, Feb. 17. 1654. S.V.</i></head>

<p>Our negotiation here seems for a while to be asleep, the Treaty of Peace betwixt <em>England</em> and <em>Holland,</em> and its likelihood of taking effect, hath caused this people to be a little wary, and it doth concern them; for if peace be ratified, it will put both Nations to take up new <reg orig="Councels">Counsels</reg>. The Queen hath promised his Lordship that she will dispatch him <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as she receives the certainty of that affair. The Senators are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg>, some think that there are commotions likely to be ratified amongst the Country-people, by reason of the great <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of Impositions. The great Assembly of States is called, and is to meet the 12 of <em>May</em> next. The Queen revives her former overtures of resigning up the Government to her successor, and desires the liberty of retiring into privacy. This she made about two years since, and she was the over-<reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg>, but now she hath again proposed it, and the Senators are consulting what answer to return her.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Regensborgh">Regensburgh</reg>, March 2. S. N.</i></head>

<p>Since his <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> last Decree to the States of the Empire, concerning the maturation and furtherance of their Treaty, they <pb n="2" />have been very forward in the same, having besides the capitulation choice, <em>viz.</em> how the new Princes, as <em>Dietrichstein, Piccolomini,</em> and <em>Aversbergh</em> are to be introduced, taken in hand again; the Justice-business in all three <reg orig="Colledges">Colleges</reg>, contributing their best <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to bring the same, and other necessary things to a conclusion before his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> departure, which was determined the 10 day of <em>April</em> next, but is now said to be four weeks prolonged. Two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> there came on here two Expresses from <em>Graitz</em>. With divers Letters to his <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> Majesty; what their business may be, is not yet known.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Colen, March 10. S.N.</i></head>

<p>We are now out of all fear for to be troubled with the <em>Lorainish</em> Troops in these Countries, who will now quickly come to lose their <em>Lorainish</em> name. Since they heard of their <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> imprisonment, they have almost been in a rage, and for madness burnt <em>Baringen</em>, and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> the City St. <em>Truyen</em>.</p>

<p>The Count of <em>Fuensoldagne</em> who thought to have got them into his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> service by presenting them with 40000 Crowns, was pursued by them to <em>Diest</em> in <em>Brabant</em>, so that he was forced <em>re in <unclear>expidita</unclear></em> to return to <em>Brussels</em>, where <reg orig="its">it's</reg> feared that Monsieur <em>Faber</em>, who with 7 or 8000 Frenchmen is arrived at <em><unclear>Luyok</unclear></em>, for the assistance of the Prince Elector, will draw the said Forces to his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> service, several Colonels and chief Officers inclining thereunto.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg>, March 7 S. N.</i></head>

<p>The news out of <em>Poland</em> is, that the <em>Cossacks</em> <pb n="3" />have agreed with the <em>Muscovites</em>, and to secure him their fidelity, are to deliver him three Earldoms, if it be not a report raised by the Court to further the agreement with the <em>Cossacks</em>, as to procure more large Contributions, which a little time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>. The Duke of <em>Moscow</em> hath already taken <em>Scion, Birla, Chircaseck, </em>and <em>Chrein</em>, and is advancing farther with a great strength, the news whereof hath caused great alteration upon the Ryxday at <em>Warsovia</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Scilly, March 12.</i></head>

<p>A small Vessel of <em>Topsa<unclear><!--one character--></unclear></em> that came from St: <em>Sebastians</em>, commanded by Capt. <em>Stafford</em>, who had a Commission for a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of War, brought in hither a French Prize of 30 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Iron, <reg orig="Licquorice">Liquorice</reg>, &amp;c. But the news, which will be most acceptable to many, is the bold attempt, and good success of Captain <em>Potter</em>, commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, who on Saturday last in a single encounter, mastered and took as Prize, the <em>Royal James</em>, commanded by Captain <em>Beach</em>, chief Admiral of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stewards">Stewart's</reg></em> Pickaroons, and hath brought him into this Port; the fight continued eight hours, and then <em>Beach</em> <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> for quarter: <em>Beach</em> had 39 guns, and 200 men, the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, had about 13<unclear>0</unclear> men, 32 guns, which indeed was an eminent service; the Captain commends both his Officers and Seamen for standing close by him, but especially his Lieutenant, for his judgement and valour in that <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> service: Captain <em>Potter</em> lost but two men, and <em>Beach</em> about twenty men; <em>Beach</em> coming aboard the <em>Warwick</em>, demanded of Captain <pb n="4" /><em>Potter</em>, the way and manner of performing his Articles, claiming it his promise to set him ashore in <em>France</em>; at which Captain <em>Porter</em> being startled, told him he never heard of such demand, and to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> <em>Beach</em> therein, commanded <em>Beach</em> aboard again his own Vessel, and to fight it out; but <em>Beach</em> refused the same. Such eminent services merit more than ordinary <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg>.</p> 

<p><em>Beach</em> and his Crew are since brought into <em>Plymouth</em>, and close-prisoners there, till further order for their trial, which will be speedily.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for appointing Commissioners for approving of Ministers throughout the Nation is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by the Council. Also an Ordinance for disposing forfeited Estates in <em>Scotland</em>, and two other Ordinances for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> and Excise, which will be forthwith published.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Harwich</em> we understand of a <em>Dutch</em> ship of four hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, <reg orig="Tarr">Tar</reg>, Masts and Iron, to a great value, brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Brussels, March 22. S.N.</i></head>

<p>Through the diligence of the Earl of <em>Sturrenberg</em>, Ambassador from the Emperor, the Secretary of State, Monsieur <em>Navarr</em> and other Ministers, the Peace or agreement hath been made between his Highness the Prince of Liege, and his Highness Arch Duke <em>Leopoldus</em>, upon certain Conditions and Articles; too long to be inserted here. Hereupon the Prince of <em>Conde</em> went from <pb n="5" />hence the 17 of this month to his Troops, which are quartered towards <em>Namur</em>, and the 18 dito the Earl of <em>Fuensaldagne</em> went also from hence to command the Spanish Army, here being news brought that the French Army under the command of the Marquis <em>Faber</em>, Governor of <em>Sedan</em>, was upon his march towards <em>Limborg</em>, into which place did enter lately, two Regiments of <em>High Germans</em>, belonging to the Count of <em>Nassaw</em>, and the Master of the Camp also, a <em>High Dutchman</em>, whereby that place is so well fortified, that there is no fear of having it <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by the French, who will run great danger of being beaten and routed by the Spanish Army that hath a <reg orig="designe">design</reg> upon them. So that they do expect here to hear of some sudden action between them, whereof you shall be advised in due time.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> will be no longer prisoner in company with the Earl of <em>B<unclear><!--1 character--></unclear>si<unclear><!--1/2 characters--></unclear>ni</em>, and the Abbot of <em>Mercy</em>, who he <reg orig="saies">says</reg> are both guilty of high Treason wherewith they stand charged at present; and he himself is only kept prisoner for being too honest a man, and a Prince too much beloved by his Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and those that belonged unto him. So that by reason of the discontent the said Duke hath taken for being imprisoned in the same prison with the two said Lords, they have been ordered to remove them to the Castle of <reg orig="Gendt">Ghent</reg>, where their Lodgings are making ready to receive them, that so the said Duke may be no longer troubled in his mind about it; there being care taken <pb n="6" />to please him in every thing as much as is possible, and as far as it may be done with safety to his person.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg> &amp; Dalkeith Feb. 28. March 6.&amp; 14.</i></head>

<p>About 8 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since, <em>Middleton</em> and his company landed in a Hoy from <em>Holland</em>. They would have put into <em>Garmouth</em>, which is at the mouth of <em>Spey</em>, the place where <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stewart</em> once landed. But understanding we had <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> near that place, they put out to sea again, and landed at the Ferry of <unclear><em>Hoey</em></unclear> in <em>Sutherland</em>, with about 80 men, as we have notice. They sent about 10 load of Arms to <em>Auchness</em>, and themselves are gone toward the Shire of <unclear><em>Assn</em></unclear>. They give out that they have another Vessel yet beside to land, but no mention of any more men.</p>

<p>He hath summoned in all the Gentlemen and heritors of <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg>, Sutherland</em>, and <em>Ross</em>, and hath appointed a Rendezvous immediately by the <em>Brays</em> of <em>Sutherland</em>. He hath forbidden the Sheriff of <em>Sutherland</em> to act any more in the names of the <em>Keepers of the Liberties of England</em>, or in the name of <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector, but faith he will give him a new Commission to act by as Sheriff.</p>

<p><em>Seaforth</em> hath raised 600 men, and is <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him. But the late blows given to <em>Glencairn</em> by Col. <em>Morgan</em> and Col. <em>Daniel</em>, and the consideration of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> arrival with so inconsiderable number, after great expectations, hath (I believe) cooled the courage of the more wary sort of men, who are of any fortune, that they will take heed how they run in to his party.</p>

<p>There is since the former, another Vessel arrived <pb n="7" />for him, and come into <em>Caithness</em>, whither he is gone to labour a drawing in of the Gentlemen of that Country to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him. There is talk of more Vessels to come with necessaries to his Forces. It is said he brought with him in his own Vessel at first, 300 barrel of powder, 1000 firelocks, with about 5000 pikes, muskets and pistols; and these, with tow field-pieces, were lodged in the Castle of <em>Skello.</em></p>

<p><em>Glencairn, Kenmore, Glengary, Athol,</em> and <em>Forbs</em>, with their several parties, intended to have a <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> as on this day, about 24 miles off <em><reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg></em>, whence Col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched out to <reg orig="trie">try</reg> if he can <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> with them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Paris</em>, March 25 S.N.</head>

<p>This week here died the Archbishop of <em>Paris</em>, being 70 years of age; some great difference it is like to cause between the Cardinal and this City, who do pretend the right to belong to them for the appointing and making choice of another in his place.</p>

<p>On Saturday last Prince <em>Rupert</em> coming home late in the evening from St. <em><reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg></em>, where he had been a hunting all day with two or three of his servants, met with the son in law of the Marquis of <em>Du Plessis</em>, with his Gentlemen of his horse, and two or three servants more in company, who having been making merry, met with the said Prince <em>Rupert</em> and his company near the Court, not far from this Town, who falling into discourse together, it bred in the end a quarrel between them, and one of Prince <em><reg orig="Ruperts">Rupert's</reg></em> men shot the Gentleman of the horse of the said <em>Du </em><pb n="8" /><em>Plessis</em> dead upon the place with his long gun; this caused the rest of the company to draw their swords, which Prince <em>Rupert</em> perceiving, discharged his pistol and shot another into the belly, who is not yet dead, but mortally wounded; this caused the Marquis to <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> with the other two of his servants leaving one dead, and the other very much wounded upon the place. The Prince hath been since with the said Marquis to excuse the matter, not knowing what he was. What will be farther done in it, you shall hear in my next.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> would fain be gone hence, if the French Court would supply him with what they have promised him, being very much in <reg orig="arrear">arrears</reg> of his pension, the payment whereof he only desireth before he goes, which he is not like to have in haste; there being no great inclination here to relieve him.</p>

<p>On Saturday next the King is to go to his Parliament, to pronounce sentence of death against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, according to the Laws and Customs of this Kingdom.</p>

<p>Some preparations for shipping, and some small levies of Mariners, are set on foot at <em>Toulon</em>, designed as it is supposed, against the Kingdom of <em>Naples</em>.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is raising two or three regiments wherewith he is to go for <em>Catalonia</em> to command in chief those Forces that are intended for those parts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for Continuation of an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for the Continuation of the Customs <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 day of March, in the year 1653.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by his Highness, the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Continuation of the Customs <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 of <em>March</em>, in the year 1653. and all Powers and Clauses therein contained, be, and are hereby continued, and shall, and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 day of <em>March</em>, in the year of our Lord, 1658. And be it further Ordained that the Commissioners of the Customs shall not hereafter make repayment of half <reg orig="Subsidie">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported, which have been, or hereafter shall be sold unto, or in the possession of any <reg orig="Shop keeper">Shopkeeper</reg> or retailer of the said Commodity, or any such goods where the property, form, or nature of the Commodity once imported, is in any wise altered, mingled, amended or confounded. And be it hereby further Ordained, That the Commissioners of the Customs for the time being shall have and receive upon every twenty shillings coming clear unto the Commonwealth upon their account such <reg orig="salarie">salary</reg> of Poundage as is or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for Regulating the Customs, or any other thereunto <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> by his Highness and his Council.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, March 8.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart's</em> Interest is now <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> on as desperate in all these parts, and they give him over in their thoughts. All the noise here is of Peace between you and the <em>Dutch</em>, and how that they have sent their Ambassadors with the Ratification fully signed. This will make the <em>Dane</em> look toward <em>England</em>; and I suppose Monsieur <em>Rosewning</em>, his Agent, may be with you at <em>London</em> ere this time.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Dalkeith, March 11.</i></head>

<p>There was taken out of the Vessel that brought <em>Middleton</em> into <em>Sutherland</em>, 300 barrels of powder, 5000 Arms, whereof 1000 inaphances<!--word as spelt in text-->; immediately after their arrival they sent out a party of Country horses to carry up their baggage to the Castle <em>Skelko</em>, where they got up also two brass field-pieces. They report that they have more men in <em>Holland</em>, but cannot get shipping for them, though they say 16 sail more are coming: Major General <em>Deyell</em>, with one Major <em>Watson</em>, and six or seven score men are in the Castle to defend their Arms and Ammunition. Col. <em>Fitch</em> hath some intentions to make an attempt upon the place by a party from <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>: <em>Middleton</em> hath been with the Lord <em>Rea</em> to procure him and his people to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, which it is said they will, <em>Seafort</em> is gathering up his men again.</p>

<p>There is a Declaration set out in writing by the enemy, of the Grounds of their present quarrel; but it being long, I could not send you a Copy of it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement</i></head>

<p>About a fortnight since, a Letter from <em>Dover, March 9.</em> was printed in this and some other Intelligences; wherein it was said, that a <i>great Fleet of Dutch Merchantmen of 140 sail, convoyed with about 60 men of War,</i> were gone to the Westward, sailing close by the French Coast. But now it appears that Intelligence was false and frivolous, no such Fleet nor number of men of War having passed that way. Nor is it easily imaginable they could have passed without being interrupted, considering the posture and diligence of our Fleet in the Channel.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<head level="3"><i>A <unclear>Declaration by</unclear> his Highness the Lord Protector, inviting the People of <unclear>England and</unclear> Wales, to a day of Solemn Fasting and Humiliation.</i></head>

<p>The common and notorious sins so boldly and impenitently <reg orig="practiced">practised</reg> amongst us, notwithstanding all our Deliverances and Mercies, together with the present rod of an exceeding and universal Drought, which hath lain upon us for some years, and still continues and increaseth upon us, threatening Famine and Mortality, are no less than the <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> of God, calling aloud in our ears to fasting and Mourning, and great Abasement of soul before him</p>

<p>And although the general end and intendment of inviting to a Day of Fast, be, that all of every condition and quality whatsoever, do try and examine their heart and way more especially, according to their own light, and in the use of such helps and means as the Lord in his providence shall afford to each and every one, before and upon the said day of meeting: Yet finding some thoughts set seriously upon our heart, we judged it not amiss to recommend the same to Christian consideration, not to impose them upon any, or to confine any within the compass thereof; but leaving every man free to the grace of God, and to the work of his Spirit, who worketh all things in the hearts of the sons of men, according to the Counsel and Good pleasure of his own will.</p>

<p>It cannot be <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, but that God hath vouchsafed to appear very much in working the deliverance of the Nation from their bondage and thraldom, both Spiritual and Civil, and procuring for them a just liberty by his own people.</p>

<p>Do we now walk worthy of our high calling in humbleness and lowliness of mind, holding forth the <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg> of Christ in time of Peace, which was our strength, by the efficacy of which all our great things were accomplished in time of war?</p>

<p>Have we a heart prepared as willingly to communicate the said just freedom and liberty to one another, as we were industrious to get it?</p>

<p>Do we thankfully acknowledge our mercy in the liberty of worshipping God in holiness and righteousness without fear, being delivered out of the hands of our enemies</p>

<p>Is brotherly love, and a healing spirit of that force and value amongst us that it ought?</p>

<p>Do we own one another more for the grace of God, and for the Spiritual Regeneration, and for the image of Christ in each other, or for our agreement with each other in this or that form, or opinion?</p>

<p>Do we first search for the Kingdom of Christ within us, before we search one without us? Or do we listen to them that say concerning the coming of Christ, lo here, and lo there?</p>

<pb n="11" />

<p>Do we not more contend for Saints having rule in the world, <reg orig="then">than</reg> over their own hearts?</p>

<p>Are not there too many amongst us that cry up the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, Joy, Peace, Meekness, Patience, Goodness, Temperance, Long-suffering, Forbearance, Brotherly Kindness, Charity, which are the fruits of the Spirit?</p>

<p>How do we carry <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, not only to the Churches of God, and the Saints, but towards them that are without?</p>

<p>Do not some of us affirm <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to be the only true Ministry, and true Churches of Christ, and only to have the Ordinances in purity, excluding our Brethren, though of equal gifts, and having as large a Seal of their Ministry, and desiring with as much <reg orig="fervor">fervour</reg> and zeal to enjoy the Ordinances in their utmost purity?</p>

<p>Do we remember the old Puritan, or rather Primitive simplicity, Self-<reg orig="denyal">denial</reg>, Mercy to the Poor, Uprightness, and Justice? or are we not herein put to shame by those we easily call Anti-Christian or Carnal?</p>

<p>Hath one that we judge to be without, equal justice with one we call a Brother.</p>

<p>Do we contend for the <em>Faith once delivered unto the Saints</em>, as the things of faith ought to be contended for, with Love, Patience, Tenderness, Zeal, by <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>? Or rather imposingly, proudly, carnally, provokingly, sensually, thereby prejudicing the Truth, and, whilst we are calling aloud for the propagating of the Gospel, do we not put stumbling-blocks in the way of the same, and too much endanger to make good the slander of the world in charging <reg orig="Prosession">Procession</reg> with <em>Faction</em>.</p>

<p>For want of Circumspection and care herein, and a due regard to sincerity and uprightness, have not many <reg orig="apostatized">apostatised</reg>, running after <em>Fancies</em> and <em>Notions</em>, listening to filthy <em>Dreams, worshipping of Angels</em>, and been carried by their impulsions; and instead of contending for the faith, and holding the form of found words, contended against <em>Magistracy</em>, against <em>Ministry</em>, against <em>Scriptures</em>, and against <em>Ordinances</em>, too much verifying the Prophesies of <em>Peter</em> and <em>Jude</em> in these following words.</p>

<p>2Pet.2.1. <i>But there were false Prophets also among the people, even as there shall be false Teachers among you, who privily shall bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that brought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction.</i></p>

<p><i>2. And many shall follow their pernicious ways, by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of.</i></p>

<p><i>3. And through covetousness shall they with feigned words make <reg orig="merchandize">merchandise</reg> of you, whose judgement now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation slumbreth not.</i></p>

<p><i>10. But chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of uncleanness and despite Government, presumptuous are they, self-willed, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities.</i></p>

<pb n="12" />

<p><i>11. Whereas Angels which are greater in power and might, bring no<unclear><!--1 character, possibly a punctuation mark--></unclear> railing accusations against them before the Lord.</i></p>

<p><i>12. But these as natural <unclear>Br<!--6 characters--> asts</unclear>, made to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things they <unclear>understand not</unclear>, and shall utterly perish in their own corruption.</i></p>

<p><i>13. And shall receive the rewards of <unclear>unrighteousness</unclear>, as they that count it pleasure to riot in the day time: spots they are and blemishes, sporting themselves with their own deceivings <unclear>while</unclear> they feast with you.</i></p>

<p><i>15. Having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot cease from sin, beguiling unstable souls, an heart they have exercised with covetous practices, cursed children.</i></p>

<p>Jude, verse 4. <i>For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus Christ.</i></p>

<p><i>8. Likewise also these filthy Dreamers defile the flesh, despise Dominion, and speak evil of dignities.</i></p>

<p><i>10. But these speak evil of those things which they know not, but what they know naturally as brute beasts, in those things they corrupt themselves.</i></p>

<p><i>11. <reg orig="Wo">Woe</reg> unto them, for they have gone in the way of <em>Cain</em>, and ran greedily after the error of <em>Balaam</em> for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core</i></p>

<p><i>12. These are spots in your feasts of Charity, when they feast with you, feeding themselves without fear; clouds they are without water, carried about with winds; trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots.</i></p>

<p><i>13. Raging waves of the Sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, to whom is reserved the blackness of darkness <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>16. These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own lusts, and their mouth speaketh great swelling words, having <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> persons in admiration because of advantage.</i></p>

<p><i>19. These be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the Spirit.</i></p>

<p>And notwithstanding all these evils, and worse, are upon, and in the midst of us, like <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> hairs, here and there, and we <i>know it not, our Pride testifying to our face</i>, Hosea 7. 9,10. and we not return to the Lord our God, nor seek him for all this, but these things are contended for, and justified under the notion of Liberty, it being too commonly said, that the Magistrate hath nothing to do either in repressing or remedying these things, We do hereby appeal to the hearts and consciences of all fearing the Lord, whether <unclear>there</unclear> be not as great cause as ever to lay our <i><reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the dust</i>, and to <i>abhor ourselves</i> before the Lord, <i>for these abominations</i>, whereby <unclear>the</unclear> eyes of his <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> are provoked, and to seek pardon and <unclear>mercy</unclear> from himself of these things.</p>

<p>And to these, The resistance, hatred, and neglect of the Gospel <pb n="13" />, by the generality of men, the contempt and despite done to the sincere Professors of it, even for the image of Christ in them (although they have been instruments of many mercies, and of the obtaining a just freedom for the Nation) The wickedness, <reg orig="oathes">oaths</reg>, drunkennesses, revellings, and all manner of licentiousness, for which things sake, the Scriptures have said, that the wrath of God shall undoubtedly overtake the children of disobedience.</p>

<p>And lastly, the impunity of these things, through the neglect of the Magistracy, throughout the Nation, and then judge whether there be not cause, that we be called upon, and do call upon each other seriously, to lay all these things to heart, being greatly abased before the Lord for them.</p>

<p>Upon the serious consideration of these things, We judge it not only warrantable, but a duty, to call upon you and <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, to set apart time to humble our souls before the Lord, to cry unto him for broken and penitent hearts, and that he would turn away his wrath, and be reconciled to us; for the Lord he is merciful, gracious, long-suffering, and abundant in goodness and truth, forgiving iniquity, transgression and sin, and will by no means clear the guilty, who are only such as go on in their hardened and impenitent hearts, refusing the grace offered by Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>It is therefore hereby declared, that We and our Council, do purpose (by the grace of God) to set apart <em>Friday</em> next, being the 24 of this present <em>March</em>, for a day of Humiliation.</p>

<p>And it is hereby Ordered, that timely notice be given to the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, who (together with the out Parishes) we doubt not, will willingly keep the <unclear>same</unclear> day. And that like notice be given throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to have their several meetings upon the same day Fortnight. And that Copies hereof be printed and published, to be sent to the several parts of the Nation, to invite them unto the performance of this duty.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, this 20 of <em>March</em>, 1653.</i></p>

<pb n="14" />

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, March <unclear><!--1 character--></unclear>.</i> S.N.</head>

<p>We hope by this time the Ratification is concluded, being our Ambassadors have been so long with you; our next business will be to burn <em>Victoria</em>, as they call it here, and then send out our Merchants, who only expect that happy hour: 'Tis said Ambassadors are to come from you to the <em>Hague</em>; whether it be for ceremonies sake, or a nearer alliance, time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> seems lost to the world; and indeed the Spaniards use to strike home when eminent strangers fall into their clutches; the poor Duke pressing for the liberty of the <reg orig="Cittadel">Citadel</reg> walls, upon denial, grew into such a rage, that he broke all of the glass windows about his Chamber, which breaches have been repaired since by immuring up the walls on all sides, only a small hole out of reach being left to let in some light; 'tis said his <reg orig="designe">design</reg> was to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> the French Troops, under Monsieur <em>Faber</em>, and so by the assistance of <em>France</em> to make himself Duke of <em>Brabant</em>, which he was to receive in homage from the French, and in exchange for his Country; they have in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> confiscated all they could lay their hands on, <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> upon his Jewels which were found with his wife; and daughter the last being possessed of one to the value of two millions.</p>

<p>It is reported, that a Marriage was concluded upon between the Scotch King and his daughter, who was immediately to receive four Millions with her, and all the assistance possible for his <reg orig="restauration">restoration</reg>; but this is not much credited.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, March</i> 14.</head>

<p>Since <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing the enemy are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in all parts, and will leave no stone unturned. They report that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor. There came with <em>Middleton</em> sixty and odd Officers, the least a Captain, and amongst the rest (besides those I formerly hinted to you) Colonel <em><unclear>Henderson</unclear>, Monro</em> and others of them had very cold <unclear>entertainment</unclear> in <em>Sutherland</em>, and the Earl himself and his Family are come away leaving directions to his Tenants, rather to suffer <reg orig="then">than</reg> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. they give out, that when all the prepared parties are ready, and the 150000 Dollars from the Emperor for raising 30 Regiments, that their King, or at least the Titular Duke of <em>York</em> will come. The Earl of <em><unclear>Athol</unclear></em> <pb n="15" />and Sir Arthur <em>Forbs</em> have placed a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Isle of <em>Lough Tay</em>, where they intend to have a flock of Provisions, and also to keep such Commissioners and Heritors as refuse to bring in their levies at 40 marks Scots for an horse, and 100l. Scots for a footman. On Saturday last Lieut. <em>Holmsted</em> of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> Regiment, with a party from <em>Linlithgow</em> took a Cornet and four more of the enemy, and 11 horse.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Dublin, March 7</i></head>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> when he comes back to you, will confute those false reports that were raised of us here, he having had a reception as a Prince, with 300 horse out of this City (most of them Citizens) with bonfires at night throughout the City.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris, March 25. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The 20 instant, the Count of <em>Aubijova</em>, the Baron of <em>Brifac</em>, and a third person, who lately fought a duel in the Palace-Royal, were hanged there in Picture, and declared to be degraded from the Title of Nobility; but without prejudice to the Nobility of their children, to whom a part of their <reg orig="Fathers">Fathers'</reg> Estates is reserved, and the rest is confiscated.</p>

<p>About Friday or Saturday next, the sentence will be finally passed against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>; but he will not be hanged in picture as was intended, because of the respect born to his brother the Prince of <em>Conti</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Westminster, March 21.</i></head>

<p>In the morning the Dutch Ambassadors were at the House of his Highness the Lord Protector. In the afternoon, the Commissioners of the Council went to the Lodging of the Ambassadors, and had Conference with them, in order to the dispatch of that business.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for Trial and approbation of Ministers, having been passed some <reg orig="daies">days</reg> past by the Council, it will now be suddenly made <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <unclear><em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</unclear></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>