<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol185">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 185</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. De Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, Decem 16. to <em>Thursday</em>, Decem 22. 1653.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Newcastle, December 21.</i></head>

<p>This day his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> was proclaimed by the Sheriffs at the high Cross of this City, the Mayor, Aldermen and <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> attending in their Scarlet, with the best Sword and Cap, all their Officers attending a Sermon for this day of Inauguration, preached before them at <em>Temple Church</em> by Mr <em>Knowles</em> out of <em><unclear>Esay</unclear></em> 33. 21, 22, 23 after the Proclamation was read, the Waites of the City <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> before the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, and the Bells rang, which they did also the Morning and the Night before, and the <reg orig="Gunns">Guns</reg> from the Castle were fired also; the <pb n="1" />Governor Col. <em>Scroope</em> being at Sermon with the Mayor, stood also with him till the Proclamation was ended: And because the day should not pass here without some gratification; the Governor at the request of the Mayor and Aldermen, granted, that the Gallows standing in the High Street next the Cross, on which the condemned by Military Laws were executed, to be taken down, which was by them accepted as a <reg orig="favor">favour</reg>.</p>

<head level="2">By the Lord Protector,</head>

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation of his Highness, with the consent of his Council, for continuing all Persons being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> his <em>Highness</em> further direction.</i></head>

<p>OLIVER LORD PROTECTOR of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland,</em> considering, That whereas the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the Administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, is invested and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council; And left thereupon the <unclear>veiled</unclear> and ordinary course of Justice in the Commonwealth (<unclear>if remedy</unclear> were not provided) might receive interruption, his Highness in his care of the State, and <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice thereof (reserving to future consideration the Reformation and Redress of any abuses by misgovernment, upon better <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> taken thereof) is pleased, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> signify, declare and ordain, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, who have power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the meeting of the <pb n="2" /> next Parliament to make <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and Ordinances for the Peace &amp; welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, That all persons who on the 10 day of this instant <em>December</em> were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction, or Government within this Commonwealth, shall be, and shall so hold <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> continued in the said Offices and places respectively, as formerly they held and enjoyed the fame, and not otherwise, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> his Highness pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which respect or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Justice, and all Proceedings of what Nature soever in Courts of common Law or Equity, or in the Court of Admiralty, or by commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said Tenth day of this instant December, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further Order given by his Highness therein; And that in the mean time (or preservation of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, and for safety of the State) all the said Persons of whatsoever Place, Power, degree, or condition, may not fail, every one severally according to his respective Place, office or charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all Duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them, whilst the former Government was in being. <i>Given at Whitehall, December</i> 21. 1653.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">From old Montross, December 13.</head>

<p>Captain Lisle being in his Quarters at old Montrosse, in the County of Anguish, received intelligence upon Friday the ninth of this instant about 8 of the clock, that there was a Regiment of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> horse quartered within 8 or 9 miles of him; of which Regiment the Lord Kinnoole is Colonel, and one David Ramsey Lieut. Col. Upon which intelligence he forthwith sent to Col. Rich his own Troop to meet him with all convenient speed that might be, at Brichin, being a place where part of Major <reg orig="Bramstones">Bramstone's</reg> Dragoons are quartered, and in the way to the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, and they meeting according to order, he and they, with part of Major <reg orig="Bramstones">Bramstone's</reg> Dragoons, and 12 <reg orig="foot-souldiers">foot soldiers</reg>, which he mounted out of his own quarters of old Montross; about 4 of the clock in the morning, marched out of Brichin, and in the break of the day, <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> into the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, where by the providence of God, there was taken a Captain 1 Cornet, one Quartermaster, a Corporal, and 20 private soldiers, and about 40 horse, and <reg orig="som">some</reg> Arms; for the Captains before they would be taken, suffered the house to be fired about their ears so that there was divers arms lost in the fire; there was 3 killed, and thanks be to God this was done without any hurt on our side, save only there was one man wounded by a shot in the thigh : the Lord of Kinnoole, and Lieut. Col. Ramsey, with about 30 of their soldiers being quartered in a very strong stone house, by that means escaped us. </p><pb n="4" />

<p>And by that time Cap. <em>Lisle</em> was in his Quarters upon Saturday night, there came Orders from Col <em>Morgan</em>, that he with his Troop should meet him near <em>Thornton</em> the next morning early, which accordingly he did; where met likewise Col. <em>Mich</em> his Troop, Major <em><reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons and a commanded party of Foot of about 30. in number from Dunoter castle. And with this party we marched 6 or 7 miles into the Highlands, and again fell into the Lord of <em><reg orig="Kinnooles">Kinnoole's</reg></em> quarters, where we took about 7 or 8 Prisoners, and about 12 horse, killed one and rescued the Lord of <em>Egles</em> Sheriff for that part of the Country, whom they had taken prisoner from his own house the day before.  <em>Kinnoole</em> and <em>Ramsey</em> themselves very hardly escaping, the whole Regiment totally dispersed; but our horses were so spent, and the way so <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>, <reg orig="becaus">because</reg> steep Rocks and dangerous <reg orig="Boggs">Bogs</reg>, and night coming on, that we were constrained to leave off the pursuit.</p>

<head level="3"><i> A List of the Prisoners taken in the Lord <em><reg orig="Kinnooles">Kinnoole's</reg></em> Regiment:</i></head>

<p> Cap. Michel Belford, Cap. Wil. Blare, Lieutenant I. Ramsey, Cornet William Grier, George Flike, I. Martin, Francis Sharp, David Ramsey, Gem. Bruse, I. Macklane, Will. Fife, D. Cuttinangus, David Lanson, Gem. Gardner, Robert Swan, I. Braud, G. Mat. Donald, Ar: Waile, I. Paperson, Will: Fumiston, Alex. Googley, H. Man.</p>

<p>Those were taken upon Saturday Decemb. 10. with 40 horse by Capt. <em>Edmond Lisle</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Upsahla">Upsala</reg> December</em> 22. 1653.</head>

<p>I understand this day from <em><reg orig="Gottenbergh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, of the <pb n="5" /> safe arrival of the English Lord Ambassador there with three men of Was, and two Merchant Ships for their baggage; they are said to be above 10 persons in company, and 30 horses, and are now shortly expected hither; they will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> doubtless extraordinary <reg orig="wel">well</reg> received one of the best Lodgings this place can afford being already provided for to attend his Lordships <reg orig="coming">coming</reg>, which God grant may be to the welfare and establishment of both Nations; I shall not fail, God willing, to acquaint you with the Reception, Entrance, Propositions &amp; Transactions of his Lordship with this Crown; forasmuch as I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be able to penetrate thereof by every Post.  It is believed here, That the great loss the Dutch sustained in the late storm will <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> humble their Spirits, and cause them to think upon more reasonable conditions for an accommodation if they expect to have peace with <em>England</em>.  Next Friday, being the 25 instant, is appointed by her Majesty a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> day of Thanksgiving all over this Kingdom, for the great plenty of Corn and other earthly blessings <reg orig="wherwith">wherewith</reg> God hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> pleased so graciously to provide this Nation this year, in so much that the like hath not been since any mans remembrance.  God make us truly <reg orig="thankfull">thankful</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen December</i> 14. S.V.</head>

<p>This Nation is much enraged, because of one of their <em><reg orig="Islands">Island's</reg></em> ships, which we hear is taken by the English, and some 5, or 6 more of the same Fleet, which are lost in the late storm; and that which aggravates their vexation, is, That some 6 <pb n="6" /> English ships, having been lately in our <reg orig="Fleets">Fleet's</reg> hands, were very friendly dismissed.  The English <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> arrival at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> is not well resented here, but makes them very jealous; the more, because we hear of her <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> kind reception of him, having caused <reg orig="som">some</reg> of her chief Noblemen to conduct him to the Court at <em><reg orig="Upsahla">Upsala</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam, December</i> 7.S.N.</head>

<p> The news of the Treaty being broken continueth , but the States have sent their Deputies order. to stay 14 days longer, and try what may be effected in that time.  There is a Report that the Lord Gen. <em>Cromwell</em> had desired them to remain a little longer at <em>London</em>, but it is not believed.  They prepare a pace for the <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> against Spring, it has some 2, or 3 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> ago been said, That 30 English ships were seen on this coast coming from the East <reg orig="Countrys">Countries</reg>, from whence they expect duly a hundred sail.  The Negotiations of the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> in <em>Sweden</em> are much longed for; <unclear>so these</unclear> say, that the French Ambassador promiseth, if they will join with <em>France</em>, he will assure them of <em>Sweden</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, December</i> 18. </head>

<p>Affairs here seem troublesome; the Highlanders have divided <reg orig="hemselves">themselves</reg> into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts; conceiving it to be more conducing to their Design than to keep in a Body.  <em>Kesmore</em> hath taken up his Territories in the West, <em>Glasgow</em> &amp; <em><unclear>Marshes</unclear></em>, Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> and <em>Ramsey</em> are at the Brayed in <em>Angus</em> and <em><reg orig="Mearnes">Mernes</reg></em>.  The Earl of  <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em> in <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em >, <pb n="7" /> and those clans above <em> St <unclear>Fobestons</unclear>. Glencarne </em> and <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> towards the North parts about <em>Innerness</em>, and thus the new <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Army have disposed their quarters; but a party of horse from hence with col. <em>Morgan</em>, <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> disturbed their Levies in <em>Angus</em>; for, they have taken about 40 men, and 60 horses, and had unregimented <em>Kinnonle</em>, if the Hills had not been Friend to a few.</p>

<p>The news from <em>Dalkeith</em> is, That the Enemies are departed from the hithermost parts of <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em> and gone to <em>Kirkmichell</em> in order to their march Northward.  We are informed, <em>Kenmore</em> and <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencarne</reg></em> are both there, and their Force reported 500 Foot, and 500 Horse; but <reg orig="som">some</reg> who saw them say they cannot be above half that number.  They <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> under many discouragements; and every place is so eaten up where they come, that they are forced upon frequent Removes; and now Provisions of Mutton and Beef begin to decay.  <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> said they intend for the North, that their Quarters upon the Lowlands may be the more allured and broader, where they expect the landing of <reg orig="Foraign">Foreign</reg> Forces, Ammunitions and Money from their King and the States of <em>Holland</em>, as they talk.  <em><reg orig="Athole">Athol</reg></em> doth nothing considerable; the People refuse him men according to command.  One that saw him and his Soldiers <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he hath not got above 40 Foot, and Major <em>Mercer</em> is there with about 60 Horse.  Captain <em>Elsmore</em> of col. <em>Riche's</em> Regiment, sent out a party the other day from <em>Drummond</em> castle, &amp; took one cap. <em>Stuart</em>, who had a commission to raise Forces, with 4 others, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> 3 on the place.  The Marquis of <em>Huxtley</em> died last week at his <reg orig="hous">house</reg> at <em>Bogy-geish</em>.</p><pb n="8" />

<p>The King of <em>France</em> having been 2, or 3 days at <em>St Germain</em>, to recreate himself with <unclear>hunting</unclear>, is returned back to this city; where great preparations are making for a Ball to be danced by all the great Ladies of the court, <reg orig="wherwith">wherewith</reg> his Majesty seems to be much taken, and hath spent some time himself in giving directions about it.</p>

<p>The Commissioners appointed for the <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg> of the Pr. of <em>Conde</em>, have had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Meetings, and have drawn up <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Things in order to his <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg>.  The Pr: of <em>Conde</em> is coming to <em>Paris</em>, and is said, to accomplish his marriage with the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece.  Here is now not so much talk of the design against Naples as formerly; and it is verily thought that that design will come to nothing.  In the mean time, those ships that were making ready at <unclear>Toulon</unclear>, are ordered to come for <em>Rochel</em> and the Isle of <em>Rhe</em>, and to guard the <em>Norman</em> coast.</p>

<p><em>Charles Stuart</em> and his party have had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> consultations together at the <em><reg orig="Lovure">Louvre</reg></em>, about his affairs in <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, and as to his removing from this Court, which is not now so much spoken of, his Motion depending solely upon the issue of the Treaty  in <em>England</em>, which is said here to be ended, to the content of both Commonwealths; which is no pleasing news to the Cavalier party here, who love to fish in troubled Waters, though it be the more to their further <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.  Pr: <em>Rupert</em> is expected here within this day or two from <em>Nantes</em>.  The Pr: of <em>Conde</em> is still at Rocroy, sick of his old disease.</p><pb n="9" />

<p>Here <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> lately a <reg orig="quarrell">quarrel</reg> between 4 Gentlemen at a Tavern; <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> <reg orig="Sonn">Son</reg> was one; who being all very much distempered in their cups, challenged one another upon the place; and after some Passes had <reg orig="past">passed</reg> between them, One of them was <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> upon the place, and the <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Son wounded in two or three places of his Body.</p>

<p>Here is a fresh <reg orig="rumor">rumour</reg> of a Tumult that should have <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> lately at <em>Nismes</em> between the Papists and Protestants.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Brussels</em> Decemb.</i> 28. S.N.</head>

<p>There is lately arrived a ship at <em>Ostend</em> from Spain with Letters, intimating, That the King of Spain was gone from Madrid to <unclear>Eseurial</unclear>, to recreate himself with hunting; and had constituted the Lord Pigneranda President of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of the Indies before he went.</p>

<p>We hear news here, that the Town of Rosa is still so close besieged by the Spaniards, that nothing can enter in or out; but this is contrary to the <reg orig="newes">news</reg> we have from France; where it is said, that the Marshal of <em>Hoquincourt</em> hath defeated the Spanish Forces that lay before it, and <reg orig="reliev'd">relieved</reg> the place; which we <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not believe here to be true, though we have no ground at all to contradict it.</p>

<p>The Letters from Naples do mention, that the new Viceroy, the Earl of <em><unclear>Castiglio</unclear></em> was safely arrived at Naples, with the Countess his wife, and were nobly entertained at the Palace of <em><unclear>Tractta</unclear></em>; he hath been daily visited by the <reg orig="chiefest">chieftain</reg> of the Town in great Solemnity.</p>

<p>The Archduke hath been very much troubled <pb n="10" /> of late with the <reg orig="Collick">Colic</reg> and gravel, but is now reasonable well in health again.</p>

<p> The Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorrains">Lorain's</reg></em> Troops are quartered at present in the Land <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg> of <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, not far from St. <em>Miel</em>.</p>

<p> In my last I begun to tell you what alterations had happened here among the Governors of this <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg>, whereof I will give you the names of a few more at present:  The Prince of <em>Chinay</em> is admitted into the Government of the Dukedom of <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>; The Earl of <em>Iseghem</em> into the Dukedom of <em>Gueldre</em>; The Earl of <em>Nassaw</em> is made Governor of <em>Lille, Donay</em> and <em>Orchies</em>; and the Earl of St. <em>Amour</em> is Governor of the Earldom, Town and Castle of <em>Namur</em>. The Lord <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Honines</em>, Lord of <em>Gouvernies</em>, is chosen Chief and President of the <reg orig="Privie">Privy</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of his Majesty.  Many other promotions and changes are like to happen amongst the remainder of the Governors now in Office, whose names you may expect still as others are chosen in their places.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, December 13.</i></head>

<p>The <em>Dutch</em> have Letters which speak the Treaty desperate in <em>England</em>, and that a new Change is not far off in <em>England</em>.  We suppose your next change will be for a <unclear><reg orig="fare">fair</reg></unclear> Settlement; which is but <reg orig="needfull">needful</reg>; for, your distempers at home are too well known to your enemies abroad; and it makes <reg orig="Forainers">Foreigners</reg> to stand off from you in affection.</p>

<p>By Letters hither from the <em>Hague</em>, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> written, that the <em>French</em> Ambassador there, said for certain of late; That if the <em>Dutch</em> would break off the Treaty with <em>England</em>, he would assure them of the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>; which may have somewhat more in it than a <em>French</em> Brag, since all men know how <reg orig="streightly">straitly</reg> that Queen is allied to <em>France</em>: But <reg orig="its">it's</reg> possible your <em>English</em> <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg> may move that Queen to mind her nearer Interest.</p>

<p>However, I hear, the <em>Dutch Merchants</em> have their goods restored again at <em>Stockholm</em>, and those who were <pb n="11" /> imprisoned are at liberty.  States have many <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> of working out their ends.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, December 26.  Stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The English Post is newly come, and our Letters tell us, that all hopes of an accommodation are laid aside, and that our Ambassadors had desired leave of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State to return home <em>re infecta</em>.  In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the French Ambassador <em>Chenn</em> urgeth hard for a near <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> with this State, and hath offered already very fairly if we will break with <em>Spain</em>.  It is said that we shall have of the French six thousand men, three or four millions yearly towards the defraying of the charges of the War, and thirty good ships to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with out Fleet.  If it be so that we do break with you, 'tis probable that <em>France</em> and we may strike up the bargain.</p>

<p>Our Defensive League with the Prince of <em>Liege</em>, doth not hold (and happily the fault is not on our side) insomuch that all our Troops, both foot and horse, are retired to their old <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> again.  The Lorainers being fairly retreated beforehand, who hereupon with some of the Condees and Spanish under that notion, have besieged a small City belonging to <em>Liege</em> which they press sore, but have been as yet but rudely entertained, it is to be feared that they will carry it with some others in that <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg>, and so put the whole <reg orig="countrie">country</reg> round under contribution.</p>

<p>Our whole <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg> is full of discourses of the Treaty with <em>England</em> if it break, this State will doubtless endeavour to make a diversion in <em>Scotland</em>, by sending assistance to the Highlanders, and it is said that Prince <em>Rupert</em> is to go Generalissimo into that <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg>; but if both States do agree, as is <unclear>much</unclear> desired, not doubt but the Triumph will be greater than that for the Spanish accommodation.</p>

<p>The Treaty betwixt the Count of <em>Harcours</em> and the Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, we hear is far advances, and 'tis not doubted but that <em>Brisack</em> will chance Master, and the whole Province of <em><unclear>Elsan</unclear></em> be lost as to the French.</p><pb n="12" />

<head level="3">From <i>Dalkeith, December 18.</i></head>

<p>We have information that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all of his endeavours to raise and force men, horses and monies in the South, and intends to make some inroads into the Borders of <em>English</em>, unless prevented, which is the more probable by that information from <em>Durham</em>, that 20 <reg orig="horsmen">horsemen</reg> <reg orig="wel">well</reg> mounted and <reg orig="arm'd">armed</reg>  with Pistols and Holsters; went through a part of that Town on Tuesday last by break of day, and amongst them (as was given out there) the Lord <em>Hopton</em>; but the fame number and party (as is supposed) lay at <em><unclear>Peblus</unclear></em> n Saturday night last, and with them Col. <em>Wogan</em>, formerly a Captain of Dragoons in the Lord Gen. <em>Fairfax's</em> Army.  The Commander in Chief <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as he had notice of it on Sunday, <reg orig="order'd">ordered</reg> several parties from <em>Linlithgow, Sterling</em> and <em>Glasgow</em>, to <reg orig="scoure">scour </reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to prevent their going to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>; but the Country is so open, and the people so backward in giving intelligence, that (notwithstanding all diligence used, and the horse almost tired out with hard duty) we seldom meet with any of them, only on Thursday night last, Lt. <em>Whitmore</em>, going from the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Downe</em>, with a party toward the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, took one Major <em>Moorhead</em> (a prisoner of War, yet out upon Parole and security) well mounted and <reg orig="arm'd">armed</reg>, going to the Army, as he himself <reg orig="confests">confesses</reg> They do hearten their party, and increase their Levies by a Report.  That their King is come into <em>Holland</em>, and that Col. <em>Drummond</em> is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 150 Volunteers, Arms and Ammunition, and that the <em>Dutch</em> have left off treating with the <em>English</em>: with all which they feign a Post came lately from their King.  On Sunday morning last, a party of these Royal Pilferers met the Post-Boy go going from <em>Leith</em>, with Letters for <em>London</em>, near <em>Haddington</em>, took his Horse, and Letters, and Coat and Belt, with twenty pence in money from the poor Boy: So that now it will be uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy; and; and without further supplies of horse from <em>England</em>, it will be impossible to settle parties between this and <em>Barwick</em>, which must be, or else correspondence will be cut off.</p><pb n="13" />

<p>A considerable supply is the only means to prevent the growing of this yet inconsiderable party of Robbers in the Hills.  Our Garrisons of <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Innerness</reg></em> and <em>Blaire</em> are well provided with all things necessary, and fear no attempt.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Berwick, December 19.</i></head>

<p>A private man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> hath brought into <em>Holy-Island</em>, 2 Dutch vessels coming from the East country, both being about 150 <reg orig="Tonns">Tonnes</reg> burden, laden with Pitch, <reg orig="Tarr">Tar</reg>, and such like Commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Falmouth, December 19.</i></head>

<p>The Dutch are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> upon these coasts; so that it is very hard to pass by the Lands-End without a good Convoy: We hear they have taken a Londoner coming from <em><reg orig="New-England">New England</reg></em>, laden with Masts, Beaver-skins, and the like Commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Deale, December 23.</i></head>

<p>We hear some of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> have taken certain Beclanders belonging to <em>Calais</em>, who were bound for <em>Caen</em> and <em>Roan</em> in <em>Normandy</em>, laden with divers Commodities, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> them into <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> at <em>Stokes-day</em>.</p>

<p><i>Towerhill, December 26.</i>  A <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> was shot to death for killing a Seaman (presently after the late Mutiny) in cool blood.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall December 26.</i></head>

<p>An Ordinance was passed for alteration of several Names and Forms used heretofore in Courts, Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, &amp;c. And <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> proceedings in Courts of Law, Justice and Equity, within the Common-wealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, according to the present Government.  The sum whereof in brief is this; That <em>Oliver Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. Having the exercise of the chief Magistracy and the Administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, invested and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council, who have Power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the Meeting of next Parliament (which is to be on the third day of <em>September</em> now next ensuing) to make Laws and Ordinances <pb n="14" /> for the Peace and welfare of these Nations, where it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be binding and in force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Order <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be taken in Parliament concerning the same, doth with the Advice and consent of his said Council, Order and Ordain, in all proceedings whatsoever in Courts of Justice &amp;c. Where the style and Title of the <em>Keepers of the Liberty of England</em> hath been used heretofore; That from and after the 26 day of December, 1653. instead thereof the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg> and Title of the <em>Lord Protector</em>, for the time being, of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging shall be used, and no other.  The ordinance it <reg orig="seis">says</reg> you may have in Print at large.</p>

<p><i>William Earl of Glencarne, Lord of Kilmort, Commander in chief of all his Majesties Forces Within the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of Scotland.</i></p>

<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission granted to me by his Majesty, for Levying of Forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> for opposing the common Enemy, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> by these Presents appoint Colonel <em>Alexander Blackedor</em> to Levy out of the Shire of <em>Cleckmennen</em> one sufficient Troop, Horse and Men well armed, out of every Thousand pound of Rent, with certification if they sail after sight of my Order they shall be esteemed Enemies to their King: and the said <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Alexander Blakedor</em>, or any having his Power are hereby authorized to take the persons of the Deficients and bring them Prisoners to the Army, and to drive away all their Goods, while they <reg orig="doe">do</reg> Duty.  Given under my Hand at <em>Glenertie</em> the <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> of December, 1653.</p>

<head level="3">Subscribed, <i>GLENCARNE</i></head>

<p><em>Loving Friend</em>, I desire that ye will intimate this order to all the Gentlemen in <em>Glackmennen-shire</em>, and send me the just Rental of every mans Estate with this bearer; and if ye shall incur any danger by giving you this Order; <unclear><reg orig="Ile">I'll</reg></unclear> answer for it.  No more, but expect your diligence and your answer, as you will have <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> freed from trouble, and rest <i>Comerie Decemb. 10. 1652.</i> Your loving Friend <em>JOHN BLAKEDOR</em></p>

<p>For his loving Friend <em>William Moris</em> Clark in <em><unclear>Alloway</unclear></em>, these.</p><pb n="15" />

<p>The last gave you an account of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> main body under Glencarne and <em>Kenmores</em> marching Northward what they have done we hear not; but if they have no better success in their Levies <reg orig="then">than</reg> Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> hath in the South, they are not like to bring their <reg orig="Hogges">Hogs</reg> to any fair Market: For Capt. <em>Hart</em> being sent out by the Commander in chief, with a party of Col. <em><unclear><reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg></unclear></em> Regiment, to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> the parts of Scotland about <reg orig="Dumfreize">Dumfries</reg>, the <reg orig="Mores">Moors</reg> and Tividale; after 10. or 12. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> searching up and <reg orig="downe">down</reg>, and <reg orig="tyring">tiring</reg> almost all his horses, the 12. instant marching towards Hawick, by the way understood the Enemy had appointed a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> at 12 hours upon Bathwick Bray; whereupon he hastened thither all he could, but  was much impeded by the foulness of the weather, and a violent drift of snow; for he could get no intelligence of them, although within a mile of their body, at last he got sight of them, they drew up into two bodies and faced our men, ours made what haste they could to charge them.  After a <reg orig="sharpe">sharp</reg> conflict it pleased the Lord to give ours the victory over them, we pursued them several miles as long as our horses would go; and although out horses were <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="wearyed">wearied</reg> and theirs fresh, not above 15. horse escaped: their number about fourscore or more, their prisoners say a hundred, our party took 65. Horses, many of them good ones, 16 prisoners, two or three seem to be of note; though they conceal themselves; in the pursuit many were cut <reg orig="downe">down</reg> and put off their horses and so left, concluding those that came afterwards would glean them up; but the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> were busier in getting horses <reg orig="then">than</reg> in securing prisoners, and so many of them escaped away on foot, but will be known <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> they are met, having the States mark on them.  There were four of them slain, Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> it is reported is dangerously wounded, and his Major Major <em>Erwin</em>, we took both their horses, they fought very resolutely a great while.  Quartermaster <em>Ward</em> with 15 or 16 <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of ours are wounded and one slain.  The fight was at Phillip <reg orig="uppon">upon</reg> Bathwick water.  <em><unclear>Senlis</unclear></em> the High Sheriff of Roxbrough is redeemed out of their hands; but one of our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> ran him into the thigh, not knowing him, he is one very affectionate to our party.  Those of the Enemy that escaped are gone by way of Bigger, towards the hills, parties are sent to interrupt them.</p>

<p>The intent of <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencarne</reg></em> and <em>Kenmore</em> in their marching to the North, is (as they give out) to secure the landing of the <em>Dutch</em> Forces, Arms, and Ammunition, which it seems they expect.</p>

<p>The <unclear>late</unclear> Revolutions are well resented here, and the Army very unanimous to assist my Lord <em>Protector</em> in the carrying on <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Affairs.</p>

<p>No News from Sea, save that one Fleet are about <unclear>60</unclear> Sail, and General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> <unclear>riding</unclear> not far from St <em>Hellens Point</em>.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>

<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>