<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol202">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 202</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, April 20. to <em>Thursday</em>, April 27. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<p>This day a party being sent from Dalkeith <reg orig="too">to</reg> Capt. <em><reg orig="Malcombe">Malcolm</reg> Rogers</em>, (who was Agent for <em>Charles Stuart</em>, and lately brought several Commissions from him, and should have been apprehended by <em>Middleton's </em>instructions to <em>Glencarne</em>) and one <em>Stevens</em> in who was his Cornet, and a <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> in Leith; but the ninth of March last.</p>

<p>On Tuesday last, Capt. <em>Southwood</em> Commander of the White Raven, was engaged by 11 Dutch men of war, and two of them boarded him in sight of two small <reg orig="Pinkes">Pinks</reg> coming from Newcastle, the Weymouth Pink, and the Sparrow; but <pb n="1" /> they escaped from them, they had like to have hindered the supplies intended in the Primrose for Col. <em>Morgan</em>, but she went forth Yesterday in the <reg orig="afternnon">afternoon</reg>, and I hope will get safe thither, our expectations being great from him.</p>

<p>This morning a little Man of war, belonging to Col. <em>Atkins</em> was blown up in Leith Harbour, and 6 men killed in her.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was published for further <reg orig="supending">suspending</reg> the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</em>, to this effect.</p>

<p>Whereas in regard of many doubts arising upon an Act of the late Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Act for the Relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</em>, and several inconveniences and mischiefs like to grow from thence, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the Creditors and Prisoners themselves, but to divers other persons, without some explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> in and by the said Act; It is by an Ordinance of the 31 of <em>March</em> last Ordained, that the said several and respective Judges should not <reg orig="procceed">proceed</reg> to sale or disposition, nor otherwise <reg orig="intermeddle">interfere</reg> in the execution of the said Act, or of any the powers and authorities given by the same, until the 20 day of <em>April instant</em>; and whereas the way for prevention of those evils, and the better accomplishing the ends intended by the said Act, is now under consideration, which will necessarily require some longer time to perfect the same: Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with <pb n="2" /> the consent of his Council, That the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the dale or disposition or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in or by the said Act, nor shall otherwise <reg orig="intermeddle">interfere</reg> in the execution of the said Act, or of any of the powers or authorities given by the same, until the fifteenth day of <em>May</em> next coming; And be it further Ordained, that all Acts and things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, colour, or pretence of the said Act from henceforth and before the said fifteenth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid (saving <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in such cases, ad according to such limitations, as by said Ordinance they had power to do, before the twentieth day of <em>April</em>) shall be and are hereby declared to be utterly null and <reg orig="avoid">void</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal the 24 of March</i>, 1653 S.V.</head>

<p>On Tuesday last my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> and Count <em>Erick</em> had a meeting, to the debate of the Articles of union: at which time count <em>Erick</em> did <reg orig="exhibite">exhibit</reg> several Articles on the behalf of Sweden, some whereof <reg orig="where">were</reg> such, that his Lordship can by no means consent unto. Yesterday, his Excellency went unto the Queen to deliver his exceptions, and the reasons why he cannot admit of some of these Articles proposed to him, and the Queen seemed to be satisfied therein. But this day Count <em>Erick</em> came again unto my Lord, and was very earnest that those might be <pb n="3" /> admitted, but his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship</reg> is as earnest to exclude them. Yet I have <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the Queen will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> some expedient to reconcile all, and will sum up things into a harmony and <reg orig="agrement">agreement</reg>. The great talks here are of the Coronation of the new King; and preparations are made thereunto; so resolved is the Queen to <reg orig="resigne">resign</reg> up the Government. <em>Piemontelli</em> the Spanish Resident suddenly takes his leave to return home. Count <em>Monte Cuculi</em>, went away last week.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Regensborgh">Regensburg</reg>, the 6 of April.</i> S. N.</head>

<p>His <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> Majesty, having declared unto the States and <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> here present by a Decree, that he could not defer his departure any longer; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> demonstrated such means, whereby with <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> and ease, they might yet absolve the most important affairs; committing the rest to a <reg orig="Deputations">Deputation's</reg> consent: it is certainly believed the latter end of the month his Majesty will surely break up hence, which is more probable, by reason divers persons by degrees droop away from the Court. His Highness Duke <em><reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg></em> yesterday, and is to receive the like honour this day from the <reg orig="Emperess">Empress</reg> and King, which being performed; he intends to prosecute his Journey for <reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg>, being presented from his <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> with Horses, Coaches, and Sedans, for the better and more convenient performance of the same.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick, the 11 <reg orig="dito">ditto</reg></i> S. N.</head>

<p>Upon dissolution of the Parliament, the King went from Warsaw a hunting, and since as we <pb n="4" /> understand hath kept divers prime Councils to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> out some means for the satisfaction of the Militia. It is said his Majesty is very pleasant, and cares not how many Parliaments be dissolved in the like nature, rather then he <reg orig="wil">will</reg> part with his power: It is confirmed also, that of what is hitherto given out of the <reg orig="Muscoviters">Muscovites'</reg> invasion of <reg orig="Ukrame">Ukraine</reg>, is a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> figment; although it is true, that the Cossacks incline much to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with, and give themselves under the protection of the said <reg orig="Moscovites">Muscovites</reg>, but as yet he hath attempted nothing to that purpose; but hitherto only prepared himself upon his own borders for a Journey, as is conceived, unto Poland.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam the 15.<reg orig="dito">ditto</reg></i>. S. N.</head>

<p>Notwithstanding the express which came on last night at the Hague, bringing with him the full conclusion of peace, wanting <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the subscription (which he affirms will also shortly follow) all diligence is used to fit their Ships of war; but men come slowly to them, the most they get are <reg orig="unexperienced">inexperienced</reg>, or <reg orig="boyes">boys</reg> that were never at Sea; these accept of service in hopes of peace, in War they would prove useless. What Ships belong to this quarter, are most gone <reg orig="downe">down</reg> to the Texel, and Ulye, where they may <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> these 3. weeks, before they be ready.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, the 29 April</i>, S. N.</head>

<p>Some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, here arrived the Secretary of the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour"> Ambassador</reg> of <reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg>, <em>Piementelli</em>, who is coming from Sweden, to reside here for some time; his Secretary having taken a house for him: he is said to come with full power <pb n="5" /> to make a truce with this Crown for ten years. The Secretary hath been several times entertained by the Cardinal since he came, and hath had several conferences with him; and much inclination there seemeth to be in the Cardinal to <reg orig="imbrace">embrace</reg> this truce that is here spoken of; and so much desired by the people in general, which may be a strong Argument to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> the Cardinal to endeavour the effecting of it, thereby to <reg orig="gaine">gain</reg> the love of the people; whose hearts do wholly hang after peace. The said Secretary hath been invited to see the mask at the Louvre, where the <em>Stuarts</em> do often meet, to drive away their <reg orig="melancholly">melancholy</reg> distempers; which the peace of the two Commonwealths hath brought upon them. They talk <reg orig="a fresh">afresh</reg> <reg orig="againe">again</reg> of their sudden remove; but as yet there is no great <reg orig="likehood">likelihood</reg> of it, this Court paying of him none of his <reg orig="arreers">arrears</reg>, which he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he shall now suddenly receive, and <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> bids his followers to prepare for their Journey.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is said to have his <reg orig="Fevor">Fever</reg> again.</p>

<p>The King of France is still taken up with his Mask, wherewith he delights himself in the exercise thereof very frequently.</p>

<p>The Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> hath communicated to this Court the advice he hath received; how that the <reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg> have wholly subdued the Hollanders in the <em>West Indies</em>, and have taken <em>Pharnambuck</em> from them, which was the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> place they held there in those parts, of any consequence.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3">Innerness, April 10.</head>

<p>The Enemy in Caithness have endeavoured all they could to raise that Country, but the people are backward in joining with them, fearing lest the Garrison which is at Sinclair Castle, commanded by Capt. Langrish, of Col. <reg orig="Fitches">Fitche's</reg> Regiment, should punish their forwardness after <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> march out of Caithness, wherefore for their encouragement, Major General Dyal with a party of Foot, and one hundred Horse, is ordered to sit down before it for the taking it in, which is conceived will not easily be achieved by them, the place being naturally strong, and a vessel within these few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> being sent from hence with 3 months provision and ammunition; so that they are, with what they had in store, well provided for at least six Months, Capt. Hill also of Coll. <reg orig="Fitches">Fitche's</reg> Regiment <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> from hence, this week thirty load of necessaries for his Garrison of Ruthen in Badgenoth of which he is <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, that Country at present being free from the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg>.</p>

<p>Col. Morgan <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> from this place on Monday, having drawn a party of Foot out of this Garrison to join with those Forces he brought from Aberdeen, so that he lies with about Eleven or Twelve hundred Horse and Dragoons, and a considerable party of Foot, betwixt the Enemy and the Passes, they must needs march through, if they intend to move out of this North Corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, or otherwise break or disband those Forces they have gathered; there being no way <pb n="7" /> left them to avoid meeting with Col. Morgan, but through such inaccessible bounds, as it is impossible for their Horse to march that way, and very difficult for their Foot, it being exceeding Mountainous, and scarcely inhabited, and the Country they are in will not long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an account of some Action betwixt him and Middleton; what the success will be the Lord knows, in whose hands are all the corners of the Earth.</p>

<head level="3">From Brussels, April 26.</head>

<p>Now the peace is concluded between the two Commonwealths, whereof we have certain advise by the Express of the Lords Ambassadors of the United Provinces who <reg orig="past">passed</reg> through these Provinces with the Ratification, most men are now full of speculation, what design the great English Fleet hath in hand, and where the storm will fall in the end: which a short time will discover, too soon I fear to those who shall feel the effects thereof.</p>

<p>The Lorain <reg orig="Armie">Army</reg> hath now their <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> between Lille, Tournay, and Courtnay, living in much disorder according to their discretion and wonted manner; there being little difference between those Troops, and the Enemies; for although the first do not force the Cities and Towns, which the Enemies do; yet they fire, plunder, and destroy whatsoever they meet <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, which is one and the same thing. In the mean time Francis Duke of Lorain is expected here, being long since <pb n="8" /> gone from <unclear><em>Rathbone</em></unclear>, with his two Sons. This Prince will be <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to the Interest of the King of Spain, and govern his Army as it ought to be, under Command and good Discipline, the want whereof hath occasioned all these disorders and extra <reg orig="agancies">agencies</reg>, which have happened in these parts, to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of many poor Inhabitants. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> </em>Duke of <em>Lorain</em> his Brother speaks all the ill he can of him, and <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That he ought not to be trusted, for there is nothing but Treachery in him, and the like malicious language.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg> 24. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>On the 14 of this Month arrived an Express at the Hague, with Letters from our <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors in England to the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, wherein they advise that the Peace was wholly finished ad concluded, That the business of <em>Denmark</em> was determined, and the <reg orig="States Generall"> States-General</reg> to be responsible for One hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling; That the ships detained in the Sound, should be restored within Fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after that those should arrive there who were to receive them; and that the <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg> shall be appraised by the First of May, by Four persons. Upon this good News the States of Holland adjourned yesterday; leaving their Order and consent with the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg> to <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> the Ratification. A few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Articles of the Treaty of Peace were signed on both sides, being sent over two <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, by two of the Gentlemen of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors, who <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> at the Hague, to the great contentment and joy of all the honest men in these parts which were no sooner read, but presently Ratified by the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, and the Ratification sent away for England immediately. So that now we no longer doubt of this blessed Peace, which hath kept us in <reg orig="suspence">suspense</reg> thus long together, however our <reg orig="Criticks">Critics</reg> will not pardon the remissness of our Governors, for making such slow preparations, when their <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> arm so vigorously.</p>

<p>The Lord Lieut: <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> Opdam, is at present at the Hague, with the Vice-<reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> Witte Wittesen, Ruyter, and John Evertson, with <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Sea-Captains, who have received order from the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> to furnish their ships with all things necessary with all speed, The <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> for the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships is to be at Goree; and no ship is to be suffered to <reg orig="goe"> go</reg> to Sea till the Peace be published: and much variety of Opinions here passeth upon the great Preparations of the English, and the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> they have in hand with their great Fleet.</p><pb n="9" /> 

<head level="3">Saturday April 22. 1654.</head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas a Peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> of the <em>United Provinces</em> of the <em>Low Countries</em>. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof shall be made on both parts on Wednesday next, being the 26. day of this instant <em>April</em>; From which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after twelve <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, within these Seas; And in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after 6 weeks, And from thence, within the <em>Mediterranean</em> Sea, and to <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line, after 10 weeks; And beyond the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg>, after the space of eight months: Which several spaces were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to all others, whom it may concern within the Dominions thereof; To the end, they may have Warning to provide for their own safety, and not expect their ships to danger within the several, and respective times aforesaid.</p>

<p><em>W. Jessop</em> Clerk of the Council.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith,</i> April 15.</head>

<p> On Monday the 10 instant, Lieut. Col. <em>Erwin</em>, who had been upon the Borders of <em>England</em> with a party of the Tories, returned (having increased his number of 17 which he took with him) with 40 horse, and passed by in view of our Garrison of <em>Kilcroock</em>, Lieut. <em>Hunt</em> that commanded there, drew out with a party, but could not overtake them till they got to <em>Aberfoyle</em>, took 7 prisoners, 11 horse, 20 cloaks and many cloakbags full of plunder, which they scattered the better to make their escape; we rescued two prisoners which they had brought out of the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills, being two ancient men whose houses they had plundered and taken away their Horses and goods. The Lords <em>Forrester</em>, and <em>Dudhop</em> are yet in <em>Athol</em>, but bring no further advantage to their party, then their persons and attendants.</p>

<p> Since the two Defeats given to <em>Mac <reg orig="Naughtons">Naughton's</reg></em> party, he is gone away being much suspected by some of the Rebels that he hath betrayed his men to us which makes many of their Officers begin to Capitulate, and to move for to have terms to come in, being also <em>Morgan</em> yet continues at <em>Dingwel</em> in <em>Ross</em> with about 220 Horse and Foot, and the Enemy within 15 Miles from them in <em>Sutherland</em> with 400 Horse and Foot, from whence they cannot advance Southwards any passable way but it must be within a mile of our Forces, or else engage us, otherwise if they march over the Hills and Rocks, it will be the loss of all their Horse, and so consequently their whole Army, they give out high language that they will make their way through <pb n="10" /> us. Our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are very hearty and <reg orig="chearful">cheerful</reg>, and with nothing more than Engagement. The last week <em>Middleton</em> took the whole charge of their Army and finds great fault with <em>Glengary</em> for bringing their horse into a pound: There were 900foot raised in <em>Caithness</em> which <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> before <em>Sinclair</em> Castle, which is in good condition and will hold out, notwithstanding all the Enemies Confidence of taking it and Resolutions to do it before they <reg orig="stirr">stir</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></i> April, 12.</head>

<p> Several Ordinances were passed; the one <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for erecting Court Barons in</i> Scotland.</p>

<p> Be it Declared, Established, and Ordained by His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and Consent of his Council, That in every place or Circuit of Land which really is, or hath commonly been called, known or reputed to be a <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>, within the Nation of <em>Scotland</em>, there shall be one Court, which shall be in the Nature of a Court Baron, or Court of a <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg> here in <em>England</em>, to be <reg orig="holden">held</reg> every three weeks; which Court shall have power, order, and jurisdiction of all Contracts, debts, promises, and Trespasses, whatsoever arising within the said <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>, or precincts thereof; Provided that the Matter in demand exceed not the value of forty shillings sterling, and that in any such action of Trespass, the Freehold or Title of the Land be not drawn into question; and it is further Declared and Ordained, That every the said Court Baron shall be held in manner following, That is to say, the style of the Court shall be, The Court of A. B. held the day of 16 by K.D.C. <reg orig="Sutors">Suitors</reg> of the said Court and the homage or <reg orig="Sutors">Suitors</reg> to be named in the entry, then after three <unclear><em>O yes</em></unclear> made, the <reg orig="Sutors">Suitors</reg>, or their Clerk, or Steward shall say, if any will be <reg orig="assoigned">assigned</reg> or enter plaint, let them come in and they shall be heard, then the Jury are to be <reg orig="impannelled">empanelled</reg> and sworn, and then a short charge is to be given concerning the several matters and things to be done there, and after presentment and enquiry made, the <reg orig="Sutors">Suitors</reg> shall proceed in the several matters presented, and give order and Relief, as the Case shall require and make execution by attachment upon the goods of the party within that <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>.</p>

<p> And it is hereby further Declared and Ordained, that the <reg orig="Sutors">Suitors</reg> in every the said Court Baron many from time to time, as there shall be occasion, make <reg orig="by laws">by-laws</reg> for the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> weal, Rule and Government of the persons within such <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>, and all and every such by-law shall be binding to every party within the <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>; And the said Suitors shall have power and authority to amerce such persons as infringe any of the said by-laws, and may give warrant to the Bailiff of the <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg> to <reg orig="distrein">distrain</reg> for such amercement by attachment upon the goods of the party offending. Provided that such by-laws be not extended to bind the Inheritance of any person who is not party to the same and agrees not thereunto</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p><pb n="11" />

<p> A second was passed also, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> <i>An Ordinance of <unclear>Parday</unclear> and Grace to the people of Scotland</i> The sum whereof is to this effect; that from and after the first day of <em>May</em> 1654. All person shall be acquitted, for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> done by Sea or Land, in relation to the late war or any proceeding wars between the two Nations, but the same shall be put in perpetual oblivion, and their estates be discharged from frequentation. From the benefit of this Ordinance these following persons are Excepted, <em>viz. <reg orig="Henrieta">Henrietta</reg>, Maria, </em>late Queen, with her two Sons <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> and <em>James Stuart, James</em>and <em>William</em> late Dukes of <em>Hamilton</em> deceased, <em>John</em> Earl of <em>Lawderdale,</em> <em>John</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Lowdoun">Lowdown</reg ></em>, Earl of <em>Seaforth, </em>Earl of <em>Athol</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Lord <em>Lorne</em> eldest son of the Marquis of <em>Argile</em>, Lord <em>Macklin</em>, eldest son of the Earl of <em>Lowdown</em>, Lord <em>Montgomery</em> eldest son of the Earl <em>Figglington</em>, <em>George</em> Lord <em>Spynie</em>, Lord<em> Crawmston</em>, Lord <em>Sincleere</em>, <em>Thomas</em> <em>Dalrel</em> late Major general of the foot in the <reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg> Army, <em>John Midletoune</em> late Leiut. General of the <reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg> Army, <em>James </em>Viscount<em> Newburgh</em>, Lord <em>Bargany</em>, Sir <em>Thomas Thompson</em>, <em>James Edmeston</em> Laird of <em>Womat</em>, Lord <em>Napier</em>, <em>William</em> Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>. These persons are excepted, and estates confiscated wholly; save that some part is <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon the wives and children of some of them, out of their respective estates.</p>

<p>There are several other persons, who are admitted to compound for their Estates, which we have not room here to insert, but you shall have it in the next.</p>

<p>As concerning the several Exceptions and <reg orig="Provisoes">Provisos</reg> contained in this Ordinance, I must refer you to the Ordinance itself, which is printed at large.</p>

<p>The same day also and Ordinance was passed, for settling the Estates of the several Excepted persons in Scotland, in the real and actual possession and <reg orig="seizin">seizing</reg> of Sir <em>John Hope</em> of Graighall, <em>William Lockard</em> the youngest Esqu. <em>Richard Saltonstal</em> and <em>Edward Siler</em> Commissioners at Leith, Leiut. Col. <em>Wilks</em> deputy governor of Leith, <em>Davis Barkley</em> Esqu. <em>John Harper</em> Advocate, and the Survivors and Survivor of them, their Heirs and <reg orig="Assignes">Assignees</reg>, for certain uses and purposes in the said Ordinance expressed, until the sale, disposition and conveyance thereof as shall be requisite for the purposes aforesaid, as is therein directed, and the remainder to the use of his Highness the Lord Protector and his successors, for the benefit of the Commonwealth.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was passed likewise, <em>for uniting Scotland into one Commonwealth, and under one Government with England</em>; And in every Parliament to be held successively for the said Commonwealth, thirty persons shall be called from, and serve Scotland. And for the more effectual preservation of this union, and the <reg orig="freedome">freedom</reg> and safety of this Commonwealth so united, it is ordained, that the people of Scotland and <unclear>Sethland</unclear>, and of all the Dominions and Territories <pb n="12" /> thereto belonging, be discharged of all fealty, homage, service and allegiance, pretended to be due unto any of the family of the <em>Stuarts</em>, who are hereby disabled to hold or <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> the Crown of Scotland, or to have the name, <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, title, or dignity of a King, or Queen of Scotland, &amp;c.</p>

<p>It is ordained also, that the said office, <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, dignity, power, and authority of King of <em>Scotland</em>, and all right of the three Estates of Scotland, to assemble in any general Convocation or Parliament, and all Conventional and Parliamentary authority in Scotland, as formerly established, be abolished, made null and void.</p>

<p>And that the Arms of <em>Scotland</em>, <em>viz.</em> A Cross, commonly called Saint <reg orig="Andrews">Andrew's</reg> Cross, be received into, and born henceforth in the Arms of this Commonwealth, as a badge of this Union, and that all the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Seals, Seals of office, and Seals of bodies civil or corporate, in Scotland, which heretofore carried the Arms of the Kings of <em>Scotland</em>, shall henceforth, instead thereof, carry the Arms of this Commonwealth.</p>

<p>No greater rate for Excise and Custom are to be imposed upon any goods transported between England and Scotland, but they are to pass with the same <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, as goods passing from port to port, or place to place, in England. Also all goods which by any law are prohibited to be transported out of <em>England</em>, are by the same law prohibited to be transported out of Scotland to any foreign parts. The like rule also for importation, and upon the same penalties.</p>

<p>Ordained likewise, that all Cesses, <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Impositions, and Taxations whatsoever, be <reg orig="levyed">levied</reg> henceforth proportionably from the whole people of this Commonwealth so united.</p>

<p>All dominion of Tenures and Superiorities importing servitude and Vassalage, are also abolished in Scotland. Concerning which more at large, and the other particulars before abbreviated, you are referred to the printed Ordinances themselves.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal in Sweden, March 24.</i></head>

<p>I begin now to believe, that we shall receive a dispatch; and though in respect of some things they offer, we seem to be at some distance; yet I have such a <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the noble Lady will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> out such an expedient, that satisfaction will be amply given to both Nations. And this to be as the last act of her <reg orig="reigne">reign</reg>; which in my poor judgement is a great <reg orig="pitty">pity</reg>, for certainly she is as accomplished a Princess, as ever had the honour of swaying a <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>; and though the French, being <reg orig="riged">rigid</reg> to their <reg orig="salique">Salique</reg> laws, will not permit the <reg orig="distaffe">distaff</reg> to <reg orig="intermeddle">interfere</reg> with a <reg orig="Crowne">Crown</reg>; yet had they such a Virgin to rule amongst them, they would hereafter blot out such a law out of their records, as being mightily prejudicial to their advantage. On Thursday last, my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> and Count <em>Erick</em> had a meeting to debate upon the Articles of union: at which time Count <em>Erick</em> <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> several articles on the behalf of Sweden, most of which were the same my Lord first gave in; but some did differ exceedingly, <pb n="13" /> so that my Lord has totally waved them. Yesterday his Excellency went to the Queen to give in his exceptions, and reasons why he could not admit some of them, but this day Count <em>Erick</em> came again to my Lord, and did very much press, that his Articles proposed might be admitted; but my Lord is very positive not to <reg orig="yeild">yield </reg> thereunto. And I doubt not, but the accord may be made without them. All the speech here is of the Coronation of the new King, and all preparations are made thereunto. The Muscovite is <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into Poland with an Army of 200000, and has taken one of the frontier Towns. <reg orig="Tis">'Tis </reg> probable, that the Pole will suffer very much, partly by this Army, and partly by their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> intestine divisions.</p>

<p>But if you consider the strange propositions made by the Queen, and the reply given by the Prince, you will hardly imagine they should agree about this business of resignation.</p>

<head level="3">March 25. 1654.</head>

<head level="3"><i>Four Propositions of the Queen to the Prince.</i></head>

<p>1. She <reg orig="wil">will</reg> retain the best part of the Kingdom and the Customs to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>.</p>

<p>2. She will be no Subject, but free of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> without <reg orig="controll">control</reg>.</p>

<p>3. She will <reg orig="Travail">Travel</reg> whither she pleaseth.</p>

<p>4. She will not revoke those Gifts of hers, which are <em>Pradia Corona</em>, and were by her given, out of <reg orig="Favor">Favour</reg>, to Courtiers.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Prince his Reply.</i></head>

<p>1. He will not be a King without a Kingdom, or at least without the better part of it.</p>

<p>2. He will have no <reg orig="Rivall">Rival</reg>, more than she a Superior.</p>

<p>3. He will not hazard himself about her <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg> abroad.</p>

<p>4. He will not be without a Revenue sufficient both for war and peace.</p>

<p>Captain <em><reg orig="Hubberts">Hubbert's</reg></em> Regiment, are Ordered forthwith to March to <em>Barwick</em>.</p><pb n="14" />

<head level="3">A List of Prizes lately taken. <em>April</em> 7:</head>

<p>A French Vessel with 25 lasts of <reg orig="Tarr">Tar</reg> and Pitch in her, taken by the Assurance<reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>April</em> 10.</head>

<p>A ship of Amsterdam, of 200 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, and 5 Guns, taken by the Assurance and Amity.</p>

<p>Two more; one with Pitch, Linseed, and Deal Boards belonging to <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>; the other a French ship taken by the Pearl.</p>

<p>Another Vessel belonging to Flushing, with 26 <em>Cases</em> of Glass, taken by the Drake <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>Also a small <reg orig="Pinck">Pink</reg> of Flushing, laden with wines from Bordeaux, taken by the Non Such <reg orig="Fragat">Fragate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>April</i> 15.</head>

<p>A Private man of War, taken by the <reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg> about <em>Flamborough</em> head.</p>

<p>The taking of the East-Indy ship mentioned in our last to be taken from the Dutch, is confirmed. <reg orig="Shee">She</reg> was of 800 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, 4 Chests of silver, and well laden with other Commodities.</p>

<p><em>April</em> 26. The Peace between <em>England</em> and the <em>United Provinces</em>, was by sound of Trumpet solemnly proclaimed; first, in <reg orig="White-hall ">Whitehall</reg> Court, in presence of his Highness and the Council. Afterwards, the <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at Arms, Heralds, and other Officers appointed, were received at <em>Temple Barr</em> by the Lord Major, and thence conducted to the<em> Old Exchange</em>, where it was proclaimed again in these following words:</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation of the Peace made between this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and that of the United Provinces of the Netherlands.</i></head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, considering how necessary it is, not only to preserve Peace and quiet at home, but as far as in him <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg>, to live in Amity and Friendship with His Neighbours, Hath by the blessing of God, with the advice of His Council, made and concluded a Peace, Union and Confederation to continue <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, between this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of the one part, and that of the United Provinces of the Low Countries, of the other part, their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories, Places, and People by Sea, Land, Fresh-waters, and elsewhere, by which Peace is agreed, That all Enmity, Hostility, Discord and War between the said <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their People, and Subjects, shall cease, and all Injuries and Wrongs whatsoever done since the 18 &amp; 28 of May 1652. Shall cease and be forgotten, except such <reg orig="Depradations">Depredations</reg> as shall be committed by either side, in these Seas, after 12 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, from the date of these presents; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after six <reg orig="weeke">weeks</reg>; and from thence, within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranian">Mediterranean</reg></em> Sea <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line, after ten weeks and beyond the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line, after the space of 8 months, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places. And that the People and Inhabitants of each party respectively, of <pb n="15" /> what condition or quality soever they be shall treat each other with love and friendship, and may freely and securely come into, and pass through each <reg orig="others">others'</reg> Countries, Towns, Villages and Precincts, and there stay and abide, and from thence depart again at their pleasure, without any <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> or molestation, and likewise trade and have commerce, and generally do use and exercise all other things (observing the Laws and Customs of each place respectively) as freely, fully and securely, as they might have done in time of Peace.</p>

<p>Whereof all Persons, whatsoever in these Nations of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland,</em> are to take notice and conform themselves accordingly.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 26 April,</i> 1654. O.P.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith,</i> April 20.</head>

<p>Col. Morgan is marched from Dingwel towards Tain with all his Brigade: On Thursday last there marched 1000 Foot over the Hills above Brahan towards Sutherland, which <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed are the Longhaber men which will add to the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> strength, which was before 4000 Horse and Foot. There was a quarrel between Sir George Monroe and the Earl of Glencarn for Plundering of and abusing the Laird of Fowlis (<reg orig="Monroes">Monroe's</reg> Brother) who was extremely abused by them, which rise so high that they appointed to fight a Combat, and accordingly on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day was 8 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in the morning they mounted and <reg orig="rid">rode</reg> to the place appointed, and because Monroe would fight on Horseback, he took his Pistols with him, but Glencairn bid him put away his Pistols and they would fight only on Horseback with their swords. In which Combat Monroe had his right Hand almost cut off, and a cut in the forehead: Glencairn was likewise cut in the head. There was also a quarrel between Athol and Glengary about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> of place, and a field appointed, but the business was taken up by the Commanders.</p>

<p> Our small Garrisons near Sterling have this week fallen with success into the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Quarters and brought away prisoners, and amongst the rest a party from Buhannon marched into the Parish of Strablain where Capt. Cunningham and Capt. Edmiston were levying of horse and foot, took Capt. Cunningham, and narrowly <reg orig="mist">missed</reg> Capt. Edmiston. General Monck intended to be back at Berwick this night, and is expected here on Saturday.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">SANCTI SANCITI; or,</head>

<p>&#x261e;<i>The doctrine of the Perseverance of the Saints vindicated</i> from the Attempts lately made against it by Mr <em>John Goodwyn</em>, in his Book <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <em>Redemption Redeemed</em>. Together with an Appendix in defence of University Learning. By <em>George Kendall</em>, <unclear>B D.</unclear> sometimes Fellow of Exeter <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Oxon.</p>

<p>Also, <em>The grand Prerogative of <reg orig="Humane">Human</reg> Nature</em>: To be sold by <em>Anthony Williamson </em>at the <em><reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Arms</em>, in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard, <unclear>near</unclear> the West end.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>