<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol184">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 184</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, Decem 16. to <em>Thursday</em>, Decem. 22. 1653.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Newcastle, December 3.</i></head>

<p>Divers cavaliers and Malignants have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> at Fairs in the <em>North</em>, where being provided of horses, they have marched in small Parties, two or three in a company toward <em>Scotland</em>. That notable Fellow Colonel <em>Wogan</em> was at a Fair in Northumberland, and <reg orig="som">some</reg> others with him as desperate as himself, who are also gone to the Scotch country.</p>

<p>From <em>Berwick</em> we hear that on Wednesday last there was a party of about 16, or 18 of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse at a Town called <em>Chernside</em>, 4, or 5 miles off <em>Berwick</em>; and a Fair being there, divers <pb n="1" /><em>Berwick</em> men, and other Gentlemen went thither about their business; where they were no sooner come, but they were <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> upon, their Horses taken away, and themselves <reg orig="stript">stripped</reg> both of their clothes, monies, and other things, and then let loose again to shift for themselves.</p>

<p>Another party of them seized likewise on two Soldiers that were bound towards the same Town to assist the Collectors in gathering in the Assessments, whom they disarmed, and then released. Those <reg orig="Horsmen">Horsemen</reg> who play <em>Rex</em> thus, are very well mounted, and have <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> away many good Horses out of the Marshes. Their Commander is said to be one <unclear><em>Meldrum</em></unclear>.</p>

<p>There are also about 140 Horse in the Marsh, and in <em>Tividale</em>, under Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>, raising both men and money.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris December 20. 1653.</i></head>

<p>The main work to do now at court and in this city, is only in making great preparations for the keeping of their great Feast of the Nativity of our <reg orig="Savior">Saviour</reg>, which beginneth next Thursday; The King since his return with his <reg orig="councell">council</reg>, hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> employed in the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Winter Quarters for the Army, which is not to Quarter in Villages as formerly, thereby to become <reg orig="burthensom">burdensome</reg> to the people, but they are to be quartered in the Frontier Towns, where some allowance will be made monthly for their Lodgings and Firings, and care taken that the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> might receive their pay to buy Provisions for their subsistence. The Marshall <em>de Foncauld</em> and others, who lately are returned into the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> obedience, came to <pb n="2" />this City, this being done by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the <unclear><!-- could be "Amnistia"--><em><reg orig="Amnistie">Amnesty</reg></em></unclear>, therefore they were presented to his Majesty, who received their thankfulness, and other submissions.</p>

<p>The last Tuesday arrived here the Marquis of <em>Uignau</em>, to bring the particulars of the Defeat given to the Spaniards in <em>Roussillon</em>, which you have heard in my last; the <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of his Majesty to go into <em>Provence</em>, continueth still, it being <unclear>easierly</unclear> followed by the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, who worketh his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> ends therein, as well as the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>, which he doth so much pretend; this doth something thwart the project of the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador, who for many months since hath <reg orig="droven">driven</reg> on the <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of making a Match between the King and his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> daughter, with whom he proffers to give many millions of gold. The Protestant party in <unclear><em>Languedoc</em></unclear> and other Counties adjacent, are in expectation of a <reg orig="favorrable">favourable</reg> answer to be given to their many and great grievances lately brought from them by the Baron of <em>Rou vigni</em>, who (as I hear) hath presented them, but as yet no answer returned to them, but was promised fair to have it within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The common report is, that the Chamber Ardent shall be put <reg orig="downe">down</reg>, it being very much exclaimed against, &amp; I hear not they have done or acted <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of late: Our <reg orig="Arch-Bishop">Archbishop</reg> is very sick, and also his Nephew the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em>, who doth yet remain a close prisoner, by reason Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> will not be able to bend him to his Italian humour. The news from <em>Alsatia</em> are various, some will have the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> to <pb n="3" />have made his agreement with the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, for the delivering up Brisack, and other places under his command to him, but others affirm this to be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a plot of the Cardinal to spread such reports, thereby to render him odious to the King and the whole Nation.</p>

<p>By the last news from <em>Naples</em> thus: the vice-King having notice that the Earl of <em>Castriglio</em> our new vice King was arrived at St. <em>Poselippo</em> with his Wife, and a great Train sent one of his high Officers, to <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> him, and make him the usual <reg orig="complement">compliment</reg>: the next day he was visited by the Cardinal <em>Filmarini</em>, with the rest of the Nobles, both spiritual and temporal: The Duke <em>de Terranova</em>, who is to be Ambassador in ordinary at Rome, is also come to this City.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Sterling</em>, December 2.</i></head>

<p><em>Glencarne</em> and his company removed from their fastness in <em>Monteith</em> towards <em>Broad-Albin</em> on <reg orig="thursday">Thursday</reg> last, upon an alarm given them by one of our Garrisons, about 8 or 9 miles hence. The Lord <em>Lorne</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> are certainly at a great difference; and some contest hath been between <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> and <em>Glencarne</em>, for the <reg orig="cheief">chief</reg> conduct, <!--??--><em><reg orig="Glencary">Glengarry</reg></em> looking on himself as the taller man and better <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>. They <reg orig="talke">talk</reg> of setting up the Standard at the head of <!--??--><em><reg orig="Lough">Loch</reg> Tay</em> very shortly; and then they will proceed in all haste with their Levies.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, our Commander in <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> is using all possible ways for securing our Forces here, and putting them into such a posture as may oppose the enemy. And no means <pb n="4" />may be left unattempted for preventing the Country from <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with this rude Rabble, he hath convened the Gentleman of the adjacent Counties, who have (some of them)m subscribed the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> <em>Engagement</em> under hand and seal, and the Gentleman of this Shire have generally engaged also; That neither themselves nor any of the people under their power, shall or will act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to the prejudice of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> or their Forces; nor any way assist or correspond in person, counsels, advice, or any other means, with the <em>Highlanders</em> now in Arms, or who hereafter shall be in arms against the Commonwealth, under the penalty of forfeiture of life and estate, And to be proceeded against as the Parliament of the Commonwealth, and those <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> by them shall appoint. This Engagement was subscribed the 28 of <em>November</em> 1653.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, Novemb.</i> 21. S.V.</head>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> arrived here upon the 15 instant with all his Retinue; they are a very gallant company, consisting of at least 90, or 100 persons; he is yet here, and I suppose will stay yet 8, or 10 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, till he get Answer of those Letters he sent to Court since he came hither; he came ashore the same day he arrived here, so that the Magistrates here had no opportunity to receive his Lordship as they intended, but have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> extremely <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> unto him since, which he doth himself <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg>; The convoy which came along with the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships are yet here, which will now get the company <pb n="5" />of the Ph&oelig;nix &amp; Elizabeth <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, which came with my Lord over. By Letters from <em>Stockholm</em> I have, that there were 3 Hollands Flyboats lading with great Guns for Holland. I have acquainted his Excellency with it, and doubt not but some course will be taken for the interception of the same.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Colen Decemb.</i> 9. S.N.</head>

<p>The differences between this City and our Bishop continues yet, the ships being detained yet as well under <em>Kepserswert</em>, as from above at <!--Bonn??--><em>Bon</em>, to the great prejudice and <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> of the poor Merchants, and greater hazard both of ships and goods, whom one hard Frost, which now is daily expected, would utterly <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, there being no protection at neither place to save them. Saturday last the Duke of <reg orig="Newburghs">Newburgh's</reg> chancellor as also deputed from the city, departed to his Highness, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed they will procure the relaxation of the said ships; which is much longed for. The <unclear>Land-day at <em>Mulbelm</em></unclear> is broke up without effect. From <em>Regensburgh</em> no news at all for the present.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen Decemb.</i> 7. S.V.</head>

<p>Since my last I received yours, which gives an exact account of the Dutch loss in the late fight; as also of their Sea Engine, wherewith they intend to do great wonders; but if they make no other Provision against the Spring to encounter the English, this will be but a poor bulwark of Defence; I have heard of many such inventions, but they are at last come to nothing else but the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of time and Treasure. The Messenger <pb n="6" />that was sent hence for Holland, is returned hither, who brings likewise the confirmation of their great loss in the late storm, which have brought them into a very low condition, so that there is no money to be had for our King, which puts us to hard shifts, and causes us to fear that the Dutch will at last quite leave us in the lurch. We understand of the English <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> arrival at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, which makes us anew jealous of the <em>Swede</em>; so that it was lately propounded in the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, to send another Ambassador for <em>Sweden</em>, but nothing was concluded upon, but our Agent there should take new instructions to oppose the Transactions of the said Ambassador.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> December 6.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> safely arrived at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> the 15th of November, where he <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in expectation of an Answer to certain Letters of his, which he had sent to the Queen. The Dutch here say the Treaty with you in England will come to <reg orig="nought">naught</reg>, and that you will <reg orig="therupon">thereupon</reg> go by the Ears more fierce <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever. Certainly, that people mean nothing; for, they in all these parts hold up their violent malice against England, and have Letters constantly out of their own <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which augment their disaffection abroad, and <reg orig="shew">show</reg> what Temper the rest are of at home.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Stockholm by the last.</i></head>

<p>The Queen with the whole Court is now at <em>Upsall</em>, and from thence she intends to visit the <reg orig="Coppermines">Copper mines</reg>. The Dutch goods are not yet restored. It is said she hath a Catalogue of accusations <pb n="7" />and Offences to produce against them; for which she intends to have satisfaction. This Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, and the Subjects thereof, have <reg orig="suffred">suffered</reg> exceedingly by the intolerance and injustice of that People.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburough">Edinburgh</reg> December 9.</i></head>

<p>Intelligence is come that Kenmore is marched into the South with some few Foot, and sevenscore Horse, <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> is gone into his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> Country with 80 Horse, to keep in the Castle of Blair, that so he may with more liberty take up his Levies there. Kinoule is to raise a Regiment in Barchlaush, and Cooper in Angus; and Ramsay (who lately brought sevenscore Horse to them, and is returned <reg orig="againe">again</reg>) to be his Lieut. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>. Lane not yet come to them, some jealousies lie upon him, that he, is not so forward as he might. Macnoughton is also somewhat cold in the work, so that no help is come from them as yet.</p>

<p>Glencarne hath sent out Warrants to several <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>, for very great proportions of Cloth, Boots, <reg orig="Shooes">Shoes</reg> Money, &amp;c. He sent for as much cloth as would <reg orig="cloath">clothe</reg> 150 <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>: <unclear><!-- approx. 5 chars-->her</unclear>, with as much <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg> and <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg> as <unclear><!-- approx 8 chars-->nish</unclear> the same number, each of them <unclear>w<!--approx 7 chars--></unclear> shirts and a pair of <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, and fifteen <unclear>hundred</unclear> pound Scotch money, threatens them, that if they delay to give obedience, he will exact the same by force.</p>

<p>The <unclear><!--approx 11 chars--></unclear> party of fourscore of these broken <unclear><!--approx 13 chars--></unclear> away 7 or 8 good Horses from <unclear><!--approx 16 chars-->ems</unclear> house in <reg orig="Fyfe">Fife</reg>, and a <pb n="8" />party of four Rogues came into the Laird of <reg orig="Womats">Womat's</reg> House three or four miles from Leith, and <reg orig="stab'd">stabbed</reg> an English man, who was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by the Commissioners to gather in the Rents of his coal-pits: by which we may perceive what usage we might expect, if we were at their mercy.</p>

<p>By a letter intercepted from one of their own party thus. All our <reg orig="Commission'd">Commissioned</reg> Officers are going now to their several <reg orig="Locallities">Localities</reg> for Levies which was not till now determined upon, both of Horses and Foot: the Earl of <reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses in Perthshire, and the whole Foot thereof: Kinolve hath the Horses of the shire of Angus and Mernes: <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses out of <reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg>, Sutherland, <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>, and Murray, and to be Commander in chief of their Foot levied there: Kenmore is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> the Horses of the shire of Aberdeen. Col. Blakader of Tulliallen is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> in a part of the shire of Fife; Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> left us two nights, being discontented for not getting a Locality on the North side of Forth; he was and is Gentleman Quartermaster, and is again reconciled, and is to have Sterlingshire for a Locality of levying the Horses there.</p>

<p>We are now about 1000 good well armed resolute Foot, and 500 Horse, the Riders are singularly good, they and the Horses are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> ill equipaged; Saddles and Bridles that are good, are rare here. I have sent you a Purse-penny, I <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> that there be not a word of the other: This is all. I remain.</p>

<p><i>Poole December 9.</i> Here hath not been any Intelligence<pb n="9" />. About fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, Captain <em>Green</em> Commander of a private man of War, brought into this Harbour a prize, pretending to be of Dunkirk, she hath about 114 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of French Wine on board, came from <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg>, the Master is a Scotchman, put in as is supposed for colour <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, which with other circumstances, give great expectation that she will prove a prize.</p>

<p>This day the same Captain <em>Green</em> hath brought in another Vessel, called the Grout pot, she names <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, the <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> name is <em>Steven van Gollen</em>, she hath about 70 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of French Wine and some Ginger, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed she will also prove a prize.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels the 20 of December.</i> Stilo novo.</head>

<p>The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the <reg orig="Cittadel">Citadel</reg> of <em><reg orig="Antwerpe">Antwerp</reg></em> by name <em>don Balsacar Mercader</em> is preparing for the voyage from hence into <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, there to remonstrate to his Majesty the condition of these Counties, which during these Wars are very much impoverished, Trade being dead, money scarce, <reg orig="Handicraftmen">Handicraftsmen</reg> have nothing to do, the people grow poor for want of <reg orig="gaine">gain</reg>, the Countrymen are ruined by <reg orig="quartring">quartering</reg> of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, who live at discretion and take what they please. The Gentry are low in revenues, and not able to hold out in the payment of their contributions and cares without some redress, which is not to be expected but by a general peace between both <reg orig="Crownes">Crowns</reg>, which is not like to be in haste, though there be great want of it at present, preparations are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> making ready against <pb n="10" />the next <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> expedition, Commissions are given out by the <em><reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg></em> for the raising of Horse and Foot to recruit his Army.</p>

<p>Here is great talk of a <reg orig="Mariage">Marriage</reg>, between the King of <em>France</em>, and the daughter of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, which we hear he doth promise to give in Marriage a very great sum of Crasados, for her <reg orig="doury">dowry</reg>. It is generally thought here that this alliance may take effect, in regard of the alliance they have together, and that the first stands in need of <reg orig="mony">money</reg> and Ships, and the second of friends and honour.</p>

<p>The great preparations which the Duke of Guise makes at the <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg> of the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em>, are in order to a second conquest of Naples, for which <reg orig="designe">design</reg> they have prepared and fitted a Fleet of Ships and <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> at <!--rep over line break-->at <em>Taulon</em> in <em>France</em>, under pretence to relieve <em>Catalonia</em>; But there is already order taken to frustrate and prevent his <reg orig="designe">design</reg> by a speedy supplying of that place with a strong party. The Earl of <em>Castrillo</em>, the new <reg orig="Vice Roy">Viceroy</reg>, was arrived at <em>Naples</em>, and the old was gone from thence for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, to give an account to his Majesty at <em>Madrid</em> of his Government of six years, that he hath been <reg orig="Vice Roy">Viceroy</reg>.</p>

<p>On Tuesday last my Lord <em>Fouines</em> was declared here by his Highness, Chief President of the privy Council of his Majesty, and my Lord <em>Rosa</em> excluded, being lately come from <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, there is great wondering at this change, the reasons hereof are not yet known.</p>

<p>The Chamber <em>imparty</em> now erected at <em>Malines</em> to judge and <reg orig="devide">divide</reg> the differences proceeding from the Treaty of peace between the King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> and the <em>United Provinces</em>, is now sat, and much expectation there is that speedy justice will be done on both sides, to the content of both parties.</p>

<head level="3">An <reg orig="Advertisment">Advertisement</reg>.</head>

<p><i>All persons who are <reg orig="Adventures">Adventurers</reg> for lands in <em>Ireland</em> are desired to take notice, That the Committee for <reg orig="Caims">Claims</reg> for <pb n="11" />lands in Thursday the 12 of <em>January</em> next coming to be a day of Lottery at <em><reg orig="Grocers-hall">Grocers'-hall</reg> London</em>, both for Provinces and Counties, and Thursday the 19 of the same <em>January</em> to be a Lottery for Counties for all such Adventurers who have made their choice in Provinces; and after the said 19 of <em>January</em> the said Committee intend to sit three mornings in a week, <em>viz.</em> <reg orig="Tuesdayes">Tuesdays</reg>, <reg orig="Thursdayes">Thursdays</reg> and <reg orig="Saturdayes">Saturdays</reg>, for preparing Certificates for such Adventurers as have, or shall by that time draw their <reg orig="Lotts">Lots</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Dover</em>, December 14.</i></head>

<p>We hear by one come this morning from <em>Deale</em>, that General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> and his squadron were safely arrived in the <em>Downs</em>. There are several Ships gone by this week bound for <em>London</em>; some from the <em>Canaries</em> laden with Wines, and one from <em>Malaga</em>, laden with fruit. There is a <em>Dutch</em> prize laden with Wines taken by a private man of war of <em>London</em>. The lading is all <reg orig="White-Wine">White Wine</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">From the <em>Hague</em>, December 19. <em>Stilo novo</em>.</head>

<p>We have little of news here since my last; the French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Monsr. de Chanut</em> hath as yet made no further <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Address unto the State, but privately he hath his visits, <unclear><!--??-->ana dlazes</unclear> abroad what great offers he hath to make from his Master; some say 10000. pistols by the month, besides the pay of divers Shipping, in case there be a final breach with <em>England</em>. Nothing is mentioned yet at all of taking in the interest of the <em><reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg></em> King, though his party here do cry it up as the great <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of the <em>French</em>, and say, that the old interest and intercourse will be revived between <em>France</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, that they may have a <reg orig="back-dore">back door</reg> <reg orig="againe">again</reg> to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the <em>English</em>, upon all occasions. They much slight the Prince of <em>Conde</em> at present, and say he will shortly be glad to <reg orig="imbrace">embrace</reg> any terms from his King; but they who are acquainted with his spirit, know he will stoop to a thousand deaths rather than live as a private man at home, of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg>. The <em>Spanish</em> power is not yet so low, as to let him sink, nor will he be without the hearts of <em>France</em>, as long <pb n="12" />as <reg orig="publick">public</reg> pressures and private discontent can blow up a party among that combustible generation: And therefore, as low as he seems now, he will be up again at <em>Spring</em>; and you may expect the <em>Archduke</em> will set him and <em>Loraine</em> both a work again in that <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>. Believe it, how serene soever the Court of <em>France</em> may seem now to be, and think of disturbing their neighbours; yet you will see the <em><reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg></em> <reg orig="designe">design</reg> upon <em>Naples</em> vanishing into Air, and that there will be little leisure to think either of <em>England</em> or <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>The People in these Lands say the Treaty hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> long in hand with <em>England</em>, that they fear nothing will come of it. It will be a difficult point to bring all the Statesmen here to agree about it, being all divided in Interest and opinion; some looking towards <em>France</em>, others toward <em>Spain</em>; <reg orig="som">some</reg> wedded to the <em>Orange</em>-party and <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and think to support themselves by lending a shoulder to that broken Family. Some few also there are who are good Patriots, and they but few, who know, <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg>, and desire an Union with <em>England</em> as the great Interest of their Country, but can do nothing, because <reg orig="over-powered">overpowered</reg> and <reg orig="out-numbered">outnumbered</reg> in all <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg>. The truth of things, and the offers made by <em>England</em> to incorporate both Commonweals into one, are kept from the <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> of the People, or else misrepresented to them, as if thereby <em>England</em> intended only to become Masters of themselves, their wealth and their Trade, and so the <em>Boutefeus</em> here do blast all belief of those Advantages that might come to the <em>United Provinces</em> by such an Incorporation; which would be a matter of so much consequence to Religion, and of terror to the Popish party, that <reg orig="its">it's</reg> no wonder if all the <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits</reg> in <em>Europe</em> (who are said to have a notable influence in the <em>Dutch</em> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>) employ all their Wits and Insinuations to hinder it. And therefore it is often beaten into the ears of the great one here a <em>Coalition</em> (as the term is) with <em>England</em>, would soon take down the dignities of these <em>Hoghen Moghens</em>; so that rather than part with their High and Mighty <pb n="13" />Titles, they seem more ready to sacrifice <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> true Religion, and the Interest of the poor People here, as the price of their ambition. It will and must be said so, and the People will at length understand it, if their Lords do neglect those great Advantages, which you in <em>England</em> have <reg orig="offer'd">offered</reg> them by this Treaty. Which God bring to a good issue, if not yet concluded.</p>

<p>What to think of it here, we cannot tell; for, great Preparations are going on here still. Much rejoicing here is at the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, and much Talk about them. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> said that some Supplies of Arms and Ammunition have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> let go from hence, or that they shall go. If true, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> no good sign; nor can I tell what to think of the great preparations in hand in this Country against Spring, no less than 30 new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> now laid on the Stocks to be added to the former 30 already built. The whole Navy of old and new together, will be (they say) above 100 sail: besides, they will <reg orig="labor">labour</reg> to hold up their Reputation in the <em>Levant</em>, by Lording it that way this next Summer: for, young <em>Tromp</em> is to go out of hand with 12 men of War to the <!--Straits?--><em>Streights</em>, and they have their eyes every way, both at home and abroad, which activity portends more than ordinary Resolutions for Action.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Westminster, December 16.</i></head>

<p>The late Parliament having upon their dissolution delivered up the power which they received from his Excellency at their first sitting by a writing under their Hands and Seals: his Excellency thereupon called a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, and advised with other persons of Interest in the Nation, how this great <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of governing <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, with the Armies therein, and Navy at Sea, should be <reg orig="born">borne</reg>, and by whom; who after several <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> seeking of God, and advising therein, it was resolved that a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of godly able and discreet persons should be named, consisting of 21. And that his Excellency should be chosen <em>Lord Protector</em> of the three Nations. In pursuance hereof, several persons of eminency and worth, are already made choice of to be the said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, which are not fit to be mentioned in this time. And this day his Excellency <pb n="14" />came down to <em>Westminster</em>, and was installed <em>Lord Protector of the three Nations</em>, the manner whereof was thus.</p>

<p>His Excellency about one of the clock in the afternoon came from <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em> to <em>Westminster</em>, to the Chancery Court, attended by the Lords Commissioners of the great Seal of <em>England</em>, Barons of the Exchequer, and Judges in their Robes; after them, the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Commonwealth, and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg>, Aldermen, and Recorder of the City of <em>London</em>, in their Scarlet Gowns; then came his Excellency attended with many of the chief Officers of the Army, a chair of State being set in the said Court of Chancery, his Excellency stood on the left hand thereof uncovered, till a large writing in Parchment, in the nature of an Oath, was read; there being the power with which his Excellency was invested, and how his Excellency is to govern the three Nations, which his Excellency accepted of, and subscribed in the face of the Court, and immediately hereupon sat <reg orig="downe">down</reg> covered in the <reg orig="chaire">chair</reg>; the Lords Commissioners then delivered up the Great Seal of <em>England</em> to his Excellency, and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> his Sword and Cap of Maintenance, all which his Excellency returned immediately to them again: The Court then rose, and his Excellency was attended back as aforesaid, to the Banqueting House in <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>, the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> himself uncovered, carrying the Sword before the Protector all the way; and coming into the Banqueting-House, an exhortation was made by Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, after which the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg>, Aldermen, and Judges departed.</p>

<p>Thus far things have been communicated already in Print. To which may be added as touching the frame and constitution of the Government established, That we shall have <em>Triennial</em> Parliaments, and the first to begin on the third of <em>September</em> next, and so from three years to three years. That Parliaments shall be chosen by the People, according to certain Qualifications set down in the said Parchment; That the time of their sitting shall be for five <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: That such Laws as shall be agreed on in Parliament shall be presented to the <em>Lord Protector</em> for his assent; which if it be not obtained within 20 days, then those Bills shall pass notwithstanding, and become Laws in <reg orig="ful">full</reg> force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>. Strict provision is made also for the succession of Parliaments, the management of Elections, and of Returns to be made by the several Sheriffs of the persons elected. That the <em>Lord Protector</em> shall govern with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, the number of which shall not be less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 13. and not exceed 21. This is the form of government in general, particulars having <reg orig="slipt">slipped</reg> my memory. Only thus much farther; That all Writs, Processes, &amp;c. shall issue forth in the name of the <em>Lord Protector</em>; That Articles of War shall be made good; That the Ministry of the Gospel shall be maintained, and the present way of their maintenance continued, till some other way more convenient <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> found out and provided. These are some few passages set down so near as I can remember, since the day that they were read in <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Many other particulars there are of great importance, which you may hear of in due time.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<head level="3"><i>December 19.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Excellencie">Excellency</reg> the <em>Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg></em> was proclaimed Lord Protector by sound of Trumpet in the <em>Palace yard Westminster</em>, and at the <em>Old Exchange</em>: Divers of the Council, and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> and Court of Aldermen in their robes, together with the three Serjeants at Arms with their Maces, and the Heralds in their Ornaments, attending.</p>

<p>The tenor of the Proclamation was as followeth:</p>

<head level="3">BY THE COUNCIL.</head>

<p><go>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, the Government of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, by a LORD PROTECTOR, and successive Triennial Parliaments, is now established; And whereas <em>OLIVER CROMWELL</em> Captain-<reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of all the Forces of the Commonwealth is declared LORD PROTECTOR of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it <unclear>necessary</unclear> (as we hereby do) to make publication of the <reg orig="Premisses">Premises</reg>, and <unclear>strictly</unclear> to charge and commend all and every person and persons of what quality and condition soever in any of the said three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, <unclear><reg orig="Majors">Mayors</reg></unclear>, Bailiffs, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers and Officers whom this may concern, are required to cause this <unclear>PROCLAMATION</unclear> to be forthwith published in their respective Counties, Cities, Corporations, and Market-Towns, to the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</go></p>

<p>Given at <em>Whitehall</em> this sixteenth day of <em>December</em>, 1653</p>

<p>The names of the persons already <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in the Council of his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, are these following:</p>

<p>Lord <em>Lambert</em>, Lord Viscount <unclear><em>Lasle</em></unclear>, General <em>Disbrow</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Major Gen. <em>Skippon</em> Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>, <em>Walter Strickland</em> Esq. <em>Lawrence</em> Esq. Col. <em>Edward Montague</em>, Col. <em>William Sydenham</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> The Highlanders have of late <reg orig="bin">been</reg> making their <reg orig="Levys">Levies</reg>, &amp; have had their design to raise Levies in most Counties. Col. Morgan met with 60 of the enemy very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in raising forces; but he <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg> them before they had made any considerable progress, took17, and pursued the rest to a house, where he surrounded them, and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> force them to a sudden surrender. Cap. Lisle, of Col. Rich's Regiment, met with a party making Levies in the County of Angus, whom he defeated, with 2 Captains, and took 50 prisoners. The Lowlanders are apt to receive them; and by stealth send them horses, and other necessaries.</p>

<p>There is no news this week from Sea, save that General Monk is out at Sea, riding with about 40 sail, in the Channel, near St. Ellens. No farther news from France, the Governor of Calais having <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> the Packet-Boat at that Town.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>