<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol190">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 190</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, January 26. to <em>Thursday</em>, February 1. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, December 3.</i></head>

<p>Since the Engagement of our party at <em>Drummond</em>, we have had little of news. We <reg orig="can not">cannot</reg> yet hear what loss of men was on the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> part, nor who the persons were that were slain. Only one Cap. <em>Ker</em> and another person of quality, who they said was the second brave man they had in Arms; but they had very many wounded.</p>

<p>The main Body of the Enemy continues still in <em>Murray</em> land, between <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg></em>. A party of 300 Foot under one Lieut. Col <em>Henles</em> of <em>Newark</em>, and 100 Horse commanded by one <pb n="1" /><em>Inchinrole</em>, came lately into <em>Dumbarton town</em>, <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg>  an hour, and went thence. At the last going away of the <em>Highland</em> Scots before this, the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> was posted on the Market-cross, with these expressions in it, <em>Our ancient old Enemy the kingdom of England</em>: so that you see by this, it is a National quarrel, and not for the <em>Stuarts</em>. Herein our enemies <reg orig="shew">showed</reg> the bottom of their design is, to destroy the <em>English</em>; and it is a sweet invitation for the <em>English</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. If their plots be laid no deeper, we suppose they will not be able much to hurt us.</p>

<p>We hear that Col. <em>Humphrey's</em> gallant Troop of Dragoons, are upon the Borders, and some other coming to reinforce us, which is welcome news; and now we shall be able at all turns to meet with the Enemy</p>

<head level="3">A Proclamation</head>

<head level="3"><i>William <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg>of Glencairn, Lord <em>Kilmares</em>, Commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the kingdom of Scotland.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and the advancement of our ancient old enemy, the Kingdom of <em>England</em>, who by their perfidious practice, and all unlawful means, still pretending the good and advancement of the Protestant Religion, has endeavoured the reducement and enslaving of us, our predecessors and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, to their subjection. Many pretended Countrymen of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> qualities within the shires of <em>Dumbarton, Aire, Renfrew</em>, and other adjacent places on the South side of <em>Forth</em>, are <pb n="2" /> not ashamed to bring in, sell and deliver to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Officers of Garrisons belonging to the said grand enemy, the whole serviceable Arms, and other offensive weapons, they either have, or possibly can acquire, whereby his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Levies in most parts of the said shires, are greatly impeded, far contrary to our <reg orig="naturall">natural</reg> <reg orig="Countreymen">Countrymen</reg>, inhabiting the Northern shires, who by their good example laying to heart the bleeding condition of this their native <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> all unanimously take up Arms and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with us for relief and recovery therof: We do therefore by these presents <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> and declare, that whatsoever person or persons, of whatever quality, within said shires of <em>Dumbarton, Aire, Renfrew</em>, or places adjacent, shall upon whatsoever pretence, after the publication hereof, presume to sell, deliver, or give up to any belonging to the said common enemy, any serviceable Horses or Arms, to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service or levies of Horse or Foot, <unclear><reg orig="imployed">employed</reg></unclear> upon any of them, that the whole good and <reg orig="geir">gear</reg> of the person or persons disobeyers of this our command (without respect of any) shall be sequestrate and confiscate for the use of any whatsoever can <unclear>first</unclear> apprehend them; for <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with, and effectuating whereof, these Presents shall be an irreducible Warrant, and ordains publication hereof at the Market-cross of <em>Dumbarton</em>, whereby they, nor none inhabiting the shires of <em>Aire, Renfrew</em> or places adjacent, <unclear>pretend</unclear> ignorance hereof. Given at <unclear><em>Weims</em></unclear> this 22 of <em>December</em> 1653. <em>Sic subseribitur,</em> <unclear>Glencairn</unclear></p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><em>From</em> Upsal <em>Decem.</em> 30. 1653.</head>

<p>Things at present look with a good face as if we should enter into a strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> with this Nation. The Queen is highly civil and courteous in her reception of my Lord Ambassador. On the 23 instant his Lordship had his <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Audience, and since that time he hath had two private Audiences, whereat he gave in the articles to Treat upon as a firm Union. The Queen receives all the overtures <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, none of the Senators being present. We hope there will be a good and speedy account given of this affair. A <em><reg orig="Muscovie">Muscovy</reg></em> Envoy is arrived here, whose business is said to be nothing else but to acquaint the Queen with his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> full resolution to make war with the King of <em>Poland.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Copenhagen Jan.</i>14. 1653.</head>

<p>Since my last no news here, but that the Dutch Fleet which then I told you were beaten in here again by some English <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> are resolved to winter here. This City had suffered much by a late fire, had not this King and Court <reg orig="bestired">bestirred</reg> themselves to quench it, which <reg orig="onely">only</reg> consumed two or three houses. We <reg orig="here">hear</reg> every day of the Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> great respect to the English ambassador, which increaseth our fears and jealousies, and now we seem more afraid than ever, that the Dutch will leave us in the <reg orig="bryers">briars</reg>, but the best of it is, we have not much wool to lose.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Dantzik">Danzig</reg></em> Jan.</i>14 S.N.</head>

<p>Some days ago news came to this City by an Express out of <em>Poland</em>, that between the King, <pb n="4" />Tartars and Cossacks a firm Peace and union was concluded; which news is confirmed by the ordinary Post, and thereby advised that the said Peace was made by the Lord Palatine of Russia, Castel Sendemer Grand <reg orig="Marishall">Marshall</reg>, and Grand Chancellor, with the great <reg orig="Visier">Vizier</reg>, and Cham the Tartars having engaged themselves to assist the Crown with all their power and strength, <reg orig="whensoever">whenever</reg> they shall have need of them.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, January</i> 17.</head>

<p>It is this day reported here, by Letters from Rotterdam, that the Deputies were <reg orig="com">come</reg> on there with the Articles of Peace, which the States had signed; which is rather desired than believed; also that the english Fleet had lately taken above 20 Sail of Dutch Merchants, which is neither desired, nor believed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, February</i> 4.</head>

<p>The last week Mr Arnolphini being many years since invested in the office of Master of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Horse, began in this quality, to teach his Majesty to ride the great Horse in the Court of the little Bourbon; where he presently <reg orig="shew">showed</reg> in his carriage, how in all exercises both of Body and Mind, that he is truly born with dispositions necessary for the obtaining without trouble all that will serve of Ornament suitable to a great Monarch. Here is a Report that this Court hath sent to propound to the Duke of Orleans the Marriage of the King with the eldest Daughter of the first Bed of his said Highness. Here is also a Report, but how true it is I cannot affirm, That the Citizens and Inhabitants of Bordeaux are up in Arms <pb n="5" />again, and have <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> the building of the Castle of <em><unclear>Tromposte</unclear></em> and intend not to lay down their arms till the Agreement be made good unto them.</p>

<p>His Majesty hath been for 2 or 3 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> taking his pleasure with the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> at <em>St Germains</em>, where they recreated themselves with the hunting of the <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> <reg orig="Boare">Boar</reg>.</p>

<p>The Parliament here hath at last agreed to the New Import to be laid upon every Tonne of Wine, by the order of the King.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em><unclear>Longueville</unclear></em> and the Prince of <em><unclear>Coute</unclear></em> are both expected here in Town.</p>

<p>All honest men here are overjoyed at the Peace between the two <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>. </p>

<p>Here is news the siege in <em>Alsace</em> is already so far advanced, that in a short time the <unclear>besieged</unclear> will be brought to <unclear>extremity</unclear> and forced to <unclear>yield</unclear> upon terms.</p>

<head level="3"><i>His Excellency the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> speech to the Queen of Sweden</i></head>

<p><em>Madam</em>. By command from my Superiors, the Parliament of this Commonwealth of England, I <unclear>do with</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 15 characters at least 2 words--></unclear> your Majesty, which had <unclear><!--approx.25 characters, unknown number of words--></unclear> <unclear>ordinary</unclear> accidents and <unclear><reg orig="engagments">engagements</reg> in the</unclear> <unclear><!--half a line--></unclear> with no few <unclear><!--most of a line--></unclear> although the <unclear>Commonwealth are not</unclear> <unclear><!--approx 20 characters--></unclear> when they reflect upon <unclear><!--approx. half a line--></unclear> in some places; yet you <unclear><!--8 characters--></unclear> Government, neither <unclear><!--approx.33 characters--></unclear> suspicion of any such entertainment: <unclear>but we who are here </unclear> present do gratefully acknowledge our experience of <unclear>the contrary</unclear>, and of much Civility to our Nation.</p>

<p>My business is to communicate with your Majesty in matters relating to the common good, which is of so great weight that it admits of no hopes of success without the special blessing, who by small means can bring great things to pass; the confidence whereof, with my <unclear>submits</unclear> to the judgement and commands of my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg> hath given me this honour of being in your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence.</p>

<p>Whom, I shall not weary with many words or expressions beyond meaning; I am <unclear>not</unclear> sent for that cause, and it is as different from my <reg orig="owne">own</reg> spirit, as contrary to the practice and commands of my <reg orig="superiours">superiors</reg>, from whom, and from their servant, according to the English reality, your Majesty will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> all manner of plainness and truth in our transactions, our deliverances and preservations, whereof we have been eye-witnesses, have been <pb n="6" />so near to miracles, and such monuments of infinite rich mercy and love from heaven, that we should sin against him, if the least guile or unfaithfulness should infect our conversation.</p>

<p>It is not my work to paint out my <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, or to draw lines upon any, though our adversaries; neither shall I take upon me to mention the excellencies of your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> person and government, of your People, and <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>, lest I should injure any merit; and because I speak to those whom God hath favoured with the enjoyment of great mercies, the increase and continuance whereof is heartily desired by my <reg orig="superiours">superiors</reg>, and by me their servant.</p>

<p>I shall not <reg orig="inlarge">enlarge</reg> my discourse with observations, concerning both Nations, of their likeness in Language, Manners, and warlike dispositions, Arguments more natural than artificial for a nearer union; but this I may not omit, the fruits whereof I have tasted the present happy Government under your Majesty, which remembers unto us those blessed <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of our Virgin Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, under whom above 40 years the people enjoyed all protection and justice from their Prince, and she obedience and affection from her people.</p>

<p><em>May</em> this and more be the portion of your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> and your Successors, nor had it been lost in those who followed Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, though <reg orig="Forainers">Foreigners</reg>, but through the extremity of their own ill government.</p>

<p>When attempts were made to ravish from us our highest interest, the orthodox Religion and just Liberty, the defence whereof undertaken by King <em>Gustavus Adolphus</em>, your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> father of blessed memory, in his <em>German</em> Expedition, for the <reg orig="Protestants">Protestants'</reg> relief, was in him most <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> and successful, and surely for us was most just and necessary, and alike crowned with gracious success by the Almighty.</p>

<p>For the extirpation of both which by force, which had long been endeavoured, otherwise <em>Auxiliaries</em> were provided, and afterwards a war raised, which first appearing in <em>Scotland</em>; but there diligently resisted, and the <em>English</em> <unclear>refusing</unclear> to be <unclear><reg orig="instrumentall">instrumental</reg></unclear> against <em>Scotland</em> for those ends, the storm was then blown over.</p>

<p>In <em>Ireland</em> it rose so hideously, that 200000 poor Creatures, Men, Women, and Children, besides what the War devoured, were in cold blood barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> for no other reason but because they were Protestants, and Commission <reg orig="alleadged">alleged</reg> for it.</p>

<p>In <em>England</em> the fire <reg orig="brakeout">breakout</reg> in all parts of it, from one corner of the Land to the other, not a place, not a family free from the <pb n="7" />rage of our <reg orig="decenniall">decennial</reg>. More <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, and yet after so much blood poured forth, we bless God we live, and after so many distractions, a stranger passing through our <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, can hardly espy the steps of it, our God hath given us <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and all the adjacent isles and Territories of the Commonwealth, a full and happy peace.</p>

<p>In all appeals to him, whereof we have seen many, he was pleased still to determine for the Parliament; and after these, and eight Tenders and Treaties of peace, wherein we received the <reg orig="deniall">denial</reg> from our Adversaries, it pleased the gracious and all-disposing hand of God for the good of <em>England</em>, to change the Government thereof.</p>

<p>Nevertheless the same common interest, which first begat former <reg orig="allyances">alliances</reg> and confederacy between the two Nations, do still continue and oblige both to desire the good of each other.</p>

<p>Whereunto they seem the more engaged, because we cannot find that in any age there hath been a declared War between them, but a constant intercourse of friendship and amity, with <reg orig="mutuall">mutual</reg> Offices of kindness, out of which great profit and happiness hath redounded unto both.</p>

<p>These things being considered, with the affairs of <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>, and especially of the neighbouring Princes and States, through Divine providence in such posture and condition, as to give greater opportunity, and lay stronger Obligations upon both Nations, to entertain a <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> union and correspondence <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore, whereby the commerce and tranquillity of both may be preserved and provided for, with respect also to the common interest and concernment of the true Protestant Religion: And your Majesty having by your late <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers to <em>England</em>, signified your <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> inclination and willingness by all good means to conserve and increase the ancient good understanding between these States. Upon these and other weighty considerations, and to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how acceptable the former overtures of your Majesty have been, the Parliament have thought fit by me to make tender unto your Majesty of the friendship of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and to let you know, that they are not only ready to renew and preserve inviolably that amity and good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> which hath hitherto been between the two Nations, but are further willing to enter into a more strict <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> and Union (<reg orig="then">than</reg> hath yet been) for the good of both.</p>

<p>And in such a way as shall be held requisite, I shall be ready more particularly to communicate what I have in charge to this purpose. Thus far the Speech.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, February 1.</i></head>

<p>The Earl of <em>Bassignee, and the Abbot of Mercy</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> remain still Prisoners in the Castle of <em>Antwerp</em>, where they are continually examined and confronted. It seems the last of these two hath accused the first <pb n="8" />of a crime, which he cannot <reg orig="verifie">verify</reg> and make good against him, so that he will have enough to do to rid himself out of the trouble he hath wilfully drawn upon himself without running the hazard of indignation and correction. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the little war in the Country of Liege doth increase from time to time; the Emperor and the Princes Electors will be of the party, so that the said <reg orig="smal">small</reg> country may become the seat of war, which may soon spread into the adjacent countries, who do already begin to fear the ill consequences that may arise from thence. The Pope, who is here <reg orig="stiled">styled</reg> the common Father of all Christians, doth begin now to use his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to persuade all <reg orig="Soveraigns">Sovereigns</reg> to a general peace. The Archduke Leopold hath commanded all the governors of the Garrisons under his command, not to absent themselves from their commands, but to cause strict guards to be continually kept, that so they may be in a readiness to defend themselves, in case the enemy should have any <reg orig="designe">design</reg> in hand for the surprisal of any one place.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rotterdam the first of <em>February</em>.</i></head>

<p>Our country here is full of joy for the peace which we conceive will now be certainly concluded with your Commonwealth, since we hear that the Lord Beverning is sent into England with the ratification of the Province of Holland, in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> that the rest of the Provinces are to meet to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same likewise, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be March first as our <reg orig="Occurences">Occurrences</reg> tells us before they can all get together. We are no less overjoyed <pb n="9" />to hear that the Treaty is so handsomely decided as they say it is, to the great <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> of our Provinces and the reputation of our Commissioners and to the good liking and <unclear>content of</unclear> the States General, who are met at the <unclear>Hague</unclear> about it, to come to a final conclusion. But yet there are many honest and faithful Patrons amongst us that are of opinion it were better to prosecute the war with <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> against England, and that the labour and the success we should have had would in the end have been more <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> and profitable, <reg orig="then">than</reg> what we can expect from this <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg> of peace</p> 

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal <em>Decemb. 30.</em></i></head>

<p>Our negotiations here make their progress with a very handsome and <reg orig="desireable">desirable</reg> appearance, and I hope there will be a very good account and a speedy one given of these transactions for the advantage of our Nation. There is a fair and promising aspect and conjunction of persons, things and circumstances, and if the mysteries of State do not <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> too deep, nor be beyond measures variable, We are verily persuaded that we shall have a dispatch very <reg orig="sudainly">suddenly</reg> to our high contentment; but these things are uncertain, I <reg orig="onely">only</reg> tell you thus much that as yet we are in a very fair way, and probability, and the Queen and Court seem very inclinable, and are in good posture to answer our present overtures. On the 25 instant, -My Lord Ambassador had his <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Audience which was performed to him with <reg orig="al">all</reg> demonstrations of civility and <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, since which he hath had two private Audiences, and hath given in the Articles whereon to treat in order to a stricter alliance.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<p>The Queen <reg orig="receivs">receives</reg> all his overtures alone by her self, there being nine of her Senators or <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> present; she seems to resent things well, and to have a good understanding of the affairs of or Commonwealth, and she hath not stuck to <unclear>say</unclear>, That she never received so much satisfaction in any Ambassador, as in this from <em>England</em>. My Lord will be very quick in his <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg>, and will put things to the <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> with all speed and <reg orig="dillegence">diligence</reg>. I hope we shall be able shortly to inform you more fully of all these transactions.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Upsall</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, Decem. 30.</head>

<p>I have here sent you an account of all that hath passed since my last, both before and since the audience of my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> in the presence of her Majesty of <em>Sweden</em></p>

<p>On Thursday the 22 instant, his Excellency had notice by my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em>, that the Queen would give him audience on the 23. after noon. And at the appointed day, about an hour after dinner, came two Senators to my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> lodging, with 6 of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Coaches, to conduct him to his audience. His Excellency met them at the <reg orig="dore">door</reg>, and according to the course, gave them precedence to his bed-chamber, where they told his Excellency that they were commanded by the Queen to conduct his Excellency to his Audience, and they did believe the Queen was ready to receive his Excellency. By this time it was dark, but the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg> had Torches lighted. All his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> company went with him, whose clothes were rich and comely, and their persons answerable: His Excellency <pb n="11" />himself was in a plain black Cloth suit, lined with the same. The Gents of the first degree were all very rich in their <reg orig="cloathes">clothes</reg> of <em>English</em> cloth, handsomely trimmed. Those of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Bedchamber were likewise richly <reg orig="cloathed">clothed</reg>: The Gent' Attendants also handsomely and well habited, and his Pages and <reg orig="Laqueys">Lackeys</reg> came after in their Liveries. In this Equipage his Excellency went to the Court; At the first Gate we passed through a lane of <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> of the <reg orig="Qu:">Queen's</reg> Guard. After we were alighted out of our Coaches, the Ryx-Marshall of <em>Sweden</em>, with the <reg orig="Marshalls">Marshall's</reg> <reg orig="staffe">staff</reg> in his hand, met us at the foot of the stairs, they call him Count <em>Oxenstern</em>, son to the Ryx <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> and kinsman to the Ryx Chancellor of <em>Sweden</em>. The Gent. attendants went first, then those of his Excel. Chamber: Next the Gent. Of the first degree in their order, his Exc. two sons next, after them the Master of the Ceremonies; next him the two Senators, then the Ryx Marshall and his Excellency; after them his Exc. Pages and <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg>; the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Pages and <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg> on each side of his Exc. with torches. We went up many stairs to a large Hall, many people in the way. From thence they led us to the great chamber where Prince <em>Adolph</em> the Grand Master met his Exc. which it is said he had not done to any Ambassador. He gave his Exc. the right hand, and some complements passed between them: His Exc. thanking him for his Letters, and for his accommodations in his journey, especially in the places of his government. He told his Exc. the Queen had <pb n="12" /><i>commanded her Officers to take care for his accommodation, which he doubted were not such as were fit, and desired Excellency to excuse his ill treatment.</i></p>

<p><i>In the next Chamber beyond this was a Guard of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, with Coats richly Embroidered with Gold. In the next Room was the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, three or four Ladies, and abundance of Lords Gentlemen of her Court. All his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Gentlemen were admitted into that Room, and made a lane for his Excellency to pass: As soon as his Excellency came into the Room, and put off his hat, the Queen came two or three steps before her Chair. It was not <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to know her to be the Queen, her habit being of plain Grey <reg orig="Stuffe">Stuff</reg>, and made after this manner, a Coat down to the ground, and over that a close Jacket that came almost to her knees, buttoned down with great buttons, with a black Scarf about her neck, tied with a little black <reg orig="Ribbond">Ribbon</reg> after his Excellency had passed his Ceremony, he put on his hat, and called to his Secretary for his Credential Letters, which he presented to her Majesty, and afterwards spake to her, and Mr. <em>De la March</em> interpreted into French every sentence his Excellency spake, which his Excellency was advised to do, as the constant practice of that Court. She was very attentive whilst his Excellency spake, and by her looks and gestures very near him, seemed often to endeavour to have daunted him: but those that have been used in Affairs of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, are not so soon put out of countenance, as some other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers have been by her Majesty.</i></p>

<p><i>After his Excellency had done, she answered him presently in the Swedish Language, which my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em> interpreted in <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, to this effect, That <reg orig="shee">she</reg> esteemed it a very great honour that the Parliament had been pleased to send an Ambassador to her, especially a person of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> condition, and that she herself would take care during his abode here, that not the least injury should be offered either to him or his Company; and that she hoped in her Government there should be no cause or doubt of the contrary; That as his person was very acceptable to her, <unclear>so was</unclear> the business which he had imparted in <pb n="13" />the Transaction whereof she should manifest the affection she bore to the Commonwealth, and her desire not only to renew former <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between them, but to enter into a nearer union <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore; That she was glad of these blessings which the Commonwealth had received in their peace and Settlement; and <reg orig="wisht">wished</reg> the continuance <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg> to them. She thanked his Excellency for his civilities to her, and for his acceptance of such entertainment as this place would afford, and that she was sorry it was not answerable to his quality, and to the respect she bore to the Commonwealth whom he served; but desired he would take it in good part, and told his Excellency he was very <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> to her Court. After she had done his Excellency spake to her Majesty in French, That there two of his sons, and other Gentlemen in his company, that much desired the honour of kissing her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> hand, if she pleased to permit it; which she readily did to those whom his Excellency appointed, which were 8. After that Ceremony passed, the Queen spake to his Excellency in French, desiring him to excuse the ill Treatment by the way in his journey, those places far off not being furnished for entertaining such a person as his Excellency was, and so attended. She was likewise sorry that this place would not afford such accommodations as were fit for his Excellency, and <reg orig="wisht">wished</reg> she might have entertained him at <em>Stockholm</em>, where it would have been better. His Excellency answered, that he was sorry for the occasion of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> remove from that place, and that he had received many favours both in his journey, and here by her command for which he returned thanks to her Majesty, and would acquaint the Parliament therewith. She then excused her habit saying she had been ill, which caused her to put <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> into the dress of her Chamber, in which she chose to appear thus <reg orig="publiquely">publicly</reg>, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to disappoint his Excellency of audience; and that she hoped they should have time and opportunity enough to discourse together. His Excellency then took his leave of her Majesty, who was very civil and courteous to him, and to all his Company.</i></p>

<pb n="14" />

<p>His Excellency was brought back to his lodging with <unclear><!--14 characters, three words--></unclear> as he went to Court. The Ryx-Marshall and the two Senators supped with his Excellency, it being the <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> for such to be at the last meal that Ambassadors are entertained at by the Queen. At supper those Senators told his Excellency it was their manner in this Country for them to begin a health to the Superiors of the Ambassador and to himself, but they understanding that it was against his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> principles, either to pledge or begin any health, they did therefore forbear, and not out of any disrespect, either to his superiors of himself.</p>

<p>The next day in the morning being Saturday, his Excellency sent to visit the Spanish Resident, who had sent twice to him before, and also to his Coach to accompany him into Town. On the afternoon he came himself to visit his Excellency, and made many Protestations of his readiness to serve the Commonwealth of England, to whom he knew his Master did bear a great respect.</p>

<p>On Monday the twenty sixth afternoon my Lord had private audience, for above two hours, with the queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, no person else with them.</p>

<p>ON the twenty ninth his Excellency was admitted again to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence, with whom he was alone <reg orig="neer">near</reg> three hours together. It was his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> wonder, to hear a Lady discourse so of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg>, and of the interested of all the States and Princes of Christendom, with such knowledge and judgement as she did.</p>

<p>His Excellency hath been visited by both the Spanish and French Agents, and by the Ryx-Hoffmaster of Denmark, by the Ryx-Marshall of Sweden, by Count Tole, Monsieur Vanderlaine, and Master Bond Senators, Count Tott, and Monsieur Banniere. Some of their visits his Excellency hath already required.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dalkeith</em>, Jan. 23.</head>

<p> The 19. instant, Col. <em>Daniel</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. <em>Johnstons</em> having intelligence that the Enemy were in or about <em>Dunkel</em>, sent out 100 Horse and 100 Dragoons under the command of Capt. Lievt. <em>Ashly</em> of Col. <em><reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg></em> Regiment, who came very <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Town undiscovered, and the Forlorn fell in with two of their Scouts, they made some resistance at the Barracdo, but our few Dragoons beat them thence, entered the Town, and <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> 6 or 7 at the entrance: Our Forlorn went in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> to the other end of the Town, and <reg orig="persued">pursued</reg> them that (upon the <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg>) got away towards the hills and passages betwixt the Town and <em>Blaire</em>, and there were seven of them <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>; many had the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> mark and most of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Troopers made Footmen; they brought 50 horses with them, and 7 prisoners of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Regiment, also many <reg orig="Carabins">Carbines</reg>, Cloaks, Boots, and other things belonging to them; and had they not escaped to the woods and crags which are at the very <pb n="15" /><reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg> end, there had been more in our custody. <em>Athol</em> was there himself, and I believe this will be a great obstruction to his levies: he has about 100 or 150 Foot with him, most of whom got to the hills. The Horse pursued them above two miles beyond the Town, and wounded many: but being very eager in the pursuit, and the woods within 1 or 3 yards of the very passage, they had no more to do, but being <reg orig="knockt">knocked</reg> off their horses to run into the Thickets, and then they were safe. It was a very seasonable mercy both to balance their height upon the business of <em>Drummond</em>, and also to lay a discouragement upon the temper of that wild people. There was one of Col. <em><reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg></em> own Troop <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>. Some of the prisoners confess that <em>Wogan</em> was run through the shoulder at <em>Drummond</em>, and lies at <em>Weims</em>. Captain <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> Lieutenant and Captain <em>Ker</em> did kill each other, both of them at one instant firing together at 4 yards distance with both their Blunderbusses, and fell from their horses immediately.</p>

<p><i>The <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> head-quarters are now in Elgan, their General <em>Glencarn</em> with about 1200 Foot and 300 Horse, besides Dragoons. They have beleaguered <em>Burgiei</em> which is a Garrison of ours. <em>Kenmore</em> is at Forres, and keeps his Guards upon the River Findern, to secure the passage from <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>. The 10 instant Col. <em>Morgan</em> was marching towards them 14 Companies of Foot and 8 Troops of Horse and Dragoons. This day there are nine Prisoners sent in from Capt. <em>Hart</em>, <reg orig="divers">diverse</reg> of them are Englishmen who were in the Engagement with <em>Forbes</em>, and one <em>Richardson</em> a Moss Trooper.</i></p>

<p> No news from the Sea, save that the Fleet continues in its former station.</p>

<p>Some <reg orig="Free booters">Freebooters</reg> have been <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg>, and brought into Newcastle</p>

<p>The Heer Beverning; one of the late Dutch Deputies in treaty, is returned hither again. It is said, that the Province of Holland is well satisfied with the terms agreed on, and that others will shortly appear here, <reg orig="in">on</reg> the behalf of the Provinces. A little time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg> in the event.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">There is lately published a most excellent Treatise entitled</head> 
<p>&#x261e; A <reg orig="REJOYNDER">REJOINDER</reg>  to Mr. <em>Drake</em>, or a Reply to his Book, Entitled. <em>A Boundary to the Holy Mount: By John Humphrey</em>, Master of Arts. Printed for <em>E. Blackmore</em> at the Angel in S. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>