<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol188">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 188</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> January 12. to <em>Thursday</em> January 19. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>By the last from Scotland, January 7.</i></head>

<p>Part of the Army is at <em>Glasgow</em>, seeing to the safety of those parts, where they are in good condition. Intelligence from that place faith, That notice was given where Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> (he that was lately routed with his Party) lay at a small Cottage, sore of his wounds that he had received. A party of <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> was sent thereupon to <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> him; but he quitted that place about 2 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> before, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> are so false to us, that they will give no direction which way to follow upon any such occasion</p>

<p>Those Scots that will not rise with the <em>Highlanders</em> are <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> by them; the Highlanders lay Contributions upon them, which bring them very low, because they pay likewise toward the maintenance of our English Army. We hear of Supplies coming out of <em>England</em>, as the <pb n="1" />Regiments if Horse belonging to Major General <em>Lambert</em>, and Commissary-gen. <em>Whalley</em> and the Regiment of Foot belonging to Sir <em>William Constable</em>, they being already on their march; by whose assistance we doubt not but to send this <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> Crew back again to the Highlands, where they will not be able to subsist in a Body, all their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> being upon <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and his endeavours with the Dutch for money and Arms.</p>

<p>But if a Peace be with Holland (as we hear it is in a faint way) the first news of it will quite take away their hearts, and make them of their own accord retire to their several Habitations, without ever drawing of a Sword against them. So great a destruction hath already been brought upon <em>Scotland</em> by these Robbers, that a few months longer continuance of spoil and disorder, would bring them into the same condition with the Irish, who have been by <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg> forced to eat the Corpses of their deceased Friends, after divers <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> interment. And yet these are not much to be pitied by us, because of their implacable enmity, who will rather suffer themselves to be undone by the Enemy, rather than give notice to our Garrisons, when any of the Highlanders come amongst them, or pass through their Country; accounting and calling it Treachery to be any way <reg orig="instrumentall">instrumental</reg> in the surprising of those that would destroy them. There is a Talk among them, as if the Highlanders had some Arms and Ammunition landed in the Northern parts.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Madrid</em> of the 16 of December, 1653. Their Majesties are here in perfect health: Two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hence they go again to <em>Escurial</em>, to be present at some Church service performed yearly in commemoration of the deceased Princes belonging to the House of <em>Austria</em>. There is to be seen in this City a copy of a Letter in Print sent from the Jesuits in <em>Armenia</em> to those in this City; wherein they express a very strange thing <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which is thus briefly; There being about Five months since many Turks and <reg orig="Moores">Moors</reg> met together at a <pb n="2" />Town called <em>Medinatalvi</em>, (but commonly known by the name of <em>Mecha</em>) in the <reg orig="Mosquee">Mosque</reg> or <reg orig="Chappell">Chapel</reg> where the body of their false Prophet hath lain many Years. On a sudden, about Ten of the clock in the forenoon, this Iron Chest (which for many years hath been suspended in the roof of that house, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Loadstone fastened there) did fall to the ground, which immediately opened and swallowed up both the Chest, and what was therein; the ground remaining open about one quarter of an hour, and in that space came forth of that Abyss a great flame, and smoke, which rendered a great stench, and so the Spectators fell on the ground, being struck with deadly fear at so <reg orig="dreadfull">dreadful</reg> a spectacle, and some of them are since become Christians, leaving their superstitious service.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement from the Lieutenant of the Tower.</i></head>

<p>At the desire of the Earl of <em>Cleveland</em> now Prisoner in the Tower, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby give notice to all persons <reg orig="allyed">allied</reg> in Blood or Acquaintance to the said Earl. That his Lordship hath lately been informed of a certain Impostor or Cheat, who under the cloak of Friendship and pretence of serving his Lordship, hath made very unworthy Addresses to divers persons of quality in the said <reg orig="Earls">Earl's</reg> behalf to borrow Money for his Relief, and to supply his occasions in the Tower; and hath counterfeited the said <reg orig="Earls">Earl's</reg> Hand and Seal for such <reg orig="leud">lewd</reg> purposes: And because a Vizard is proper for such Practitioners, he goeth sometimes under the mane of <em>Buck</em>, sometimes <em>Braithwaight</em>, and <em>Butler</em>; and that he hath by this means obtained <reg orig="severall">several</reg> sums of money from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Persons who are deluded by this knavery, and although the <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> (at the desire of the said Earl<unclear>)</unclear> hath granted many Warrants for the apprehending of this person, yet it hath hitherto been his Fortune to escape.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>The Earl of <em>Cleveland</em> desires this may be <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> known, that this <reg orig="Villains">Villain's</reg> proceedings may be prevented for the future, and also that it may be believed, that when the said Earl hath any occasion to use money, it hath been his custom <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> to use such honourable means of procurements as are suitable with his degree and honour.</p>

<p>The like abuse hath been offered by the same person to the Lord <em>Grandison</em> also, a prisoner in the Tower, which is likewise desired to be made known.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the Spanish General, from <em>Badaiocio</em> to a Portugal <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>.</i></head>

<p>This Messenger I send to know assuredly whether the Count <em>Almarantius</em> be slain, or only a Captive. And this I must needs know, for it imports much in his <reg orig="Ladies">Lady's</reg> behalf. Again, whether or no there be not among the Captives one <em>Don William Puitavilla</em> and <em>Luis Bricula</em>, Captains; and if any of them be grievously wounded, there shall come from us a Coach to fetch them; yea and if any <reg orig="Commanders">Commander's</reg> <reg orig="corps">corpse</reg> be with you, I desire that they be honourably sent us.</p>

<p>And I do hope for civility and <reg orig="charitie's">charity's</reg> sake, you will decently <reg orig="interr">inter</reg> the dead; and if need be, let this man know and inform himself and you of each of them whom notice ought to be taken.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration by the Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent, that (notwithstanding my Proclamation of <em>September</em> 27. Last) <pb n="4" />many serviceable horses daily go to the enemy, to the great disservice of the Peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much connivance of the Owners or Possessors; These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons who now are, or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable horses or mares, exceeding the value of 5l. sterling, to bring in the same within 48 hours next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such horses and mares as shall not be brought in; the one moiety thereof to the use of the State, and the other moiety to the party informing; but also be deemed as an open enemy, and dealt with accordingly; which horses and mares so brought in, shall nevertheless be at the <reg orig="owners">owner's</reg> choice either to have meet satisfaction for them, as they shall be reasonably worth, or keep them within the said <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> or Quarters of our Army; and the respective Sheriffs and their Deputies within their Sheriffdoms, are hereby required, to cause these presents solemnly to be proclaimed and published according to accustomed manner of publishing Proclamations. And afterwards (that none may pretend ignorance) to cause to be distributed to the several Presbyteries within their said Sheriffdoms, a competent number hereof.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and Seal at <em>Dalkeith</em> R.<unclear>LILBURN</unclear></i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Lyme in Dorsetshire, January 10.</i></head>

<p>We hear by a By a Barque come from <em>Bretaigne</em> <pb n="5" />in <em>France</em>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch Pickeroon near <em>Ushant</em>, gave him <reg orig="chace">chase</reg>, and followed him so close, that he forced him to run aground on the other side of the Bay of <em>Carmaret</em>, and by reason of his shooting hard at him made the Country come down to the <reg orig="water side">waterside</reg>. It <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> that some shot did make execution of the shore, <reg orig="thore">there</reg> being four killed and wounded; yet because of night approaching, and the Country being <reg orig="alarm'd">alarmed</reg> thereby, could not fetch her off: but ours put to Sea again, to clear from the Rocks, because it was dark.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, January 17. stilo novo. 1654.</i></head>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is quite given over here by the Court-party, as desperate, and they suppose he is not to be brought back again by any tolerable means of accommodation. There was a suspicion among the Spaniards, as if he had intended to have made his peace with the Court of <em>France</em>, and it was given out that a Treaty for that end was actually on foot which did the Prince a great deal of wrong among the Spanish party, upon whom is all his dependence: But now it appears no such matter, only it was raised here out of policy. And he is since <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to <em>Brussels</em>, to the Arch-Duke <em>Leopold</em>, partly to take the air there, and perfect his recovery from his late dangerous Ague, but principally to give assurances of his resolution against the Court of <em>France</em>, and against all the <em>Mazarin</em> party; and thereupon to procure monies and recruits, that <pb n="6" />he may be in some good equipage at Spring, to infest this Kingdom.</p>

<p>Just such another story was raised of his Brother, the Prince of <em>Conti</em>, as if he had had an intention to come to Court, and not only so, but with an intention to marry one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces; which it is believed he scorns to do. The Courtiers (however) say, that he will shortly be here.</p>

<p>There have of late been very strong <reg orig="sollicitations">solicitations</reg> used, to move his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Uncle, the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, to come again to Court; but hitherto he <reg orig="waves">waives</reg> the business, and will by no means give consent to it, but pleads excuses still in his wonted way, which are here but ill resented; and he knows that very well, which makes him keep at a distance, rather than trust himself in the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> clutches, knowing that he shall become a either a sacrifice to violence, or Treachery. Therefore he is so much Italian by the mother, as not to trust an offended enemy. The truth is, if the Cardinal could but get him to Court, it would exceedingly advantage his affairs, because as the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Uncle he hath a great influence upon the hearts of the people, who pay a reverence to his <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>: But it will not be, and there is somewhat more than ordinary that holds up the <reg orig="Dukes">Duke's</reg> <reg orig="humor">humour</reg>, or else he useth not to be so hardy. It is to many men a presage, that some strange turn of affairs is yet to be expected, for the heaving out of the Cardinal. This is certain; if the Princes ever make up a considerable party again within the bowels <pb n="7" />of <em>France</em>, the people will turn to them, most of the good Towns will stand for them, and if ever they approach this City the Inhabitants <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be as high for them as ever, and stick the more surely to them, because they are deceived in all their expectations of those golden <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, that they thought to have seen again upon the return of the Court; who have dealt so <reg orig="impolitickly">impoliticly</reg> and tyrannically with the poor people here, and in all parts of <em>France</em>, since the composing of the last tumults, that they will never have any hope or confidence in them any more.</p>

<p>The Court have been long a drawing up a Declaration against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, but as yet they think not fit to make it <reg orig="publick">public</reg>. They have of late had good success against the Spaniard in <em>Catalonia</em>. The Cardinal <em>De Retz</em> continues still in prison, and no hope there is as yet of his release.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, January 18, stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>since my last here have been several Treasons discovered in these parts, and amongst the rest, one remarkable piece of Treason to have been executed against one of the chiefest Frontier Towns of this Country, which the Traitors had agreed to betray and deliver into the hands of the French for a good sum of money. The <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of their treachery was laid after this manner; In the Town of <em>Armentiers</em>, <reg orig="scituated">situated</reg> upon th River <em>Lisle</em> in <em>Flanders</em>, about three leagues from <em>Lisle</em> and <em>Bassee</em>, and not far from <em>Bethune</em>, there was amongst other <reg orig="Troopes">Troops</reg>, a Regiment of Irish for their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, The Irish knowing <pb n="8" />that there were some of their own Nation in the French <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, of <em>Bassee</em> and <em>Bethune</em> aforesaid; some of them running away discontented from <em>Armentiers</em>, went and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with those of the <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> of the said place, and on the other side some of the French <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> left their own and came over to the Spaniards in <em>Armentiers</em>, and there listed themselves, speaking very ill of the French Officers. At last these runnagadoes <reg orig="broacht">broached</reg> a <reg orig="designe">design</reg> together to deliver the Town of <em>Armentiers</em> into the hands of the Duke of <em>Elbeuf</em>, who was the Buyer, and they the Sellers; the Duke was to have taken possession of one of the Gates when they were upon the Guard, who were to let him in with four or five thousand men which he had in readiness at a Village called <em>Bevery</em>, on this side of <em>Beshune</em>; and to this end they had appointed a night, that their design was to have been executed; but that night one of the Irish men who was of the plot, considering with himself the horrible <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of putting to the sword so many innocent creatures, was troubled in his conscience about it, and went and discovered the whole <reg orig="designe">design</reg> immediately to the Governor, who whilst he was a telling him the business, a Sergeant brings him word that the enemy was <reg orig="approacht">approached</reg> near the Town. Thereupon the Governor doubles his Guards, an puts the Town in a posture to defend <reg orig="its elf">itself</reg>. The Duke of <em>Elbeuf</em> perceiving by the <reg orig="signes">signs</reg> that were made, that the design was failed, retreated to the place from whence he came. The Governor presently <pb n="9" />seized upon the <unclear>Contrivers</unclear> of this <reg orig="designe">design</reg>, to the number of <reg orig="eightteen">eighteen</reg>, whereof four are Captains, five other Officers, and nine <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, all Irish, who will be soon rewarded according to their deserts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rotterdam, January 16. stilo nove.</i></head>

<p>There is no Post come this week from <em>England</em>, we are still in hopes of a peace: here is a report at present that the peace is concluded between us, which we desire may prove to be true. The burning down of so many houses, and the loss of twenty ships in the <em>Tessel</em> upon the sixth of this month through a <reg orig="Hericane">Hurricane</reg>, mentioned in my last, hath been since confirmed to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and sorrow of a great many who were interested in them. Our Eastland Fleet, to the number of 190 Sail, was come near our own Coasts, and through the same storm that <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> on the sixth aforesaid, was forced to sail back into the <em>Sound</em>; what losses they have sustained thereby, is not known.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Berwick, January 11.</i></head>

<p>They write from <em>Scotland</em> that the Lord <em>Kenmore</em>, and <em>Mac Aldore</em>, with 6 or 700 men, are about the Lord of <em>Grante Gracents</em> Bounds, and <em>Straths-pey</em>, where they expect <em><reg orig="Seaforthes">Seaforth's</reg></em> Party to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath drawn out a party of horse and foot to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them (if possible) in case they come down from the Hills. Capt. <em>Hart</em> lately sent a party of horse from <em>Kelsoe</em> into <em>Northumberland</em>, where they tool one <em>Richardson</em>, a Moss-Trooper who lay there to be a guide to some party put of <em>England</em>, and one <pb n="12" /><em>John King</em> who was a <reg orig="Corporall">Corporal</reg> with Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>. Sir <em>Arthur</em> is not yet heard off: whether dead or living. Young <em>Montross</em> is lately joined with the Enemy, and also the Lord <em>Charles Gourdon</em>, only Brother to the late Earl of <em>Huntley</em>, and the Head of their Clan, is gone unto them. They proceed very vigorously in their new Levies.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Athole</em> was lately with about Two or Three hundred horse, and Five hundred Foot, at <em>Cooper</em> in <em>Angus</em>, and from thence went to <em>Meagil</em>, and so back to the Hills.</p>

<p>You may perceive their greatest Confidence is the Hills, who rather by cunning and Craft <reg orig="doe">do</reg> shelter themselves, then to come out and fight as Men, but the Lord will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> them out in his due time.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, January 21. stilo novo</i></head>

<p>This Court is now wholly taken up with discourse of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, whose Condemnation hath been agitated and at length concluded in Parliament. The King would have had the Parliament the arrest of their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> accord; but they pleading, it was against the <reg orig="custome">custom</reg>, that any proceeding should be to condemn a Prince of the Blood without the presence of his Majesty, desired the King that he would come an sit in his great <reg orig="Tribunall">Tribunal</reg>. Whereupon, his Majesty, the 19. instant went to the Parliament, <pb n="11" />accompanied with the Dukes and Peers of <em>France</em>, and many other great Lords, and then sentence was passed against the said Prince, and that all his Estate should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> immediately confiscated, if he come not within a <reg orig="Monneths">Months</reg> time, and submitted to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> obedience. It is reported that the Duke of <em>Orleans</em> intimating a desire of marrying one of his own Daughters to the said Duke of <em>Enguien</em>: which Message and Request makes many men <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg>, that <em>Orleans</em> is now disposed to comply with the Court.</p>

<p>Here is an extraordinary Courier arrived from <em>Rome</em>, who came within 9 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and hath brought Letters pressing, that his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> of <em>France</em> would be pleased to hearken to a Pacification with <em>Spain</em>, and give way to the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Peace; wherein his Holiness hath promised to contribute his best assistance. He departs this day with the like haste for <em>Spain</em>, with Letters of the same nature to that King. What this may produce, time may <reg orig="shew">show</reg>. It may be said of these Monarchies which is spoken of the Sea, that what it gains in one place it loseth in another, and so <em>e contra</em>: Just so, is Fortune ever ebbing flowing between these two mighty Monarchs, what they gain one year they lose the next, and what in one place, they lose in another, and that is the issue of their <reg orig="Warrs">Wars</reg>, to <reg orig="vexe">vex</reg> themselves and all <em>Europe</em> to no purpose.</p>

<p>This Town swells perpetually with <reg orig="Rumors">Rumours</reg>. Nothing now, but that one of your Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> daughters is to be married to the Prince of <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> son, the Duke D'<em>Enguien</em>; though others will have the young Gentleman to be bestowed upon one of the Duke of <em>Orleans</em> his Daughters.</p>

<p>The like care they have taken here to bestow the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> upon the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> son, who is called King of the <em>Romans</em>, which truly is no Tavern nor Street Talk but <pb n="12" /><reg orig="discours">discourse</reg> at Court among those that would be thought serious men: and this last Match, they say, is promoted by <em>Piemontelli</em>, the Spanish Ambassador, in the Swedish Court.</p>

<p>The Pope hath sent order to his <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg> residing with this Court, to make enquiry (which he doth) what <em>Irish</em> Bishops and Priests are in this City, with their Names and <reg orig="Sirnames">Surnames</reg>, and how they live at present. What the occasion is, none can tell.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his Followers are of an inclination to leave <em>France</em>. It's thought, if they remove it will be for <em>Germany</em>. They have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> pumping with those of the Reformed Religion here in <em>France</em>, to try what, and whether they would or could do <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> for them. His <reg orig="Councellors">Counsellors</reg> have had a sharp quarrel among themselves, <em>Ned Hide</em>, who is called Chancellor of the <reg orig="Dutchy">Duchy</reg> or Exchequer (but which I cannot well remember) having been accused of Treason by the Lord <em>Gerard</em>. There hath been somewhat to do among them about it, to no purpose.</p>

<p>Divers Protestants of great and eminent quality having been at the Church at <em>Charenton</em>, were returning back hither by water, and the boat breaking in two, many were drowned, among <unclear>them</unclear> the Son of the Chancellor of <em>Poland</em>, both the Sons of the Marquis <em>de <unclear>Clerainbout</unclear></em>. There were ain all 60 persons, most of them lost.</p>

<p>The Peace between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> is taken for granted here, and concluded on all hands. Several Letters are come hither from <em>Holland</em>, which confirm it. <pb n="13" />And <em>Bereel</em> the Dutch Ambassador, who resides with this Court, declares that he hath Letters from his Country of the 14 instant, <em>stilo novo</em>, <reg orig="whice">which</reg> assure him of it. Which is an alarm here to your enemies at the English Court</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague, January 17. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>We are here very apt to believe a peace, because it is a thing exceedingly desired all over these Lands: And there is the more hope, because all things are very still and calm, both at Sea and Land: And we have added to all our conceits the like out of <em>England</em>, by the way of <em>Flanders</em>; from whence Letters say, that there was not much difference between the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at their parting. Some things have been communicated from them to the States General, which take up a great part of their time in consultation, but nothing can be certainly <reg orig="know">known</reg> yet of the event, because it depends upon their <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> present Resolution: But we <reg orig="guesse">guess</reg> things may go well, because men are not high in discourse (as formerly) against <em>England</em> besides, we observe little talk of a War, or of a desire to it. Thus we live by our Guesses. The Princes about us are <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to see two such formidable Commonwealths in so near a Conjunction; especially now that <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em> are united under one Head, and that a wise and an active one too; and therefore they bid high, in hope to keep open the breach; of whole fears and jealousies the States here will be able to make many an <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> use, and wind them up to their own Conditions, as they shall see <pb n="14" />cause. The French Ambassador, by his diligence, <reg orig="shews">shows</reg> that he hath little else to do here in this <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg>, but to hinder peace if he can. You have formerly heard of his large offers and promises. What to think we know not; but it cannot be long ere the mists be over.</p>

<p>If War go on the Governors here are in no great forwardness of shipping; besides, guns is a great commodity wanting. The late fire in the Bemster hath proved a cooler, and occasioned a great loss, besides the Merchant-men lost at the same time in the <em>Texel</em>. It was a most violent storm; and the fire took first from a Mill used in making <reg orig="Oyle">Oil</reg>. When the wind was high, the Owner of the Mill used all possible means to stop it, but could not, the wind was so strong; and so the stone whirling around with extraordinary swiftness, contracted such heat, that at length the Mill fired, and the storm conveyed fire thence to the houses. Since this <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, these Provinces have had invaluable losses, one way or other.</p>

<p>The Lorainers seemed to come on again, but have not visited the Frontiers.</p>

<p>We expect the coming home of the East-land Fleet from the <em>Sound</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, January 7.</i></head>

<p>The Supplies are safely and timely arrived here, for the encouragement of our Forces in this Nation, where affairs look with no pleasant face, by reason of the great devastations, <reg orig="spoyls">spoils</reg>, and devourings, made by the <em>Highland</em> <pb n="15" />Locusts, who have been swarming and pilfering up and down in all parts. And now they are very active in their Levies.</p>

<p>Doubtless, the enemy have been fed and heightened with more than ordinary hopes and promises; and so mat be more considerable than is believed, as to matter of resolution; but how to accomplish <reg orig="any thing">anything of moment, as yet is not seen: but great men do still flock to them.</reg> </p>

<p>As this week, the Commander in chief hath received an account of the flying out of young <em>Montross</em>, and <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> Lord <em>Gourdon</em>, only brother to the late Marquis of <em>Huntley</em>, and Chief of that Clan, who are gone in to the enemy.</p>

<p>Here is news come this day, that a Letter came to <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, from <em>Aberdene</em>, importing the arrival of seventeen Dutch Ships in the North, with fifteen hundred <reg orig="Foreiners">Foreigners</reg>, and Arms, and two hundred horse. But we have not yet had any account of it, from any of our own people.</p>

<p>No news from Sea, but that the Fleet is riding about <unclear><em>Stoaks</em></unclear> Bay.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">There is lately printed and published</head>

<p>&#x261e; A DISCOURSE of CONSTANCY,</p>

<p>In two Books, written in <em><reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg></em> by <em>Justus Lipsius</em>, containing many Comfortable consolations for all that are afflicted in Body or in Mind. Printed for <em>Humphrey Moseley</em> at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Arms in St. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>