<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol204">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 204</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, May 4. to <em>Thursday</em>, May 11. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Edinburgh</i>, April 25.</head>

<p>This Highland Enemy will not yet <reg orig="shew">show</reg> <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> as an Enemy should, but they harbour still in the Hills, and all that <reg orig="Coll.">Coll.</reg> <em>Morgan</em> could do after his tedious march that way was only to get a sight of them on the other side of the River <em>Tain</em>, a broad dangerous River, and without Boats, so that there was no getting to them, and so he though fit to return back to his Quarter at <em>Dingwel</em>, having no Enemy to encounter.</p>

<p><em>Middleton</em> goes on still in his Levies, forcing men in, in the Counties of <em>Caithness</em> and <em>Ross</em>, but not with such success, as he expected.  The Quarrel between <em>Glencairn</em> and <em>Monro</em> hath bred <pb n="1" /> Factions  among them, so that they are ready to devour one another, and if they linger a little longer in the hills, want of Provision and hunger, will make them.  Therefore we expect that necessity will shortly force them out; but which way is uncertain, and therefore a strict eye is had upon all the Passes.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Because I had not room last week, I could only give you part of the Articles of Peace made with the Dutch, and then you had the substance of 21. Articles.  The rest follow in order:</i></head>

<p>XXII.  That if any ship or ships of the People, or Inhabitants of either Commonwealth, or of a Neuter, shall be taken in the Havens of either, by any <reg orig="3d">3rd</reg> party, being none of the People or Inhabitants of either Commonwealth; They, in or from whose Havens and Liberties the said ships shall be taken, shall be bound together with the other party, to endeavour that the said taken ship or ships may be followed, brought back, and restored to the Owners, but all at the charges of the proprietors or <reg orig="interessed">interested</reg>. <!--Archaic meaning - to concern or affect.  From Anglo-French interesse.--></p>

<p>XXIII.  That Searchers and other Officers of that nature; on both parts, shall in execution of their Offices, regulate themselves according to the Laws of each Commonwealth respectively, and shall not <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> or take more than they are allowed by their Commission or Instructions.</p>

<p>XXIV.  That in case any wrong or injury be done by either Commonwealth, or by the People or Inhabitants thereof, against the people or Inhabitants of the other, either against any the Articles of this Treaty, or against common Right, there shall yet no Letters of Reprisals, Mark or Countermark, be granted by the one or the other Commonwealth, whose people or inhabitants have suffered wrong, or from such as the supreme Power shall depute, to that Commonwealth where justice is as aforesaid <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, or <reg orig="delaid">delayed</reg>, or to such Power as shall be by them appointed to receive such Demands, that all such differences may be composed amicably, or in the ordinary course of Law.  But if there shall be yet delay, and that Justice be not done, nor satisfaction given within three months after such demand made, that then Letters of <reg orig="Reprisall">Reprisal</reg>, <reg orig="Marque">Mark</reg> or <reg orig="Countermarque">Countermark</reg> may be granted.</p>

<p>XXV.  That all persons on either side that shall <reg orig="goe">go</reg> out to Sea upon particular Commissions shall be bound before they take out their Commissions to put in good and sufficient Security by responsible Men not of the <reg orig="ships">ship's</reg> company, before the Judges of the <pb n="2" /> Court whence the said Commission is issued, that they shall do no wrong or injury to the People or Inhabitants of either side.</p>

<p>XXVI.  That the People of either side shall have free access to each others Ports, and may there stay and thence depart not only with their Merchant ships, and such as are laden, but also with their ships of War, whether belonging to the State, or to such as have obtained particular Commissions, whither they shall <reg orig="arive">arrive</reg> either by stress of weather, or to avoid the danger of the Sea, or for provision of Victuals, so be it they exceed not the number of eight ships of War when they come in of their own accord, not that they continue to make stay in the Havens or about the Ports, longer than for the reparation of their ships, buying in of Victuals or for provision of other necessaries.  And whensoever any greater number of ships of War than is above specified, shall have occasion of access into those Ports, then shall it not be lawful for them to make any entrance, without first obtaining leave for this purpose from those to whom the said Ports belong, unless they be constrained by weather or any other force or necessity for avoiding the danger of the Sea.  And when it shall make no longer stay there then the Governor or chief Magistrate shall permit, and during their stay in those Ports they shall commit no hostile Act, nor do anything to the prejudice o the said Ports.</p>

<p>XXVII,  That the <em>Lords</em> the <em><reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg></em> of the <em>United Provinces</em> shall take care that Justice be done upon those who were Authors or Abettors of the <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> committed upon the English in <em>Amboyna</em>, as the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> was pleased to <reg orig="qualifie">qualify</reg> it, if any of them be yet alive.</p>

<p>XXVIII  Whereas certain English ships and goods have been seized and detained within the Dominions of the King of <em>Denmark</em>, since the 18 day of <em>May</em>, in the year 1652, it is on both sides concluded, accorded and agreed, and the <em>Lords the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg></em> have obliged themselves, as they also do by these presents.  That Restitution shall be made of all and singular the English ships &amp; goods detained as aforesaid and remaining yet in <em>specie</em> together with the true and just price of such as are told, <reg orig="imbezled">embezzled</reg>, or otherwise disposed of, within Fourteen days after the <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the Merchants and Masters interested therein, or their Affairs, for the receiving of them.  And also that Damages be given for the losses sustained by the English by Reason of the said detention, according to what shall be arbitrated and awarded by <em>Edward Winslo, James Russell, John Becx, William Vander Craysen,</em> Arbitrators indifferently chosen, <pb n="3" /> as well on the part of the Lord Protector, as the said <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> (the form or instrument of which Arbitration is already agreed upon) to examine and determine the demands of the Merchants, Masters and Owners, to whom the said ships, goods, and damages appertain.  Which Arbitrators are to meet at <em>Goldsmiths Hall</em> here in <em>London</em>, the 27 of <em>June</em> next, old Style or sooner if may be; and shall the same day make solemn Oath before the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty of <em>England</em>, that they will proceed without respect or relation had to either State, or any particular Interest whatsoever.  And moreover, the foresaid Arbitrators shall from the first day of <em>August</em> next, unless they agree upon sentence sooner, be shut up in a chamber by themselves, without Fire, Candle, Meat, Drink, or any other Refreshment, till such time as they come to an Agreement concerning the Matters referred to them; And the Sentence which they shall award shall be obligatory to both Parties.  And the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> of the United Provinces do firmly oblige themselves by these Presents, to execute and perform the same; as also, to pay such <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of money here at <em>London</em>, as the said Arbitrators shall adjudge to be paid, for the use of the said Owners, to such person or Persons as the Protector shall nominate, within 25 days after Adjudication made.  And the said <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> shall, within two days after the Instruments of Ratification of the said Articles of Peace are mutually delivered, pay here at <em>London</em> the sum of 5000l. sterling, towards the Charges of the Merchants, Masters, or their Assigns, for their Journey to <em>Denmark</em>, and the sum of 20000. Rix <!--Unable to find meaning or replacement for Rix--> Dollars, to such Persons as his said Highness shall appoint, within six <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the arrival of the said Persons there, for the use of the Merchants, Masters and Owners, towards repairing their ships and fitting them for Sea.  Which said <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> shall be accounted in part <reg orig="paiment">payment</reg> of such sum, as shall be awarded by the said Arbitrators.  And that Caution and Security be given (the form of which Caution is already agreed upon) by sufficient and responsible Men, living here in <em>London</em>, and binding themselves in an Obligation of one hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling (which Obligation is to be delivered at the same time with the instrument of Ratification) that Restitution shall be made according to the premises; and that the submission and payment as well of the 20000 Rix Dollars, as of such <reg orig="summ">sum</reg>, or other things, as shall be adjudged and determined, as aforesaid, shall on their part be duly performed.  And if all and singular the Conditions be not really and effectually performed on the part of the Lords the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg>  in manner and time aforesaid, then the said Obligation shall be forfeited, and the said <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of one hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling shall be paid to such person and persons as his Highness shall nominate, to the end the losses of the Merchants, Masters and <reg orig="interessed">interested</reg> may be satisfied.</p>

<p>XXIX.  <em>Item</em>, That whereas certain questions and differences have <pb n="4" /> arisen between the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> and the King of <em>Denmark</em>, by reason of  the detention of the ships and goods mentioned in the former Article, and  the <reg orig="States General">States General</reg> of the United Provinces have undertaken the restitution of the said ships and goods, and agreed to give security and caution for the <reg orig="dammages">damages</reg> in the manner <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in the former Article; It is agreed and concluded that the same being done and performed, all questions, strifes, wrongs and acts of hostility between the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> and King, by reason of the said detention, shall cease and be forever forgotten, in such manner, that the said King with his Kingdoms and Dominions shall as a friend, be comprehended and included in this Treaty and Confederation, so as to be restored to the same friendship and alliance with either Commonwealth, in which formerly he was, before the said detention, and as if it had never been.  As also his Deputies and Ambassadors shall be admitted with like <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> as the Deputies and Ambassadors of other States are being Friends and Allies.</p>

<p>XXX.  <em>Item</em>, agreed, that, at the time of the delivery of the Instruments of Ratification, four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides to meet here in <em>London</em>, upon the eighteenth day of <em>May</em> next old style, who shall authorised and <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg>, as also by these presents they are authorised and <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to examine and determine all the losses and injuries which either side <reg orig="alledges">alleges</reg> to have sustained from the other since the year One thousand six hundred and eleven, unto the <reg orig="eighteen">eighteenth</reg> day of <em>May</em>, 1652. Old style, as well in the East Indies, as in <reg orig="Groenland">Greenland</reg>, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brazeel">Brazil</reg> or in any other place: the particulars of all which are to be delivered into the Commissioners nominated as above, before the said eighteenth day of <em>May</em> under this restriction, that after the said day prefixed no new allegations shall be admitted.  And if the <reg orig="abovesaid">above said</reg> Commissioners shall not within three months space, to be accounted from the said eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, come to an agreement, concerning the differences aforesaid delivered in writing &amp; expressed in particulars; that in such case the aforesaid differences shall be submitted, as by these presents they are submitted, to the judgement &amp; arbitration of the Protestant Cantons of <reg orig="Swisserland">Switzerland</reg>, who by an Instrument for this purpose (the form of which is already agreed upon) shall be desired to take upon them that Arbitration, and appoint like Commissioners <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> &amp; instructed to give final judgement <reg orig="thereup">thereupon</reg>, on within six months next following after the expiration of the three <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg> aforesaid.  And whatsoever the said Commissioners or the major part of them, shall award and determine within the said six months, shall oblige both parties, and be performed accordingly.</p>

<p>XXXI.  It is also agreed, That both parties shall firmly and truly perform and observe this present Treaty, and every Article and thing contained and concluded therein; and shall cause the same to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> performed and observed by their respective People, Subjects and Inhabitants.</p> <pb n="5" />

<p>XXXII.  For better Security that this Peace and confederation shall be truly and sincerely performed on the part of the Lords the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, their People and Subjects, it is agreed and concluded, and the Lords the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, do by these Presents agree and firmly oblige themselves, that all and singular, whom, either they the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, or the States <reg orig="Provinciall">Provincial</reg>, shall at any time elect, constitute, or appoint captain General, chief Governor, or Stadtholder, commander of their Army or Forced at Land, or Admiral of any of their Fleets, ships, or Forces at Sea, shall confirm by Oath this Treaty, and all the Matters and things therein contained and shall promise by Oath to observe, and as much as in him or them lies, inviolably to perform and keep the same: And as far as concerns them, command the same to be performed and put in execution, and take care that they be performed and executed by others accordingly.</p>

<p>XXXIII.  Lastly, it is agreed, That the present Treaty, and all and singular Matters and Things therein contained and agreed on, shall within fifteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> next ensuing, or sooner, if it may be, be confirmed and ratified in due and <reg orig="authentick">authentic</reg> form, by the said Lo: Protector, and the said <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg> of the United Provinces by their Letters Patents under their great Seals, and that Instruments of Ratification shall be delivered interchangeably within the time aforesaid.  And furthermore, that this Treaty and confederation shall immediately after delivery of the Instruments, be published according to the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> Solemnity, and in the places accustomed; and that all acts of hostility shall cease on both sides from that time.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Isle of Wight, May 4.</i></head>

<p>A Bark come hither out of France adviseth, That in her way homeward she met two of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, who had met about Ten sail of small French ships near Conquet, and had taken about five of them, and were in pursuit of the rest, being about 2 Leagues from them, and very likely to take them.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Brest-Pirats">Brest Pirates</reg> are very rife abroad, and have taken an English ship of late bound from Morlaix for London, laden with <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> cloth.</p> <pb n="6" /> 

<p>Take next the Copy of a <em>Congratulation</em> presented in the name of the County of <em>Buckingham</em>, as followeth.  It should have been published a while since, but by accident, it lingered till now.  It was presented to his Highness by Sir <em>Richard Temple</em>, and Sir<em> Heneage Proby</em>, and about 30 Gentlemen.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland.</em></i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The Congratulations of us the Knights, Gentlemen, Ministers and Yeomen of the County of <em>Bucks.</em></i></head>

<p>We do desire to rejoin in the hand of Divine Providence over your Highness in all the dangers of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> (which have been many and great) in which the Lord of Hosts hath protected your Highness, and hath made you nently <!--Unable to find meaning or replacement for nently.--> Instrumental of the great good of Peace and Quiet, which for the present we enjoy.  And whereas of late we were sinking, and should have stuck fast in the Quicksands of Trouble and Confusion (which fiery and furious spirits did desire to have seen) we with thankfulness and Admiration do acknowledge the late Turn of Providence, in that we, (which yet are upon the troubled Sea) do now see Land, and have a foundation of some settles Government held cut unto us.  And as it is the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> duty to strengthen the hands of their <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, so we (in this Address to your Highness) do engage <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to stand by and assist you to the uttermost in the discharge of the Trust which so remarkably is devolved upon you: in the promoting of the Cause and Interest of Jesus Christ, <pb n="7" /> in the Countenancing of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Congregations, the encouraging of the able, painful and pious Ministers of the Gospel, the <reg orig="removeall">remove all</reg> of those that are scandalous, negligent, and insufficient, and putting better in their places, the preservation of the fundamental Laws and Liberties of the Nation, and shall ever pray.  &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels,</i> May 10.</head>

<p>The Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Loraign</em> with his two sons is arrived here at last, he was met out of Town by the Archduke <em>Leopald</em> and all his whole train, who gave him with great civility, (the Complements being first <reg orig="past">passed</reg> between them) the upper hand which he did in manner when he arrived at Court, where he was received with open arms and other sufficient demonstrations of love and <reg orig="and"></reg> affection to each other: After some short stay here; he is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to command his Army, and in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> of his abode here, he will get the acquaintance of the Officers of the Army, and so by degrees the love of the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, who are said to be averse to serve under him.  The Spanish troops are upon their march to begin the <reg orig="Campagn">Campaign</reg>.  They are <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> towards <em>Doway</em> and <em>Valenchienne</em>, many suppose they are designed against <em>Bethune</em> or <em>Bassee</em>; whilst that the French are <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon their Confines and Borders, through the apprehension of the English Fleet, which hath put the people of <em>Normandy, Britain,</em> and <em>Guienne</em> into a very great fright, that they do guard and watch their Coasts, and have also fortified and reinforces their Cities and <reg orig="strong holds">strongholds</reg> with double <pb n="8" /> guards; the better to prevent and hinder any <unclear>surprise</unclear> or landing that may be intended against them.  The general discourse here, now the peace is concluded with <em>Holland</em>, is, of the Treaty between <em>France</em> and <em>England</em>.  Some say, it <reg orig="wil">will</reg> take the same effect as that of <em>Holland</em>, which would very much prejudice the affairs of the Spaniards, if it should fall out to be so.  Others again say, that his Highness the Protector will take the present opportunity which is so <reg orig="favorable">favourable</reg> unto him to put in execution, the ancient pretences of <em>England</em> to the Kingdom of <em>France</em>, all things concurring to <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> him thereunto.  And of late it is said, there hath been a Comet seen at <em>Paris</em>, with a long tail, which the wise Prognosticators do conjecture, to be the messenger or <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, Sicknesses, and Miseries.</p>

<p>Here <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> lately a kind of tumult between the <reg orig="Lackies">Lackeys</reg> and Footmen of the Lords of this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and  those of <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> parts, but they were presently parted by the Officers of the city, who apprehended some of the chiefest of them, and have had them since soundly <reg orig="whipt">whipped</reg> for their pains.</p>

<p>Here is great expectation of the publication of the Peace, that the Merchants may safely venture to revive their Trade.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Deal, May 4.</i></head>

<p>Here are arrived a great number of our State-ships, and the rest of the Fleet are expected tomorrow.  It is said that this is appointed for the <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> of general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>.</p> <pb n="9" /> 

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal in Sweden, April 7.</i></head>

<p>I may tell you that our business here is almost at an end: And I hope, it will not be long ere we set forwards towards our desired <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.  The Queen hath now manifested, that she hath been <reg orig="reall">real</reg> in all her demonstrations of respect to my Lord Ambassador; And though for some reasons of state, we could not hitherto prevail to get a particular Answer, <reg orig="onley">only</reg> Promises, yet she hath now been as good as <unclear>her word</unclear>, and hath given my Lord a grand Dispatch before her retirement.  The Queen <reg orig="Commissionated">Commissioned</reg> the Grand Chancellor, and his second Son, Count <em>Erick</em>, to Treat with my Lord and to conclude.  And after some expedients found on both sides, they are come to their <reg orig="journeys">journey's</reg> end: and after the Articles are <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>, they will be signed: So that now we shall have nothing to do, but to wait for an order to recall us home.</p> 

<p>The Queen is positive in her Resolves of quitting the Government: Her <reg orig="Succeeder">Successor</reg> the Prince Royal, is a person of large Wisdom, Martial Courage, and a sweet natural disposition.  And it is believed withal, that this Nation will be happy under his Government.  We now dream of nothing but returning to you.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Additional Ordinance for the Excise.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance of the seventeenth of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for continuing the Excise,</i> it is next after the Rates therein specified, generally declared <pb n="10" /> and provided, <i>That all other goods and <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> (except <reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg>, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of brass or iron, imported, or to be imported) not specified, or the <unclear><!--approx. 3 characters--></unclear> rated, should pay after the rate of five pounds <em>per centum,</em> according as the same are charged by the book of Rates, for the Customs to be paid by the first buyer one shilling.</i></p>

<p>Be it ordained, and it is ordained and declare by his Highness, with the advice and consent of his Council, That the said Clause be null and void, and instead thereof, be it hereby <reg orig="ordain-">ordained</reg> and declared, That all other goods and <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg> mentioned in the Book of Rates for the Customs (except <reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg>, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron, and Wools of Sheep) imported, or to be imported which are not in the said Rates of Excise, before or otherwise Charged, shall hereafter pay Excise, after the rate of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, to be paid by the first Buyer from the Merchant or Importer, and the same is to be collected accordingly.</p>

<p>And to the end the whole receipts of the Excise may be the better reduced into one cash, and the charge and number of Officers thereby retrenched, It is hereby ordained by authority aforesaid, That from and after the <reg orig="twenty fifth">twenty-fifth</reg> day of March last, the Revenue of the Excise shall be but one Receipt, and so <reg orig="accompted">accounted</reg> for, and that all receipts and <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg> heretofore taken or kept of any payments of Excise or new Impost, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any Addition Act, Ordinance, or order of Parliament, and designed <pb n="11" /> to any separate use or uses whatsoever, shall from thenceforth cease and be void, and be brought and reduced to one general Cash, and <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Revenue.  Provided nevertheless, that the <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> or fines and forfeitures, imposed and received since the twenty fifth of March last or that hereafter shall be imposed and received shall be still kept in an <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg> apart, and be paid out towards the maintenance of widows and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, according to Ordinance of Parliament of the thirteenth of July, one thousand six hundred and forty seven.</p> 

<p>And it is hereby for the further relief of the said Widows and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, ordained, That from and after the said five and twentieth day of March last, there shall be, out of the general Cash and Revenue of the Excise, allowed the certain yearly sum of twenty six thousand two hundred sixty pounds, to be paid weekly by equal portions out of the said <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Receipt unto such person or persons as is, are, or shall be appointed thereunto by his Highness and His Council, and be <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for <reg orig="imploying">employing</reg> and disposing thereof to the use aforesaid.  Which yearly <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of twenty six thousand two hundred and sixty pounds is to be in lieu of all and every <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> and <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of money assigned by any Act, Ordinance or Order of Parliament out of any the Receipts of the Excise, for the Relief of the said <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg> and maimed Soldiers, other then the Moiety of Fines and Forfeitures before excepted; and the present Commissioners of the Excise, or <pb n="12" /> any <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> of them, shall have power from time to time to issue our <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear>, either delivered over unto them, by the Commissioners <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> them, or which hath, or shall be directed by his <unclear>Highness</unclear> the Lord Protector and his Council, or by Authority thereof.  And the said Commissioners for Excise, and their Subcommissioners, are hereby <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to make repayment of the Excise to any persons whatsoever, for any Goods imported upon the Exportation <reg orig="therof"> thereof</reg>, in such sort as the late Commissioners might have done before the 25 day of May last, It appearing unto them that the duty of the said Goods have been fully paid; any former Clause, Article or Provision to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobell</em> Clerk of the Council.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, May 8. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>This day the Peace was proclaimed, and a day of Thanksgiving is to be appointed for this great blessing.  Great shouts of joy were made at the publication thereof by the people, who are generally well pleased with this good news.</p>

<p>The Secretary of the deceased Lord Le Brun, Ambassador of Spain, hath signified to the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, that he had order from the Archduke Leopold to take upon him the management of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> affairs, in the quality of a <reg orig="publique">public</reg> person; till such time that the place of Ambassador should be <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg>.  He did also represent unto them, that his Majesty doth desire to be comprehended as an <reg orig="Allie">Ally</reg> and Friend in the <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg> made with the Commonwealth of England, as he hath written to his Ambassador in England.  But he did also complain that the Hollanders <reg orig="doe">do</reg> undertake to Trade in the East-Indies to the prejudice of the ancient Agreements; upon which he hath yet received no answer.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> we are preparing all what we can our Pitch barrels and Fireworks against the Day of Thanksgiving, which <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said will far exceed those that were made for the Peace with <em>Spain</em>.  This is all the news at present that these parts will afford.  Our Merchants are preparing all what they are able, to have their ships in a readiness to go to Sea, <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as ever the day limited for their safe passage is expired.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris May 13. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>The French Court is still as <em>Fontainbleau</em>; and great Preparations are making for his Coronation at <em>Rheims</em>, which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> within a Fortnight after his Return hither from the said <em>Fontainbleau</em>.  All the Foreign Ministers are invited to the Coronation, and a day appointed for their meeting at <em>Rheims</em>.</p>

<p>The Protestant Commissioners are gone after the Court, supposing the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> will be better at leisure to hear their complaints, where he is, then when he is in Town.</p>

<p>The Princess of <em>Conde</em> hath petitioned to the Parliament to have her Jointure secured, and <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon her: And the Prince of <em>Conti</em> <pb n="13" /> hath also petitioned to have his <reg orig="fathers">father's</reg> Will <reg orig="annull'd">annulled</reg>, <reg orig="alleadging">alleging</reg> there are many things contained therein which <reg orig="doe">do</reg> tend very much to his prejudice, wherein he ought to have <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg>:  Both their Petitions were referred back to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<p>Here is news that the Prince of <em>Harcourt</em> hath in the end agreed with <em>Spain</em>; so that all <em>Brisat</em> and <em>Alsatia</em>, except <em>Philipsbourg</em>, will be delivered into the hands of the Spaniards, of whom he hath received a good sum of Money.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his Brother are also in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> taking the fresh <reg orig="aire">air</reg>, curing the absence of the French Court, at whose return he thinks to remove out of France, if the money be ready when he expects from them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An <reg orig="Advertisemnt">Advertisement</reg></i></head>

<p>Whereas several persons have presented unto his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> divers patterns for the making of a common Farthing for the use of the Common wealth; and have attended several times about the same, and at this day the business is depending  before his honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and then pleasure as yet not signifies therein.  And yet notwithstanding in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> several persons have presumed without any Authority or Declaration of the State to set the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> Arms on a piece of pewter of  the weight of about a quarter of an ounce, and have procured intimation in Print to be made, that these pewter farthings are allowed to pass current through the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, &amp;c. and in pursuance thereof, have and do daily vent these <reg orig="unauthorized">unauthorised</reg> pewter farthings in <em>London</em> and other parts of this Commonwealth, to the great deceit and <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> of this Nation.</p>

<p>These are to give notice to all men, that if there be not a sudden stop of the making and venting of those pewter farthings, the Commonwealth will be greatly deceived, both by mixing the Pewter with Lead, and also every Tinker and other lewd persons will get <reg orig="molds">moulds</reg> and make said pewter farthings in every corner.  Therefore all people ought to take notice that no farthings are to pass, but such only as shall be <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg>, by his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to pass through the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness the Lord PROTECTOR of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>,</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The Major, Burgesses, and Commonalty of the Town and Country of Pool, with a long and happy Government on Earth, and Eternal felicity above, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>The series of mercies (or rather miracles) the which the Father of Mercies hath of late years encompassed his people in these Nations, as it eminently commenced, and continued in raising up your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> spirit suitable to so great things as he hath brought to pass by your hand; namely, the enlargement of his people both in spiritual concernment, and temporal enjoyment, so we trust will still continue towards you and us, until our deliverance be <reg orig="compleated">completed</reg>, <pb n="14" /> and your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> actions Crowned with perpetual praise: And seeing by Divine Providence your Highness hath been made in so large a measure, the happy repairer of our breaches, defender of truth, and procurer of Peace in these Nations, as we desire to bless the name of the most High as the efficient cause, so also to manifest our duty and thankfulness to your Highness, as the instrumental means of so great enjoyments, <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> in the Lord, who hath given us a Governor that seeks the good of <em>Sion</em> <!--Variant of Zion-->, under whose protection, as we have much confidence of living happily, so we also engage to live Loyally, dedicating our hearts and hands, lives and fortune to your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Service, for accomplishment of the good work so <reg orig="farr">far</reg> by you promoted in opposition to all the enemies of the truth, piety, and peace, which being the full purpose of our hearts, we hold it our duty to declare, the more to confirm your hand in the work of the Lord and his people, humbly subscribing <reg orig="our selves">our selves</reg></p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> very faithful Servants.</i></p>

<p>Presented by Major <em>Skutt</em> and some other Gentlemen of the Town of <em>Pool</em>, and his Highness returned hearty thanks both to the Gentlemen that delivered it, and also to the Town.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsall">Upsala</reg> April 7.</i></head>

<p>We can now in some measure make you a <reg orig="requitall">requital</reg> of News, by telling you that his Excellency hath concluded the Treaty here to a full and large satisfaction on both sides, and that within Fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after he began to Treat with those Noble persons that were <reg orig="Commissionate">Commissioned</reg> for that purpose by her Majesty.  We must confess it was beyond our expectation, when we considered the difficulties, the greatness of the business, the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> to obstruct it, and the <reg orig="aversness">averseness</reg> of divers great ones towards it: But the grand <reg orig="Chancelor">Chancellor</reg>, and his son Count <em>Erick</em>, who were the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Commissioners, came off with good respect to my Lord Protector, and to my Lord Ambassador also himself, who with great wisdom and dexterity hath managed this business.  The Queen also hath manifested incomparable affection to his Highness, and <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> to my Lord Ambassador, with whom she hath kept her Word very <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg>.  <reg orig="Shee">She</reg> told my Lord Ambassador, That she would have the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> to make the <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> with my Lord Protector, and in respect to him, and she said, because my Lord Ambassador treated her like a Gentleman, <em>avec franchise et rondeur, et ne pas comme un Marchand</em>, she did consent to more than any other could have obtained from her.</p>

<p>It hath pleased God to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> much mercy to us in our voyage hither, and in our business here, and we hope to enjoy the like in our return, which will be now out of hand.</p> <pb n="15" /> 

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>,</i> April 25.</head>

<p>The only news here is, that my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> hath finished his affair at <em>Upsal</em>, and we expect his Lordship in this <unclear>City</unclear> within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>.  There is a firm Alliance and friendship made, which is as much as either side could expect or desire, as things stand.</p>

<p>You Tantalise our expectation about the issue of the Dutch Treaty, touching which our <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> works stronger than our faith.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal, April 8.</i></head>

<p>The Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> wrote Letters of late to the Q. of <em>Sweden</em>, wherein he signified the cause of his <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> with the <em>Pole.</em>  Two reasons he mentioned; one because a certain <em>Poland</em> Poet writing a Narration of former <reg orig="Warrs">Wars</reg>, wherein the <em>Pole</em> had the better, said, they had beaten the <em>Muscovite</em>, without adding his Title, <unclear><em>plain Muscovite</em></unclear>.  The other, because in quoting something touching the Genealogy of the <em>Muscovites</em> Ancestors, he named one as father which was the son; and for these two grand offences, he demanded of the <em>Pole</em> the <reg orig="offenders">offender's</reg> head; which being <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, he makes <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> upon them and hath taken one City; and hanged one of the most considerable in <em>Poland</em>.  These were the contents of his Letters.  In his long title he hath of late called himself <em>Dominus parentum &amp; avorum suorum</em>.  The Queen being forced to answer something, because he asked her advice, returned, That she neither approved nor disapproved, his reasons, but thanking him for his civil Communication, wished that he might receive good satisfaction from the <em>Pole</em>, being troubled that Christian Princes should disagree.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April 29.</i></head>

<p>There is little News since the last.  All are yet quiet in these parts:<em> Middleton</em> and <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> yet continue in the same posture; only the Enemy are often quarrelling among themselves: The last was between <em>Glengary</em> and Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>: <em>Kenmore</em> took <em>Forbes</em> his part, but <em>Middleton</em> parted them.  The <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> intends next week to March towards <em>Sterling</em>, and so for the Hills.  The Lord <em>Craighall</em>, one of the Judges at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> died this day.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">&#x261e; <i>The Art of COOKERY,</i></head>


<p>Returned and augmented; Containing some rare and rich unpublished <em>Receipts</em> of Cookery.  Whereunto is added, A Compendious way for making, Preserves, Conserves, &amp;c.  By that Incomparable Master of these Arts, Mr. <em><unclear>Jos</unclear> Cooper</em>, Chief Cook to the late King.  And are to be sold by <em>Richard Lownds</em>, at the <em>White Lion</em>, near the West <reg orig="end">End</reg> of <em>St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>.</em></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>