<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol191">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 191</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, February 2.to <em>Thursday</em>, Febru.9. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Edinburgh, February 1</i></head>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> marching from <em>Aberdeen</em> with 14 Companies of Foot, an 8 Troops of Dragoons towards the Enemy, <em>Glencairn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> the same day went out of <em>Murrayland</em> towards the Hills, they burnt all the Lord <em><reg orig="Lothans">Lothan's</reg></em> land (the Lord <em><reg orig="Brodies">Brodie's</reg></em> Uncle) because he kept his house out against them in the late infall into the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> quarters at <em>Dunkel</em>: there was killed one Capt. <em>Robertson</em>, one Capt <em>Hunter</em>, (a young Laird who attended <em>Athol</em>) the Laird of <em>Baillachan</em>, Major <em>Mercer</em> run into the body with a <pb n="1" />Tuck, and throgh the arm, it is believed he will not live; there were about twenty more slain and desperately wounded. The 23 instant <em>Athol</em> had a Rendezvous of the country at a place called <em>Cairane</em>, two or three miles Northeast from <em>Dunkel</em>, but had a very slender appearance. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> and <em>Wogan</em> lie ill of their wounds at <em>Weems</em>, <em>Wogan</em> is not likely to recover: Col. <em>Hume</em> with about 16 or more out of the <em>Merch</em>, or <em>Berwickshire</em>, are this week gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those in the Hills.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Newcastle, Feb. 1.</i></head>

<p>For news we have very little, only that which we suppose you may have heard of, The interception of many Letters that came from the <reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg> Cavaliers to the Malignant Party here, but they were by a person of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> sent up to his Highness. The truth is, there is such continual meetings of the Cavaliers that any may judge without the intercepting Letters, they have great designs in hand. Here is much doings about the Quakers; they were at a place called <em>Hasington</em> on the Sabbath day, and as they were speaking to the Minister, the Country people fell upon them, and abused them very much, almost killed one or two; but going out; falling upon their knees, seeking to God to forgive them, saying they knew not what they did, and afterward speaking to them, many of the people were so convinced of the evil they had done in beating of them, that returning back to the residue of the people that were on the Green in the Town, beginning to accuse one another as <pb n="2" />the occasion of beating those men who had done them no hurt, nor <reg orig="oppossed">opposed</reg> till he had done, and the Minister being earnestly pressed to go and discourse with them, and he refusing, this discourse went so high, that the townsmen generally went to go by the ears, and did so exceedingly beat one another, that such a fight hath not been seen. There was very few that went home without their faces or heads broken.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Isle of Wight, Feb.3.</i></head>

<p>Our Fleet hath now set sail, and put to Sea from St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg></em> point, they are divided in three Squadrons, but are not at so great a distance but that upon any occasion they can soon <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> into on entire body, there being scouts appointed, who are to give notice upon any appearance of the enemy.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Deal, February, 2.</i></head>

<p>Here is little news at present; a good number of ships bound to the Southward, as also for several Ports of <em>France</em>, are gone from hence and from <em>Dover</em>. The French Pikeroons do haunt about these parts, and are often seen, <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as any of our Ships set Sail to give them <reg orig="chace">chase</reg>, they get their own Coast before he can come upon them, there being two at present who are riding in <em>Calice</em> Road.</p>

<p>Paris the 7 of February 1654. stilo novo. There is a great alteration made in the preparation of Taxes and Imposts, there being new Offices made, and new Officers created, where old ones are put out of service: and among many <pb n="3" />remarkable things, it is to be wondered, that many Protestants are admitted to places of some honour, and more profit: There is now at present in this City the Earl of Harcourt his Secretary and one from the Marshal Seneterre; therefore now a Treaty is in hand concerning the Agreement between the <reg orig="Courtand">Court and</reg> the said Earl touching Alsatia, there hath been some progress made in it, but nothing agreed upon. During this Treaty the siege of Beffort goeth on with as much gallantry as may be expected, considering the season, and the great opposition of the Besieged, who neither spare valour nor labour in the defence of that place. The Marshal Ferte is <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> seen in the Trenches, thereby to animate the Soldiers; so that it is expected in a short time you will hear of the surrender of that place. The great preparations made at Toulon goeth on, and it is variously reported to what intent it is; for some will have it for to get the mastery of the Seas in the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>; others will have it <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in part that way and the other part to be sent to the aid of the Venetian State; but some who do think themselves wisest, believe that it is the old design for Naples; and for a confirmation of the same, it is observed that the Duke of Guise doth make <reg orig="mony">money</reg> at all hands, having sold and pawned such things whereby to raise a very considerable sum of moneys, and we do hear that he is to go from hence within this month: but of this more by the next. The Pope seemeth to be very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the making of a general peace between us and Spain, and the other <pb n="4" />Allies; and to that end, we are told of an extraordinary Nuntio that is now on his journey hither; another also being sent into Spain: Our <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from Rome is to be here the next week; and now all things are ready for the dancing of the great <reg orig="Balet">Ballet</reg>, which will be between this and shrove Tuesday: and for the consecration of the young King it will not be so soon as was expected.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels the 8 of February</i></head>

<p>We are very barren of News in these parts at present, and here is nothing to advise you of, but the sad condition of the Country of Liege; which is like to be ruined by the Troops of several parties, who are now lodged therein. The Duke of Loraine hath quartered his Troops there, partly by consent &amp; partly by force, under pretence (as it is said) that the States of the Country did invite him to come there; because their Prince the Bishop of Liege did govern altogether absolutely, and against the Laws &amp; <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> of their Country, so that he was come to redress their grievances, and to breed a good understanding between the Bishop and his people. On the other hand, the Troops of the Prince of <em>Conde</em> do pretend that those of Liege are affected to the French, that they hold correspondence with them, wheresoever they come, and that they do them all the mischief they can possibly contrive against the; therefore they are come to secure them and their Country from being made a prey of the Lorainers. Now there is a third and <pb n="5" />fourth party, which are the Troops of the King of France and of the Empire, that are upon their march towards that Country also; and they pretend likewise they come to relive the afflicted, and to the assistance of a Prince of the Empire, who is <reg orig="quarreld">quarrelled</reg> and abused wrongfully in his rights and prerogatives. All these <reg orig="forraigne">foreign</reg> Troops drawing towards one <reg orig="Center">Centre</reg>, have caused the Troops of <reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg>, and those of the United Provinces to march also towards that said Country; as well to secure their frontier places, as also to hinder the French Troops from <reg orig="entring">entering</reg> into the Country of Liege; for if they enter into the Country, all the rest will do the like: and since the Country is <reg orig="newter">neuter</reg>, neither the one nor the other, ought to come there. But in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> during these debates and quarrels, the Inhabitants are miserably used, like Enemies on all hands.</p>

<p>They are raising great sums of money here, to prepare for next <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> expedition, which will be more carefully prosecuted <reg orig="then">than</reg> that of last year, they intend to have their Army in the field, about the middle of April next, which will be sooner <reg orig="then">than</reg> according to their <reg orig="custome">custom</reg>.</p>

<p>The Earl of <em>Bassigny</em> and the Abbot of Mercy are still prisoners in the Castle of <em>Antwerp</em>, where they have been several times examined, and now it is said that their crime is not so <reg orig="fowl">foul</reg> as was reported in the first. Three other Governors of Towns have been condemned for their extortions, to be held incapable of commanding any Regiments, Towns, places, or Troops for <pb n="6" />the space of ten years, and one of them to make restitution of 4000 Escus, and the other two, each of 2000 Escus; this to serve for an example to others not to do the like, to the discredit of the Generals and Commanders in chief, and to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of the poor people.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorain">Loraine</reg></em> and the Prince of <em>Conde</em> are both arrived in this City to resolve upon the Affairs of the Country of <em>Liege</em>, which are come to a very great extremity.</p>

<head level="3"><i><em>From</em> Bristol, February 1.</i></head>

<p>We have three of our <em>Mallago</em> ships arrived, and a fourth is in the River, and expected every moment. Our <em>Cadiz</em> Fleet we cannot hear of, both have so long <reg orig="outstaid">outstayed</reg> their time, that being almost given up for lost; much sadness hath thereby been upon our Merchants, who are in those ships deeply <reg orig="concern'd">concerned</reg>. We have lost lately three ships of this Port laden for <em>France</em>, <em>viz</em> the <em>Unicorn</em>, of 120 tons, and 8 guns, taken by two <em><reg orig="Brest-men">Brest men</reg></em> of War, one of them of 36 guns, commanded by Captain <em>Beach</em> an Englishman; and the <em>Mary</em> taken by an <em>Ostend</em> man of War, and carried to <em>Dunkirk</em>; also three <em>Barnstable</em> ships taken by <em><reg orig="Brest-men">Brest men</reg></em> of War, and carried to <em>Brest</em>. One of the former ships was towed by one of the men of War of <em>Brest</em>, to whom a man of War of ours gave chase 36 hours, and yet could not fetch her up, such heavy slugs are appointed for those seas, whereas the most nimble <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> should be thereunto <reg orig="design'd">designed</reg>. The Western parts have <pb n="7" />paid more deeply than all <em>England</em>, both by want of Guards on those Coasts, and the Jadishness of those appointed, who are indeed worse <reg orig="then">than</reg> none in regard we fail upon presumption of their security, otherwise we should be more wary.</p>

<head level="3">From aboard the <em>Saphire</em> in <em>Plymouth-Sound, January</em> 31.</head>

<p>Since my last I had not sight of any ship till the 26 instant; and then S.W. from <em>Scilly</em> in 90 <reg orig="fatham">fathom</reg> water, I met with 5 sail that came from <em>Mallago, viz</em> 2 Ostenders, 2 <unclear>Dunkirkers</unclear> and 1 Hamber, who told me there was not one Hollander at <em>Mallago</em>. I found them unwilling to go into any Port of <em>England</em>; their carriage being something rough made me jealous, I therefore thought it was my duty to bring them to <em>Plymouth</em>, and only kept the Masters and Papers but sent not one man on board them.</p>

<p>On the 27 I had sight of 8 English that came from <em>Mallago</em>.</p>

<p>On the 28. in sight of <em>Scilly</em>, I <reg orig="plyed">plied</reg> toward 15 sail, and spoke with one who told me they were all English.</p>

<p>On the 29 I <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg> to get the wind of the Fleet homeward bound, being 28 sail, so that I might be able to secure them from such as might lie near the <em>Lizard</em>, the wind a long time being <reg orig="Eastly">Easterly</reg> on the 30. in sight of the <em>Lizard</em>, as I <reg orig="plyed">plied</reg> on the weather-bow of the Fleet, I met with a Dutchman of War, by two in the afternoon I got up with him, after some scuffling, through <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> mercy I became Master of her <pb n="8" />without the loss of any <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> hair: It is the same ship that your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> heard had chased a ship ashore at <em>Pricksome</em>, and the same that fought with the <reg orig="Nightingall">Nightingale</reg>, the <reg orig="Captains">Captain's</reg> name is <em>Daniel Wildbore</em>, the ship is called the <unclear><em>Walkerron</em></unclear> of <em>Middleborough</em>, of 20 Guns and 70. men, whereof 6 are slain: she hath not been home in 7 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, but hath sold his prizes in <em>France</em>, was in the Isle of <em>Bass</em> six days gone, and made his ship clean; he did always make his voyage upon our west coast. I hope in short time God will deliver that and the rest into our hands.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Paris, Feb. 10.</em></head>

<p>The Duke of <em>Longueville</em> is arrived in this Town, and hath been to salute their Majesties, who received him with a deal of respect according to his merit. The Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> hath made <reg orig="severall">several</reg> instances to this Court to advance the <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> of a League Offensive and Defensive, between the King of France and his Master, and the marriage of said King and the Daughter of the King of <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg>, with whom he doth offer a Dowry of four millions of Gold. The Marshall of Hoquincourt, Viceroy of <reg orig="Catalogne">Catalonia</reg> for the King of Spain, hath leave to return to his Government of Peronne, and it is said that the Duke of Guise is to go to command in his place. All the preparations that were made at Toulon, and other places of Provence being designed for <reg orig="Catalogne">Catalonia</reg>, and not for Naples, as was reported. The siege before Beffort is still continued by the French, who notwithstanding the vigorous <pb n="9" />opposition they meet withal from the besieged do behave themselves with great courage and resolution for the gaining of the place, which will not be so soon as was expected.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From aboard the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, at <em>Falmouth</em> January 31.</i></head>

<p>I gave you an account of the taking of the <em>Dorgord</em> of <em>Flushing</em>, the 26 instant, and the recovering of the Patrick of <em>Liverpool</em>, from the <em>Brest</em> men of war on the 27th. On the 28 standing over <em>Scilly</em>, we chased a <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, which we understand by our prisoners aboard, was made for Cap. <em>James Dillon</em>. The <em>Old Warwick</em>, being between the shore and us, and we plying large, that he should not pass between the shore and us, came up with him before us. He was under the <reg orig="commatd">command</reg> of the <em>Mount</em> before our ship came up, and ran so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the shore, that we durst not go <reg orig="neer">near</reg> him, by which means he ran very <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Pensance">Penzance</reg></em> Key, and there Anchored. The old <em><reg orig="Warwicks">Warwick's</reg></em> boat taking her, found her to be one of <em>St. Malo's</em> coming from <em>Faro</em>. The <em>Middleburgh</em> went to the Lands-end, and I intended to follow, but did not; very little wind made us stand off two or three leagues farther than ordinary, which brought us (the 29 in the morn) within sight of four ships of <em>St. Maloes </em>coming from <em> Marseilles</em>, bound for <em>Newhaven</em>, viz. The St. <em>Martin</em> with 18 guns and 44 men, the St. <em>Helena</em> with 14 guns, and 32 men, the <em>Protection</em>, with 12 guns and 32 men, and the <em>Francis</em> with 38 men and ten guns, laden with <em>soap, <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, cotton</em> &amp;c. With whom we <pb n="10" /> came up about one <reg orig="aclock">o'clock</reg>, and fought them till Sun-set. The St. <em>Martin</em> and St. <em>Helena</em> had both yielded, but we had none of our men aboard; it beginning to be dark, and we being ready to board the <em>Protection</em>, whom we had well paid with shot, bethought <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> that we should lose the other two in taking her, and so <reg orig="cleered">cleared</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with much ado, and stood to the other, who being secured we were bearing for the other yet untaken; but these two ships we had take were so much disabled, as we were forced to keep by them to save them from sinking, and sent our Carpenter aboard to stop leaks, and men to fit the Rigging and Sails, <em>viz.</em> in the main-mast three shot, the top mast two, in the head of the fore-mast one, in the <reg orig="mizen-mast">mizzenmast</reg> two, our fore-yard, and <reg orig="mizen">mizzen</reg> yard made unserviceable; we had several shot between wind and water, but the worst loss is five of our men killed, and 19 wounded, some of whom have lost their limbs.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Bristol</em> Feb. 4. 1654</i></head>

<p>Since my last some of our <em>Cadiz</em> ships are arrived, and bring notice that the rest are in <em>Ireland</em>, having made our Land a month since, but by contrary winds forced and kept there, which is very good news to our <reg orig="Marchants">Merchants</reg>, who had almost given them up for lost; it being eight weeks since they set sail from <em>Cadiz</em>; some of them have brought a Dutch man of about 300 <pb n="11" /><reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, laden with salt, which they took a little off that Port as they put homewards. The <em>Brest</em> men of war of whom I wrote you in my last, have since taken two vessels of <em>Milford</em>, of which we had notice this day, and about the time of the taking of the former, they took three ships, one of 18 Guns, another of twelve, laden with Lead, and Red Herrings, who pretended themselves of <em>Amsterdam</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, being Dutch men, but had <unclear>Cocquets</unclear> from north <em>Tarmouth</em>, the seamen being Dutch and indeed the commodities English, it is a shame that these Rogues should be permitted thus, to rob our Fleet, and that such Cow ships are <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> westward, whereto all ships make, that are bound for <em>England</em>. One of <em>Bristol</em> ships, of which I wrote you last was taken half a league from <em>Scilly</em> and though one of our ships pursued them thence 48 hours as the Master of that ship which was taken, since hath informed me, and the <em>Brest</em> man of war of 38 Guns towed her, yet could not reach her.</p>

<p>I should have informed you that the last week a <reg orig="Bakers">Baker's</reg> house in the middle of this City was set on fire, but quenched before it had taken hold on any other house, it might probably have otherwise destroyed the chief part of the City, and was a great Mercy.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3">From Falmouth, February 1.</head>

<p>In the <em>Patrick</em> of <em><reg orig="Liverpoole">Liverpool</reg></em>, which we lately recovered from the <em>Brest</em> men of War, was one <em>Walter Roche</em>, who was to carry her to <em>Brest</em>, and he informed us, that there are these Ships following belonging to <em>Brest</em>, who do so vex us in these Seas, <em>viz.</em></p>

<p>The <em>Royal James</em>, with 38 guns; Richard <em>Beach</em> Commander.</p>
<p>The <em>Michael</em>, 14 guns <em>James Smith.</em></p>
<p>The <em>Briget</em> with 8 guns; <em>William Smith.</em></p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> 10 guns; <unclear><em>Meldrium</em></unclear>.</p>
<p>The <em>Mall</em> 10 guns; <em>Covel</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Loyal James</em> with 12 guns <unclear><em>Tom</em></unclear> <em>Dillon</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Saint Mary</em> 4 guns; <em>Richard D</em></p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> with 22 Guns; <em>Martin</em>.</p>
<p>The &mdash; with 8 guns; <em>Jones</em></p>
<p>The <em>Patrick</em> with 18 guns; <em>Swart</em></p>
<p>The <em>Katherine</em> with 6 guns; <em>Estmond</em></p>
<p>The <unclear><em>Small</em></unclear> <em>Michael</em> with 6 guns; <em>Peters</em></p>
<p>The <em>Snow</em> with 4 guns; <em>Nich. Murro</em></p>
<p>The <em>Adventure</em> with 2 guns; <em>George Lodde</em></p>
<p>Three <em>French men</em> with 15. 18. 20.</p>
<p>Three in the Stocks of 4 guns <reg orig="apeece">apiece</reg>.</p>

<p>These commonly lie about the <em><reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end</em> and <em>Lundy</em> easterly winds, and 10 or 20 leagues to the westward or <em>Scilly</em> westerly winds. Their Prizes are always sent for <em>Brest</em>, or <em>Port-Lewis</em>. We hope we shall suppress this perverse generation of <reg orig="Free-booters">Freebooters</reg> and Pirates.</p>

<p>The <em>Helena</em> we towed in here, and do hope the St. <em>Martin</em> is in <em>Plymouth</em>, having towed her within four leagues of the <em>Ram head</em> this morning. The <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> we have sent to the <em>Middleburgh</em> about the <reg orig="Lands-end">Land's End</reg>; we shall sit ourselves for Sea again suddenly.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dalkeith, January 31.</em></head>

<p>The enemy went for <em>Ross</em> and the Hills, as Col. <em>Morgan</em> <pb n="13" /><reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> from <em>Aberdeen</em> towards them, who is returned to his Quarters. Major <em><reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg></em> Cornet with a party of <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment took <em><reg orig="Glencarnes">Glencarne's</reg></em> Capt.Lt and 5 others, horsemen. A party of 40 <reg orig="Scotchmen">Scotsmen</reg> under one <unclear><em>Forgison</em></unclear>, employed by us on Saturday last, fell into <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> quarters, about 4 miles from <em>Glams</em>, took a Captain Lieutenant and Cornet, and 15 other Prisoners, with 20 horse and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> ten.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg>, February 6. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>I advised you in my last that the Lord <em>Beverning</em>, one of the three Commissioners was returned into <em>England</em>, with the Ratification of <em>Holland</em>, which is contradicted by man, that he is gone with no such Message, but that <em>Holland</em> and <em>Zealand</em> are both resolved to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> it with the very first, in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> it would be very <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> for us, if we might have a cessation of Arms, which we hope will be granted and obtained by the means of our Commissioner the Lord <em>Beverning</em>. The 26 of the last month month the Lord <em>Chaimt</em>, Ambassador of <em>France</em>, had Audience in the Assembly of the States General, wherein he represented the Interest of the King his Master. It is thought he will receive an answer agreeable to his mind, in favour of those <reg orig="fignal">final</reg> testimonies of amity which this Commonwealth hath already received from that Crown. The Elector of <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em> hath declared that he is willing to enter into the defensive Alliance to be concluded between the Elector of <em>Cullen</em> and the States of these Provinces. Our new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> are making ready with all the haste that may be; some of them will be quite finished about the middle of <em>March</em> next; but we hope we shall not <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> them in the service they were first intended for.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Upsall">Upsala</reg></em> in <em>Sweden, January 5.</em></head>

<p>The Festivals are not yet past, and that is the reason why the Senators are not here; and our Negotiation doth at present make a little Pause. The grand <reg orig="Chancelor">Chancellor</reg> is expected here very suddenly; who as yet hath not been here since the Court came to this place. I suppose it will not now be long ere they meet to debate upon the Articles given in, and so return some answer thereunto.</p>

<pb n="14" />

<p>There is lately arrived here an <em><reg orig="Envoye">Envoy</reg></em> from <em>Russia</em>, who hath brought a Letter from the great Duke or Emperor to this Queen. On Tuesday last he had his Audience. Some whisperings there are as if this State had meant to attempt upon that Country, and therefore the Duke hath sent this message to prevent it; and to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, that he will be ready to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with this Queen, to help her against the <em>Pole</em>: But of this we have no certainty.</p>

<p>Here is a rumour of an Extraordinary Ambassador coming hither from <em>France</em>, and another from <em>Holland</em>. You may expect within a little while some account of this Affair. The <em>Swede</em> will be put to it for a speedy answer.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dublin, January</em> 25.</head>

<p>News here is none; <unclear>all thing</unclear> continue quiet.</p>

<p>The Irish have of late had a general Fast, the occasion is not known unless to themselves, nor what <unclear>expectation</unclear> they have.</p>

<head level="3">From Dalkeith, January 31.</head>

<p>Upon the March of Col. Morgan from Aberdeen, the Enemy hastened their march out of Murrayland towards Ross and the Hills; so that Colonel Morgan returned back to Aberdeen without doing <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against them; only Major <reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg> Cornet with a party of that Regiment, took <reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg> Capt. Lieut. And 5 horsemen, and sent them prisoners to <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>. There being a party of <reg orig="Scotchmen">Scotsmen</reg> who have formerly done good service in a familiar party, the Commander in chief gave them <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> to raise about 40 horse, with which they have more advantage to come upon the enemy (by their Scotch tone) <reg orig="then">than</reg> our forces have.</p>

<p>On <reg orig="Saturdoy">Saturday</reg> last this party fell upon the <pb n="15" />Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Guards took a Capt. A Lieutenant, Cornet and 15 other prisoners, with 20 horse, and killed 9 or 10 in all: and 2 or 3 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> before sent in a Captain and another horseman prisoners, to <em>Dundee</em>. The Ministers in these parts daily praying for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> as their King, for <unclear>which</unclear> they pretend conscience, the Commander in chief <unclear>hath secured</unclear> divers of them. There is a very strange report here, That the Lord of Seafort hath stormed our Fort <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters then "sland"-->island</unclear> with 1400 men, and taken it, which I cannot believe, in regard the <unclear>Governor</unclear> there was confident to defend it against thousands yet it is certain that Seafort was <unclear>preparing</unclear> to attempt it, &amp; we had no ship on those coasts.</p>

<head level="3"><em>London</em> February 8.</head> 

<p>An entertainment was given to his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, in a very magnificent manner, by the city of <em>London</em>. His Highness being very nobly attended by his <unclear>council</unclear> and the Officers of the Army, his own Life guard <unclear>and many</unclear> persons of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, was met by the Lord Mayor and the <unclear><!--3 characters: Aldermen?-->men</unclear> his brethren at <em>Temple-Bar</em> where his Highness <unclear>alighting</unclear> out of his Coach, <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> horse. The <unclear><em>Recorder</em></unclear> presented the <unclear><!--4-5 characters--></unclear> and duty of the City in an eloquent Speech; the Streets <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> Railed all along from the Temple with seats (wherein <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> all the Companies of the City in their Livery-Gowns) <unclear>as far as</unclear> <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall, which was the place appointed to <unclear>Feast</unclear> his Highness. Being come in, the Recorder made another Speech (but more brief) to let his Highness understand how happy the City were in the enjoyment of his Person. After he had done, his Highness having retired himself awhile above stairs, came down to dine in the great Hall, where he <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> in the middle of a long Table his Son the Lord <em>Henry</em> on the left hand, and the Lord Mayor on the right, and on each side of them the Council, General <em>Monk</em> Commissary Gen. <em>Whalley</em>, and Mr. <em>Claypole</em>, Master of the horse to his Highness, being entertained (besides <reg orig="Cheare">Cheer</reg> ) with <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>, Voices, Drums, and Trumpets. After this his Highness was conducted upstairs again by my Lord Mayor, to a noble Banquet. This being done, his Highness departed, being <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> out by <reg orig="Hoboys">Hautboys</reg> and other loud <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>. In all which this famous City have by these solemn expressions of affection to his highness, given a good example to the rest of the Nation, being sensible of the great benefits they are like to enjoy under his Protection and Government.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">There is published a satisfactory Piece Entitled,</head>
<head level="3">&#x261e;<i>A true State of the Case of the Commonwealth, &amp;c.</i></head>
<p>In reference to the late established Government by a <em>Lord Protector and a Parliament</em>. Fit to be perused by all. To be sold at the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Booksellers">Booksellers'</reg> shops.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>