<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol203">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 203</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, April 27. to <em>Thursday</em>, May 4. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Leith April 20.</i></head>

<p>The Enemy continues still in the North, <em>Middleton</em> drawing into <em>Sutherland</em>; <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> he must attempt with speed, because the Hills will not <reg orig="yeild">yield</reg> sufficient to feed him and his Forces; but how he will get Southward is a question, having a great River on this side of him, and all other Passes so well guarded by our forces.</p>

<p>They have lately had some quarrels amongst Themselves about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> and Command, which have somewhat retarded their Levies, and disjointed them among <reg orig="Themselvs">Themselves</reg>; so that some are retired through discontent. If so be we could hear of a confirmation of the Dutch peace, I <pb n="1" />believe more would desert them, and look to the securing of their private Fortunes, because many have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> drawn to engage, <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> by Brags and reports of great assistance from abroad, especially out of the United Provinces.</p>

<p>We hear not yet of Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> remove from <em>Dingwell</em>, nor of any Attempts made thereabout by the Enemy.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall, March</i> 31. S: V.</head>

<p>My Lord Ambassador presses very earnestly to have conclusion of his long attendance, and he had Audience both <reg orig="to day">today</reg> and yesterday. The Queen seems now to be in good earnest to lay down her Crown. She did discharge last week most of all her Servants and Retinue, and hath reserved to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> a very <reg orig="thinn">thin</reg> Court. I must profess I understand not the mystery of it; She professes her desires of Solitude and retirement: and some others say, The Debts grew so high, that she was, as it were, forced hereunto. But whether any other secret thing is couched under it, Time will discover. Don <em>Piemontelli</em>, the Spanish Resident had audience on Wednesday last, and took his leave of here Majesty. He intends to take his Journey homewards within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, by the way of <em>Denmark</em>. I believe he doth not well relish our <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg> of Peace with <em>Holland</em>. He hath <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> it very fair to my Lord Ambassador. But we think we espy some little alteration in him, since the news of the Treaty being almost finished hath arrived here; <em>Spain</em> would have gladly kept us still at odds. </p><pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>From Copenhagen, April</i> 9. S: N.</head>

<p>A Dispatch is come on here from <em>Holland</em>, bringing news that those States had fully <reg orig="condiscended">condescended</reg> to the Articles of the Lord Protector, concerning the satisfaction for the English ships that were detained here. This Court is glad that the returning of the ships, Goods, and Guns, in the condition they are in at present, is all that is demanded of them (the <em>Hollanders</em> having engaged to pay for the <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>) and are now very confident shortly to understand the full conclusion of Peace with <em>England</em>. It is said here, the Prince Palatine who is to succeed the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> in that Crown, is shortly to marry with the Duke of <em>Holsteins</em> daughter; which is thought will cause somewhat a more strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between the two Crown of <em>Denmark</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, as hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> heretofore.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Regensborgh">Regensburg</reg>, April</i> 6. S: N.</head>

<p>The States have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> assembled about the departure of his <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> majesty, being appointed on the 28 of this month, S: N: without <reg orig="faile">fail</reg>; to which end about 130 ships <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> ready upon the <em>Donaw</em>, to attend his Majesty and the Court. The Swedish Ambassadors did in the said Assembly highly protest against his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> so sudden departure, <reg orig="alledging">alleging</reg>, That upon that account the <em>Instrumentum pacis</em> would not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> not be satisfied, but rather in all particulars unreasonably violated, and a more heavy and insupportable <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> laid upon the almost languishing States of the Empire, if at least his said Majesty were not pleased most graciously to continue the <pb n="3" />Rixday <em>per Deputatos</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> such time as they might be able with better order and leisure to dispatch such business as are of most importance. News is come to the Emperors Court, that a disguised party of 250 horse, had <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> upon the Troops which conveyed the Du: of <em>Lorain</em> from <em>Antwerp</em> to <em>Genee</em>, with such fury, that without doubt they had quickly <reg orig="master'd">mastered</reg> them, and freed the Duke, if the Spanish <reg orig="Avantguard">Avant-garde</reg> had not come in to their succour; by whose assistance the said disguised party were all slain, save only 13 persons; who being taken Prisoners, were condemned to be hanged at <em>Genee</em> aforesaid; from whence the said Duke is to be transported for <em>Spain</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick, 18 dito,</i> S. N.</head>

<p>Out of <em>Poland</em> no other <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, but that the King hath now bestowed the <em>Littawship Blanck</em> on Prince <em>Radzevil</em>, but the <em>Ryx blanck</em> his Majesty reserves for himself, saying, <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> knows no person more worthy of it. A new Convention is voted in June next, where if the matter be not compounded, it is like to turn into a Rokes, that is to say, into an honest Rebellion.</p>

<p>In our last we promised to give you account of those persons in <em>Scotland</em> who are admitted to compound for their Estates, that is to say, <em>David Lesley</em> late Lieut. <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Scottish Army 4000<em>l</em>. Sterling, Marquis of <em>Douglas</em> 1000<em>l</em>. sterl. Earl of <unclear><em>Selorigg</em></unclear> 1000<em>l</em>. sterl. The heir of <em>Francis</em> late Earl of Bucleuch deceased 1500<em>l</em> sterl. Earl of Galloway 4000<em>l.</em> sterl.<em> William</em> Earl of Roxburgh 6000 <em>l</em>. sterl. <em>William</em> Lord <pb n="4" />Cockeram, 5000 l. sterling. <em>James</em> Lord Forester, 2500l. sterling. <em>Philip Amstuther</em> son of Sir <em>Robert Amstruther</em>, 1000 marks sterl. Sir <em>Archibald Sterling</em> of <em>Carden</em>, 1500l. sterl. <em>James Drummond</em> of <em>Mackensey</em>, 500 l. sterl. <em>Henry Mawl</em>, son to the Earl of <em>Panmure</em>, 2500l. st. Sir <em>James Levingston</em> of <em>Kilsith</em>, 1500 l. sterl. <em>William Murray </em>of <em>Polemaise</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Buchane</em>, 1000 l. Sterl. Viscount <em>Dudope</em>, 1500 sterl. <em>Preston </em>of <em>Cragmiller</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Sir <em>Andrew Flesher</em> of <em>Inner Pether</em>, 5000 l. sterl. Sir <em>John Wauchab</em> of <em>Netherey</em>, 2000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Perth</em>, and Lord <em>Drummond</em> his eldest son, 5000 l sterl. Earl of <em>Winton</em>, 2000 l. ster. Earl of <em>Findlater</em>, 1500 l. st. Earl of <em>Murray</em>, 3500 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Quinsburgh</em>, 4000l. sterl. Earl of <em>Eithy</em>, 6000l. sterl. Lord <em>Duffus</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Lord <em>Grey</em>, 1500 l. sterling. Sir <em>Henry Nisbett</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Panmure</em>, 10000 l. sterl. Laird of <em>Lundee</em>, 1000 l sterl. Earl of <em>Arroll</em>, 2000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Tullibardine</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Sowthesk</em>, 3000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Daulhousie</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Hartfield</em>, 2000. Sterl. <em>William</em> Lord <em>Ross</em>, 3000 l. sterl. Lord <em>Samyle</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Lord <em>Elphinston</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Lord<em> Boide</em>, 1500 l. sterl. <em>James</em> Lord <em>Cooper</em>, 3000 l. sterl. Lord <em>Balvaird</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Lord <em>Rollock</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Kinghorn</em> 1000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Kinkardine</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Lord <em>Bamse</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Mr. <em>Robert Meldrum</em> of <em>Tillybody</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Sir <em>Robert Graham </em>of <unclear><em>Morphie</em></unclear> 1000 l. ster. Sir <em>William</em> <em>Scot </em>of <em>Harden</em> <unclear>3000</unclear> l. sterl. <em>Hay </em>of <em>Nachton</em>, 1000 l. sterl. <unclear><em>Remon</em></unclear> of <em>Lamberton</em>, 1000 l. sterl. <pb n="5" /><em>Colquhoun</em> of <em>Luz </em>2000 l. sterl. <em>Hamilton</em> of <em>Preston</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Mr <em>Francis Hay </em>of <em>Bowsey</em>, 2000l. sterl. <em>Arnot</em> of <em> Ferney</em>, 2000 l. sterl. Sir <em>Robert Forqubar</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Sir <em>Francis Reven</em>, 3000 l. st. <em>Scot </em>of <em>Montross</em>, 3000 l. st. Larid of <em>Rothemegordon</em>, 500 l. sterl. <em>Colerney</em>, the younger, 1000 l. sterl. Sir <em>John Scot</em> of <em>Scots-Tarbut</em>, 1500 l. sterl. Laird of <em>Gosfrid</em>, 1000l. sterl. Laird of <em>Bachilton</em>, 1500 l. sterl. <em>James Mercer</em> of <em>Aldey</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Earl of <em>Rothes</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Lieut. Col. <em>Elliot </em>of <em>Stebbs</em>, 1000 l. sterl. Sir <em>Lewis Stuart</em>, Advocate, 1000 l. sterling. Patrick<em> Scot </em>of <em>Thirlstone</em>, 2000 l. sterling.<em> </em>Sir <em>James Caimeghil</em>, 2000 l. sterl. Sir <em>Patrick Cockborn</em> of <em>Clarkington</em>, 2000 l. sterl. Sir <em>George Morison</em> of <em>Preston-Grange</em>, 2000 l. sterl. <em>Murrey</em>, Laird of <em>Stanhop</em>, son to Sir <em>David Murrey</em> deceased, 2000 l. sterl. All and every which sum and <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of money, shall be paid unto <em>George Bilton</em>, Deputy Treasurer at <em>Leith</em>; one <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg> thereof, on, or by the second day of <em>August</em>, 1654; and the other <reg orig="moyetie">moiety</reg>, on, or by the 2 of <em>Decemb.</em> Then next ensuing; and in default of such payment, all and every person and persons so making default; shall from thenceforth be absolutely confiscate; and the Commissioners for <reg orig="Sequestrations">Sequestration</reg> are hereby <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to seize the same accordingly.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, April </i> 27.</head>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors (the Peace having <reg orig="bin">been</reg> <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> proclaimed the day before) were very nobly entertained and feaster by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, May</i> 4. S:N:</head>

<p>The continuing of some English <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> upon the French coast, doth give fresh Alarms to the Court here, who have sent 2 Regiments to Rochel to reinforce that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: From whence they write, That the English have lately taken 42 of their ships laden with Wines; which doth very much trouble the fancies of our Grandees here. The King and Cardinal, with the rest of the Court, are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to divert themselves at Fontainbleau, for a week or a Fortnight, and from thence to return hither again to celebrate the memory of the death of the King his Father.</p>

<p>Here is a fresh Report of the Kings going, after he hath ended that ceremony, to Rheims, there to be Crowned. Notice is said to be given to all the Nobility and their followers, to wait upon him there for that purpose. The Italian Ball or Masque was represented for the last time before the King went out of Town. Notwithstanding the report of a Truce with Spain for Ten years, the Hangman hath defaced the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> of the Prince of Conde, which were painted over the <reg orig="dore">door</reg> of his Palace in this City, which the Prince of Conti did all <reg orig="what">that</reg> he could to prevent; but he could not prevail, the Cardinal would have it done.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and Prince Rupert are still at Daggers drawing about the Guns of the Swallow which have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> twice sold; it seems, once by Pr: Rupert, and afterwards by <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart to the Cardinal; who coming to demand his money of him for the Guns, Prince Rupert <reg orig="tels">tells</reg> him he had <pb n="7" />sold them before to another, as Goods belonging to him: This is likely to breed a deadly quarrel between them. And the truth is, the business is no better <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Cheat on either side; &amp; <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> <reg orig="som">some</reg> think they will understand one another <reg orig="wel">well</reg> enough in the end.</p>

<p>If you will have any more news, you must <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Pope Innocent the Tenth, who is now going to his grave; his death will make the Johnsonists high in France, and will occasion some tumults in the Clergy there.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels May</i> 3. S. N.</head>

<p>This day Francis Duke of Lorain, with his two sons are expected at Lovain, and <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> here in Town, where his lodgings are made ready for him at Court. The Field Preparations here advance but slowly, in regard that they <reg orig="doe">do</reg> stay to see what end and success the French Treaty will take in England; for as that business takes effect, so they intend to order their <reg orig="Campagne">Campaign</reg> preparations accordingly.</p>

<p>There come every day great store of Irish Soldiers to serve the Prince of Conde, who are no sooner <reg orig="enter'd">entered</reg> into pay, but they are presently debauched by the French, and made to serve in their Troops.</p>

<p>The Ambassador of France, Monsieur <em>Vautorte</em>, <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> at Ratisbone the 19 of the last month.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dover, April 25.</i></head>

<p>Yesterday in the Evening came into this Road a private man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, being a Marget Hoy of 6 Guns, and about fifty men, who having found a Dutch ship in the <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the <pb n="8" />West-Indies that had been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent through tediousness of the voyage, did of a <reg orig="suddain">sudden</reg> clap them aboard, and after a little dispute become Master of her, and brought her along with them. The ship is said to be of great value; for, beside Plate, whereof is said there is a good quantity, there are other rich Commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rotterdam</i>, May 1.</head>

<p>It would be a vain thing to trouble you with the recital of the odd reports these parts are filled with in the intervals of Posts, but let them die with their begetters, for notwithstanding that the Articles are ratified by the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg>, and sent over to be ratified in <em>England</em> likewise, yet the incredulity and doubts of some are yet so great, that they will not <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> that there is a Peace till they hear it published, and that they do assist at the <reg orig="Bone fires">Bonfires</reg>, and it may be then they will give credit to it, though I think there are some that will hardly believe their own eyes; indeed here is much of the <em>Thomas</em> though but little of the Apostleship amongst us: yet our merchants are rigging and making ready to hoist sail with the first wind that shall assure them of a safe passage. It is thought that as soon as the Ratification is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> here will be a terrible reducing and cashiering of the Militia, on purpose to be good husbands for the State.</p>

<p>It is said here that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath resigned her Crown, and is expected this Summer at the <em>Spaw</em>, where <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Steuart">Stuart</reg></em> and his brother <pb n="9" />with the rest of that crew, do intend to meet here there and divert themselves at the season.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dublin</i>, April 6. 1654.</head> 

<p>Since my Lord <em>Henry</em> left us, things have been very Calm and well here, and so have persons. This day there met a General <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers to consider of some proposals to be sent to his Highness touching the four Counties reserved from the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> security, and the way and manner of satisfying Arrears. And <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> a Paper was presented signed by several chief Officers and to be after signed by the whole, in way of approbation of the present Government that thereby the <reg orig="Scandall">Scandal</reg> which lay on <reg orig="som">some</reg> Regiments, as if they were unsatisfied, might be taken off which begot a Letter congratulatory to his Highness to that purpose, it is engrossed in parchment, and signed by a numerous Company of Officers, indeed all for ought I hear except two or three, and will be sent by an Express to his Highness. Coll. <em>Herbert</em> is chosen Secretary of State.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Chester</i>, April 29.</head>

<p>Coll. <em>Alured</em> who is said to be bound for <em>Ireland</em> to draw down some Forces to the Sea side to be <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> for <em>Scotland</em> is here arrived and gone to <em><reg orig="Leverpole">Liverpool</reg></em> in order to the providing of shipping and Provisions. The Lord hath been gracious to this City in <reg orig="onely">only</reg> shaking his Rod of Pestilence over it; for since we humbled <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> before him in two solemn <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Fasting, now eleven <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> past it hath stayed, and not one person dead in any house shut up, nor in the <reg orig="Cabbins">Cabins</reg>, <pb n="10" />nor is it farther broken out or dispersed then in the first 8 Families out of which only ten in all <reg orig="dyed">died</reg>, and they most of them Children; and since not one is sick that I hear of. Col. <em>Venables</em> is here <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> out of <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<head level="3">May 2. Came a Proclamation abroad <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> thus:</head>

<head level="3">By the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<p><i>A Proclamation of his Highness concerning a Cessation of all Acts of Hostility between the Commonwealth of England, and that of the United Provinces, and their respective People, and the restitution of all things taken and <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> upon by either party, after the fourth of this instant May.</i></p>

<p><em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland,</em> and the Dominions thereto belonging: Whereas the Commissioners appointed by us to Treat with the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the United Provinces, and the said Ambassadors, by way of Explanation of the third of those Articles of Peace, lately concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Netherlands, and for removing all questions and differences which may arise thencefrom, have agreed and concluded the following Article, viz. [That whereas in the third of those Articles of Peace, Union and confederation made, established, and <reg orig="promulged">promulgated</reg> between the <em>Lord Protector</em> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland, </em>and <em>Ireland,</em> and the Lords of the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg> of the United Provinces, it is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges and Damages, which either party hath sustained by the other since the 18, &amp; 28 of May, in the year 1652. shall be taken away and forgotten in such manner as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any <reg orig="mater">matter</reg> against the other, for, on occasion of any the aforesaid Injuries, Charges, and Damages, but that there shall a perfect abolition of all and every of them until this present day. And all Actions for the same shall be held and reputed void and null, excepting such <reg orig="depradations">depredations</reg> as shall be committed by either fine in these Seas after the space of twelve days, and in all other places on this side the Cape of <em>St Vincent</em>, after six weeks, and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean </em>Sea, and to the <em>Equinoctial</em> Line after ten weeks; and beyond the <em>Equinoctial</em> Line, after the space of Eight Months, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places.] And whereas certain questions may possibly <unclear>arise</unclear> about the fore rehearsed words, which may minister occasion of debates and disputes, The said Lord Protector, and the said <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> to the end all manner of <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> and difference may be removed, which might arise by Reason of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> <pb n="11" />in the aforesaid Article contained, Have unanimously accorded and agreed, and do by these Presents publish and declare to all and singular their People and Subjects respectively, That immediately after publication of the Treaty of Peace, which is already done, all Acts of hostility shall immediately cease in all places expressed in the said Article, and in all others wheresoever. And that all <reg orig="depradations">depredations</reg>, damages and injuries which shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> alone or committed by one party against the other after the fourth day of this instant May, in all places whatever, mentioned in the aforesaid Article, or <reg orig="elswhere">elsewhere</reg>, as well on this side the Line as beyond, shall be accounted for. And all things taken or seized after the abovesaid fourth of May, shall be restored without any Form of Process, as also damages growing by occasion thereof. And to the end this Agreement and Article may be the better known both parties shall publish the same within their respective Territories and Dominions, and <reg orig="straitly">stringently</reg> charge and command as well their ships of War, as others, whether in Port, or at Sea, to observe the same.</p>

<p>Wherefore we having considered what is agreed as aforesaid, have confirmed and ratified, as <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same by these presents, which we have caused to be published, that all persons concerned therein may take notice thereof. And we <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby <reg orig="straitly">stringently</reg> charge and require all the ships of War, and others, either belonging to the State, or to any particular persons set forth upon private Commissions, or otherwise, to observe the said Agreement. And to the end none may pretend ignorance herein, The Commissioners of the Admiralty are hereby required to give <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> notice hereof to all the ships of War of this State, either at Sea, or in Port, within these Dominions or elsewhere. And the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty are also by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of these Presents, forthwith to call on upon their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Securities given in that Court, all such ships as have been set forth upon private Commissions against the United Provinces, or the People thereof. Given at Whitehall this First of May, in the year 1654.</p>

<p><i>In witness whereof as will the Lords Commissioners of his Highness, we the Ambassadors extraordinary of the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>, have signed these Presents with their own hands. Done at Westminster the <unclear>18</unclear> of <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>, Old style in the year 1654.</i></p>

<p>H: Laurence <em>Pres.</em>	H:Beverningok.</p>
<p>Gilb: Pickering, Wil: Nieupoort.</p>
<p>E: Mountague, Alar, P: Jongestall.</p>
<p>Walt: Strickland.</p> <pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>The Articles of perpetual Peace between us and the <em>Dutch</em> being translated out of the Dutch copy, and published, I have abbreviated, and give you the sum of them, as followeth.</i></head>

<p>1. That from henceforward there shall be a firm unchangeable Peace, sincere friendship, and <reg orig="streighter">straighter</reg> alliance, confederation and union than ever heretofore, between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> and the <reg orig="States General">States-General</reg> of the United Netherlandish Provinces, and the respective Lands, Countries, and Cities <reg orig="every where">everywhere</reg> under their obedience, wheresoever they are situate, and their People and Inhabitants of what quality or condition soever they be.</p>

<p>2. That from henceforwards, all enmity, hostility, <reg orig="dissention">dissension</reg>, and war, between the said two Commonwealths, and their People and Subjects shall cease, and that either party shall henceforwards abstain from all offences, spoils, depredations, and injuries, <reg orig="aswell">as well</reg> at Sea as at Land, and in Fresh-waters, in all their respective Lands, Countries, Dominions, places, or Governments whatsoever.</p>

<p>3. That all offences, injuries, costs and damages, which either party hath suffered by the other, shall be abolished and forgotten so that henceforward neither party shall pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other, for or by reason of any such damage, offence, injury, or costs, but that there shall be a perfect abolishment of all and every the same, unto this present day, and that all actions touching the same shall be held taken for null and of no value, except such Depredations as shall be done in the British seas after the term of 12 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and from the said seas unto the Cape of St Vincent after the term of 6 weeks, and from thence into the Mediterranean sea and to the Line after the term of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to be accounted from the day of the publication of the Peace, or immediately after that sufficient notice of the Peace shall be given in the said places; and all depredations and spoils committed and done by either party after the said terms, or notice given as aforesaid, shall be accounted of and restitution thereof made, as also of the damages arising through means or occasion of the same.</p>

<p>4. That all prisoners on both sides, of what condition or <pb n="13" />quality soever they be, shall be released, without paying any ransom or consideration for the same.</p>

<p>5. That the two Commonwealths shall remain confederated friends, united, and allied for the defence and preservation of the Liberties and Freedoms of the people of either, against all whomsoever who shall endeavour to disturb either State by Sea or Land, or being declared Enemies of the Freedoms and Liberties of the People, do shelter themselves under either of the said Governments.</p>

<p>6. That neither Commonwealth may do, act, or undertake against the other, nor the people of wither do or consent to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to the prejudice or injury of one another.</p>

<p>7. That neither shall help, counsel, or favour the enemies or rebels of either, nor supply them with ships, arms, ammunition, or other <reg orig="Contrabanda">Contraband</reg> goods, or money, victuals; and if any be used against the intent of this Article, they shall be confiscated, and the persons wittingly or willingly so offending be declared enemies of both Commonwealths, and be punished as Traitors: And as touching the specification of <reg orig="Contrabanda">Contraband</reg> goods, it shall be done in due time by Commissioners which shall be named to that purpose, with this Proviso that in the mean time it shall not prejudice <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in this Article.</p>

<p>8. That the two Commonwealths shall assist each other against the Enemies and Rebels of either, at the cost and charge of the Parties who desire the same &amp;c.</p>

<p>9. That neither of them, nor the People of either, shall not within their dominions havens or any part of them, &amp;c. receive any who are or shall be declared Enemies, Rebels, or Fugitives be either, nor in any wise relieve them &amp;c. but rather hinder and oppose the same.</p>

<p>10. That if either Commonwealth shall by Letters unto the other declare, that any Enemies Rebels and Fugitives do hide themselves in the territories of either, then they are to command them to depart within 28 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> to be accounted from the day of notice given; and <unclear>in case</unclear> the said Enemies &amp;c. do not depart within <unclear>15 days after command given, then they are to be punished with death, and <!--approx. 4 words--> goods.</unclear></p><pb n="14" />

<p>11. That no Rebel or declared Enemy of <em>England</em> whatsoever, shall be harboured in any Castles, Cities, Havens, Creeks, or other places, &amp;c. belonging to the United Provinces, nor be there in any wise relieved or favoured; and if any Governors or Officers infringe this, they shall for term of their lives lose and forfeit their Commands, Offices, Lands, &amp;c. The Like Provision and Penalties are made also by this Article, to prevent the harbouring or relieving of any declared Enemy or Rebel of the <em>United Provinces</em>, in <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>12. That the people of either may freely and friendly trade to and fro, by Water and Land, in all places fortified and <reg orig="unfortified">not fortified</reg>, situate in Europe, not paying any higher Customs or Duties, then other Foreign Nations, trading in either, do.</p>

<p>It is likewise added in this Article, <i>That they may trade in any goods and Commodities that they please, and to import and export the same as they please</i>: But this Translation which pretends to be faithfully done according to the Dutch <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> omits one main and principal Clause immediately following, which remains in the Original, under the broad Seal of that Country, which is this [<i>Salvis etiam alterutrius pariter reipub. Legibus &amp; statutis omnibus</i>; that is to say, <i>Saving all the Laws and Statutes of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> respectively.</i>] This should have been added in this Article, but the Translators (for what reason I know not) thought fit to omit it. <i>Therefore it will be best for the Reader to see the true <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg>, now printed by his Highness Printers, and not trust a Pamphlet that is set forth without any name to own it.</i></p>

<p>13. That the ships and vessels of the <em>United Provinces</em> as well Men of War as others, meeting in the Narrow Seas, commonly called the <em>British Seas</em>, any Men of War of the State of <em>England</em>, they shall strike the flag, and let fall the fore-<reg orig="sale">sail</reg> in such manner as the same hath been observed in former times in any Government.</p>

<p>14. The 14. Provides against the harbouring of Pirates and Sea-Rovers, in the Havens &amp;c. of either &amp;c.</p>

<p>15. That in case either <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> do make any Treaty of Amity or Alliance with any <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg>, Princes, or States, they shall comprehend each other therein, with all their dominions, if they desire to be comprehended; and that either shall be bound to give the other notice of such Treaties.</p>

<p>16. That if any of the People of either, chance to do or attempt <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against this Treaty, &amp;c. nevertheless the Alliance shall not thereby be broken or interrupted, but only the offending persons be punished, and satisfaction given to the persons injured, within certain limited times, as is more at large set down in this Article; and if the persons offending do not give satisfaction within the times there set down, they are to be declared Enemies to both Commonwealths, and to have their estates and goods confiscated, and their persons punished accordingly, &amp;c.</p>

<p>17. That the people of either &amp;c. may pass to and fro in all Quarters of the United Provinces, and in England, Scotland, or Ireland, but in case armed, not above 40 in company, to drive Trade, &amp;c.</p> <pb n="15" />

<p>18. That all ships of either, who shall by storm or pirates be driven into the havens, &amp;c. of either Commonwealth, may depart without paying custom, molestation, or searching Provided, they do not break bulk nor receive any persons or goods aboard, or otherwise offend.</p>

<p>19. That the Merchants &amp; Seamen of either, with their ships, goods, &amp;c. shall not be arrested in the Lands, Havens, and Rivers of the other, to serve at war or otherwise unless upon as inevitable necessity, and upon having satisfaction for the same.</p>

<p>20. That the Merchants on both sides, with their Factors, and Servants, Skippers, and others travelling, may, when they go on Land in either Country, use all sorts of weapons for defence and offence, but being come into their Lodgings or Inns, they shall there lay by their arms, until they return again on board.</p>

<p>21. That the men if war of either Commonwealth, meeting or hailing at sea any Merchants ships or shipping belonging to the said Commonwealths, holding the same course, or going the same warm shall be bound as long as they keep one course together, to protect and defend them against all and singular, who would attempt <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against them.</p>

<p><i>There remain yet twelve Articles more, which not being to be contracted into so narrow a compass, as part of a Pamphlet, I must for them, refer you till the next.</i></p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dublin</em>, 15 April, 1654.</head>

<p>The General Council hath proceeded so far, as to resolve to cast Lots who shall be in each Province. The General Officers are fallen in Munster. A letter owning the Government of the Lord Protector is also signed unanimously, and to be sent by Officers of quality. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> feared the Lands will fall short of satisfying the whole Arrears, and therefore the standing Army who have Arrears due since June, 1649. are consent to take but two thirds at present, leaving the other as a pawn for their brethren who have Arrears due before 1649. until either more can be found upon an exact survey (for as yet we compare only by the gross) or that more be got from England, and then take in their pawn again.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dalkeith</em>, 25. April, 1654.</head>

<p>&#x25a0; There hath little of <reg orig="Concernment">Concern</reg> happened since General <em>Monks</em> arrival here, Col. <em>Morgan</em> with his brigade lieth still at <em>Dingwell</em>, and the enemy under<em> Middleton</em> in <em>Sutherland</em>, most of their forces being lately drawn from all parts towards the North. So that there are not so many <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> parties in the Lowlands as formerly, only some few in <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em> and <em>Galloway</em>. A party of about thirty (which are under the English Capt. Lieut. to <em>Kenmore</em>) came about four days since to Provost <em><reg orig="Marburnies">Marburnie's</reg></em> house near <reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg>, which they burnt, and many goods. The Provost got to a little old Tower, which himself with half a dozen more held out against them. The Tories endeavouring to storm it, they killed 2 <em>English</em> and two more, and so secured themselves.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>