<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol195">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 195</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> March 2. to <em>Thursday</em> March 9. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Portsmouth March 1.</i></head>

<p>At present I have nothing to communicate of <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, you may talk of the <reg orig="Politicks">Politics</reg> of <em>Aristotle</em>, and those <reg orig="exercis'd">exercised</reg> of States abroad, but neither are comparable to the Merchants at Sea, who outwit you all. There is not one ship now that comes out to Sea, but hath free Passes, and Cockets, with Letters, to consign his Goods to persons that will own them, into whatsoever Port he or they shall be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> by any ship or ships, of or belonging to any Port or Ports of England or Scotland; so that if the <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> go on, then, till you have a War with all that speak not your language <pb n="1" />of <em>Canaan</em>, or (as one at a Council of war lately, not more bluntly <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="rationaly">rationally</reg> said) with all that speak <em>Ya</em>, or <em>Yea</em>. The Dutch <reg orig="wil">will</reg> maintain a Trade. I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> assure you, of 45 ships, and them <reg orig="Forainers">Foreigners</reg>, <reg orig="over-hawled">overhauled</reg> by the Taunton-<reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> since we were <reg orig="comanded">commanded</reg> to Sea, we found not any just reason to send above 3 of them in; <reg orig="tho">though</reg> I am bold to say three Thirds of the Goods were of Holland; and of them 3. two only endured the <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg> of a further sentence in the Admiralty Court, where <em>Quo jure, quinque injuria nescio</em>, they are acquitted; albeit they were <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg> and convicted Hollanders before sent in: so <reg orig="unproportion'd">unproportioned</reg> are the old Laws of the Admiralty, to the new Politic of the Merchant, at least in the Management. <i>Sed verbum sat.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>, Febr. 4.</i></head>

<p>The Enemy have divided themselves into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parties, to raise their assigned Levies, keeping themselves in secure places about the Brays for their safety, from whence they summon into the Country to provide both <reg orig="Hors">Horse</reg> and Foot, whom they threaten with Fire and Sword, if they neglect to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> them in their Demands, though never so unreasonable.</p>

<p><em>Glencairn</em> is to command all the Levies in these shires of Murray, and so Northward. He with 80 Horse and 100 Foot, keeps near the Hills, that upon notice of the approach of any of our Forces they may secure themselves in the inaccessible Bounds. Our Horse-Scouts now and then glean up some of them, having lately taken among others a notorious Rogue, that threatened <pb n="2" />to burn divers of the <reg orig="Inhabitants">Inhabitant's</reg> houses who are serviceable to the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsall, Feb. 3. S.V.</i></head>

<p>The Treaty with the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is followed very close; so that it is said that in the last conference between his Lordship and the grand Chancellor as they were in debate together, the Chancellor professed, That he had received full satisfaction to all his Objections; and afterwards related so much unto the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>. The grand <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of the Kingdom meets the next week; and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed the full determination of things is deferred till then. Sir <em>William Ballantines</em> and some other Cavaliers are observed about this Court, lurking to do what mischief they may.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Dantzick">Dantzig</reg> 18 Feb. S.N.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="Warsow">Warsaw</reg> of the 8. instant, we understand, That the Tartars, who as yet continue their robbing and plundering through this whole Kingdom have now taken a <reg orig="partyof">party of</reg> those 8000 horse that were sent after them, with the commander of the same <reg orig="cald">called</reg> <em>Sapiha</em>, a great Officer and <reg orig="favorite">favourite</reg> of the King. As also, that they had certain information there of the great Duke of <reg orig="Moscovies">Moscovy's</reg> decreed hostility against this Kingdom, being resolved to invade the same with 3 Armies in 3 sundry places. How this will be resented, and what it means to oppose the violence of the said Duke, will be pitched upon, the close of this Ryxday which is shortly expected, will discover.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>From Regensburgh, 14 dito, S: N.</i></head>

<p>It is feared that his Imperial Majesty <reg orig="wil">will</reg> very shortly, and it may be sooner, at is thought upon. move hence, it being very much talked of here; the more, because there is a new <reg orig="Visier">Vizier</reg> come on at Ossen, as also no Palatine in Hungaria; The Estates of which Kingdom <reg orig="doe">do</reg> urge very much upon a land day; all which, together with his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> great desire to go home, will doubtless more further then delay his departure. But whether his Majesty will leave any Commissioners or this Ryxday <reg orig="bee">be</reg> therewith concluded, time will discover.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 21 dito, S.V.</i></head>

<p>The Agent for the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> here, having purposed to build a seat for himself in the <em>Dutch</em> Protestant Church near this City, hath thereby so offended the <reg orig="Brandenburghers">Brandenburgers'</reg> Agent, (who likewise resides here) That <reg orig="som">some</reg> days ago he sent him a Challenge; but was slighted by the other who told him, That it did not become a man of his character to send Challenges, neither himself to answer the same.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Wentworth, <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> late Agent in Denmark, who is now here, and as it seems in want of money, thought to frighten the Treasurer of the English company out of a good sum by a bold threatening Message sent unto him by some of his Faction, That if he did not lend him the Money suddenly, he would cause him to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> affronted. But the Treasurer complaining of it to the President, and he to the Senate, they <reg orig="injoined">enjoined</reg> Wentworth not to meddle with him; who came off very poorly</p>

<pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall February 28.</i></head>

<p>It was Ordered by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, that the following Ordinance should be printed and published.</p>

<p><i>An Ordinance for reviving the Jurisdiction of the County Palatine of <em>Lancaster</em>, and for holding an <reg orig="Assises">Assizes</reg> there.</i></p>

<p>Be it Declared and Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That all <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> and Jurisdictions belonging to the County Palatine of <em>Lancaster</em>, and the Inhabitants thereof, be, and are hereby revived and continued, as fully and amply to all intents and purposes, as the same were at any time before the tenth day of October last. And that all Actions as well <reg orig="reall">real</reg> as personal, and all other Actions <reg orig="mixt">mixed</reg> or otherwise, Pleas, Precepts, Writs, Process, Demurrers, <reg orig="Recognizances">Recognisances</reg>, Fines, Recoveries, and all other Proceedings, Matters, and Things, of what nature or quality soever, now depending in any Court within the said County Palatine, or there commenced or prosecuted since the said Tenth day of October, shall be and stand revived, continued and of full force and effect in the Law, to all intents, constructions, and purposes. And that all Process, Pleas, Demurrers, and Proceedings in every such Action, Actions, Suits, <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg>, or Plaints, which were there depending the said Tenth day of October last, or commenced or prosecuted there at any time since, shall stand good and effectual, and be proceeded in according to the Laws of the Nation, and the proceedings used within the said County Palatine of <em>Lancaster</em>.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>And be it hereby further Ordained, That <em>Mathew Hales</em>, one of the Justices of the Court of Common-Pleas at <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Hugh Wyndham</em> Sergeant at Law, shall be Justices of the <reg orig="Assises">Assizes</reg> and Goal delivery within the said County Palatine; and that the said Justices, or either of them, shall and may act, do and perform all matters and things, as well concerning criminal as Common Pleas, and all other Pleas and <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg> whatsoever, in such manner and form as any other Justice or Justices of <reg orig="Assises">Assizes</reg> at <em>Lancaster</em> have usually acted, done and performed at any time heretofore. And the Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County Palatine of <em>Lancaster</em> hereafter named, is hereby <reg orig="Authorized">Authorised</reg> and appointed to issue forth to the said Justices, for the execution of the premises, such Commission or Commissions as in such cases have been heretofore in the said County Palatine used and accustomed. And that <em>Thomas Fell</em> Esquire be, and is hereby made and appointed Commissioner for keeping of the seal of the said County Palatine of <em>Lancaster</em>, and shall have all such powers as any Chancellor or Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County Palatine hath formerly lawfully used and exercised concerning the same, till further order.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From</i> Brussels <i>the 8 of</i> March, stilo novo.</head>

<p>In my last I advised you of the imprisonment of the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, who sits confined in the Castle of <em><reg orig="Antwerpe">Antwerp</reg></em> as quiet as a Lamb, having resigned up to his Majesty and his Highness the <pb n="6" />Arch Duke, his Person, his Estate, and his army; the Lieutenant General whereof being the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em>, is come hither to make oath of his fidelity and faithfulness in the hands of his said Highness: and the other chief Officers and Captains are to make the same Oath in the hands of the Earl of <em>Fuensaldagne</em> at <em>Diest</em>, a Frontier place bordering upon <em>Brabant</em>, towards the Country of Liege: the said Earl hath distributed some <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> among the Soldiers of the Duke; so that it is hoped they will remain obedient and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> in the service of the Spaniards, as the Duke of Lorraine himself hath seriously exhorted and <reg orig="comanded">commanded</reg> them to do by his Letters and Patents. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> they have <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg> away the Earl of <em>St Amour</em> in all haste to Vienna with Letters from his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> to <em>Francis</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, who is expected here very suddenly, and is to have the command of his <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> Army <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as he doth arrive. The said Duke of Lorain is most nobly treated in his Imprisonment, and hath that service and <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> <reg orig="don">done</reg> him at present, due to the person of a Prince, which in all his liberty he never did enjoy the like; for, besides the noble Table he keeps, his Highness the Archduke hath set him up a Court, and appointed <reg orig="severall">several</reg> great Persons to attend him. The Earl of <em>Bruayis</em> to be Overseer <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> and <reg orig="Superintendant">Superintendent</reg> of his whole Family; but all this you must know will be at the charge of the Duke, who is like to pay for <reg orig="al">all</reg> this bravery and gallantry that is put upon him; for he hath <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> and Means enough able to bear it <pb n="7" />and those that have the disposing of it now, will be no <reg orig="Nigards">Niggards</reg> in spending of it upon him; so that what he has got by roving and plundering, which was much to his dishonour, will redound to his credit, by having it laid out towards the supporting of the Dignity and Grandeur becoming the Person of a Prince. Thus will he be taught how to Govern and behave himself now <reg orig="hee">he</reg> is confined, who whilst he held his liberty, knew no other delight, but to tear, scrape and destroy the very being of a company of poor people.</p>

<p>There having been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of his Money discovered amongst his Officers and others since his Imprisonment, but no extraordinary ones. The Jewels that were found about his Daughter which the young Lady did wear about her <reg orig="conceald">concealed</reg>, are <reg orig="valu'd">valued</reg> at One hundred thousand pound sterling.</p>

<p>The French Army here under the command of Mr <em>Faber</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em>, hearing of this great Change, thought to get some great advantage by it, and thereupon came marching toward the River <em>Mense</em>, which (by the means of a <reg orig="Bridg">Bridge</reg> which those of Liege <reg orig="furnisht">furnished</reg> them with) they have made a shift to pass over, and are come into the Country of <em>Hesbaye</em>, 3, or 4 leagues from these Frontiers; which bold attempt of the French, if not <reg orig="backt">backed</reg> by some private correspondence with the Lorainers, or the assistance of those of Liege, may either turn to their <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, or otherwise will prove very troublesome to these parts; whereof I shall advise you in my next.</p>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3">From <em>Mylor</em> in <em>Cornwall</em>, February 28.</head>

<p><i>Here is this day arrived Captain <em>Wall</em>, in the <em>Castle-<reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg></em> from the <em>Canaries</em>, but brings no news.</i></p>

<p><i>About ten <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since, Major <em>Ceely</em> had a small Barque returned to St. <em>Ives</em> thus, Being one hundred leagues off, bound for <em>Bayonne</em> with Pilchards, she was taken by a <em>Dutch</em> Merchantman of 28 guns, who only took 100 pieces of Beef, and 2 Hogsheads of strong beer from the Barque, and inquired whether we had peace in <em>England</em>. Answer was given, that there were hopes of it. Hereupon the <em>Dutchman</em> told him he would give him his Ship again, and at length gave him his Ship and lading, saying, we had a new King in <em>England</em>. Whereto ours answering no, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, but you have one of more power; which ours said was a mistake, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> importuned the <em>Dutch</em> Captain, to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> so much favour as to slack sail, for them that night, because a Brest-man of War <reg orig="hover'd">hovered</reg> about them, and <reg orig="profer'd">proffered</reg> money for our <em>English</em> vessel. The <em>Dutch</em> Captain asked for the <em>Ghelt</em>. The Brest-man answered it should be secured in <em>France</em>. No (said the <em>Dutch</em> Captain) the <em>English</em>-man shall have his Ship. So she came home in safety.</i></p>

<head level="3">From <i>Milford-Haven, February 28.</i></head>

<p><i>Here are some lately come from <em>Ireland</em>, who bring no news, save only that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Mortogh</em>, there are great numbers of <em>Irish</em> ready to take shipping for <em>Flanders</em>, to serve the King of <em>Spain</em>. But yet there are still small parties of <em>Tories</em>, which lie lurking in the Woods and Bogs, and do much disquiet the peace of the Country, which is much unpeopled, and Men are extremely wanting to inhabit those parts. The Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> is safe arrived in <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">From <i>Deal, March 2.</i></head>

<p><i>Two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> all the Merchant ships that were here, and in <em>Dover</em>-Road, set sail, to go for <em>France</em>, and other parts to the Southward, having several Convoys to carry them to their designed Ports. There have been also some of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> here, but are all gone again to the Westward, where we <pb n="9" />hear our Fleet rises still near <em>St. <reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg></em> point, not far from the Isle of <em>Wight</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Mastricht">Maastricht</reg>, March 6.</i></head>

<p><i>Our Governor doth keep a good number of Troops in readiness to march at an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> warning, to repulse the <em>Lorrainers</em> and <em>Spaniards</em> in case they do offer to make any attempts, or do intend to come upon any of the Territories of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> General, after they have ransacked the poor Country of <em>Liege</em>, from whence many Inhabitants are fled into this City to avoid their cruelty. They have pillaged and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> most of the Monasteries in the said Country, and committed such <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> abuses, that most people leave and forsake their dwellings and habitations wheresoever they come.</i></p>

<head level="3">From <i>Rotterdam, March 6. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p><i>We do now hope that he business of the peace is so far advanced that there is now no further doubt to be made but that the Treaty will be suddenly ratified by both States. All the Provinces have brought in their ratifications; and ere this we hope also that our Extraordinary Ambassadors are arrived at <em>London</em>, and have signed the Articles formerly agreed upon.</i></p>

<p><i>The <em>Heer Stockhare</em>, Agent for the Protestant Cantons of <em>Switzerland</em>, having been of late in <em>England</em>, and now come over hither, being sent by the said Cantons for a Mediator between the two Commonwealths, hath had an audience of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> General, and hath made offer of his service to <unclear>adjust</unclear> any question that should yet remain undecided between the two States.</i></p>

<p><i>The Lord Ambassador of <em>France</em>, Monsieur <em>Chanut</em>, hath also had audience of the said States, and doth very much desire that <em>France</em> may also be included in the Treaty. It is said here that the <em>French</em> and <em>English</em> are like to come to as good agreement.</i></p>

<p><i>There is lately an <em>English</em> Prize brought into the <em>Texell</em>, taken by a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of War, called the <em>Bee Hive</em>, laden with piece-goods, and is said to be worth 3000l.</i></p>

<p><i>We are <reg orig="hastning">hastening</reg> out our Fleet with all the expedition that may be.</i></p>

<pb n="10" />

<p>There hath been <unclear>lately</unclear> printed a scandalous Pamphlet against the <em>Lord Protector</em>; it being full of injurious calumnies, tending to no other end but to make the Commonwealth of England odious, and to raise further <reg orig="dissentions">dissensions</reg> between the 2 States: And because it did highly concern this State to prohibit the divulging and publishing of the said Pamphlets, the States have put forth their Ordinance, strictly forbidding the sale upon pain of bodily punishment; and whosoever can discover the Author or Printer, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have the sum of 500 l. given him, in case the party be apprehended; and his name that shall give the Information shall be kept private.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, Feb 26.</i></head>

<p>The Levies that were made by the Earl of <em>Athole</em> are certainly spoiled, and the People now quite <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg> out with them, seeing no help comes out of the Low countries, as they were made to believe it would be; so that they now despair of any assistance to come that way. Besides, there is among them a report of a Vision seen lately by a Gentleman (a friend of theirs) in <em>Fife</em>; in which he was commanded by one in the form of a Man to speed to <em>Glencairn</em> and tell him, That he must decline the course he is in, otherwise it will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> destructive to him, and to all under his Command, after which (they say) the Vision vanished. The <unclear>Gentleman</unclear> neglected, and then had a second Vision, in which he was sentenced to be dumb for his neglect, which he is now, &amp; certifies the same under his hand, as They report. This latter prevails much among the vulgar Soldiers, &amp; the <pb n="11" />two former have influence on all their Army, so that they are much dejected with the conceit.</p>

<p>Athole is now about Glenlyar, and hath about 30 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> and Foot. He hath sent forth the Fiery-Crosses, but they are little regarded. Some of his Men are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to Badgenoth; where <unclear>'tis</unclear> said Glengary is. The old Laird of <unclear>Glenviqs</unclear> hath sent for a Protection from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St Johnstons. Athole was there to demand the demolishing of his house (<unclear>as</unclear> Weyms was) but the old Gentleman (who is 80 years of age) gave him absolute refusal. On Tuesday last Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, with what horse Athole could make, marched toward Monteith or Lenox, in design (as it is conceived) for the South.</p>

<p>The 22 instant, there was one of Col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg> Regiment <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> at St Johnstons for running to Athole, having <reg orig="bin">been</reg> taken <reg orig="againe">again</reg> at Dunkeil the last week: and another was <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> up to the Gallows, who had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> intercepted as he was running to Athole. There are some others that ran from the same Regiment to Athole, who were taken likewise at Dunkiel; but saved by Articles.</p>

<p>Major Gen. <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg> and Commissary Gen. Whalley's Regiments of horse are come up, and will be a very reasonable reinforcement.</p>

<p><i>London, March 3.</i> The Lords <em>Newport &amp; Tongstall</em>, Ambassadors Extraordinary from the States of the United Provinces landed with their Retinue at Tower wharf, where were Coaches provided for them. Their Lordships were received in one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> coaches, and the Master of the Ceremonies with them. Next <pb n="12" />followed the French and the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Coaches, with above 20 more all with six horses, beside above 40 Coaches more, most of them with 4 horses apiece. They passed in stately equipage through the City, from Aldgate by the Royal Exchange, and so to the new Palace yard Westminster, to receive Entertainment at the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> charge for some days.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, March 9. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>Since the surrender of Beffort, the Court have again assailed Count <unclear>Harcourt</unclear> with new Temptations for a surrender of what he holds in <em>Alsatia</em>, and the Marshal <em>de la Ferte Seneterre</em> hath Instructions sent him for that purpose; but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> apprehended he <reg orig="wil">will</reg> never trust the Court, nor the Charms of the Cardinal.</p>

<p>The Prince of Conti, and his new Princess the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Niece, have spent their days hitherto in Balls and Feasting among the great Ones; at which Solemnities both the King and <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> have made all possible expressions of mirth and contentment. The Lady is one of much beauty, and considering her <reg orig="husbands">husband's</reg> stature, may soon look over his shoulder, in such an active Court as this is. The cardinal keeps servants of his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> about him, that as Policy and Interest made this wonderful match, so Policy may keep it, till personal and State-<reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> chance to break it; for, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought &amp; said already, there is not much affection, nor confidence on either side. The <reg orig="Populacy">Populace</reg> talk of a prodigious sum appointed for the <reg orig="Ladies">Lady's</reg> Portion, and they have most reason to talk (though they seldom hit right) because it <pb n="13" />goes out of their Purses, whatever it be. It is not liked, that so many Persons interested in the City, should be visiting of Conti, where it is not known what his and his brother <em><reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg></em> Interest may yet effect, notwithstanding the late Marriage, seeing it were no new thing in <em>Paris</em>, if the highest <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> of malice should break out at, or after a Wedding.</p>

<p>His brother the Prince of Conde, is preparing to make work at Spring. That little Cloud upon the Frontiers may chance to gather, now that the Duke of Lorrain, his great Rival and Competitor in the Spanish Interest, is laid in Limbo; for he was the great impediment to the Prince's designs, having (as he is charged) been tampering with France, to the prejudice of the affairs both of Spain and Conde, but being removed, and his Army disposed into the hands of his younger brother, Francis of Lorrain, a person not so debauched nor odious, but more firm at the devotion of the Spaniards, it is supposed they may be able to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on the more current in their designs upon this Kingdom. And in Flanders they are very forward in their Preparations already; which being observed here, Orders are issued out by Marshal Tureine, his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> General, for putting the Army with all speed into a convenient posture to prevent them.</p>

<p>The young King here follows his pleasure; he and the Cardinal have lately been a hunting the wild <reg orig="Bore">Boar</reg> at Saint <reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg>. His Majesty shall not want delights to put State-business out of his head. His Eminence is sending for his father, the old Mazarini, to follow the sisters, daughters, and Nieces into the Kingdom. By matches or one way or other, they are like to be of the <reg orig="Bloud">Blood</reg>.</p>

<p>These things are <reg orig="stomackt">stomached</reg> still by the Duke of Orleans, who keeps close still at Blois, and will not be interested by any means to entrust his brother at Court. The Cardinal de Retz is still kept a prisoner, to the great discontent of the Clergy, and there he is like to be kept; for Mazarin <pb n="14" />knows well enough that this man was made a Cardinal, <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> to out brave and supplant him, and in the end drive him out of the Nation.</p>

<p>The inclination of Holland and the rest of the Provinces, to make a firm peace with England, hath filled this Court with the same affections. And the next thing that will be done to smooth the way, will be to be <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> rid of <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and his Retinue, who (they say) are already providing to be gone; but whether, none knows, unless it be to Germany.</p>

<head level="3">Whitehall, March 4.</head>

<p>In the afternoon the Ambassadors had Audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector, in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House. The Room was richly adorned with Hangings, and a rich Chair of State set for the Lord Protector, who was attended by his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>. The Entertainment was stately; the Ambassadors bowing several times, as they came up the Room, his Highness rose up when they drew near. The subject of this Audience was partly Congratulatory; but the main was to declare the intent of their coming which was to make and settle a firm Peace, and to renew the ancient friendship between the Nations. And to assure his Highness, that to this purpose their Superiors of the seven United Provinces, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> all of them unanimously consent to the Agreement of Peace, and that they as their Ambassadors Extraordinary, are <reg orig="impower'd">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same, desiring a speedy Cessation of Arms, and that there may be a Cessation of hostility on both sides. This is the effect of what was by them <reg orig="deliver'd">delivered</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, February 2<unclear>8</unclear>.</i></head>

<p>The last week Lieut. <em>Hellin</em>, Lieut. to Major <em><reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons having notice that one Capt. <em>Thompson</em> and Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Ramseys">Ramsey's</reg></em> Lieut. with 5 more of the enemy were <unclear>come</unclear> down into the <em>Mearns</em>, presently mounted with 6 more of the Troop, traced them about 10 miles into the Hills, and at last took them, their horses, with their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, and one of them being an Englishman, refused to take quarter and was killed. A party of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> horse and foot being before <em>Downe</em> Castle five miles from <em>Sterling</em>, Major <pb n="15" /> <em>Bridges</em> went forth with a party of 60 horse, upon which the enemy fled, our men pursued, and about 4 miles from <em>Downe</em> came in sight of them, but most of them got into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. We took only six prisoners and about 19 or 20 horse. Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> was there, and escaped very narrowly, as did Captain <em>Hamilton</em>, whose horse was taken, but he escaped over a bog. The 10 of <em>March</em> is appointed for the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> great Rendezvous about <em>Badgenoth</em>. <em>Montross</em> and Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> came with Orders to <em>Athol</em>, when he slighted <em>Weems</em>, to prepare all the Forces he could against that time. There was a late falling out amongst them, and one <em>Graham</em> shot <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Groom through the head, and young <em>Montross</em> had like to have killed <em>Lorn</em>. The enemy have put in a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of 30 men into <em>Gaith</em> castle, about a mile from Weyms. I have sent you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> one of Sir Mungo <reg orig="Murrays">Murray's</reg> Warrants, threatening fire and sword.</p>

<p>These are to require the Gentlemen, Heritors, and others concerned in the Parish of Drummond and Buchannan, that immediately after sight hereof they send to the Craig of Erne out of every hundred pounds of Rent half <unclear>Bell Cone</unclear>, one Furlet Meat, one Turf of Hay, one <reg orig="Legg">Leg</reg> of Beef, one stone Cheese, 4 <reg orig="Henns">Hens</reg>, or satisfaction <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg>, as also to be immediately at the appointed place with your proportion of Troop-Horse with Certificate; if you fail I will pursue you with Fire and Sword, according to the general Order.</p>

<p>From <em>Blaniavard</em> in <em>Drummond, Febr: 23: M. Murray</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, March 8.</i></head>

<p>An Ordinance is preparing, for the Trial and approbation of Ministers; and thirty Commissioners (Ministers and others) will be appointed to put them in execution; but the power extends only to the trying of such Ministers as have been admitted within these six months last past, or that shall be admitted hereafter.</p>

<p>As concerning the Dutch Peace, the Articles of the late Treaty are <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>, and six Members of the Council are appointed Commissioners to meet with the Dutch Ambassadors; whereupon <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed Subscriptions will be made on either side in order to a firm Peace and Amity.</p>

<p>No <unclear>news</unclear> from the Sea save that our Fleet ride near St. <em>Ellias</em> Point, in gallant Equipage, and more ships are putting forth with speed. On the other side the Dutch are preparing to put out to Sea; but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> written over, that their great Fleet will not be ready till May.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">&#x261e;<i>There is lately published an ENGLISH GRAMMAR,</i></head>

<p>Containing all Rules and Directions necessary to be known for the judicious reading, right speaking and writing thereof, very <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> for all that desire to be expert in the foresaid facilities; as also a special preparative to the learning of the <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg> tongue, or any other <reg orig="Grammarized">Grammarised</reg> language, which is to be sold by <em><unclear>Philenious</unclear> Soephens</em> at the Golden Lion in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>