<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol196">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 196</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> March 9. to <em>Thursday</em> March 16. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkeith, March 4.</i></head>

<p>Since my last, there is certain Intelligence come of the landing of <em>Middleton</em>, at the Ferry of Uney in Sutherland on Monday was seven-night, about twelve <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> in the night, in a <unclear>Hoy</unclear>, wherein were some Arms. There came with him Sir <em>George Monroe</em>, the Lord <em>Napier Thomas Deyal, alias</em> Major General <em>Deyal, Lo&agrave;owick Drummond</em>, and about 80 more. The Vessel was unladen and sent away next morning. They sent 40 of their men, or thereabouts, up to Atheness, with 8 or 10 horse-load of Arms; the rest they carried along with <pb n="1" />themselves, and went up Strathfleet, toward Affine, otherwise called Sky <unclear>r</unclear> Affine.</p>

<p>It is reported there is another ship laden in Strathnever with Arms, but no men. They speak of meeting with <em>Glencairn</em> in the Brays of Murray, where they have their Rendezvous, and from thence intend to press all the Countries to rise. This may put some new life into them; but immediately before <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> arrival they were much dejected, and were <reg orig="moldering">mouldering</reg> very fast, and I do not find but those that are most sensible and rational are much discouraged by this inconsiderable appearance of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em>, and some are of opinion it will tend to their total dissolution.</p>

<p>the Commander in chief hath sent more Horse Northward, to help to keep them up in the hills, where they cannot subsist long in any Body.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement</i></head>

<p>Whereas in last <reg orig="Weeks">Week's</reg> Intelligence I printed a Letter from the Sea, wherein were some things respecting the Court of Admiralty; upon information I find that that Court proceeds by certain rules of Law and Justice, such as are known and practised in other Nations abroad, as well as in that Court at home. And finding that of those 45 ships mentioned in that Letter, 42 were discharged by the Captains at Sea, and never sent in to the Admiralty, and that though the Gentleman that wrote that Letter was pleased to say, that 3 thirds of the goods were Holland, (which if it be marked, was the whole, <pb n="2" />for, dividing them by thirds, 3 thirds make up the entire) yet he doth not so much as say that there was any evidence concerning them sent in, to prove any part of the goods to be Holland; nor were there above 3 of 45 transmitted to the Admiralty Court. So that no Evidence being sent in, that Court, which must proceed by the certain Law of Nations, could not but according to Law and Right, award Restitution, and so did it <em>Jure &amp; non Ijuria</em>; And if the Captain knew of any evidence, he was in the fault that suppressed it, and not the Court that did Justice in it; whose certain rules are sufficiently fitted by the Laws of Justice, to do right in all Cases, if there be no <reg orig="sailer">sailor</reg> in the Captains and other inferior Officers who are at the taking of them; so that if there were any default, it could not be in the Court of Admiralty for discharging of three only, when there was no evidence brought in to condemn them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, March 14. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>Orders are issued out by Marshal <em>Turein</em> for all Officers of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Army, to make speedy repair to their respective charges. If the weather hold thus dry, it will bring on a Campania sooner <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary. There is not the least talk now of the general Peace, but Counsels are taken rather, on both sides, how to prosecute the War. The House of Austria (as Letters say) are mediating a very strict Combination, the Spaniard fearing the English conjunction with the Hollander, may take in the French. If so, then Spain must look other where to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> an Interest.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>In <em>Germany</em>, there is a great dissatisfaction between the Emperor &amp; the States of the Empire, which (they say) portends a new <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> in those Parts. Those divided Interests upon the same Spot of ground, ever have <reg orig="bin">been</reg>, and will be perpetually wrangling. And now that the Swedes have gotten a quiet share and possession among them, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> a great question with which Party they will side; for the Queen is at this time highly courted by the Spanish Ambassador at her court, in the behalf of the Emperor.</p>

<p>The news of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorains">Lorain's</reg></em> being <reg orig="coopt">cooped</reg> up in <em>Antwerp</em> castle, was exceeding welcome to this City, he having the luck to be no better beloved here than in all other places; especially because of his Treachery to the Pr: of <em>Conde</em>, whose Interest and Person is yet in credit here amongst the Inhabitants; not so much for any cause of love they have towards him, but because of the deadly hate they still bear to others, who oppose him.</p>

<p><em>Conde</em> is still at Brussels, but his Troops on the Frontiers. The war (as appears by the Preparations in Flanders, and the imprisonment of Lorain) will be vigorously <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on; and the Prince will (as is said) have a very considerable Army, thereby to endeavour a new In-road into France by Midsummer. If he can clear his way on the Frontiers to effect that, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought he <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not be without a party in the Bowels of this Nation, and perhaps of this City, when time shall serve. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> all things go smoothly on here without <reg orig="controll">control</reg>. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is <pb n="4" />still a Prisoner, and so like to continue, while <em>Mazarin</em> is in power, which exceedingly disgusts the Clergy; and so much the more, because they have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> frequent Intercessors to his Majesty for him, and could never prevail.</p>

<p>It is much <reg orig="mervailed">marvelled</reg>, that the Du: of Orleans should hold up still so courageously against the Court, and all their <reg orig="Intreaties">Entreaties</reg>, This resolution of his makes men <reg orig="imagin">imagine</reg>, there may be <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> a brewing, which yet remains invisible, and that Conde's Fortunes are not so desperate but they may revive again. The <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Guards have had a Muster without the City, at which his Majesty and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> were both present.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is shortly to be gone from hence, <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as the Monies are paid him, which are appointed to be paid to set him forward. It is said a Pension will also be assigned for his subsistence when out of the Kingdom. This is one effect of the intended Agreement between England and the United Provinces.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em>, Feb.16. By a ship that came from Candia, we hear, That <em>Ussaim</em> Bassau who is <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Turkish Army in that Island, intending to besiege anew that City, had brought all his Forces near that place, intending to <reg orig="intrench">entrench</reg> and <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> themselves close to the <reg orig="wals">walls</reg>, but that our Forces within had made such a <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> Sally upon those Infidels, that they had not only made them to forsake their new works, but also made them retreat in a disorderly manner, but not without some considerable loss on our side: here are now four ships under sail, which carry <pb n="5" />men, monies, &amp;c. for the Relief of Candia; and there are more ships which will be ready for the same purpose in a few days, our Levies likewise <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on gallantly, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in <em>Germany</em>, but also those in several parts of <em>Italy</em>: divers persons who had been exiled from this City, have made their peace with considerable sums of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, amongst whom is the Earl <em>Porcellago</em> of <em>Brescia</em>, who upon his Agreement is to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> and maintain for One month 1200 men in <em>Candia</em>, &amp; moreover to serve in person during the Wars.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dover, March 9.</i></head>

<p>By a small Barque come this morning from France, we hear that a great Fleet of Dutch Merchantmen, consisting of about 140 Sail, are gone to the Westward, sailing close by the French coast. And having a fair wind, 'tis like they may pass without any interruption from our Fleet; who are (we hear) still near St Ellen's Point: this Dutch Fleet had a convoy of about 60 Sail of Men of war (as they say) but they are to be divided, the Merchantmen being bound to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Ports and Countries.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, March 9.</i></head>

<p>Part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church falling down this week, at the great South <reg orig="dore">door</reg>; It was under consideration in the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> for taking down, but nothing was done in it.</p>

<p>Orders were issued from his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, for all Officers concerned to repair to their respective Charges in Scotland.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Advertisement</i></head>

<p>All Adventurers for Land in <em>Ireland</em> are desired <pb n="6" />to take notice, that the Committee for Claims have appointed a Lottery for <em>Narroines</em>, to be at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg>-hall London, on Thursday the Thirtieth of March, 1654. to begin at 8 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> in the forenoon of the same day.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels, March 15. S. N.</i></head>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> begins to take some contentment in his Imprisonment, and hath himself <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg> and declared those persons who have any thing in their hands belonging to him; so that by little and little they get to discover all his Treasure Jewels, and other rich <reg orig="Moveables">Movables</reg>. In short, he is well in bodily health at present, though of late <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was taken with very much vomiting, which has <reg orig="clear'd">cleared</reg> his stomach, and it may be prevented some further disease that was creeping upon him; the cause <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> is attributed to <reg orig="som">some</reg> kind of <reg orig="surfet">surfeit</reg> he had taken with <reg orig="over-eating">overeating</reg> of himself, being most nobly entertained with all manner of varieties; which civil carriage toward him, hath so wrought upon him, that he <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg> himself, That he lives more nobly now than ever he did in his life, and thinks himself in a happy condition. But how long this entertainment of him will last, is not certain: In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> his <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> pays for all. His Troops have voluntarily submitted <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> to the King of <em><reg orig="Spains">Spain's</reg></em> service; and have made Oath of Fidelity; They are quartered upon our Frontiers, and in the country of <em>Liege</em>, on this side of the River <em>Meuse</em>, and the army of the Marquis of <em>Faber</em>, <reg orig="Governer">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> for <em>France</em>, is quartered on the other side of the River <em>Meuse</em>, in the Country <reg orig="cald">called</reg> <em>Condioux</em> <pb n="7" />demanding of the Prince and States of Liege the sum of two hundred thousand pattacoons for the said Army, for being come to their relief and assistance; and to clear their Country of the <reg orig="Loreiners">Lorainer's</reg>, High <reg orig="Germans">German's</reg>, and the Prince of <reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg> Forces, so that these poor men of Liege will suffer as much trouble and mischief by the French, before they be rid of them, as they did by all the rest of their Enemies.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Earl of <em>Starrenbergh</em> Imperial Ambassador doth all what he can to agree and content both Parties, for which purpose he makes several journeys to Brussels, Liege, and to the French Army.</p>

<p>They are beginning to prepare here for this next Campania; and to that end there have been several meetings held of the chiefest of the Towns, and they have resolved to raise a very great <reg orig="subsidie">subsidy</reg> for his Majesty.</p>

<p>There happened lately a very sad accident at the Prince of <reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg> Court; two young Gentlemen being invited thither, by a Gentleman that liveth there, and <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> dinner was carrying up to the table by the servants they fell out amongst themselves, and went presently out of the hall, and drew their short swords, and run at one another, and were both killed upon the place before <reg orig="any body">anybody</reg> came to them; the one was Lord of Cincq; Bourgs, being two Villages, called Morel, Lord of Haulterive, the only son of the Family; the other was called Le Cherf, Lord of Leystrate, the one was run quite through the heart, and the other below the pap <pb n="8" />of his right Breast; and because they <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> one another in heat of blood, their Bodies were suffered to be <reg orig="buryed">buried</reg>, and their Estates freed from confiscation.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg> March 13. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>Yesterday in the forenoon arrived at the <em>Hague</em> an Express out of <em>England</em>, who brought news to the Lords-States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, that the Lords Ambassadors <em>Newport</em> and <em>Tonstall</em> arrived at Gravesend the third of March; but the Post is not yet come, through contrary winds and bad weathers; <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as the Letters are come, we hope to hear of the reception of our Ambassadors, and other affairs more at large; and in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> <reg orig="wee">we</reg> make no doubt of the Peace. Some four days ago here arrived a Scotch Seaman, who brought news hither of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> safe landing in Scotland, with his Officers and Ammunition, which he carried from hence; and that the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Seaforth</em> had for certain taken the Island of <em>Lewis</em>; and that the Highlanders, with the English, made an Army of 20000 men, when they are altogether, but that they were divided in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts of Scotland; and that the English had sent out a body of Four or Five thousand men against them, but the Highlanders meeting with them had totally routed them, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> 500. of them upon the place. The truth of this is not credited here, though much blazed abroad by the Cavaliers, with many circumstances to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> men to believe their abominable <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg>; which they forge to deceive the Inhabitants, and to elevate the drooping spirits of the People of <pb n="9" />these Countries. The Coach and Horses, with other <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> for the service of the Lords Ambassadors in England, were <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> yesterday to be sent thither.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, March 18. S.N.</i></head>

<p>In my last I told you what this Court was <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about, since which time little or nothing of any moment hath past here. Upon Thursday next two of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces are to be <reg orig="marryed">married</reg>, the one to the Duke of <em>Candale</em>, the other to the Marshall of <em>le Milleray's</em> son. The Dutch Ambassador here hath spoken <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg>, on behalf of the Protestants, that they may be redressed in what they desire of his Majesty; and that some <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> Order may be speedily taken to prevent all further complaints. Furthermore, that his Majesty would be pleased to cause to be made good unto them, all that his <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> favour hath vouchsafed to allow unto them, and all what hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> granted them by the King his Predecessor.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his brothers are still here, but are resolved not to stay long, having no encouragement given them at this Court, where they do so much desire a Peace with England. And this week here was a strong Report, That Monsieur <em>de Bordeaux</em> had very near finished the Treaty between France and England, with the Lord Protector; wherein we make no doubt but the said Monsieur <em>de Bordeaux</em> will be able to give consent to his Highness in any thing that can in Justice be demanded of this Crown. Preparations are making for this <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> Campania, <pb n="10" />both against the Prince of Conde and Catalonia, whither the Prince of Conti is to be sent with an Army, which he is to command in chief. Some talk there is of a Design going against Naples again, but most men suppose that that Enterprise will dwindle to nothing; there being Work enough cut out already to keep them in play: Besides, not knowing certainly what the issue will be of the Treaty between France and England, this Crown is necessitated to provide for the safety of the Coasts of Normandy and Picardy, for fear of <reg orig="Surprisall">Surprisal</reg>, in case both Nations should not agree in Amity, whereunto this Crown doth much incline, and stands well affected.</p>

<p>There is great rejoicing at the Palace <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> at the news of the safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of Lieutenant <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Middleton</em> with his Officers and Ammunition in Scotland, where they say the Highlanders are numerous and courageous enough to manage their business, now so gallant a Commander is come amongst them. And that in the last <reg orig="Rencounter">Reencounter</reg> they totally Routed the English, and slew many of them upon the place. They have great hopes from those Tories, hoping they will prove formidable to their Enemies in those parts; That so <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> Interest there may not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> altogether extinguished.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dublin, March 1.</i></head>

<p>Your news of Holland is very welcome, and of more immediate concernment to us here, <reg orig="then">than</reg> any of the rest of these Dominions.</p>

<p>Your other Advertisements are good Hint, <pb n="11" />for us to improve, and to say something more to that of rumoured Dissatisfaction here, which indeed hath been <reg orig="onely">only</reg> so much as to occasion People to talk of at a Distance, and nothing in Substance: Neither have I ever observed any thing of such seeming <reg orig="shew">show</reg>, and so little moment, that indeed the Spirit spent itself, without receiving the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> of any Opposition; and if it should <reg orig="doe">do</reg> us hurt there in England, I am sure it is more <reg orig="then">than</reg> it was ever like to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> them here in Ireland.</p>

<p>We have advertisement of the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> being near <reg orig="Holy-head">Holyhead</reg>, ready to come over to us; which occasions the stay of our Friends, <em>Allen</em> and <em>Standish</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> over, who were otherwise in readiness to have come away from hence, according to my Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Orders and commands.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam, March 14. S.N.</i></head>

<p>The most remarkable thing that hath happened in these Countries of late is, that <em>Middleton</em> is at length gone away for Scotland, with a Retinue of Cavaliers along with him, and some Arms and Ammunition, in a big-bellied Hoy. I was ever boasted by his Party, that he would obtain great matters from this State, for the setting him out in gallant equipage, and good supplies from some Princes also in Germany; but she hoped effects of all these things are as yet invisible; and his proportion of Arms, and of men that went with him doth not answer expectation, but sufficiently declares, that it was not so much Design as Necessity that carried <pb n="12" />him out of these Provinces; for, he saw that if a Peace be with England, there would be no abiding for him here: so that he must either go and run at adventure in Scotland, or else wander in some foreign Country. Notwithstanding the well-willers of his Party do give out here, what great Bodies of Forces are ready to receive him upon his Landing, and make no question but he will presently over-run Scotland, and drive out the English. It is observed here, that these beaten Royalists are a hearty Generation; they are always thriving and conquering, if we may believe themselves; no sooner hath time and observation confuted one story, but immediately they are up with another, and all goes well with them, let the world turn which way it will; their Tongues still run a-tilt and in Triumph. Their Master is (we hear) still at Paris, but in a departing posture. It is thought the affairs of that Crown in the present Juncture, will not permit his stay there any longer. We hear not of any Applications made by him of late to this state, but we suppose he gives it over for <reg orig="drie">dry</reg> meat. Nothing can be more unwelcome to him, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to hear that any Country should be in Amity with England; for his interest lies in troubled Waters, and he must be hoping for the wracks of other States, that he may lay hold, though it were but upon a <reg orig="Planke">Plank</reg>, to save a sinking Fortune. It is said at his <reg orig="sisters">sister's</reg> Court, that the first place of his retirement from France, will be at the Court of the Duke of <reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg>, but whither afterward, is not spoken.</p>

<pb n="13" />

<p>The French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, Monsieur <unclear><em>Chamot</em></unclear> hath been labouring very hard at the <em>Hague</em>, to put on the Interest of his Master, so as that it may not be left to stand or fall by itself, when the Conjunction between both the <reg orig="Rupublicks">Rupublics</reg> shall be completed. The Spaniard will (it is said) be put to play a new Game before he thought of it. This Peace, if it prove so, is a hinge upon which all the Affairs of <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>, must have a new Turn. The Popish party frown at it, and talk of a Conjunction too between the Emperor, Spaniard, and I know not who; it may be they may think on the <unclear><em>Stewarts</em></unclear>, if any good may be done against England, upon the score of that Family. It seems, by the working of Affairs, as if there would be a Confederacy against the <em>Reformed Religion</em>, though (perhaps) it shall be managed upon other pretences.</p>

<p>An <em>Eastland</em> fleet of about 150 sail hath brought home the great necessaries of this Country.</p>

<p>Here is much discourse of the great Preparations made for Sea by you in England, which causeth the State to be very quick in theirs, yet here is all hope of Peace, and the affections of men seem ripe for it, expecting to hear of it very <reg orig="sodainly">suddenly</reg>, especially the Merchants. Our Neighbour States and Princes wonder much at the great number of ships that are to be equipped on either side; and therefore if a Peace be, must needs say, it was not Necessity but Reason that made it.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal in Sweden, February 10.</i></head>

<p>We are yet expecting the good hour of a dismission, which will not be too suddenly: though I hope we shall be ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> away by that time the weather will give us leave. The Chancellor is an old Statist, and he makes excuses and <reg orig="delayes">delays</reg>, <reg orig="till">'till</reg> he see what the issue will be of our Treaty with the Dutch. Neither can I blame him, for according to that, it will be necessary to guide their answers unto our proposals. This afternoon my <em>Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg></em>, and the <em>Chancellor</em> have had another meeting; there is a very fair <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> between them: but according to the <reg orig="policie">policy</reg> of State, I suppose as yet there passes only discourse between them and nothing is drawn up unto a head, he being willing to see, whether there is likely to be a Peace, or a continuation of war with the Hollander. There is an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> come from <em>Russia</em>, he that was before is gone into <em>Denmark</em>; 'tis <reg orig="talkt">talked</reg> of that the Duke of <em><reg orig="Muscovie">Muscovy</reg></em> will make a war with the Pole, and therefore he courts these neighbouring Princes.</p>

<p><i>From Dalkeith, March, 7.</i> A <reg orig="partie">party</reg> of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Forces Horse and Foot, came the last week and faced <em>Blair</em> Castle, the Governor Capt. <em>Witter</em> sent out a <reg orig="partie">party</reg> within protection to skirmish with them: whereupon one Capt. <em>Johnston</em> and 2 more with him, charged up to our men on horseback, but himself and one more were killed; then they all came up, whereupon our men retreated, they <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> off their 2 dead men, and buried the said Captain with Col. <em>Wogan</em> at the Kirk of <em>Kenmore</em>. His death is much lamented amongst them, being very stout, but in this business he was too fool-hardy; we had either one or two shot. There have of late been some private overtures made from some in the Hills of some proposals which would probably much allay the present distempers without any harsh corrosives, which though I have hinted before, yet since nothing is done tending to satisfaction in any of them, I shall again inculate, 1 the sequestration that was upon many (and of little or no advantage to the State) made many desperate, &amp; so to be removed. 2 That personal Arrests might cease, and Creditors contented to take all their lands and goods, for satisfaction, or to cease prosecution <reg orig="till">'till</reg> there be ability to pay: the want of this makes others desperate. <pb n="15" />3 That such as were <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of fortune had past the prime of their time in Wars, and were void of Callings, or <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, might be considered to be transported to some Prince or State in amity with the Commonwealth, for they are born and they must be kept, or will have a <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> as long as they can get it. If these thing were put in Execution it would prevent many from going to them, and bring many from them.</p>

<p><i>From Plymouth, March 11.</i> About three days since, the Portsmouth <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and the Constant Warwick being together met with the <em>Brest</em> Man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, commanded by Captain <em>Beach</em> Admiral of that <reg orig="Pyratick">Piratic</reg> Crew which <reg orig="lurke">lurk</reg> in <em>Brest</em>; he had with him two Prizes which he had newly taken, but perceiving that our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the Prizes, and was afterward secured by night coming on. The same night the Portsmouth <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and the constant Warwick chanced to part company; and it so fell out about midnight that <em>Beach</em> roving about, lighted on the Constant Warwick all alone, which before he came near, he took to be a Merchantman, and went on with an intent to board him; but the Warwick demanding who he was, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> he was the Portsmouth <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and for <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>. But the Warwick suspecting him, bade him stand off. Then <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake, and seeing the Warwick to be a man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, he presently made away; but the Warwick being a good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg>, made after him, and kept company with him all night. About 6 in the morning, <em>Beach</em> began the fight, firing 3 Guns, which were answered by the Warwick. The encounter lasted till <unclear><!--3 characters--></unclear> clock in the afternoon; at which time <em>Beach</em> and his men called for Quarter, and had it. He had 5 foot water in the hold when he yielded; he had 200 men, 20 whereof were killed; his <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> is a gallant new Vessel, of 42 Guns, <unclear>whereof</unclear> but 38 were mounted. There are taken aboard with him <unclear><!--approx. 3 characters--></unclear> Captains besides himself, and divers Gentlemen, who are all prisoners. This is that <em>Beach</em>, the ring-leading Pirate, who hath done <unclear>our Merchants</unclear> so much mischief this winter, that he lived like a P<unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear>; for which 'tis like he will receive his reward, being <unclear>brought</unclear> hither, with the rest of his companions.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, March 15.</i> The six Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> had Conference this afternoon with the Dutch Ambassadors at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em> house in the Palace-yard, in order to a final close of that Affair, which (<reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived) will be within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>.</p>

<p>It is supposed the Lord Protector will remove his Family to <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em> at the latter end of this week.</p>

<p>No news from Sea, save that our fleet rides still near St. <em><reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg></em> point, and that the Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> is out again, riding in <em>Stokes-Bay.</em></p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>