<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol198">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Mercurius Politicus, Issue 198</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus,</i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. de Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Thursday</em> March 23. to <em>Thursday</em> March 30.1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, March 18.</i></head>

<p>The landing of <em>Middleton</em> hath filled these parts with a thousand <reg orig="rumors">rumours</reg> and as many stories are coined on purpose to incense this People to run the hazards of <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>. They are told of their late <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> being resolved to visit them, and that his Brother <em>York</em> will bring Forces, and from <em>Germany</em> and <em>Holland</em> the say they shall have <reg orig="mony">money</reg>. These <reg orig="phantsies">fantasies</reg> are <reg orig="scatter'd">scattered</reg> with a great deal of Art among the common sort; and if the Artists effect nothing else, they will by this means unsettle men in their Affections, and put many in a tottering <reg orig="humor">humour</reg>.</p>

<p>The Enemy here had their general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and are <unclear>since <!--approx. 4 characters--> active</unclear> in their Levies, <pb n="1" />summoning and forcing in the Countries, as they <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> on toward our Quarters, which they must attempt, or else they will not be able to keep long in a body. In Sutherland <reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg> and Ross, they have been very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, and drawn in as many as they could of the Gentry in those parts, by whom the common sort are led like sheep to the slaughter. We do not hear that they have as yet attempted the Low Lands; but expect it, and therefore for preventing their excursions, our Commander in chief is resolved to take the Field out of hand.</p>

<head level="3">Paris, March 25. S.N.</head>

<p>The 20 of this instant the Count of Aubijoux, the Baron of Brifac, and another of the four Duelists, which fought awhile <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> in the Palace Royal, were hanged in Picture, and declared unnoble without any prejudice to their <reg orig="childrens">children's</reg> Nobility, and their Means confiscated; one third part to the King, the other to their Family, and the last to the poor; I am informed the said Mr. D'aubijoux Governor of the City of Montpellier, having put in it a Lieutenant at his devotion, is gone into Flanders.</p>

<p>The next day the King being gone to take his seat in this Parliament, the Pieces of Mr. le Prince's Process were read aloud therein in full Assembly of the Chambers, and in presence of six Dukes and Peers, two Marshals of France, and of several <reg orig="Councellers">Councillors</reg> of State. In consequence whereof it was ordained that the witnesses should be confronted.</p>

<p>The same day the Archbishop of this City, <pb n="2" />Uncle to the Cardinal of Retz, died aged 70 years, soon after the Chapter of his Cathedral Church assembled and received <reg orig="Proxie">Proxy</reg>, the said Cardinal in the place of his said Uncle, as soon as the Court had been informed of his death, Mr. le Tellier went to the Chief of the said Chapter, to tell him from the King, that they ought not yet to proceed to the reception of any Archbishop; and when it was told him, that the business was done, he said his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> were resolved to laugh at it, and never to give the said Cardinal liberty <reg orig="untill">until</reg> he renounce the said <reg orig="Archbishoprick">Archbishopric</reg>, which he protests not to forsake, though they should kill him. They did what they could possible to hide the said death from him, but a signal of <reg orig="bels">bells</reg> ringing did immediately announce it unto him from Paris. Now for as much as this Court is vexed at that surprisal, and the said Chapter hath been threatened for it, as if they intended hereupon to make the said <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Process for some criminal cause, therefore many of his friends being in fear, would not assist on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> in the Procession which is yearly made on the same day in this City; and amongst others, the said <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> <reg orig="Atturny">Attorney</reg>, who feared to be one of the first that should be arrested; 'tis thought this business will occasion some considerable contests, if so be the said prisoner hath any stout friends among the Clergy.</p>

<p>Yesterday the witnesses nominated for Mr. le Princes Process were confronted, and Friday or Saturday next one will pass unto his condemnation; <pb n="3" />but he shall not be hanged in picture by reason of the respect born to the Prince of Conti his brother.</p>

<p>The last Letters from Flanders bear, that the said Mr. le Prince was in the field since the 14 of this of this present, but it is not true that he hath undertaken any siege, I am informed a Post that he sent into Guienne hath been taken, and the <reg orig="rumor">rumour</reg> runs that some Spanish ships are again come to infest the mouth of Garrone, and interrupt the Trade of <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>.</p>

<p>It is certain the Dutch Ambassador hath spoken here for the Protestants.</p>

<p>The Duke of D'elboeuf is few <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since deceased in this City.</p>

<p>The cashiering of the Elects and <reg orig="Syndicks">Syndics</reg> of Rents is at a stand, and Mr. de Servient brags he will reform the whole State; that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Crown-land shall be bought again, and that after that the people will not be undone by so many Taxes.</p>

<p>Upsal, Feb. 24. 1654 S. V.</p>

<p>We cannot receive any dispatch <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the Queen understand the true State of the Treaty between England and Holland, she persists in her desires of resigning up the Government, and thereupon she is gone this week to Westraas, to meet Prince Palatine, her Cousin German, and declared Successor, and to treat with him concerning the same; yet she hath promised the Lord Ambassador to accomplish his affair before that time, and that to his contentment. But it is questioned what the Grand Assembly of the <pb n="4" />States which are to convene shortly, will determine in that particular, as to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> overture. The discourses here are various, some think that Don Piemontel hath lain here to negotiate a match between this Queen and the Roman King, and that Count Montecuculi, General of the horse to the Emperor, came hither to agitate the same; but those that pretend knowledge, think no such thing, and are confident the Queen is resolved never to marry.</p>

<head level="3">Regensborgh, March 12. S. N.</head>


<p>The <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> departure remains determined on the 20 of April next. The States in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> are very forward in their meetings, and absolving of business. <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last the 4 new Princes, namely Salin, Detrichstein, Piccolomini, and Aversburgh were by his Highness our Prince Elector, in the name of his <reg orig="Emperial">Imperial</reg> Majesty, personally introduced in the Princely Ryx <reg orig="Colledg">College</reg>, where the Ryx Marshal Lord Papenheim did <reg orig="shew">show</reg> them their respective places, which immediately they possessed.</p>

<p>The point of Justice is now fully resolved, and the Vechtisch business propounded, which would easily be brought to the like perfection, if the restant monies were but ready.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg>, the 4 ditto. S.N.</head>

<p>Upon the Ryxday at <reg orig="Warschaw">Warsaw</reg> is concluded, that the Treasurer shall give an account to the Commonwealth of the monies he received and disbursed. Some other secret <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg> are kept, but unknown what is treated of in the same. Some are of opinion that they have concluded to send an Ambassage for Sweden with the first opportunity, for to admonish that Queen to the inviolable observation of the Inducies, and to prevent her alliance with the Grand Duke of Moscow. But I shall be able to give you more certain information of this hereafter</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p><i>March 23.</i> The expected Ordinance, appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Preachers, came forth in Print, which being of universal concernment is here inserted;</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance appointing Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Preachers.</i></head>

<p>Whereas, for some time past, hitherto there hath not <reg orig="been">bin</reg> any certain course established for the supplying vacant places with able and fit persons to preach the Gospel, by reason whereof not only the Rights and Titles of Patrons are prejudiced, but many weak, scandalous, popish, and ill-affected persons have intruded themselves, or been brought in, to the great grief and trouble of the good people of this Nation; For remedy and prevention whereof, Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, that every person who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from and after the five &amp; <reg orig="twentyeth">twentieth</reg> day of March instant, be presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with Care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Lecture in <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, shall before he be admitted into any such Benefice or Lecture, be judged and approved by the persons hereafter named, to be a person for the grace of God in him, his holy and <reg orig="unblamable">unblameable</reg> Conversation, as also for his knowledge and utterance, able and fit to preach the Gospel; And that after the said five and <reg orig="twentyeth">twentieth</reg> day of <em>March</em>, no person, but such as shall upon such approbation be admitted by the said persons, shall take any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Lecture, having <pb n="6" />a <reg orig="constent">constant</reg> stipend <reg orig="legaly">legally</reg> annexed and belonging thereunto, or take or receive any such Benefice aforesaid, or the parts thereof; And be it further ordained, That Francis Rous Esq; Dr Thomas Goodwin, Dr John Owen, Mr Thankful Owen, Dr Arrowsmith, Dr Tuckney, Dr Horton, Mr Joseph Caryl, Mr Philip Nye, Mr Will: Garter, Mr Sidreah Simpson, Mr William Greenhill, Mr William Strong, Mr Thomas Manton, Mr Samuel Slater, Mr William Cooper, Mr Stephen Marshal, Mr John Tombes, Mr Walter Craddock, Mr Samuel Faircloth, Mr Hugh Peters, Mr Peter Sterry, Mr Samuel Bamford, Mr Thomas Valentine of Chaford, Mr Henry Jeffee, Mr Obadiah Sedgwick, Mr Nicholas Lockier, Mr Daniel Dyke, Mr James Russel, Mr Nathaniel Campfield, Robert Titchborn Alderman of London, Mark Hildesley, Thomas Wood, John Sadler, William Goff, Thomas St Nicholas Wil. Packer, &amp; Edward Cresset Esquires, shall be, and are hereby nominated, constituted and appointed Commissioners for such approbation and admission is <reg orig="abovesaid">above said</reg>, and upon death or removal of any of them, others shall from time to time be nominated in their places by the Lord Protector and his successors, by advice of his Council, in the Interval of Parliaments, and sitting the Parliament, by the Protector and Parliament; and the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, met together in some certain place in the City of London and Westminster, as his Highness shall appoint, are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to judge and take of the ability <pb n="7" />and fitness of any person so nominated, chosen or appointed, according to the qualification above mentioned, and upon their approbation of such his ability and fitness, to grant unto such person admission to such Benefice or lecture by an Instrument in writing under a Common Seal to be appointed by his Highness, and under the hand of the Register or Registers for the time being to be also nominated by the Lord Protector and his Successors, which Instrument the said Register or Registers shall cause to be <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in a Book for that purpose, and kept upon Record.</p>

<p>And it is hereby declared, That the said person so admitted into any such Benefice, shall be Possessor and Incumbent of the same, and <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg> thereby to the Profits, <reg orig="Perquisits">Perquisites</reg>, and all Rights and Dues incident and belonging thereunto, as fully and effectually as if he had <reg orig="bin">been</reg> instituted &amp; inducted according to the Laws of this Realm; as also the person that <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be so admitted to any Lecture as aforesaid, shall be thereby enabled, according to the establishment and constitution of such Lecture, to preach therein, and to have and receive the Stipend or Profits to such Lecture belonging. Provided always, That no person who shall tender himself, or be <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg>, for approbation as aforesaid, shall be concluded by any Vote of the said Commissioners which shall pass in the Negative as to his approbation, unless Nine or more of the said Commissioners be present at such Vote.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That all Patrons <pb n="8" />of all Benefices that are now void, shall within 6 months next after 25 of this instant <em>March</em>, and of any Benefice that shall hereafter be void within 5 months next after the avoidance of the same, present unto the said Commissioners, or any five of them, some fit person to be admitted, and for default of such Presentation within that time, the Presentation for that turn shall devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his successors.</p>

<p>Providing <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That in case the Patron be disturbed to Present unto such Benefice, and thereupon within 6 months after the avoidance of such Benefice a <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> be commenced for the Recovery of such Presentation, and notice thereof in writing left with the said Commissioners, or by any five of them, or effectual to prevent the lapse, as where the sure was heretofore commenced against commenced against the Bishop of Ordinary.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That during the vacancy of such place by reason of such <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg>, the said Commissioners, or any 5 or more of them, have hereby authority to sequester the fruits and profits thereof for supplying of the place with an able Preacher, by the said Commissioners, or any 5 or more of them, to be nominated and approved of as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And forasmuch as many persons since the first day of <em>April</em> last <reg orig="past">passed</reg> have been placed in such Benefices, and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Lectures, It is hereby Ordained, That in case such person shall not before the 24 of <em>June</em> next, obtain approbation and admittance in the manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, Then such person or persons as have right thereunto shall or may present or nominate some other fit and able person to such place.</p>


<p>And in default of such Presentation within two months after the said 24 day of <em>June</em>, or within six months after the place became void, the Presentation for that turn shall likewise devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>And for the Better satisfaction of the said Commissioners touching the godly and unblameable conversation of such persons as are to be admitted into any place as aforesaid, It is further declared and Ordained, that before any admittance of any person as aforesaid, there shall be brought to the said Commissioners, or any 5 of them, a Testimonial or Certificate in writing, subscribed with the hands of three persons of known godliness and integrity, whereof one at least to be a preacher of the Gospel in some constant <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> places <reg orig="testifiing">testifying</reg> upon their personal knowledge the holy and good conversation of the person to be admitted: which said <reg orig="Certificat">Certificate</reg> shall be duly <reg orig="Registred">Registered</reg> and filed. And it is also declared, that the penalty for or in respect of the not subscribing or reading the Articles mentioned in the Act of the 13 year of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>Reform of Disorders in the Ministers of the Church</em>: or for not producing such testimonial as in the said Act is required, shall from henceforth cease and be void.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<p>And whereas for the better maintenance of preaching Ministers, several Augmentations by Authority of Parliament have been heretofore granted. Be it further Ordained, that all person or persons, who claim or <unclear>shall</unclear> hereafter claim the benefit of such Augmentation, shall before he or they shall receive the same, obtain the approbation of the said Commissioners or five of them, as a person qualified as is before mentioned. And in case of approbation, such approbation shall be <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> by the Register, who under his hand shall also <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> the same to such person or persons as are or shall be <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to pay such Augmentation, who are hereby required and <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> from time to time to pay the person or persons so approved, such Augmentation as hath been or shall be granted unto him or the place where he preacheth, taking his or their Acquittances for the same. Provided, and it is hereby declared, that this Ordinance or anything therein contained, shall not be construed to extend unto, or to revive any dignities, offices or benefits Ecclesiastical, suppressed by Authority of Parliament. Nor to any benefices Ecclesiastical that were not presentative before the Ordinance for suppression of Bishops: Nor to any Lectures preached or read in any of the Universities.</p>

<p>And it is hereby lastly Declared and Ordained, That the Approbation or admittance aforesaid, in such manner is before prescribed, is not intended nor shall be construed to be any Solemn or Sacred setting apart of a person to any particular office in the Ministry: but only by such trial and approbation to take care that places destitute may be supplied with able and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Preachers throughout this Nation And that such fit and approved persons faithfully labouring in the work of the Gospel, may be in a capacity to receive such <reg orig="publick">public</reg> stipend and maintenance as is or shall be allotted to such places.</p>

<p>HENRY SCOBEL, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>Friday, <em>March</em> 24 was kept (according to the late Declaration set forth by his Highness the Lord Protector) a very solemn day of Humiliation, throughout <em>London, Westminster</em> and the Liberties thereof. There prayed and preached before the Lord Protector and his Council, Mr <em>Lockier</em>, Mr. <em>Strong</em>, and Mr. <em>Craddock</em>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was published for continuing the Act for laying an imposition upon Coals towards the building and maintaining Ships for the guarding of the Seas, to be in force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 of <em>March</em>, 1655.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for passing Custodies for Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance for continuing the Act of Impressing of Seamen to be of force until the first of <em>November</em>, 1654.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<head level="3">From <em>Brussels, March</em> 29. stilo novo.</head>

<p><i>The Marquis of <em>Faber</em> commanding the French Army, which is quartered at present in the Country of <em>Liege</em>, having seen the conclusion of the peace between the Prince and the Elector of <em>Collen</em>, Bishop of <em>Liege</em>, and his Highness the Archduke <em>Leopold William</em>, whereby the first is bound and obliged to the second by an Article of the Treaty, that he should endeavour all what he could to cause the said French Army to retreat and withdraw out of his Territories, by using first all gentle and <reg orig="milde">mild</reg> <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them <reg orig="therunto">thereunto</reg>, and in case they should not take effect, he was then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> his Forces with those of the said Archduke, and should force him to remove by foul and rigorous means, if they should conceive it to be most advantageous to that purpose. But the Marquis perceiving how it was like to go with him would not stay either to receive the one message or the other, but presently removed his quarters from <em>Limbourg</em>, and is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> with his Army the same way he came in, towards the woods of <em><reg orig="Ardenne">Ardennes</reg></em>, having lodged his Army the 22 of this month at <em>Beanfay</em>. But he is not yet got out of <reg orig="harms">harm's</reg> way, he is still in a great deal of danger of being set upon by the <em>Spaniards</em>, who follow him close at the heels with several Bodies of Horse and Foot to encounter him on all sides, intending to fleece him if they can meet with him, before he can make his escape. The <em>Spaniards</em> under the command of the Earl of <em>Fuensaldagn</em>, have made a bridge of Boats at <em>Seille</em>, not far from <em><reg orig="Ardenne">Ardennes</reg></em>, upon the <em>Meuse</em>, who are upon their march to hinder and molest the said <em>French</em> on the right hand: and Monsieur <em>Pardo</em>, Commander in chief in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> and Dukedom of <em>Luxembourg</em>, hath likewise gotten his Forces together, and is marching therewith in hope of hindering them from passing on that side of the world: And in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Prince of <em>Conde</em> his Lieutenant is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> with his Forces, and some <em>Lorainers</em>, to meet the said <em>Faber</em> in the Front, who is said to be environed on all sides, and that it is impossible for him to escape without being fought by the one party or the other, who lay wait for his coming: yet he, like a crafty Monsieur, may lead the Fox a dance before he be made his</i> <pb n="11" />prey. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> whilst all parties are so well <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> in the Country of <em>Liege</em>, the Duke of <em>Newbourgh</em> is raising of an Army in his Country of <unclear><em>Iuillers</em></unclear>, and the Prince Elector of <em>Brandenburgh</em> doth the like in his Country of <em>Cleve</em>. Neither of their <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> are as yet known, unless it be done to preserve and defend their own Territories from being invaded by their friends.</p>

<p>I told you in my last, that his Highness the Archduke had ordered the Earl of <em>Bassigni</em> and the Abbot of <em>Mercy</em> to be removed from the Castle of <em>Antwerp</em> to that of <em><reg orig="Gaunt">Ghent</reg></em>, on purpose to please the Duke of Lorain, who was very much offended to be imprisoned in the same prison with them: but as they were going to remove them, the first of them was taken very ill on the sudden, the occasion of whose sickness is variously spoken of, many suspecting he hath not been kindly dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>. Here do daily arrive a great many Irish out of Ireland, who go to serve the Prince of Conde, and are marching towards <em>Namur</em>, where they will be <reg orig="cloth'd">clothed</reg> and <reg orig="arm'd">armed</reg>: They are most of them very poor men, and for the most part naked; many of them die through want and poverty by the <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>.</p>

<p><i>March 25.</i></p>

<p>About 3 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> in the morning, the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg> with the <em>Dutch</em> Letters going towards <em>Dover</em>, was seized and opened by Thieves within a mile of <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> Church in <em>Southwark</em>, which they did in hope to have found money; but missing that, broke open all packets, and <reg orig="strawed">strewed</reg> them upon the ground.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors removed from the house of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> entertainment in the Palace-yard <em>Westminster</em>, to Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevors">Trevor's</reg></em> house in <em>Channel row</em>, where they reside. The Monday following was appointed to receive Monsieur <em>de Bordeaux</em> from his Majesty of <em>France</em>, and to conduct him by Coach through the City to <em>Westminster</em>, to be entertained at the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> charge, according to his quality: whereupon he is to have audience of his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Bristol</em>, March 27.</head>

<p>Yesterday, a new <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> was launched here for the Lord Protector and the Commonwealth, and another of the 3. Rate is raising on the blocks.</p>

<p>The sufferings of this City of late from the <em>Brest</em> men of war have been great,; scarce a week, but one ship or another of this Port hath been taken by them.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3">From <em>Paris</em>, March 28. 1654.</head>

<p>Yesterday the King, accompanied with several Dukes and Peers Marshals of France and other great ones, went again to take his seat in this Parliament, where after the ordinary formalities in the revision of the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Process, a sentence of death followed, the which his Majesty is this morning gone to cause to be pronounced in that Assembly.</p>

<p>The Reformed Churches begin to be mistrusted here, both by reason of the <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> their Deputies do more and more demonstrate, as also because the Baron of <em>Estssac</em>, who is a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since returned from his Government of <em>Rochel</em>, avers they have sent Ministers into <em>England</em>, and that they have for certain some designs contrary to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="seruice">service</reg>, which they do formally deny.</p>

<p>It is said that the Protestant German Princes and the King of <em>Denmark</em> have of late given <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Seuart">Stuart</reg></em> to understand, that the desolation of the late wars hinders them from being able to entertain him, if he forsakes <em>France</em> to come unto them.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Amsterdam</em>, March 27. <i>stilo novo</i></head>

<p>After long expectation, we hear not yet of a Conclusion of Peace so much desired and expected by the Merchants of this City, who had great hope upon the going away of the Ambassadors for <em>England</em> that the business would have been fully and finally ended without any farther delay; and it was given out over all these Lands, that they had full power and instructions for that purpose: so that men are much troubled here, that they cannot burn the triumphant Pitch-barrels which stand ready for the sacrifice.</p>

<p>Where the obstruction is we know not, nor indeed whether there be any obstruction at all: but this long pause <reg orig="fils">fills</reg> <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> mouths with various discourses, calls upon their fears, and quells their hopes; especially because they think this dilatoriness will give an opportunity to those who <reg orig="maligne">malign</reg> our Peace to throw in some odd bone or other betwixt the <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg>. Doubtless it is the true Interest of these Provinces by all means to maintain Peace with England, and their necessities call aloud for it; and if it be not obtained, manifold &amp; miserable hazards must be undergone by the people, to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of Trade <pb n="13" />if not the Country: which those who are Patriots, and without particular by-interests of their own, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> sufficiently and seriously apprehend.</p>

<p>But there are yet a sort of men lurking, who we know <reg orig="doe">do</reg> long to see the two Commonwealths at it again. These are they who give ear to vain stories, and propagate and countenance them. Great reports they have of <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> proceedings in Scotland, on purpose to lessen the reputation of affairs in England: but hitherto we have always been deceived by those <reg orig="phansies">fantasies</reg>, which have been followed by great and extraordinary successes, and yet they get ground among men in opinion; and those who believe them not, yet love to talk of them, such is their madness. Notwithstanding all these <reg orig="vapors">vapours</reg>, we hope to see Peace, and upon that account rely much on the wisdom and diligence of our Ambassadors.</p>

<p>Here is news which affrights us, of an extraordinary Fleet a setting forth in England: besides, divers of your men of war have been upon our Coasts, and taken Vessels, which hath given the States occasion of issuing out immediate Orders to all the <reg orig="Colledges">Colleges</reg> of the Admiralty to make all possible speed with the Fleet to Sea; but its hoped an Accommodation may be signed before the two Fleets do meet abroad; and that all these storms will at length end in a happy and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Calm, which would be a blessing to both the Nations.</p>

<pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><i>A List of <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Prizes taken by the <em>Phoenix, Newcastle, Assurance, </em>and <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, since February, 1653.</i></head>

<p>March 2. taken by the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot hoy, whose mast being shot by the Board, she was burnt.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the Assurance <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg>, the Hope of Housdown, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p>Taken then also by the Phoenix, the Claus of Housdown, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p>March 14. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaids">Mermaid's</reg></em> Boat, the <em>Fortune </em>of<em> Mazeland Sluys</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 32 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, wherein were many barrels of Fish, and 6 of Salt, with about 40 empty Cask.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the <em><reg orig="Newcastles">Newcastle's</reg></em> Boat, the <em>Skell fish</em> of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, with Fish, Salt, and some empty Cask.</p>

<p>Taken the same day also by the Phoenix her Boat the Plumpart of Mazeland Sluys, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 30 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise.</p>

<p><i>March 12.</i> Taken by the <reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg>, the <em>Providence</em> of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 28 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading.</p>

<p><i>March 17.</i> Brought by the Lee by the Phoenix and her Boat sent on board, and afterward run on board by the Newcastle, who broke her head and Boltsprit, and forced the Phoenix her Boat off, viz. the Fortune of Delfs haven, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>, laden with Brandywine, French wine, Prunes, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the Phoenix the Blew Pigeon of Pumurland, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 Tons, laden also with Brandywine, French wines, and Prunes.</p>

<p><i>March 18</i> Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 25 <reg orig="Tonns">Tons</reg>.</p>

<p><i>March 19</i> Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, two Scotch vessels; the one laden with Beef, Flower, Train-<reg orig="Oyle">Oil</reg>, Deer-skins, and Sugars the other had only Ballast. Both of them were going for Holland, having been first taken by a Private man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> belonging to Enchuysen, but thus recovered.</p>

<p><i>March 20.</i> Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> the Wakeing Buy of Enchuysen, and with her eight Guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportional, 12 Picks, ten Muskets, eight Pistols, and a Boat with four Oars.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<head level="3">From <i>Dalkeith, March 21.</i></head>

<p>The Lord <em>Ray</em> hath sent to <em>Skelco</em> for Arms for his men, <em>Seafort</em> was expected the 10 instant within five mile of <em>Crabsdale</em> with his men, Sir <em>Geo. Monroe</em> and <em>Middleton</em> were then in <em>Stranraver</em>, and to meet <em>Seafort</em> and <em>Ray</em> at <em>Inra</em> with their whole force, where also <em>Glengary</em> with his rabble are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, and so force <em>Suthrland</em> and <em>Caithness</em> to rise. It is reported that since <em>Middleton</em>, a Lord is landed with some men and arms.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Lewis</em> have made slaughter of the Country people that <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Seafort</em>; and they have also slaughtered some of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the old Natives <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with our men against the rest of the Country, so that these divisions cause great devastations in those parts. Those of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniels'</reg></em> Regiment which quartered in the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Logie</em>, have found 22 new Muskets, 9 firelocks, 11 Swords, 9 or 10 sets of <reg orig="bandaliers">bandoleers</reg>, three quarters of a barrel of powder, and 13 Bundles of Match, they were close made up in a wall, and found out by accident. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> is again come from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and divers parties in these parts stealing horses, which the wit of man cannot prevent, the Country are so false, and yet cannot but see that all those people from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> can <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, is to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> them, rather than injure the English, against whom they pretend their chief quarrel.</p>

<p>The Commander in chief hath apprehended and confined some who discover themselves addicted to the other Party; <reg orig="on">one</reg> of them being Mr. <em>Knox</em> of <em>Kelfray</em>, partly for praying for the pretended King, and declaring his affection to the Rebels that are in Arms against us, and partly for somewhat of correspondence.</p>

<p>The Book <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <em>The true State of the Case of the Commonwealth</em> as now in a <em>Lord Protector</em>, which was printed lately at <em>London</em>, being a <reg orig="Peece">Piece</reg> that gives good satisfaction, is reprinted at <em>Leith</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Whitehall, March 29.</i></head>

<p>Audience was given by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> to Monsieur <em>de Bordeaux</em>, Ambassador from his Majesty of <em>France</em>.</p>

<hr />
<p>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the <unclear>Act</unclear> for Printing</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>