<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol206">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 206</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. d Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, May 18. to <em>Thursday</em>, May 25. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Dalkieth, May 11.</i></head>

<p>COL: <em>Morgan</em> quarters about the River <em>Tane</em>, guarding all the Passes, that (if possible) he may prevent the Enemy from making way <em>Southward</em>, if anything of that nature should be attempted. But as yet there is no likelihood of that; for the enemy are as yet in Parties remote from each other, <em>Middleton</em> one way, and <em>Glencairn</em> another. Besides, out Intelligencers agree, that their number diminisheth. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> brother, with some few Officers, and a party of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, ventured down upon some <!--typo or reg??-->parrt of our Forces, which were roused and repelled, and most of them taken; among others, the brother of <em>Middleton</em>. The General hath hanged <pb n="1" /> up two lately as <reg orig="Spyes">Spies</reg>, and caused an Inn in <em>Musselborough</em>, which received &amp; concealed them, to be burnt down to the ground. He marched yesterday from hence toward <em>Sterling</em>, and thence he goes to take the field.</p>

<p>Since the concluding of the <em>Dutch</em> peace, the enemy is much broken in point of resolution, and their Adherents and <reg orig="Favorers">Favourers</reg> are not so ranting, as heretofore, in their expressions; for they were made still to believe, that great supplies would be brought them out of the <em>Low-<reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris, May 23. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>Preparations are now in a manner <reg orig="compleated">completed</reg>, for carrying on his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service in the field; the Prince of <em>Conti</em> is gone hence with considerable Recruits toward <em>Catalonia</em>, which being united with the old Forces, will much expedite the affairs of that Kingdom or Province.</p>

<p>The Fortifications go on still on all sides, upon the sea-coasts of this Kingdom, because of the English Fleet, which put <em>France</em> upon its guard, because a great storm hovers upon the sea, and none knows where it <reg orig="wil">will</reg> fall, nor will these fears and jealousies be over, till it be known what the issue of the French Treaty will be in <em>England</em>. Upon this consideration it is, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his brothers, take encouragement, and are not without such <reg orig="shews">shows</reg> of countenance and favours from this Court, as Complement and Courtship amounts to. They have been <reg orig="re-visited">revisited</reg> by them; and no doubt but many more the like <pb n="2" />complements will pass between them, till it be known how things will go between your <em>Lord Protector</em> and this Kingdom; and if there be not Peace in the close of this Negotiation, then perhaps the <em>Stuarts</em> may continue here, and receive more respects <reg orig="then">than</reg> formerly, in hope use may be made of them and their broken Interest, to your disturbance and vexation. Hence it is that many stories are spread beforehand concerning the Royal Affairs in the <em>Scottish Highlands</em>, where <em>Middleton</em> (they say) hath gathered together a very great force, and is marched thence to the <em>Lowlands</em>: But how true is this, we shall know in time. Nothing is omitted that may represent the Scots formidable, and the English contemptible. In sum, the matter is clear, that if you and the French agree not, then <em>France</em> will <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to renew the old game, by creating you all the troubles they can in <em>Scotland</em>, and make use of it as a Back door to vent their designs upon <em>England</em>, as in the days of yore. But the <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> here is, that there is hope of peace with the <em>English</em>, and it is desired much the more, because of your conclusion with <em>Holland</em>, and the rest of the <em>United Provinces</em>.</p>

<p>The <em>Campania</em> is now ready to begin here, and Marshal <em>Tureine</em> is ready to advance toward the General <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>; and the more expedition will be used, because of the forwardness of the <em>Archduke</em>, the <em>Lorainers</em>, and the Prince of <em>Conde</em>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, the Court is dissolved in mirth and Comedy, and the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> day of Coronation at <em>Rheims</em>, which now draws on, is ushered in <pb n="3" /> with Balls and Masques, and Stage-plays, at which none (or very few) of the Princes of the Blood will be present.</p>

<p>May 19 Was published the following Ordinance:</p>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <em>An Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair the Common <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg> within this Nation</em>, among other things, It is Ordained, That if any <reg orig="waggons">wagons</reg>, carts or carriages wherein any <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg> of dead <reg orig="commodies">commodities</reg> or wares shall at any time from and after the first day of May, then next be drawn upon any such <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>, Roads or Streets, with above five Horses, or Mares, or six Oxen and one Horse or Mare, in any one cart for any Constable or Surveyor of Highways, or other Inhabitant in any Parish where such <reg orig="Loaden">Laden</reg> wagon, cart or carriage shall pass and be drawn as aforesaid, to distrain and seize all such supernumerary horses, mares or oxen, as he shall find in any such wagon, cart or carriage over and above the number five horses or mares, or six oxen and one Horse or Mare respectively to detain and keep, until such owner or driver have paid and answered into the hands of the Surveyors of <reg orig="high ways">highways</reg> within the parish where such Distress and Seizure shall be made, or one of them, the sum of twenty shillings for every such supernumerary horse, mare or ox. Be it now ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. by and with the consent of his Council, <pb n="4" /> That the said Ordinance, or any clause therein contained, shall not extent to any cart or carriages at any time used in the conveying, draught or carriage of any ordinance, timber or artillery, of any sort or kind whatsoever, for the use of the Army or Navy, but that such carts, draughts or carriages may be drawn with any number of horses or oxen necessary for the drawing thereof, without incurring any of the penalties in the said Ordinance mentioned, or without any stop, molestation or disturbance of any Constable, Officer, or other person whatsoever, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Provided, that such persons that attend the said Draughts, carts or carriages for the use of the said Army or Navy, have some order or pass under the hands of his Highness the Lord Protector, or the Lord President of his Council, or of the Commissioners of the Admiralty and Navy, or Generals of the Fleet, or other Field Officers of the Army, Commissioners of the Navy, or some Governor of a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, or under the hands of some of them, signifying that such carriages and draught are for the use of the said Army or Navy, as is aforesaid.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Gottenbugh, April 24.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> having happily concluded the Treaty between us and <em>England</em>, is on his way homewards; and all things are now in a readiness at <em>Upsal</em> for the beginning of the Diet, which is to be on the first of May, the Queen then <reg orig="its">it's</reg> fully resolved will surrender <pb n="5" /> her Crown and Government unto her <reg orig="cosin">cousin</reg> the Prince Palatine <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, who is to be crowned King of <em>Sweden</em>, his brother Prince <em>Adolphus John</em> having laid down his Patent of Lord High Marshal of the King, and is gone to <em>Stockholm</em>, and from thence to <em>Braburgh</em>, and so for the Isle of <em>Oeland</em>, to confer with his brother the future King who will tarry there till the beginning of the Diet: we hear likewise that the Earl <em>Erick Oxenstern</em> is now appointed to go as an Ambassador extraordinary into <em>England</em> with a great retinue. Here is lately deceased the Lady <em>Fletwood</em>, late wife of Sir <em>George Fletwood</em>. The funeral is appointed in great pomp. The Queen and many of the Nobility of <em>Sweden</em> are to be present.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Upsal the 21 of April,</i> 1654, S.U.</head>

<p>My last told you of the Agreement of all things here. The Articles are <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>, but not yet signed, by reason of the absence of the Queen. Her <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> is expected to return this night, and if so, I doubt not but all things will be <reg orig="dispatch'd">dispatched</reg> so as to quit this place within this week. All things are busily preparing for the sitting of Parliament, which will be about the beginning of May and then they will proceed to the election of a new King.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Regensburgh, May 3.</i> S.N.</head>

<p>The <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> departure hence is not yet certainly known, although the 28 of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> be appointed. This point of justice is now fully dispatched, to the great contentment of all, as also the point of credit, concerning <unclear>the instant</unclear> pensions, whereof only the <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear><pb n="6" /> to be paid, and that ten years hence. The point of security will be likewise shortly resolved. But the Gravamina are deferred to a Ryx Deputation, which is appointed at <em><reg orig="Franckfurt">Frankfurt</reg></em> against the first of September next.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> this 9 Dito </i> S.U.</head>

<p>This day there came on here a passenger from <em>Bremen</em>, who having, because of the Swedes taken his journey about through the Land of <em>Luneburgh</em> relates upon his oath, that the Duke of <em>Lunenbourgh</em> was raising all the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> people, and <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> of the <em><reg orig="Neather">Nether</reg></em> Saxish crays <!--Unable to find meanings or replacements for saxish and crays-->, together with those <em>Westphalen,</em> for the assistance and defence of the city of <em>Bremen</em>, against general <em>Konigsmarck</em>, and that the said city had also raised 1800 men, which are to be paid out of the cash of the Empire. If this business comes not quickly to composition, we may be sure of another general war in Germany, which the Lord avert in mercy.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick, the 3</i> Dito.</head>

<p>From hence no news at all. The Treasurer of <em>Poland</em> is come on here about, moneys, what answer will be given him is yet unknown. It is believed he <reg orig="wil">will</reg> get but small comfort here without <!--??-->ait be a little for himself.</p> 

<p>May 16. It was ordered, that the following Ordinance be published, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for relief of Debtors in <em>Scotland</em>, in some cases of extremity.</i></p>

<p>For the better moderating the severity of the proceedings, which by the Laws of Scotland are had by creditors against their Debtors, in <pb n="7" />several cases of great extremity; and so to the end such Creditors may have satisfaction of what is or shall be due unto them; be it ordained, and it is hereby ordained, by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, that the Commissioners for administration of Justice in <em>Scotland</em> for the time being, be <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> and <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to moderate Decrees, to be by them given out against such Debtors as shall manifestly appear to them not to be able to procure money for paying such Debt, by allowing some fit and convenient time or days for payment of the said Debt, with interest for the same, until such time or days of payment, and at the expiration of such time appointed; in case the said Debts be not satisfied, to appoint and set out Debt, as such values as the same were worth in the year, One thousand six hundred forty eight, and to decree the same to be enjoyed by such Creditors, and their heirs, or otherwise according to such Decree, in satisfaction and discharge of such debt, and all further proceedings against such Debtor or his estate for the same. This Ordinance to continue in force until the <reg orig="Twelth">Twelfth</reg> day of May, One thousand six hundred fifty five.</p>

<p>May 18. Monsieur <em>de Bordeaux</em> the French Ambassador, had audience of his Highness the Lord Protector at <em>Whitehall</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, May 9.</i></head>

<p>The publication of peace hath <reg orig="fixt">fixed</reg> and filled us here with joy; but that you press Seamen out <pb n="8" /> of the very companies ships coming hither, puts us upon expectation of some notable design in hand, yet on this side we fear not, the <em>Dane</em> being included.</p>

<p>Sure the Articles of peace will be made <reg orig="publike">public</reg>, how else can they be observed: I hear not of any that have yet seen them; if you divulge them not, the world will think and say they are less <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> might be expected and concluded.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brussels the 24 of May.</i></head> 

<p><em>Nicolas Francis </em>Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, is now at last gone from hence, to command his Army, which is quartered at <em>Courtray, <unclear>Meuyn</unclear></em> and <em>Armentiers</em> upon the River of <em>Lisse</em>: The reason of his stay here <!-- one word or two??-->thuslong was occasioned through the multiplicity of business, which required a great deal of time, before they could be <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg> in order to his Army. He was nobly received and entertained at <em>Gent</em>, and other Towns through which he <reg orig="past">passed</reg>. The Prince his eldest son is in his company, of the age of 14 years. The said Duke is like his brother Duke <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, who is still close prisoner in <em>Antwerp</em> Castle, but there is a great deal of difference in their dispositions and behaviours; <em>Francis</em> Duke of <reg orig="Lorraign">Lorain</reg> being of a good and pleasing nature, the other malicious, rough and deceitful, his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> and his Highness the Archduke have given the whole administration of all the estate to <em>Francis</em> Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, to be at his disposal. Those of the Army do <reg orig="shew">show</reg> themselves very willing to serve under him; they have sent several of their <reg orig="Troups">Troops</reg> to meet him, and to <pb n="9" /> congratulate his safe arrival amongst them: so that all things seem to favour his designs, and comply with the desires of those of the Court.</p>

<p>There are great preparation a making for the speedy setting forth of a good fleet of ships to sea, for the service of these parts, their design is not yet known.</p>

<p>His Highness the Archduke is not very well to pass at present, his excellency the Earl of <em>Fuenseldagn</em> is here at present, being very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> to raise a supply of moneys for the recruits of his Army.</p> 

<p>Here is a report, that the French having drawn out several troops of their <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> of <unclear><em>Arvas</em></unclear>, <em>Bethune</em> and <unclear><em>Basse</em></unclear> have fallen upon the Spanish troops, and have ruined part of them, to the number of a thousand horse <reg orig="kil'd">killed</reg> upon the place, and a great number besides taken prisoners; the confirmation whereof is daily expected, very few here will give credit to it.</p>

<p>May 6. It was ordered by his Highness and the Council, that the following Ordinance be published, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for holding the County Court for the County of <em>Chester</em>, at the Town of <em><reg orig="North-wich">Northwich</reg></em>, during the continuance of the infection of the plague in <em>Chester</em></i>.</p>

<p>Whereas the Shire-Hall of the County Palatine of <em>Chester</em> is situate within the Castle of <em>Chester</em>, which City is now visited with the plague, by reason whereof the Sheriff of the said County Palatine of <em>Chester</em> cannot, without danger to the whole County, keep his Court in the said Shire-hall, where the same ought to be, <pb n="10" /> and usually hath been kept; Be it therefore ordained by his highness the lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, by and with the consent of his Council, That the Sheriff of the said County shall have full power and authority, and he hath hereby <reg orig="ful">full</reg> power and Authority given upon the same Tuesday every Month as formerly, to keep his said County-Court in the Town of <em>Northwich</em>, in the said County of <em>Chester</em>, and to adjourn the same from time to time to any other Market Town or <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> place within the said county, where he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> think convenient for the ease and safety of the Inhabitants of the said County, until the <!--said??-->sid infection of the Plague in <em>Chester</em> aforesaid shall cease, and no longer; at which time the said Court shall or may be adjourned unto the said Shire hall again, there to be held and kept upon the same Tuesday every <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> in such manner as formerly it hath been used and accustomed, and that all Acts, Things and Proceedings in Law, had and done, and to be had and done in the said County Court, since the now last Court, kept in the said Shire-hall in the said Castle of <em>Chester</em>, and until the said Court <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be adjourned to the said Shire-hall again, shall be, and shall be adjudged, deemed, taken and construed to be to all intents and purposes of the same force, effect and validity in Law, as if the same had been kept still in the said Shire-hall, the Statute, made in the three and thirtieth year of the Reign of the late King <em>Henry</em> the eight, or any other Statute, Law, Order or Ordinance of Parliament, Usage or <pb n="11" /> Custom to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris the 15 of May.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> hath deferred his day of <em>Sacr&eacute;</em> till the day of the Holy Trinity, as they call it, and have resolved to have it in the City of <em>Rheims</em>, whither they have sent great store of <reg orig="tapistry">tapestry</reg> and other luggage, and great quantity of provisions of all sorts.</p>

<p>All <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Ministers of State are invited to it. The Commissioners of the said City have assured his Majesty that he shall be very welcome to it, obeyed and <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> by his most humble subjects The design of the Duke of <em>Guise</em> is to make a <reg orig="desent">descent</reg> in <em>Andalusia</em>, with the assistance of the King of Portugal, the Marquis of <em>Plessis Belliere</em>, and the Lord of <em>Bellesands</em>, are to go with him as his Lieutenant Generals. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is ready to depart to go and command the Army of the King in <em>Catalogne</em>; he is to take <reg orig="shiping">shipping</reg> in Province, where there is a fleet ready to transport him on that side of Rhodes. The Card <em>de Rhets</em> is still close Prisoner at Rheims. Here <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> lately <reg orig="Mounsier">Monsieur</reg> de Broussel, one of the <reg orig="chiefest">chief</reg> authors of the war in Paris, and the differences between those of the Parliament. The Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> is now agreed with this Court, &amp; the business composed on both sides. The Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Arms are now defaced <reg orig="every where">everywhere</reg>. There is a report of a league offensive and defensive between <em>France</em> and <em>Portugal</em>, who doth undertake to set forth a fleet to assist that of <em>France</em> The Treaty of <em>France</em> with <em>England</em> is said to be well <pb n="12" /> accepted of by those of the Government there, &amp; that there is a great likelihood of an accommodation between both nations. Prince <em>Robert</em> is said to go suddenly for <em>Germany</em>. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> intends likewise to be going from hence very suddenly:</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dublin, May 7.</i></head>

<p>All is (we tank God) very quiet in this country. The Transplanted <em>Irish</em> have many of them gone into <em>Conaught</em>, according to the time appointed, which was the first of <em>May</em>. Others there are that linger and keep back; for remedy whereof, the Commissioners have published a Declaration. A declaration is likewise put forth by the <em>General</em>, wherein you may see what course is taken in reducing part of the Forces.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsall">Upsall</reg>, <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg> 21.</i></head>

<p>We are now about leaving this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, as we hope: The Negotiation here being brought to a period, only there wants the signing of the Articles, by reason of the absence of the Queen: But her Majesty is upon her Return, and is expected here this night: And I question not, but we shall be dismissed in very few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and that to satisfaction on all parts.</p>

<p>They are preparing here for the sitting of the next Parliament, which will be the beginning of May. And that my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> departure may not be too near the Election of the succeeding King, for the avoiding of all exceptions He is resolved to hasten all that possibly he may, out of this Country.</p> <pb n="13" /> 

<p>There is nothing more here, that these Parts afford: We are exceedingly glad that you are likely to enjoy that blessing of Peace in England; which I wish from my heart were sanctified unto the Nation.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg> May 23. stilo novo.</i></head>

<p>Here are three Ambassadors arrived from the great D. of <em>Muscovy</em> one of them is a going for <em>France</em>; the other 2 had Audience the other day; they gave to understand that the said Duke had resolved to wage war against the King of <em>Poland</em>; and desired leave to buy Arms and Ammunition in these Provinces. They <reg orig="doe">do</reg> likewise assure, that they have great quantity of Corn, that in the City of <em>Archangel</em> alone, there is above sixty thousand <reg orig="Tonn">Tonne</reg> of Corn ready to be exported. It seems that they will not hearken here to the demand which the Great Master hath made here for some Goods which he claims in this Country, as belonging to him; however the <reg orig="maretime">maritime</reg> Towns, who do not pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>, desire he may have satisfaction given him, for fear their Commerce be not interrupted upon the Mediterranean Sea by the <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> of that Order.</p>

<p>We are now taken up with Preparations for our Triumph and Thanksgiving day, which is to be celebrated next Wednesday, but here is a great deal of noise about a secret Article, which is said to be added by the States of Holland, without being communicated to the <reg orig="States Generall">States-General</reg>; whereby the Prince of Orange and his whole Race and Posterity, in case he hate any, are to be excluded out of all the charges and dignities, which the deceased Prince of Orange did possess. This caused some of the Cities to protect against it, and the six other Provinces desired a copy of what the States of Holland had agreed and concluded upon this subject. Likewise it is said, that the said States have sent an express into England, to <reg orig="recal">recall</reg> their Messenger that was <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg> by them with this private article but a little before, to prevent the delivery thereof to the Lord Protector; a great reward is promised him, in case he can overtake him. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, they debate about the disposal of their fleet, which is said, will be sent for <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg>, to re-establish our affairs there.</p>

<head level="3">From aboard the <em>Tauton</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> off of <reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg>, May, 13.</head>

<p>I believe you may not expect what we have not to answer your <pb n="14" /> expectation in, <em>Viz,</em> Of news from sea; yet to the great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> of all honest hearts I hope, this I can tell you, I saw the Dutch do Homage to the English ships, in the very place, or near to it, where they sought and desired to have destroyed them, now three years ago almost. <em>Deus nobis <unclear>h&aelig;c otia fecit</unclear></em>. On Thursday 11. Instant, <em>De Wits </em>Reer Adm. of Adm. with a ship of 56 Guns, and two more proper ships, convoy to 70 sail of Dutch bound for <em>Greenland</em>, struck flag and topsails to Vice Admiral <em>Lawson</em>, and his squadron, and suffered themselves to be visited, and searched by yours, when was as much as could be expected; and very liberally saluted ours, and were re-saluted by ours.</p>

<head level="3">From Glasgow in Scotland, May 14.</head>

<p>Col. <em>Cooper</em> having occasion to send his wife and his Lieut. Col. To the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Ayr</em>, sent a party of 22 Dragoons to convey them. As the Dragoons were returning back, they met with a party of the enemy rambling about the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, being <unclear>60</unclear> horse, under command of the Laird of <em>Cairdennis</em>, and charged and routed them, killed the Laird <em>Cairdennis</em> himself, with two Corners, and 9 more upon the place, took divers horse and men, and the rest fled for it. This is all the action and enemy that hath of late been in these parts; which was indeed very handsomely performed, not one of our men being lost, and but two wounded, which are upon recovery.</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector.</head>

<p>Whereas the Enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal <reg orig="providences">providence</reg> of God in frustrating of their former counsels and Malicious designs) do appear still restless in their Attempts, to involve this Commonwealth in blood and confusion. In Order whereunto dicers of them have lately repaired to London, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this Commonwealth. His Highness, with the advice of his Council, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby expressly charge and command, That for the better discovery of persons <reg orig="il">ill</reg>-affected to the peace of this Commonwealth, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the cities of London and Westminster, Borough of Southwark, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith, after the publication hereof, repair from the <reg orig="housholders">householders</reg> a list of the name of all such persons as now do, or did lodge in their respective houses on Friday night last, being the nineteenth of this instant May, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodges there.</p>

<p>And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such Names upon <reg orig="perill">peril</reg> of being reputed and dealt withal as <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg> and Partakers <pb n="15" />in the said <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>, which Lists so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of London and Westminster, Borough of Southwark, and Lines of communication, are within forty eight hours to deliver to the Lord Major of London, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to fail at their utmost peril. And the said Lord Major and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Council at Whitehall, immediately after the receipt thereof.</p>

<p>And his Highness doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever, lodging within the lines of Communication, do change his or their respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the date hereof, without a special Licence and Pass in that behalf obtained from the Lord Major of the said City of London, or Bailiff of Westminster or Southwark respectively, are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to give to all such persons concerning whom they shall be satisfied, that they have no ill intentions or designs against the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to none else. And if any such person shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without licence obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a Contempt of this his Highness Command, and be punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Major of the City of London, and Bailiffs of Westminster and Southwark respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after Publication thereof, to be sent to the several Constables as aforesaid, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> the 23 of May, 1654.</i></p>

<p>These are to give notice, that the News which hath been published once this week already, and may be printed perhaps again by other hands, concerning some of our English Mariners landing in <em>France</em> near S. <em>Malo's</em>, and driving away <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg>, &amp;c. is false.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em>, May 20. Discovery was made of a barbarous Conspiracy, undertaken by divers persons, concerning which more hereafter; in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, you may know in general, that their intent was, by <reg orig="vilainous">villainous</reg> Assassinations, to have returned the State into blood and confusions. A piece of Treason so much the more to be detested in <em>England</em>, in regard the generous nature of the English doth usually abhor such unmanly practises, so that they have very rarely been heard of among us. Divers persons have been apprehended about it, and examined, as <em>Gilbert Gerard</em> Esq; commonly called <em>Sir Gilbert</em>, and <em>John Gerard</em> his brother, <em>Humphrey Bagaley, Sidney Fotherby, John Jones</em> an Apothecary, and <em>Thomas Tuder</em>, who were all of them ordered to be committed to the Tower of <em>London</em>.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>