<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="MPol200">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Mercurius Politicus, Issue 200</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><i>Mercurius Politicus, </i></head>
<head level="1">Comprising the sum of all Intel-</head>
<head level="2">ligence, with the Affairs and Designs</head>
<head level="3">now on foot in the three <em>Nations</em></head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="3">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>
<head level="2">In defence of the Commonwealth,</head>
<head level="3">and for Information of the People.</head>
<head level="3">&mdash; <i>It&agrave; vertere Seria</i>. { Horat. De Ar. Poet.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Thursday</em>, April 6. to <em>Thursday</em>, April 13. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>From Sterling, March 28.</i></head>

<p>Our expectations here are very great touching the business of a close with the Dutch; and so much the rather, because we observe the enemy here waits for an hour of a wider breach, reckoning that the only opportunity to put people into a Flame. Divers of the great ones Northward, who yet appear not themselves, send out their second and third Sons, but keep the eldest at home, as not willing to hazard estates, and others they set on underhand, which gives the Enemy great encouragement.</p>

<p>It is a rare thing to meet with a man that will <pb n="1" />give us any Intelligence. I could not have imagined they had been so rotten, as now we <reg orig="finde">find</reg> them in this hour of <reg orig="Triall">Trial</reg>. Their Army, as they own now and call it, is still in the North, perfecting the Levies, that they may come on with the more <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> toward the South.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsall">Upsala</reg> l March 10.</i> S. V.</head>

<p>We are here expecting the issue of the Treaty between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>. That being once fully known, I doubt not but we shall have a very speedy and desirable dispatch. My Lord Ambassador is not altogether idle, he <reg orig="plyes">plies</reg> the Queen very hard, and hath put his Negotiation into a very great forwardness. All those things which are of an indifferent cognisance, and not of that grant respect, touching upon a necessary consideration either as to peace or war with the <em>Dutch</em> receive a very candid acceptation.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Danzick March 25.</i> S: N:</head>

<p>The Polish <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> should end this day, but is supposed will be prolonged for 3, or 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, as yet we cannot hear of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that's done, the lower House refusing to act till the <em>Vacantia</em>, especially the office of the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, be disposed of by the King. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> thought he would willingly bestow it upon Duke <em>John Radzevil</em>, but expects he should petition for it, which the other will not do, conceiving <reg orig="its">it's</reg> his due by merit; a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will now <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the effect of this, and what will be done concerning the Cossacks and Muscovites, which is most likely will be war.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Regensborgh 25 dito,</i> S: N:</head>

<p>Yesterday the business concerning the <em>Vecht</em> was <pb n="2" />brought so far to an end, that on the 15 of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em> next the said place is to be evacuated. His <reg orig="Emperiall">Imperial</reg> Majesties departure stands determined on the 20 day of the next month precise. The point of Justice is almost brought to perfection. But about the <reg orig="Paragraphe">Paragraph</reg> and Indaganda they <reg orig="canot">cannot</reg> yet agree, which causeth many <reg orig="to">too</reg> long to see the event thereof. Last night the Grave of <em>St Amour</em> who was sent to <em>Wein</em> to his Highness Du: <em>Francis</em> of Lorrain, returned hither, and brought news that his said Highness would very shortly be break up thence, and repair hither with a considerable Train. From <em><reg orig="Insbruck">Innsbruck</reg></em> we have information of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> great Earthquakes that have been there of late.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> March 28.</i> S: V.</head>

<p>Some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> ago a Letter from the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> came to the King of Denmark, who was then within half a Mile of this City, intimating unto him, that by some words which their Ambassadors had gathered at Sir <em>Abraham Williams's</em> house, they conceived, that a Fleet of English ships were appointed shortly to visit the Sound. Whereupon the King instantly sent Port to Denmark, and it was reported that himself was gone also, but this continues not, he being seen since at <em>Gluckstadt</em>. This City is much displeased by reason the King at his being at <em>Alcena</em>, came one time with 30, or 40 horse quite up to their walls; so that the Century thought he would have <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> the City; but he suddenly turning his horse, rounded only the walls, and so left them; but the chief reason of their displeasure; is the refusing of their Present.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>From <em>Aberdeen</em> March 24. The Earl of Athole is come to <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencarne</reg> with about 700 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> &amp; foot, Seaford, and some new raised Forces by him are daily expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. Glencarne with his whole Force, being 2000 Horse and Foot, is at Dingwell, two miles from Brahan, not undeserving the name of an Island, which gives hopes of engaging the Enemy there. In order to which, Lieutenant Col: <em>Mitchell</em> is to march tomorrow towards <reg orig="Innernesse">Innerness</reg> with 9. Companies of Foot, and <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> follows him the day after with 5 Troops of <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Rich</em> his Regiment, and four Troops of Dragoons. He intends to take with him <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment, which in his way, and to draw five companies of Foot out of <reg orig="Innernesse">Innerness</reg>.</p>

<p>Some young Lairds and others that had a purpose to glean a party of Horse in <em>Lothian</em>, and so repair to the enemy, were lately taken, and <reg orig="caryed">carried</reg> Prisoners to <em>Dalkeith</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Cowes</em> in the Isle of <em>Wight</em>, <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg> 6, A private Man of <reg orig="warr">war</reg> hath brought in Two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, Two small French Vessels, the One laden with Salt, the other hath little in her but Ballast; There is nothing more of our Fleet but that they are most of them rear to <em>Hellens point</em>, and the rest at the <em>Spits head</em>, being in all near 100 Sail, gallant ships, and bravely accommodated; Here are at present <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Merchant ships in this Road, being wind-bound, and expecting some Easterly winds to carry them on their voyage, and many that were here, went away yesterday morning toward the <em>Downs</em>.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>The ships which were in this Road, are for the most part gone up into the Thames; There remaineth <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a few which are bound to the Southward, this day also passed by about 40, or 50 Sail of ships great and small, which we suppose to be the Dunkirk Fleet bound for London; for Holland, to get the Ratification of the Peace made with them, and an <reg orig="Expresse">Expression</reg> from the Dutch Ambassadors of the Agreement.</p>

<p>To say something further of the Peace between England and Holland, because we <reg orig="finde">find</reg> many so hard to give credit to it; The Articles of the Treaty, we assure you, were Signed and Sealed by the Commissioners on both sides, on Wednesday night last, as before expressed, and within 14 days are to be Signed and Sealed by the Lord Protector, and the States of Holland, and then to be <reg orig="publiquely">publicly</reg> proclaimed and published, both in England and Holland in one day. The Agreement with Denmark is also taken in upon Articles; And for the loss sustained by the English Merchants, whose demands amount to about 150000 <em>l</em> It is referred to Two English, and Two Dutch Merchants, absolutely to determine those Demands within Twenty days; and their place of fitting appointed at Guild-Hall. Also the business of <em>Amboyna</em> is referred to Eight Commissioners, who have 6 Months time to determine thereof; and in case they agree not, Umpires are nominated.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3">From Brussels, April 12. S.N.</head>

<p>Last Wednesday his Highness the Archduke went from hence accompanied with a great many persons of <reg orig="qualitie">quality</reg> for Mantagu, to <reg orig="conferr">confer</reg> and discourse with the Prince Elector of Cullen, who was arrived there already with a great train of Gentlemen.</p>

<p>The Earl of Basigny and the Abbot of Mercy prisoners in the Castle of Gant, are to be proceeded against very suddenly, Commissioners are already appointed to draw up their Charge, in order to their <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>: they are kept from speaking or seeing one another.</p>

<p>There are two ships arrived at Ostend that came from Spain with <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, for the raising of men in Germany, who afterwards are to be transported again into Spain.</p>

<p>All things are preparing here for the next <reg orig="Campagn">Campaign</reg>, and most part of the Spanish Troops are already in Arms near Mons, Valenchiennes and Doway, either to defend or offend.</p>

<p>On Thursday last went also from hence the Prince of Conde for Valenchiennes, to take order about his Forces.</p>

<p>The Earl of St. Amour arrives here two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since out of <em>Germany</em>, who hath brought news that Francis Duke of Lorain will be here very suddenly to command his <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> Army. Here is a report as if the French Troops that were in the <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg> of Liege, were joined with the Marshal la Ferte Seneterre, and had besieged a place called Hermestein upon the Rhine, the certainty whereof is daily expected.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>We wonder here what you mean to linger the Treaty and enlarge your Fleet. You have a <reg orig="alarmd">alarmed</reg> the King of Denmark by some words let fall to the Ambassadors at their entertainment, which were posted on to the Hague, and thence by those States to the King at Glucstat, as if your whole Fleer were going to shovel his Island into the <reg orig="Baltick">Baltic</reg> Fish pond.</p>

<p>If your next Letter tell us not what you intend, we shall conclude no Peace.</p>

<head level="3">From Paris April 15. S.N.</head>

<p>In my last I told you how that the King and Cardinal refused to give audience to the Protestant Commissioners, upon some fine invention they had formed, of not displeasing the Pope at this present conjuncture of Affairs; but they have considered of it since, and have ordered some kind of answer to be drawn up to their desires, on purpose not to displease them on the other hand. In the mean time the good news of reception and entertainment of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> at London by his Highness the Lord Protector, hath <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> pleased this Court, being at the same time freed from the report which we had here, having put most into a fright, that the English were landed in some part of France, but the same not proving true, his Majesty the next night danced the first time his great Ball whereof I have formerly mentioned, Two or three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since there happened a great disturbance in the Church of St. Paul in this City, where one of the Priests preached <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg><pb n="7" /> in his Sermon, that it was lawful for any of his <reg orig="Parishionesrs">Parishioners</reg> to make their confessions to any Priest whom they please to make choice of, which <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> of Confession, the <reg orig="Curats">Curates</reg> pretend to belong to them alone; and thereupon they raised a <reg orig="hubbarb">hubbub</reg> in the Church and tumbled down all the benches, that the poor Priest could not be heard, nor suffered to proceed any further, but was fain to come down and shift for himself; since that the Curates have cited him before the <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, where they intend to proceed against him, as an <reg orig="Incroacher">Encroacher</reg> upon their <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>.</p>

<p>It is said that his Majesty hath sent to the little Queen and her Children to desire them to remove out of his Territories, for that the English were resolved to send an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> reciprocally into France, and that their pensions should be paid them where they should please to appoint to have it paid; and it is supposed that they did return answer that they would be gone to take the fresh air, upon this doleful news to them, of the agreement between the English and the Dutch, the better to consult together what course to steer, whether for Germany or Scotland.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Bassee is gone from hence for Bassee; against which place it is said the Spaniards have designed some enterprise, being upon their march near to that place.</p>

<p>The Cardinal of Retz is arrived at Nants, where <pb n="8" />he is fairly promised he shall have his liberty given him. Some hazard he did run in his passage of being cast away, there arising a great storm in his way. Many if his friends do from hence to see him with the good liking and pleasure of both their Majesties, who have only ordered a flight guard to wait upon him when he goes abroad</p>

<head level="3"><em>An Ordinance for Adjourning part of Easter Term</em>, 1654.</head>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to adjourn part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>; Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That part of the said Term of <em>Easter </em>now next coming be Adjourned, that is to say, from and after the first Return, called <em>Quindena Ascensione</em>; And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em> Westminster</em>, in or at any day or time, form and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, may tarry at their dwelling, or where their business shall <reg orig="lye">lie</reg>, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, until the said last Return, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf.</p>

<p>And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, and Barons of the <em>Exchequer</em>, giving them authority to adjourn the said part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the said first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, until the said last Return of the said Term, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made, ad aforesaid. And be it further Ordained, That all Matters, Causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suites</reg>, depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained, That a former Ordinance of the sixth day of this instant <em>April</em>, for the Adjourning of part of the said Term, until the first Return of <em>Trinity</em> Term next, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, be from henceforth Repealed and void. And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England </em>and <em>Wales</em>, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the Chief Market Towns and usual places within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From the Hague</em>, April 10.</head>

<p>The last Letters from <em>London</em> sent by an Express from the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> to the States, do import that the Peace between this State <pb n="9" />and the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> was almost concluded, and that there wanted nothing to be decided between them, but the business of <em>Denmark</em> as to reparation suffered by the English in their ships formerly stayed in the <em>Sound</em> by the King of <em>Denmark</em>; which point was likewise near concluded, so that by the next we doubt not we shall hear the joyful news of Peace, which God grant to continue amongst us. In the mean time the States do further all what they can the setting out of their Fleet, which we suppose will be ready in a short time, since there is such a concourse of <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> everywhere to supply our ships. It is said that there are 50 good ships ready at <em>Amsterdam</em>, besides a good number in the other Ports and <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg> of these Provinces.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From Cullen</em>, April 6.</head>

<p>The Electors of <em>Cullen</em> and <em>Triers</em> have laid close siege to the Fortress of <em>Harmestein</em>, which they do batter with two pieced of Ordnance. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> defends himself very <reg orig="cauragiously">courageously</reg>, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed, he will endeavour to make some handsome composition for himself, and so surrender the place, which is very much suspected.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Iliustrious">Illustrious</reg> Prince of <em>Leige</em> hath taken some Prisoners of good quality.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From Upsal in Sweden</em>, March 3.</head>

<p>I have in former dispatches acquainted you, that our affairs here suffered some delay by reason of the Treaty between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>; The event of which being not yet known, causes those here to suspend giving in their answer to our Proposals: And I think it to be of so just and truly <reg orig="politique">politic</reg> an account, that they are much to be commended for it. It will enable them to shape a more full clear answer; and they will thereby take in what will be for the larger interest, and advantage of the two Nations. If there be a Peace concluded betwixt the two States of <em>England </em>and <em>Holland</em>, the designs and interests will run in another kind of Channel then if there was a continuation of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> between them. You may easily perceive a vast difference. Can any then imagine, that wise men will huddle up a business of consequence, establishing it upon an uncertain <em>basis</em>? The foundation of our Union with <em>Sweden</em> must be diversified according to our having Peace or <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> with the Dutch. The State of <em>England</em> hath received as great an addition of advantage and honour by this <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> entrusted in the hands of so wise and <reg orig="accomplisht">accomplished</reg> a person to manage it, as ever any State hath, or can receive in such an affair. His parts and prudence has at once gained the respect and admiration of all that he hath conversed with: And I am <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> has more friends in <em>Sweden</em> by the true and faithful account his Excellency has given of our English Matters, then they could have had here by any other means whatever. It is not unknown to you by the piercing <reg orig="rayes">rays</reg> of truth<pb n="10" /> <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg> in a lovely garment, the affections cannot but follow with all delight and <reg orig="endearedness">endearment</reg>. My Lord Ambassador has done this right for his Country, that he has given candid information of things, begot heartiness in the most eminent towards it; and they now begin to say that they are convinced that wise men are in the management of the affairs of the State of <em>England</em>. I hope we shall not long want a dispatch when the certainty is here known of the Treaty with the Dutch; and I believe we should by this time have accomplished our business, had not there been an intervention of so great and considerable an affair. The Queen is returned from <unclear><em>Westrads</em></unclear>, and has discoursed with the <em>Prince Royal</em>, her successor, about her desires of resigning up the Government. And <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said all things are agreed on between them, but it cannot have its full determination till the Parliament fit, which will be on the second of <em>May </em>next; and how they will cast it, is as yet uncertain. <em>Piementelli</em> the Spanish Resident, is commanded to return home; who intends to take his journey within this fortnight, or thereabouts.</p>

<head level="3">From aboard the <em>James</em> in <em>Stoakes-Bay</em>, April 6.</head>

<p>We have, with other things, received the news of an Agreement signed between our Commissioners and the Dutch Ambassadors, which is welcome.</p>

<p>We have no news, save that here are Orders come for the Examination of Ministers, and for a Fast, which will be very strictly kept <reg orig="too morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From <reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg></em>, March 28.</head>

<p>I have little to write save only to let you know, that all our Enemies, <em>Glencarn, Glengarie, Kenmore, Atholl, Forbes, </em> are North of <em>Innerness</em> within 12 miles, and <em>Middleton</em> with <em>Seaforth</em> is expected with Levies out of <em>Cathness</em> and <em>Southerland</em> this week, I have receives earnest letters from Col. <em>Fitch</em> for more Forces, so that this day I am marching with a considerable strength of Horse and Foot towards them, but I fear <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> retreat into <em>Cathness</em> and <em>Southerland</em>, where there is so many <unclear>Ferries</unclear> that it will be impossible for us to reach them: they give out that we shall have no peace with the Dutch, and that within a fortnight <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> be 6000: and truly I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> if we do not hinder their intentions by this March, <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> be 3 or 4000, and then let us have a care of our selves, for they threaten this Town much, though indeed we should be glad if they would come to us and save us the labour of long Marches: The two Men of War which transported the <unclear>foot</unclear> to <em>Orkney</em>, took and Dutch prize laden with French and Spanish wine and other commodities, the <unclear>Prize..., but we know not where... are that took it.</unclear></p>

<head level="3"><em>Paris</em>, April 15. 1656.</head>

<p>The news of the Reception made unto his Majesties, Ambassadors and Mr. <em>De Bas </em> at <em>London</em>, have wholly satisfied this Court, and have <pb n="11" />so much the more enjoyed it, that one was in some apprehension of a landing the English Fleet had made in Port <em>Lovis</em> in <reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg>, whereof the rumour <reg orig="runned">ran</reg> through <em>Paris</em>: one hath since given to understand, unto the little Queen and her Children, that <em>England</em> having resolved to send a reciprocal <reg orig="Embasie">Embassy</reg> into <em>France</em>; the King desired that for the good of his affairs, they had to retire out of his Estates, and that their Pension should be sent them where they would.</p>

<p>They thereupon prepare themselves: the little Queen <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to go and dwell at <em>Angers: Charles Stuart</em> and his Brothers are bound with Prince <em>Rupert</em> for <em>Chantilly</em>, there to take their <reg orig="mezures">measures</reg> either for <em>Germany</em> or for <em>Scotland</em>, and the Prince <em>Edward Palatin </em>for <em>Bourbon</em>, under a pretext to take the waters, great conferences on Saturday last have been made in the <em>Louvre</em> concerning their affairs.</p>

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, most part of the Deputies from the reformed Churches, having met to consider of a Decree, whereby this Court thinks to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> them in the Marquis of <em>Lerans</em> business, purporting that the general <reg orig="Atturney">Attorney</reg>, and the reporter of that process, in the Parliament of <em>Toloze</em>, should be summoned to appear two Months after the signification of the same, before his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Council, to have the second process reviewed &amp; justice done, &amp;c. They <reg orig="finde">find</reg> it to be a right put off, which had but little relation to their <reg orig="demnds">demands</reg>; which so particularly tend <i>to have the King revoke the Commission of the 12 members of that Parliament, which have voice in the Chamber of the <pb n="12" />Edict of Castres</i>; that others may in their places be established, which may not depend of any jurisdiction: That the said Chamber be unmoveable, and that such express prohibition be made unto the said Parliament, that it may no more infringe his Majesties Edicts; and therefore it was resolved the said Decree should be receives after that the Baron <em>de Ruvigny</em> (in whole name it hath been given) has <reg orig="disadvowed">disavowed</reg> it.</p>

<p>The Count of <em>Harcourt</em> is still in <em>Brisac</em>, expecting the effect of the promises made him.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From Major Bridge to the Commander in Chief, dated at Hamilton, April 3.</em></head>

<p>According to your <reg orig="Honours">Honour's</reg> command I drew out an hundred men, out of my Col. Regiment, and we met at Hambleton on Tuesday last, from whence I sent 40 to <em>Duglass</em> and <em>Zancker</em>; appointing them to meet me within 2 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at a place appointed; and with the rest of the party I marched to <em>Newmills</em>, where I lay one night; making it my business to get what intelligence I could of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> motion. The next morning by break of day, a Lieute. And nine Mossers came to the <reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg> end, upon whom our sentinel fired, and they presently betook themselves to the Mosses; and notwithstanding they were closely pursued by the guard, they could get but two prisoners, and six horses, which were not so serviceable, being but that night taken from some Country people, which I caused to be restored <reg orig="againe">again</reg>, upon some small consideration to the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that took them. The same day Lieut. <em>Evans</em> marching with his party from me to <pb n="12" /><em>Duglass,</em> through the <reg orig="mores">moors</reg>, took 8 Mossers more, notable Villains &amp; sturdy. I sent to the Governor of <em>Air</em> to desire him to acquaint me with the condition of Lieut. <em>Hickman</em>, who marched out with 70 <unclear>horse</unclear> from <em>Glasgow</em>, by reason it was reported he forced the Enemy in <em>Carick</em>, who was said to be double his number, but his Return to me was, that he was considerable enough, and that he had met and fought some of the Enemy, touted and pursued them to <em>Chapell</em>; &amp; so did <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> that my party might be most <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> about <em>Zanker</em> and those Passes, to that purpose I divided, and sent Lieut: <em>Evans</em> with fifty horse that way.</p>

<p>But 2 miles from <em>Comlock</em> I <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> to hear the Enemy by a Country man, who reported them to be about 12. I sent a party to the place where they were, but they had the Alarm, and rid for it; their party still increased <reg orig="til">till</reg> they came to the number of 60, which were <reg orig="stil">still</reg> pursued by a <reg orig="Corporall">Corporal</reg> and ten men; at last they faced about, <reg orig="feeing">fleeing</reg> no more, and our party made a halt, but so soon as ever they discovered my party coming, they presently began to flinch, and turn Tails, I sent the Corporal therefore presently to charge their Rear, but they soon fled, and betook themselves to the Mosses, whither we pursued them, at least Ten miles, in the most doleful place that ever I beheld; He followed them so long as our horses could step forward, and <reg orig="till">until</reg> they had not above 12, or 14 together in a body, the rest dispersed, many leaving their horses; which we picked up to the number of 25. but could that day take no more prisoners but 8, and 2, or 3 slain in the pursuit. This party was commanded by Major <em>Hamilton</em>, Capt; <em>Legau</em>, and <em>Campbell</em>, the last of which was not there- here was besides, <em>Cragdorough</em>, with 50 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> that came up from about <em>Dumfreize</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with these, and was quartered within a mile or two, where I fell upon these Youth; but by reason of our interposing could not come to them, but marched off <reg orig="intirely">entirely</reg> in a body to the left of us; I <reg orig="endevored">endeavoured</reg> to get what Intelligence I could of their motion that night. The next morning I understood where they were; and what they intended which was to go by the way of <em>Douglas</em>, and so unto the North over <em>Cluyd</em>. I presently mounted and marched another way, as fast as I could, thinking to have been before them, but it so <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> that they were gotten past <em>Douglas</em> a full hour before me; I found out their Tract and pursued after them as fast as I could, sending 16 of our best horse, if it were possible to engage them; but all was to little purpose we pursued them until we came within 4 miles of <em>Hamilton</em> long within night, but then lost them. I came to <em>Hamilton</em> this morning about one <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>, and presently sent out all the <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> that were here, to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> upon the Passes of <em>Cluyd</em>, and to range the<pb n="13" />Country between <em>Evandale</em> &amp; <em>Senerick</em>, where about I judge they will attempt to get over <em>Cluyd</em>. I have also dispatched an express to Col. <em>Cooper</em> desiring him to send to <em>Kilysthe</em>, and they to send to <em>Sterling</em>, to draw forth their horse on the Passes, That so it we miss of them here, they may perhaps light on them; they cannot but be much <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg>. I have also sent to <em>Aire</em> to Cap: <em>Robson</em>, to desire him to advise Lieut. <em>Hickman </em>with his party, which I understand is <reg orig="com">come</reg> out of <em>Carick</em>, to lie about the Country near the Passes over <em>Dumbarton</em>-shire, where those dispersed people of <em><reg orig="Hamiltons">Hamilton's</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Leglans">Leglan's</reg></em> will certainly privately <reg orig="endevor">endeavour</reg> to get over. The eight prisoners first taken, I sent to <em>Aire</em>, the rest I shall send this day to <em>Glasgow</em>: One is said to be a Capt. Another a Lieutenant, and one a notorious murdering Moss Trooper, known to be so by the Country about from his Childhood. Truly Sir, I must now of necessity take some rest, both men and horses, but also those we took from the Enemy. I shall not further trouble your <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg>.</p>

<p><i>The Committee for claims for Land in Ireland, having determined to give Certificate to each adventurer, are resolved to seal the same on Thursday each week, and intend to meet at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> hall, London, on each Tuesday and Saturday, to dispatch claims and other <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> not yet presented, and all persons concerned therein, are desired to take notice thereof.</i></p>
<p><em>William Tibbes Clerk.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Upsall">Upsal</reg> in Sweden, March 10.</i></head>

<p>This Post brought no Letters to us from England; so that we are still in the dark, as to the success of the Treaty between England and the United Provinces. We are very greedy in our expectations to understand the full of it; for we do confidently believe, That then we shall receive a very speedy and satisfactory answer. My Lord Ambassador is not idle; He takes all advantages to promote his negotiation: And, indeed, the Queen has so great an affection for England, and in particular to his Highness my <em>Lord Protector</em> that she is very inclinable to make up this <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg>. The wheels are in motion, the Affair does make its progress; Those things which are of a single relation, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not depend either upon a War or Peace with the Dutch, have received a candid acceptation. But as to <reg orig="others">other</reg> things, you must be content to let them pause awhile, till the great business between us and Holland have one way or other received a period. The Queen is fixed in her Resolves of quitting the Government, yes she will dispatch us first: And it will be a very fair and specious conclusion of her Reign, that she has gained to Sweden so considerable <reg orig="a">an</reg> Allie as the State of England.</p><pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><em>From Dalkeith</em>, April 4:</head>

<p>The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> will inform you what kind of task the Horse are put upon in these parts, to suppress the Rebels and Mossers, who daily gather and are as often scattered. Besides what was done by Major <em>Bridge</em>, a party of Twenty of Major-<reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, commanded by Corner Kenner, coming from Dumfrieze, with some Sesse which they had collected, were set upon by 40 of the Enemy, received their charge, and then charged by the Rebels, routed them, and had <reg orig="onley">only</reg> 4 of his party wounded. Lieutenant Hickman with another party <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> upon 60 of the Enemy under the command of one Captain Campbel, took 6. above 20 horse: Capt-Campbel was shot in the back, his horse taken but he himself escaped amongst the <reg orig="Whinns">Whins</reg> and bogs. <em>Glencarnes</em> and <em>Glencary</em>, &amp;c are gone over Taine into Sutherland to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, and then they will be <reg orig="neer">near</reg> 4000. yet I doubt not but Col. <em>Morgan</em> will endeavour to engage them with his party. <em>Montross</em>, and the Lord Dudhoppe are raising men in the Brays of Angus, and report already speaks them 300 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg>. Thus do they daily strive to make themselves and the Country miserable, having yet appeared the most cowardly enemy that ever we dealt with, but enough of this.</p>

<head level="3"><em>From Dalkeith</em>, April 6.</head>

<p>Upon Monday night last the Enemy had a party returning from the South towards Aberfoy pass, to which joined another <reg orig="partie">party</reg> of the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg>, of about 60 Horse and 60 Foot, commanded by Col. Mac-Naughton; at which time Cornet Keys with about 20 Horse from Dunbarron, and Lieut. Francis Young of Capt. <reg orig="Callants">Callant's</reg> Company of Coll. <reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg> Regiment, with 18 Horse and 30 Foot from Bohannan made after them; the Enemy got the pass first, nevertheless they were totally routed by ours who killed one Capt. And 12 private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, took Lieut. Coll. George Herriot, William Bohannan Capt. Robert Campbel Cornet, Hugh Wells Quartermaster, above 40 private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and above 20 Horse, Mac-Naughton fled with 16 Horse, all of them being killed and taken save himself and 3 others. We had only one killed, one wounded, and two horses killed.</p>

<p>Sir, This is all the Intelligence that affords <reg orig="its self">itself</reg> at present having had nothing from our parties that are abroad in these parts since the last.</p>

<p><em>Whitehall</em> April 12. <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monck</em> went two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since toward Scotland. The Return of the Instrument of Peace, with the Ratification under the Hands of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, is expected by the first opportunity out of Holland, and then it is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> signed by the Lord Protector; after which a Day will be appointed for proclaiming it here and in the United Provinces. The effect whereof you may expect ere many days be over. No news further from Sea.</p>

<p>Monsieur <em>Rosenwing</em> the Danish Agent is arrived in this City.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</head>
<head level="3"><em>London</em> Printed by <em>Tho. Newcomb</em>, 1653.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>