<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc169">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, issue 169</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The titular King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg>, and the Duke of <reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg> Letters to the Highlanders in Scotland; with several Engagements there between party and party, and what success the English have had in many Fights. The last News of the Treaty of Peace between the English and the Dutch, and their Agreement upon the Articles. The taking of several ships at Sea. The selling of above Thirty Prizes. The last news out of Sweden, touching the proceedings of that renowned Queen. And three new Ordinances of His Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em>, March 29. to <em>Wednesday</em>, April 5. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>March 29.</em></i></head>

<p>From Sea we hear, that many foot <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> are put on shipboard lately from Portsmouth and other places, which maketh the inhabitants conceive, that there is little expectation of a peace with Holland (which hath been so much spoken of) but the Merchants and others of quality, and better understanding, are of a contrary opinion, and say, that a peace will be concluded of suddenly between the States of England and Holland, France, and Denmark; the truth whereof we earnestly desire to know.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>We have had a List of divers ships taken this week, which hath been published already, and therefore shall spare the recital thereof.</p>

<p>This day several persons were apprehended in London (at least) upon suspicion that they had a hand in the late Robbery on Blackheath near Greenwich.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday March 30.</head>

<p>Am Ordinance is passed for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, intituled, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>; which being of so general concernment, take as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas upon perusal and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament intituled, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners,</i> many doubts and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorized for sale of such Estates, as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such Explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges, authorized in and by the said Act, several inconveniences and mischiefs would grow, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the said Creditors and prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles and suits in Law, and Equity; For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: And whereas many of the said Prisoners have offered really to <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the satisfaction of the said Creditors, if some further time may be given for that purpose: Be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or<pb n="2" /> disposition of any the Estates <reg orig="reall">real</reg> or <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, of any of the said prisoners, or of any other person or persons, whatsoever mentioned or intended in or by the said Act; nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act; or any of the powers or authorities given by the same, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 20 day of April next. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Acts or things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, <reg orig="color">colour</reg>, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said 20 day of April, shall be utterly void, null, and of none effect; saving <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that it shall and may be <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> for the said several and respective Judges that have bailed or let out any Prisoners upon Sureties or otherwise, out of Prison (which Prisoners are to appear again at a certain day before the said Judges) and are not absolutely discharged by any Order of the said Judges, <i>as see further by the Act.</i></p>

<p>Paris April 1, 1654. All the discourse at present is concerning that which was acted in the Parliament on Saturday last, when all the Chambers being assembled, and every Member in their Scarlet Gowns, the King then came, and being sate in his bed of Justice, they proceeded in the business of the Prince of Conde, his Sentence being read, which containeth, That for being found guilty of high Treason and Rebellion, against the King his Lord and Liege, he was to be put to death, and that so soon as he should be apprehended, his Sentence to be executed, his lands and goods all forfeited to the Crown; in regard of his quality he is not to be executed in <reg orig="Effigie">Effigy</reg>, and as touching the manner and how to put him to death the Parliament would not determine but left it to the <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure</p><pb n="3" />

<p>The Prince of Conti was not then in Town, but had taken an occasion to go to <reg orig="Chantilli">Chantilly</reg>, as some <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg>, because he would not be present at the condemnation of his Brother, which he could not have excused if he had been in the City. The Treaty of the Earl of Harcourt goeth on apace, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought will be finished within ten days. The Cardinal Mazarini is not a little troubled because he cannot finish the marriage of his two <reg orig="Neeces">Nieces</reg>; for when it was thought quite done, it was found further off, and very little hopes of the Treaty with the Cardinal de Retz, who doth still remain a close prisoner in the Castle of Vicennes. The Governor of Rochel hath charged the Reformed Churches with some designs prejudicial to his Majesty; which they formerly deny.</p>

<head level="3">Friday, March 31.</head>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, March 25. The Commander in Chief having issued forth a Proclamation, requiring all Burroughs and other Parishes to secure all <reg orig="suspitious">suspicious</reg> persons, or otherwise to give intelligence of them to the next adjacent <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> or Quarters, under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present Government, and proceeded against accordingly: Several Towns have been found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a Court <reg orig="Martial">Marshal</reg> for the same. The last week the Parish of Liberton, two miles from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, for harbouring 15 of the enemy by the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving intelligence of them, and the Tories at their going away stealing 15 horses, the Parish was for that <unclear>offence</unclear> fined 200 l. <em>sterling</em> the person in whose house they were concealed sentenced to imprisonment during pleasure, and the house where they were harboured to be <reg orig="raced">razed</reg> to the ground, and a pair of Gallows to be built there. There are divers other Parishes who are summoned in to the Court <reg orig="Marshals">Martials</reg> upon the very same account, who will suffer for it. It is hoped this course will in time compel the Scots not to give any entertainment unto the Tories, but give notice of them <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> they shall come; otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>

<p>The 21 instant Col. Cooper with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of Leven, where about 300 of the Enemy quartered (about 4 in the morning) took <reg orig="Mac Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg> Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, and narrowly missed <reg orig="Mac Naughton">McNaughton</reg> and Newark, who were both there. They killed 12, whereof one of the, (as the enemy <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg>) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 Horse, and some Arms, totally scattered the whole party, and returned without any <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>This week Capt. Orton, Commander of the Sun, and Capt. Lilburn of the Union, came into <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> road, from Lewis and Orkney, and brought 3 Companies of Col. <reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg> Regiment, and therewith a particular relation of the late infall of the Lord Seafort into Lewis Island, much to the same purpose formerly related.</p>

<p>Dublin, March 18. Since the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg> departure for England we have nothing further of news, but that about 1200 Tories are shipped away from Limbrick, and 1700 more are ready for transportation; which renders the whole Nation more free, <reg orig="then">than</reg> in times of the greatest peace this Land hath enjoyed.</p>

<p>Plymouth Fort, March 24. The news this place affords is, The Commander of the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a Dutch prize, which hath no lading, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some few barrels of pitch, &amp;c. This week the Paul, a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met with a Flushen man of War in the Channel of 15 Guns, who after 5 <reg orig="hours">hours'</reg> fight took her, and this day brought her in hither; we lost not any man in the fight, but sustained some damage in Masts, Sails, and Rigging; the Enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and the ship much torn, she hath some silver in her, and some small quantity of Wines.</p>

<p>Great have been the expectations and hopes of a Peace and Union between the two Commonwealths of England and Holland upon this last Treaty, which we have several weeks mentioned, and we can now safely assure you, that the Articles of Peace both in relation to them and Denmark are absolutely concluded on, and for a full confirmation (undoubtedly) will be signed and sealed by Commissioners on both sides, before the publication of our next.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, April 1.</head>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg> in Germany, it is certified, that the Emperor is wearied with the long sitting of the Diet, and presseth earnestly, that they should adjourn or dissolve themselves; but as yet they continue to their sitting. The Turks begin to be something <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the borders of Hungaria, so that his presence is there required to provide against their invasions.</p>

<p>We understand from Poland, that the Inhabitants are possessed with great fear, hearing of the mighty preparations that are made in Muscovia, where they have levied above two hundred and fifty thousand men, wherewith they threaten to enter and destroy that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> three <reg orig="severall">several</reg> ways at once. <reg orig="Mean while">Meanwhile</reg> the Turk and Tartar laugh, hoping to thrive by the <reg orig="ruines">ruins</reg> of them both.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>From Upsal the 27 of Febr. 1654. S.N. All the actions of our great Queen are as so many wonders, and continual effects of her royal virtues, and of the <reg orig="greatnesse">greatness</reg> of her incomparable courage, but some few days in special she did give such proof thereof, that the same may be called the Crown of all her other actions, seeing it doth manifest to world how this admirable <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> hath set <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> above the Crowns, under which men commonly do seek their satisfaction and glory. The 23 of this instant she having summoned all the Senators of the Land, they all made their appearance except 9. who were out of the Land upon <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>; there this Princess did declare unto them the design she had to leave the charge of the Kingdom, and to that end that she was resolved to go to Nicoping to confer with the Prince Palatine of Sweden her Cousin, having sent him Letters to invite him thither, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to accept the charge of the Kingdom, and the managing of the State affairs; this Prince is the same who was heretofore <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> of the Swedish Armies in Germany, concluded first a peace with the Duke Picolomini, and in the year 1650, at the Coronation of the Queen, was then declared heir apparent to the Crown of Sweden, and by the States and Commonalty acknowledged so, having made their Oath of Allegiance to him, as unto their future King, after the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> death.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 3.</head>

<p>It is advertised, that the titular King of Scotland is yet in France, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty will produce betwixt England and France. He had a Present given him a little before Easter by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom.</p>

<p>In the Holy days his Mother came to see him in the<pb n="6" /> <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal, and the King her Nephew in the Louvre and on the next day returned to her devotions in the Nunnery. There is a report of two English ships brought into Tholoon, which it is said, were taken by the French not far from Messina.</p>

<p>The Letters from Scotland speak of the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> Army joined all into one body, which no doubt will be dispersed again into several parties for the Countries where they are, are so wasted, that they cannot maintain them, and it is probable they will not draw together with an intent to give <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the middle of May, before which time the Peace with Holland, and Denmark will so startle them, that they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> have but little Resolution to fight.</p>

<p>The Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath taken a Dutch Man of war of fourteen Guns, and sent her into Burlington Bay; This was one of the four Capers that did much annoy us on the Northern Seas. The Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> lay cruising three or four days before he handsomely could snap her.</p>

<p>Take this in brief from <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> parts. They write from Leghorn that they heard by a ship which came from Barbary, that the Turkish Agent being come to Tunis, hath pressed or taken up all the <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> or ships fit for service, and intends to do the same at Algier and Tripoli; in her voyage thither; she met with two Turkish <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg>, who being come up to him on both sides, supposing themselves not able to grapple with her, they tacked about and left her. There is likewise a flying report, that the French <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> have met with two English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships homeward bound, and after a tedious fight had taken them; but by reason those that brought the news vary very much, therefore little credit is to be given, <reg orig="til">till</reg> further confirmation.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, April 4.</head>

<p>The Letters further this Post from Scotland <reg orig="advertize">advertise</reg> us, that parties which have been sent out by <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan have dispersed two other parties, which were sent out by the enemy to plunder and steal away <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> out of the Lowlands. But their main body doth not yet appear, for that they are not in an equipage to take the field; therefore they wait and earnestly expect the further supplies that were promised from beyond Sea, by the late Letters they had from the titular King of Scots, and the Duke of York.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> taking into consideration the great abuses which have been practised in the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Cockpits by reason of Matches of <reg orig="Cock-fighting">Cockfighting</reg>: An Ordinance is issued forth, <reg orig="straightly">straitly</reg> forbidding all such set meetings at <reg orig="Cock-fightings">Cockfightings</reg>; and all Justices of Peace, and other Officers are required to take notice hereof, and to punish all such persons as shall be found to offend contrary to the said Ordinance.</p>

<p>There is another Ordinance for continuing the Act of the late Parliament, touching the Probate of Wills, and granting Letters of Administration.</p>

<p>Also a third Ordinance for settling the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Farmlingham and Sexstead in the County of Suffolk, (given by Will by Sir Robert Hitcham late Sergeant at Law) to charitable uses.</p>

<p>On Thursday next there is to be sold at the Sale Office in <reg orig="Beer-lane">Beer Lane</reg>, above thirty several parcels of good commodities, as Wines, Sugars, Silks, Stuffs, and other Merchandize, which were taken prizes.</p>

<p>From Plymouth they write, That a private man of War hath brought into that port a prize laden with Tobacco, and divers other commodities. The Brest men of War are often seen about the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end and near the Isle of Scilly; we hear that they took the last week an English Vessel belonging to Bristol, but what her lading was we cannot yet learn.</p>

<p>Our Fleet yet floats upon the Narrow Seas; they have lately sent in some prizes to Portsmouth, and others are come about into the River of Thames.</p>

<p>The Dutch Fleet is not yet put out to Sea, they need not make any great <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, if their Ambassadors would but make <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to sign the Articles of Peace, which they have been so long about: but weighty Affairs commonly move slowly; and the Proverb is, <i>That which is once well done, is twice done.</i></p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>