<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn231">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 231</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, May. 8. to <em>Monday</em>, May. 15. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> May. 8.</head>

<p>This from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> May 3. General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> hath had meetings with a Council of Officers, and we are in preparations against the forces from <em>England</em> come, to be ready to march into the field after Col. <em>Morgan</em>, who hath so frighted the Enemy in the Hills, that they durst not venture to come out, but have found a way through the Hills to get provisions, which we wonder how they come by. <em>Middleton</em> hath, we hear, sent a Messenger to the Islands, to double their Guards. Some Scotch Towns have made stay of a few passengers, but not considerable: We have taken a few Country people that were going towards the Hills. There hath been great <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in the North of <em>Scotland</em>: but there hath been lately no considerable action</p><pb n="1" />

<p>By Letters from the <em>Hague</em> in <em>Holland</em> we understand, that on the (7 May, that is) 27 <em>April</em> English account, the States General received an express from the Ambassadors in England, with the Ratification of Peace subscribed <em>OLIVER</em> P. sealed with the Great Seal of <em>England</em> in a silver and gilt box. The 28 <em>April</em> it was appointed to be proclaimed, and the Lord States concluded a Thanksgiving day to be kept with great expressions of joy.</p>

<p><i>Here followeth the residue of that part of the Vindication of the Proceedings in the Law, promised in the last.</i></p>

<p>And that if such Confession, Answer, or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> be, or shall be so left, the same shall be so left upon Oath, or Oaths taken, or to be taken before some Justice of Peace within the County, place, or Jurisdiction, where such Copy, Confession, Answer or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> be, or shall be left, or otherwise such Answer or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> to be void and null. And such Action to be brought or commenced, and prosecuted, notwithstanding the same; and that such Justice be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and compelled to administer, and take such Oaths.</p>

<p>And that if any such person or persons, to, or for whom such Copy be, or shall be so delivered, or left, do, or shall as before is mentioned, leave such Confession, Answer, or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> then may such party or parties, so delivering, or leaving such Copy, commence, or begin and prosecute such his, her, or their Action within so long time as is or shall be from the time of the leaving of such Confession, Answer, or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg>, as for every several and respective Action or Suit is mentioned in the said Statute to be commenced or begun after the arising, <reg orig="accrewing">accruing</reg>, or happening of the Cause or Causes of every of such respective Action or Suit, and upon, and under the same <reg orig="provisoes">provisos</reg> and conditions, as in the same Statute be mentioned and expressed.</p>

<p>And that if any Action, or <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> have been, be, or shall be hereafter brought, or prosecuted in the Court of Chancery, or elsewhere, by Bill of Discovery, or otherwise upon such Cause arisen, <reg orig="accrewed">accrued</reg> or happened, or hereafter to arise, <reg orig="accrew">accrue</reg>, or happen; then such Cause or Suit may be again brought and prosecuted in any other Court, which be, or shall be most proper for the Determination of the same, after such Bill, or<pb n="2" /> Matter, be or shall be dismissed out of, or from the Court, where the same be, or shall be so first Commenced or brought.</p>

<head level="3"><i><em>Part 3</em>. For Costs in Demurrers, and Issues to be upon, and by the Records.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as many Sheriffs, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other contentious persons have brought and prosecuted diverse Actions against honest people upon Bonds made to such Sheriffs and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and otherwise, when nothing hath been due, upon which (after much trouble and charge occasioned by such Prosecutors) Issues have been <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> upon Demurrer, or Matter in Law by the Court to be heard; and upon no Record, or to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> whether or not there hath been such a Record; Many of which, after chargeable and tedious Arguments and Motions have passed, <reg orig="gon">gone</reg>, and been considered of, and adjudged for the Defendants in such Actions, and yet no Costs allowed to them therein, nor by Law could or can be.</p>

<p><i>For Remedy whereof, it is proposed to be desired that it may Be Enacted</i>, That the Defendant or Defendants in such Actions shall and may be allowed, have and recover his, her, or their Costs and <reg orig="Expences">Expenses</reg> in such Actions, after Judgment pronounced and given upon such proceedings beforementioned, as after Verdicts, Defaults, or Non-suits.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 9.</i></head>

<p>Paris the 13 of May 1654. We hear from <em>Rousillon</em>, that notwithstanding all the endeavours of <em>Dom John D' Austria</em> to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg> the differences between the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> and the Country people, yet their hatred is so great to the Spaniards, that whensover they meet with any at advantage, they give them no quarter, chiefly they are much incensed, since they are sorely <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> of some Forces which are to come from <em>Biscay</em>, The so much renowned <em>Balzac</em> is deceased at <em>Angoulesime</em>, and having given divers pious Legacies, made the Masters of the Hospital in that City his Executors; they write from <em>La Bassee</em>, that the <em>Lorrain</em> Forces are yet quartered about 3 miles from that place, expecting the Orders of the Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em> for their further advancing, yet are they so <reg orig="straightned">straightened</reg> by the great care<pb n="3" /> of the Earl of <em>Broglio</em> their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, that he will not suffer those <em>Lorrainers</em> to have any horse meat on his side, but forceth them to get it upon their friends side.</p>

<p>From St. <em>Menehold</em>, some few days since a party of ours being gone over the <em>Mause</em> to get some contributions into the County of <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, did bring back with them a great quantity of Cattle belonging to those that refused to pay, and since the Earl of <em>Grandpre</em>, that there was a Convoy of about 6 hundred-men which was come to <em>Stenay</em> did send to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> that he might send him as many horse as he could well spare from his Garrison, but before they could get to him, the Convoy and Provisions was got safe into <em>Stenay</em>. This day the Court is to remove from <em><reg orig="Fontainbleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em>, to return to this City, the King having spent there some days in the exercise of hunting the wild Boar in that <reg orig="Forrest">Forest</reg>, and are expected here this Evening. There came hither the day before some Commissioners from the City of <em>Rheims</em>, to assure his Majesty that they forgot none of that care which they ought to have for the manifesting their zeal and fidelity for their <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, the same being for his due reception into the City, that so the Ceremony of his Anointing, and Coronation may be performed with more solemnity. We hear from <em>Dole</em> in <em><reg orig="Bargundie">Burgundy</reg></em>, That their Assembly of States began there the 24 of the last <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, the Baron <em>de Stey</em> being appointed chief Commissioner by his <reg orig="Catholique">Catholic</reg> <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, and the first President his Assistant, and being met in the great Hall of the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> of St. <em>Jerome</em>, and taken their feats according to their <reg orig="destinct">distinct</reg> qualities, there were presented to the Dean of <em>Besancon</em> the Moderator of the Assembly his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Letters, which being open were immediately read, there were several speeches made as well on the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> behalf upon his several Propositions, as also in answer to them. The Town of <em>Rosa</em> hath been again relieved with provisions, but in so small quantity that it will require a further supply in a short time: We hear from <em>Provence</em> that the ships intended to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Sea are near ready, that design being carried on with more vigour since there was some Monies sent thither for that purpose, and it is thought they will be ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Sea, for the beginning of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>From several parts this. From <em>Prague</em>: The Assembly of the States of <em>Bohemia</em> being met, the Commissioners for the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> made several Propositions, whereof these are the chief, That they will maintain to their utmost the <reg orig="Catholique">Catholic</reg> Religion, That they shall pay to his Imperial Majesty a considerable <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of moneys towards the payment of his <reg orig="houshold">household</reg> Officers, of his <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, and Residents, and also of the frontier places of <em>Hungaria</em>. That they shall continually provide for the payment of such forces as are now or shall be hereafter quartered in the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>, and to provide money for the payment of such forces as shall be thought fit to be disbanded, That they shall not suffer any salt to come into the Country without paying the ordinary duty, That they shall prevent the importation of bad Wool from <em><reg orig="Turkie">Turkey</reg></em>, and shall use all means possible that the River of <em>Elbe</em> may be cleansed from shelves, and other <unclear>lects</unclear> which hinder the trade thereon, and lastly shall <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> all, which being agreed in former Assemblies is yet unaccomplished. From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>: The Prince <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> is come hither, but with a small <unclear><reg orig="attendace">attendance</reg></unclear>, and the next day after his arrival had audience of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, who hath put off his departure from hence until the middle of <em>May</em>, that so he may be present at the conclusion of the Diet, and so expected to answer of the States of the Empire, concerning a great <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of money which he doth demand of them, to make good those costs and charges that he hath been at during his abode there. From <em>Lubeck</em>: The Earl <em>Benedictus Oxenstorm</em> hath passed by this place, and is gone to <em>Studen</em> to meet General <unclear><em>Koninnsroark</em></unclear>, and its said that he brings him express order from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, that with all speed he may block up <em>Bremen</em>, after he hath taken in all the small Towns and Villages about it, thereupon this General doth compel all the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> in that County to take up <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, and so intends to <reg orig="besiedge">besiege</reg> <em>Bozerkesse</em>, where there is a Bremish Garrison, that City likewise doth give out Commissions for raising of men, intending to defend themselves to the uttermost, in hopes that they will be protected by their neighbouring Princes, and States, and chiefly by the Hollanders, which is very <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg>, by reason that it will be feared by assisting them to draw upon themselves<pb n="5" /> those great Sea and Land forces which are ready in <em>Sweden</em> to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon any occasion.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness the Lord PROTECTOR of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg>, Burgesses, and Commonalty of the Town &amp; County of Pool, wish <reg orig="along">a long</reg> and happy Government on Earth, and eternal felicity above, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>The series of mercies (or rather miracles) the which the Father of Mercies hath of late years encompassed his people in these Nations, as is eminently commenced, and continued in raising up your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> spirit suitable to so great things as he hath brought to pass by your hand; namely, the <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> of his people both in spiritual concernment, and temporal enjoyment, so we trust will still continue towards you and us, until our deliverance be <reg orig="compleated">completed</reg>, and your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> actions crowned with perpetual praise: And seeing by Divine Providence your Highness hath been in so large a measure the happy repairer of our breaches, defender of truth, and procurer of Peace in these Nations; as we desire to bless the name of the most High as the efficient cause, so also to manifest our duty and <reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> to your Highness, as the instrumental means of so great enjoyments, <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> in the Lord, who hath given us a Governor that seeks the good of <em>Sion</em>, under whose protection, as we have much confidence of living happily, so we also engage to live Loyally, dedicating our hearts and hands, lives and fortune to your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Service, for accomplishment of the good work so far by you promoted in opposition to all the Enemies of the truth, piety, and peace, which being the full purpose of our hearts, we hold it our duty to declare, the more to confirm your hand in the work of the Lord and his people, humbly subscribing <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> <i>Your Highness very faithful Servants.</i></p>

<p>Presented by Major <em>Skutt</em> and some other Gentlemen of the Town of <em>Pool</em>, and his Highness returned hearty thanks both to the Gentleman that delivered it, and also to the Town.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>, April 25. The only news here is, that my L. Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> hath finished his affair at <em>Vpsal</em>, and we expect his Lordship in this City within a few days. There is a firm Alliance and Friendship made, which as much as either side could expect or desire, as things stand.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>An Ordinance was published for further Doubling upon and finishing the Sale of Deans, <reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg> and <reg orig="Chapters">Chapter's</reg> Lands, and of <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories, <reg orig="Gleab">Glebe</reg>-lands, &amp;c. whereby it is Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, That over and above the sum of three hundred thousand pounds, appointed to be borrowed upon the Security held forth by the first recited act of Parl. for the sale of <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories and <reg orig="Gleab">Glebe</reg>-lands, and over and above the sum of twenty thousand pounds more, borrowed upon the Security of such of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg> respectively, exposed to sale by the said Acts, or either of them, in such sort as is hereafter expressed, by way of doubling the like sum, as shall be due to any person or persons, Body-politick or Corporate, for any <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg>, Plate, Horse, Arms, or other thing advanced upon the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Faith, or which hath been at any time allowed by any Act or Ordinance of Parl. To be doubled, as <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> faith debts, after the rate of eight pounds in the hundred, by the year, until the stating of such debts and Interest, by the persons named and appointed in and by an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Additional Act for sale of several Lands and Estates forfeited to the Commonwealth for Treason</i>, to be Register <reg orig="Accomptant">Accountant</reg>, or any of them which the said persons, or any of them, are authorized to state accordingly. And after the stating of such debts and Interests, and doubling thereof, the respective Creditors to be allowed <reg orig="onely">only</reg> six pounds in the hundred by the year, for the whole of such doubled <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Faith Debts, until the payment thereof, or defalcation upon purchase, In relation to which doubling, intended by this Ordinance, the Trustees, Treasurers, Register and <reg orig="Accomptant">Accountant</reg>, and all other Officers concerned, are authorized to proceed according to the directions of the Act of Parliament in like case made and provided, save only as to what is hereby altered, restrictive to the debts, and to allowance of interest as aforesaid, and all and every person or persons, body politick and corporate, to whom any debts capable of doubling within this present Ordinance, shall be due, and his and their respective assigns, and all persons doubling such debts and their respective<pb n="7" /> assigns shall have all and the like liberties, <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, benefits and advantages respectively in reference to the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, as any such person or persons, bodies politick or corporate, their or any of their assigns might or ought to have had by the aforesaid recited acts or either of them, save only what is hereby altered with restriction to debts and interests as aforesaid and all and every person and persons who shall have their debts and interests stated as aforesaid, shall pay into the Treasurers named in the said Act for sale of the said <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories, or one of them, the money wherewith he or they ought to double within ten days next after certificate thereof, to the Treasurers, or otherwise shall lose his or their <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Faith debts <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> he or they <reg orig="shew">show</reg> good cause to the Treasurers or any one of them for his or their <reg orig="failer">failure</reg> therein.</p>

<p>And be it further Ordained and declared by the Authority aforesaid, That where any present Estate of, or in any the Lands or Possessions of the late <reg orig="Arch Bishops">Archbishops</reg>, Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Cannons, Prebends, and other the persons aforesaid, shall be doubtfully returned upon any Survey, either as to the certain being or legality of any Lease, or Copy of Court Roll, or any Life or Lives upon any Lease or Copy of Court Roll; the Tenants or Tenants claiming such Lease, Copy or Estate; shall (as the Lands already Surveyed) before the first day of <em>July</em> 1654; and as to the Lands unsurveyed, within 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> next after the respective Returns of the Surveys thereof to the respective Registers for sale of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, make proof of his or their Estate or Estates before the Commissioners for removing of Obstructions and procure their Order for allowance thereof, or otherwise shall be for ever barred and excluded from any benefit or advantage thereby. Provided <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> that the power given by the former Acts to the Surveyor General, as also the power given by Ordinance of Parliament to the Contractors for sale of <reg orig="Bishops">Bishop's</reg> Lands, for allowance of any estates made good by proof before them respectively, within forty days next of the return of the Survey of any of the premises, be not any way impeached. And provided also, that the Power given or transferred to the Commissioners for removing of Obstructions, by any Ordinance or Act of Parliament for allowance of Estates, be not any ways hereby enlarged.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 10.</i></head> 

<head level="3">By the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, setting apart Tuesday the 23 of this present May for a <reg orig="publique">public</reg> day of Thanksgiving, for the Peace concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces, and for the late seasonable Rain.</i></p>

<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the <reg orig="out-stretched">outstretched</reg> arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment, and wonder, Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter and they will <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, and <reg orig="indeeed">indeed</reg> the dispensations of the Lord have been as if he had said, <em>England</em> thou art my <reg orig="first-born">firstborn</reg>, my delight amongst the Nations, under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us.</p>

<p>The Lord having added another Link to this golden Chain of his loving <reg orig="kindnesse">kindness</reg> by giving us a Peace with our Neighbours the United Provinces, (whereby he hath not only stopped a great issue of blood, but we trust also given us hearts to unite our blood and strength for the mutual defence of each other) calls for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>

<p>It is therefore thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, and for the thankful acknowledgement of this blessing of Peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other blessings.</p>

<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up, that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg>, and did cause the Beast of the field to mourn for want of food, &amp; water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord imparted this mercy to us, did any amongst us, foreknow it was <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, was it not by stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that immediately before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy? And doth not this bespeak? 1. That the manner of convey this mercy is the best part of the mercy.</p><pb n="9" />

<p>2. That the Lord has not cast us off, that his Spirit yet strives with us, that he hath a people of his love amongst us, and loves the Nation so far as to provoke it to be in love with calling upon the Name of the Lord for better things than Corn &amp; Wine.</p>

<p>3. That he knows best how and when to answer the expectation of the Husbandman, and when to hear, even the mourning of the brute Beast, who will yet much more hear the desires of them that fear him, and that in the fittest season.</p>

<p>4. That the Heavens having thus declared the Glory of God, and the Earth answering thereunto in its fruitfulness, Why should we be melted and <reg orig="softned">softened</reg>, humbling <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> under these marvellous kindnesses, &amp; abounding unto all fruitfulness in every good word and work of love; And if every place hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> made partaker of his <reg orig="showres">showers</reg>, Why should not we (laying aside our differences) be <reg orig="inlarged">enlarged</reg> also each to other?</p>

<p>5. That seeing the Lord hath been thus universal in this Mercy, Why should we not universally turn from the National Evils and vain Practices which are yet too superstitiously and customarily exercised amongst us, which we need not repeat here, because they are too well known, and We trust will be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg> by those godly Ministers who shall be called to preach unto the People upon this occasion? Conclude we with the words of <em>David, Psalm 107. v.</em></p>

<p><i>30. Then they are glad, because they be quiet, so he bringeth them unto their desired Haven.</i></p>

<p><i>31. O that Men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> works to the Children of Men.</i></p>

<p><i>32. Let them exalt him also in the Congregation of the People, &amp; praise him in the Assembly of the Elders.</i></p>

<p><i>33. He turneth Rivers into a Wilderness, and the water-springs into dry ground.</i></p>

<p><i>34. A <reg orig="fruitfull">fruitful</reg> Land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell in it.</i></p>

<p><i>35. He turneth the Wilderness into a standing water, and the dry ground into Water-springs.</i></p>

<p><i>36. And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a City for Habitation.</i></p><pb n="10" />

<p><i>37. And sow the Fields, and plant Vineyards, which may yield fruits of increase.</i></p>

<p><i>38. He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly, and suffereth not their Cattle to decrease.</i></p>

<p><i>O that Men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the Children of Men.</i></p>

<p>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 9th of <em>May</em>, 1654.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Italie">Italy</reg></em> and parts adjacent. From <em>Venice</em>. The new <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> <em>Moccenigo</em> is now ready to take shipping for <em>Candia</em>, and with him are to go 12 of our Nobles, four thousand Foot <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, one hundred Horse, and divers <reg orig="Enginiers">Engineers</reg>, who are to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to make new Fortifications, and <reg orig="repaire">repair</reg> the old where it shall be thought <reg orig="needfull">needful</reg> in those places which we possess in <em>Candia</em>; from whence we hear that the Turks are now repairing the Fort called <em>Lazaretto</em>, thereby to hinder all relief from <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> into the City of <em>Candia</em>, whose <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> is likewise employed in repairing some Outworks which were decayed. Our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is not so great in <em>Dalmatia</em> as it was esteemed, by reason that many of our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> who were counted to be dead, or taken prisoners, were fled into the Mountains for shelter, and so come in daily to our Army. <reg orig="Neverthelesse">Nevertheless</reg>, upon the advice received from General <em>Delfino</em>, that the Enemy had appointed a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> to their forces, and that they have some <reg orig="designe">design</reg> upon <em>Spalatto</em>; therefore the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> <em>Vincentino</em> was commanded that way to observe the march. There is a ship lately built here of a new structure, or invention by one <em>Angelo Barberigo</em>, who promiseth that this ship with thirty Guns, and eight great Murderers will perform extraordinary Service, the Senate hath promised him a very great Gratuity in case it doth prove effectual, according to his engagement.</p>

<p>From <em>Milan</em>. The five hundred men landed at <em>Finall</em> to serve in this State, have been brought into the County of <em>Alexandria</em> to take their quarters, and so to remain there until they remove into the field; there are likewise daily expected some of the new Levies made by the <reg orig="Commandour">Commander</reg> <em>Precivallo</em>, as also those raised by the Earl <em>Barromeo</em>. Here is lately deceased<pb n="11" /> the <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> <em>Trivultio</em> of a burning <reg orig="feaver">fever</reg>, being 27 years old.</p>

<p>From Turin. Our chief work is now to make all things ready with all expedition for the next <em>Campagna</em>, and doubt not but that our Army will be ready to march into the field the middle of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, as soon as the Marq; <em>de Caracena</em>, who will scarce be ready so soon, one of the main <reg orig="hinderances">hindrances</reg> being, the want of new levies in <em>Germany</em> not yet come, neither he money expected from <em>Naples</em>, as also some <reg orig="brasse">brass</reg> pieces of Ordnance which were lately cast there. From <em>Rome</em>, The Pope is not yet recovered of his <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg>, <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> he hath been lately carried in a horse litter to see the new building of the <unclear>Church</unclear> of St. <em>Agnes</em>, founded by him, and endowed by great revenues, he was accompanied of 25 Cardinals, many Princes, <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> and other persons of great <reg orig="ranck">rank</reg>, and having dined at the Palace of the <em>Pamfilii</em> returned again to the Quirinal, and at the last consistory was made a decree that from henceforth there shall not be held any Congregations, in private houses but only at the <em>Vatican</em>. From <em>Naples</em>, There hath been lately mustered here twenty two Companies, and about 5 Troops of horses, being all of new Levies, but the Companies and Troops being all very thin, and wanting much of their full number, some small quantity of moneys being given to each <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> thereby to make him <reg orig="goe">go</reg> more <reg orig="chearfully">cheerfully</reg> in the service. One of the chief of the <reg orig="Bandity">Banditti</reg> whom they call King <em>Saul</em> having with 16 of his men met the Post going to <em>Bari</em> at the bridge of <em>Lavignano</em> had robbed him of all, and as he was about to strip him, there happened some <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of <em>Montesoscoli</em>, who having fought with him, not only made him leave all his prey, but also killed him, one Officer, and took one of his men prisoners, and chased the rest for many miles: They write us from <em>Ortranta</em> that there hath been lately in those parts two great Earthquakes, which hath caused much <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> among the Inhabitants.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 11.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris May 16</em>. All things are now preparing for the next campagna, His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> forces which are quartered in <em><reg orig="Picardie">Picardy</reg>, Champagne,</em> and <em><reg orig="Burgundie">Burgundy</reg></em> having received an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg><pb n="12" /> Order to be in <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> to march upon the first command to the <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> which shall be appointed them by the end of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, in the mean time the new levies, as well in this <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> as in other parts of the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> are so forward, that <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought that for many years past the Armies have not been in more gallant posture <reg orig="then">than</reg> they shall be this year, chiefly that which is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> towards <em>Flanders</em>, and to be commanded by the Marshal <em>de Turenne</em>. The Order being given that all the Nobility should attend the King at the time of his Coronation, therefore all the Officers belonging to the Crown, the Dukes and Peers of the Realm as well spiritual as temporal, with their Train will be ready to go to <em>Rheims</em> there to be present at the Ceremonies which are to be performed upon the 24 of this instant, the forces which were quartered at and near <em>Compeigne</em> have received a command to march up to <em>Mouzon</em>, there to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> who is there with about 6 thousand men, and so <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said they will <reg orig="besiedge">besiege</reg> some place or other to begin the campagna: The Priests of St. <em>Paul</em> having resolved to shut up their Church, by reason that their Parson had been exiled this City, with the clamour of the people thereupon, hath had so much power, as to get a Letter of the Signet, whereby the King calls him back from his exilement, and thereupon he returned upon Sunday last; the Order of the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> for the suppression of those who are called <em>Eleue</em> is also annulled, but with this proviso, that they shall enjoy their places 24 year, and pay ready money into the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> coffers 6 hundred thousand Livers, there is likewise great probability that those <reg orig="Counsellors">Councillors</reg> who were lately exiled shall also be called home, the Parliament having sat divers times to Artillery which is to be sent to Marshal <em>Turenne</em>, Commander <em>Marin</em> having this week sent to the Arsenal a hundred thousand Livers, that so the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> may be set more <reg orig="foreward">forward</reg>, and we are told that the Duke <em>de Joyeuse</em> is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> in that Army as General of the horse, the <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> Minister who was lately put under restraint for speaking evil of this present Government is again set at liberty, and all his Papers which had been <reg orig="seased">seized</reg> upon were restored him again.</p><pb n="13" />

<p>Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> is now very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in restoring his Library to its former Lustre, having already brought in near forty thousand Volumes, whereof a part being formerly his own, he taketh them wheresoever he can find them by open force, and others which he hath procured from several places, The Commissioners from St. <em>Malos</em> and other places in <em><reg orig="Britanie">Brittany</reg></em> have made great complaints concerning the taking of many of their ships by the English <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, demanding that they might have liberty to <reg orig="sease">seize</reg> upon the ships and goods of the English on the land, but that would not be granted; then they petitioned for leave to set out men of War, and that Letters of Mart may be granted them to make them satisfaction for their losses which they say are very great. Yesterday arrived here an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em>, which as we hear hath brought Letters from the said Earl intimating that he doth submit to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> pleasure, and is ready to deliver up his charge unto the man whom the King will be pleased to send, as well for the City of <em>Brisack</em>, as for those places which depend thereof.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday May 12, 13.</i></head>

<p><em>Scilly Island</em> the 5th of <em>May</em> 1654. A Master of a ship from <em>Virginia</em> reports, that an Indian <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> himself unto the English there, and discovered unto them a design of the Natives to fall on the English about the beginning of this instant May, and that the English would be ready to prevent their bloody purposes, a Vessel of <em>Tixgmouth</em> bound for <em>Walls</em> for Coals came in hither yesterday, she was taken about the middle of the day a league to the East of those <reg orig="Ilands">Islands</reg> by <em>Mildrum</em> a <em>Brest</em> man of War of about 10 Guns, who having plundered the Vessel, dismissed her again, and bad her to make <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> into <em>Scilly</em>, for there were 4 or 5 more of his Comrades coming down the North <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, whom he should avoid, and that they had 10 or 12 guns a piece. There were aboard <em>Mildrum</em> some English that were lately taken by our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, and being brought ashore they suddenly obtained their liberty, and got to <em>Brest</em> again, so that there is little hopes that <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> but a Halter will <reg orig="reclaime">reclaim</reg> those rogues from their <reg orig="Theeving">Thieving</reg> kind of life. The chief Gunner of <em><reg orig="Mildrums">Mildrum's</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> named <em>Thomas Sloe</em>, was very lately taken in another <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> of <em>Brest</em> by one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, and is now with <em>Mildrum</em> again.</p><pb n="14" />

<p><em>Dublin</em> May 1. We have nothing of News to send you from hence, only here hath been of late a general Council of Officers to divide their lands, the result whereof I shall acquaint you by my next. The L. <em>Broghil</em>, and Sir <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Cools">Cool's</reg></em> Brother are sent to England with a Congratulatory Message from Gen. Council of Officers in <em>Ireland</em>, to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, the Lord Gen. <em>Fleetwood</em> will be also in <em>England</em> suddenly.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> May 4. This day came Gen. <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> from <em>Dalkeith</em> to <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, attended by the chief Officers of the Army, who were received at the Netherbow by the English Judges in their scarlet Robes, and the Town Magistrates, the Provost and the <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> in theirs likewise. The Gen. and Officers alighting from their horses, marched with those that met them in Order up the High street to the Cross, which was adorned with <reg orig="Tapstry">Tapestry</reg>, and there <reg orig="Advocat">Advocate</reg> Gen. <em>Whalley</em> proclaimed his Highness Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. as also the Ordinance for uniting <em>Scotland</em> to <em>England</em>, before a great concourse of people, Drums beating, Trumpets sounding, and voices <reg orig="ecchoing">echoing</reg> forth acclamations. After this was done, a great dinner was provided by the Magistrates of this Town to entertain the General, his Officers, and others, and to close the solemnity, this night was variety of Fireworks which continued till 11. of the clock. There is 12 <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of our men of war now riding in <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em> Road, which together with the <reg orig="Generals">General's</reg> speedy preparation for a march into the field, strikes terror into the spirits of the Highland <reg orig="spoylers">spoilers</reg>.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Edinburgh</em>, May 6. 1654. Major Gen. <em>Drummond</em> came from <em>Middleton</em> to <em><reg orig="Loughtay">Lough Tay</reg></em> about 3 instant, and <em>Glencarn</em> with a with about 100 horse, and one <em>Murray</em> with the like number of foot came into <em>Athol</em> about the 4 instant. They give out, they <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by Col. <em>Morgan</em> in a mist, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed they came by <em>Loughaber</em>. They intend to hasten their Levies, and speed to the North to surround Col. <em>Morgan</em>. <em>Montross</em> is raising his levies at <em>Branar</em>, and some small parties which are come from <em>Middleton</em> are <reg orig="joyn'd">joined</reg> with him. They say they expect <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> when their design is a little more ripe. Sir <em>Will. <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> 5 Companies are come up. The Gen. will be at <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> next week. The Ministers in this City prayed for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> the next day after the<pb n="15" /> Lord Protector was proclaimed, and the Union published; <reg orig="its">it's</reg> hard that they must <reg orig="stil">still</reg> go <reg orig="unpunisht">unpunished</reg>. The Enemy have received provisions, contrary to expectation, lately by two ships from <em>Dunkirk</em>, laden with Men, Arms, and Ammunition.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Milford-haven">Milford Haven</reg></em> May 8. All those that were here waiting for a fair wind to go over into <em>Ireland</em>, went away 2 days since, we have not heard <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> from thence lately, only by a vessel come to <em>Blewmorris</em> we hear that all things are in a peaceable condition, but want people to manure the ground, the Tories being now very few, have stirred very little of late, there were the last week seen near this place 2. <em>Brest</em> <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> who were coming from the Northward, and had with them 3 <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg>, which they had taken coming from <em>Dublin</em> to <em>Liverpool</em> and <em>Chester</em>, as they told a fisherman who was aboard of them, one of them had 12 guns, and 90 men, and the other 4 guns, and 40 men.</p>

<p>From <em>Rie</em>, May 12. We have little of new to write at present only that we see <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> now freed from the Dutch men of war, the little <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> of <em>Ostendt</em> do much vex and torment the Fishermen upon this coast, under pretence of seeking after French Vessels. This week a Barque being on her way between <em>Diep</em> and this place with 4 small guns attempted to take her, but the Barque having many <reg orig="passenges">passengers</reg>, as well English as French, did defend themselves so gallantly, that in a little dispute the <em>Ostender</em> last 7 men, and some wounded, and it is probable they might have got away, but that unhappily a shot took place in the Barque between wind and water sunk her down <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg>, but saved of most the Passengers.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Universal Medicine, or, The <reg orig="Elixer">Elixir</reg> of life, for expelling and curing of all diseases, and to keep the body sound, and in good health to the last day that God hath appointed. By Major <em>Erasmus Purling</em>: <em>London</em>, Printed by <em>John <reg orig="Crowch">Crouch</reg></em>, and are to be sold at Mr. <em>Richard <reg orig="Dikes">Dike's</reg></em> Keeper of Newgate, where the Author is resident for them that have occasion of him.</p>

<p>The 3 of <em>May</em> instant, a lusty brown bay stone horse, <unclear>crop <reg orig="ear'd">eared</reg></unclear>, a white foot behind, and a short Tail, with a very little star is his forehead, he doth both trot and pace, was stolen out of Mr. <em>Everard Goodman's</em> Stable of <em>Bleston</em> in the County of <em>Leicester</em>, whosoever shall make stay of, and give notice to Mr. <em>Adrian Hall</em> living over <em><unclear>Alckace</unclear></em>, or to Mr. <em>Everard Goodman </em>at his house aforesaid, shall be very well rewarded for their pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>