<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn224">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 224</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, March. 20. to <em>Monday</em>, March 27. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg>.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> March. 20.</head>

<p>This Day his Highness the Lord Protector passed a Declaration inviting the People of <em>England</em>, and <em>Wales</em> to a day of <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> and <reg orig="Humilliation">Humiliation</reg>, and <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the grounds thereof, as followeth.</p>

<p>The common and notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised amongst us, notwithstanding all our Deliverances and <reg orig="Moroies">Morays</reg>, together with the present rod of an exceeding and universal Drought, which hath lain upon us for some years, and still continues and increaseth upon us, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <unclear><!-- 7 characters --></unclear> and <unclear>Moruditu</unclear>, are no less than the voice of God calling aloud in our Ears to Fasting, and Mourning, and great Abasement of soul before him.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>And although the General end and intendment of inviting to a Day of Fast be that all of every condition and quality whatever, do try and examine their heart and way more especially, according to their own light, and in the use of such helps and means as the Lord in his Providence shall afford to each one, before and upon the said day of meeting. Yet finding some thoughts set seriously upon our heart, we judged it not <reg orig="amisse">amiss</reg> to <reg orig="recommed">recommend</reg> the same to Christian consideration, not to impose them upon any, or to confine any within the compass thereof but leaving every Man free to the grace of God, and to the work of his Spirit who worketh all things in the Hearts of the <reg orig="Sonnes">Sons</reg> of Men, according to the <reg orig="Counsell">Counsel</reg> and Good pleasure of his own will.</p>

<p>It cannot be <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, but that God hath vouchsafed to appear very much in working the deliverance of the Nation from that bondage and thraldom, both spiritual and <reg orig="evil">evil</reg>, and procuring for them a just liberty by his own People.</p>

<p>Do we now walk worthy of but high <unclear>easing</unclear> in <reg orig="humblennesse">humbleness</reg> and <reg orig="lowlinesse">lowliness</reg> of mind, holding forth the Virtues of Christ in the time of Peace, who was our strength, by the efficacy of which all our great things were accomplished in time of war.</p>

<p>Have we a heart prepared as willingly to communicate the said just <reg orig="freedome">freedom</reg> and liberty to one another, as we were industrious to get it.</p>

<p>Do we thankfully acknowledge our mercy in the liberty<pb n="2" /> of worshipping God in <reg orig="holinesse">holiness</reg> and <reg orig="righteousnesse">righteousness</reg> without fear, being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies?</p>

<p>Is brotherly love, and a healing spirit of that force and value amongst us that it ought?</p>

<p>Do we own one another more for the grace of God, and for the spirit of Regeneration, and for the image of Christ in each other, or for our agreement with each other in this or that form, or opinion.</p>

<p>Do we first search for the Kingdom of Christ within us, before we search one without us: Or do we listen to them that say concerning the coming of Christ, Lo here, and lo there?</p>

<p>Do we not more contend for Saints having rule in the world, than over their own hearts?</p>

<p>Are there not too many amongst us that cry up the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, Joy, Peace, <reg orig="Meeknesse">Meekness</reg>, Patience, <reg orig="Goodnesse">Goodness</reg>, Temperance, Long-suffering, Forbearance, Brotherly-<reg orig="Kindnesse">Kindness</reg>, Charity, which are the fruits of the Spirit?</p>

<p>How do we carry <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> not only to the Churches of God, and the Saints, but towards them that are without?</p>

<p>Do not some of us affirm <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to be the only true Ministry, and true Churches of Christ, and only to have the Ordinances in purity, excluding our Brethren, though of equal gifts, and having as large a Seal of their <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, and desiring with as much <unclear><reg orig="fervor">fervour</reg></unclear> and seal to enjoy the Ordinances in their utmost purity.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>Do we <unclear><!-- approx. half a line --></unclear> <unclear>to</unclear> <reg orig="simpathy">sympathy</reg>, Self-denial, Mercy to the Poor, brightness and Justice - or we not herein put to shame, by those we easily call Anti-Christian or Carnal?</p>

<p>Hath one that we judge to be without, equal Justice with one we call a Brother.</p>

<p>Do we contend for the <i>Faith once <reg orig="delivere">deliver</reg> unto the Saints</i>, as the faith ought to be contended for, with Love, Patience, Tenderness, Zeal, by <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg> ? Or rather imposingly, proudly, carnally, provokingly, sensually, <reg orig="therby">thereby</reg> prejudicing the Truth, and, whilst we are calling aloud for the propagating of the Gospel, do we not put stumbling blocks in the way of the same, and too much endanger to make good the slander of the world in charging Profession with <em>Faction</em>.</p>

<p>For want of Circumspection and car herein, and a due regard to sincerity and uprightness, have not many <reg orig="apostatized">apostatised</reg>, running after <em>Fancies</em> and <em>Notions</em>, <reg orig="listning">listening</reg> to filthy <em>Dreams, worshipping of Angels</em>, and been carried by their impulsions; and instead of contending for the faith, and holding the form of sound words <unclear>committed</unclear> against <em>Magistracy</em>, against <em>Ministry</em>, against <em>Scriptures</em>, and against <em>Ordinances</em>, too much verifying the prophesies of <em>Peter</em> and <em>Jude</em>, <em>viz</em>. 2. <em>Pet. 2. chap. 1, 2, 3, 10, 11, 12, 13, 15. Jude, 4, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 16, 19.</em></p>

<p>And notwithstanding all these <reg orig="evills">evils</reg>; and worse, are upon, and in the midst of us, like <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> hairs, here and there, and we know it not, <i>our Pride <reg orig="testfying">testifying</reg> to our face</i>, Hosea 7, 9, 10. and we not return to the Lord our God, nor seek him for all this, but these things are contended for, and justified under the notion of Liberty, it being too commonly said, that the Magistrate hath nothing to do either in repressing or <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> dying these things, We do hereby appeal to the hearts and consciences of all fearing the Lord, whether there be not as great cause as ever to lay our <em><reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the dust</em>, and to <em>abhor <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg></em> before the Lord, <em><unclear><reg orig="forbere">forbear</reg></unclear> abominations</em>, whereby the eyes of his <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> are provoked, and to seek pardon and remedy from himself of those things.</p>

<p>Add to these, The resistance, hatred, and neglect of the Gospel,<pb n="4" />, by the generality of men, the contempt and <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> done the sincere Professors of it, even for the image of Christ in them (although they have been instruments of many mercies, and of obtaining a just freedom for the Nation) The wickedness, oaths, <reg orig="drunkenesses">drunkenness</reg>, revellings, and all manner of licentiousness; for which things sake, the Scriptures have said, that the wrath of God shall undoubtedly overtake the children of disobedience.</p> 

<p>And lastly, the impunity of these things, through the neglect of the Magistracy throughout the Nation, and then judge whether there be not cause, that we be called upon, and do call upon each other seriously, to lay all these things to heart, being greatly abased before the Lord for them.</p>

<p>Upon the serious consideration of these things, We judge it not only warrantable, but a duty, to call upon you, and <reg orig=" our selves"> ourselves</reg> , to set apart time to humble our souls before the Lord, to cry unto him for broken and penitent hearts, and that he would turn away his wrath, and be reconciled to us; for the Lord he is merciful, gracious, long-suffering, and abundant in goodness and truth, forgiving iniquity, transgression and sin, and will by no means clear the guilty, who are only such as go on in their <reg orig="hardned">hardened</reg> and impenitent hearts, refusing the grace offered by Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>It is therefore hereby declared, That We, and our Council, do purpose (by the grace of God) to set apart <em>Friday</em> next, being the 24 of this present <em>March</em>, for a day of <reg orig="Humilliation">Humiliation</reg>.</p> 

<p>And it is hereby Ordered, that timely notice be given to the cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, who (together with the out Parishes) we doubt not, will willingly keep the same day. And that like notice be given throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to have their several meetings upon the same day Fortnight. And that Copies hereof be printed and published, to be sent to the several parts of the Nation, to invite them unto the performance of this Duty: <i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, this 20 of <em>March</em>, 1653.</i></p>

<p><em>Newcastle</em>, 16 March. Our fleet is gone from hence, a great fleet for <em>London</em>, and other parts that way, they had a good convoy. There were a few small ships, more should have <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> with them from <em>Sunderland</em>, but got not out soon enough, they lost a tide of two, and there was such a strong and seasonable wind, that the<pb n="5" /> fleet thought it not discretion to stay, when they had so fair opportunity; yet there were ten ships that got out on <em>Monday</em> last from <em>Sunderland</em>, and though they had no Convoy with them, yet they thought they might venture between <em><reg orig="New-castle">Newcastle</reg></em> and the Fleet there so lately put out before, and accordingly they put out to follow the Fleet; but were presently set upon by the Capers, and <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather than to be taken, they were forced to run their 10 ships all a ground; but the Capers pursued them, and after the Men were got out, the Capers got off five of them, and the other five are lost, so that within about a <reg orig="Fortnights">Fortnight's</reg> time, we have lost 22 <reg orig="Coalships">Coal ships</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday March 21.</i></head>

<p>This day was published an Ordinance for the continuance if the Excise for one year from <em>March</em> 1654. by which His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, doth ordain, that from and after the five and twentieth day of this present <em>March</em>, the several Rates and Charges hereafter set down, and every of them and none other, in the right of the Duty of Excise, shall be set, laid, and imposed, and are hereby laid, set, and imposed, to be had, levied, and demanded, collected, received, recovered, and paid, in and through <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, and Town and Port of <em><reg orig="Barwick">Barwick</reg></em>, upon all and every the Commodities, Merchandizes, and Manufactures, Native and Foreign, in manner following, that is to say,</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rates of Excise and Commodities of <em>Inland</em> making or growth.</i></head>

<p>For every Barrel of Beer or Ale of above six shillings the Barrel brewed by the Common Brewer or any other who sell Beer or Ale, to pay 2 s.</p>

<p>For every Barrel of six shilling Beer or Ale, or above four shilling the Barrel, brewed by the Common Brewer, or any other who sell Beer or Ale to pay 6d.</p>

<p>And so <reg orig="proportiably">proportionally</reg> for a greater or lesser quantity of Beer or Ale above four shillings the Barrel.</p>

<p>And no allowance to be made from henceforth for any Beer or Ale to be used in Fishing Vessels at <unclear>Sea</unclear>, which is bought of the Common Brewer of Retailers of Beer or Ale.</p>

<p>Allum English, the hundred weight, <unclear>containing</unclear> one hundred and twelve pounds, to be paid by the Maker <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear>.</p>

<p>Coperas English, the hundred weight to be paid by the Maker, <unclear>4d.</unclear></p><pb n="6" />

<p>Hops English, the hundred weight, to be paid by the Planter 2 s. Saffron English, for every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the Planter, <em>1s</em>.</p>

<p>Tin, for every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the buyer <em>2s</em>.</p>

<p>Iron English, for every hundred weight, to be paid by the Maker 1s. <em>6d</em>.</p>

<p>For all the Aqua vit&aelig; or Strong water, made or distilled within the Commonwealth, whether of <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> or <reg orig="Domestick">Domestic</reg> Spirits or Materials, to be sold, upon every Gallon, to be paid by the first Maker or Seller thereof respectively, <em>2d</em>.</p>

<p>For every Barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within this Commonwealth of what sort soever, to be paid by the Maker, and so <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> for hard <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> or soft <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within the Land, <em>4s</em>.</p>

<p>For every Ounce Troy of Silver or Gold, prepared, melted down, or disgrossed for <!--Wire??-->Wyer, to be paid at the Bar where the same shall be disgrossed, <em>2d</em>.</p>

<p>For every pound weight of any Copper, or other Metal, that shall be prepared, made fit, or disgrossed, to be paid at the Bar where the same shall be disgrossed <em>1s</em>.</p>

<p>For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Whale <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, <reg orig="Blubbar">Blubber</reg> <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Rape <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Pilchard <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, and all other <reg orig="Oyls">Oils</reg> made within this Commonwealth, upon every <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, to be paid by the Maker, 6.s. per <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>.</p>

<p>For every Fother of Lead, containing two thousand pound weight, at one hundred and twelve pounds to the hundred, to be paid by the Maker or Smelter, <em>6s 8d</em>.</p>

<p>For all Salt, made, or to be made within England, or Wales, or Town of Berwick, which is or shall be shipped or conveyed by water, to be paid by the first buyer thereof upon the first delivering upon every Gallon, a half penny.</p>

<p>For all other Salt, made, or to be made within England, or Wales, or Town of <em>Berwick</em>, which is or shall be shipped or conveyed by water, to be paid by the first buyer thereof upon the first delivering upon every Gallon, a half penny.</p> 

<p>Upon all Salt upon Salt, that is made of Salt within <em>England, Wales</em>, or Town of <em>Berwick</em>, to be paid by the Maker thereof, upon every Gallon a Farthing.</p>

<p>For all <reg orig="Sider">Cider</reg> and Perry, made, and sold by way of Retail, whether it be by the first Maker, or any Buyer or Receiver thereof, from the First Maker upon every Hogshead, and so for<pb n="7" /> a greater and lesser measure <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg>, <em>2s. 6d</em>.</p>

<p>For all Metheglin or Mead, and such like Drinks sold out by Retail, to be paid by the Retailer, upon every Gallon, and so provato, 1d.</p>

<p>For all Starch, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, to be paid by the first maker, <em>1s</em>.</p>

<p>For all sorts of Glass or Glasses, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, to be paid by the Maker, <em>1s</em>.</p>

<p><i>Thus <reg orig="farr">far</reg> of the Rates of all Inland Commodities, which we conceived was so general for all persons to take notice of; for the Rates of all Foreign Commodities, more particular to Merchants, see the Act at large printed.</i></p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, March 14. Since <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing, the Enemy are very active in all parts, and will leave no stone unturned. There hath been a conjunction of Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em>, Mr. <em>Gregor</em>, and Mr. <em>Naughton</em> lately, and their general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> was to be the 14. instant at <em>Rothemacchos</em>, or <em>Abernathy</em>. <em>Glengary</em> hath obtained a man out of every Plough in <em>Strathtick</em>, and is to have horse and money according to former <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and requires the like from <em>Strathspey, Straddowne, Glenrennos, Bellevine, <reg orig="Murrieland">Murrayland</reg></em>, and of the <em>Frazers</em> in <em>Stranglas</em>, and if they fail to send in their proportions according to the several Warrants, they must expect fire and sword.</p>

<p><em>Glencarne</em> with his men are in <em>Badgenoth</em>, from whom a Servant of one Lieut. Col. <em>Smith</em> with his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> horse ran into our Garrison at <em>Ruthven</em> Castle. They report that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor. There came with <em>Middleton</em> sixty and <reg orig="odde">odd</reg> Officers, the least a Captain, and amongst the rest (besides those I formerly hinted to you) Col. <em>Henderson, <reg orig="Monro">Monroe</reg></em>, and others of them had very cold entertainment in <em>Southerland</em>. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> and Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> had a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> on <em>Wednesday</em> last of about 300 horse, and 230 foot, they have placed a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in a little house upon <em>Lough Tay</em>, where they intend to have a store of provisions of about 1500 <reg orig="Bolles">Boles</reg> of victual, and to send such of the Commissioners and Heritors thither as refuse to send in their Levies. In Saturday last Major <em>Holmes</em> at <em>Binlithgow</em> having notice of a party of the Enemy in the Country, sent out a Quartermaster of <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> Regiment with a party, who took a Cornet and four others of the Enemy, and 11 Horse.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 12.</i></head>

<p>Several Conferences have been this Week by the Commissioners of the Council to the Lord Protector, and the Dutch Ambassadors in order to the dispatch of that business which a few more <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> (no doubt) will bring to perfect end.</p>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em>, March 20. There can be nothing else gathered out of the Letters come lately from <em>England</em>, but that our Ambassadors have been received there with great magnificence, and that we are like to hear by the next post of a full conclusion of the Peace, Some do say that the Ratification thereof shall be delivered of both sides within few weeks. The news concerning the Affairs in <em>Scotland</em> are very various here amongst us.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> seems lost to the world; and indeed the <em>Spaniards</em> use to strike home when eminent strangers fall into their clutches; the poor Duke pressing for the liberty of the <reg orig="Cittadel">Citadel</reg> walls, upon denial, grew into such a rage, that he broke all the glass-windows about his Chamber, which breaches have been repaired since by immuring up the walls on all sides, only a small hole out of reach, being left to let in some light; 'tis said his design was to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Troops under, Monsieur <em>Fabert</em>, and so by the assistance of <em>France</em> to make himself Duke of <em>Brabant</em>, which he was to receive in homage from the French, and in exchange for his Country; they have in the mean time confiscated all they could lay their hands on, seized upon his Jewels which were found with his Wife, and Daughter, the last being possessed of one to the value of two millions.</p>

<p>It is reported, that a Marriage was concluded upon betwixt the Scotch King and his Daughter, who was immediately to receive four millions with her, and all the assistance possible for his <reg orig="restauration">restoration</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em>, the 25 March, stilo novo. The Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> is still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in furthering the great preparations which are to be made at <em>Touland</em> or the great design intended against <em>Naples</em>, as the report goeth, although others will have it for the receiving of <em>Rosa</em>, and other places in <em>Catalonia</em> and <em>Rousillon</em>, The Duke <em>de Guise</em> who is said to be chosen Commander for <pb n="9" /> that design, hath got together great sums of Money having borrowed divers sums from several Men in this City; The States of <em>Languedoc</em> having promised a great sum of money to his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, there hath now orders issued out for the payment thereof within the several hundreds of that Province, some of those forces which were of late in <em>Rousillon</em> not being able to subsist there any longer, have been sent about <em>Narbonne</em> to quarter. There is of late but little news come from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, only that they are still very discontented at the death of one of their Commissioners mentioned some weeks since having made a deep impression in the hearts and affections of many: They complain much of the dearth of all manner of provisions, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> of the want of Trade. The <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> <em>de Estissa</em> doth still continue to be <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Rochel</em>, and doth keep all things there in peace and <reg orig="quietnesse">quietness</reg>. There hath been this week an encounter between Prince <em>Rupert</em> and some of our Gentry who were worsted by the first, leaving one dead and another mortally wounded on the place. The prince of <em>Conti</em> is to be Commander in chief of all the Forces in <em>Catalonia</em>, and to that end is now raising four Regiments of Horse and Foot, who are to be ready by the middle of <em>May</em> at the furthest, upon <em>Saturday</em> next the King is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to the Parliament there to have the Declaration against the Prince of <em>Condi</em>, who shall be declared guilty of high Treason, with all his adherents, and his Estate forfeited to the King, with many other particulars therein contained.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday March</em> 23.</head>

<p>This day was published the Ordinance appointing the Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Preachers, and is to this effect.</p>

<p>Whereas for some time past hitherto there hath not been any certain course established for the supplying vacant places with able and fit persons to preach the Gospel, by reason whereof not only the rights and Titles of Patrons are prejudiced, but many weak scandalous, popish, and ill-affected Persons have intruded themselves, or been brought in, to the great grief and trouble of the People of this Nation; for remedy and prevention whereof, It is ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the<pb n="10" /> Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council that every Person, who shall from and after the five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> instant be presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publique">public</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Lecture in <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, shall, before he be admitted into any such benefice, or Lecture be judged and approved, by the Persons hereafter named, to be a Person for the Grace of God in him, his holy and unblameable conversation, as also for his knowledge and utterance, able and fit to preach the Gospel; and that after the said five and twentieth day of <em>March</em>, no Person, but such as shall upon such approbation be admitted by the said persons, shall take any <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Lecture, having a constant stipend legally annexed and belonging thereunto, or take or receive any such benefice as aforesaid, or the profits thereof; And be it further ordained, That <em>Francis Rous</em>, Esq; Dr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, Dr. <em>John Owen</em>, Mr. <em>Thankful Owen</em>, Dr. <em>Arrowsmith</em>, Dr. <em>Tuckney</em>, Dr. <em>Horton</em>, Mr <em><reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg> Cary</em>, Mr. <em>Philip Ny</em>, Mr. <em>William Carter</em>, Mr. <em>Sinrach Simpson,</em> Mr. <em>William <reg orig="Greenhil">Greenhill</reg></em>, Mr. <em>William Strong</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas Manion</em>, Mr. <em>Samuel Slater</em>, Mr. <em>William Cooper</em>, Mr. <em>Stephen Marshal</em>, Mr. <em>John Tombes</em>, Mr. <em>Walter Cradock</em>, Mr. <em>Samuel Faircloth</em>, Mr. <em>Hugh Peters</em>, Mr. <em>Peter Aterry</em>, Mr. <em>Samuel Bamford</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas Valentine</em> of <em>Chaford</em>, Mr. <em>Henry Jessee</em>, Mr. <em>Obadiah <reg orig="Sedgewick">Sedgwick</reg></em>, Mr. <em>Nicholas Luckier</em>, Mr. <em>Daniel Dyke</em>, Mr. <em>James <reg orig="Russel">Russell</reg></em>, Mr. <em>Nathanael Campfield</em>, <em>Robert <unclear>Tichborn</unclear></em>, Aldermen of <em>London, Mark Hildesly, Thomas Wood, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Sadler, William Goff, Thomas St. Nicholas, William Packer</em>, and <em>Edward Cresset</em>, Esquires, be, constituted and appointed Commissioners for such approbation and admission as is abovesaid, and the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, met together in some certain place in the City of <em>London</em> or <em>Westminster</em>, as his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> shall <reg orig="apoint">appoint</reg>, are authorized to judge and take knowledge of the ability and <reg orig="fitnesse">fitness</reg> of any Person so presented, and to grant admission to such Benefice or Lecture by an Instrument in writing under a Common Seal to be appointed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That no person who shall tender himself, or be <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg>, for approbation as aforesaid, shall be concluded by any Vote of the said Commissioners which shall pass in the<pb n="11" /> Negative as to his approbation, unless nine or more of the said Commissioners be present at such Vote.</p> 

<p>And it is further Ordained; That all Patrons of any Benefices that are now void, shall within six Months next after the five and twentieth of this instant <em>March</em>, and of any Benefice that shall hereafter be void within six Months next after the avoidance of the same, Present unto the said Commissioners, or any five of them, some fit person to be admitted, and for default of such Presentation within that time, the Presentation for that turn shall devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That in case the Patron be disturbed to Present unto such Benefice, and thereupon within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the avoidance of such Benefice a <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> be commenced for the Recovery of such Presentation, and notice thereof in writing left with the said Commissioners, or any five of them, or the Register, that then such notice shall be as effectual to prevent the lapse, as where the <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> was heretofore commenced against the Bishop or Ordinary.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That during the vacancy of such place by reason of such <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg>, the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, have hereby authority to sequester the fruits and profits thereof for supplying of the place with an able Preacher, by the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, to be nominated and approved of as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And forasmuch as many persons since the first day of <em>April</em> last past, have been placed in such Benefices, and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Lectures, It is hereby Ordained, That in case such person shall not before the four and twentieth day of <em>June</em> next, obtain approbation and admittance in the manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, Then such person or persons as have right thereunto shall or may Present or nominate some other fit and able person to such place.</p>

<p>And in default of such Presentation within two <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the said four and twentieth day of <em>June</em>, or within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the place became void, the Presentation for that turn shall likewise devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>And for the better satisfaction of the said Commissioners<pb n="12" /> touching the godly and unblameable conversation of such persons as are to be admitted, into any place as aforesaid. It is further declared and ordained, that before any admittance of any person as aforesaid, there shall be brought to the said Commissioners, or any five of them, a Testimonial or Certificate in writing subscribed with the hands of three persons of known godliness and integrity, whereof one at least to be a Preacher of the Gospel in some constant <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> place; <reg orig="Testfying">Testifying</reg> upon their personal knowledge, the holy and good conversation of the person to be admitted: which said <reg orig="Certificat">Certificate</reg> shall be duly <reg orig="Registred">Registered</reg> and filed. And it is also Declared, That the penalty for or respect of the not subscribing or reading the Articles mentioned in the Act of the 13th <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, Intituled, <em>Reformation of Disorders in the Ministers of the Church</em>: or for not producing such Testimonial as in the said Act is required, shall from henceforth cease, and be void.</p>

<p>And whereas for the better maintenance of preaching Ministers, several Augmentations by Authority of Parliament have been heretofore granted, Be it further <reg orig="Ordeined">Ordained</reg>, That all person or persons, who claim, or shall hereafter claim the benefit of such Augmentation, shall before he or they receive the same, obtain the approbation of the said Commissioners, or five of them, as a person qualified, as is before mentioned.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 28 of <em>March</em>, 1654. The Archbishop of this City is lately deceased, and thereupon are new controversies raised, in regard that the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> who is his Nephew, a Coadjutor, and thereupon hath a Reversion, with the City of <em>Paris</em>, who seem to pretend a title in the choosing of a new Peer, and upon that <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> <reg orig="its">it's</reg> like to the same dispute at Court, in regard <reg orig="its">it's</reg> a place both of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> and profit. The <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> lately returned from <em>Rome</em>, have not given any other <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg>, but that finding <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> thwart him too much, and that he was <reg orig="somethin">something</reg> slighted at Court, therefore he thought most safe to come home: According to the late Edict made and published by the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Command against Duels, there have been some who have incurred that censure, their Bodies being executed in <em>Effigies</em>, and other penalties inflicted by the Law. The Prince of <em>Conde</em> hath been some time at <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em><pb n="13" />, and now hath been at the town of <em>Louuain</em>, and now intends to set his Army in a posture ready to take the field with the first opportunity. The Court is not yet gone to <em><reg orig="Fontainbleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em>, and that upon some eminent occasions, for there remaineth the prosecution of the Declaration against the Prince of <em>Conde</em> which is to be passed <reg orig="to day">today</reg>. The Prince of Conti doth <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on in his new Levies, there being not any more monies wanting, and by the next June we are promised to see very strange effects between the two Nations of <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em>, some will have it all fire and sword, and others will have it upon accommodation by way of marriage, which shall be known shortly: The Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> will not yet submit to the Court although there are strong <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> to draw him thereunto: The taking of several places near <em>Brisack</em> hath made him to stand the more upon his guard, and to try once for all whether he can make an honourable accommodation. There is order given for the sitting of some ships at <em>Brest</em>, and other places in these Seas, which as it is said are to go and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those that are to be made ready in Toulon.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday March 4, 5.</i></head>

<p><em>Friday</em> was kept (according to the former Declaration) a very solemn Fast throughout <em>London, Westminster</em>, and the liberties adjacent, there prayed and preached before the Lord Protector and his Council at Whitehall, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, Mr. <em>Strong</em>, and Mr. <em>Cradock</em>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was published for continuing the Act for laying an imposition upon Coals towards the building and maintaining ships for the guarding the Seas to be in force until the 26 of <em>March</em> 1655.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for passing Custodies for Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance for continuing the Act of impressing of Seamen to be of force until the first of <em>Nov</em>. 1654.</p>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven the 13 of <em>March</em> there is arrived this week from <em>Ireland</em> three Vessels laden with Irish Commodities, and brought over some few passengers; they say little<pb n="14" /> for news from thence, only that the Country in many parts wants People to till and manure the ground, that the <em>Tories</em>, and others of that bloody crew are very near all <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg>, there being only very small parties remaining on foot but dare not to stand to any <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> with such parties of ours as are sent for to destroy them, and so clear the Country from them, upon the least report that they hear of our men approaching they presently run into the Woods and <reg orig="Boggs">Bogs</reg> where there is little or no <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> to them, we have not been much troubled of late with any <reg orig="Pikeroons">Picaroons</reg>, one only was seen the beginning of this Week to the Westward of the Isle of <em>Lundy</em>, but upon the report made him by a Fisherboat, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> appointed to keep these Seas was in pursuit, he <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> went away, and left this <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, sailing towards the Lands end, he hath about 6 Guns and 60 men being a Dutch Vessel, but a singular good Sailor.</p>

<p>From <em>Scarborough</em>, March 20. Since that the fleet of Colliers bound for the Southward hath passed by, there hath not sailed this way many ships, save only a few bound for <em>Newcastle</em>, <em><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em>, and the <em>Frith</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, two days since two Dutch Freebooters were seen about <em>Fylie</em> Bay, and seeing nothing to prey upon, they went about <em>Flamborough</em> into the Bay, as near <em>Bridlington</em> as they durst: but seeing nothing ready to be <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg> up, they sailed into the Sea, and were seen this Evening hovering about the mouth of <em>Humber</em>.</p>

<p><em>Leith March</em> 18. There is no Account yet come of the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlander's</reg> great <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be about <em>Wednesday</em> last in <em>Badgenoth</em>, in order to which all their forces are drawn Northwards, where they will arm those that want, and <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to raise <em>Sutherland, <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>, and so drain the Country of all the sensible Men they can get together, though I suppose when that is done they will not be able to keep them, without coming into the Lowlands, which if they once become more numerous they will attempt.</p><pb n="15" />

<p>By another Letter further thus, <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to 700. and the last general rendezvous of them all they spake themselves to be 7000 armed, but have no moneys, only are fed with hopes of great sums to come out of <em>Germany</em>, and that the Titular Duke of <em>York</em> is to bring from thence an additional supply of men under his Conduct, and upon this depends the great expectation of <em>Charles <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> arrival amongst them. In the interim they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p>

<p>Saturday morning about three of the clock the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg> with the Dutch letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, was <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> and broke open by Thieves within a mile of St. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> Church, which they did as supposed upon hopes to find money, but finding none, broke open all the Letters that were in packets, and throwed them upon the ground and turned the man back again.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors being removed from Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his House in the Palace yard <em>Westminster</em> to Sir <em>John Trevors</em> his house in <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> Row, which they have taken to reside in during the perfecting of the Peace, and their stay here, whereof a good <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> ('tis believed) will be given shortly. On Monday Monsieur <em>Burdeaux Neusville</em>, Ambassador from the King of <em>France</em> is to be brought in state of an Ambassador in Coaches throughout the City to <em>Westminster</em>, to Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his House, and to have audience of his Highness the Lord Protector the day following.</p>

<hr />

<p>About the 12th of this instant, there was lost, strayed or stolen <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> park; near <em>Youghall</em> in <em>Surrey</em>, a little Bay Mare, about <unclear><!-- approx. 19 characters --></unclear> doth amble, trot, and gallop, with a blackish Mane and a Blackish <unclear>flash</unclear> which reacheth down near the bocks, if it be not cut since she was lost. And she hath a few white hairs in the forehead, mingled in the place of a <unclear>Scar</unclear> amongst other parts, she is pretty round, straight &amp; clean limbed. If any one <unclear><!-- approx. 21 characters --></unclear> Owner may have her again, and bring or send word to Mr. <em>Thomas Lenner</em>, Stationer at the Royal Exchange in <em>London</em>, he shall have twenty shillings for his pains.</p>

<p>A bright bay pacing Mare with a small <reg orig="starre">star</reg>, black mane, and black <reg orig="tayl">tail</reg>, locks somewhat short, great with foal, with an old sore upon the withers, healed up, but no hair upon it, a little hip shotten, but hardly to be discerned. 14 handful high and 8 years old. She was lost from <em>Hampton</em> Court <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Leompster</em> in Herefordshire, about the end of December last, whosoever shall give notice of her to the <unclear>owner</unclear> abovesaid, or to Mr. <em>Lewes</em> at the white Hart in St. Johns street shall have twenty sh. for his pains.</p> 

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>