<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn227">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 227</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, April. 10. to <em>Monday</em>, April. 17. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> April. 10.</head>

<p>This day was published a farther Ordinance for adjourning part of Easter Term, 1654. repealing the Ordinance on <em>Saturday</em> before as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; out of a tender care and desire, that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, it is held convenient and necessary to adjourn part of the Next Term of <em>Easter</em>; Be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector<pb n="1" />, by and with the consent of his Council, That part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em> now next <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> be Adjourned, that is to say, from and after the first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, unto the last Return of the said Easter Term, called <em>Crastino Ascensione</em>; And all and every person and persons, which have cause, or commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, may tarry at their dwellings, or where their business shall lie, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, until the said last Return, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf.</p>

<p>And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, and Barons of the <em>Exchequer</em>, giving them authority to adjourn part of the said Term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the said first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasc&aelig;</em>, until the said last Return of the said Term of Easter, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the said first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasc&aelig;</em>, until the said last Return of the said Term, called <em>Crastino Ascensionis</em>, as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained, That all Matters, Causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastnino Ascensionis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained, That a former Ordinance of the 6th day of this instant April, for the Adjourning of part of the said Term, until the first Return of <em>Trinity</em> Term next, called <em>Crastino Triniatis</em>, be from henceforth Repealed and void. And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em><reg orig="Middl-sex">Middlesex</reg></em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the chief Market Towns, and usual places within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<p>This Congratulation to his Highness the Lord Protector from the Mayor and Common Council of <em>Newcastle</em> was this day presented, as followeth.</p><pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>For his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging; May it please your Highness,</i></head>

<p>Many of the precious servants of God in these Nations (over which the Lord hath set your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>) have gotten upon their watch Tower, to see if they can discover what hath been the eminent design of the Lord in these latter <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. For the All-wise God hath of late visibly been out of his common road, of Providences, his paths have been in tempests and thick <reg orig="darknesse">darkness</reg>, plucking up by the roots the greatest of men, and the highest of Powers, like Cedars in <em>Lebanon</em>, that he might make way for the glorious bringings forth of Truth and <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg>. And we question not but the Lord is fulfilling that great <reg orig="Phrophesie">Prophesy</reg>, <i>Isa. 60. 17. I will make thine Officers Peace, and thy Exactors Righteousness</i>. For when we consider how the Lord hath eminently made your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <reg orig="Instrumentall">Instrumental</reg> for the breaking off the Iron <reg orig="yoak">yoke</reg> from off the necks of the three Nations, and likewise hath invested you with the Supreme Power of this Commonwealth, whereby you may be exceedingly Instrumental to the Lord Jesus in the advancing of his Kingdom in <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg> and Peace, We having the sense of these things with weight upon our spirits, having judged it our duty to <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> our great Resentment of this signal mercy from the hands of our God, and do solemnly <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the Lord for setting up your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> over this great people, and shall endeavour through the strength of Christ, to live in all humble obedience to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as <reg orig="becommeth">becometh</reg> those who are under your Government and Protection.</p>

<p>Febr. 25. 1653.</p>

<p><i>Signed in the name, and by Order of the Common Council of <em>Newcastle</em> upon <reg orig="Tine">Tyne</reg>, <em>Will: Johnson</em> Mayor.</i></p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dalkieth</em>, April 6. Concerning affairs here, besides what was done by Major <em>Bridge</em>, whereof the enclosed is an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> under his own hand, a party of Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment, commanded by Cornet <em>Kenner</em>, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg> with some Sesse which they had collected<pb n="3" />, were set upon by 40 of the Enemy, received their charge and then charged through the Rebels, routed them, killed 4 on the place, took 6, whereof 3 mortally wounded, and had only 4 of his party wounded. Lieutenant <em>Hickman</em> with another party fell upon 60 of the Enemy under the command of one Captain <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em>, took 6. above 20 horse: Capt. <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em> was shot in the back, his horse taken, but he himself escaped amongst the Whins and bogs. <em>Glencarne</em> and <em>Glengary</em>, &amp;c. are gone over <em>Tain</em> into <em>Sutherland</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, and then they will be near 4000. yet I doubt not but Col. <em>Morgan</em> will endeavour to engage them with his party. <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em>, and the Lord <em>Dudhoppe</em> are raising men in the Brays of <em>Angus</em> and report already speaks them 300 horse.</p>

<p>Upon Monday night last the Enemy had a party returning from the South towards <em>Aberfoy</em> <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, to which <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> another party of the Enemy, of about 60 Horse and 60 Foot, commanded by Col. <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em>; at which time Cornet <em>Keys</em>, with about 20 Horse from <em>Dunbarton</em>, and Lieut. <em>Francis Young</em> of Capt. <em><reg orig="Callants">Callant's</reg></em> Company of Col. <em><reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg></em> Regiment, with 18 Horse and 30 Foot from <em>Bobannnan</em> made after them; the Enemy got the <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> first, <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> they were totally routed by ours, who killed one Captain and twelve private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, took Lieut. Col. <em>George Herriot, William Bobannan</em> Capt. Robert <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em> Cornet, <em>Hugh Wells</em> <reg orig="Quattermaster">Quartermaster</reg>, above 40 private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and above 20 Horse, <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em> fled with 16 Horse, all of them being killed and taken, save himself and three others. We had only one killed, one wounded. and two horses killed.</p>

<p><i>From Major Bridge, to the <reg orig="Commandour">Commander</reg> in chief, dated at Hamilton April 3.</i> According to your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> command I drew out an 100. men out of my Col. Regiment, and we met at <em>Hambleton</em> on Tuesday last, from whence I sent 40 to <em><reg orig="Duglasse">Douglas</reg></em> and <em>Zanker</em>, appointing them to meet me within 2 days at a place appointed; and with the rest of the party I marched to <em>Newmills</em>, where I lay one night, making it my <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> to get what intelligence<pb n="4" /> I could of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> motion. The next morning by break of day, a Lieut. and nine Mossers came to the Towns end, upon whom our Sentinel fired, and they presently betook themselves to the Mosses; and notwithstanding they were closely pursued by the guard, they could get but two prisoners and six horses, which were not so serviceable, being but that night taken from Country people, which I caused to be restored again, upon some small consideration to the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that took them. The same day Lieut <em>Evans</em> marching with his party from me to <em><reg orig="Duglass">Douglas</reg></em>, through the Mores, took 8 Mossers more, notable Villains and sturdy. I sent to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg> to desire him to acquaint me with the condition of Lieut. <em>Hickman</em>, who marched out with 70 horse from <em>Glasgow</em>, by reason it was reported he forced the Enemy in <em>Carick</em>, who was said to be double his number, but his Return to me was, that he was considerable enough, and that he had met and fought some of the Enemy, routed and pursued them to <em>Chapel</em>; and so did judge that my party might be most useful about <em>Zanker</em> and those passes, to that purpose I divided, and sent Lieut. <em>Evans</em> with fifty horse that way.</p>

<p>But 2 miles from <em>Comlock</em> I <reg orig="happpened">happened</reg> to hear the Enemy by a Country man, who reported them to be about 12. I sent a party to the place where they were, but they had the Alarm and rid for it, their party still increased till they came to the number of 60, which were still pursued by a Corporal and 10 men; at last they faced about, seeing no more, and our party made a halt, but so soon as ever they discovered my party coming, they presently began to flinch, and turn Tails, I sent the Corporal therefore presently to charge their rear, but they soon fled and betook themselves to the Mosses, whither we pursued them at least 10 miles in the most doleful place that ever I beheld; He followed them so long as our horse could step forwards, and <reg orig="til">till</reg> they had not above 12 or 14 together in a body, the rest dispersed, many leaving their horses, which we picked up to the number of 25, but could that day take no more prisoners but 8, and 2 or 3 slain in the pursuit.<pb n="5" /> This party was commanded by Major <em>Hamilton</em>, Capt. <em>Leglan</em> and <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em>, the last of which was not there. There was besides <em>Cragdorough</em>, with 50 horse that came up from about <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with these, and was quartered within a mile or two where I fell upon these Youths; but by reason of our interposing could not come to them, but marched off <reg orig="intirely">entirely</reg> in a Body to the left of us, I endeavoured to get what intelligence I could of their motion that night. Next morning I understood where they were, and what they intended, which was to go by the way of <em>Douglas</em>, and so into the North over <em>Cluyd</em>, I presently mounted and marched another way, as fast as I could, thinking to have been before them, but it so happened that they were gotten past <em>Douglas</em> a full hour before me; I found out their Tract, and pursued after them as fast I could, sending 16 of our best horse, if it were possible to engage them, but all was to little purpose, we pursued them until we came 4 miles within <em>Hamilton</em> long within night, but then lost them. I came to <em>Hamilton</em> this morning about one a clock, and presently sent out all the Horse that were here to lie upon the Passes of <em>Cluyd</em>, and to range the Country between <em>Evandale</em> and <em>Senerick</em>, whereabout I judge they will attempt to get over <em>Cluyd</em>. I have also dispatched an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> to Col. <em>Cooper</em> desiring him to send to <em>Rilsyth</em>, and they send to <em>Sterling</em>, to draw forth their horse on the Passes, that so if we miss of them here, they may perhaps light on them, they cannot be much <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg>. I have also sent to <em><reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg></em> to Cap. <em>Robson</em>, to desire him to advise Lieut. <em>Hickman</em> with his party, which I understand is come out of <em>Carick</em>, to lie about the Country near the passes of <em><reg orig="Dunbarton-shire">Dunbartonshire</reg></em>, where those dispersed people of <em><reg orig="Hamiltons">Hamilton's</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Leglans">Leglan's</reg></em> will certainly <reg orig="privatly">privately</reg> endeavour to get over. The eight prisoners first taken, I sent to <reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg>, the rest I shall send this day to <em>Glasgow</em>: One is said to be a Capt. another a Lieut. and a notorious <reg orig="Mosse Trooper">Moss-trooper</reg>, known to be so by the Country about from his Childhood. Truly Sir, I must now of necessity take some rest, both men and horses being utterly spent, and having not only <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg> out our own horses, but also those we took from the Enemy.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, March 10. We are very greedy in our expectations to understand the full of the success of the Treaty between England, and the United Provinces; for we do confidently believe, That then we shall receive a very speedy and satisfactory answer. My Lord Ambassador is not idle; He takes all advantages to promote his negotiation: And, indeed, the Queen has so great an affection for <em>England</em>, and in particular for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> my Lord Protector, that she is very inclinable to make up this <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg>. The wheels are in motion, the Affair does make its progress: Those things which are of a single relation, and do not depend either upon a War or Peace with the Dutch, have received a candid acceptation. But as to other things, you must be content to let them <reg orig="pawse">pause</reg> a while, till the great business between us and <em>Holland</em> have one way or other received a period. The Queen is fixed in her Resolves of quitting the Government, yet she will dispatch us first: and it will be a very fair and specious conclusion of her Reign, that she has gained to <em>Sweden</em> so considerable an <reg orig="Allie">Ally</reg> as the state of <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 11.</i></head>

<p>The return of the Ratification of the Peace under the hands of the States General is expected within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and then the same is to be signed by the Lord Protector, and a day appointed for proclaiming of it here and in <em>Holland</em>, as also the Articles at large will be published, whereof more then.</p>

<p><i>All Adventurers for lands in <em>Ireland</em> which have not drawn lots for Baronies, are desired to take notice, That the Committee for Claims, have appointed Thursday the 27 of this instant April 1654. To be a day for drawing of Lots for Baronies, at <em>Grocers</em>-Hall <em>London</em>, to begin at Eight of the clock in the forenoon of the same day.</i></p>

<p>William Tibbs, Clerk.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 15 of April 1654. We have from <em>Languedoc</em>, that the troubles and civil <reg orig="jarrs">jars</reg> in that Province are so far from being appeased, that they rather increase, the complaints being<pb n="7" /> great concerning the putting to death the Viscount <em>Leran</em> a Protestant, by an unjust sentence; for the which, and for many other grievances and oppressions, the Protestants have now their Commissioners at Court suing for satisfaction, and now in a <reg orig="shew">show</reg> there is kind of satisfaction, by way of answer to their Remonstrance, to be drawn in a Declaration as from the King, but no good is likely to come of it, seeing so many times before the like Papers have been given, which have proved no better than <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Court flourishes; but more of this shortly.</p>

<p>From <em>Perpignan</em>. The <em>Spaniards</em> being wholly bent to bring under <em>Catalonia</em>, and hinder them from making a new revolt, or falling away from them, besides the demolishing of several fortifications in that Country have likewise apprehended all those of that Company, called the Royal Deputation, upon pretence that they did still incline more to the <em>French</em> than <em>Spanish</em> party. From <em>Champaigne</em>: The news is little at present, only that the Garrisons of <em>Stenay</em> and <em>Clermont</em> do much spoil in the Country; and though there is a watchful eye over them, yet they make great inroads into the Country, wasting and spoiling all as they <reg orig="goe">go</reg> in a most hostile manner. Marshal d<em>e la Ferte</em> is now wholly recovered of his late <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg> which he got at the <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg> of <em>Beffort</em>; and as for the Treaty with the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> that hitherto is unfinished, and so is very doubtful, there being a strong report that there is an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> Order gone to <em>Marshal la Ferte</em> for the <reg orig="besiedging">besieging</reg> of <em>Brisack</em>; the removing of the Cardinal <em>de Retz </em>from the Castle of <em>Vicennes</em> to the Castle of <em>Nantes</em>, is taken here very ill by all men of all conditions, who thereupon make weekly divers private meetings, and besides there are found at the Corners of the Streets, Bills, or Libels to incite the people to a new rising, which hath caused Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> name to forbid all such assemblies upon pain of exemplary punishment. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Sedan intended to have returned homewards with his Forces, that so he might put them into quarters, but on notice of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> motion, he is marched towards <em>la Bassee</em>, where it is supposed the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> chief design was <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> bent.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 12.</i></head>

<p>A farther Ordinance passed touching Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-Ways">Highways</reg> for this present year, 1654. as followeth. Whereas in an Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg> within this Nation, it is ordained, amongst other things, that two or more able and sufficient <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg>, as in that Ordinance is expressed, should be elected and chosen upon the first <em>Tuesday</em> next ensuing the five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> yearly, to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg>, within their respective Parishes for the year ensuing: And whereas by the reason of the publishing of the said Ordinance, the time aforesaid for such election for this year was elapsed, so as such election could not be made on that day in pursuance of the said Ordinance, whereby the benefit intended to the People thereby is obstructed; It is Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the Persons which already are chosen, or shall be chosen before the first day of <em>May</em> 1654. to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> (which election is hereby <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> to be made in every Place and Parish by the time aforesaid, under the penalties in that Ordinance expressed) in case no election hath been already made, shall undertake the said Office, and be sworn on, or before, the sixth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, under the said penalties in the said ordinance set down in that behalf, and shall be Surveyors for this present year, as if such election had been made on the first said <em>Tuesday</em> after the said five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding, And the said Surveyors so sworn, and all others authorized by the said Ordinance, shall be, and are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, to proceed in, and put in execution, all the Directions, Powers and Authorities in the said Ordinance contained, as fully to all intents and purposes, as if the election had been made on the day therein appointed.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance <reg orig="impowring">empowering</reg> Commissioners to put in execution an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> (<i>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco in <em>England</em>.</i>) That upon consideration had of the great prejudice arising to the English Plantations in Foreign<pb n="9" /> parts, and the great Damage and Loss to Trade at home, by the planting of Tobacco in this Nation; It is <reg orig="Ordeined">Ordained</reg> by Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That Sir <em>William Robert, John Stone, Gervas <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg>, Hen: Elsing, Adam Bains</em>, and <em>Jo. Bocket</em>, Esqs; or any 3. or more of them, be and are appointed Commissioners, and are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, authorized and required, by all fit and <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> ways and means, to put in Execution an Act of Parliament, dated the first of April, 1652. <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, (<i>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco in <em>England</em></i>) and every clause, article, matter and thing therein contained, and Act or Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding; And all Officers, Civil and Military, and all other persons, are required to be <reg orig="ayding">aiding</reg> and assisting unto the said Commissioners, or any person or persons <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by them in this service, for the effectual execution of all the powers and authorities, by the said Act or Ordinance, granted and <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> to the said Commissioners.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 6. The enclosed is all we have of news here. But we expect <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> to hear something from Col. <em>Morgan</em>, who is marched towards <em>Caithness</em> with a considerable party. The <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> is exceedingly much broken in most parts, but the news of the consummation of the Peace will much startle them.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> March 27. <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> having <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Glengarry</em> and <em>Athol</em> marched within 7 or 8 miles of this Garrison, on Friday last into <em>Ross</em>, being about 2000 horse and foot; they are drawing towards <em>Sutherland</em> to meet with <em>Middleton</em> and his party, with whom they expect to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg>; the Lord <em>Lorn</em> with 500 foot, and 100 horse intends to follow them, he is now about <em>Abertaf</em>, twenty four miles from this place, in the Rear of him follows <em><reg orig="Mac Vldow">McVldow</reg></em>, with what force he can make, so that shortly their whole force will be North of us, and what may then be effected upon them, we must leave to the disposing of the Almighty.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em>, The <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> is now in Treaty with divers particular persons for the furnishing in a set time so many <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of the New levies, that is to say four thousand <reg orig="sutes">suits</reg> of <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg>, 1800 shirts, two thousand swords<pb n="10" /> and as many hats, <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, and stockings; also he hath caused to be made great store of shovels, and such like tools for the <reg orig="pioniers">pioneers</reg>, as also 30. pieces of Brass Ordnance newly cast; all these things are to be sent with all <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> into <em>Catalonia</em>; he hath likewise sent his Master of the horse into <em>Spain</em>, to hath from thence 6000 Spaniards, who shall be dispersed into several <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> of this Kingdom, and those that are now in them shall be drawn into the field for service. By a small <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> come from <em>Messina</em>, we hear, that the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of that <reg orig="Iland">Island</reg> is now in perfect health. From Venice, <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> <em>Moccenigo</em> is now almost ready to depart from hence to <em><reg orig="Candie">Candia</reg></em>, and besides what we have formerly spoken, he is to carry with him those ships which were hired at <em>Leghorn</em> for the service of this State; We hear from <em>Dalmatia</em>, that the Turks have lately made an inroad at <em>Narrata</em>, where they have taken much Cattle, and made many persons prisoners. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> likewise confirmed, that the General <em>Delfino</em>, <!--??check??-->goeth on in his design to besiege <em>Clim</em>, which is built by the Turks on this side the Mountains being very strong, and made their chief <reg orig="magazin">magazine</reg>. The Dukes of <em>Florence, Parma</em>, and <em>Modena</em>, are now raising of men, but as yet it is unknown upon what ground. From Genoa, By the last letters from <em>Cagliari</em> in <em>Sardinia</em> we have it confirmed, that the Plague is wholly ceased at <em>Barcelona</em>, being declared so <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> that the neighbouring Nations might take notice of it. By the last Letters from <em>Madrid</em> we hear, that the Fleet expected now from <em>Nova Hispania</em>, and the other from <em>Peru</em>, will not come <reg orig="til">till</reg> <em>June</em> next. This last week was discovered a plot how some young men of this City intended to have seized upon a great ship, called <em>The five Saints</em>, laden with rich goods, and ready to depart for <em>Spain</em>; and thereupon some have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> apprehended, and a strict search is made all over the City, for the finding out, and laying in prison of their <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg>. From <em>Milan</em>, The new levies in <em>Germany</em>, as also in the Country of the <em>Grisons</em>, are almost finished, and there doth daily come in some of them, who are forthwith provided with quarters by the several Officers sent upon our <reg orig="Frontires">Frontiers</reg>, for that purpose; there hath likewise passed near this place 400 men, who are going towards <em>Casal</em> for the strengthening of that Garrison.<pb n="11" /> From <em>Turin</em>: The great preparations which are made by the Spaniard in the <reg orig="Dutchy">Duchy</reg> of <em>Milan</em> doth give some <reg orig="allarm">alarm</reg> in these parts where there is yet but little done concerning our next <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> expedition, seeming rather to intend a defensive than an offensive war, and to that end the fortifications of the Towns of <em>Verva</em>, and <em>Crescentino</em>, are carried on vigorously, and are near finished.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 13.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris April</em> 18. 1654. The 12 instant the Earl <em>Broglio</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> <em>de la Bassee</em> went from this City to that Town upon intelligence received the Enemy was in a march that way, although since the same hath been contradicted. By the last news from <em>Flanders</em> we hear, That the Earl of <em>Ligneville</em>, who as yet is the Commander in chief of the <em>Lorrain</em> Army which consisteth in 23 Regiments of Horse, and 7 of Foot, making in all about 6000 Men, is upon the march, and came the 12 instant at <em>Owing</em>, and there remained till the <em>Tuesday</em> following, on <em>Wednesday</em> all those forces went over the <em>Escaut</em> upon a bridge made to that effect near <em>Valenciennes</em>, their Train of Artillery and baggage following after, that Evening the said General lodged at <em>Horning</em>, a small Town, and his Army in the Country adjacent. <em>Thursday</em> 16 came to <em>Marchiennes</em>, and so drew out towards the Frontiers, but as yet none can tell their design. The young Lord Son to the Marshal <em>de la Mesteray</em>, hath been sworn to the place of Lieut. General of <em><reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg></em>, after the decease of his Father, as he hath been sworn formerly to that of Master of Artillery likewise in reversion of his Father; this maketh for the going on of the match between this young Lord and one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces, and although daily there is discourse about it, as yet I cannot hear that the work is finished. This 14 last past was acted at the <em><reg orig="Louure">Louvre</reg></em> the stately <em>Italian</em> Comedy, called, the Nuptials of <em>Peleus</em> and <em>Thevis</em>, being a thing of rare invention, and no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> costly; There was a mighty affluence of People, and among others was the little Queen, her Sons, and Daughter with all the Nobility then in Town. Concerning the Prince of <em>Condi</em> he doth now begin to move, but by reason that the Spring hath<pb n="12" /> been backward, therefore he can hardly make as yet any great <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> upon his design by an order from the Council of <em>Spain</em>, the Governor of <em>Artoys</em> called the Earl of <em>Bagsigni</em> is removed from the Castle of <em>Antwerp</em>, to be transferred to another place; The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> doth still remain there likewise a very close prisoner, and there is a strong report that he is to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> Prisoner into <em>Spain</em>, which is <em>malum omen</em>, for the obtaining that liberty which was promised him when he was apprehended, this is like to prove as bad to him, as is already the disposing of all his estate which hath been found in that City, The Marshal <em>Turenne</em> is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> from hence in a few days into <em><reg orig="Picardie">Picardy</reg></em> to take a view of the Army, and set it in a posture fit for a march, he is to have the command in chief of that Army, and I hear that the King will <reg orig="goe">go</reg> likewise and the Cardinal to view all the <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> Towns and Castles in <em><reg orig="Picardie">Picardy</reg></em>, Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em> is also to be the General of another Army which shall be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> as occasion shall serve. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is said also to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>Catalonia</em> in a very short time to be there <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of what we yet <reg orig="possesse">possess</reg> in those parts, and now they are making his equipage ready for the journey, the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is still at <em>Nantes</em>, and a close prisoner in the Castle, no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg> of any <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> to be obtained, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> he will submit to our chief Minister and accept of his Propositions.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> on the Main: We hear from <em>Basil</em> that the Captain <em>Bosman</em> is gone from thence to <em>Paris</em>, where was also arrived shortly after an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> with a Packet for the Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em>, and also for that Captain whereof we know not yet the Contents, seeing that both of them were already gone from that Country: In the interim the <reg orig="Quarter-master">Quartermaster</reg>, General <em>Brachet</em> hath quartered the <em>French</em> forces in the County of <em>Altkerkferdt</em>, and <em>Brandseck</em>, while they have new order from the Court of <em>France</em>: The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Castle of <em>Falbenstein</em> having in a most cruel manner <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> a Ministers house, ruined him and his family out of doors, it so incensed the Country adjacent, that watching their opportunity when one half of the Garrison was absent, they coming at unawares, got <unclear><reg orig="possest">possessed</reg></unclear> of the Gate, and as many as were found in opposition were all<pb n="13" /> put to the Sword, and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> for his cruelty stabbed in his bed.</p>

<p>From <em>Dantzick</em>, The <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> having put themselves under the protection of the Muscovites, have done in a very <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg> and shameful manner, not only in regard of their Church discipline, but likewise concerning the politick and military affairs, having bought a heavy <reg orig="yoak">yoke</reg> on their necks; their new Lord hath already got into his hands three of the principal places in <em><reg orig="Vkraine">Ukraine</reg></em>, and for their better <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, they have divided their Army into three, the first under the great Duke, which is to besiege <em>Smolensko</em>, the other way to enter is designed by <em>Podolia</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the General of the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, and the third party is to go towards <em>Ploskow</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>. The Diet is not yet concluded, there being so much left to be done that it will take up much time the next Diet, in the mean time the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> doth prepare himself to go for <em>Vienna</em>, where having remained some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, he is to go for <em>Hungaria</em>; to be present at the Diet which is to be held at <em>Presburgh</em>, which is not only to reform several things, which are out of frame, but also to put the Country into a posture of defence against the Turks who are very strong upon the Borders, and have already made several inroads into the Country. We hear from <em><reg orig="Friburgh">Fryeburg</reg></em>, that the horse of the Archduke of <em><reg orig="Inspruck">Innsbruck</reg></em> being fallen under him, the said Prince had been very sorely wounded in the head, and that his Subjects were assembled at Tortes, for to conclude among themselves a defensive league against any <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> power that would enter the Country.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday April 14, 15.</i></head>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Rochell">Rochelle</reg></em> by the last Post thus; upon the report of the conclusion of the Treaty between <em>England</em>, and the united Provinces, and that <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> there was a mighty Fleet ready to go to Sea, riding near <em>Portsmouth</em>, the same hath given a strong <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg> along the Coast of <em><reg orig="Brittanny">Brittany</reg></em>, in these parts, as far as the River of <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, each <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Commander of Castles standing much upon their guards, and not only so, but they have likewise sent letters to the Court, not only to demand assistance, but also to know his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure therein.</p><pb n="14" />

<p>From <em>Minehead</em> April 10. Here is little news in these parts, only that the <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> of <em>Brest</em> do much harm in this <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, having of late taken several vessels, whereof some of a considerable value which belonged to <em>Bristol</em>, some of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that were appointed to keep these Seas, being gone towards <em>Dublin</em>, and so to the Westward of <em>Scotland</em>, giveth more <reg orig="libertie">liberty</reg> to these Rogues to commit their <reg orig="villanies">villainies</reg> without any opposition, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> into the very mouth of <em>Severn</em>; there is lately come some Barks from Ireland, who bringeth news, that the plague is well appeased in most parts of that Country, and all things quiet, only a great want of people to manure the ground in many parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 10. I have nothing to add to the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>, but that we are now very quiet in these parts; The party that went from hence towards <em>Kelsay</em>, have secured the parts thereabouts, and the Borders of <em>England</em>, and are <reg orig="Return'd">Returned</reg> with some prisoners: The ship with Ammunition, &amp;c. came yesterday into <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em> road, That about 10 other Merchants were conveyed by the <em>Raven</em>, and the <em>Providence</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Inverness</em>, April 2. Yesterday the Enemy had a general <reg orig="Randezouz">Rendezvous</reg> in <em>Sutherland</em> near <em>Skilbo</em>, they were about 1200 Foot, and 800 Horse, (500 little better <reg orig="then">than</reg> baggage horses, and many wanting pistols) and after the receipt of Orders from Lieut: Generalissimo <em>Middleton</em>, most were to march for the South Highlands, and the rest to continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. <em>Middleton</em> added to their number at the <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about 200 horse and foot, and hath ordered to be levied out of <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> 250. <em>Sutherland</em> 300, <em><reg orig="Cathnesse">Caithness</reg></em> 600, and <em>Stranavar</em> 300. He expects hourly <em>Seaford</em> with 500. and <em>Mackoldwy</em> to be ready with his Levies; He gives out that he hath brought a great store of Spanish gold sent his Master by the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, from whom is expected a great Loan, and many men, which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother-in-law, which he had <reg orig="stayd">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends for his often sailing in his promised coming to them. This day <reg orig="Leiut">Lieut</reg>. Col. <reg orig="Mitchil">Mitchell</reg> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> hither with 9 Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of Horse, and a commanded party 180, with 5 Troops of Dragoons, which are to march <reg orig=" to morrow "> tomorrow </reg> <pb n="15" /> to <em>Brahan</em>, to which are added 4 Troops of horse, and 3 Companies of Foot. The use of the March is to keep a Pass at <em>Dinghill</em>, which by a numerous concurrence of knowing men of the Country, will force them to fight us, stay where they are, or hazard the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of their horse, by length, badness of way, and want of provisions, if they march to the South by the Northwest <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, they having no other way to march otherwise.</p>

<p>From the Isle of <em>Wight</em> the same day. There is no news to impart you since my last, only that our Fleet hath weighed anchor from <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg>-point</em>, and is now come further in, and are now riding in <em>Stoaks</em> Bay, which is not far from the place they were at before, those ships that were gone into <em>Portsmouth</em> to take in their provisions, and to be new fitted for the Sea are near ready, there being no care nor <reg orig="dilegence">diligence</reg> wanting to have the same done with all expedition.</p>

<p>The return of the ratification from the States of <em>Holland</em> is not yet come, but hourly expected, and by several private Letters to Merchants, they all <reg orig="concurr">concur</reg> that the States of <em>Holland</em> have fully ratified the Agreement with great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> in all parts.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is lately published another Volume of the Works of Dr. <em>Jackson</em> Pi&aelig;s. of <em>Corp. Christ.</em> Col. <em>Oxon.</em> Consisting of such new pieces as were never printed before, viz. of the Knowledge of <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, Servants to Sin, and of the Son of God by the exercise of his everlasting Priesthood making us Free from Sin, &amp;c. with other considerable Treaties. Also Three Dissertations in Latin, viz. An <unclear>Alearsit</unclear> Sortitia? De Templis &amp; omni veneratione sacra. De Sanctitate Relativa. By Mr. <em>Joseph Mead</em> sometimes Fellow of <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> College in <em>Cambridge</em>, dedicated to Bishop <em>Andrews</em> and never before published. Both sold by T. <em>Garthwait</em> at the little North-door of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Dr. <em><reg orig="Drakes">Drake's</reg></em> Bar to the Sacrament removed, or a Vindication of Mr. <em><reg orig="Humphreys">Humphreys'</reg></em> Free Admission to the Sacrament: wherein the most materials in Dr. <em>Drake</em> are <reg orig="answer'd">answered</reg>; with a Speech to them of the Congregational way, and an Examination of the Scripture Rail made by some Ministers in <em><reg orig="Glocester-shire">Gloucestershire</reg></em>, done by <em>Jo. Timson</em>, And are to be sold by <em>Tho. Williams</em> at the Bible in Little Brittan.</p>

<p><em>Cyrus le Grand</em>, the entire Story, done into English by a person of quality, and dedicated to the late King. Also <em>Bethel</em>, or a form for Families, in which all sorts of both Sexes are so <reg orig="squard">squared</reg> and framed by the word, as they may best served in their several places for <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> pieces in <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Building. By <em>Matthew Griffith</em>: Both of them printed for <em>William Hope</em> at the <reg orig="Blew">Blue</reg> Anchor on the backside of the Royal Exchange.</p>

<p>The Art of Cookery <reg orig="Refind">Refined</reg> and augmented, collected from the practise of that incomparable Master of these Arts Mr. <em>Jos. Cooper</em> chief Cook to the late King, Printed for <em>R. Lownds</em> at the White <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg> in St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Censure upon Recusants, that refuse the Sacrament of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Supper. By <em>Tho. <reg orig="Marshal">Marshall</reg></em> Minister. Printed for <em>Francis Coles</em> in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>