<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc171">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 171</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The Letters from the States General of Holland to His Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, concerning the Articles of Peace, and the day when the same shall be Proclaimed both in England and Holland. The Declaration of General Middleton to the Highlanders at their late general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and the coming in of their new Levies upon his Summons. The great Preparations that are making for War in most places of <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>, and their Designs. With Letters from Ireland, and choice Intelligence from several other parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> April 12. to <em>Wednesday</em> April 19. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>April 12</em>.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from Ireland it is certified, that <reg orig="al">all</reg> things are very quiet, yet the Tories continue their old trade of filching and stealing as bad as ever, according to their power; therefore all the benefit we have more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary, is, that their number is much less <reg orig="then">than</reg> once it was.</p>

<p>From Amsterdam they write, that the Deputies of the several Provinces were met together in order to the confirmation of the peace betwixt England and them, and that the Deputies have signed and sealed the Articles whereof more in the last <reg orig="days">day's</reg> intelligence.</p><pb n="1" />

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April 6. The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> is all we have of news here, but we expect <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> to hear something from Col. Morgan, who is marched towards <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg> with a considerable party. The Country is exceeding much broken in most parts, but the news of the consummation of the Peace will much startle them.</p>

<p><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg> March 27. Glencarn and Kenmore having joined with Glengarry and Athol marched within 7 or 8 miles of this <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> last into <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>, being about 2000 horse and foot; they are drawing towards Sutherland to meet with Middleton and his party, with whom they expect to join; the Lord Lorn with 500 foot and 100 horse intends to follow them, he is now about Abertaf, twenty four miles from this place, in the Rear of him follows Mac Usdow, with what force he can make, so that shortly their whole force will be North of us, and what may then be effected upon them, we must leave to the disposing of the Almighty.</p>

<p>Paris April 18, 1654. The 12 instant the Earl Broglio <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> de la Bassee went from this City to that Town upon intelligence received the Enemy was in a march that way, although since the same hath been contradicted. By the last news from Flanders we hear, That the Earl of Ligneville, who as yet is the Commander in chief of the Lorrain Army, which consisteth in 23 Regiments of horse and 7 of Foot, making in all about 6000 men, is upon the march, and came the 12 instant at Owing, and there remained till the Tuesday following, on Wednesday all those forces went over the Escaut upon a bridge made to that effect near Valenciennes, their Train of Artillery, and baggage following after, that Evening the said General lodged at Horning, a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Town, and his Army in the Country adjacent. Thursday: 6 they came to Marchiennes, and so drew out towards the Frontiers.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>The young Lord Son to the Marshal de la Mesteray, hath been sworn to the place of <reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. General of Brittany, after the decease of his father, as he hath been sworn formerly to that of Master of Artillery likewise in reversion of his Father; this maketh for the going on of the match between this young Lord and one of the Cardinals Nieces, and although <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> there is discourse about it, as yet I cannot here that the work is finished.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday April 13.</head>

<p>Further from Paris April 20. The Prince of Condi doth now begin to move, but by reason that the Spring hath been backward, therefore he can hardly make as hath been backward, therefore he can hardly make as yet any great progress, upon his design by an Order from the Council of Spain, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Artoys called the Earl of Bassigni is removed from the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Spain, the Governor of Artoys called the Earl of Bassigni is removed from the Castle of Antwerp, to be transferred to another place, the Duke of Lorrain doth still remain there likewise a very close prisoner, and there is a strong report that he is to be carried prisoner, and there is a strong report that he is to be carried a prisoner into Spain, which is <em>malum olem</em>, for the obtaining that liberty which was promised him when he was apprehended, this is like to prove as bad to him, as is already the disposing of all his estate which hath been found in that City, The Marshal Turen is to go from hence in a few days into Picardy to take a view of the Army, and set it in a posture fit for a march, he is to have the command in chief of that Army, and I hear that the King will go likewise and the Cardinal to view all the frontier Towns and Castles in Piccardy, Marshal de la Ferte is also to be the General of another Army, which shall be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> as occasion shall serve.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, April 14.</head>

<p>By the last Post from Rochel we have received advertisement, That the Treaty between England and the United Provinces of the Low <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> being concluded, the report thereof, and of a mighty English Fleet ready to go to Sea, riding near Portsmouth, the whole <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> thereabouts took a strong alarm, every <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Commander of Port, Castle, and Fort, causing strong guard to kept, fearing lest the said fleet should have any Design to land some forces there; they likewise sent to the Court to know his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure therein, and to desire assistance in case his Majesty shall think the same requisite; what the issue will be, we as yet know not.</p>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>, dated April 4, thus. Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Mitchel">Mitchell</reg> marched hither with 9 Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of Horse, and a commanded party of about 180, with 5 troops of Dragoons, which marched yesterday to Brahan, to which 4 troops of horse and 3 companies of foot are added. The cause of this march is to keep a Pass at Dinghill, which in the judgement of many knowing men of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, will constrain them either to fight with us, stay in the place where they now are, or run the hazard of losing their horse, by length, badness of way, and want of provisions, in case they march by the <reg orig="North-west">Northwest</reg> hills to the South, one or other of which exigencies they cannot avoid. The Enemy had a general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> on the first of this instant, near the Castle of Skilbo in Southerland, where (as they give out) appeared between 4 and 5000 horse and foot; but upon better information, we hear they were not fully 3000, viz. about 1600 foot, and about 1000 horse, the one half of which are very unfit for the service of war, and many not half armed, some wanting swords, and some pistols. Middleton added to their number about 200 horse and foot. At this <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> Middleton declared; That he had brought some good quantity of gold with him into Scotland, which he said the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of Germany had lent his Master, and that the said Emperor was raising a far greater sum, and a great number of men, which be said he would have staid and brought with him, but that he heard there was some discontent among his friends, arising from his often failing in his promised <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to them; He then exhorted them to prosecute the work they had in hand effectually, and to use their uttermost <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to enforce the enemy to depart the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</p>

<p>After this he gave Order, that the most of them should march for the South Highlands, and the rest continue in the North, and both to go<pb n="4" /> on vigorously to prosecute their new Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. He hath likewise ordered 250 to be levied out of Ross, 300 out of Sutherland, Caithness 600, and Stranarvar 300. He hourly expects Seafort with 500 men, and Mackoldwy to be ready with his Levies.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, April 15.</head>

<p>From Minehead, April 10. Here is at present but little news in these parts, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, The <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> who lurk in Brest, though at first something startled by the loss of Captain Beach, yet are grown bold again, and have of late done much harm in the Channel, having taken several vessels belonging to Bristol, some of which are of great value; the absence of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which were appointed to guard these seas, being gone towards Dublin, and so to the Westward of Scotland, give, opportunity to these Rogues to commit these Robberies without fears who now adventure to come into the very mouth of Severn.</p>

<p>The last Letters from Dublin, and other places in Ireland, <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, That the plague is pretty <reg orig="wel">well</reg> appeased in most parts of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and nothing wanting but Inhabitants to manure the ground in many places.</p>

<p>From the Isle of Wight, April 13. There is no news to impart you since my last, only that our fleet weighed anchor from St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point, and is now come further in, and are now riding in Stokes Bay, which is not far from the place they were at before; those ships that were gone to Portsmouth to take in their provisions, and to be new fitted for the Sea, are near ready, there being no care nor diligence wanting to have the same done with expedition.</p>

<p>The return of the Ratification from the States of Holland is not yet come, but hourly expected, and by several private Letters to Merchants, they all concur, that the States of Holland have fully ratified the Agreement with great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> in all parts.</p>

<p>From Naples it is certified, That the Vice-King is providing 4000 suits of <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, 1800 shirts, 2000 swords, and as many hats, shoes and stockings; he hath caused to made many shovels, and such like tools for <reg orig="Pioniers">Pioneers</reg>, and 30 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of new Brass Ordnance; all these things are to be sent will all <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> to Catalonia; he hath likewise sent to Spain for 6000 Spaniards, who shall be dispersed into several <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> of that Kingdome, and those that are now in them, shall be drawn into the field for servicer.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 12.</head>

<p>From <reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg> on the Main: We hear from <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg> that Captain Bisman is gone from thence to Paris, where was also arrived shortly after an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> with a Packet for the Marshal de la Ferte, and also for that Captain, whereof we know not yet the Contents, seeing that both of them were already gone from that Country: In the Interim <reg orig="Quarter-master">Quartermaster</reg> General Brachet hath quartered the French forces in the County of Altherkferdt, and Brandseck, while they have new order from the Court of France: The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Castle of Falkenstein having in a most cruel manner plundered a <reg orig="Ministers">Minister's</reg> house, turned him and his family out of <reg orig="dores">doors</reg>, it so incensed the Country adjacent that watching their opportunity when the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> was half absent, they <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> at unawares got possession of the gate, and as many as were found in opposition were all put to the sword, and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> for his cruelty stabbed in his bed.</p>

<p>From Dantzick, the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> having put themselves under the protection of the Muscovites, have done it in a very <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg> and <reg orig="shamefull">shameful</reg> manner, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in regard of their Church discipline, but likewise concerning the politick and military Affairs, having brought a heavy yoke on their necks; their new Lord hath already got into his hands three of the principal places in <reg orig="Ukrain">Ukraine</reg>, and for their better <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, they have divided their Army into three, the first under the great Duke, which is to besiege Smolensko, the other way to enter is by Podolia, to join with the General of the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, and the third party is to go towards Ploskow.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>. The Diet is not yet concluded, there being so much left to be done, that it will take up much time the next Diet, in the mean time the Emperor doth prepare himself to go for Vienna, where having remained<pb n="6" /> some few days, he is to go for Hungaria; to be present at the Diet which is to be held at Presburgh, which is not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to reform several things which are out of frame, but also to put the country into a posture of defence against the Turks, who are very strong upon the Borders, and have already made several inroads into the Country. We hear from <reg orig="Friburgh">Freiberg</reg>, that the horse of the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> of <reg orig="Inspruck">Innsbruck</reg> being fallen under him, the said Prince had been very sorely wounded in the head, and that his Subjects were assembled at Tortes, for to conclude a defensive League against any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> power that would enter the Country.</p>

<p>From Milan, The new levies in Germany, as also in the Country of the Grisons, are almost finished, and there doth daily come in some of them, who are forthwith provided with quarters by the several Officers sent upon our <reg orig="Frontires">Frontiers</reg>, for that purpose; there hath likewise passed near this place 400 men, who are going towards Casal for the <reg orig="strengthning">strengthening</reg> of that <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>.</p>

<p>From Venice thus. Generalissimo Moccenigo is now almost ready to go for Candia, and besides what we have formerly spoken, he is to carry with him those ships that were hired at Leghorn for the service of this State. We hear from Dalmatia, that the Turks have lately made an <reg orig="inrode">inroad</reg> at Narrata, where they have taken much cattle, and made many persons prisoners. General Delfino goeth on in his design to besiege Clim, which is built by the Turks on this side the Mountains, being very strong, and made their chief Magazine. The Dukes of Florence, Parma, and Modena are all of them very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> raising of men, but upon what design is not yet known.</p>

<p>Letters from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> say, that the City of Glurkstadt is much displeased, that the King of Denmark approached to their Walls with 30 or 40 horse.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, April 18.</head>

<p>A return came yesterday from Holland, concerning the signing and sealing of the Articles of Peace, and the Ratification by the States General of the seven United Provinces; as also the day which they have prefixed for Proclaiming the said Articles of Peace in Holland, at which time the same will likewise be Proclaimed in England: All which His Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have debated of, and all things here go on in a way of Love, and sweet harmony of Peace, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> with Holland and Denmark, but also with France, Sweden, Portugal, and other <reg orig="Kingdomes">Kingdoms</reg>.</p>

<p>From Newcastle they write, That there is a great Fleet of Coals ready laden, and bound for London, they make some small stay in hopes the Peace will be confirmed and Proclaimed betwixt England and Holland; and after that it is expected out Fleet should scour the Narrow seas of all the <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> and Freebooters, who of late have done much mischief in these parts.</p>

<p>The former subject should have been more enlarged, if another Letter from Scotland had not in this interim of time come to my hands, the contents whereof is as followeth.</p>

<p><em>SIR</em>, You have before this received the Intelligence of a late <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of General Middleton (as they call him) and the rest of the Enemy in the Highlands, with their numbers and equipage. That which remains is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> this: Here is great joy amongst the English which heard of your last Letter, which gave us to understand, That General Monk is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> hither; for the very name of him strikes the Enemy into the very heart and bowels; and if we may <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> some of their Officers lately taken prisoners, the enemy fear nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the face of General Monk; for (say they) if we refuse to accept of such conditions he brings, <reg orig="then">than</reg> nothing can be expected but fire and sword.</p>

<p>The new Levies appointed to be raised in the places before mentioned in a former Letter, came not in according to the Summons sent out by Glencarn and Middleton, which is no small discouragement unto them: Yet their numbers have been sufficient to spend their provisions, the exhausting whereof will necessitate them shortly to an Engagement, which is that we daily long for, and their cow hearted spirits tremble to think of.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop 1654</em>.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>