<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc176">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 176</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> particulars.</head>

<p><i>The <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of the Armies in Scotland. The <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> with the Highlanders, and Gen. Middleton's brother taken prisoner, and other held Officers, also the further resolution of Gen. Monk, and his firing and destroying the houses of such as have relieved the enemy. The number of the English fleet at their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and the honourable enterprises they are now going upon. The particulars of the proceedings of the French against the English at St. <reg orig="Malloes">Mallows</reg>, as it is under examination. The returning of the L. <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> out of Sweden. With variety of intelligence.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em>, May 17. to <em>Wednesday</em>, May 24. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, May 17.</i></head>

<p>Came Letters from Scotland, thus, Gen. <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg> is gone to Dalkieth, in order to the drawing his main forces together, and to take the field against the Enemy: He is resolved to fire and destroy some places and houses which have been receptacles of parties of the enemy to lie lurking in all the day time and then sally forth and do mischief in the night; which is the best way to deal with a people so inexorable, or incorrigible as we find many of this Nation to be. Order is taken to disperse Gen. <reg orig="Moncks">Monk's</reg> Declaration before him, and if it work not<pb n="1" /> such effect as it ought, yet it will carry that force with it, that none shall plead ignorance; and being a thing of great concernment, we cannot omit it here.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in Chief of all the Forces in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England having used all the means of tenderness and affection toward the People of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> War into Union with England, and investing them with all the Liberties and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much <reg orig="Bloud">Blood</reg> and Treasure) and daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more than equal proportion with England) against their enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace: Yet divers lewd persons, broken in their fortunes, and dissolute in their lives, are run into Rebellion; and being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Brethren, Tutors, Masters, and people among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder the Country, <reg orig="wherby">whereby</reg> the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof, I by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the authority to me given by his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, do declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 days after publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby freely pardoned for any offence, spoil, or plunder committed by him or them in this present Rebellion (the killing of any<pb n="2" /> person in cold <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> excepted.) And I do declare, that if any Parents, Brethren, or Tutors, who have assisted and connived at any their Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within 20 days after publication hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, to render themselves, and give security as aforesaid, That then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are hereby freely pardoned; but if otherwise, then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion. And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion without the knowledge or consent of some of the inhabitants of that Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived before their breaking forth: I do therefore hereby declare, that if the said parish or presbytery, where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth, to render him or themselves within 20 days after publication hereof, and give security as aforesaid, that then the said parish or presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned: But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said parish or presbytery, 2s, 6d, a day for each <reg orig="horsman">horseman</reg>, and 10d. a day for each footman so broken into rebellion, over and above their ordinary Sess, out of the said presbytery, which the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> is authorized to levy, and receive monthly during the time the said persons shall so continue in rebellion. And I do likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into rebellion, or attempt so to do, and safely to deliver him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>; and in case of resistance, to take such weapons as they can get, and to<pb n="3" /> fight the said person or persons; and if they shall kill any of the said persons so resisting, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive as reward of their good service, all such moneys, goods, horses and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg>, as the said rebellious persons are then possessed of, besides full satisfaction for their pains and travel therein. And in regard this present rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General Middleton, the Earl of Athol, the Earl of Seaforth, Viscount Kenore, Donald <reg orig="Mac Donald">McDonald</reg> Laird of Glengary, and Major General Dayel, I do hereby therefore declare, That what person or persons soever of this Nation (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> he or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but shall also receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of 200 l. sterling, for every person so killed or brought prisoner, as aforesaid. And lastly for the encouragement of all peaceable and well affected people both English and Scots, I do also hereby declare, That what damage shall be done to their persons, goods, or <reg orig="geer">gear</reg>, for their good affection to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, that same shall be again repaired out of the Estates of the friends and harbourers of such <reg orig="wrong doers">wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the parish, presbytery, or shire where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said offenders, or give the English forces such timely notice thereof, that the said offenders may be apprehended by them. And I do hereby require all Provosts, Bailiffs, and chief Officers of Head Burghs, in their several Burghs, to cause these presents to be duly published and posted up, according to the usual form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me in writing under his or their hands.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Given under my hand at Dalkieth, this 4 day of May, 1654.</i></head>
<head level="3">GEO. MONCK</head>

<head level="3">Thursday May 18.</head>

<p>This day the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> had audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at Whitehall, with the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> Ceremonies and formalities.</p>

<p>The Letters from Upsal in Sweden say, that the Articles of Peace between England and that Crown are signed and sealed by her Majesty, and that my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> is returning again for England.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>The Packet boat coming form England was taken by a <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> and the Passengers all robbed and abused.</p>

<p>Gen. Pen went to the Fleet upon the Downs, they write that the number of our Fleet when they came together, was at least 140 sail.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> May 19.</head>

<p><reg orig="Rochel">Rochelle</reg> 14 May. We have news that the English Fleet the last week at their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> on the Downs were 150 sail. Our fears are great here in France (as our preparations <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> manifest) some are of opinion you will rather revenge an injury done further off, and steer your course to Legorn, then shall fall upon your next neighbours first. That which most amazeth us is, that you impress more men, and put your whole Fleet is so high a warlike posture: we are informed you have <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> mortar pieces, great numbers of spades, pickaxes, <reg orig="wheel barrows">wheelbarrows</reg>, and other things necessary for land service.</p>

<p>Dalkeith May 9. The General marcheth <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> from Dalkeith towards <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, and from thence to some of our frontier <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> and so to the fields. The Proclamation you had before he sendeth out as a <reg orig="fore-runner">forerunner</reg>, which will probably effect something considerable; Middleton continues still in <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg>, with some broken Regiments, which as intelligence <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, rather decline than increase in number. Glencarn hath made his way over the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, through some obsolete path, with a small party of horse, who purposeth if he can to join with Athol and Glengary, and make a body. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan is still about Tane, watching every <reg orig="opportunitie">opportunity</reg> to come to engage them, if possible.</p>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, May 11. We have as yet little of news, General Monk hath yesterday removed his <reg orig="Head quarters">Headquarters</reg> from Dalkeith to <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> from whence he intends, after securing of some new passes, to take field: We beat the enemy in all parties that engage, we have lately taken <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> brother, and 5 or 6 Officers more, and routed that party. General <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg> hath hanged two of them already as spies burnt an <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg> in Muscleborough that harboured them, and is resolved to scour them, as you may perceive by his Proclamation.</p>

<p>Guernsey Island, May 12, 1654. The Hector <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> attending without St. Malo divers days, for conveying the English from thence, who are still detained under the arrest, a shallop was sent out of the Town to tell the Captain that the English should have all freedom: but this was found to be <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> a Decoy, to draw him in, and so not trusted.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>Further from Jersey we understand, that some ships of ours lying near St. <reg orig="Malloes">Mallo's</reg>, about 60 of the men (greedy to get fresh victuals) went ashore into the Country, and <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg> to drive away some <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg>, but the country rising, rescued them, and fell upon the <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg>, and killed several of them, and pursued them to two of our ships which were left ashore by the going out of the Tide. This gave an <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> to St Mallo's, who thereupon brought down Ordnance to batter the ships, which they <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg> to do, but did them little hurt; the Tide coming in, the ships got off, and the <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> ceased. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. <reg orig="Malloes">Mallo's</reg> apprehending this to be a design against the Town, took an occasion to turn out all the English Merchants, and <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> upon all their houses, wares and goods, and hath made himself Master of what was theirs. The truth of this <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is now under examination, and the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> hath this week had audience thereupon, the results upon the whole you shall have in my next.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> May 20.</head>

<p>From Paris 19 May, <em>stilo novo</em>. Their <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> being newly returned to this City, some few days they were devoted to feasting and visits, and amongst the rest of persons of note which came to visit the Court, there was the late Queen of England, the titular King of Scots, and the Dukes of York and <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>. There was acted at night a very famous Comedy called <em>Peleus</em> and <em>Thetis</em>.</p>

<p>Yesterday was a Treaty at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> with the Denmark <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> May 22,</head>

<p>The Lo. Mayor of London set forth a Proclamation for the better observation of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day.</p>

<p>The Declaration of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector<pb n="6" /> for keeping Tuesday next a day of Thanksgiving, was published in the Churches yesterday.</p>

<p>Also in the Churches in Surrey was published an Order made by the Justices of the Peace at the Sessions, for the better observation of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day, which is a very good example for all other Magistrates whatsoever to follow.</p>

<p>From Regensburgh. There is now daily expected the conclusion of our Diet, the Members thereof having agreed before they dissolve that assembly, to meet again that time 2 years, to determine such affairs which could not be agreed upon this Diet, and are of too great consequence to be done in an <reg orig="inferiour">inferior</reg> Assembly.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg>. This City, and that of Lubeck, have sent Commissioners to Bremen, to make some overtures for an accommodation between them and the Crown of Sweden, in the mean time the circle of lower Saxony <reg orig="indeavoureth">endeavoureth</reg> that the Swedes may cease all acts of hostility in that County.</p>

<p>By Letters from Cullen we are to understand. Although by the Treaty of Munster it was agreed that upon the payment of certain <reg orig="summes">sums</reg> of money to the Swedes, they should them deliver up unto the Bishop of Munster the <reg orig="strong hold">stronghold</reg> of Wecht, yet hitherto it could not be effected, the Swedish Commander in that place, having received those <reg orig="summes">sums</reg> which were due unto that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and the other <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> agreed upon being sent to Oldenburght to be paid upon the surrender of the place, <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> new difficulties arise, which puts the business in a doubtful condition.</p>

<p>Our <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> is now gone to Kerpen a Castle which he hath lately bought of the Spaniard, for a great sum of money.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday May 23.</head>

<p>This day was solemnly observed as a day of Thanksgiving for the happy peace concluded with the Dutch. His Highness the Lord Protector kept it in his <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg> at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>; and at St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> London there was the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Sheriffs and Aldermen of the City of London in their Scarlet Robes and the Twelve Companies all in their Livery Gowns, and Mr. Obadiah <reg orig="Sedgewick">Sedgwick</reg> prayed and preached. After Sermon ended, they feasted and gave thanks together at their respective Halls, and the day concluded with ringing of Bells, Bonfires, Fireworks, and other expressions of joy befitting this happy solemnity: And it is observable, that people did more cordially <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> now at a lasting Peace, <reg orig="then">than</reg> before for a Deliverance after very great and eminent Victories, for that we gained nothing that way without much <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> spilling.</p>

<p>This Post from Scotland brought us intelligence that General <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg> is resolved to bring down the proud and haughty spirits of those Rebellious persons now in Arms against us. They might have lived quietly if they had delighted themselves in peace and amity; but in regard they have made choice of the contrary, they are like to have their bellies full of war; for where lenity will not at all penetrate, force and rigour are made to subdue and overcome.</p>

<p>We have met with several parties of the enemy, and although they themselves acknowledge, that they make choice of the ablest and best fighting men to go forth upon parties, yet it is our good hap (or rather providence to ordereth it) to worst them all, though oftentimes they far exceed us in number. They brag and boast much notwithstanding, and say they dare fight us with their whole Army in the field, could they draw them once together: but what I think will not be in <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> for some of them are but in the <reg orig="middest">midst</reg> of their Levies.</p>

<p>It is thought we shall engage Middleton very shortly, or drive him further back upon the Mountains: Yet it may be we shall not move far after them, until we hear that the forces are landed in the North, which are designed thither from Ireland.</p>

<p>We hear from Poland, that General Chimeluiski and the Cossacks are already weary of the Muscovite and desire aid of the Tartars.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>