<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc157">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 157</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, the Navy at Sea, and other transactions of, and in relation to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> January 4. to <em>Wednesday</em> January 11. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, January 4.</head>

<p>There have been many various reports concerning the Lord Whitlock, who is gone <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> for Sweden: He was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon the account of the late Parliament, which dissolved themselves; and since that, some of the adverse party have given forth in speeches, that he was stabbed or killed: Now that the world may take notice what such discontented spirits may utter in a case of such consequence, be pleased to take a true relation, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> passage, but his safe arrival there, as it came from a known hand, in near <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> to his Honour.</p>

<head level="3">SIR</head>

<p>We began to set sail from Gravesend, Novemb. 6. but the wind <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> too much into the North, and being not able to get clear of the sands that day, we were enforced to cast anchor near Quinborow; The next day, the wind standing fair, we set sail again, and <pb n="1" /> made a very large course, until about noon the day after, at which time the wind turned full against us, so that we were afraid that we should have been necessitated to put into Yarmouth Road. But the wind favoured us again for a little time, and we made forwards, yet it was not long ere we were very much becalmed; and so we were exercised with uncertainties of winds until the 12 instant, when there came a very fair wind, which carried us on with full sail, so that on the 14 instant at night we cast anchor on this side the Scagen, and we came on the 15 betimes in the River.</p>

<p>As we came along our ship met with some Holland Fishermen, and boarded one of them, but my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> willing to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> peaceably over the sea, released it again, which did exceedingly overjoy them, who had been undone in his own thoughts before; yet the Elizabeth, being one of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that carried some of our Company, staying behind to bring up one of the Baggage ships, met with a small Dutch Caper, and boarded it, and brought it along with them. We were not altogether without rough and stormy weather, especially the last night, when we anchored at the Scagen, insomuch that we were afraid we should have lost one of the Baggage ships, which was but very slenderly provided with tacklings, yet (through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God) we were all come safe, and there is none sick amongst us, nor any thing lost; As soon as ever we were come into the River, being weary of the sea, we made <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to the shore, so that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Magistrates of the town could not be ready to give us that solemn reception as they intended. The next day the three Presidents, with the Magistrate, came to salute my Lord in a very handsome Equipage, and one of them made a Speech to him in <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, wherein he acquainted his Lordship, That they had <pb n="2" /> received positive commands from the Queen to demonstrate all respects to the English <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, whom she had received notice would arrive here in a short time; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> desired his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> excuse, that they were not prepared to give him a more pompous entertainment at his first landing. Afterwards the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> came to give his Salutation, which he performed with great civility and respect. And indeed they are very ready to accommodate us in any thing, and to give us all possible help and assistance in our intended <reg orig="journy">journey</reg> towards the Court. The Queen is at present at Upsalia, but we are uncertain whether she intends to <reg orig="recide">reside</reg> there all this winter; it is supposed that she may return again to Stockholm, there dying but two of the <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg> the last week; our journey thither will be very tedious and chargeable; and we now begin to find experience that those that are <reg orig="imploied">employed</reg> upon such solemn Missions into so barren a Country, must needs be supplied with a very large purse: After that we have refreshed <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, and rested our horses here for a few days, we shall begin our journey, having already sent Letters to the Court of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> arrival; we must be <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to carry all our baggage by land; the Presidents of the City after consultation had amongst themselves giving us this advice, which will be a very vast charge.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Guttenburgh, November,</em>18, 1653</head>

<head level="3">Thursday, January 5.</head>

<p>Weymouth 2 Jan. 1653. A Jersey vessel went Saturday last out of this Harbour homewards, but the same nigh a very great storm rose at Sea, and brought the ship back again upon our Coast, where she was cast away in the West-bay between Portland and Rotberry all the men being cast away but the shipman and two passengers that were <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> going over to Jersey or Guernsey</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>From Milford Haven, Jan. 2. There are several Vessels here bound for Ireland, but stayed here by reason of the contrary winds; we have not of late heard any news from thence: The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> are full plying about the Isle of Lundy, and often come into the Severn mouth, where sometimes they catch some of our small vessels.</p>

<p>There is nothing more from our Fleet, but that part of them are about Plymouth, and other places to the Westward, some be out towards the coast of Brittany, to try whether they can meet the Brest men of War, who have now got good ships, and have a considerable strength at Sea.</p>

<p>This week arrived the fleet from Dunkirk consisting of about 40 sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as silks wrought and unwrought <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg>, <reg orig="thred">thread</reg> &amp;c. There is come likewise 5 ships from the East-land, as also one from Zant with Currans, but as yet not come up the River.</p>

<p>The Dutch Commissioners, whom we mentioned before to be gone to Gravesend in order to take shipping for Holland, have not yet set sail, but remain there, and have some further application to his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> which whether or no it will occasion their <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> back again to make absolute Agreement, a short time will discover.</p>

<p>By several Letters from Holland yesterday, we had the certain Intelligence, That upon Tuesday last was sevennight they had about Amsterdam, a most <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> Thunder, Lightning and Tempest, (as about the same time we had by other letters was the like at <reg orig="Pembrook">Pembroke</reg> in Wales) and that by this Thunder and Lightning there were about 500 houses burned and destroyed in and near Amsterdam, besides above 40 <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships sunk in the Texel, and many other great damages, the particulars whereof you shall have further by the next, when a more exact <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> comes.</p>

<p>Dalkeith Decemb. 29. Major <reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg> <unclear>pa<!--approx 6 characters-->d</unclear> light upon Sir Arthur Forbs upon <reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> last, had not <unclear>a <!--approx 12 characters-->Pebbles</unclear> sent him notice of our parties <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> thither, he being then at the Kirk of Atterick very sore wounded, yet upon hearing of their approach marched towards the Hills, his number being <unclear>th<!--approx 5 characters--> made</unclear> 70 horse by the occasion of one Capt. Steward with 20 horse, our men took two more of them also, who were in the former fight, and took one Moss-Trooper also.</p>

<p>The enemy have now a garrison in Roldeu about ten miles from <pb n="4" />Dunbarton, from whence they came commanded by one Colgrave, with about 80 foot last week to Dunbarton, and in the dead of the night took two of the Bailiffs and other principal men of the town to the number of 36, whom they threaten to keep till they send in 4 horsemen, and 37 footmen for their levies.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Jan. 6.</head>

<p>From Paris, Janua. 10. 1654, <em>stilo novo</em>. The last news from our Army in Alsatia imply, That the Marshal de la Ferte hath invested <unclear>B stort</unclear>, and is now making his Lines of Communication, and other works belonging to a siege; there hath been several pieces of <reg orig="Ordnance">Ordinance</reg> drawn out of Nancy, which are on the way, and will come to the Leaguer as soon as any <unclear>batteries</unclear> will be raised to plant them upon; the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> de <unclear>Uxeiles</unclear> is to be Lieutenant General, and is expected to be there with 3000 men. This design hath much alarmed the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so much the more, since the <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up of the strong Castle of Philipsburgh, which was taken by a surprisal without the loss of one, the manner thus, The Deputy Governor being gone a hunting with <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg><reg orig="som">some</reg> of the high Officers of that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, notice being given to one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> creatures, he <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg> with alacrity that occasion, and being come into the place, he so prevailed upon the <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, that he became Master of the place, and this Deputy <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> being come in the evening, knowing not what had passed, found the bridge drawn up, and entrance denied him; whereupon he was forced to retire speedily. The Duke d'Amville being sent by the King to Blois, to try once more whether he could prevail with the Duke of Orleans, and to bring him again to the Court, returned back this week, and the report is at Court, that he hath brought a very good answer, and that he will be shortly in this City, but others are of a contrary opinion. The Duke de Guise is still going on in his preparations for his intended design for Naples against the next Spring.</p>

<p>The States assembled in Provence are now sitting at Bagnolle, where the Duke of Mercoeur the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and the other Procurators are also gone: they sit daily, and hope to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> many abuses, and <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> <reg orig="greivances">grievances</reg> which much <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> the people there. The Charge of High Treason against the Prince of Conde is finished, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> it wants to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>. The Prince hath <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> a little Town and a Castle in Champagne, and plundered the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> <reg orig="pittifully">pitifully</reg>. A List hath been brought to his Majesty of the Regiment of the Guard, which is found to consist of about 6000 men fit for service.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3">Saturday, January 7.</head>

<p>The Commissioners for Creditors and poor prisoners sit constantly at <reg orig="Salters">Salters'</reg> Hall, and have done much good during the time of their sitting.</p>

<p>From France the Letters say, that there be 26 Articles of High Treason drawn up against the Prince of Conde, and though he was once so exceeding popular that he was for a time able to maintain a war against the King; yet now he is fallen from the top of that slippery <reg orig="Pinacle">Pinnacle</reg> on which he <reg orig="climed">climbed</reg>, there be but few that can afford him a good word.</p>

<p>Further from Holland, thus. We daily expect 150 ships from the Sound, several Men of War are gone for their Convoy. The Ordnance brought from Sweden have been <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> at Amsterdam, there are 500 pieces, most part half Cartows. Captain Nicholas Pater hath taken an English Ketch before Hull, another at Flamboroughhead; a Flute of 12 Guns, and 4 of Wood, of about 130 Lasts, with Hemp, Flax, Coals, and some Salt-peter. Also near Whitebay a Pinnace of fix Guns, with refined Salt, and one by the Hover, laden with Salmon, Sheep skins, and Herrings; but the loss of Captain Hans <reg orig="Margarens">Margaren's</reg> ship, a man of War with 18 guns, which we hear the English have taken near Newcastle, is worth almost all these; and we hear of eight ships taken from the Caribes, with Sugar, Tobacco, and other <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>, with their Convoy of thirty guns. Eight of the <reg orig="New-found-land">Newfoundland</reg> Fleet we took, are made men of War. We have taken a Turkish ship and another in Smyrna. One Goldshalk hath rowed an English prize of 12 Guns into Brest. An English <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> met with 5 French ships of St. <reg orig="Mallo">Malo</reg>, took one called the Year of Grace, the Three Kings hardly escaped, not yet heard of, the other three are at Calice.</p>

<p>Cornelius Joast, with Thymen <unclear>Theancase</unclear>, with the <pb n="6" />Ammunition are safely arrived from hence in Muscovia.</p>

<p>By Letter from several parts beyond the seas, we hear, That there is like to be hot War by Russia and Muscovia against Poland, and is already proclaimed in Muscovia, and the Deputies are sending to all the Princes in <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg> about it. One Army (and the biggest) is marched from Muscovia, towards Smolonsko, and so on in the County; The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> will be there in person. A second commanded by Field-Marshal Bows, Petrootts, Sermotoft, and Semon, Gock, Janovies, Streesnop, go from Blascow in Rusland with 40000 men, amongst which 20000 well <reg orig="treined">trained</reg> Russians. The third of 30000 from Potien, to the help of the Zaporasse Cossacks.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 9.</head>

<p>This day the great calamity in Holland was again confirmed; it is affirmed that the Lightning leaping from the clouds, when the Thunder chid, the Houses began to take fire, and that 500 of them suddenly were devoured by it. At the same time the wind arising, the Billows in vast tumults began to move towards the Town, as if they made <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to put out the fire. By the high workings of the Sea the <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> did presage the danger to come, and therefore used all their art and care to keep their ships at a distance, lest in the <reg orig="foulnesse">foulness</reg> of the weather, they should fall foul on one another, but their diligence could not make that quick dispatch, before a most violent gust clapped them together, and being involved in one danger, about 40 of them did suffer in one <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>

<p>But others (to whom rather I incline) do affirm, that the fire was four miles from Amsterdam, at their rope <reg orig="mils">mills</reg>, where were their stores both of Hemp, and Oil, which served to increase the flame, 400 houses are said to be there burned, and about 30 ships sunk by the Tempest.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, January 10.</head>

<p>By this Post from Scotland it was certified, that, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a pretended Commission from <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, Glencarn, whom the Highlanders call their General, issueth forth Warrants for the levying of men, horse and arms in a high nature, beginning thus.</p>

<p><em>James, Earl of Glencarn and Kenmore &amp;c.</em> These are straightly to charge and command you, to levy and have in readiness out of your <reg orig="Shierdome">Shiredom</reg>, 100 horse well manned and armed, by the <unclear><!--approx 5 characters--></unclear> day of January; at which time you shall receive further Orders from me, to repair to such place of <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> as shall be appointed: Whereof you are not to fail, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<p>Our men are drawn forth of <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and other <reg orig="garisons">garrisons</reg>, and are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in chasing the enemy from place to place, and daily take many of these thieving Villains, and three Regiments are marched from hence towards Scotland. It is likely they would soon be <reg orig="quel'd">quelled</reg> if they would stand to fight.</p>

<p>From Portsmouth they write, That a Squadron of our fleet have taken very lately 6 prizes from the Hollanders.</p>

<p>The preparations in Holland for War is very great, and they talk of some great matters agreed upon betwixt them and the French, but nothing openly declared, till they hear what becomes of their Treaty with England.</p>

<head level="3">Thus you have an Account of</head>

<p><i>The titular King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> Commission to the Highlanders, and the warrants issued forth thereupon, in the name of <em>James Earl of Glencarn and Kenmore.</em> The strange accidents that have <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in Holland by Thunder, Lightning and Fire. Further news concerning the Treaty. <reg orig="Leeters">Letters</reg> from the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <unclear>Whitlock</unclear> out of Sweden. Several Prizes taken from the Hollanders by our Fleet, and other intelligence from several parts.</i></p>

<p>An iron <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> Nag, between 6 and 7 years old, about 13 and 14 hand high, with a white saddle spot on each side of the back, towards the <unclear>wither</unclear>, with a straight <unclear>back, well raised</unclear> together, with a sound buttock; a long thin ear, something uptight, paces very even and well, and flat limbed, <reg orig="dock't">docked</reg> and <unclear><reg orig="bob'd">bobbed</reg></unclear>, and about an <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> grown below the dock, if not cut since he was <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg>; lost out of the ground of James Hawks of Hebridge in the County of Essex, within a mile of Maldon, on the 3 of this instant January. If any can give notice of him to the said James Hawks at Hebridge; or to Mr. Games at the White Horse within Algate, London; or to Edward Vaentine of Hockleton in the County of Northampton, and they shall have Thirty shillings for their pains.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>