<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc173">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 173</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>A Proclamation of His Highness the Lord Protector, signed by the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> of the States General of Holland. A Letter from Paris, touching the Proceedings of Charles Stuart and the Duke of York, upon notice of an Agreement betwixt England and the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces. The particulars of what hath lately happened in Scotland betwixt <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan and General Middleton. The selling of many Prizes at Plymouth and other places. The Publication of the Peace in Holland. And news from Sweden, and many other places.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> April 26. to <em>Wednesday</em> May 3. 1654.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, April 26.</i></head>

<p>This day was Proclaimed (in London and Westminster with great solemnity) the Peace between England and Holland, the Proclamation <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> followeth in these words.</p>

<p><i>By the Lord Protector</i></p>

<p><i>A Proclamation of the Peace made between this Commonwealth, and that of the united Provinces of the Netherlands.</i></p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, considering how necessary it is, not<pb n="1" /> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to preserve Peace and quiet at home, but as far as in him lies, to live in amity and friendship with his Neighbours; Hath by the blessing of God with the advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, made and concluded a Peace, Union, and confederation to continue for ever, between this Commonwealth of the one part, and that of the United Provinces of the Low Countries, of the other part, their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories, Places, and People by Sea, Land, fresh waters, or elsewhere, by the which peace it is agreed, That all Enmity, Hostility, Discord and War between the said Commonwealths, their people, and subjects, shall cease, and all injustices and wrongs whatsoever, done since the <unclear>18</unclear> and 28 of May, 1652. shall cease and be forgotten, except such <reg orig="Depradations">Depredations</reg> as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be committed on either side, in these seas, after twelve days, from the date of these presents; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St Vincent after six weeks; and from thence within the Mediterranean sea, and to the &aelig;quinoctial line, after ten weeks, and beyond the &aelig;quinoctial line, after the space of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places, and that the people and inhabitants of each party respectively, of what condition or quality soever they be, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> treat each other with love and friendship, and may freely and securely come into, and <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through each others Countries, Towns, Villages, and Precincts, and there stay and abide, and from thence depart again at their pleasure, without any hindrance or molestation, and likewise Trade and have Commerce, and generally do use and exercise all other things (observing the Laws and Customs of each place respectively) as freely, fully, and securely, as they might have done in the time of the Peace. Whereof all Persons whatsoever, in these Nations of England, Scotland, and Ireland,<pb n="2" /> are to take notice, and to conform themselves accordingly.</p>

<p>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 26 of April, 1654</p>

<head level="3">Thursday April 27.</head>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April 20. There is yet no considerable news from the North, that I can understand; for Middleton with his forces is drawn into Sutherland, betwixt whom and our forces, there is a Navigable River, not passable but by boats, and those the enemy hath drawn to their own Banks. In many parts of the Country there is all possible <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> used to carry on their Levies, and not a few desperate persons continue their recourse to them. There hath been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Officers and others of them gathered up lately, and committed to safe custody. In some of their pockets hath been found a paper, called <reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg> declaration, <reg orig="stuff'd">stuffed</reg> with many expressions that carry little consistency with their course. I may possibly help you with a Copy by the next.</p>

<p><reg orig="Invernesse">Inverness</reg> April 14. I can <reg orig="adde">add</reg> nothing to my last, yet would not omit writing to you by this Post. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan is at <reg orig="Dingwel">Dingwell</reg> with his forces. The enemy still North of him, and past getting out of that Country without either <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> or dispersing their own force, <em>Badgenoth</em>, and other parts of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> are quiet.</p>

<p>From Milford Haven April 24. As for news in these parts, it doth afford little. The last vessels come from Ireland, brought with them several passengers, which tell us no further, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Tories who remain hid in corners, are as ready as ever to do mischief, but that they want strength, and so narrowly looked after, that they are presently suppressed, and driven into their Dens: as for other matters all things are quiet over the country, as they are likewise in these parts.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>Falmouth, April 23. All the news at present is, that we are expecting to hear the peace proclaimed between us and the Dutch, that so some course may be taken to clear this coast of so many <reg orig="Pyrating">Pirating</reg> Rogues, who have of a long time so much annoyed us, and do the same now, though not so bad as formerly, they do no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> about <reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg>, and so along that Channel. One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> lately chased two Brest <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> even to their own doors, but being got among the Rocks, out <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> durst not venture after them, and so gave them over; here are several ships bound to several parts to the Southward, who are <reg orig="onely">only</reg> expecting a fair wind to proceed on their voyage.</p>

<p>Portsmouth, April 27. Our Fleet is still riding in Stoaks Bay, and most of those ships which are come in to victual, and be new <unclear>fired</unclear> for the Sea are gone out, and the rest will be ready by the next week. We are in a <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> expectation of <reg orig="Heroick">Heroic</reg> General Pen from London, and then upon his arrival we doubt not, but that this Fleet will be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon some <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> design, which I hope will prove for the good of the Nation.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> April 26.</head>

<p>From Upsal the 24 of March 1653. On Tuesday last my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> and Count Erick had a meeting, to the debate of the Articles of Union: at which time Count Erick did <reg orig="exhibite">exhibit</reg> several Articles on the behalf of Sweden, some whereof were such, that his Lordship can by no means consent to. Yesterday his Excellency went to the Queen to deliver his exceptions, and the reasons why he cannot admit of some of these Articles proposed to him, and the Queen seemed to be satisfied therein. But this day Count Erick came again unto my Lord, and was very earnest that those might be admitted; but his Lordship is as earnest to exclude them. Yet I have a <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the Queen will find some expedient to reconcile all, and will sum up things into a harmony and agreement. The great talks here are of the Coronation of the new King; and preparations are made thereunto; so resolved is the Queen to resign up the Government. Piemontelli the Spanish Resident suddenly takes his leave to return home. Count Monte Cuculli went away last week.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, April 29.</head>

<p>It is observable, that our ships have entertained the Proclamation of Peace with the greatest solemnity that can be, and General Pen being gone down to sea, you will now find what will be the Expedition which <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg> so much looks upon, whether they will go to<pb n="4" /> Legorn, or the high Determinations of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> so shall order it, as they shall call the Turks to an account at Tunis or Alger for the injuries they have done unto the Christians.</p>

<p>You shall observe that there have been taken some Dutch Merchants, and the Dutch will <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> us that they have taken some ships of ours which they have carried to Flushen and <reg orig="Enchysen">Enchusen</reg>, they were taken on the Northern Seas; and if the curious please to look upon them, they will peradventure find them to be those ships which the Dutch Men of War did meet with, as I made mention in my last.</p>

<p>I had almost forgot to acquaint you, that on Thursday last the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> who were resident in London, were magnificently entertained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>By Letters from Paris, dated May 2 <em>stilo novo</em>, thus. The titular King of Scots and all his friends and adherents stand amazed at the concluding of a peace between the Lord Protector of England, and the States of the United Provinces of Holland. The Duke of York was intended for Scotland, but the news of peace with Holland puts him into a <em>Dilemma</em>. The Court also took this <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> much to heart, and so it is thought will all the Courts in Christendom; for now there be two such potent Commonwealths United, you must expect that all the <reg orig="Kingdomes">Kingdoms</reg> in Europe will put themselves into a posture of defence. The Earl of Merinville, Commander in Chief of the French forces in the County of Roussillon hath <reg orig="releived">relieved</reg> the strong Port and Town of Rosa, which was besieged by the Spaniard. At the relief of this place there was slain on both sides about 1500 men, whereof there were many Officers of good account fell of the French.</p>

<p>From Venice thus. The Senate having received news of the defeat of some of our forces in Dalmatia, which was done by a party of 5000 Turks, who lying in an <reg orig="Ambuscado">Ambuscade</reg> took ours at advantage: But this Victory cost them dear; for our men and the Morlacks behaved themselves with such resolution, that they killed above 1800 of the Turks upon the place, and many wounded, our loss amounting to somewhat more <reg orig="then">than</reg> 2000. To repair this <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>, the Senate have issued out new Orders for the raising of more forces, which are speedily to be sent thither.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, The King of Denmark hath been to visit the new Church of Altenaw, and the next day went back to Gluckstadt. The General Koningsmark hath at last <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> the Town of Bremerburgh, and likewise the Fort which is near it.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 1.</head>

<p>This day <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Prides">Pride's</reg> Regiment exercised themselves in Tuthil fields, where they had such new Arms given them as was convenient; <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> they march towards Harwich, where shipping will be ready to transport them into Scotland, they all express themselves to be most willing for the present service.</p>

<p>It is advertised from Scotland, that <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> forces do lie along the banks of the River, to observe the motion of our men, who will be with them before they are aware of us, some forces both of horse and foot are expected from Ireland, so that let the enemy stir which way they will, they shall find us both before them, and behind them.</p>

<p>In the mean time many men are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> snapped who are going to the enemy.</p>

<p>This day in <reg orig="Hide">Hyde</reg> Park there was the hurling of a great Ball. Fifty Cornish Gentlemen played against fifty, one party played in white Caps, and the other in Red, there was great agility of body <reg orig="shewn">shown</reg>, and wrestling proper to that Nation, at every meeting one with the other, which was ordered with such Dexterity, there it was to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> more the strength, the vigour, and <reg orig="nimblenesse">nimbleness</reg> of their bodies, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to <reg orig="indanger">endanger</reg> their persons. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector was there; the Ball they hurled was silver, which that party had, who did win the <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>.</p>

<p>Paris May 2. 1654. <em>stilo novo</em>. The 20 instant two Counsellors of the Parliament went to Chantilli, and Monimorency, two places formerly belonging to the Prince of Conde, and according to the Sentence lately given against him, did there declare those Houses and Castles to be reunited to the Crown, and accordingly did take possession of them. The Cardinal de Retz was no sooner come to the Castle of Nants, but that within two<pb n="6" /> days after, and for several days following, he was complimented, by the Dean and Chapter, and by all the Courts of Judicature in that City, he was also visited by the D. of Brissac, and others the Nobility and Gentry of the Province; nevertheless the Marshal de la Mesteray doth narrowly look over all his actions, and of those that visit him. There are great complaints made against the Parliament at Rennes by most of the Gentry of that Province; this being occasioned by one Morbeuf, who sitting there upon the reversion of a <reg orig="Presidents">President's</reg> place, hath lately offered some great abuse to a Gentleman of quality, who was <reg orig="solliciting">soliciting</reg> a <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> in that Court for some Pupils, whereof he is the guardian.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Jamerz and Mouzon having a design to rifle the small Town of Veron, came thither in the night, and having plundered it, carried away the chief men prisoners to make them pay a ransom. The Chancellor hath this week sent for the Parson of St. Paul, to declare unto him some order from the Court about a <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> which had lately happened in his Church: The Parson answering he could not obey it, an Officer was sent to him with an Order from the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, whereby he is <reg orig="injoined">enjoined</reg> to depart the City within 24 hours, which he did accordingly.</p>

<p>There hath been of late great troubles in this City among the people by reason of the great imposts laid upon them and although that imposts upon all Cattle which was so much cried against be taken of; yet there are many other new one which are little better, some fortifications are to be made at the Castle of Vincennes, and the K. Guards have received order to be in a march about the 10. of this instant; it is variously spoken whether the King shall go to the army or to be crowned, as it was intended.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, May 2.</head>

<p>Whereas in the third Article of Peace, Union, and Confederation made, established and <reg orig="promulged">promulgated</reg> between the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces; It is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges and Damages which either party hath sustained by the other since the 18 of May 1652, shall be taken away and forgotten in such manner, as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other, for, or upon occasion of any the aforesaid Injuries, Charges and Damages; but that there shall be a perfect abolition of all and every of them until this present day, and all actions for the same shall be held and reputed void and null, excepting such depredations as shall be committed by either side in these seas after the space of 12 days, and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. Vincent after 6 weeks, and from thence within the Mediterranean sea, and to the Equinoctial Line after 10 weeks, and beyond the Equinoctial Line after the space of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said peace given in those places.</p>

<p>Wherefore we having considered what is agreed as aforesaid, have confirmed and ratified, as we do confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same by these presents, which we have caused to be published, that all persons concerned therein may take notice <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>: and to the end none may plead ignorance, the Commissioners of the Admiralty are hereby required to give effectual notice hereof to all ships of War of this State, either at Sea, or in Port within these Dominions, or elsewhere. And the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty are also forthwith to call in upon their several securities given in that Court, all such ships as have been set forth upon private Commissions against the United Provinces, or the People thereof.</p>

<head level="3">Given at Whitehall the first of May, 1654.</head>

<p>In <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> whereof, as well the Commissioners of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as the Ambassadors extraordinary of the States General, have signed these presents with their own hands.</p>

<p><i>H. Lawrence, Pres. H. Beverningck.</i></p>
<p><i>Gil. Pickering. W. Nieupoort.</i></p>
<p><i>E. Montague. Alex. P. Iogestall.</i></p>
<p><i>Walter Strickland.</i></p>

<p>The like is to be published in Holland. This day many goods were sold by the Candel at the Prize Office. The Letters from Bristol and Plymouth say, that 9 ships lately taken and adjudged prize, are now upon sale, with great quantity of goods.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>