<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn212">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 212</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, Decemb. 26. to <em>Monday</em>, January 2. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> Decemb. 26.</head>

<p>This day from <em>Scotland</em> by Letters <em>Decemb</em>. 22. came as followeth. Capt. <em>Hart</em> being sent out by the Commander in chief, with a party of Colonel <em>Twistleton's</em> Regiment, to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> the parts of <em>Scotland</em> about <em>Dumfrieze</em>, the Meres, and <em>Tividale</em>; after 10 or 12 days searching up and down, and <reg orig="tyring">tiring</reg> almost all his horses, the 12 instant marching towards <em>Harwick</em>, by the way understood the Enemy had appointed a Rendezvous at 12 hours on <em>Bathwick</em> Bray; whereupon he <reg orig="hastned">hastened</reg> thither all he could, but was much impeded by the <reg orig="foulnes">foulness</reg> of the weather, and a violent drift of snow, so that before he came, the Rendezvous was broken up, he pursued them by the track in the snow, for<pb n="1" /> he could get no intelligence of them, although within a mile of their body, at last he got sight of them, they drew up into two bodies and faced our men, ours made what haste they could to charge them. After a sharp conflict, it pleased the Lord to <unclear><!--approx 7 characters--></unclear> the victory over them, we pursued them several miles as long as horses would go; and although our horses were <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> wearied and theirs fresh, not above 15 horse escaped: their number about fourscore or more, their prisoners say a hundred, our party took 65 horses, many of them good ones, 16 prisoners, two or three seem to be of note, though they conceal themselves; in the pursuit many were cut down, and put off their horses, and so left, concluding those that came afterwards would glean them up; but the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> were busier in getting horses than in securing prisoners, and so many of them escaped away on foot, but will be known wherever they are met, having the States mark on them. There were four of them slain, Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> it is reported, is dangerously wounded, and his Major, Major <em>Erwin</em>, we took both their horses, they fought very resolutely a great while. Quartermaster <em>Ward</em> with 15 or 16 soldiers of ours are wounded, and one slain. The fight was at Phillip upon <em>Bathwick</em> water. <em>Sealis</em> the High sheriff of <em>Roxborough</em> is redeemed out of their hands, but one of our <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> ran him into the thigh, not knowing him, he is one very affectionate to our party. Those of the Enemy that escaped, are gone by the way of <em>Bigger</em>, towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, parties are sent to interrupt them.</p>

<p>The intent of <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> in their marching to the North, is (as they give out) to secure the landing of the <em>Dutch</em> forces, arms, and ammunition, which it seems they expect.</p>

<p>The late Revolutions are well resented here, and the Army very unanimous to assist my <em>Lord Protector</em> in the carrying on <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Affairs</p>

<p>Take herewith a <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of Capt. <em>Hill's</em> excellent Letter, <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Ruthen</em> Castle, to the Gentlemen of <em>Bagdenoth</em> in <em>Scotland</em>.</p><pb n="2" />

<p><i>Gentlemen</i>,</p>

<p>The next day after I had meeting with some of you, the Guideman of <em>Nede</em> (I suppose directed from the rest) came to me, with that which seemed a very strange Overture, how be it, I believe it to be the result of that your Convent, <em>viz</em>. to inquire of me, whether or not (in case the Enemy should <reg orig="approch">approach</reg> these parts) you might have liberty to give them some men and provisions to put them by the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, to which I have taken this occasion (by the hands of the same agent) to give you the ensuing answer, (the effect whereof I gave <em>Nede</em>, at such time as he made that needless offer,) That you may take it for granted, that whosoever shall either directly or indirectly, assist those <reg orig="Theevish">Thievish</reg> Rebels, either with men, money or provisions, shall be deemed by us as one of them, and shall forfeit whatsoever he hath both real and personal; And whereas it hath been said that some of our chief Officers have granted such Liberty, or (as you call it) Favour, to other parts of the Country, I must assure you (as I first told <em>Nede</em>) that report was, and is, as false in <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, as it hath been weakly <reg orig="secconded">seconded</reg> by your belief; neither will those who first spoke it, be able to hold up their faces when called to account for it.</p>

<p><em>Gentlemen</em>, You may be confident that if you suffer anything by submission to the present power, the State is better able to make you some kind of satisfaction, (as on the contrary they are to give you the reward of your doings, in case you submit, or give assistance to their (and indeed your own) Enemies) than any other now in <em>Scotland</em>, who may seek such things from you. And (that I may reason with you a little) what may you expect from a inconsiderable party (yea, though they were more numerous) of <reg orig="depserat">desperate</reg> men, of broken fortunes, or none at all; who dare not keep their homes, for fear the just <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> of the Country should be executed upon them; but that they should bring you the same headlong and vagabond condition with themselves.</p>

<p>Whereas on the contrary (<reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> may in great part witness)<pb n="3" /> the care of this State to settle your peace, and endeavour your prosperity (and, if you will but cast your eye upon things most profitable) is not this State more likely to protect and make you prosperous, than those who not only seek to destroy your peace, and devour that little morsel which they (and others like them) have left you, (&amp; which this state <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> to preserve to you) but even like Vipers, gnaw out the bowels of their Mother Countries? Again is not the State of <em>England</em> immediately about to incorporate, and make you one free Commonwealth with them? and what greater favour could they cast upon you? &amp; are you not tenderly dealt with (your condition <reg orig="consider'd">considered</reg>?) what burden do you undergo, which <em>England</em> is free from? And (if friendly and civil dealing may gain anything upon you) I am sure there was never any people (under the lash of the sword) more friendly <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg> &amp; civilly used, by those in whose power it is, to exact and sweep their all from them, than you are? So indeed I could almost afford to ask you what was become of your Reason, while you assaulted me with this unreasonable overture? Again, consider that God hath delivered into our hands the most potent and best appointed Armies, that <em>Scotland</em> hath been able to raise; and is it likely that this <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> of <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> and Robbers should stand before us?</p>

<p><em>Gentlemen</em>, What I have spoken is out of a desire to your welfare, &amp; I hope you will consider it accordingly, as also that you will give me some testimony of the <reg orig="realitie">reality</reg> of your intentions towards this State (to whom you stand <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> ) and so take off that doubt which (by your late offer) you have given <reg orig="mee">me</reg> occasion to harbour, at least by hasting in such firing, and other things as are by you deficient for the use of this Garrison, and the speedy payment of your Assess. To conclude, this is to require you, neither to <reg orig="ayd">aid</reg>, <reg orig="abett">abet</reg>, or any ways assist the Enemy with Men, Money, Arms, Provisions, or ought else, either directly or indirectly, as you will answer the contrary with the loss of your estates, and <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of your persons; and such as<pb n="4" /> your carriage is herein, you may expect the like from</p>

<p><em>Ruthen Castle, Decemb. 1653.</em></p>
<p><i>Gentlemen, Your humble servant, Jo: Hills.</i></p>
<p><i>For the Gentlemen of Badgenoth.</i></p>

<p>Letters from Swedeland give to understand the safe arrival of the Lord Ambassador Whitlock from England, and of his gallant Reception there.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> the 6 of <em>Dember</em>, 1653. The last news came from the Arms in <em>Poland</em> import, that two parties being sent by the King to discover the <em>Tariarian</em> and <em><reg orig="Cosachs">Cossacks</reg></em> Army; their report was to the King, that the Kam (or King) of the <em>Tartars</em> was there in person, with an Army of 50 thousand men, that the <em><reg orig="Cosachs">Cossacks</reg></em> were not yet <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with them, but in a distinct Army consisting of 25 thousand men, but as yet no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg> to any Marital action, by reason that the last Orders come from <em>Constantinople</em> give direction to the said Kam of the <em>Tartars</em>, how far he must proceed in his expedition, and thereupon things lay in a <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Regensborough</em>: This last week the differences between the Prince <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg>, and the Duke de <em>Simmeren</em> were agreed upon by the mediation of the <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of Mentz: The Bishop of <em>Spire</em> is likewise upon agreement with the Bishop of <em>Munster</em>: The whole body of the Diet hath not met for three weeks together, but only private conferences, where businesses have been debated and some concluded; others are put off for a longer time.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>: The difference between our Magistrate and us is not yet reconciled, and the owners of those Barges and goods that were stopped at <em>Bonne</em> are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> soliciting for the releasing of them, but as yet can do little good; yet there is some hopes by reason that the <reg orig="Electours">Electors</reg> of <em>Mentz</em> and <em>Triers</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> take the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> upon them, and have promised to see all things reconciled.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Strasburgh">Strasbourg</reg></em>: We hear that there are great preparations making at <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> and <em>Birch</em> for the reception of the Duke of<pb n="5" /> <em>Lorrain</em>, whose coming doth affright very much the whole Country, being assured that all the benefit they can expect by his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> is only to have those forces which he bringeth with him take winter quarters in those parts: The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of the <em>Switzers</em> is totally agreed, being well united amongst themselves.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday December</em> 27.</head>
<head level="3"><i>Advertisements to the several Garrisons and Navy, <em>&amp;c</em></i></head>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Ordinances of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> benefit (this week) have been passed by the Lord Protector and his Council, which in Order briefly we shall give you this <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of, <em>viz</em>. An Ordinance for continuing the Excise and new impost until the 25 day of <em>March</em> next coming in the hands of <em>Luke Hodges, Thomas Bullrode</em>, and <em>William Parker</em> appointed Commissioners of Excise for that time: Also an Ordinance for continuing the Act for redemption of Captives until the 3 of <em>October</em> 1654.</p>

<p><em>Whitehall</em> December 26. An Ordinance was passed for alteration of several Names and Forms used heretofore in Courts, Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, &amp;c. and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> proceedings in Courts of Law, <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> and Equity, within the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, according to the present Government. The sum whereof in brief is this, That <em>Oliver Lord Protector</em> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. having the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the Administration of Government within the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, invested and established in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, assisted with a Council, who have power until the meeting of next Parliament, (which is to be on the 3 day of <em>September</em> now next ensuing) to make Laws and Ordinances for the Peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force until order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, doth with the advice and consent of his said Council order and ordain, That in all Courts of Law, <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> or Equity, and in all Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, Indictments, Informations, <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, return of Writs,<pb n="6" /> and in all Fines, Recoveries, Exemplifications, <reg orig="Recognizances'">Recognizances,</reg> <reg orig="Processe">Process</reg>, &amp; other proceedings of Law within <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, instead of the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title, and Test (of the Keepers of the Liberties, &amp;c.) heretofore used, that from and after the six and twentieth day of December, 1653. the Name, Stile, Title, and Test of the Lord Protector for the time being, of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging shall be used, and no other; and the date shall be in the year of our Lord, and no other.</p>

<p><em>Downes</em> 22 <em>Decemb</em>. Capt. <em>Richard Newbury</em> Commander of the <em>Lawrell</em>, is come in hither, who hath been out by order from the Generals, with his ship and the <em>Ruby</em>, the <em>Kent</em>, and the <em>Industry</em>, to ply between the Isle of <em>Wight</em> and the <em>French</em> Coasts, where he took <reg orig="som">some</reg> prizes: when they were towards the <em>French</em> Coasts, they made discovery of 4 <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of ships, to whom they gave chase, and <reg orig="followd">followed</reg> them so close that they took 2 of them. Men were taken out of the <em>Kent</em> to man one of the prizes, which is come hither into the <em>Downes</em>.</p>

<p>The other prize was manned by men out of the <em>Lawrell</em>, which is also coming hither. Their lading is French Wines, which they had taken in at <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The <em>Lawrell</em> and the <em>Kent</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are again preparing to go out to ply to the Westward.</p>

<p>Capt. <em>Martin</em>, Commander of the <em>Bristol</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, who hath the Command of the Western squadron, meeting with Captain <em>Crispin</em>, Commander of the <em>Assistance</em>, he appointed him to convoy some <em><reg orig="Hamburghers">Hamburgers</reg></em>, and <em>Swedish</em> ships, which he carried safe to <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>, and his Order being then to go out upon a design with the <em><reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg></em> from <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> to seek out if they could meet with any of the ships from <em>Brest</em>.</p>

<p><em>Paris December</em> 27. The last news we have from <em>Catalonia</em> import, that upon our late Victory with the Enemy, we have forced them to retire, and take their quarters in and about <em>Gironne</em>, leaving us the opportunity to take our winter quarters, where they intended to have been during this Winter season.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>From <em>Aix</em> in <em>Provence</em>: We hear that the States of that Country are now gathering to be there the 18 of this instant <em>December</em>: We hear that in <em>Languedoc</em> there hath happened some great differences between the Protestants and Papists chiefly of <em>Nismes</em>, where there was some <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> spilt, yet by the care and discretion of the Magistrate all was prevented.</p>

<p>The great design concerning the war at <em>Naples</em> is not prosecuted so violently as formerly, and therefore many are of opinion that it will not go on but fall off <reg orig="it selfe">itself</reg> others who count themselves clear sighted, say that it is only a wile of the Cardinal, who doth seem to wave it for a while until his <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> will grow to a greater perfection: the Commissioners appointed for the <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg> of the Prince of <em>Conde</em> have met already twice, they are, the Lord <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg>, the first President, and two Counsellors of the great Chamber: The Prince of Conti is not as yet come to this City, but expected here <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, there being no other talk but that he will be here within three of four days.</p>

<p>The report concerning the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Coronation is renewed <reg orig="againe">again</reg>, and it is said for <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> it will be done at <em>Rheims</em> about the middle of March next. The King hath <reg orig="beene">been</reg> with the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> at Saint <em>Germaines</em>, to spend some days in the sport of Hunting: <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have nothing this <reg orig="weeke">week</reg> from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Plague doth continue there, and that they are thereby deprived of Trade from the High Country, which bringeth Wines and other commodities to them, besides the Spanish <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> from St. <em>Sebastians</em> do much annoy their trade, lying still about the mouth of the River.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg> <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <reg orig="heare">hear</reg>, That the States of that Province and Parliament are not yet agreed, each of them standing upon high terms, and resolving to maintain their anticut Privileges.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday Decem.</em> 28.</head>

<p><i>An Ordinance appointing Commissioners for the better ordering and bringing in the duty of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, and the <reg orig="arreares">arrears</reg> thereof, whereof this is the sum.</i></p>

<p>For the more speedy and <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> getting in of all <reg orig="Arreares">Arrears</reg> of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, it is Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, the Lord Protector, with the consent of his <reg orig="Counsell">Council</reg>, That Sir <em>Will: Roberts</em> Knight, <em>John Stone, Gervas <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg>, John Hildesley, Rich: Lucy, Ed: Clud, Tho: Wood, Ant: Rous, James Phillips</em>, and <em>Nath: Barton</em>, Esqs; of any three of them, be authorized and required, to consider and examine, by Oath or otherwise, what <reg orig="Arreares">Arrears</reg> of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> are not yet paid into the Treasury for the same, and what remaineth in the hands of any Farmer, Commissioner, Sub-Commissioner, or other person whatsoever, or for which any person or persons stand engaged with any Farmer or Sub-commissioner, and to send for <reg orig="persons">person's</reg> <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg>, Articles, Receipts, Bonds, or any Writings concerning <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, or relating thereunto; and to <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> all parties, and to determine all differences concerning the same, according to the power formerly given to the Commissioners in the like case, That the said Commissioners or any three of them, be authorized to give Order to the Commissioners of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, to Farm out the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> of such Counties, places, and commodities, in <em>England, Wales</em>, and <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> of <em>Warwick</em> upon <em>Tweed</em>, as to the said Commissioners shall <reg orig="appeare">appear</reg> to be most <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> to the Commonwealth, and the ease of the people; to commence from the 23 of <em>Decemb</em>. 1653. and to continue till the 25 of March 1654. so as the same be not at a <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> rate <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> of such County, place, or commodity, was farmed at the last year.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for the reviving of an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, An Act for the probate of Wills, and granting Administrations to this effect.</p>

<p>That whereas the late Act <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for the probate of Wills, and granting Administrations, had continuance<pb n="9" /> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first day of <em>October</em>, one thousand six hundred fifty and three, It is Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the consent of His <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, That the said Act, and the Authorities, Matters and Things therein contained, shall stand and be revived to continue in <reg orig="ful">full</reg> power and force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first day of <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg> next, to all intents and purposes.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That Rich: Lucy, John Hildesley, Nath: Barton, Jervas <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg>, Anthony Rous, Joachim Mathews, Ed: Clud, Thomas Wood, Esqs; and Robert Tichburn, Alderman of <em>London</em>, be added to the Judges mentioned in the said Act, to execute all and every the powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named may do.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Holland, Decemb</em> 26. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> are at a great stand, what to expect concerning the Treaty with England, most are of opinion upon receipt of the last Letters from England, that our Ambassadors will <reg orig="returne">return</reg> home <em>re infecta</em>. In the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> time the French Ambassador <em><unclear>Chonn</unclear></em> urgeth hard for a <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> with this State, and hath offered already very <unclear>tamely</unclear> if we break with Spain. In is said that <reg orig="wee">we</reg> shall have of the French six thousand men, three or four millions yearly towards the defraying of the charges of the war, and thirty good ships to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with our Fleet. If it be so that we break with you, <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> probable that France and we may strike up the bargain.</p>

<p>Our defensive League with the Prince of Liege, doth not hold (and happily the fault is not on our side) insomuch that all our Troops, both Foot and Horse, are retired to their old Garrison <reg orig="againe">again</reg>. The Lorainers being <reg orig="fairely">fairly</reg> retreated beforehand, who hereupon with some of the Condees and Spanish under that notion, have besieged a small City belonging to Liege, which they <reg orig="presse">press</reg> sore, but have been as yet but rudely entertained, it is to be feared that they will carry it with some others in that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so put the whole Country round under contribution.</p><pb n="10" />

<p>Our whole Country is now full of discourses of the Treaty with <em>England</em>, if it break, this State will doubtless endeavour to make a diversion in Scotland, by sending assistance to the Highlanders, and it is said that Prince <em>Rupert </em>is to go Generalissimo into that Country; but if both States do agree, as is much desired, no doubt but the triumph will be greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> that for the Spanish accommodation.</p>

<p>The Treaty betwixt the Count of <em>Harcourt</em> and the Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, we hear is far advanced, and it is not doubted but that <em>Brisack</em> will change Master, and the whole Province of <em>Elsas</em> be lost as to the French.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> 25 <em>Decemb</em>. Cap <em>Crispin</em> with the Assistance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come in hither, he was in a <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> <reg orig="neare">near</reg> <em>Scilly</em> four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, but afterwards sailed Eastward of Tor Bay, and is come safe hither, he hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> with Cap. <em>Hatsel</em>, and is to go to Portsmouth to be new fitted and <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg>, and out <reg orig="againe">again</reg>.</p>

<p>He <reg orig="weat">went</reg> from hence twelve <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, and hath been a great check to the <em>Brest</em> Men of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>: After which he sent with the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> that went out with him, on the 16 instant anchored in Conquet Road, where the Boats were sent to fetch off two Vessels, one laden with wine from <em><reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg></em>, the other light, and there were then in the same place <reg orig="neare">near</reg> 30 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> more, two of which were supposed to be men of war, whop with the rest hauled close under the Houses, which were lined with what <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> could afford,<pb n="11" /> with which (it being half <reg orig="ebbe">ebb</reg>) they bear of our boats, but Gods providence without <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to us; the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> Boat going in with a small Gun, ours also returned with them, and attempted to set the said Vessels on fire, but could not make way for our Boats, so that Captain Crispin was constrained to fire out of his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Town, and upon the Vessels, against whom he made about two hundred and thirty great shot, which in sight of our men, did the enemy very much spoil: the Enemy made use of only one Gun, which they kept playing all the time in at <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> we beat them from it.</p>

<p>That afternoon we discovered a ship of the Enemies plying in towards Brest, and the Non-such sailed after her, and that evening took her, she being a great Holland Fly-boat of eight Guns, laden with wine from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>.</p>

<p>This day the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother was received from his close imprisonment in Newgate to the Tower.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday Decemb.</em> 29.</head>

<p><em>PARIS</em> 31 <em>Decemb</em>. 1653. There is a strong report here, that the coming of the Prince of Conti to the City, is for <reg orig="severall">several</reg> ends: first, that he is to marry one of the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces, and that thereupon he will have the confiscation of his <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> Estate: the match between the Duke of Nemours, and the Duchess of <em>Longueville</em> goeth on, and many believe that it will be accomplished in a short time.</p>

<p>By letters from <reg orig="Marseillis">Marseilles</reg> we hear, that the great Pirate the Knight Paul, hath brought into <em>Tulon</em> a great ship laden with Corn, which he pretends was going from Leghorn to Spain: We have from St. Menehaud, that they have near finished those breaches which were made the late fledge in their fortifications, that nothing more hath passed there of novelty, but that the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> hath been new modelled: the Switzers being appointed for the guard of the Castle, and the French being commanded to secure several passes over the River <em>Aisne</em>.</p><pb n="12" />

<p>The Court returned the last night from St. Germains where they have remained 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and now do spend much time partly in their superstitious devotion, and the major part in feasting, dancing, and the like <reg orig="frolicks">frolics</reg>.</p>

<p>The Earl <em>de Amanze</em> is made Lieut. Gen. in <reg orig="Burgundi">Burgundy</reg>, as also the Marshall <em>de Turenne</em> is made <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the County of Limosin.</p>

<p>Yesterday was published an Ordinance from our Magistrate, forbidding all manner of persons to meet together in multitudes, and chiefly not to fight each against the other with stones, staves, swords, or any other offensive weapon, upon pain of death, which hath been much practised of late among our Citizens.</p>

<p>Two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since his Majesty with his Brother, the Cardinal Mazarini, and many Noble men went to Chailot to visit the late Queen of England, who is very much <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> for the advancing of her new Convent there: being she can do little good <reg orig="else where">elsewhere</reg>, Prince <em>Rupert</em> is expected here from <em>Nantes</em>, having made an end of selling these ships; and goods, which he had sent before, or brought along with him thither, and according to the French Relation, the Cardinal Mazarini compelled him to make full restitution of the last Ship and Goods taken upon the English.</p>

<p>By the last letters from Naples thus. The Earl de Ognate our late Vice King being <reg orig="imbarqued">embarked</reg> with all his followers upon 4 Gallies of this squadron, is gone from hence taking his way for Genoa. The next day after the Duke de Terranova went likewise from hence for Perlamain Seiritia. One ship coming from Sardinia to this City was cast away near Terracini, where many men were drowned, and among them Don Francisco Poderico, Mr. Drampo, with many Reformadoes.</p>

<p>From Venice thus: There are come two ships lately from Candia, that bring news how the <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> Foseole continuing to be dangerous sick, the Proveditor Morisini hath taken upon him the sole or absolute command, and hath<pb n="13" /> brought one part thereof into the Arch Spelago: partly to keep his men in exercise, as also to take the contributions which this State doth raise yearly up on those Islands: we hear also that the ships lately gone from hence, were <reg orig="safly">safely</reg> arrived in Candia, the Commissary Francisco Barbaro being gone hence with a considerable sum of money for the pay of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<p>The Thunder-bolt is lately fallen at Tina, where it hath consumed a <reg orig="Magazin">Magazine</reg>, wherein were besides other Ammunition, two hundred and fifty Barrels of Powder, and the Church that was near it. That some of our forces being landed at Spina Longa, had got a good booty upon our enemy, and besides, had destroyed all the salt Pans, which yield the Turk a very considerable sum yearly.</p>

<p>From Milan: By the often meeting of the Officers of our Army, with the French Officers, there hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> a continuation of the Truce between both Armies, and so both remain in good correspondence: during this <reg orig="intervail">interval</reg>, our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> having received some monies from this city, hath caused it to be distributed among the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<p>Here are now met of the Officers of the Army, but they are to return to the Army within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>: there are several commissions that are issued out for the raising of more Horse and Foot in this State.</p><pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><em>Friday, &amp; Saturday</em> 23 &amp; 24. <em>Decemb</em>.</head>

<p>It is the Lord Protector with his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> and Officers of the Army <em>Friday</em> kept a solemn Humiliation at <em>Whitehall</em>, where they prayed &amp; preached before them Mr. <em>Leckier</em>, and <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, and Mr. <em>Sterrey</em>.</p>

<p>The agreement with the Dutch upon the Treaty with their Commissioners is not concluded (as is reported) the Commissioners are returning home within a departure.</p>

<p>Plymouth Decemb. 26. Friday last about 12 of the Clock my Lord Gen. <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> was proclaimed Lord Protector of the 3 Nations afore the Guild-Hall, where were present the <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen in their scarlet Robes, the common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in their Gowns, the Officers of the Fort and Island, the Commissioners of the Navy, with many other of all sorts: the Proclamation was made by one of the <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> of the Tower, who stood on a place higher <reg orig="then">than</reg> the rest, with the Tower Mace on his shoulder, who when he had with a loud voice read the Proclamation, he <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg>, <em>God save the Lord Protector</em>; at which there was a very great shout made by all the people: the Guns at the Fort and Island, and Mount Battin discharged, the Bells ringing, and Trumpets sounding, with very great acclamation of joy. This place affords little else of news, only the sad news of two ships coming from New England, laden with Masts, <em>&amp;c</em>. taken about 40 leagues to the Westward of Scilly, by 3 Dutch men of War, and carried into Brest: there is at present but one of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, all the rest of this Western squadron are at Sea.</p>

<p>Weymouth Decemb. 28. Yesterday the Lord Protector was solemnly proclaimed in the Tower, the <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen being all present in their Gowns, with a great concourse of people, which being ended, was seconded by discharge of the great Ordnance, and other tokens of joy.</p>

<p>Letters also from several other places, as Bristol, Shrewsbury, Exeter, Yarmouth, <em>&amp;c</em>. speak the same of proclaiming the Lord Protector, with the like solemnity and <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg>.</p>

<p>Paris Jan. 3. stilo novo. We have here a strong report that Pr: Rupert is come to this City, and about twenty men with him: Others <reg orig="affirme">affirm</reg> he will be here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> <reg orig="heere">hear</reg> also that the prince was yesterday at <reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg>, and within<pb n="15" /> two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will be in this City; thereupon his servants make all things ready for his reception: there is <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> advice come from Brest, that there was arrived there, from the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg> nine <reg orig="shippes">ships</reg> of the Kings, which were part of the Navy which is kept at Toulon, to what end or upon what design is not know.</p>

<p>The first instant, being <reg orig="New-years">New Year's</reg> day, the King, his brother with the Cardinal Mazarini, went into one of the <unclear><reg orig="Jeshuits">Jesuits'</reg></unclear>, Convents, where they assisted at evening prayer; there was at present also the Titular King of Scots, with his two brothers the Dukes of <reg orig="Yorke">York</reg> and <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>; after all was done, a collation was prepared for them, and then departed, the King, his brother, and the Cardinal returned to the <unclear>Louvre</unclear>, and the others to the Royal Palace.</p>

<p>Deale the 29 Decemb. There hath come into this Road, <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Merchants <reg orig="shippes">ships</reg>, who are most of them bound for London, among them are the two Morlex ships, besides others that are come from other places from the Southward; there are also many ships bound for Malaga, the Canaries, and the West-Indies, who expect a fair wind and a good convoy.</p>

<p>Dalkeith Decemb. 26. The broken people under <reg orig="Glencairne">Glencarn</reg> and Kenmore, are now gone towards the North, by the Bray of <unclear>Marre</unclear>, report <reg orig="speakes">speaks</reg> them 5000 Horse and Foot, and by a <reg orig="joynt">joint</reg> concurrence of Intelligence they cannot <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> 3000. As soon as the Marq. of Huntley was dead, divers of his Followers went to the Hills, and being met by 8 Troopers of col. <reg orig="Thomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg> Regiment, who questioned them for riding with <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, they pleaded that they were allowed them by the capitulation, but at last fell to <reg orig="blowes">blows</reg>, in which one of them and two of ours were <reg orig="slaine">slain</reg>, and at last a party of the enemy came up and over-<reg orig="powred">powered</reg> our men, took four more, and the other two narrowly escaping. Whether they intend for <reg orig="Aberden">Aberdeen</reg>, or to <reg orig="ly">lie</reg> in <reg orig="Murray-land">Murrayland</reg> for <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> of Quarters is not <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg>, but our Forces are ready to oppose them with what strength <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have in those parts. They have lately taken and imprisoned some Heritors <reg orig="neere">near</reg> Blackford in <reg orig="perth-shire">Perthshire</reg>, for denying their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and give <unclear>out</unclear> they will proceed in like manner with others.</p> 

<hr />

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>