<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn226">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 226</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, April. 3. to <em>Monday</em>, April. 10. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> April. 3.</head>

<p>These several Addresses were this day presented to his Highness the Lord Protector, as followeth;</p>

<p><i>To his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> Oliver Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></p>

<p><i>The Recognition of the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> City of York.</i></p>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord to run to and fro through the earth to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself strong on the behalf of them whose hearts are perfect toward him, to make bare his arm, and bring salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, and to break many <reg orig="yoaks">yokes</reg> from off our <unclear>heels</unclear>, in accomplishment whereof, though humane power and might have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and <reg orig="over-ruled">overruled</reg> by the Spirit in the midst of the Wheels, that we may justly say, we are<pb n="1" /> not saved by Bow or by Sword, but by the Lord our God. And therefore in the first place we look upon it as our duty, to acknowledge Salvation and Blessing to him that sits upon the Throne of Heaven judging right, who hath done whatsoever it pleaseth him in Heaven and in earth, and in all the deep places.</p>

<p>Yet when we also consider, how it seemeth good in the eyes of God to single out your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> as the Man of his right hand, whom he hath made strong for himself, and through your <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg>, courage, and constancy, to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> great and wonderful things in the midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left; while we <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the Lord, our heart is also to the <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> of <em>Israel</em>, who have <reg orig="jeoparded">jeopardised</reg> their lives in the high places of the Field, and are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> going on to second their valiant acts by prudent Counsels, if we may enjoy the end of every just War, which is a safe and honourable Peace. Unto your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> therefore, as once the People of <em>Israel</em> to their Ruler, we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and Peace be to thine helpers</i>.</p>

<p>If we should promise to <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> too much concerning your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, or any of the Sons of men, <reg orig="especialy">especially</reg> in this day wherein the Lord hath so much rejected our confidences, and proclaimed to us by the voice of manifold Providences, <i>Cease from Man whose breath is in his Nostrils</i>, we should not only <reg orig="intrench">entrench</reg> upon the Honour of God and our own Peace, but be injurious to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, who are better able to bear the burthen of much trouble, than a little of that trust which we owe to him alone, in whom there is everlasting strength, who turns every Staff into a Reed, when it is rested out. Yet we cannot but declare our great hopes, that the Lord will still delight to use your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> as a blessed instrument of much Honour to his great Name, and <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg> to this Commonwealth; That as he hath <reg orig="helpt">helped</reg> you to build the Walls of <em>Jerusalem</em>, the defence and safety of his People, even in troublous times, so he will also engage your heart, and enable your hands, according to your eminent station, to further the spiritual work and welfare of this Church and Temple which waits for a season of more <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>We add only the Declaration of our satisfaction in the present Government <reg orig="adminstred">administered</reg> by your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and our <reg orig="cheerfull">cheerful</reg> submission unto it, which we shall be ready to second with our prayers and endeavours for your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> prosperity, and the people of God who sit under your shadow, humbly begging your favourable aspect and influence, upon the Honour and privileges of this ancient City, whose strength is much decayed, though their <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg> be increased, which yet they are more willing, though unable to <reg orig="undergoe">undergo</reg>, till a just and seasonable remedy be procured. Our lot is fallen something remote from the great scene of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> affairs, which hath been prejudicial to us; but we trust, though we enjoy not so much warmth of the Sun as the Southern parts; yet the beams of your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> goodness and justice, whom God hath set up in the midst of us, shall comfortably reach this place, which though in many outward advantages, it may come behind others, yet will strive to an equality with the best, in their affection and <reg orig="faithfulnesse">faithfulness</reg> to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and this Commonwealth.</p>

<p><i>Signed by the Mayor, in the name and by the appointment of the Aldermen and <!--typo or reg?--><reg orig="Commanalty">Commonalty</reg> of the City of <em>York</em>. <em>John Gildert Maj.</em></i></p>

<p>To his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the dominions thereof.</p>

<p><i>The humble Petition and Representation of the grand Juries, at the Assizes held at <em>York, March 1653</em>. in the behalf of themselves and of the Nobility, Justices, Gentry, and Freeholders, with the other Inhabitants of the County of <em>York</em></i>.</p>

<p>Whereas it seemed good unto the Almighty and wise Disposer of all things, by many great and admirable Steps of Providence, to advance your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to the present and peaceable administration of the Government of this Nation, in which we trust that all friends to true Religion and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> liberty shall have cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>. We your Petitioners, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> humbly and cheerfully <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg> our <reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, for your great care in preserving us from those evils of Tyranny and confusion, which we have very lately apprehended <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> in eminent danger of; as also in satisfaction and acquiescence in the Government now established, which we shall in our places and stations be ready with all <reg orig="faithfulnesse">faithfulness</reg> <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> <unclear>and maintain</unclear>.</p><pb n="3" />

<p><i>Farther representing and humbly desiring.</i></p>

<p>That countenance may be given to godly and able Ministers of the Gospel, such as have or shall give Testimony of their good affections to the State, as it is now constituted; and that for their encouragement, some timely provision may be made for a competent and comfortable <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, and that they may be vindicated from oppressions and affronts arising from Principles of Prophanesse and Superstition, or other more precious pretexts, alike dangerous to the propagation of the Gospel, and in opposition to Government.</p>

<p>That scandalous Ministers may be removed, and former superstitions and corruptions, still tenaciously retained by many, to the hurt of ignorant persons, and prejudice of such Ministers as desire to be <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg>, may be reformed, and that those disorders and disturbances which daily break out in matters of Religion, may be rectified.</p>

<p>That the Augmentations to Ministers already made, may be more equally, and impartially distributed: And for all these ends, that some <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> and Godly men may be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> in this County, So as we may not be necessitated upon every occasion to repair to <em>London</em>, where many necessary things are not prosecuted, by reason of the <reg orig="tediousnesse">tediousness</reg>, and great <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of such journeys.</p>

<p>That Courts of Judicature may be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in this great County, it having been under consideration, and a great <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> therein made formerly in Parliament upon the Petitions of the people in these parts, for the preventing of excessive <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg>, and other inconveniences in <reg orig="Law-suits">Lawsuits</reg>, occasioned by the <reg orig="remotenesse">remoteness</reg> of this County from the City of <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>That some way may with all <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> be directed and <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> for <em>Probates of Wills</em> within the same County.</p>

<p>And that these Courts may be without unnecessary appeals to <em>London</em>.</p>

<p><i>Thanks was returned by his Highness to the City of <em>York</em>, the Grand Jurors of Assize there, and to the Gentlemen the presenters.</i></p>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em>, 28 March. Our forces from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> have taken 60 Horse, and 36 Prisoners beyond <em>Dunbarton</em> Castle. Since which one of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Captains was taken near <em>Haddington</em>, with six more. About 50 Gentlemen are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> from the West to the Hills, with good Horses, Arms, &amp;c of which <unclear><!-- approx. 13 characters --></unclear><pb n="4" /> and two of the Lord <em>De la <reg orig="Banks">Bank's</reg></em> Brothers. <em>Glencairne, Kenmore, Athol, Forbs</em>, and <em>Glengary</em>, &amp;c. are gone Northward to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton, Seafort</em>, and the Lord <em>Ray</em>, and so to force <em>Southerland</em>, and <em>Caithness</em>, to rise with them; their return it is thought will be about a fortnight hence. <em>Seafort, Middleton</em>, and <reg orig="Rayes">Ray's</reg> men, <reg orig="suprized">surprised</reg> a Vessel of ours going to the <em>Lewis</em> by some Boats they sent out; we had in her 14 men, Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg> for that Garrison. <em>Middleton</em> hath besieged <em>Cinker</em> Castle in <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, but they bad him defiance. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> returned from <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> the 21. instant over the Hill for <em>Aberdeen</em>. The Enemy have been cruel in burning and destroying the Country that do not freely <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; yet Sir <em>James <reg orig="Mac Donald">McDonald</reg></em>, and the Captain of the <em>Clan <reg orig="Renolds">Reynolds</reg></em>, are in arms against <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, for preservation of their <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em> had this day audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at the <reg orig="Cock-pit">Cockpit</reg>, attended by Sir <em>Oliver <reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg></em> Master of the Ceremonies, and many Gentlemen, there being also divers of the Lords of the Council present with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>The Committee for approbation of Ministers sat this Day, chose their Register, and other Officers, and began to proceed in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> according to the Ordinance of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector. The place they sit in is Whitehall, at the end of the stone Gallery, at the corner of the Court, and they have appointed to sit on <reg orig="Mondayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg>, and Fridays.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em>, the 16 of March, 1654. The ships which have been taken up at <em>Leghorn</em> for the service of our State have order to go directly from thence to <em>Candia</em>, and not come to this City. The <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> <em>Moccenigo</em> is also ready to depart from hence, there being Eight ships appointed to carry him, the State having ordered that he carry with him Three hundred thousand Duckets; in his way he is to stop a <em>Zante</em>, there to take with him the <reg orig="Commandour">Commander</reg> <em>Cornare</em>, and afterwards put him in possession of the place of General in <em>Candia</em>; from whence we hear, that the Generalissimo <em>Foscolo</em> having divided his Fleet into three Squadrons, is pursuing the <em>Caravana</em> of <em>Alexandria</em>, which is composed of many great and small vessels, and doth bring the Tribute which the great Turk <unclear><!-- 1 complete line cut off bottom of photocopy --></unclear></p><pb n="5" />

<p>That our General <em>Delsino</em> is now in good earnest resolved to besiege <em>Clim</em>, having already landed his Ordinance at <em>Sebenico</em>, and given the Rendezvous to his forces which are to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> in that design.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em>, the 11th of March 1654. The 5th instant the Knight <em>Baptista Brancaccio</em> had audience of our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg>, whom he complimented in the name of the great <reg orig="Commandour">Commander</reg> of <em><reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg></em>. The mount <em>Vesuva</em> having again cast out flames and ashes in abundance, caused the Bells to be tolled in many Churches, whither the people resorted to their Devotions. The two Galleys which had transported monies, and ammunitions, to those places which the King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> holds in <em><reg orig="Toscany">Tuscany</reg></em>, and are returned again, having left all those places in a very good condition.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 4.</i></head>

<p>This Day was published an Ordinance by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for probate of Wills, and granting Letters of Administration; Whereby it is ordained, That the Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>. <em>An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations</em>: And all the Powers, Authorities, Matters and things therein contained, shall be, and are hereby revived and continued, in full power and force, to all intents and purposes, until further Order. And further ordained, That <em>Richard Lucy, John Hildesley, Nathaniel Barton, Jervas <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg>, Anthony Rous, Joachim Mathews, Edward Cludd, Thomas Wood</em>, Esqs; and <em>Robert Tichbourn</em> Alderman of <em>London</em>, be added to the Judges named in the the said act, and in this present Ordinance, or any three of them, be, and are hereby authorized to put in execution all and every the powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named might have done by force of the said Act.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance prohibiting Cock-matches to this effect. That whereas the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> meetings and assemblies of People in several parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cock-fighting are by experience found to tend many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practices, to the dishonour of God, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of Persons and <unclear><!-- approx. 12 characters --></unclear></p><pb n="6" />

<p>For prevention thereof it is ordained, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publik">public</reg> or set meeting or assemblies of any Persons within <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, upon matches made for Cock-fighting, And that every such meeting and assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an <reg orig="unlawfull">unlawful</reg> assembly, and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be punished: And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, Majors, Bailiffs, Constables, and Headboroughs within their several Counties, Cities, Limits and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg>, hinder, and disperse all such meetings and assemblies.</p>

<p>This day the Agent from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had audience given him by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and divers Lords of the Council present.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsalia</em> March 3. The Queen came from <em>Westraas</em> on Sunday last, and it is reported that the Prince <em>Palatine</em> hath accepted of the Propositions, since which Summons are issued for the calling together the States of this Nation by the 2. of May next, before which time we shall hardly hear <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> more of this great and strange <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>. Don <em>Piemontel</em> the <em>Spanish</em> Resident is remanded home by his Master, who intends to take his journey over land within this fortnight or thereabouts. We are not likely to receive any answer until the certainty of our Treaty with the Dutch is known, and I believe, when that is understood we shall be dispatched, and that to our contentment. From <em>Bristol</em>, April 1. We have little news here, but of continued losses. The <em>Charity</em> of above 100 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, taken by two <em>Brest</em> men of war, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> her port in <em>France</em>, the Master whereof they detain for that villain <em>Beach</em>; besides this ship of <em>Bristol</em>, they took a Vessel of <em>Westchester</em>, and a day or two before four Vessels of <em>Weymouth</em>, and the Western parts: The <em>Wild boar</em>, also of 250 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> 40 guns, taking in some lading at the <em>Mederas</em>, and intending for <em>Barbados</em>, was forced by a storm to cut Cable, and to Sea, where he met with a <em>Flushinger</em> of 22 guns, whom with those men she had she fought stoutly, till being overmastered, she was brought into <em>Cadiz</em>, the ship and goods worth 5000 l. belonging to honest men, as Mr. <em>Speed</em>, who hath lost 280 l. <em>sterl</em>. <em>James Powel</em>, Capt. <em>Beal, Jeremy Holwey</em>, and several Families, who usually trade to the Western <reg orig="Ilands">Islands</reg>: most of the best ships of this Port are lately taken, especially by the <em>Brest</em> men. This City by <unclear><!-- another whole line cut off the bottom the page, in fact it could be two lines --></unclear>.</p><pb n="7" />

<p><em>Paris April</em> 8 1654. The Commissioners for the Protestants of <em><reg orig="Languedock">Languedoc</reg></em> are here still, and have neither had audience, and as little hopes to have any, being paid with delays from time to time, and nothing effected. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is at last removed from the Castle of <em>Vicennes</em>, and went the first night to <em>Chilli</em>, and so to <em>Amboise</em> taking the way towards <em>Nantes</em>, where he is to remain in the Castle until a further Order.</p>

<p>The same day the Abbess of St. <em>Antonie</em> in the fields having made great preparations for the solemnizing of <em>Easter</em>, among which was that which they call a fiery <reg orig="chapell">chapel</reg>, it <reg orig="hapened">happened</reg> that one of the Lamps, not being well <reg orig="fastned">fastened</reg>, fell down, and set all their <reg orig="fabrick">fabric</reg> on fire, and having found much combustible matter, it was soon reduced to ashes, the whole house being in great danger to be burned to the ground. We hear from <em><reg orig="Rochell">Rochel</reg></em>, that there is of late gone from hence one ship, who carrieth some <reg orig="Friers">Friars</reg> who go to <em>Sale</em> in <em><reg orig="Barbarie">Barbary</reg></em>, there to redeem such of that Nation who are slaves among the Infidels, having carried good store of money to that effect. The Report is here, That the Cardinal <em>Mazarin's</em> Father is to remain at <em>Rome</em> as <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> in Ordinary, and that he is made Duke and Peer of <em>France</em>, and likewise a <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="ribband">ribbon</reg> sent him, being made Knight of the Order called of the <em>Holy Ghost</em>: This Cardinal having sped so well with his Nieces, intends to have more come from <em>Rome</em>, that so <em>France</em> may be well stocked with <em>Italian</em> breeders, although some that are here do not go off as he expected, there being obstructions to be removed before that those Marriages can be consummated: The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is returned to this City, and cannot yet brook well the hard proceedings used against his Brother; but yet to please his good Uncle the Cardinal, is forced to put a good face upon it to salve up the matter; The Duke <em>d' Amville</em> is sent again to the Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> to tamper with him, and <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> him to return to the Court, no promises being wanting to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him thereunto, and among others, that the Prince of <em>Conde</em> his Estate should be transferred unto his <reg orig="Sonne">Son</reg>, in case he will agree to a match between him, and one of his young Daughters. The Duchesse his Wife, hath taken very much to heart the imprisoning of her Brother the Duke of <em>Lorraine</em>, (who doth still continue to be a close prisoner) but as yet she can work nothing for the procuring his <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 5.</i></head>

<p>The Commission of the great Seal being <reg orig="alter'd">altered</reg>, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, and Sir <em>Tho: Withrington</em>, are sworn Commissioners for the custody of the great Seal of <em>England</em> for the Court of Chancery, by the Clerk of the Commonwealth, before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and his Council, in the Council chamber at Whitehall. The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em> who is now in <em>Sweden</em>, is also to be one with them.</p>

<p>This Evening between 6 and 7 a clock, the Lord <em>Lambert</em>, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, the Lord <em>Strickland</em>, and the rest of the English Commissioners, went to the Dutch Ambassadors at Sir <em>John Trevors</em>, in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coaches, with Mr. <em>Thurlo</em>, Secretary of State, and Mr. <em>Scobel</em> Clerk of the Council; and about 9 a clock at night totally finished the Ratification of Peace, and the Articles were then signed and sealed by the Lord Ambassadors on the one side, with full power from the States, and the Lord Commissioners with full power from the Lord Protector on the other side. And within 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> the Peace is to be ratified by the Principals on each part, and <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> proclaimed both in <em>England</em>, and the <reg orig="Low-Countries">Low Countries</reg>. To which purpose a Messenger was sent away for <em>Holland</em> this night, and is to return within the time aforesaid with the subscriptions of the States Generals and the particular Provinces.</p>

<p><em>Inverness</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, March 20. thus. These parts affords little more news of the Enemy (this week) <reg orig="then">than</reg> what I formerly gave you an account of. <em>Middleton</em> and his <reg orig="Crue">Crew</reg> continues still in <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> and <em>Sutherland</em>, in prosecution of their business; <em>Glencarne</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> with about 500 horse and foot marched by the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Badgenoth</em>, and faced <em>Ruthen</em>, where he sent the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Letter, and received <reg orig="under-written">underwritten</reg> the answer; they were expected to quarter at the head of <em>Loughnesse</em> the 17th instant, and having <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Glengary</em>, were afterward to march to <em>Middleton</em>. They expected <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> should follow them within one <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> march, of which if he failed<pb n="9" />, they feared he had deserted them. <em>Glengary</em> still threatens fire and and<!--good rep or typo?--> sword to them that fails of answering his Warrants for Levies.</p>

<p><i>For Capt. <em>John Hill</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Ruthen</em> Castle of Badenoch.</i></p>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>The last time I was in this Country, one of my Troopen named <em>Angus, <reg orig="Mac Pherson">McPherson</reg></em> being commanded to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> near the Castle, was by some of your Horsemen made a Prisoner, if you will <reg orig="doe">do</reg> me the favour to release him presently, and send him to me by this Bearer my Trumpet, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> oblige <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> upon my Honour, to release to you any other Prisoner of the same quality of yours, that shall happen to fall in my hands upon your desire made known unto me, who am</p>

<p><i><em>Sir</em>, Your affectioned Friend and Servant. <em>GLENCAIRNE</em>.</i></p>

<p>15 of March, from <em>Knigxsie</em>.</p>

<p><i>For the Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>My Lord,</i></p>

<p>Your Trooper is where he wants not that <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg> Usage which you may befit his quality and Condition, neither shall, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> you have one of ours of like quality to offer in exchange for him, until which time your Lordship must excuse my Detention of him; who am, My Lord,</p>

<p><i>Your humble Servant, <em>JO. HILL</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>Ruthen-Castle, March 15. 1653,</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 6.</i></head>

<p>An Ordinance was published for mending and keeping in better repair the <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg> in this Nation, the substance. That every Parish is to choose once in the year two or more <reg orig="Survayers">Surveyors</reg>, to serve one whole year. A Tax to be made for the payment of such charges as shall be requisite for that work, the Justices being <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> within the several limits of their Commission. That no <reg orig="Waggon">Wagon</reg> or Cart <reg orig="goe">go</reg> or travel upon the <reg orig="High way">Highway</reg>, having any more than five Horses, or Mares, or six Oxen, and one Horse, That to any party so offending, all<pb n="10" /> and every Constable hath power to stop all those that are supernumerary, or beyond the number specified, the party so offending, paying within seven days after the <reg orig="distresse">distress</reg> or <reg orig="seasure">seizure</reg> aforesaid, the Sum of twenty shillings for each Horse or <reg orig="Oxe">Ox</reg> so distressed or <reg orig="seased">seized</reg>, and in default thereof the Officer is <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to fell them, levy the fine and other charges ho hath been at for keeping of the said Horse or Oxen, and return the overplus to the party owner of them, That any Streets or Pavements in any City or Town Corporate, shall be counted as <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg>, and each respective Scavenger to be as a <reg orig="Survayer">Surveyor</reg> to his Parish, or Precinct: And lastly that the Act made in the time of Queen <em>Mary</em>, concerning the mending of the Causie between <em>Shaftsbury</em> &amp; <em>Sherbonne</em> shall be received and be in full force until the first of <em>September</em> 1662, you may see further at large by the Act <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> printed.</p>

<p><em>Paris April</em> 11 1654. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> being removed from <em>Vicennes</em> by the Marshal <em>de la Mesteray</em>, is now safe arrived at <em>Nantes</em>, and put into the Castle. The Court Emissaries give out that he is not to be long there, but in a few days to be set at liberty, only that his Majesty desireth satisfaction upon some certain points, although the main drift is to make him surrender his place of Archbishop of this City. The Commissioners of <em>Languedoc</em> cannot yet prevail in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> upon their Complaints, but are like the Commissioners of <em>Catalonia</em>, who hitherto have prevailed no further than to receive many fair words, but nothing effectual, the main work now in hand is to find moneys speedily for the setting forth of the Army, that they may be in the field as soon as may be, and to that end the <em>Partizans</em> are not wanting to find out new ways for exacting of moneys, proffering large sums to be put into the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Coffers, the difficulty <reg orig="lyeth">lieth</reg> only in the effecting of it, by reason that the Country is in most places so exhausted of Moneys, that they are scarce able to live: The design for the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Coronation is now on foot again, and if I am rightly informed, it will be done about the middle of <em>May</em> next, which being done, his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> shall <reg orig="goe">go</reg> upon the borders and<pb n="11" /> down to <em>Picardie</em> to forward his Army in their Action, so much the rather, by reason that the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, whom we hear was last week at <em>Valciennes</em>, and then taking a view of his Army, is returned back to <em><reg orig="Braxells">Brussels</reg></em>, there to <reg orig="conferre">confer</reg> with the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em> for to obtain money and other necessaries for the march of his Army, that so they may fall to action as soon as the weather and season will give them leave, his Lady and <reg orig="Sonne">Son</reg> are still at <em>Rocroy</em>, where they are expecting some alteration to their present condition. The Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> hath not yet received any answer from the Court upon those proposals which he lately sent to the Court. We have news, that the Duke <em>Francis</em> hath at last accepted the command of his Brother the Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg></em> Army, and is expected there in a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, which our <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> doth not very well relish. The forces that were in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em> are now marching homewards, and are to be quartered in <em>Lorrain</em>.</p>

<p>The great preparations for an <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg> to go from <em>Marseilles</em> and <em>Toulon</em>, is much at a stand, only there are lately 5 great men of War gone to Sea, and three more are to follow, but upon no other <reg orig="designe">design</reg> than to <reg orig="robb">rob</reg> and plunder upon the Sea, sparing scarce any they encounter, whether they be friends or foes.</p>

<p>By the last Letters from <em>Warsovia</em>, thus. The <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> hath not only delivered up three very considerable places to the great Prince, or <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of <em>Moscovia</em>, for a pledge of his future security; but a further assurance hath caused himself to be re-baptized, after the Muscovite manner, which is taken so ill of the Priests that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and to all the Commonalty, that the greatest part of the Commanders, have refused to make any oath of allegiance unto the said Prince, upon this reason, that having sworn fidelity to the King of <em>Poland</em> at <em>Soczana</em>, and <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> never to bear Arms against him, they knew none could free them from that Oath, and thereupon have sent to the King, that if he pleased to send a general pardon, for what hath been acted by them, and the<pb n="12" /> rest of the Army, they will return with the major part of the Army into the <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, which have so incensed the General, that having caused them to be apprehended, they have lost their heads, which hath made much stir among the people.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>, the 28 <em>ditto</em>. After many conferences had between our Magistrates, and the <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg>, and the <em>Spanish</em> Commissioners, the treaty hath been brought to a perfection, and signed; which is in brief, That both French and Spaniards shall have a free passage through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em>, not committing any acts of Hostility upon each other, That the Spanish party, in point of satisfaction for the losses received from them and the <em>Lorrainers</em>, shall pay unto the said <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> the <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of Two hundred thousand Rixdollars, to be taken out of the Duke of <em>Lorrain's</em> Estate, and for security of performance shall put into the hands of the said Elector, the Lordship of <em>Kerpen</em>, and another in the County of <em>Galick</em> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> full payment.</p>

<p>From <em>Legorn</em> the 23 of March. As for news in these parts thus. The ships which are to go to serve the State of <em>Venice</em> in <em>Candia</em>, are near ready, and will set sail in a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, there being only a few men wanting of their <reg orig="compleatment">completement</reg>; this week in sight of this City was a sore fight between two ships at Sea, the one a Dutch man of <reg orig="warr">war</reg> of 32 guns, and the other an English ship called the Expedition, who was coming from <em>Zante</em> laden with currants, the fight continued above 6 hours, and at last, night having parted them, it so <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> that both ships sunk, most of the men were saved, and are now in this Town, but nothing is saved from them, although they were not <reg orig="farr">far</reg> from the shore, 3 French men of <reg orig="warr">war</reg> upon the Coast of <em>Apulia</em> in the Kingdom of <em>Naples</em> have of late done much harm, and taken many prizes, among whom is an English ship said to be of great value, taken at <em>Cape Spativento</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday April 7, 8.</i></head>

<p>This day was published and Proclaimed in <em>London</em>, an Ordinance for Adjourning part of <em>Easter</em> Term, 1654: Which<pb n="13" /> for better publication, and notice to all Men, as well in Country, as City, we have inferred at large, as followeth.</p>

<p><i>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to Adjourn part of the next Term of Easter; Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council. That part of the said term of Easter now next coming be Adjourned, That is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em> unto the first Return of Trinity Term called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>: And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or Commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day, or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, and during the said term, called <em>Easter Term</em> may tarry at their dwellings, or where their <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> shall lie, without resorting any of the said Courts for that Cause, and without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf. And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that the Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, giving them Authority to Adjourn the said Term of <em>Easter</em> as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the first return, called <em>Quindena Pasc&aelig;</em>, until the first return of <em>Trinity Term</em>, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em> as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made as aforesaid, And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that all the Matters, Causes, and<pb n="14" /> <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> depending in any of the said Courts shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the Chief Market Towns within their several and respective Counties.</i></p>

<p><em>Dalkieth</em>, April 3. The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> relates the Northern news, To which I have only to <reg orig="adde">add</reg>, That Captain <em>Sherwin</em> Commander of the <em>Primrose</em>, and Captain <em>Smith</em> Commander of the <reg orig="Dutchesse">Duchesse</reg>, in their Return from <em><reg orig="Orknay">Orkney</reg></em> took a Dutch Vessel laden with French, and Spanish Wines, <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg> Cloth, and other good Commodities, bound for the West Indies, which they sent into <em>Aberdeen</em>.</p>

<p><em>Aberdeen</em>, March 28. 1654. The Earl of <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> is come to <em>Glencarne</em> with about 700 Horse and Foot, <em>Seaford</em>, and some new raised Forces by him are daily expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. <em>Glencarne</em> with his whole Force, being 2000 Horse and Foot, is at <em>Dingwell</em>, two miles from <em>Braban</em>, not undeserving the name of an Island, which gives hopes of <reg orig="engageing">engaging</reg> the Enemy there. In order to which, Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Mitchil">Mitchell</reg></em> is to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> towards <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em> with 9 Companies of Foot, and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan follows him the day after with 5 Troops of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Rich</em> his Regiment, and four Troops of Dragoons. He intends to take with him <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment, which is in his way, and to draw Five Companies of Foot out of <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Some young Lairds and others that had a purpose to glean a party of Horse in Lothian, and so repair to the Enemy, were lately taken, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> Prisoners to <em>Dalkeith</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Cowes</em> in the <em>Isle of Wight</em>, April 6. A <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of <reg orig="warr">war</reg><pb n="15" /> hath brought in two days since two small French Vessels; the one laden with salt, the other hath little in her but ballast; there is nothing more of our fleet, but that they are the most part near to <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point, and the rest at the Spitts head, being in all <reg orig="neare">near</reg> 100 sail, gallant ships, and bravely accommodated; here was likewise the Holland ship taken by one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, who had 8 Bales of Paper, and some small quantity of Indigo, and she is <reg orig="caried">carried</reg> to <em>Portsmouth</em>: here are at present several Merchant ships in this road, being wind-bound, and expecting some Eastern winds to carry them on their voyage, and many that were here, went away yesterday morning towards the Downs.</p>

<p>From <em>Deale</em> the 7 instant: The Ships which were in this Road are for the most part gone up into the Thames, there remaineth only a few which are bound to the Southward, this day also passed by about 40 or 50 Sail of ships great and small, which we suppose to be the <em>Dunkirk</em> Fleet bound for <em>London</em>; And this morning is gone one of our Men of War for <em>Holland</em> to get the ratification of the peace made with them, and an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from the Dutch Ambassadors of the Agreement.</p>

<p>To say something further of the Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, because we find many so hard to give credit to it, The Articles of the Treaty (we assure you) were Signed and Sealed by thee Commissioners on both sides, on <em>Wednesday</em> night last (as before expressed) and within 14 days are to be Signed and Sealed by the Lord Protector, and the States of <em>Holland</em>; and then to be <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> proclaimed and published, both in <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> in one day. The agreement with Denmark is also taken in upon the Articles; And for the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> sustained by the English Merchants, whose demands amounts to about 150000 l. It is referred to two English, and two Dutch Merchants absolutely to determine those demands within twenty days, and their place of sitting appointed at <em>Guildhall</em>: Also the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of <em>Amboyna</em> is referred to 8. Commissioners, who have six <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg> time to determine thereof, and in case they agree not, Umpires are nominated.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>