<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfOcc4">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
Perfect Occurrences, Issue 4
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">Perfect</head> 
<head level="1">Occurrences,</head>
<head level="2">Faithfully <unclear><reg orig="comunicating">communicating</reg></unclear>,</head>
<p><i>A great and bloody fight obtained against the Highlanders in <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>; with a List of the names of the prisoners taken, and the loss on both sides: Also, an Ordinance for the relief of prisoners and creditors; and the names of the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> that are to sit constantly concerning the same. Likewise, the erecting an High Court of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> for the trying of all the plotters, and prisoners now in the Tower, <reg orig="Iameses">James'</reg>, Fleet, Gatehouse, and other places: With a List of the names of the names of the Commissioners that are appointed for the same, Together with the last Letters from the K. of Scots and divers other parts.</i></p>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Friday</em> <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 9. to <em>Friday</em> <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 16. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Friday</em> <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 9.</head>
<p>A Letter came this day to my hands certifying that there hath been a great engagement between the two Armies in Scotland, and that we have totally routed their whole body. The full particulars whereof you <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have in the next:</p>
<pb n="1" />
<head level="3"><em>Saturday <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 10.</em></head>
<p>By Letters from Newcastle it is thus signified, that about 40 sail of Colliers are come from thence, for London, and other <unclear>ports</unclear>, and, that another fleet are almost ready to <unclear><reg orig="hoyst">hoist</reg></unclear> sail.</p>
<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, that the General, for want of provisions for his horse, is returned again to <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> and can by no means possible engage the enemy, who intends conjunction in our absence, and then to play their game on the Lowland. Divers other prisoners have made their escape out of <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Castle; as the Earl of <em><reg orig="Kinoul">Kinoule</reg></em>, the L. <em>Lugton</em>, Col. <em>Hay</em>, Lieut. Col. <em>Montgomery</em>, who broke his neck, by the breaking of a piece of sheet, in his escape. The rest got safe <reg orig="a way">away</reg>, and a <reg orig="centinel">sentinel</reg> with them, Besides many others have made an escape out at a little hole; but one Capt. Ward, having a great head had not wit enough to get forth.</p>
<p>As touching the business of the late Plot, many from beyond Sea should have come to have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> in this <reg orig="Bloudy">Bloody</reg> massacre throughout all England; and cap Foster commander of the <reg orig="Phenix">Phoenix</reg>, coming from <em>Callice</em> affirms, That all Shallops belonging to that town were taken up for transportation of the Cavalry, in case this timely discovery had so happily taken effect.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of the prisoners in custody about the plot, daily under examination.</i></head>
<p>Sir Richard Willis, Sir Gilbert Gerhard, Col Gerhard. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Gerhard, Col, Ashburnham, Esq. mr. John Wiseman, Agent. <em>Mr.</em> <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Finch, <em>Mr.</em> Peter Vowel, Tho. Sanders Silkman, <em>Mr.</em> Baggaly, Secretary to the late E. of <em>D</em>erby, <em>Mr.</em> Mason a Fencer at <reg orig="Iameses">James'</reg>, Col. Aldridge, formerly under the Earl of Essex. Col. <unclear>Villers</unclear>, Col. Honywood Dr. <unclear>Naudin</unclear>, <em>Mr.</em> <reg orig="Iones">Jones</reg>, <em>Mr.</em> Tho. Brown, <em>Mr.</em> <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Brown. <em>Mr.</em> <pb n="2" /> Gifford, <em>Mr.</em> Hanford, Robert Skerow Henry Taylor, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Wharton, Thomas Barns, Nich. Watson Wil. Dod, Francis Fox, Summerset Fox Thomas Fox, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Brooks, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Goodwin, Henry, <unclear>Peirce</unclear>, Francis Newbow, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Pearsel, Henry <unclear>Barwieks</unclear>, Robert Fickegot. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Andrews, <reg orig="Ieremy">Jeremy</reg> Ellis, Robert Wiseman, Thomas Vinet, <em>Mr.</em> Harlow, Fane Hake,</p>
<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 12</i></head>
<p>This day passed an Ordinance for the erecting of a high Court of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>, to try all the plotters prisoners in the Tower, St. <em><reg orig="Jameses">James'</reg>, Fleet, Gatehouse</em> and other places. The <reg orig="Commissionets">Commissioners</reg> therein are 30. in number, and any 13. of them are to be a Court; the Commissioners therein named are, <reg orig="Iudg">Judge</reg> <em>Atkins</em>, Mr. Barron <em>Nicholas</em>, <reg orig="Iudg">Judge</reg> <em>Asks</em>, the Lord Commissioner <em>Lile</em>, Mr. Recorder <em>Steel</em>, Alderman <em>Titchbourn</em>, Mr. Alderman <em>Allen</em>, Mr. Alderman <em>Underwood</em>, Mr. Alderman <em>Estwick</em>, Mr. Alderman <em>Phillips</em>, Mr. Alderman <em>Atkins</em>, Mr. <em>Edward Winslow</em>, and these are to Proceed and try according to the late Ordinance for High Treason and <unclear><reg orig="m sprision">suspicion</reg></unclear> of treason lately made by his Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>. The Court will begin to sit the next week.</p>
<p>We hear from <em><reg orig="Lisbone">Lisbon</reg></em>, that there hath been a conspiracy against the King of <em>Portugal</em> discovered, and divers of the Plotters taken. Four ships from Venice going for Candia were cast away by a storm. The Spaniards take the ships of Genoa they meet at Sea; they are <unclear><reg orig="sitttng">sitting</reg></unclear> at Genoa 10 Galleys and 4000 men for their defence, and send to France for help, but have sent some Deputies to treat with the King of Spain for peace.</p>
<pb n="3" />
<head level="3"><i>Tuesday <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 13.</i></head>
<p><i>This day was published an Ordinance for enabling the <reg orig="Judg">Judge</reg> or Judges of the <reg orig="Northen">Northern</reg> Circuits, to hold <unclear>Assizes</unclear> and <reg orig="Gools">Goods</reg> delivery at Durham.</i></p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of the Judges appointed to go the Circuits for this <reg orig="Lummers">Summers</reg> Assizes</i></head>
<p><i>1 Berks &amp;c. Lord chief Justice St. <reg orig="Iohns">Johns</reg>, and Sergeant <em>Glyn</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>2 <em>Hertford</em> &amp;c. Baron <em>Pepe</em></i></p>
<p><i>3 <em>Bucks</em> &amp;c. <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Atkins</em>, and <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Aske</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>4 <reg orig="Forthern">Northern</reg> Circuits, <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Windham</em>, and <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Newdigate</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>5 Western Circuits, <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Roll</em>, and Baron <em>Thorpe</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>6 <em>Warwick</em> &amp;c. <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> <em>Hales</em>, and Baron <em>Nicholas</em></i>.</p>
<head level="3"><i>A List of the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Assizes in the several Counties</i>,</head>
<p><i>1 <em><reg orig="Barkshire">Berkshire</reg></em> <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> 14 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Abbington</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>2 <em>Oxfordshire</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 17 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Oxford</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>3 <em><reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg></em> Friday 21 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>.</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Monmouthshire</em> Wednesday 26 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Monmouth</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em>Herefordshire</em> <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> 28 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Hereford</em>,</i></p>
<p><i>6 <em>Worcestershire</em> and the City, 2 August at <em><reg orig="Worecester">Worcester</reg></em>.</i></p>
<p><i>7 <em>Staffordshire</em> Saturday 5 August at <em>Stafford</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>8 <em>Salop</em> Thursday 10 August at <em>Bridgenorth</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>1 <em>Hartfordshire</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 17 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Hartford</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>2 <em>Essex</em> Wednesday 19 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Chelmsford</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>3 <em>Kent</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 14 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Maidstone</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Sussex</em> <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> 28 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Horsham</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em>Surrey</em> Tuesday 1 August at <em>Kingston</em>. upon Thames.</i></p>
<p><i>1 <em>Bucks</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 17 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em><reg orig="Chepping Wiccomb">Chipping Wicomb</reg></em>.</i></p>
<pb n="4" />
<p><i>2 <em>Bedford</em> Thursday 20 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Bedford</em></i>.</p>
<p><i>3 <em>Huntington</em> Saturday 22 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Huntington</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Cambridge</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 24 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Cambridge Castle</em>,</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em>Suffolk</em> <reg orig="Wednesdny">Wednesday</reg> 26 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Bury St. Edmonds.</em></i></p>
<p><i>6 <em>Norfolk</em> and <em>Norwich</em> 1 August at <em>Norwich</em>.</i></p>
<p><i><em>Yorkshire</em>, and <em>York</em> City <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 17 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>York</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>2 <em>Durham</em> Wednesday 26 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Durham</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>3 <em>Northumberland</em>, and <em>Newcastle</em> Tuesday 1 August at <em>Newcastle</em>,</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Cumberland</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 7 August at <em>Carlisle</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em><reg orig="Westmorland">Westmoreland</reg></em> Thursday 10 August at <em>Appleby</em>,</i></p>
<p><i>6 <em>Lancashire</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 14 August at <em>Lancaster</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>1 <em>Hampshire</em> <reg orig="Tursday">Thursday</reg> 20 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>Winchester</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>2 <em>Wilts</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 24 <reg orig="Iuly">July</reg> at <em>New Sarum</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>3 <em>Dorset</em> Thursday 27 at <em>Dorchester</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Cornwall</em> Wednesday 2 August at <em><reg orig="Lanceston">Launceston</reg></em>.</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em>Devonshire</em>, and <em>Exeter City</em> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 7 at <em>Excester</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>6 <em><reg orig="Summersetshire">Somersetshire</reg></em> <reg orig="Mtnday">Monday</reg> 14 August at <em>Wells</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>1 <em>Warwickshire</em> Wednesday 23 August at <em>Warwick</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>2 <em>Coventry</em> City <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> five &amp; twenty. August at <em>Coventry</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>6 <em><reg orig="Leycestershire">Leicestershire</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Leycester">Leicester</reg></em> Burrough, eight &amp; twenty August at <em><reg orig="Leycester">Leicester</reg></em>.</i></p>
<p><i>4 <em>Derbyshire</em> Thursday 31 August at <em><reg orig="Derbey">Derby</reg></em>.</i></p>
<p><i>5 <em>Nottinghamshire &amp; Nottingham</em> Town 4 September at <em>Nottingham</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>6 <em>Lincolnshire</em> and <em>Lincoln</em> Town, 7 September at <em>Lincoln</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>7 <em>Rutland</em> Tuesday 12 September at <em>Okeham</em>.</i></p>
<p><i>8 <em>Northampton</em> Thursday fourteen Septem. at <em>Northampton</em> Castle.</i></p>
<p>From Portsmouth we hear that a man in the swift-sure <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> turning the <reg orig="biskets">biscuits</reg>, and drying the room with Rosin, was <reg orig="choaked">choked</reg> and <reg orig="dyed">died</reg>.</p>
<pb n="5" />
<head level="3"><i>Wednesday <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 14.</i></head>
<p>This day an ordinance passed for the relief of Creditors and poor prisoners, wherein are made <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> Mr <em>Nathaniel Bacon</em>, Mr. <em>Francis Bacon</em>, Mr. <em>John Wilsby</em>, Mr <em>Peter <unclear>Brereton</unclear></em>, Mr. <em>Henry Pit</em> Mr. <em>Peter Elliston</em> Mr. <em>John Aldsworth</em>, Mr. <em>Edmand Giles</em>, Mr. <em>Clement <unclear>Jreton</unclear></em>, Mr. <em>Arthur Barnardiston</em>. Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Parker</em>, and <em>Robert Warcup</em>, but he is but <em>Durant bene placito</em>, I shall not need to repeat the particulars of the Ordinance, because it will be out speedily, but this in general the prisoners never had a better law, and very <reg orig="mercifull">merciful</reg> and gracious to all prisoners in debt.</p>
<p>From Paris we are thus certified, that K. <em><reg orig="Lewis">Louis</reg></em>, and the whole Court, are gone to <em><reg orig="Rhims">Rheims</reg></em>, to perform the grand ceremony of Coronation, the little Queen and the Dukes of York and <unclear><reg orig="Cloucester">Gloucester</reg></unclear>, are to be present; but the K. of Scots is <reg orig="othetwise">otherwise</reg> designed, and divers Princes of the Royal <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, as the Dukes of <em>Orleans, Beaufort</em>, &amp;c. are inclined to the contrary. <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>Tureen</em> has taken the field with ten thousand horse &amp; foot, where the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> other General Marshal <em>de la Forte Seneterre</em> is <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with him; yet the <em>Spaniard</em> has got <em><reg orig="Mim">Him</reg></em>, by the <reg orig="fore lock">forelock</reg> and the Prince of <em>Conde</em> draws up too; but what attempts they will make, is yet uncertain; for <em>Conde</em> is rather for an inroad, and a Field fight, <reg orig="then">than</reg> digging before Towns: if he become Master of the field, Towns will follow, and perhaps a party appear for him. To speak truth they have so many Irons in the fire, and the affections of the people so wavering, that if no peace be had with England, they will soon by in flames.</p>
<p>By an express From Scotland thus: Gen. <em>Monck</em> hath set considerable Guards upon three most eminent <unclear>parties</unclear> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Brayes, where our parties appearing early in the morning took six of the Enemies Scouts, <pb n="6" /> and <reg orig="alarum'd">alarmed</reg> <em><reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Brigade, Lieut. <em>Goff</em> commanding a party of ours, met with a party commanded by Cap. <em>Forester</em> (kinsman to the Lord <em>Forester</em>) who drew up into a body, which Lieut. Coff perceiving, commanded his (being about 40) to give the Enemy a <reg orig="thorow">thorough</reg> charge, and his <reg orig="frontires">frontiers</reg> not to give fire until they came within pistol shot of the enemy, who came galloping down a hill, and gave fire at 20 yards distance, which gave us such advantage that we <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> rode up, <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> on with swords and pistol totally routed them, yet in the pursuit could take but six prisoners besides the Captain, which we have no great cause to brag of by reason that not long before they took as many more of ours, whom they used most inhumanely, not only by wracking but by hanging, yet had not the power to execute them: for it pleased God to dispose and determine by his especial providence, that the first five that were <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> off the Ladder brake their ropes three times together, which did so astonish the enemy, that a pardon was granted, but the prisoners (as yet) detained.</p>
<head level="3"><i>Thursday June 15.</i></head>
<p>This day a Resident from the <reg orig="Republick">Republic</reg> of <em>Genoa</em> had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
<p>A <unclear><reg orig="Gentle woman">Gentlewoman</reg></unclear> was this day committed, who had been taken away from her father by one with whom she married.</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Whitlock</em> is shortly expected with the Agreement. The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> summoned an Assembly in which she commanded the Lord Chancellor to declare her purpose to resign the Government, which after three times calling upon, though <reg orig="unwilingly">unwillingly</reg>, it being his place he did, The Speaker of the Nobility declared their wishing she would continue, but accepting of it, so did the Speaker of the Gentry; but the Speaker <pb n="7" /> of the Bores begged of her that it might not be, lest they suffer by tyranny, or worse oppression by a change And when all the speakers came up to the Throne, and kissed her hand, the speaker of the Bores Begged of her that she should not so degenerate from the spirit of her Ancestors to lay down the Crown. <reg orig="A nother">Another</reg> Assembly is appointed, and the young Prince <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> to be there.</p>
<p>From <reg orig="Hamamburgh">Hamburg</reg> we received Intelligence thus. Though the fortress of bederks was sufficiently provided of all necessaries for a long siege, yet it hath been <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> by Capitulation to General <em>Conismark</em> of the <reg orig="sweeds">Swedes</reg>, having made but little resistance. The <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> have been shut up in a hole by order of the General until the Ammunition lately taken from the <reg orig="sweedes">Swedes</reg> by the <reg orig="Majestaates">Magistrates</reg> of <em>Bremen</em>. A great treason hath lately been discovered in the place, the Authors whereof are apprehended, who were to <reg orig="sit">set</reg> the Town on fire in two places, and <reg orig="theredy">thereby</reg> <unclear>ray</unclear> it to the <reg orig="sweads">Swedes</reg>. The Deputies of the states of the Lower Saxony, who were <reg orig="her">here</reg> assembled, are returned and kept their <reg orig="Resoutions">Resolutions</reg> very secret.</p>
<p>From Naples we are advertised thus. Our <reg orig="Vice Roy">Viceroy</reg> had seized all the barks of Genoa of Genoa in these parts, and obliged the General of our Galleys to disband the <reg orig="marriners">mariners</reg> and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of that nation, and to take <reg orig="n&aelig;opolitans">Neopolitans</reg> in their place; but <reg orig="uon">upon</reg> advice that divers Vessels of Genoa are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to fetch Corn for this City out of Apulia, to be <unclear><reg orig="rebenged">revenged</reg></unclear>, might run away to Genoa with their Charge, <unclear>he <reg orig="hat">hath</reg> <reg orig="aestored">restored</reg> <reg orig="al">all</reg> <reg orig="he">the</reg></unclear> vessels he had seized on. and re-established their trade. yet two men of war of <reg orig="outs">ours</reg>, with about two thousand foot <reg orig="a board">aboard</reg> of <unclear><reg orig="teem">them</reg></unclear> are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> that way, under <reg orig="pretance">pretence</reg> to be a Convoy for them against the French.</p>
<p>Finis</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>