<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc155">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 155</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, the Navy at Sea, and other transactions of, and in relation to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1653.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> Decemb. 21. to <em>Wednesday</em> Decemb. 28. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, Decemb.21.</head>

<p>That I may a little <reg orig=" satisfie"> satisfy</reg> the great expectation of the people, who desire to be informed the constitution of the Government now <reg orig="stablished">established</reg>; and for present satisfaction herein, you may briefly have it as followeth.</p>

<p>1. There shall be Triennial Parliaments the first to begin the third of September next.</p>

<p>2. That the Parliaments shall be <unclear>cho<!--cut off, prob == chosen--></unclear> by the people, according to certain qualifications too long to be inserted here.</p>

<p>3. That the time of their sitting shall be for 5 months and no longer.</p>

<p>4. Such laws as shall be agreed on in Parliament, shall be presented to the Lord Protector for his assent, which if it be not obtained within 20 days, then those Bills shall pass notwithstanding, and become law in full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>.</p>

<pb n="1" />
<p>5. Strict provision is made also for the succession of Parliaments, the management of Elections, and of Returns to be made by the several Sheriffs of the persons elected.</p>

<p>6. That the Lord Protector shall govern with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, the number of whom shall not be <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> thirteen, and not exceed twenty one.</p>

<p>7. That all Writs, Process, &amp;c. shall issue forth in the name of the Lord Protector; That Articles of War shall be made good; That the Ministry of the Gospel shall be maintained, and the present way of their maintenance continued, till some other way more convenient shall be found out and provided.</p>

<p>8. All Magistracy to be deprived from him, all hours to be conferred by him, Peace and War to be made by him, and the Militia by Sea and Land to be ordered by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and the major part of His <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday Decemb. 22.</head>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector.</head>

<p><i>A Proclamation of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, with the consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for continuing all persons being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> further direction.</i></p>

<p><em>Oliver</em>, Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland, considering, that whereas the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, is invested and established in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, And left thereupon the <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and ordinary course of Justice in the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (if remedy were not provided) might receive interruption, His Highness in His Care of the State, and <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Justice thereof (reserving to future consideration the reformation and redress of any abuses of Misgovernment <pb n="2" /> upon better knowledge taken thereof) is pleased, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, declare and ordain, by and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who have power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the meeting of the next Parliament to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, That all persons who on the tenth day of this instant December were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction of Government, within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, shall be, and shall so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and places respectively as formerly they held and <reg orig="injoyed">enjoyed</reg> the same, and not otherwise, until His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> pleasure be further known; And all Commissions Patents, and other Grants, and all Proceedings of what nature soever, in Courts of Common Law, or Equity, or in the Court of Admiralty, or by Commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said tenth day of December, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further Order given by His Highness therein, And that in the mean time (for preservation of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, and for Safety of the State) all the said Persons, of whatsoever Place, Degree or Condition, may not fail every one severally according to his respective place, Office or Charge, to proceed the performance and execution of all Duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> the former Government was in being.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Given at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 21 of <em> December</em>, in the year of our Lord, 1653</i></head>


<pb n="3" />
<p> Those of His Highness <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> already chosen, and which now sit in the Old <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> Chamber at <reg orig="White-Hal">Whitehall</reg>, are these following, viz.</p>

<p>Major General Lambert, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Peter Jones.</p>

<p>Major General Desborough, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Mountague,</p>

<p>Mr. Henry Lawrence, Richard Major, </p>

<p>Sir Charles Worsley, Walter Strickland, Esq.</p>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Sydenham, Sir Gilbert Pickering,</p>

<p>Francis Rous, Esquire, Major General Skippon.</p>

<p>Philip Lord Viscount Lisle, Sir Anthony Ashley Cooper,</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Decemb. 23.</head>

<p>Barwick, Decemb. 19. We have intelligence, that a private man of War hath brought into Holy Island two Dutch vessels <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the East <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, both being about one hundred and fifty <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, laden with Pitch, Tar, and like commodities.</p>

<p>From Falmouth the 19 instant: There are many ships in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> which are now all gone to their several intended Ports; the Dutch are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts, so that it is very hard to pass by the Lands end, without a good Convoy; we hear they have taken a ship of London <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from New England, laden with masts, Beaver skins and the like commodities Here have been some of the states ships to wash and tallow, and to take in fresh water, but they are all at Sea again, there remaining none at present in this harbour.</p>

<p>From Deal the 23. We have news this day, that some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken some Beelanders belonging to Calice, who was bound for <reg orig="Roan">Rouen</reg> and <reg orig="Cane">Caen</reg> in Normandy, laden with <reg orig="divers">diverse</reg> sorts of commodities, and carried them into Stoaks Bay, where we hear that General Monk with his squadron was about four days since. Those ships lately gone from hence bound for <reg orig="Roan">Rouen</reg>, <reg orig="ore">or</reg> lately arrived there, and their convoy is returned back.</p>

<p>Further from Scotland, Decemb. 19. The enemies dispersing themselves into several parts is confirmed; they are now endeavouring to reduce their levies into form, by laying them them upon all the nearest Parishes to the hills, but their demands so high, that it is impossible the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> (though willing) should be able to bear them. We have information, that Kenmore will use all his endeavours to raise and force men, horses, and moneys in the South, and intends to make some inroads <pb n="4" /> into the borders of England, unless prevented; which is the more probable by that information which we received from Durham, That 20 horsemen well mounted, and armed with pistols and swords, went through that Town on Tuesday last by break of day, amongst them a person of Quality. The same number and party lay at Peblis on Saturday night last, and with them Col Wogan, formerly a Captain of Dragoons in the Parliaments Army. Thursday night last, Lieutenant Whitmore going with a party towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, took one Major Morehead (a prisoner of War, and yet upon parole and security) well mounted and armed, going to the Enemy, as himself <reg orig="confesd">confessed</reg>. They do much hearten their party, that their King is come into Holland; that Col. Drummond is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>, arms and ammunition; and that the Dutch have left off treating with the English: with all which they feign a Post came lately from their King. On <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> morning last a party of these Royal Pilferers met the Post boy coming from Lieth with Letters for London, and near Haddington took his horse and Letters, and some money, so that now it will be very uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy.</p>

<p>The Letters out of the West make mention of the <reg orig="predominancy">predominance</reg> of the <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> thereabouts, yet are several vessels safely arrived from the Canaries and Malaga.</p>

<p>The remainder of the English Fleet are hastening out of the River of Thames (and other Ports) and will be ready to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those already out, and then no doubt but they will quickly clear the seas both to the North and West.</p>

<p>There came Letters this week which say, That the Lord Ambassador Whitlock is well and safely arrived on the confines of Sweden.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, Decemb.24.</head>

<p>From <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> in France thus. The people are in great fear and discontent here, by reason of the building of two Castles near the City, for which they conclude that they are now a new enslaved with the Kingly Yoke, There is very <reg orig="lictle">little</reg> Trade, the Spanish men of War lying still about the rivers mouth. The Duke of Orleans is not yet come to Court, though he hath been often invited thither.</p>

<p>There is great preparations at Toulon for a Fleet to be ready next spring, and those men of war which were gone out with Letters of <unclear>Mart</unclear> are commanded in, and against they come, great store of Bisket is making,<pb n="5" /> and a good quantity of Arms and Ammunition; what the <reg orig="enterprize">enterprise</reg> will be is not yet known, where ever it happeneth.</p>

<p>It is certified from <reg orig="Edenbrough">Edinburgh</reg>, that the Writs issued out against persons in debt, do make many of the Lowlanders to run to the Highlands. It is said that there are about four thousand Writs issued out against several persons who have neither money, nor Estates to pay their Debts. Proposals therefore have been <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the Commander in chief for the relief of poor Debtors.</p>

<p>1. That the Debts of the inhabitants of Scotland, may be judged according to Law, and that those who are not able to pay their debts presently, may give security to pay it in a reasonable time, at a day appointed, without any <unclear>rise</unclear>.</p>

<p>2.That such as <reg orig="wil">will</reg> have benefit of the <reg orig="Infesment"> Investment</reg> upon land, may have the land made over to them at such a rate as it would have <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> at such time as the monies was lent upon it.</p>

<p>3. That the Act of pardon and Confiscation may be passed with much mercy for time past.</p>

<p>4. That a Proclamation be issued out, that after the said Act of Favour, those that are to receive benefit thereof, may be so curbed. That if any person <reg orig="contem">contempt</reg>, or shall thereafter rise in Arms against the Powers of the Commonwealth; that they be banished the three Nations, and all their Estates to be confiscated.</p>

<p>Captain Lisle of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg> Regiment having once of the Lord Kinnoul's raising new levies in Angus and Mearns, fell upon them with 100 Horse and Dragoons by the break of day, and took 40 horse, 19 private <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> Captains, 1 Cornet and a Quartermaster, and <unclear>killed nine</unclear> or ten more, being all of the Earl of <reg orig="Kinnouls">Kinnoul's</reg> Regiment.</p>
<pb n="6" />
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Decemb. 26.</head>

<p>This day came forth the Ordinance for the continuation of the Excise, which is to be managed and carried on by such good ways and means as may be most for the case of the people, and advantage of the Commonwealth.</p>

<p>It was this day advertised, that the titular King of Scots was coming down to Cleave, and that he was invited by the Duke of Brandenburgh, into his territories which are the furthest of Germany, whether he will move it is yet uncertain. Prince Rupert hath been often heard to lament, that he ever <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> himself in the late unnatural war in England, wherein so many <reg orig="mis-fortunes">misfortunes</reg> and such ill-will attended him.</p>

<p>There were some ministers this last week under custody, and examined before the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for preaching against the present Government, but promising more care for the future they were discharged.</p>

<p>It is advertised from Scotland, that the Highlanders new levies, and those that were in arms before, are all marched Northwards to receive monies, Arms, and Ammunition, which (it is told them) is sent from their King, and from the States of Holland. Those who stay behind are quartered in those Parishes amongst the Lowlands, which are nearest to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. The Lord Kenmore doth resolve (as it is informed) to raise men, horses, and <reg orig="mony">money</reg> on this side of <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and to make some <reg orig="Inrodes">Inroads</reg> into the Borders of England. Twenty horsemen well mounted and armed with pistols, and swords did very lately ride through Durham, and took up their Quarters at <em>Plebees</em>, where the dumb Prophet is still alive. It seems by this that they hold a correspondence with some in England, and that the Design is greater then represented.</p>
<pb n="7" />
<head level="3">Tuesday, Decemb. 27.</head>

<p>The treaty with the Dutch goes hopefully forward in order to an Agreement: The Dutch Ambassadors have sent the substance of what is propounded by the High and Mighty states of Holland; and it is conceived, that in a short time, much (more than now) may be known of that business. But however it goes, the Dutch are high in their preparations both at Sea and Land, and in February next their great Fleet will be ready to put forth to sea. The great ship lately built at Rotterdam, lies close up in harbour. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg> Agents are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts of late, and yet Middleton continues here, although much talk hath been of his going into Scotland, to the party up in arms there, which will make little of it: Yet to answer all Objections, they give out, that the Monsieurs of France will venture far in that service; and many other things are talked on, <em>and that I think is all.</em></p>

<head level="3">Thus have you an Account of</head>

<p><i>News from the English Fleet at Sea. The Transactions in Holland about Men, Arms, and Ammunition for the Highlanders in Scotland, with the Highlanders bold attempts in the North of England, and their seizing upon the English Post with Letters. The news of the Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> <reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg> landing safe in Sweden. The Treaty between the English and the Hollander, and other things of great importance.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>There is published five new plays in one <reg orig="vollum">volume</reg> <i>viz. The mad couple well <reg orig="matcht">matched</reg>; The Novella; The Court Beggar; The City Wit; and the <unclear>Damoisella</unclear>: <em>all written by</em> Richard Brown. A collection of those excellent Letters to several persons of Honour: <em>written by</em> John Donne <em>sometimes Dean of</em> St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <em>London. Likewise</em> a Poem called the <reg orig="Shepheards">Shepherd's</reg> Oracles, delivered in certain <unclear>Eglogues</unclear>: <em>by</em> Francis Quarls. And the Poems of John Donne <em>sometimes Dean of</em> St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <em>London</em>; with Elegies on the <reg orig="Authors">Author's</reg> death:</i> to which is added divers Copies under his own hand never before printed. All which are to be sold by <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Sweeting</em>, at the <reg orig="Angell">Angel</reg> in Popes-Head <unclear>Alley</unclear>.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>