<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn214">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 214</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><em>From Monday</em> January. 9. to <em>Monday</em>, January. 15. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Monday, January 9</i></head>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em> Jan 5. <em>Glencarn, Erwin</em>, and <em>Athol</em> were <unclear>about</unclear> <unclear>ten</unclear> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since <unclear>in</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> <unclear>with</unclear> about 2000 Foot, and 600. Horse, <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glengary</em> went North, having 400 Horse and betwixt 200 and 300 Foot. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> being acquainted with the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Proclamation, told his people, that all the horses they have will be taken away by the English, and hath thereupon given orders that his men should take all the horses they can lay their hands upon.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration by the Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent. That (notwithstanding my Proclamation of Septemb. 27. last) many serviceable Horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great disservice of the Peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much <reg orig="conivance">connivance</reg> of the Owners or Possessors; These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons who now are, or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable Horses or Mares, exceeding the value of 5l. sterling, to bring in the same within 48 hours, next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such Horses and Mares as shall not be brought in; the one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the use of the State, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to the party informing but also be deemed as an open enemy, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly; Which Horses and Mares so brought in, shall nevertheless be at the <reg orig="Owners">Owner's</reg> choice either to have meet satisfaction for them, as they shall be reasonably worth, or keep them within the said <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> or Quarters of our Army; and the respective Sheriffs and their Deputies within their Sheriffdoms, are hereby required to cause their presents solemnly to be <reg orig="proclaimd">proclaimed</reg> and published according to accustomed manner of publishing Proclamations. And afterwards (that none may pretend ignorance) to cause to be distributed to the several Presbyteries within their said Sheriffdoms a competent number hereof.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and Seal at Dalkeith, 14 Decemb. 1653.</i></p>
<p>R. <reg orig="LILBVRNE">LILBURNE</reg>.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>From <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> the same date thus: The last Week the Enemy had a <reg orig="Randezvouse">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Hough (a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of plain ground near <em>Weyme</em>.) The parts about <em>Weyme</em> are miserably waned, and the Gentlemen of <em>Atholl</em> ill resenting their oppression. <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarry</em> marched Northward, with about Eight hundred Horse and Foot; <reg orig="intonding">intending</reg> to meet <em>Seaforth</em> at <em>Lagon Morghamdrum</em>, where their whole Body intends to <reg orig="Randezvouse">Rendezvous</reg>. Before their going there was a falling out between <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarry</em>, and a Duel appointed, but prevented by the <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> and <reg orig="witts">wits</reg> of their Associates.</p>

<p><em>Wogan</em> with his <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg> are at present with <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Logiret</em>, well mounted, and armed, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> of them in rich <reg orig="apparell">apparel</reg>, which <reg orig="addes">adds</reg> encouragement to the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlander's</reg> fury, the Enemy have generally spoiled most of such horses as they have taken out of <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> stables, their bellies almost <reg orig="dryed">dried</reg> up with heats, too much corn, and ill dressing.</p>

<p>On Friday last the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Kinnoule</em> about Eight in the morning appeared <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Glans</em> with a party of Horse, consisting of seventy or <reg orig="thereaboutr">thereabouts</reg>, his <reg orig="designe">design</reg> was to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the Horse belonging to <em>Glans</em>, as they came from watering, lying in a covert place for that purpose, thinking thereby to increase his number, and to procure exchange for his men taken at <em>Eghill</em>, and coming at first with a small party riding into <em>Glans</em>, took three of our men, which Major <em>Ducker</em>, who commanded <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Riches">Riche's</reg></em> Troop there, having notice of it sent out his Quarter-master with Twenty horse to discover his party, who advancing with two files of Foot that were to make good a bridge, gave them a charge, and routed and dispersed their whole party, took the Lord <em>Kinnoule</em>, and fourteen men, all much wounded, and about thirty five Horse, and at the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> away of the Letter had sent a party to gather up the rest, all quitting their Horses, and betaking to the Boggs: Major <em>Ramsey</em> was there, but escaped, we had one man <reg orig="kild">killed</reg>, and seven wounded, all slightly<pb n="3" />, three of the Enemy were <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> on the Plain. <em>Glencairne</em> lately made this following Proclamation.</p>

<p><i><em>William</em> Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>, Lord <em>Kilmore</em>, Commander in Chief of all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of SCOTLAND.</i></p>

<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission from His Majesty granted to me for levying of Forces within the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of <em>Scotland</em>, for opposing the common Enemy, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> by these Presents Ordain <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Alexander Blacader</em> to Levy out of the Presbytery of <em><reg orig="Dumferling">Dunfermline</reg></em> a sufficient Troop of Horse, with one well armed man out of every thousand pounds of Rent, with Fortifications. If they fail after the fight of this my Order, the said <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Alexander Blacader</em>, or any having his power, is to seize on the Person of the Deficients, and carry them prisoners to the Army, drive their goods away until they do duty; and likewise they shall be esteemed Enemies to their King and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. Given at our Quarters this 16th of December, 1653.</p>

<p>Subscribed, <em>GLENCAIRN</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Italie">Italy</reg></em> and parts adjacent. The late Vice-king of <em>Naples</em> before his departure from that City, hath sent rich presents to divers noble men, as to the Prince of <em>Avellino</em>, and others: The Earl <em>de Castrigho</em> his successor is come to <em>Naples</em>, and hath taken possession of the Royal Palace, where he remaineth <em>incognate</em> until he hath made a Cavalcato from the Palace to the High-Church, as the manner is for the new Vice-kings to do at their first <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to that Kingdom, in the mean time he hath sent to the D. <em>Cirifalco</em> to send him a List of all the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg>, and other <reg orig="inferiour">inferior</reg> Officers of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>; as also of all prisoners, and the causes of their imprisonment.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em> thus. The last Letters come from <em>Malamocco</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> advise us, that the Turkish Navy is to winter into the <em>Archipelago</em>, thereby hoping to surprise our Vessels who upon several pretexts come to buy provisions in the Islands that are in that<pb n="4" /> Sea, which they afterwards carry to <em>Candia</em> to relieve that City; <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> many believe that their Galleys being so much out of repair, are not capable to do much service, and therefore <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought they will be forced to go back to <em>Constantinople</em>, there to be repaired and newly fitted for the Sea: Our Senate being certainly informed of the great <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg> fallen to the <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> <em>Fosculo</em>, they have thereupon made choice of the Lord <em>Moccenigo</em> to <reg orig="succed">succeed</reg> in his place, the Proveditor General being <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with all the Military affairs since the <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg> of the said <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg>, who being landed with some forces in the Island of <em>Zia</em> to gather contribution, there came to him four of the chiefest in the Island, who represented him that they were <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> disabled from paying any moneys, by reason that not long since the Turkish Galleys had visited them lately, and had got from them both money and provisions great store; but this excuse would not prevail, but he detained them, and hath sent them with twenty more to a place called <em>Castelrosso</em>, where they remain as prisoners, our ships are safely arrived at <em>Candia</em> with moneys and ammunitions,</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> December 26. We hear from <em>Stockholm</em> that the Plague doth rage much in and about the City, but most without the Walls, thereupon most of the Persons of Quality are fled into the Country; the Queen and a great part of the Nobility are at <em><reg orig="Ypsall">Upsall</reg></em> where they expect daily the English <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> the Lord <em>Whitlock</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Warsovia</em>: We hear that the Tartars and Cosacks are not in good intelligence together, yet by some prisoners we heard, that there had passed a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> <reg orig="Treatie">Treaty</reg> between the Kam of the <em>Tartars</em>, and the General of the <em>Cosacks</em>, who doth promise him great matters in case he can obtain his ends, whereof the chief is, that he might make a peace at advantage with the King of <em>Poland</em>, whose Army is now very strong, and doth consist in two bodies, which make in all one hundred thousand fighting men: therefore the King finding his Army in a very good condition, intends without any further delay to fight<pb n="5" /> with the Enemy who in all cannot make above 80 thousand men, the <em>Tartars</em> being 50 thousand, and the <em>Cosacks</em> but 30 thousand.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>: The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> had a mind to have spent some time <reg orig="neer">near</reg> that City in hunting, but news being come from <em>Hungaria</em>, that the Palatine of that Kingdom was dead, therefore his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> is stayed here, and hath sent thither the <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg>, and some other Ministers of State to quench a fire of division lately kindled among the Nobility and Gentry since the death of that Prince, and that without delay they cause the States of that Country to be summoned to meet the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> at <em>Presburgh</em>, and his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> intends to be there in person.</p>

<p>The Swedish Commissioners being come to several places in the Circle of <em>Westphalia</em>, for to get contribution for the payment of the Garrison of <em>Weekt</em> have returned without money, which was like to have bred ill blood, but that the Bishop of <em>Munster</em> hath pacified the matter. We hear from <em>Callen</em> that the great difference between that City and their <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> is now even agreed, the Mediators having reconciled all differences, and the Barges and Boats that were stopped at <em>Boone</em> are all freed.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 10</head>

<p>The Dutch Deputies are returned home, but no news since from <em>Holland</em>, what the Issue of the Treaty will be, a very short time will discover.</p>

<p>What we mentioned last Week of the loss the Dutch sustained by the great storm of fire, take a further <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> by the Extract of a Letter from <em>Amsterdam <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 6</em> as followeth. I cannot omit to acquaint you with the great <reg orig="sadnesse">sadness</reg> that is here; to wit the hand of God manifesting <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> by a very great and lamentable fire breaking forth in the night; it began at the South-end, in a Mill that beats hemp, called by the name of the <em>Reyger</em>, which could not be quenched in any wise by reason of the <reg orig="vehemency">vehemence</reg><pb n="6" /> of the wind. So that the fire <reg orig="over-running">overrunning</reg> that in the first place, with over-<reg orig="violency">violence</reg> consumed all to the very ground, as well in the South-end, and in all St. <em>Jarvis</em> Street, and the Meal-sacks neighbourhood, as also the Anabaptists Congregation House and a Church of ours, with the Church-house, and Town-house, leaving in the room much desolation. The number of houses destroyed as men compute, are between five and six hundred, besides the Busses, Boats, and fishing Vessels, whose number is not yet known. Thus the fire continued (being driven with the wind) as far as the <unclear><!-- approx 10 characters--></unclear>, the bridge in the way also being fired. Some men give out that the fire flew over into the Bemster, to the damage of many there. Moreover it is affirmed that divers people, great and small, have been overtaken by the fire, and burnt; but whether so or no, time will produce it to us. The <reg orig="sadnesse">sadness</reg> is here greater than I can intimate or transcribe God in his mercy preserve all people from such sad disasters, and doleful visitations. Farewell, and rest commended in the Lord; more particularly with the next.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, November 29. After that Captain <em>Welsh</em> had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, he put to Sea again, and met with two Hollanders riding at the <em>Scab</em>; the one 400, the other 350 Tons, laden with Wheat, <reg orig="Rie">Rye</reg>, Wool, and Planks, both which he took, and brought away with him, and by storm was forced to come a little way within this Port, but without the command of the Forts. The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> was earnestly pressed to send for the Captain, and to discharge the Prizes, but answer was given, That it was conceived a matter not appertaining either to himself, or to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Officers to meddle with; and believed, that the <reg orig="Queenes">Queen's</reg> Ports would not be <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> to any <reg orig="English-man">Englishman</reg>, who had Commission by Authority of Parliament, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> here to shelter himself against storms, That the Conflict had been upon the high Sea, betwixt the English and Dutch, who were enemies. For these Reasons, his Excellency the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> refused to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> any thing n it.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>This day some of Captain <em>Welsh</em> his men coming to this Town, were <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> and brought before the Landisher, who examined them, and sent his Major to the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, to know whether he would own the Captain; whereto the answer was given, that his Excellence did own him, as one who he did believe had had a Commission by Authority of Parliament; whereupon the men were dismissed. But our English people have the more trouble here, and the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> favour, because the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Admiral is a Hollander.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Madrid</em> of the 16th of December, 1653. Their Majesties are here in perfect health: Two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hence they go again to the <em>Escurial</em>, to be present at some Church service performed yearly in commemoration of the deceased Princes belonging to the House of <em>Austria</em>. There is to be seen in this City a copy of a Letter in Print sent from the Jesuits in <em>Armenia</em> to those in this City, wherein they express a very strange thing happened in that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which is thus briefly; There being about five <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> since many <reg orig="Turkes">Turks</reg> and <reg orig="Moores">Moors</reg> met together at a <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> called <em>Medinatvi</em>, (but commonly known by the name of <em><reg orig="Mecha">Mecca</reg></em>) in the <reg orig="Mosquee">Mosque</reg>, or <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, where the body of their false Prophet hath <reg orig="layn">lain</reg> many <reg orig="yeares">years</reg>; On a sudden, about ten of the clock in the <reg orig="forenoone">forenoon</reg>, this Iron Chest (which for many years hath been suspended in the roof of that house, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the <reg orig="Load-stone">Loadstone</reg> <reg orig="fastned">fastened</reg> there) did fall down to the ground, which immediately opened, and swallowed up both the Chest, and what was therein; the ground remaining open about one quarter of an hour, and in that space came forth of that <reg orig="Abysse">Abyss</reg> a great flame, and <reg orig="smoake">smoke</reg>, which <reg orig="rendred">rendered</reg> a great stench, and so the ground closed up as formerly; that thereupon all the Spectators fell on the ground, being struck with deadly <reg orig="feare">fear</reg> at so <reg orig="dreadfull">dreadful</reg> a spectacle, and some of them are since become Christians, leaving their superstitious service.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>.</em> 11.</head>

<p>The last news from <em>Warsovia</em> import that the King with all his Army, consisting of about eighty thousand men, Horse and Foot, was upon their march to encounter the Tartars and <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together, but remain a sunder, being in two distinct bodies: by some prisoners lately brought to his Majesty, we hear that the General of the Cossacks hath made a particular Treaty with the Kam of the <reg orig="Tartares">Tartars</reg> (which if true) will exclude him from making any peace or accommodation with the Crown of Poland.</p>

<p>From Regensburgh thus: The Diet is not yet concluded, there being new differences <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> between the Prince Elector, and his <reg orig="Unckle">Uncle</reg> the Duke of Simmereu, about the enjoying of some Land which each other pretended to be his: some Commissioners are appointed to examine the matter, and so to report it: as also some differences between the Landgraves William, and the Earnest of Hassia.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Dasseldorf">D&uuml;sseldorf</reg>: The Duke of Newburgh is still at Mulheim: being not well pleased with the Assembly met in this City, by reason that they have <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> him the sums of money which he demanded of them.</p>

<p>There is great fear in these parts, that the Lorrain forces will come to take their winter quarters in these<pb n="9" /> parts, so much the rather, by reason that the Electors of Mentz, Triers, and Cullen intended with main force to oppose them and prevent the same in case they attempt it by force of Arms; we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that some of them are marched <reg orig="alreadie">already</reg> from <reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg> to <reg orig="Limburgh">Limburg</reg>, and so along by Maestrick as if they purposed to come into the County of Gulick; some say also that part of the Prince of Condi his Forces are to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with them, they being more <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> and able to <reg orig="worke">work</reg> his <reg orig="designe">design</reg>.</p>

<p>The difference <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> the City of Cullen, and their Elector is <reg orig="neare">near</reg> agreed, he having set at liberty all the Barges and <reg orig="Boates">Boats</reg> which, by his Order had been stopped at Bonna.</p>

<p>From Italy and <reg orig="parth">parts</reg> adjacent thus: The Infanta Maria of Saucy is here at <em>Rome</em>, but yet as <em>incognito</em>; she intends to <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> here for some time. The Pope hath also given <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg> and other good Benefices to some of the <reg orig="Domestick">Domestic</reg> Servants, and appointed new Nuntios to go in to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places of those parts.</p>

<p>From Genoa thus: <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> from Madrid that an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> was come to the Court to <reg orig="informe">inform</reg> His <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> that there was landed at Coronnal in Galitia, three thousand Irish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were appointed to winter quarters, which doth something startle the <reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg>, who made a <reg orig="shew">show</reg> as if they would have<pb n="10" /> besieged Cindad Rodrigo. The Duke of Turfi is also expected at Barulona with <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="Galleyes">Galleys</reg>, who are to bring good store of Ammunition and Moneys for the payment of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: One of the Spanish <reg orig="Galleyes">Galleys</reg> hath lately taken a very rich prize upon the French, being a ship bound for Marscillis.</p>

<p>From Milan thus: The <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquess</reg> of Caracena our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> is gone from hence to Uereel, and from thence to Trin, as also all the high Officers who were all come to this City to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the time of the Truce, and are all come to the Army, to observe the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> march; the most part of whose <reg orig="Armie">Army</reg> is still posted <reg orig="neare">near</reg> the River Po, it being yet <reg orig="unknowne">unknown</reg> what Resolution they will take, and where, and when they will take their Winter Quarters: although many <reg orig="doe">do</reg> assure that the French <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> hath received Orders from the Court of France, to cause all the Horse of his army to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> over the <reg orig="Alpes">Alps</reg>, and quarter in Dauphina, and that the Foot shall be quartered in Piedmont, by reason that the time of <reg orig="yeare">year</reg> is so <reg orig="farre">far</reg> gone, and so much snow fallen upon the <reg orig="Mountaines">Mountains</reg>, that being so <reg orig="poorely">poorly</reg> <reg orig="cloathed">clothed</reg> they cannot undertake the journey. There hath been likewise some moneys gathered, and is to be for payment of our Army one <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday Jan.</em> 12.</head>

<p>Paris the 10 of <em>Jan</em>: 1654. <em>stilo novo</em>. We hear from <em>Campagne</em>, that the Country suffers much by that part of the Army which is quartered there, and although some small allowance is given to those where they are <reg orig="billited">billeted</reg>, yet they suffer much thereby, the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> not receiving their constant pay, are not kept in so good a Discipline as it is requisite, notwithstanding the taking of St. <em>Menebold</em>, the blocking up of Clermont, yet the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Stenny</em> doth make frequent inroads<pb n="11" /> in this Country: there is nothing more from Cavalonia, only that the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> of Hoequincourt having well supplied Rosa with all necessaries for their defence, hath put his forces into winter quarters.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is not yet <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg>, but is expected here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>: there is strong report that this Prince intends to match with one of the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces, but many are of a contrary opinion, which is truest, will be known very shortly.</p>

<p>The Lord Chancellor hath been this week at the Parliament, to have a supersedeas to the passing the Declaration which is drawn up against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, the same to continue for 6 weeks.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> doth still lie a close prisoner, there being little hopes as yet of any <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>, his Antagonist the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> being very obstinate in the demand he hath made so many times, that he should resign his Coadjutership of <em>Paris</em>, and to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> him the more, there is offered him the two rich <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg> of St. <em>Denis</em> and <em>Cluni</em>, which offer he will by no means accept.</p>

<p>The Court is not well pleased with the Governors of <em>Charleville</em> and <em>Mezieru</em>, by reason that they hath passed Articles of Neutrality with the Prince of <em>Condi</em>.</p>

<p>It is generally reported, that the Duke <em>de la Pieuville</em> shall go Ambassador in Ordinary to <em>Rome</em>, he that was there being now on his way homewards, and that the Earl <em>de Anangour</em>, shall have the same <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> into <em>Swethland</em>.</p>

<p>Three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since the Earl <em>do Noville</em> was sworn as one of the Captains of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Life-Guard.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em> Jan: 14</head>

<p>Claseo Jan: 5. We have little of new more <reg orig="then">than</reg> what you had by the last, only that part of the Army is here, and in good condition, I had intelligence of Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>, being<pb n="12" /> sore of his wounds, at a Cot-house at <em>Tushilaw</em>, and sent a party of Horse to <reg orig="seaze">seize</reg> him, but he was gone two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before from that House, and the Country so true to him, that we could not find him.</p>

<p><em>Scilly</em> Jan: the 2d. The <em>Elias</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come safe into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, and brought us six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> pay which we were in Arrears, other news, all being quiet, this place affords not.</p>

<p>Paris Jan: 17. 1654. By Letters from Perpignan, we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that the Spanish Army are quartered in and about Gironne, although the Plague doth rage much there still; One party is gone about Palamas, and the Field-<reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> de Serra hath an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> Order from Don <em>John d Austrin</em>, to take care that the country be not oppressed by the quartering of the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, but to keep them in a strict discipline.</p>

<p>From Champagne, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that the Irish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were at saint Meneholds, are gone from hence to Chaalons there remaining no more but those companies of Switzers, who were there at the reduction with the Regiment of Dambrole, and the six companies more who upon agreement between the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and the Townsmen, are <reg orig="joyntly">jointly</reg> to have the guard of the City, there being an <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> number of the Town, with the Garrison, to watch day and night: Those of Clermont have not of late made any inroads, the reason we here is because many desert the place.</p>

<p>From Alsatia, we hear that the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> de la Forte is come before Beffort, where the lines are <reg orig="neare">near</reg> finished, and the Ordnance within a <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> journey of the place; but on the other side, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> intends to defend it gallantly; which to effect, and for his better <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> he hath commanded all the Country adjacent to bring in their <reg orig="corne">corn</reg> and other like provisions which are necessary for him.</p>

<p>The 15 instant the Provost and Eschenins of this City, went to the <reg orig="Lawne">Lawn</reg>, where they had an audience, the subject being about those monies due to the Citizens upon the Town-house.</p><pb n="13" />

<p>The next day Prince Rupert <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> here from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>, to this City. The same day returned here from Catalonia the Marquess du Plessis Belliere, who hath been for many late years an eminent Commander in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army: there is little news at present, only great preparations are made here for the solemnizing his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> consecration the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday, Januar.</em> 14.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Lime</em>: we hear by a Barque come from <em>Britannia</em>, that one of our <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroon">Picaroon</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Vshant">Ushant</reg></em>, gave him chase, and followed so close, that he forced him to run on ground on the hither side of the Bay of Camaret, and by reason of his shooting hard at him made the Country to come down to the water side; it happened that some shot did make execution on the shore, there being four killed and wounded; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the Country being all <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg> thereby could not fetch her off; but ours put to Sea again, to clear from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>

<p>By several other Letters from Scotland, which contracted speak to this effect: The Highlanders continue their stealing and plundering of their own Countrymen that will not rise with them, or pay the contribution money that they lay upon them, though I am confident many have not <reg orig="wherewithall">wherewithal</reg><pb n="14" /> to subsist, paying likewise their Assessments for the maintenance of the English Army: but when Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em>, Commissary General <em><reg orig="Whalleys">Whalley's</reg></em> Regiments of Horse, with Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment of Foot (which we hear are upon their march) are come in to us, we doubt not but to send this Heathenish and plundering Enemy so far back into the Highlands, as they shall not dare to approach the Lowlands, whereby to do the Inhabitants any considerable prejudice; And how the Highlanders are able to keep Horse and man, is <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be imagined, all their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> being upon <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and His endeavours with the Dutch for <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> and Arms; but a Peace with Holland (which we hear is in a very probable way for a very speedy conclusion) disperses them to their several mountainous Habitations, without ever drawing the sword against them; and then the Lords and Chieftains amongst them may expect a liberal Reward of Justice for doing their Master such rebellious service, which hath been and is destructive to the generality of Scotland, that a few months continuance will bring them to the sad condition of the Irish, that have been forced to eat the <reg orig="Corps">Corpse</reg> of their deceased Friends after many days interment; yet are not the people of Scotland very much to be <reg orig="pityed">pitied</reg>, in regard they will seldom give notice to any of our Garrisons when any party of the Enemy marches<pb n="15" /> through the Country, whereby they might be the better preserved from their <reg orig="violencs">violence</reg> and cruelty, <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather to be willingly destroyed by them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> be treacherous (as they call it) to their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Country-men">Countrymen</reg>: Some Arms they pretend are lately landed for the Enemy in Scotland, but this is more to encourage their forced and naked party, <reg orig="then">than</reg> otherwise considerable.</p>

<p>No News from Holland since the Dutch Commissioners set <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> from Gravesend: by way of Calice we have a further confirmation of the great fire <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in Holland, which began at Waterland, about 500 Houses burned to the ground, and many persons perished in that fire, as also some <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>. The contrary winds have withheld the Dutch Post this week, so that a more particular account cannot be given from thence for the present. Concerning our Fleet by letters from Portsmouth thus. Gen: Blake and General Monk being now at London, Gen: <reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg> rides as Admiral of the Fleet without St <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point 3 Leagues from Portsmouth with forty sail of gallant ships ready upon any advice of the Dutch ships <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> out to put to Sea: some part of them are already sent out to ply between this place and the Lands end, and over upon the Coast of France, to suppress the Brest and Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, who of late begin to be strong, and have done much harm upon the western Coast.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>