<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn228">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 228</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, April. 17. to <em>Monday</em>, April. 24. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> April. 17.</head>

<p>This day came the Ratification of the Peace from the States General of the United Provinces to their Ambassadors here, and by them presented to the Lord Protector in a Silver Box, signed and sealed by their <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg>, the States of the United Provinces, all concurring; whereupon all things are preparing for a final Ratification to be made by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and forthwith returned to the States of <em>Holland</em>, and upon signification of their receiving thereof, a day will be appointed for Proclaiming it both in <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p><em>Leith, April</em> 13. This day a party from <em>Dalkeith</em> took one <em>Malcolm Rogers </em>(Agent for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, who brought several Commissions from him) and also one <em>Stephens</em>, who had been a Soldier in <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em>, little above a month since. On <em>Tuesday</em> last, Captain <em><unclear>Southwood</unclear></em> Commander of the <em>Black Raven</em>, going from <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em> Road towards <em>Newcastle</em>, was set upon by eleven Dutch men of War, boarded and taken. This day also a private man of War of ours, was <reg orig="accidently">accidentally</reg> blown up in <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em> Harbour, and 6 Men killed.</p>

<p>Col <em>Morgan</em> with 850 horse and 1600 foot, hath beset the enemy, who is 800 horse, and 3000 foot, resolving to fight them, and they can hardly escape him.</p>

<p>Captain <em>Staner</em>, and Captain <em>Smith</em>, Commanders of the <em>Tonington</em> and <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, have taken an Holland East-India ship outward bound of 800 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, <reg orig="loden">laden</reg> with 75 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of goods, and four chests of silver.</p>

<p>Colonel <em>Pride</em> with his Regiment now in <em>London</em> have received orders to march for <em>Scotland</em>, as also 5 Companies of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment that are in <em>Yorkshire</em>, General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> (say the Letters) is passed well in health through <em>Yorkshire</em>, and is by this time 'tis conceived in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>This day came Letters from <em>Portsmouth</em> of a notable <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of Service by the <em>Portsmouth, <reg orig="Middlebrough">Middlesborough</reg></em>, and <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, against a Fleet of 48 Sail of Frenchmen, as by this following from the Commander of the <em>Portsmouth</em>, take at large.</p>

<p>We departed from <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> the 1 of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, that night we met the <em>Falmouth</em>, and visited some ships of <em>Ostend</em> which came from St. <em>Lucas</em>. The third, West-south-west from the Lizard 12 leagues met several ships of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Stockholm, Emden</em>, and <em>Lianbick</em>, with two ships of <em>Dover</em> in their Company, all which came from Saint <em>Martins</em> with Salt and Wine, from that time until the 7 we were without the <reg orig="chanel">channel</reg> 20 or 30 leagues off. The 7 day the <em><reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesborough</reg></em> came to us. The 9 we met with one with one who told me that I might expect with the first wind, from Saint <em>Mellons</em> 4 ships laden with Cloth, bound for Saint <em>Lucas</em>, and 6 ships that were to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for the Bank. The<pb n="2" /> 10 we chased a <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into <em>Broadsound</em>. The 11, the wind coming to the South, and South-south-east, we with the <em><reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesborough</reg></em>, and <em>Falmouth</em>, very early in the morning passed to the Northward of <em>Vbsant</em>, and about 3 leagues to the eastward of the <em>Loor Rock</em>, descried a fleet of ships standing to the westward, 48 sail, I knew not what to make of them at first, their number being so far exceeded what I expected, but found them to be French ships we got the wind of them, and took a full view of their Fleet, we took their <reg orig="Flag ships">Flagships</reg> to be cloth ships, fell in among them. The Rear Admiral being windermost, and the best ship in the Fleet, I came up with him first very close, and passed a broad side on him, and was very well seconded by the <reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesborough</reg>, the first and the second time. And as we received shot from several of their ships which lay by him, so especially from the Admiral which laid to the Leeward, upon which also we spent some shot, one of which about this time of Service carried his Main mast by the board, and that <reg orig="halled">hauled</reg> his foretopmast after it, so as he could do us little more hurt. Going to pass our third Broad side, I shot the Rear <reg orig="Admirals">Admiral's</reg> main <reg orig="Top-mast">Topmast</reg>. After the fifth broad side from us, and two from the <em><reg orig="Middlebrough">Middlesborough</reg></em>, as above, he took in his Flag, and called for quarter, came aboard with their boat, and I sent men to <reg orig="possesse">possess</reg> her, but found it impossible to save her, being all torn to pieces. As soon as their men were aboard of us, she sunk without saving the value of six pence besides the Flag. She was a ship of 260 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, 18 guns, 4 <reg orig="brasse">brass</reg> Stock fowlers, and 85 men, bound to <em>Burneuf</em> for Salt, and thence to <em>Canade</em> to fish, her name the <em>Fourdore</em>, <em>Sebastian Penoire</em> Commander, who informed me that all the rest were on the same design, only two bound for St. <em><reg orig="Christophers">Christopher's</reg></em> with passengers. Having freed <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> from her, we bore with another, and coming to take her, we found her left by the Company who were got into <em>Shallops</em>, one of which we took, and learned by them she was sinking, she was then on the <em>Curene</em>, her name the St. <em>Clement</em>, <em>John Gerrat</em> Master, she had 70 Men<pb n="3" /> and 14 Guns, she received her shot from us about the time the <em>Fourdore </em><reg orig="yeleded">yielded</reg>. The wind very much increasing, we stood after some which stood into the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, and near the Isle of Bass <em>took</em> the <em>John Baptist, John Paus</em> Master, with 14 Guns and 70 men. The night approaching, and the ships out of sight we came away with these. This was all done in sight of that coast or <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>. I <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God we lost not a man, had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> two hurt. The <em><reg orig="Middleburgh">Middlesborough</reg></em> took the <em>Veirge bon Voyage</em>, that <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> whose Masts were shot off as aforesaid with 18 Guns and 70 men, and the <em>Lou Blanch</em>, with 11 Guns, and 60 men. The <em>Falmouth</em> took the <em>Jaques</em> with 8 Guns, and 40 men.</p>

<p><i>Portsmouth <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> in the <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> Sound, the <em>13 April</em>, 1654.</i></p>

<p>By the last Letters from <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> thus. The Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em> with his two <reg orig="Sonnes">Sons</reg> being arrived to this City, had audience the next day after his <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, and the next day he visited the Imperatrix, and the King of the <em>Romans</em>, and so intends to go on his journey into <em>Flanders</em>; whereas it was agreed upon that the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> should depart from hence upon the 20th of <em>April</em>, it is put off for eight <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> longer, upon the earnest <reg orig="intreaties">entreaties</reg> of the States assembled at the Diet, but with this proviso, That all other affairs laid aside, they shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> take the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> in hand concerning the defence of the Frontier places, and thereupon the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath sent to <em>Presburgh</em> (the chief City in <em>Hungaria</em>) to repair the old Fortifications, and put the place in a posture of defence.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>. The Duke of <em>Brunswick</em> hath sent some Forces towards <em>Winsen</em> and <em>Harborough</em>, but as yet it cannot be conceived what his intent is: The design of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Koningsmarck</em> in sending to <em>Bremerburgh</em> hath proved abortive, by reason that the City of <em>Bremen</em> had prevented it; We have likewise intelligence, that some Forces come from <em>Denmark</em> and <em>Holstein</em>, are come to quarter about <em>Altenaw, Ottensee</em>, and parts adjacent, which doth give a great terror in these parts, which<pb n="4" /> hath given occasion to make new levies for our own defence, but that which doth cause more amazement, is, by reason that the King of <em>Denmark</em>, who is still at <em>Gluckstadt</em>, hath sent an Order to all his Officers of the Admiralty in Norway, to search all our ships that are in that Land.</p>

<p>From <em>Lubeck</em>. We hear from <em>Muscovia</em>, that a Proclamation hath been made commanding all strangers, Merchants or others, to depart the Country within a set time, under great penalties; this being <reg orig="don">done</reg> upon the <reg orig="sollicitation">solicitation</reg> of the <reg orig="Patriark">Patriarch</reg>, who hath made very great <reg orig="rejoycings">rejoicings</reg> upon the birth of a young Prince.</p>

<p>From <em>Munster</em> in <em>Westphalia</em>. Our Bishop having gathered up all the moneys which are to be paid to the Swedes, is now expecting that upon payment thereof they should deliver up the <reg orig="strong hold">stronghold</reg> of <em>Weckt</em>, according to their agreement. After a siege of eight <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> followed very close, the Castle of <em>Hammerstein</em> was delivered up to the Elector of <em>Triers</em>, they being taken at Mercy; the common <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> were set at liberty, only the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and others of the high Officers were kept prisoners, who are to be called to <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> for their high oppressions they have done in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> adjacent.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April. 18.</i></head>

<p>This day Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>, Colonel <em>Sidenham</em>, and Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, three of the Lords of the Council, were sent Commissioners, with Mr. <em>Jessop</em> Clerk of the Council, to the Lord Ambassador <em>Bourdeaux</em>, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from the King of <em>France</em>, to Treat with him touching the Treaty with that Kingdom.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is passed the Council for continuing the Imposition upon Coals for building of Shipping.</p>

<p>A second Order of Reference made by the Council for <reg orig="renuing">renewing</reg> the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of Improving of <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> had under consideration an Ordinance touching Postages.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>An additional Ordinance touching the Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-Ways">Highways</reg> for this present year, 1654.</p>

<p>Whereas in an Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair the Common <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg> within this Nation, it is ordained, amongst other things, that two or more able and sufficient <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg>, as in that Ordinance is expressed, should be elected and chosen upon the first <em>Tuesday</em> next ensuing the five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> yearly, to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> within their respective Parishes for the year ensuing: And whereas by reason of the late publishing of the said Ordinance, the time aforesaid for such election for this year was elapsed, so as such election could not be made on that day in pursuance of the said Ordinance, whereby the benefit intended to the People thereby is obstructed; Be it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the Persons which already are chosen, or shall be chosen before the first day of <em>May</em> 1654. to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> (which election is hereby <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> to be made in every Place and Parish by the time aforesaid, under the penalties in that Ordinance expressed) in case no election hath been already made, shall undertake the said Office, and be sworn on, or before, the sixth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, under the penalties in the said ordinance set down in that behalf, and shall be Surveyors for this present year, as if such election had been made on the said first <em>Tuesday</em> after the said five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>And the said Surveyors so sworn, and all others authorized by the said Ordinance, shall be, and are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, to proceed in, and put in execution, all the Directions, Powers and Authorities in the said Ordinance contained, as fully to all intents and purposes, as if the election had been made on the day therein appointed.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, April</em> 15. Here are four French prizes brought in by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and the <em>Falmouth</em>, and <em><reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesborough</reg></em><pb n="6" />, which they took in a late engagement with a Fleet of them near the Isle of <em>Basse</em>, besides 2 sunk; They will suddenly be fitted out again; and the <em>Paul</em>, and old <em>Warwick</em> are ready to <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> and the <em><reg orig="Saphir">Sapphire</reg></em> and <em>Constant Warwick</em> will be ready this night, or <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em> March 17. The Grand Chancellor being sickly, the Queen hath given order to Count <em>Erick</em>, his second Son, and a person of very great accomplishments, to Treat with my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>. And on Monday last they both had a meeting to debate upon the Articles. Our being here hath not been without its use and advantage to <em>England</em> in several respects: Not long since, a <reg orig="Senatour">Senator</reg> here, and He not one of the least ability, was pleased to say, That my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> being here had been of greater fruit to our <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, than if we had sent an Army of 10000 into Holland. And, I suppose, the Issue will countervail the charges of the <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg>, should they be never so great. The Queen is yet resolved for privacy; and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said, That the Senators have <reg orig="complyed">complied</reg> with Her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desires in that particular. But an affair of this nature cannot be actually determined but in Parliament; which will now meet shortly. The Prince Royal, to whom the Queen resigns, is expected here very speedily, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed for no other end but to treat with the <reg orig="Senatours">Senators</reg> about that affair. The Queen proposes to have the Lands in <em>Bomerania</em>, as part of her maintenance, and some say that the Senate have agreed thereunto; and that the Castle of <em>Stetin</em> is making ready for her Majesty, where she intends to reside. Others are bold to think, that this pretence of resigning, and the coronation of the Prince, is but to Usher in their Marriage together with more Pomp and Solemnity. But a matter of this weight, so blinded, and so hidden in its circumstances may be censured, and guessed at by all, but can be apprehended by very few.</p>

<p>From Paris the 22th of April, 1654. This <reg orig="weeke">week</reg> the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> of the Prince of <em>Conde</em> are to be defaced from all his<pb n="7" /> Houses, or places hereabouts where they are affixed, and the late Sentence given against him and his Adherents, is prosecuted with all severity. This Court hath spent much time and moneys about their Masks, <reg orig="Playes">Plays</reg>, and the like Court <reg orig="Toyes">Toys</reg>, and that being over, they intend to think upon the next Field Expedition. Charles Stuart, and the little Queen his Mother are here still, but as we are certainly informed, they are to go from hence very shortly, only those moneys which are promised them are not yet brought in, which doth make a great <reg orig="demurr">demur</reg> upon their Journey: This week the Protestants Commissioners had a large Audience, where having represented at large all their grievance, and prayed for a speedy relief, they had a very mild answer returned unto them, That all <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> should be taken into consideration, and in a short time they should be relieved, and now they are in expectation of that answer, which, it's to be feared, will be no other than complimental, and nothing <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg>.</p> 

<p>The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is still close prisoner at the Castle of <em>Nantes</em>, and being earnestly <reg orig="sollicitted">solicited</reg> to the leave the <reg orig="Archbishoprick">Archbishopric</reg>, he is still in the same resolution as formerly, <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather to suffer a long and tedious imprisonment, than to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> in the least to part from that which is his right. The <reg orig="maritim">maritime</reg> parts of <em>Brittany</em>, and so on to the River of <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> are still to <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg>, being much afraid of the great fleet which is now <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Portsmouth</em>; We hear from <em>Bethune</em>, that the 5000 Spaniards which were in <em>Brabant</em> and <em>Haynault</em>, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> much toward <em>Lile</em>, and that those forces which had their winter quarters about the River <em>Lis</em>, have received Order to be ready for a march upon the first command. The <em>Lorrainers</em> do not stir, but are expecting the Prince <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em> who is now coming to them from <em>Germany</em>, to be their Commander in chief in his <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> absence. Marshal <em>de Turenne</em> is not yet gone to <em>Picardy</em>, and I <reg orig="supose">suppose</reg> his greatest <reg orig="demurr">demur</reg> is for want of that money which is promised him, which he cannot have this week, and the next hardly obtain it.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 19.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Lodowick de Gand</em>, Lord of <em>Brachey</em>, and Resident here in <em>England</em> in the behalf of the High and Mighty Prince <em>Lewis</em>, Duke of <em>Gueldens</em> and <em>Iuliers</em>, Conte of <em>Egmont</em> and <em>Zutphen</em>, &amp;c. yesterday, with many Gentlemen of quality accompanying him in Coaches, was attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, unto his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector; The Lord President <em>Laurence</em> and some other Lords of the Council, with the Secretary of State being present in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Chamber at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, where the said Lord Resident had audience, and made a congratulatory Speech, which was Answered with a great deal of respect from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was published for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners, to this effect.</i></p>

<p>Whereas in regard of many doubts arising upon an Act of the late Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>, and several inconveniences and mischiefs like to grow from thence, not only to the Creditors &amp; Prisoners themselves, but to divers other persons, without some explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges authorized in and by the said Act; It is by an Ordinance of the 31 of March <unclear>last</unclear> <reg orig="Ordeined">Ordained</reg>, that the said several and respective Judges should not proceed to sale or disposition, nor otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or any of the powers and authorities given by the same, until the twentieth day of <em>April</em> instant; and whereas the way for prevention of those evils, and the better accomplishing the ends intended by the said Act, is now under consideration, which will necessarily require some longer time to perfect the same: Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, That the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any of the estates real or personal, or any of the said prisoners, or<pb n="9" /> of any other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in or by the said Act, nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or any of the powers or authorities given by the same, until the fifteenth day of <em>May</em> next coming; And be it further <reg orig="Ordeined">Ordained</reg>, that all acts and things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by virtue, colour or pretence of the said Act from henceforth and before the said fifteenth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid (saving only in such cases, and according to such limitations, as by the said Ordinance they had power to do, before the said twentieth day of <em>April</em>) shall be and are hereby declared to be utterly null and void.</p>

<p>By the last Letters from <em>Naples</em> thus. There hath been a view taken of all the new Levies under the command of the Prince <em>San Severino</em> but they do not answer near the number what was expected, there being not one thousand of able fighting men. The Prince <em>de la Rocca</em> is likewise to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> into <em>Apuglia</em>, there to command some forces, and to endeavour to secure them from any <reg orig="forain">foreign</reg> attempt, our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> being resolved to keep a small body of an Army in each Province thereby to put all <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> places in a posture of defence, and in a capacity to assist each other, have also sent lately a small vessel with some necessaries to <em>Porto Longone</em>. From <em>Venice</em>: We hear by the last Letters from <em>Candia</em>, that the <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> <em>Foscolo</em> before his departure is taking all care possible to set all things in good order: Our <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Capello</em> is still a prisoner at <em>Andrinopolis</em>, and there is little hopes hitherto of his enlargement, or a further Treaty with those Infidels, seeing their extraordinary preparations which they make for this next Summer, their <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg> being more than thirty Galleys stronger than the last year: The news from <em>Dalmatia</em> are yet worse, for the General <em>Delfino</em> having as you have heard <reg orig="besiedged">besieged</reg> <em>Clim</em> with an Army of about 6000 men, the Turks having privately sent a strong supply of men into the place, our men found a very cold welcome, for those Infidels sallied out our men in great numbers, whereby they were <reg orig="overpowred">overpowered</reg>, our men were forced to<pb n="10" /> leave the place, above one thousand slain and taken prisoners, all the baggage lost, with two <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance. From <em>Turin</em>: Upon the advice received that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Milan</em> intended to be shortly in the field with a powerful Army, therefore an Order is <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> sent to all the Commanders, that they do repair every one to their several <reg orig="imployments">employments</reg>, and that all things be put in a posture of defence, as well the Army as the garrisoned places, yet considering the Enemy doth not receive that aid from the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of <em>Naples</em> which he expected, therefore <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought he will not act much this Summer.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 20,</i></head>

<p><em>Paris April</em> 25 1654. The last Letters of <em><reg orig="Catalogna">Catalonia</reg></em> advise that there hath been lately a great difference between the Country people near <em>Terragona</em> and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and his Garrison, after many hot words they fell to blows, insomuch that Captain and some Officers were slain in the fray, now both parties are gone to <em>Barcelona</em>, the one side to <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> themselves against the accusations of the other, this action doth make the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of that place to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> the place, and put himself into a posture in case of a <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg>. The <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> de St. <unclear>Genoa</unclear> field Marshal in his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Armies is come to <em><reg orig="Phillipsburgh">Phillipsburg</reg></em> where he is to be <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Secretaries who was made Commander <em>pro <unclear>tempure</unclear></em>, having resigned him the place according to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> orders thereupon. We hear from <em>Flanders</em> that the <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of <em>Cullen</em>, and the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em> have had a meeting at <em>Louuain</em>, and having tarried there about two days, did part with much satisfaction <unclear>one</unclear> of each other, the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> having at his departure presented him with some rich <reg orig="Tapistry">Tapestry</reg>, and four of his best horses; We have by Letters from <em>Sedan</em>, that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em><unclear>Jeamis</unclear></em> having made a design with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Mouson</em> to beat up some of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters who had their Winter quarters at <em>Wirton</em> in the Province of <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, they carried their work on so gallantly, that the several Troops there quartered were for the most part slain, and the rest taken prisoners, with a company of Spanish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> who were left for the guard of that Town.</p><pb n="11" />

<p>The 22th instant, one <em>James Darry</em> an <em>Irish</em> Gentleman was made by the King Lieutenant of the Duke of <em>York's</em> Regiment, and the next day was made Knight by <em>Charles Stuart</em>; the same day the King went with the Cardinal to the Park of <em>Vicennes</em> where he was a hunting, and so returned hither at night. The preparations at <em>Toulon</em> goes on still, but not so fast; it is not yet certain whether the prince of <em>Conti</em> shall go on into <em>Catalonia</em>; neither have the Commissioners from that Country prevailed <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> towards those Propositions which they presented at their first Audience, but are delayed, and receive no other satisfaction than Court language. We have from <em>Thionville</em>, That the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> having passed the <em>Mosell</em> with his Army, passed at <em>Estain</em> into the County of <em>Vouure</em>, and so intends to go to <em>Sedan</em>, and send those Forces under his command unto the Quarters. The Duke of <em>Orleans</em> is still near <em>Blois</em>, and notwithstanding the many allurements from the Court to invite him hither, yet he remaineth <reg orig="unflexible">inflexible</reg>, and will not in the least hearken to it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday April 21, 22.</i></head>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em> 13 April 1654. On Monday morning last a party of 40 of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse or more came in view of our Garrison of <em>Kilcrooch</em>, and passed by it. Lieutenant <em>Hunt</em> that commanded there drew out with a party, but could not overtake them, <reg orig="til">till</reg> they were got to <em>Aberfaste</em>, took 7 prisoners, 11 Horse, 20 Cloaks, and many <reg orig="Cloake">Cloak</reg> <reg orig="baggs">bags</reg> full of plunder, which the Enemy scattered the better to make their escape: we rescued two prisoners which they had brought out of the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills; <reg orig="Leiut">Lieut.</reg> Col. <em>Irwin</em> commanded, and brought up to the Rear. The Lords <em>Forrester</em>, and <em>Dudhopp</em> are in <em>Athol</em>, but bring no further advantage to their party, than their Persons and Attendants<pb n="12" />. Since the two Defeats given to <reg orig="Mac-Naughtons">McNaughtons</reg> party, he is gone away, being much suspected by some of that party that he hath betrayed his party to us, which makes many of their Officers begin to Capitulate, and to desire Terms to come in.</p>

<p>The 9th instant Col. <em>Morgan</em> was at <em>Dingwell</em> in <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>, within a mile whereof the Enemy must march, or else engage, otherwise go such way as never Horse went over Hills and Rocks. Their number is 4000 Horse and Foot, ours about 2200. our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are very hearty, and wish nothing more than an Engagement.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 17. The enclosed is all the account we have had from the North of <em>Scotland</em>, the only place now for action, since my last.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Invernesse">Inverness</reg></em> April 10. The Enemy in <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> have endeavoured all they could to raise that Country, but the people are backward in <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with them, fearing least the Garrison which is at <em>Sinclair</em> Castle, commanded by Captain <em>Langrish</em>, of Col. <em><reg orig="Fitthes">Fitth's</reg></em> Regiment, should punish their <reg orig="forwardnesse">forwardness</reg> after <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> march out of <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em>, wherefore for their encouragement, Major General <em>Dyal</em> with a party of foot, and one hundred horse is ordered to sit down before it for the taking it in which is conceived will not easily be achieved by them, the place being naturally strong, and a vessel within these few days being sent <reg orig="fro">from</reg> hence with 3 months provision and ammunition; so that they are<pb n="13" /> with what they had in store, well provided for at least six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, Capt. <em>Hill</em> also of Col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Regiment <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> from hence this week thirty horse load of necessaries for his Garrison of <em>Ruthen</em> in <em>Badgenoth</em> of which he is <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, that Country at present being free from the Enemy.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> from this place on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, he having drawn a party of Foot out of this Garrison to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those Forces he brought from <em>Aberdeen</em>, so that he lies with about Eleven or Twelve hundred Horse and Dragoons, and a considerable party of Foot betwixt the Enemy and the Passes they must needs march through, if they intend to move out of this North Corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, or otherwise break or disband those Forces they have gathered; there being no way left them to avoid meeting with Col. <em>Morgan</em>, but through such inaccessible bounds, as it is impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their Foot, it being exceeding Mountainous, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> they are in will not long be able to <reg orig="sustaine">sustain</reg> them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of some Action betwixt him and <em>Middleton</em>; what the <reg orig="Successe">Success</reg> will be the Lord knows, in whose hands are all the corners of the Earth.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="an other">another</reg> <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> from <em>Leith</em> the same date. We have little here but what's in expectation, <em>Morgan</em> and <em>Middleton</em> have continued at an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> distance from each other for<pb n="14" /> some <reg orig="dayr">days</reg> past, and 'tis conceived that the little Colonel has some advantage of him in respect of ground, and will endeavour by all means to engage him, though his number at present be much inferior to his. In the mean while, there is many dissolute persons from several parts run to the Enemy. One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that convoyed ammunition and some Merchants ships hither, in her return off from Dunbar was confronted with 7 Dutch ships, and after hot skirmish boarded, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> away; two light Vessels that went with her made their escape, and brought the news to <em>Leith</em>.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, April</em> 16. Wednesday last Capt. <em>Potter</em> Commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em> (who three weeks since brought in Beach) did bring in hither another of the Brest <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg>, viz. The <em>Bridget</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a small Vessel of 4 Guns, but one of the neatest things, and the best Sailor that hath been known. <em>Beach</em> and <em>Jones</em> say (who are now together lamenting their <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>, and bemoaning their misfortune as they call it) that Capt. <em>Potter</em> hath taken two of the principal <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that belong to <em>Brest</em>.</p>

<p><em>Tuesday</em> last the <em>Portsmouth, <reg orig="Middleborough">Middlesborough</reg></em>, and <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> met with 48 sail of French men upon their own Coast, 24 of them were ships of force, and the other great Vessels all bound for the <reg orig="New-found land">Newfoundland</reg>, there was an hot fight for the space of five hours, in which time there were three of the best French ships sunk, but most of the men which were alive saved by our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, there are four taken, one of which is brought in hither, the other three are brought in at <em>Foy</em>, they have nothing in them but provisions and some salt, I cannot learn of any men we have slain, but some wounded, neither have we sustained much damage in our shipping.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Paris</em> April 25. In answer to yours concerning the little Queen, and her Son the <reg orig="titulary">titular</reg> King of <em>Scots</em>, thus much at present, Three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since she went from hence, having two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before taken her leave of the King and Court, there went with her, her two Sons, Pr. <em>Rupert</em>, and some others, in all about 12 Coaches; some say she intends for <em>Orleans</em>, others, to the Duke her Brother, at his house near <em>Blois</em>. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is<pb n="15" /> only gone to convoy her on her way, and to return, but not yet quite to leave <em>France</em>, as reported.</p>

<p><em>Deal</em>, April 21. This afternoon is arrived here the <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> who doth return into <em>Holland</em> to carry to the States General the ratification of the peace, signed and sealed by his Highness the L. Protector, which upon signification of their receiving, will be suddenly proclaimed both in <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>. There is brought into this Road 3 Dutch prises, whereof one was a ship bound for the East-Indies, and the other two of good value; there are also brought into <em>Harwich</em> 2. Dutch prises which came from <em>Norway</em>, and some Busses, we hear, are taken by a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of war, and carried into <em>Yarmouth</em>, having some fish in them, but not fully laden: Nothing further from our Fleet, but that they ride still in <em>Stoaks-Bay</em>.</p>

<hr />

<p>&#x261e; There is newly published an <em>Excellent Romance</em> in <em>Folio, <reg orig="Scholastick">Scholastic</reg>, Witty</em>, and very <em><reg orig="Delightfull">Delightful</reg></em>, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>Festivious</em>: Or, <em>Pleasant Notes</em> in <em>Verse</em> and <em>Prose</em>, upon that <em>Famous History</em> of <em>DON QUIXOT</em>: By <em>Edmund Gayton</em> Esq; Printed by <em>William Hunt</em>, and are to be sold by most <reg orig="Book-sellers">Booksellers</reg> in <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>.&#x261c;</p>

<p><em>Atheinus Vapulans</em>, or A Treatise against Atheism, rationally confuting the Atheists of these times; By <em>William Towers</em>, B. D. sometimes Student of <reg orig="Christs-Church">Christ's Church</reg> in Oxon. Printed for <em>Humphrey Moseley</em> at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> in St. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p>The grounds and validity of Instant Baptism is answer to Mr. <em>Tombes</em>, by <em>John Horn</em> Minister at <em>Lin</em> in <em>Norfolk</em>. A Vindication of the late change of Government, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, Peace protected, by <em>John <reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em>. Water <reg orig="Dippin">Dipping</reg>, no firm footing for Church Communion, by <em>John <reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em>, To be sold by <em>H: Cripps</em>, and <em>Lodo. Lloyd</em> at their shops in Popes-head alley.</p>

<p><em>Animal Cornutum</em>, Or, The <reg orig="Horn'd">Horned</reg> Beast; <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the grounds of Christian Astrology: With a Narrative of all the Visible Eclipses, both of Sun and Moon for these 15 years to come, together with an Answer to some impertinent objections against Astrology. Sold by <em>William Larnar</em> at the <reg orig="Blackmores">Blackmore's</reg> head near <reg orig="Fleet-Bridge">Fleet Bridge</reg>.</p>

<p>The Sun of <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg> shining upon the Sons of <reg orig="Unrighteousnesse">Unrighteousness</reg>, or a Treatise written by Mr. <em>John <reg orig="Sheffeild">Sheffield</reg></em> Minister at <em>Swithins</em> London, and are able to be sold at the Ball in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<p>There was stolen this 20th of April from <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Warde">Ward</reg> of Bolney in the County of Sussex Gent. And John Petto Minister, one bay Gelding, about 15 hands high, with a small star in his forehead, and a white Lock or tuft of hair in his Tail. Also a sad bay Nag with a hooked Nose, and a bright bay Mare, <reg orig="grisled">grizzled</reg> on the back, and a white spot in one of the hinder <reg orig="Pastols">Pastels</reg>: Whosoever shall apprehend, and give notice of any of the said horses to Mr. Bonner at the Cathern Wheel, on <reg orig="Fish-street">Fish Street</reg> hill, London, shall be very well satisfied for their pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>