<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc01">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Perfect Diurnall Occurrences, Issue 1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">Perfect</head>
<head level="1"><reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> Occurrences</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em>. 1. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em> 8. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<p>By Letters from <em>Leith</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, dated the 27. of <em>April</em> thus. Many of the chief Officers have had a meeting with Gen. <em>Monk</em> since his coming hither, and have consulted of many things, in order to quelling the spoil and fury of the Enemy, and to that end, some additional Forces are to march unto Colonel <em>Morgan</em>, who attends <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> motion at <em>Dingwel</em>, but betwixt him and the Enemy (in Southerland) is a great depth and <reg orig="bredth">breadth</reg>, and the passages on the other side so narrow and dangerous (even in more seasonable times, and favourable weather, <reg orig="then">than</reg> of late hath been in Scotland) that he thought it a dangerous resolution to adventure over; and besides, he discovers the Enemy on the foot of the Hills to exceed him in number, and that they have <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> all the <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg> and provisions in that place to themselves, which it's thought will not hold them long, and then they must either<pb n="1" /> come forth and fight, or else <reg orig="clime">climb</reg> with their horses over the steep and craggy Mountains. We hear of an Ordinance of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, tendering pardon unto some, and the expulsion of others, I hope it will work good amongst them, and cause many to lay down Arms, or accept of conditions to go beyond Sea: And truly, if you knew the conditions of this <reg orig="deceiptful">deceitful</reg> Nation so well as we do, it would not much pity you if you see them put to great extremities. One that was a person of Eminency amongst them was lately taken at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and was this week hanged for a Spy: General <em>Monk</em> hath sent for his Officers that are in <em>England</em>, which belong to any of the Forces here: A party of the Highlanders this came down as far as Provost <reg orig="Marburies">Marbury's</reg> house, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Dunfrize">Dumfries</reg>, and set fire thereon, killed four men, and put the Provost himself to a great fright, but getting into a place of defence with twelve men armed, they repulsed the Enemy, being about thirty in number.</p>

<p>Since the Peace was proclaimed betwixt England and Holland, the Lord Protector did feast, and most nobly entertain the Dutch Ambassadors at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>, his Highness hath entertained a Foot-guard of sixty proper men to attend and carry up meat; they have grey Cloaks, with black Velvet, and Silver-lace.</p>

<p>Great resort was this day (being the first of May) to <reg orig="Hide">Hyde</reg> Park, expecting to have seen his Highness the Lord Protector there, but he and the Lords of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> sate in debate on the great and weighty affairs of the Commonwealth.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 2.</head>

<p>This day came to our hands a perfect Copy of the Articles of Peace, as they were printed, published, and proclaimed in Holland, the Heads whereof follow.</p><pb n="2" />

<p><i>The Articles of the perpetual Peace concluded between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. on the one part, and the High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the United <em>Netherlandish</em> provinces on the other part.</i></p>

<p>1. That from hence forward there shall be a firm, and <reg orig="unchangable">unchangeable</reg> Peace, sincere friendship, and <reg orig="straiter">straighter</reg> Alliance, confederation and Union, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever heretofore between the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, the States General of the United <em>Provinces</em> of the <em>Netherlands</em>, and the respective Lands, Countries, and Cities <reg orig="every where">everywhere</reg> under their obedience, and their people, and Inhabitants.</p>

<p>2. That from henceforth all enmity, discontention, and War between the said two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, and their people, and Subjects shall cease.</p>

<p>3. That all offences, injuries, costs and damages which either party hath suffered by the other, shall be abolished, and forgotten.</p> 

<p>4. That all Prisoners on both sides, of what condition or quality soever they be, shall be released without paying <reg orig="ransome">ransom</reg>.</p> 

<p>5. That the two <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> shall remain confederate friends against all whosoever, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> endeavour to <reg orig="disturbe">disturb</reg> either State by sea, or Land, or being declared enemies to the freedoms, and liberties of the people <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> shelter themselves under either of the said <reg orig="Govrnments">Governments</reg>.</p>

<p>6. That neither of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> may make, do, act, deal, or undertake against the other, but shall actually oppose all whomsoever, who shall act, or deal, or undertake <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against either <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>

<p>7. That neither <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, nor the people dwelling or residing therein, shall give, or lend any help, counsel,<pb n="3" /> or favour to the Enemies, or Rebels of either, upon pain of Treason.</p>

<p>8. That the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> assist each other as need shall require by sea and Land, with men and ships, at the charge of the parties who desire the same.</p>

<p>9. That neither of the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, or the people hereof shall receive any person or persons, which by their <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> shall be declared Enemies, Rebels, or Fugitives.</p>

<p>10. That in case either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> <unclear>yet</unclear> their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Letters shall declare unto the other, that any persons are their Enemies, <em>&amp;c</em>: then upon such notice the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> where such person or persons resideth, shall warn them to depart within 28. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death, and loss of Lands.</p>

<p>11. That no Rebel of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> shall be received, or suffered to remain in any of the Castles, Cities, Havens, and Cricks, or other places <reg orig="priviledged">privileged</reg> within the Jurisdiction of the <em>United Provinces</em>.</p> 

<p>12. That the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the people <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, and the <em>United Provinces</em>, and the inhabitants of the same, shall be bound to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> each other with all love, and <reg orig="frindship">friendship</reg>.</p>

<p>13. That the ships of the <em>United Provinces</em> meeting in the Narrow Seas any of the English men of War, shall strike the <reg orig="Flagg">Flag</reg> as in former times.</p>

<p>14. That neither of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall receive in any of their <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg>, or assist, or refresh any <em><reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg></em>, or Sea Rovers.</p>

<p>15. That either of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> make a Treaty of Amity with any <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg>, Princes or States, they shall comprehend each other, in case they desire it.</p>

<p>16. That if <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> shall be done, or committed by any of the People of either party against this Treaty, by Land or Sea, the confederation <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be broken, but the particular party <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be punished, <em>&amp;c.</em></p> 

<p>17. That the People of this Commonwealth may freely, and with all safety travel through all quarters of the <em>United Provinces</em> to drive their Trade, armed, or unarmed, and the people of the <em>United Provinces</em> shall have the like <reg orig="priviledg">privilege</reg> here.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>18. That in case any <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships of either State by any accidents be driven into any Havens, <em>&amp;c</em>. they may depart at their pleasure without paying Customs if they break not Bulk.</p>

<p>19. That the <reg orig="Marchants">Merchants</reg>, Skippers, <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg>, <em>&amp;c.</em> of either <reg orig="Common.wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their ships, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall not be Arrested, nor seized to serve at War, unless upon inevitable necessity.</p>

<p>20. That the Merchants, and Skippers on both sides, when they go on Land, may carry any weapons of defence, and offence.</p> 

<p>21. That the Men of War of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> meeting, and holding one course, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> defend, and protect each other.</p> 

<p>22. That if any ships be taken by a third party, they shall do their endeavour to recover the same, and restore it at the charges of the owners.</p> 

<p>23. That the Searchers, and other Officers shall regulate themselves according to the Laws of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>

<p>24. That in case any injury be done by any people of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> contrary to this Treaty, no Letters of Mart shall be granted until Justice have been sought in an ordinary way.</p> 

<p>25. That all persons on both sides going to Sea with particular Commissions, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give security that they shall do no <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> to either side.</p> 

<p>26. That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be lawful for the People on either side to repair to any Port, <em>&amp;c.</em> with <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, and Men of War to victual, <em>&amp;c.</em></p> 

<p>27. That Justice be done against such as are living which had a hand in the business of <em>Amboyna</em>.</p> 

<p>28. That the King of <em>Denmark</em> pay 14000 <em>l</em>. for seizing some <em>English</em> ships, and Goods, and other injuries, are referred to arbitration.</p>

<p>29. That all discords, <em>&amp;c</em>: shall be forgotten in eternal oblivion betwixt this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the said King.</p> 

<p>30. That Commissioners to meet of injuries, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall meet in <em>London</em> the 18 of this instant <em>May</em>.</p> 

<p>31. That both parties shall firmly keep this Treaty.</p>

<p>32. That such as the States at any time shall make Captain General, <em>&amp;c:</em> shall be bound by Oath to confirm this Treaty.</p> 

<p>33. That all this Treaty shall be confirmed by the Lord Protector, and the States General, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 3.</head>

<p>Colonel <em>Nath: Fines</em> is added to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> this day was published a Proclamation of his Highness the Lord Protector in confirmation of the Treaty, and Articles of Peace before mentioned, which was signed by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Commissioners, and the Dutch Ambassadors.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>From Upsal in Sweden thus. The Queen hath now discharged the major part of her servants and Retinue, and in every respect acts to the degrading of <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, of the Government, which she <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> hath proved a burthen unto her: It is thought, that the Prince <em>Palatine</em>, who is to succeed the Queen in Government, will marry the Duke of <em><reg orig="Hosteins">Hostein's</reg></em> Daughter, by which means the two Crowns of Sweden and Denmark are like to be <reg orig="neer">near</reg> united.</p>

<p>The last night we received certain intelligence, that the Peace is fully concluded between England and Holland, and now we shall quickly see what will be done here, for my Lord Ambassador will hasten what he can, he is to have audience again <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</p>

<p>I will assure you this peace with Holland works much upon the <reg orig="stomacks">stomachs</reg> of other Nations, and I hope England will be happy, now in a full enjoyment of that which makes any Nation flourish with plenty. We cannot but admire here at the great things that have been done in England since our departure, and what an excellent choice they have made of a Protector, who is come to that <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> by the right degrees of <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, and it doth not a little <reg orig="beautifie">beautify</reg> and adorn his <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> and renown, that is <reg orig="indowed">endowed</reg> with <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg>, and all other faculties that may make his Neighbours that were at variances, his friends. One of the <em>Sages</em> of this Nation, who hath endeavoured to take a full view of his Highness the Lord Protector, with his actions and fortunes, said: <i>From such persons as these, all true glory, fame, <reg orig="graise">grace</reg>, renown and dignity, spring and grow.</i></p>

<p><i>Thursday <em>May 4</em> A Letter from Poland dated <em>24. April 1654</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>Sir,</i></p>

<p>Though for long I have kept silence, yet knowing the news we have at present to suit with your affections, I shall impart it to you: The Lord Deputy, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, have ordered a considerable number of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to go from hence to the North of Scotland to Col. <em>Allured</em>, and other Commanders, and Colonel <em>Venables</em> is gone to Chester, as it's said, to give order for shipping to meet them at Sea side. The General <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> hath cast lots for the Provinces, for satisfying the arrears of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, and the lot of the General Officers is fallen in Munster: The standing Army from <em>June</em> 1649. are content to take two thirds at present: The Officers of the Army have <reg orig="joyntly">jointly</reg> subscribed a Letter to his Highness the Lord Protector, owning the Government which is invested in him. The Native Irish are summoned to meet together in <unclear>Conagh</unclear>.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><em>Prize Office,</em> May 3. 1654.</head>

<p>Ordered that <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Baptist</em>, and the lading with <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg> Skins, <reg orig="Wooll">Wool</reg>, and other commodities, be put to sale at <em>Plymouth</em>, the tenth of this instant <em>May</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Amsterdam</em> April 28.</head>

<p>Now we believe that Peace is concluded between England and this Commonwealth, for by the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> order it hath been proclaimed, at the proclaiming whereof there was present divers Lords of the States, the <reg orig="Burgamasters">Burgomasters</reg> in great pomp, with Trumpets sounding, and in the evening many Bonfires were made, and the Magistrates of the Town sent out Wine for the young people to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> with, and keep in memory this day of Solemnity, whereas every one <reg orig="rejoyceth">rejoiceth</reg>, except the Cavalier Party, whereof many will be put to great straits, for that they must be <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to leave their friends here, and know not how to subsist <reg orig="elswhere">elsewhere</reg>, which makes some that are indebted to their Hosts very much, and others break forth into a rage, and to comfort themselves report, that <em>Charles Stuart</em> and the Duke of York are invited to meet the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> at the Spaw this Summer, and from thence they <reg orig="phancy">fancy</reg> great matters to themselves, but those which are more solid say, that this Treaty and union is so considerable, that the House of the <em>Stuarts</em> in England is eternally broken, and that the young Prince of Orange hath no abode but in Germany.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, May 5.</head>

<p>The Committee sate, in order to the regulation of the Law, and many gallant things are in agitation for ease of the people, and the due administration of Equity and Justice, in pursuance whereof, these particulars are laid before them, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p><i>1. That Justice is the Mother of <reg orig="Vertues">Virtues</reg>, the right Spouse of Fortitude, for which <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> are created, and by whose <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> they rule.</i></p>

<p><i>2. Justice allots not pardon to the wicked, which might bring the hazard of the Country.</i></p>

<p><i>3. Justice requireth Equity, Equity judgeth with Lenity, Lenity produceth <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg>, which sometimes must extend to extremity.</i></p>

<p>This day came another Letter from Holland thus. The Royal Party say, that there hath been a great fight in Scotland, and that <em>Middleton</em> hath gotten the better, and killed Colonel <em>Morgan</em>, but this is <reg orig="look't">looked</reg> upon only as a framed thing of their own, to support for a time their drooping Spirits, and therefore is little minded. There is also a report here, that a Spanish Man of War hath seized upon an English Merchant Ship, and carried her into Dunkirk: Here be many Merchantmen going forth upon Trade to several <reg orig="Countryes">Countries</reg>, and some have set Sail already.</p>

<p>This day we were advertised of a gallant Ship brought up into the River of Thames as a Prize, she was taken of an English Hoy, but of six Guns, and fifty men, the Ship is a Dutch Bottom, and came from the West-Indies very <unclear>finely</unclear> laden with Plate, and other good commodities.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Prides">Pride's</reg></em> Regiment is marching towards Scotland.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador makes many applications to his Highness the Lord Protector, by way of negotiating of a Peace between England and his Majesty (who is now of years to be crowned very suddenly) if he propound <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg> safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, he need not doubt of his errand, <i>For it is a sign of godliness to be at peace with all men, yet peace cannot triumph, except reason ruleth.</i></p>

<p>The Portugal Ambassador had <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> audience by the Lord Protector this week.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday May 8.</i></head>

<p>The Ambassador from the King of <em>Denmark</em> intimated to his Highness the Lord Protector, that he had Letters <reg orig="credentiall">credential</reg> from the King his Master &amp;c. whereupon his Highness appointed a day to give him audience, and yesterday he came to Whitehall in his Highness coach attended by Sir Oliver Fleming Master of the Ceremonies, his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> coach attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies; his Highness coming forth, the Ambassador congratulated him in his place of Government, and seemed to <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> it in happiness that so much of the differences were taken up by the Treaty with the Dutch, and hoped all would conduce to a happy peace, to the advancement of the Protestant Religion, and stopping the effusion of innocent <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>. <i>This appears very <reg orig="faire">fair</reg>, but he had <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> more of State affairs, which he imparted in writing unto his Highness</i>, and will afterwards be taken into consideration.</p>

<p>The Yeomen of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Guard wait by turns <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, M. <em>Ingoldsby</em>, brother to Col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>, is made Captain of the Guard.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and her Highness Protectoress went this day to <em>Hampton Court</em>.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for approbation and <reg orig="triall">trial</reg> of Ministers at Whitehall sate yesterday in debate of <em>Presentations</em>, and <reg orig="to day">today</reg> upon <em>Augmentations</em>.</p>

<p>Many arms are ordered to go for <em>Ireland</em>, the ship that carries them lies at Bulls Key in S. <em>Katherines</em>.</p>

<p>The East India Company have ordered that there shall be a general Court the tenth of this instant May, at which time they are to consult in this time of peace on the best <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> they can for the advance of the East India trade.</p>

<p><em>Deale</em>. 4 May 1654. we understand by a vessel that is come hither, that General <em>Pen</em> is come to the fleet with some private instructions from his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, and that within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> there will be a general <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of our Fleet upon the <reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg>. <reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> the narrow Seas will be quiet and without danger of any acts of hostility betwixt the Hollanders and us (the Articles afterwards being in force) and if any Freebooters or <reg orig="Pickerons">Picaroons</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> <reg orig="appeare">appear</reg>, we shall take a course to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> and <reg orig="sweipe">swipe</reg> the English coasts of such guests.</p>

<p><em>Leith 1. May</em>. We have little of action but what you have heard already for the Enemy avoids a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg>, in hopes to make themselves stronger: But when they hear that <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> are agreed, many will fall off from them: in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> some discontented persons, as well <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> as others, have <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> away to them, for which they may have time to repent hereafter.</p>

<p>A small Hoy went lately from hence for <em>London</em>, with goods and rich furniture belonging to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<hr />

<p>Reader, take notice, that for thy ease and satisfaction, the sum of the whole <reg orig="Weeks">Week's</reg> Intelligence is here <reg orig="comprized">comprised</reg> in one sheet.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>