<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc166">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 166</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>Letters intercepted in Scotland sent up to London, and Lieu. Gen. <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> joining with Gen. Glencarn, with 16 loads of ammunition, and the names of the Officers and Commanders, which he brought with him into Scotland. The proceedings betwixt the L. Lisle, Maj. Gen. Lambert, Sir Gilbert Pickering, &amp; the rest of the Commissioners with the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> of Holland, concerning the treaty of peace. And letters from Amsterdam touching the Orange party, and other transactions. The L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> order for the Commanders of the Army to repair to their several charges.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> March 8. to <em>Wednesday</em> March 15. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, March 8.</head>

<p>The great ship built at Wollage was lanced (<unclear>for</unclear> length she exceeds the Royal <reg orig="Sovraign">Sovereign</reg> 6 yards) she is falling down towards Gravesend in stately Equipage, and it is said that our whole Fleet will very speedily have a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs; in order whereunto Gen. Desborow, and Gen. Monk are now at Chattam, shipping of land <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, yet doth the treaty with the Holland <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> go on here, and the Articles will suddenly be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>, and after that is done, we shall very suddenly know what <pb n="1" />will be the issue of all that hath been treated of.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is preparing for the <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> and approbation of Ministers; and thirty Commissioners (Ministers and others) will be appointed to put them in execution: but the power extends <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the trying of such Ministers as have been admitted within these six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> last past, or that shall be admitted hereafter.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, March 9.</head>

<p>From Paris, March 12. Since the surrender of Beffort, the Court have assailed Count Harcourt with new temptations for a surrender of what he holds in Alsatia, and the Marshal de la Ferte Seneterre hath instructions sent him for that purpose; but it is apprehended he will never trust the Court, nor the charms of the Cardinal.</p>

<p>The Prince of Conti, and his new Princess the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, have spent their days hitherto in Balls and Feasting among the great ones, at which solemnities both the King and Cardinal have made all possible expressions of mirth and contentment. The Lady is one of much beauty, and considering her <reg orig="husbands">husband's</reg> stature, may soon look over his shoulder, in such an active Court as this is. The Cardinal keeps servants of his own about him, that as Policy and Interest made this <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> match, so Policy may keep it, <reg orig="til">till</reg> personal and State <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> do chance to break it; for, it is thought and said already, there is not much affection, nor confidence on either side. The popularity talk of a prodigious sum appointed for the <reg orig="Ladies">Lady's</reg> Portion, and they have most reason to talk (though they <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> hit right) because it goes out of their purses, whatever it be. It is not liked, that so many persons <reg orig="interestest">interest</reg>  in the City, should be visiting of Conti, where it is not known what his and his brother <reg orig="Condes">Conde's</reg> interest may yet effect, notwithstanding the late marriage, it being no new thing here, if the highest designs of malice should break out at, or after a wedding.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>His brother the Prince of Condi, is preparing to make work at Spring. This little cloud upon the Frontiers may chance to gather now that the D. of Lorrain, his great Rival and Competitor in the Spanish Interest, is laid in Limbo: for he was the great impediment to the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> designs, having (as he is charged) been tempering with France, to the prejudice of the affairs both of Spain and Condi, but being removed, and his Army disposed into the hands of his younger brother, Francis of Lorrain, a person not so debauched nor odious, but more firm at the devotion of the Spaniards, it is supposed they may be able to go on the more current in their designs upon this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>. And in Flanders they are very forward in their preparations already; Marshal <unclear>Furen</unclear> hath issued out Orders for putting of the Army with all speed, into a convenient posture to prevent them.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> March 10.</head>

<p>Dover the 9 of March, by a small <reg orig="Bark">Barque</reg> come this morning from France, we hear that a great Fleet of Dutch Merchant men, consisting of about 140 Sail is gone to the Westward, sailing close by the Coast of France, and having a fair wind, it is like they have <reg orig="past">passed</reg> without interruption from our Fleet, whom we hear is still near St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, this Dutch Fleet hath a convoy of about 60 sail of men of War, but they are to be divided, the Merchant ships being bound to several Countries and Ports: we are expecting some ships from Dunkirk, and Ostend, but as yet they are not arrived.</p>

<p>Lieth the 4 of March 1653. Since my last there is certain intelligence come of the landing of Middleton at the Ferry of Uney in Southerland, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> was sevennight, about 12 of the clock at night in an Hoy, in which was some Arms: there came with him Sir George Munroe, the Lord Nappier, Tho. Dyell, Aldermen, Major <pb n="3" /> Gen. Dyell, Lodowick Drumland, and above 100 more. The vessel was unloaded, and sent away the next morning. They sent 40 of their men or thereabouts, up to Achness with 8 or 10 Horse load of Arms, the rest they carried along with themselves, and go up Strach fleet, towards Assigne. It is reported there is another Ship loaded in Strathnemer with Arms, but no men, they speak of meeting with Glencarn in the Brays of Murray, where they are to have their <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> and from thence to <reg orig="presse">press</reg> all the Countries of Rise.</p>

<p>It was this day advertised by Letters from the North, that the Dutch Freebooters, have taken six or seven small vessels which came from Sunderland, and caused another to run ashore near Hartlepool. A Freebooter of Enchuysen hath lately taken the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ship, called <em>The Chestnut Tree of Amsterdam</em>, which had been taken by our ships not far from <unclear>Ulie</unclear>. There is arrived at Uly a Fleet of 140 sail, which came from the Eastland, a great part whereof are come to Amsterdam, and the rest to several other Ports in that Country, their lading is chiefly corn, and divers other materials for the setting forth of ships.</p>

<p>By Letters from Deal it was advertised, that on Thursday last another Fleet of Merchants belonging to the Dutch, consisting of about 150 did steer Westwards, they sailed close by the Coast of France, and had a fair wind which was the reason that our Fleet lying near St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, could not so suddenly discover them, nor easily overtake them. This Dutch fleet had a fear they should be <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> in their passage, they had therefore a strong convoy with them consisting of 60 men of War, but having brought them beyond the danger which they feared, a great part of them returned the same way they came, the others did go along with the Fleet, being bound to several Ports lying on the Western seas. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> we make great preparations for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> our <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> Fleet, 1000 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> besides Seamen were on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last drawn out of the 4 Regiments about London, and sent on shipboard.</p>

<p>Gen Desbrow, and Gen. Monk, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty are at Chattam; The <reg orig="Prest">Pressed</reg> men are put on board, and many <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of the Army: the Dutch having added 60 new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> to their Fleet, so you see what readiness the Fleets are in on both sides; and if a Peace should not be concluded, it is likely that the greatest blow would be struck that hath been yet, but it is thought there is not any question now of a full agreement.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<head level="3">Saturday, March 11.</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protectors <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> had under consideration the taking down of <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> to prevent the danger of the falling of <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, for that the cracks in the roof increase and wax greater, and much more is newly fallen where that formerly did, near the great <reg orig="fouth">fourth</reg> door: but nothing is yet ordered therein.</p>

<p>It is advertised from Scotland, that since the arrival of General Middleton, the Highlanders do grow numerous; at the <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in Murray land the Arms were distributed, some moneys received, and Letters read from their titular King, promising his assistance to the uttermost of his power, at which some signs of great joy were made, which were suddenly cooled by the tidings of the approach of our Army, of which more in the next.</p>

<p>The titular King of Scots of his own accord did choose to go into Germany, it being a journey a long time in his intention. The Queen of Bohemia is going to Frankendale, which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place, and of great frequentation, it being the middle way betwixt Worms and Spiers, where she will do the best she can to entertain him; some Letters affirm, that the titular King of Scots is way discouraged at his removal out of France, so familiar are his misfortunes with him.</p>

<p>Antwerp, March 14, 1654. The Duke of Lorrain doth still remain in our Castle, as a close prisoner; the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> doth use him with all the civil respects that may be and as <reg orig="becommeth">becometh</reg> a Prince: His brother Duke Francis (as I hear) will be <reg orig="hear">here</reg> tomorrow to command the Army. There is an Express sent to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, and another into Spain, to give notice of all that hath passed in that business; there hath not been discovered as yet any considerable sums of money in his possession; the greatest business is those jewels found about his daughter amounting to a good round sum: he keepeth <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> a very good Table, having many men to wait on him.</p>

<p>Several complaints have been made, that some differing in judgement in point of Religion from others, have affronted them in their Pulpits, to the scandal of Religion, whereupon there is something under consideration for a severe punishment to be inflicted impartially upon all whatsoever, who shall disturb the Congregation in their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> worship of God.</p>

<p>Monsieur Williamson, <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> for Denmark, is very suddenly expected to make his application to his Highness the Lord Protector</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, March 13.</head>

<p>Amsterdam the 14 of March. The Commander Ruyter is chosen Vice-Admiral for this City. The 140 sail that came from the Eastland, are part <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up to this City, and the rest go to divers ports in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. There is likewise come to the Hague an Agent or <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Minister of <reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg>, who is called the Chevalier Palant, he hath an Audience of the States General, and after that hath delivered in certain papers, wherein are expressed at large the occasion of his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, and his Demands. A <reg orig="Free-booter">Freebooter</reg> of Enchuisen hath lately retaken a ship that had been taken by the English near the Vlie: Here are two great ships also come from the Charibdie Islands.</p>

<p>From Venice the 6. Febr. 1654. By a ship that came lately from Candia, we hear that <unclear>Uslaim</unclear> Bashaw, who is General of the Turkish Army in that Island, intending to besiege anew that City, had brought all his forces near the place, intending to <reg orig="intrench">entrench</reg> and <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> themselves close to the walls, but that our forces within had made such a <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> <reg orig="salley">sally</reg> upon those infidels, that they had not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> made them to forsake their new works, but likewise made them to retreat in a disorderly way, but not without some considerable loss on our part. Here are now four ships under sail, which carry men, moneys, and the like warlike necessaries for the relief of Candia; and there are more ships which will be ready for the same purpose in a few days. Our Levies likewise go on gallantly, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> those in Germany, but also those in several parts of Italy: Divers persons who had been exiled from this City, have made their peace with considerable sums of money, among whom is the Earl Porcellago of Breseia.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>Further from Paris thus. The Marshal de la Ferte having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things at Beffort, is marched towards Brisack, with an intent to bring the Earl of Harcourt to accept those conditions mentioned in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Declaration, which <reg orig="setleth">settleth</reg> him on those conditions as he was when he left the Leagure of Villanova in Agenois, and in a case of denial, the said Marshal is to block him up, and reduce him by force of arms, having already taken some Castles which are leading on to the work. The garrison that marched out of Beffort came to <reg orig="Luxenburgh">Luxembourg</reg> in a reasonable good condition. The French forces are still quartered in Languedoc and now the provisions brought into Rosa being near spent; therefore care is had to relieve the place with more. There have been some motisons made of late by friends behalf of Cardinal de Retz, yet hath he not his <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>This <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> Letter is said to be written by the Cardinal to the Duke of <em>Orleans.</em></i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>I can no longer live without writing, for I understand the Court hath done some kind of Justice wherewith you are reasonably well pleased, but if this content be not absolute, I am resolved not to rejoice; and truly it is a shame to see the bounties of Princes in the hands of such persons, who can neither be useful nor pleasing unto them and that honest men must still <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves with the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> testimony of a good conscience, and in the content they receive in well doing, for my part I will not complain of fortune, if others must have the use of her. Now if the Ministers of State understood my secret, and that for satisfying of two, it were <reg orig="onely">only</reg> necessary to oblige one, by acquitting themselves of what they <reg orig="ow">owe</reg> another, they might easily spare what they have done unto me.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday March, 14.</head>

<p>Philip Lord Lisle, Major Gen. Lambert, Sir Gilbert Pickering, John Lawrence, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> George Mountague, and Walter Strickland, Esq. had this day a large conference with the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> concerning the explaining of some words which seem to afford some ambiguity in the Articles. Thus you see how weighty matters of State go on by gradations; a few more steps will lead to a period of this great business.</p>

<p>From Deal we hear that upon notice given to our Fleet that about 60 Dutch Merchants ships ere lately gone forth with a small convoy, a squadron of ours sailed forth towards the Coast of France, <reg orig="indeavouring">endeavouring</reg> for to meet with them, but as yet <reg orig="wee">we</reg> cannot hear what <reg orig="successe">success</reg> they had.</p>

<p>The Merchant adventurers for Ireland are to meet at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall London on Thursday next, for making a Lottery for the Narronies.</p>

<p>The Committee for Obstructions sitting at Worcester house in the Strand, have <reg orig="adjorned">adjourned</reg> till the 13 of April next, at which time the Commissioners for the sale of the Lands, &amp;c. belonging to the late King, Queen, and Prince sit there again.</p>

<p>In some Churches in London many godly people kept this day in fasting &amp; prayer, for imploring the blessing of rain from above, in this time of drought, which we the rather mention, that people may with <reg orig="thankfull">thankful</reg> hearts take notice of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg>, in his <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> to answer their prayers, in sending down sweet and refreshing showers upon the earth, at the very same instant, in which they are seeking unto him for that mercy.</p>

<p>There be some Copies of Letters intercepted from Scotland, sent to London, which within few days will be made <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>

<p>From Amsterdam they write of a stately Fleet almost in readiness, and say, that it far exceeds the number they have yet had forth to fight, and their <em>Prospective</em> out of England is Reciprocal, and (say some of the Letters) all Christendom stand amazed at the transactions of these so mighty and considerable <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, yet they seem not to doubt but their <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> have before this time ratified the Peace with England, saying that they had but six weeks allotted for their stay in England.</p>

<p>The Orange party are indifferent quiet for the present, though they talk very high, but being they are put to play an after game, the matter is so much the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> considerable.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>