<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc175">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 175</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> particulars.</head>

<p><i>The dividing of the English Fleet into several Squadrons to go against the Enemy, and the great Design of the main Fleet. A new Plot discovered against the English. The Aid and Assistance which is lately come to General Middleton and the Highlanders in Scotland; with their design to surround <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan, and his Forces. The Declaration of <em>William of <reg orig="Nassaw">Nassau</reg></em> touching the Articles of Peace between England and Holland. The Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> Order for the besieging of Bremen. With variety of other Intelligence from several parts of the World.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em>, May 10. to <em>Wednesday</em>, May 17. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, May 10.</i></head>

<p>By Letters out of Berkshire it was advertised, that the seventh of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> there were nine persons apprehend for Witches in that County, and sent to <reg orig="Redding">Reading</reg> <reg orig="Gaole">Gaol</reg>.</p>

<p>This day the Sessions began in the Old <reg orig="Bayly">Bailey</reg>; there were upon their <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> Master Downs and Master Smith for <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> of moneys, and several persons for Felony.</p>

<p>An Ordinance of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> was set forth for setting apart Tuesday May 23 instant for a day of Thanksgiving for the happy Peace with the Dutch, and the<pb n="1" /> seasonable Rain, which it pleased God to send us since our seeking in that behalf in fasting and prayer.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday May 11.</head>

<p>Scilly Island the 5th of May 1654. A Master of a ship from Virginia reports, that an Indian <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> himself unto the English there, and discovered unto them a design of the Natives to fall on the English about the beginning of this instant May, and that the English would be ready to prevent their <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> purposes, a Vessel of Tixgmouth bound for Walls for Coals came in hither yesterday, she was taken about the middle of the day a league to the East of those Islands by Mildrum a Brest man of War of about 10 Guns, who having plundered the vessel dismissed her again, and bad her to make <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> into Scilly, for their were four or five more of his Comrades coming down the North Channel, whom he should avoid, and that they had 10 or 12 guns a piece. There were aboard Mildrum some English that were lately taken by our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, and being brought ashore they suddenly obtained their liberty, and got to Brest again, so that there is little hopes that <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> but a Halter will reclaim those rogues from their <reg orig="Theeving">Thieving</reg> kind of life. The chief Gunner of <reg orig="Mildrums">Mildrum's</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> named Thomas Sloe, was very lately taken in another <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg> of Brest by one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, and now is with Mildrum again.</p>

<p>Dublin May 1. We have nothing of news to send you from hence, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> here hath been a general <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers to divide their lands, the result whereof I shall acquaint you by the next. The Lord Broghil, and Sir <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Coots Brother are sent to England with a Congratulatory message from the general <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers in Ireland, to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, the Lord General Fleetwood will be also in England suddenly.</p><pb n="2" />

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 4. This day came General Monk from Dalkieth to <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, attended by the chief Officers of the Army, who were received at the Netherbow by the English Judges in their Scarlet Robes, and the Town Magistrates, the Provost and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> in theirs likewise. The Generals and Officers alighting from their horses, marched with those that met them up the high street to the Cross, which was adorned with <reg orig="Tapistry">Tapestry</reg>, and there Advocate General Whaley proclaimed his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, &amp;c. as also the Ordinance for uniting Scotland to England, before a great concourse of people, Drums beating, Trumpets sounding, and voices <reg orig="ecchoing">echoing</reg> forth acclamations. After this was done, a great dinner was provided by the Magistrates of this Town to entertain the General, his Officers, and others; and to close the solemnity, this night was variety of fireworks which continued till 11 of the clock. There is 12 sail of our men of war now riding in <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> Road, which together with the <reg orig="Generals">General's</reg> speedy preparations for a march into the field, strikes terror into the spirits of the Highland spoilers.</p>

<p>Further from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, May 6, 1654. Major Gen. Drummond came from Middleton to <reg orig="Lough-Tay">Lough Tay</reg> about 3 instant, and Glencarn with about 100 horse, and one Murray with the like number of foot came into Athol about the 4 instant. They give out, they past by Col. Morgan in a mist, but it is supposed they came by Loughaber. They intend to hasten their levies, and speed to the North to surround Col. Morgan. <reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg> is raising his levies at Branar, and some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties which are come from Middleton are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with him. They say they expect <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart when their design is a little more ripe. Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> 5 companies are come up. The General will be at <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> next week.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>From Milford Haven, May 8. All those that were here waiting for a fair wind to go over to Ireland, went away, 2 days since, we have not heard <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> from thence lately, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> by a vessel come to Blewmorris, we hear that all things are in a peaceable condition, but want people to manure the ground; The Tories being now very few, have stirred very little of late. There were the last week seen near this place, two Brest <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> who were <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the Northward, and had with them three <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg>, which they had taken <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from Dublin to <reg orig="Leverpool">Liverpool</reg> and Chester, as they told a fisherman who was aboard of them, one of them had 12 guns and 90 men, and the other 4 guns, and 40 men.</p>

<p>From Rye, May 12. We have little of news to write at present, only that we see <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> now freed from the Dutch men of war, the little <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> of Ostend do much vex and torment the fishermen upon this coast, under pretence of seeking after French vessels. One of them this week having 4 small guns, attempted to take a Barque, being on her way down between Deep and this place; but the Barque having many passengers, as well English as French, did defend themselves so gallantly, that in a little dispute the Ostender lost 7 men, besides some wounded, and in all probability they might have got away, but that a shot most unhappily took place in the Barque between wind and water, which sunk her down immediately, but most of the passengers were saved.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, May 12.</head>

<p>Paris, May 14. 1654. The last night his Majesty returned from <reg orig="Fontanbleau">Fontainebleau</reg> to this City. Cardinal Mazarine rode in his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> own Coach, and after them came about 50 Coaches more with Noblemen and their attendants. This day some Commissioners from the City of Rheims made their addresses to his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, declaring the constant and <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> obedience of that City to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> commands, and that the day of his <reg orig="Annointing">Anointing</reg> or Coronation was very desirable to them. The King returned thanks for their good affections, and told them that that he should come shortly to that City in order to his Coronation.</p>

<p>By Letters from Germany we hear, that the troubles of the famous <em>Lutherans</em> increase; for the Earl of Oxenstern hath carried express orders from the Queen of Sweden to General Koningsmark to block up the City of Bremen, after he hath taken all the small Towns about it; whereupon this General doth compel all the <unclear>Boots</unclear> of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to<pb n="4" /> take up Arms against the Bremish <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>; and the Citizens act as fast as they can for their own preservation, and force in all they can to aid and assist them, hoping likewise that they shall have some assistance from their neighbouring States, especially from Holland, which it is thought the Hollander will be backward in doing, for fear of bringing down the mighty Land Army against themselves which is prepared and ready to move in Sweden.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday May 13.</head>

<p>By Letters from Venice it is thus certified. The new Generalissimo Moccenigo is now ready to take shipping for Candia, and with him are to 12 of our Nobles, 4000 foot <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, 100 horse, and divers Engineers, who are to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to make new Fortifications, and repair the old where it shall be thought <reg orig="needfull">needful</reg> in those places which we yet possess in Candia; from whence we hear that the Turks are now repairing the Fort called Lazaretto, thereby to hinder a relief from coming into the City of Candia, whose <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> is likewise employed in repairing some Out-works which were decayed. Our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is not <unclear>so great</unclear> in Dalmatia as it was esteemed, by reason that many of our <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were counted to be dead, or taken prisoners, were fled into the Mountains for shelter, and so come in daily into to our Army. Nevertheless upon the advice received from General Delfino, that the Enemy had appointed a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> to their forces, and that they have some design upon Spalatto; therefore the Earl Vincentino was commanded that way to observe their march. There is a ship lately built here of a new structure or invention, by one Angelo Barberigo, who promiseth that this ship with 30 guns and 8 great <reg orig="murtherers">murderers</reg>, will perform extraordinary service; the Senate hath promised him a very great gratuity, in case it proveth effectual according to his engagement.</p>

<p>From Paris, May 16. Cardinal Mazarine is very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in furnishing his Library, he hath already near 40000 <reg orig="Volumns">Volumes</reg>, and daily <reg orig="encreaseth">increaseth</reg> the same. The Commissioners from St. Malo, and other places in Brittany have made great complaints concerning the taking of many of their ships by the English <reg orig="frigots">frigates</reg>, desiring liberty to seize upon the ships and goods of the English on the land, but that would not be granted: then they petitioned for leave to set out men of War, and that they may have Letters of Mart to make them satisfaction for their great losses. Count Harcourt hath sent an Express to the Court intimating, that he doth submit to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> pleasure, and will deliver up his charge to <reg orig="whom soever">whomsoever</reg> the King will send.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>From Turin. Our chief work is now to make all things ready with all expedition for the next Campagna, and doubt not but that our Army will be ready to march into the field the middle of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, as soon as the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> de Caracena, who <reg orig="wil">will</reg> scarce be ready so soon one of the main <reg orig="hinderances">hindrances</reg> being, the want of new Levies in Germany not yet come, neither the money expected from Naples, as also some <reg orig="brasse">brass</reg> pieces of Ordnance which were lately cast there.</p>

<p>From Rome. The Pope is not yet recovered of his <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg>, <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> he hath been lately carried in a horse litter to see the new building of the Church of St. Agnes, founded by him, and endowed of great Revenues, he was accompanied of 25 Cardinals, many Princes, <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> and several other persons of great rank, and having dined at the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> of the <em>Pamfilii</em> returned again to the Quirinal, and at the last Consistory of all, there was made a decree that from henceforth there shall not be held any Congregations, in private houses but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> at the Vatican.</p>

<p>From Naples, There hath been lately mustered here 22 Companies, and about 5 Troops of horses, being all of the new Levies, but the Companies and Troops being all very thin, and wanting much of their full number, <reg orig="som">some</reg> small quantity of monies being given to each <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> thereby to make him go more <reg orig="chearfully">cheerfully</reg> in the service. One of the chief of the Bandity whom they call King <em>Saul</em> having with 16 of his men met the Post going to Bari at the bridge of Lavignano had robbed him of all, and as he was about to strip him, there happened some <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of Montesocscoli, who having fought with him, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> made him leave all his prey, but also killed him, one Officer, and took one of his men prisoner, and chased the<pb n="6" /> rest for many miles: They write us from Otranta that there hath been lately in those parts two great Earthquakes, which hath caused much <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> among the inhabitants.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 15.</head>

<p>This morning we received the welcome news of 300 sail of Coals which are come into the River from Newcastle, but the wind which hath blown this fortnight from the East and Northeast, hath not been altogether so favourable to some ships of ours bound for the North of Scotland.</p>

<p>It is certain that the last week a Woman in this City coming casually into a room where she found her husband kissing another Woman, she immediately departed to her own house, and for all the declarations, and protestations of her husband, she refused to be comforted, having her heart so much contracted with the suddenness of that most ungrateful sight, that the next day she died for grief.</p>

<p>The Letters from Scotland do advertise, that General Monk was lately in <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, and is now on his advance towards the Highlanders, to whom divers Renegadoes do still resort. Their <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of new provision for the War doth much <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> them, so that their Levies of late do much increase. Middleton knowing what an Enemy he hath to deal with, doth the manage the War with great dexterity. Some Letters do represent, that he will fight with Col. Morgan before the <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of more forces are added to him. There was lately a great dispute at the maintaining of a Pass, in which Sir Arthur Forbs was routed, and divers killed and taken. The titular King of Scotland hath sent a Letter to Middleton, in which he exhorteth and conjureth the Commanders to an Union in this time of their greatest necessity.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, May 16.</head>

<p>From Deal we understand by Letters that a Squadron of our Fleet are gone Northward to scour those seas, and to prevent the coming over of assistance to the enemy in Scotland: but they could not come thither time enough to meet with the late supplies of men, money, and ammunition, which was conveyed into Scotland out of France by the way Dunkirk. Another part of our Fleet are gone Westward, to chase away the Brest men of War, who have done us much mischief at several times upon the West of England; but the main body of the Fleet are appointed for a greater design.</p>

<p>The Committee sit <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> for regulation of the Law, or at least the course of proceedings, for which we find much reason to do it; but as for the Fundamental <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg>, or the Common <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> of this Nation, they are so full of reason, that it were even against reason to alter them.</p>

<p>The Letters from Scotland this Post, make no mention of any further action <reg orig="then">than</reg> what you have in the <reg orig="fore going">foregoing</reg> passages; only we hear the Enemy swells pretty big in his own conceit: And I do not wonder that they are so high in words, seeing their persons continue the ambition rather of dwelling upon the tops of the highest mountains <reg orig="then">than</reg> to charge us fairly in the valleys.</p>

<p>Plymouth, 12 May, 1654. Two Merchant men are come into this Port, or rather driven in for fear of the Brest men and <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, who are still thick upon this coast: But we hear that a Squadron of our Fleet is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> this way, the very appearance whereof will half sink them, or (in conceit) drive them aground. These two ships are bound for London, and bring news of some late losses sustained by the Dutch about Brazil. There is great preparations for War in several parts beyond the sea; what the designs are, and what effects they will produce, time will discover. Here is great talk of some new differences or discontents in Holland, and some say, that William of <reg orig="Nassaw">Nassau</reg> hath declared. That he is against the Articles of Peace concluded on with England: they say also that the most part of the Land <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> do adhere to him, and in his behalf have seized upon divers eminent places there. But we take this as a bare rumour, raised by some of the adverse party.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>