<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfII2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect and Impartial Intelligence, Issue 2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">Perfect and Impartial</head>
<head level="1">INTELLIGENCE,</head>
<head level="3">The Affairs in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, And other Parts beyond the Seas.</head>
<head level="3">Together with the Continuation of the History of CAIUS JULIUS <reg orig="CESAR">C&aelig;SAR</reg>.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em> May 23. to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg></em> May 26, 1654.</p>
<hr />

<p>This day was kept a day of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Thanksgiving to Almighty God, according to the Declaration of the Lord Protector, lately mentioned, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, and Mr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, prayed and preached at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, where the Lord Protector and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> were present. And after Sermon a Woman made a disturbance by reproaching the present authority. It was kept in many Parishes in London, and by divers Churches, yet some would not observe it, and some kept a day of Humiliation.</p>

<p><em>Hague 6 (alias 16) May</em>. Here is arrived an Envoy from the City of <em>Bremen</em> to acquaint the States General of the condition they are in, are to desire Counsel and help against the Invasion of the Swedes.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Hague 10 (alias 20) May.</i></head>

<p>Besides the first private Publication and Thanksgiving, the next <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the Publication of the Peace concluded between England and this State, is to be made through all the United Provinces, and in the evening <reg orig="Bonefires">Bonfires</reg>, with shooting off the Ordnance, and there shall be eight days after a day of Thanksgiving shall be kept. The States of Holland are yet sitting. The <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg><pb n="1" /> went yesterday to <em>Onstaerdiick</em> with the young Prince her Son. There is a triumphal Arch built at Amsterdam upon the place called the Dam, where also all the <reg orig="Cannons">Canons</reg> have been brought from the Arsenals to made use of for the expressing our joy upon the news of peace.</p>
	
<head level="3"><i>From the River Elve 6 May.</i></head>

<p>The Magistrates of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> and Lubeck have sent some Deputies to mediate an agreement between the Swedes and the City of Bremen, whereupon the quarters of the Low Saxony, have also Deputed to Hamburg, to join with them in that mediation. We hear from Swedeland that the Queen hath already discharged a great many of her Court Officers and Servants, and that the Lord <em>Erick Oxenstern</em> is named to be sent extraordinary <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> into England.</p>

<head level="3">From Bremen 17 May.</head>

<p>The Swedes have commanded upon great penalties the Inhabitants of this County to work about the fencing of the Suburbs of this City, lately taken by them. The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath in the mean time issued out a command, by which the General Koningsmark is almost forbidden to molest any more this City, and commanded to deliver us up again our Suburbs, Veghensack, and all the other places he hath taken from us, forbidding also the Bores, or any other of these parts to assist the Swedes.</p>

<p><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 12 May</i>. The Deputies of the Low Saxony have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> met here with our Commissioners about the relief of the City of <em>Bremen</em> but also to make a defensive league with us.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the enemies of the peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal Providences of God in frustrating of their former counsels and malicious Designs) do appear still <reg orig="restlesse">restless</reg> in their attempts, to<pb n="2" /> involve this Commonwealth in <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> and confusion. In order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to London, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> with the advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> charge and command, that for the better discovery of persons <reg orig="il">ill</reg> affected to the peace of this Commonwealth, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of London and Westminster. <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Southwark and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication hereof, repair to the several houses within the respective Parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as now do, or did lodge in their respective houses on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> night last being the 19 of this instant May, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names, upon peril of being reputed and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> as <reg orig="complices">accomplices</reg> and <reg orig="pertakers">partakers</reg> in the designs. Which List so delivered, the respective Constables of the parishes within the Cities of London and Westminster, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Southwark and Lines of Communication, are within 48 hours to deliver the Lord Mayor of London, &amp; <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster &amp; Southwark, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril.</p>

<p>And the said Lord Mayor and Bailiffs are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, immediately after the receipt thereof. And his Highness doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever, lodging in the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several<pb n="3" /> and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of 10 days after the date hereof, without a special <reg orig="Licence">License</reg> and <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor of the said City of London; or <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of Westminster or Southwark respectively, under their respective hands and seals; which <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark respectively, are hereby authorized to give all such persons concerning whom they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be satisfied, that they have no ill intentions or designs against the Commonwealth, and to none else. And if any such person shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without <reg orig="Licence">License</reg> obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a contempt of this his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> command and be punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of London, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after publication thereof, to be sent to the constables as aforesaid, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> 23 May.</i></p>

<p>The Plot upon the best intelligence I have, was to have <reg orig="murdred">murdered</reg> the Lord Protector, the time to be <reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> or Sunday last. A vessel was taken with letters from <em>France</em>, and he whom they say should have <reg orig="murdred">murdered</reg> his Highness leaped overboard and drowned himself.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The names of those that are taken about the Plot.</i></head>

<p>Gilbert Gerhard Esq. John Gerhard a Kinsman of Gilbert <reg orig="Gerhards">Gerhard's</reg>, Mr. <reg orig="Tuedor">Tudor</reg> Apothecary, M. Jones, Sidney Fothers, M. Baggly, Dr Naudiu, Maj. Mason, M. Peter Brown, M. Hill.</p>

<hr />

<p>It is hereby promised that the 1 Book of the observations on <em><reg orig="Aristotles">Aristotle's</reg> Politicks</em>, shall be published three <reg orig="Moths">Months</reg> hence <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> together; excepting the first parts which may be had at Mr. <em><reg orig="Moons">Moon's</reg></em> at the <reg orig="seaven">seven</reg> stars in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> churchyard. this work shall be <unclear>continued</unclear> <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> and Tuesday weekly containing all the news that is beneficial for the Reader.</p><pb n="4" />

<hr />
<head level="3">CHAP. II.</head>
<hr />

<p>As <em>C&aelig;sar</em> was crossing the sea to the Isle of <em>Rhodes</em>, his fortune was about the Isle <em>Pharmacusa</em>, to be taken by Rovers or <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg>, with them he remained in custody, not without exceeding indignation for the space of 40 days, accompanied with one <reg orig="Phisitian">Physician</reg> and two grooms of his Chamber, for his Companions and the rest of his Train, he had sent away immediately at the very first, to procure him money with all speed for his <reg orig="ransome">ransom</reg>: upon their return and his <reg orig="paiment">payment</reg> of 50 Talents, being set on shore, he delayed not time, but presently procured a small Fleet of his friends who aided him with men as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as ships he puts to Sea: pursued the <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, fighteth with them, overcommeth and taketh them prisoners, and hangeth them, as he <reg orig="often times">oftentimes</reg> had <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> them in his mirth, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was a prisoner with them.</p>

<p><i>Great and <reg orig="ambicious">ambitious</reg> spirits never omit making of opportunity to increase their fame, and opinion of worth in the people: <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> maketh use of opportunity, he calleth it the will of the Gods: <reg orig="Highway men">Highwaymen</reg> have opportunity to rob, and kill sometimes, the Divel had opportunity and <reg orig="permition">permission</reg> to torment <em><reg orig="Iob">Job</reg></em>.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Mean while">Meanwhile</reg>, <em>Mithridates</em> wasted the Countries next adjoining his Dominion, <em>C&aelig;sar</em> because he would <reg orig="shew">show</reg> his active spirit in so dangerous and <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> a state of the Confederates and Allies of <em>Rome</em>, he left <em>Rhodes</em>, and gathered a power of <reg orig="Auxilary">Auxiliary</reg> or <reg orig="voluntier">volunteer</reg> <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, expelled the <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> of <em>Mithridates</em> out of the Provinces and kept the Cities and States in their Allegiance, which were wavering, and at the point to revolt.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> had no Commission for what he did but because he had success and the Commonwealth the benefit by having its enemies vanquished: <reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> is not called to account, in this be <reg orig="usurpt">usurped</reg> absolute authority in raising<pb n="5" /> forces and attempting to make war without authority of the Senate; by which it appeareth the Senate did decline in their policy as well as the Commonwealth in <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>: the Senate should have taken his head <reg orig="of">off</reg> for that Act, and so have ridded the Commonwealth of a Usurper, the <reg orig="Commonweal">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>Rome</em> turned to a Monarchy because the Senate did not keep the arms of the Commonwealth in their hands: the Senate after the disposing of the absolute power of Arms, signified no more <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Cipher, those <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and Senates that will be <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> and just, must be free, not <reg orig="over-awed">overawed</reg> with Arms, those that are, are not free.</i></p>

<p>After this victorious <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, <em>C&aelig;sar</em> returneth to <em>Rome</em>, and is by the Commons elected Tribune, he assisted <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> his might the Patrons of the Commons. <em>M. Crassus</em> and others, who stood out for the <reg orig="Tribunes">Tribune's</reg> authority, the force and strength whereof <em>Silla</em> had abated, he effected moreover thus much, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of an Act proposed by Plotius a Tribune of the Commons, that they who together with him in the time of civil discord, took part with <em>Lupidius</em> (who after his death fled unto <em>Sertorius</em>) might return safely into the City, and <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> their freedom, touching which matter he made an Oration before the people.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> now had great authority with the people, he pretendeth much zeal to restore the authority of the Tribunes of the people, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to weaken the authority of the Nobility, who diligently watched to prevent the usurping of one as absolute Lord, that thereby they might maintain equal authority amongst themselves; but <reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> that he might oblige more to strengthen and own his <reg orig="intrest">interest</reg> obtaineth an Act to call home several mutinous persons: Senates when they are <reg orig="over-awed">overawed</reg>, are but as Moulds in which are cast what forms of Laws the Usurpers or over-awers please.</i></p>

<p><em>C&aelig;sar</em> upon the death of <em>Julia</em> his Aunt by the <reg orig="fathers">father's</reg> side, and upon the death of his wife <em>Cornelia</em> both late deceased, made a funeral Oration in their praise, where he spake of their pedigree and descent namely his Aunt, and also of her father he maketh report in manner following. My Aunt <em>Julia</em> (quoth he) by the mother is lineally descended of Kings, and by the father was united, to the race of the immortal Gods: for from <em>Ancus Marcius</em> are derived the <em>Marcii</em> surnamed <em>Reges</em>, <em>id est</em> Kings, which name my mother was <reg orig="stiled">styled</reg> with, and from <em>Venus</em> the <em>Julii</em> drew their original; of which house and name is our family, so then in this stock they concur and meet together, as well the Sanctity and sacred Majesty of<pb n="6" /> King, who among men are most <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg>, as the religious ceremonies and services of the Gods, in whose power Kings themselves are.</p>

<p><i>It is a thing frequent that when any have lifted their heads <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> above their brethren or their contemporaries, although they descended of never forbade Parents, or their beginning were never so obscure, as Potters, <reg orig="Black-smiths">Blacksmiths</reg>, or other such like, they or some Flatterers for them, <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to produce their pedigree of noble Houses, give honourable arms. <em>Alexander</em> must be the Son of <em><reg orig="Iupiter">Jupiter</reg> Olimpius</em>: <em>C&aelig;sar</em> must be descended from the Gods and the Kings; <em>Castruccio Castricave</em> of Lucca, who when an Infant was found in an Orchard, who came of unknown Parents, must take upon him the name of <em>Castricani</em>, the name of the most honourable family of that State, after he made himself Lord thereof as <em>Machivil</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>.</i></p>

<p><em>C&aelig;sar</em> after the death of his wife, wedded <em>Pompeii</em> daughter of Q. <em>Pompeius</em>, and <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> to L. <em>Sylla</em>, afterwards divorced her, suspecting she had been <unclear>naught</unclear> with P. <em>Clodius</em> of whom there was a report, that at the celebration of certain <reg orig="publick">public</reg> divine Ceremonies, he being disguised in <reg orig="womans">woman's</reg> apparel had <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> secretly unto her: to find out the truth of this matter the Senate by decree directed a Commission to <reg orig="Iustices">Justices</reg> Inquisitors.</p>

<p><i>These Ceremonies was performed in <em><reg orig="C&aelig;sars">C&aelig;sar's</reg></em> house when he was Poutifex they were for the cleansing of the women.</i></p>

<p>While <em>C&aelig;sar</em> was Quester it <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> out to him by lot to execute that Office in the further Province of <em>Spain</em>; where, when as by command by the Lord Pretour: he rode his Circuit to keep the Assize coming to <em>Gades</em>, beholding advisedly the Image or Portraiture of K. <em>Alexander</em> the Great, in the Temple of <em>Hercules</em>, at the sight thereof he fetched a deep sigh, in that he had performed yet no memorable act at those years, wherein <em>Alexander</em> had conquered the whole world, he presently made earnest <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> for his discharge and licence to depart, thereby to take the first opportunity to purchase great <reg orig="enterprizes">enterprises</reg> at home within the City.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Cesars">C&aelig;sar's</reg> ambition pricked him forward to great undertakings, his Cloak or <reg orig="vizard">wizard</reg> for his ambition was <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affection to the <reg orig="intrest">interest</reg> of the Commons, who he made Slaves of as well as the Lords or Nobility, whose estates he made use of to maintain arms to defend him in his usurpation: to effect which he cunningly makes his repair to the City the heart of the Empire, he that will poison sure must poison the heart; or so<pb n="7" /> effectually poison other part or parts, that in the operation thereof it shall immediately convey <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to the heart, the <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> parts being poisoned or infected may be cut off to save the whole, as the hand or <reg orig="legg">leg</reg>. A Usurper or a Tyrant is not so dangerous <reg orig="any where">anywhere</reg> as in the Metropolitan City or the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg> or Senate. Out of both City and Senate the State of <em>Venice</em> do <reg orig="expell">expel</reg> such who they stand so in fear of, especially such who have arms in their hands, they shut out, and by no means permit.</i></p>

<p>The night before <em>C&aelig;sar</em> undertook his <reg orig="journy">journey</reg> towards the City of <em>Rome</em> he <reg orig="dreampt">dreamt</reg> that he had carnal company with his own mother, the Diviners and Wizards incited him thereby to the hope of most glorious achievements, making this exposition of his Dreams that thereby was portended to him the <reg orig="soveraignty">sovereignty</reg> of the whole world, considering that his mother that he saw under him betokened nothing else but the subjection of the earth, which is counted the mother of all things.</p>

<p><i>This dream troubled <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> sorely, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> this interpretation was made of it, the knowledge thereof prompt him much; in which service the <reg orig="Divels">Devil's</reg> Emissaries the Wizards was very diligent, he is an enemy to mankind; he practiseth the death, slavery, and servitude of man continually, man was in Paradise alive, innocent, and in <reg orig="freedome">freedom</reg>; he practiseth and accomplisheth his fall, death, guilt and slavery to sin, he is very ready to assist Tyrants and Usurpers: he sendeth of his most exquisite art, viz. to counterfeit even an Angel of light that he may deceive, he hateth <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that may be called liberty of mankind; he <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> assisteth in <reg orig="excesse">excess</reg> of liberty, to put a necessity on them of servitude; Tyrants are the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> servants of the <reg orig="Divel">Devil</reg>, and the plague of <reg orig="man-kind">mankind</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>Would it not have been incest, a sin against nature for <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> to have lain with his mother, was it not as much a sin against nature, for him to ravish the Commonwealth, and take away its liberty, and put a necessity upon them to accept him to be their Lord without their free consent, ye sure it was.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> in his way went unto the <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg> Colonies, which were at that time devising and in counsel to sue for the freedom of the City of <em>Rome</em>, and no doubt had <reg orig="sollicited">solicited</reg> and excited them to attempt some tumult and trouble in the State, but that the Consuls for the avoiding of this danger, kept back for a time, those Legions that were <reg orig="inroled">enrolled</reg> to be sent into <em>Cicelia</em>.</p>

<p>The end of the 2d. Chapter.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>