<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc159">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>
A Perfect Account, Issue 159
</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" /> 
<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="2">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>
<p><i>The several offences which are made high Treason by his Highness the L. Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. An order for repealing of several Acts of Parliament for the ease of the people of fines and penalties. With the proceedings of his Highness concerning taking off Taxes and other grievances. A Messenger from the States of Holland concerning the Treaty. The great increase of the Rebels in Scotland. The new mischiefs done by the Tories in Ireland. General <reg orig="Blakes">Blake's</reg> going forth with the fleet to Sea, Several Dutch Ships taken, and other news from many other parts.</i></p>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> January 18. to <em>Wednesday</em> January 25. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>January</em> 18.</i></head>
<p>The <unclear>Sessions</unclear> in the <reg orig="Old-Bayly">Old Bailey</reg> now sitting, it was expected that the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> brother should be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>; but upon a petition, and other considerations, his <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> is put off till the next Sessions.</p>
<p>A man that made or caused to be stamped Brass Farthings, &amp; refused to take them again by way of Exchange, was lately indicted for uttering four brass pieces for a <reg orig="peny">penny</reg>, which were not worth so much; and the party being found guilty, suffered a Fine, according to the mercy of the Bench.</p>
<pb n="1" />
<p>We hinted in our last of an <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> to be subscribed by the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army, the which hath now been signed by the greatest part of them; the Copy whereof followeth.</p>
<head level="3"><i>To his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, Our Lord General.</i></head>
<head level="3"><i>The humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army.</i></head>
<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services wherein through the blessing of God upon the <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg> and <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, we have in some measure been instrumental in our places to free the Commonwealth from its enemies: So we now cannot but above all worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations after all the shakings which have been in the midst of us, set <unclear>np</unclear> upon its true and proper Basis and Foundation, and thereby brought into a harbour of rest and safety. The sense whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your Highness and the whole Nation at this time, when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment by inclining you to accept the Government and Protection of this Commonwealth; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the people, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We judge it highly incumbent upon us to make our humble <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> unto you, and to declare that we shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be obedient unto you <pb n="2" /> in the performance of your great Trust; but in our places most faithfully and diligently to the hazard of our lives, and whatsoever is near and dear unto us be serviceable unto you in the Station God hath places you against all opposition: <unclear>Not</unclear> doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; So you will to the utmost of your power and <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> lay forth <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> for the glory of God, and the good of this people amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take this <reg orig="boldnesse">boldness</reg>, most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, more especially to spread the wing of your protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, which you continuing to do. We are confident their Father which is in heaven, will be unto you a Buckler and a Shield and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>
<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> most humble and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servants.</i></p>
<head level="3">Thursday, Jan. 19.</head>
<p>Dalkeith, Jan. 14. Kenmore and <reg orig="Glencary">Glengarry</reg> with their force, marched by the way of Strathspey, and <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>, Mac Aldney, and some of <reg orig="Mac Griggers">Macgriggors's</reg> men, with the rest of the gang (<reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg> being left behind) marched by the head of <reg orig="Badgnoth">Badenoch</reg>, and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> their forces within 3 miles of <reg orig="Ruthen">Ruthven</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>. Upon their approach, <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> sent a Letter to the Governor of the Castle, inviting him to come into his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> force, telling him, That all Scotland was up in arms, and many had marched through England to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. To which he received a very resolute and ingenious answer from the Governor, Cap. Hill; and it was not probable that his Lordship had so great an Army, when he could provide no better quarters for <pb n="3" /> them. After they had been a while in <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>, there fell a discontent between <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> and <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>, about the men of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg> saying, They being his men, he ought to have the ordering and disposal of them, as the Earl of <reg orig="Athol">Atholl</reg> had of his: But <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> told him, That although he took up the Rents of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, the men were the Marquess of <reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg>.</p>
<p>After many high words, <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg> offered to draw his sword, and <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg> went away in a great rage, swearing, That rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> he would see his own people abused by <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, he would lose his life, and thereupon drew to the other side of the water, with some of <reg orig="Mac Griggers">Macgriggors's</reg> men, and about 60 horse with him: This difference hath put the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> to a stand, who otherwise would have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>; so that some of them are fled to <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>, and other parts, to secure themselves. Parties of Horse and Posts are directed every way, for the apprehending of <reg orig="Lorn">Lorne</reg>. The Enemy take up all the horse that they can find in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> January 20.</head>
<p>This day further from Scotland came as followeth. These parts afford no news, the enemy is preparing to make ready for the season of the year, and do the utmost this Winter to promote their design, and do send into our quarters their Warrants for their levies, but dare not come themselves to see performance, <reg orig="onley">only</reg> in the night do come and steal horses, and at sometimes do carry away some men, you may by the <unclear><reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg></unclear> see their Warrants, and what the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of this place Col. Cooper is constrained to do, to <reg orig="counter-work">counterwork</reg> them, or else the people would be too willing to answer their expectations, no more but that I am Sir,</p>
<p>Glasgow, Jan. 12. 1653.</p>
<head level="3"><i>William Earl of Glencairn, Lord <unclear>Kallmarrs</unclear>, Commander in chief of His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of Scotland.</i></head>
<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to us by his Majesty, for levying of forces, Horse and foot, for suppressing the common enemy within this Kingdom; we do hereby require you &amp; every of you, within the shires of <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg> &amp; Renfrew, upon sight thereof, to send forth for His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, forth of every Thousand pounds rent within your said Shires respectively, one sufficient well mounted man, with Pistols, and other furniture, and weapons belonging thereto, and to deliver the <pb n="4" /> same at Rosdew, to Lieu. Col. George <reg orig="Maxwel">Maxwell</reg>, Lieu. Col. George Herriot, and Cap. James Cunningham, or any having their Orders for that effect, certifying all persons of whatsoever quality, within the said Shires respectively, that doth either refuse or delay to give obedience to this our Order and Commands, they shall be taken notice of, and proceeded against as disloyal subjects, and professed enemies to the present Expedition. Whereas by the contrary, we do hereby oblige <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to protect and defend against all enemies whatsoever, all such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> willingly put forth their several proportions of the aforesaid Horse <reg orig="levie">levy</reg>. And whatsoever horses, or any other goods shall be taken from any one of them so protected, in any disorderly manner, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be restored again, but the person or persons offenders shall according to the quality of the offence, at the sight of the party offended, be severely punished, to the terror of others; And ordains this to be published at every Headborough, or Parish Church within the said Shires respectively, that every Heritor, and others <reg orig="therin">therein</reg> contained pretend no ignorance of the premises. Given at Garth, Decemb. 23. 1653.</p>
<p><em>Sic <unclear>subscribitur</unclear></em>, <reg orig="GLENCARN">GLENCAIRN</reg>.</p>
<p><i>We expect your answer at Rosdew,</i> Jan. 6. 1654.</p>
<head level="3"><i>For the whole Noblemen, Gent. Heritors, and others, Inhabitants within the Shresdomes of <reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg> and <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg>.</i></head>
<p>This from Col. Cooper upon the aforesaid Paper to the Noblemen, Gentlemen, &amp;c. of Ayr and Renfrew as followeth.</p>
<p>Having seen a Paper, subscribed <reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg>, directed to the Noblemen, Gentlemen Heritors, and all others within the shires of <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg> and Renfrew, commanding them to set forth horses furnished for war, with sufficient riders thereon, and to bring in the same to Rosdew, and to deliver them to such persons as shall be there to receive them. And lest big words should <unclear>fright</unclear> some, and <reg orig="subtlll">subtle</reg> <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> delude others into obedience of the same Papers, to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of the persons so yielding, but to the apparent hazard of the peace and welfare of the said Shires, and the inevitable mischief that will <reg orig="insue">ensue</reg>; These are therefore to require all Noblemen, Gentlemen, Heritors and others in the said Shires of <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg> and Renfrew, to refuse obedience to all such Commands, and not in the least be aiding and assisting to the said Levies, directly or indirectly, nor to hold any correspondence with the said Glencairn, or his associates, now in Rebellion against the Commonwealth of England, as they would not be held and deemed <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <pb n="5" /> enemies, and proceeded against as such with the utmost of extremity. And lest any should pretend ignorance in the same, the <unclear>Sheriffs</unclear> of the respective Shires are required to take special notice, that copies hereof may be sent to every Church within the said Shires, to be published. Given under my hand at Glasgow, this fifth of January, 1653.</p>
<p>THO: COOPER.</p>
<p>We hear by a ship come from <reg orig="Hambrough">Hamburg</reg>, and also many ships this week come from Dunkirk, of ten of our merchant men come safely to <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, laden with all Eastern commodities, and five of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> convoy to them, who have also homewards bound made several prizes upon the coast of Norway, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be in England very shortly.</p>
<p>All persons are desired to take notice, that the Committee for Claims for Lands in Ireland, have appointed Thursday the ninth of February, 1653. for Adventurers to draw Lots at Grocers hall, London, for <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>, and that all persons who intend then to draw Lots, do before that day pay in their pence,</p>
<p>WILLIAM TIBBS.</p>
<head level="3">Saturday, Jan. 21.</head>
<p>General Blake took his leave of the Lord Protector, in order to his repairing down to his Command in the fleet.</p>
<p>The Letters out of Ireland, say, That the Tories begin to play their pranks again, and some hundreds have been discovered together in a body; yet if but a party of ten or twenty of our men do but appear, they all fly away, and hide themselves in the woods.</p>
<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> January, 23.</head>
<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his Honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> set forth an Ordinance declaring, That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be high Treason for any person (not being  an Officer, <pb n="6" /> <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Member of the Army) to plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the stirring up of any mutiny in the said Army, or if any person shall invite or assist any <reg orig="Forrainers">Foreigners</reg> invading England, Scotland, or Ireland, or if any person shall plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the betraying or yielding up any City, Town, Fort, Ship or Vessel, belonging to this Commonwealth, or if any person shall <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg> or imagine the death of the Lord Protector for the time being, or if any person or persons shall maliciously or advisedly either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector, and the people in Parliament assembled, are not the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority of this Commonwealth, or if any person or persons whatsoever, shall proclaim, declare publish, or any way promote <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, eldest son to the late King, or <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em> one other of his sons, or any other the issue or posterity of the said late King or any other person or persons, claiming by, from, or under him or them, or either or any of them, or any of the Dominions to them, or either or any of them belonging; or if any person or persons shall give, keep, or hold any intelligence whatsoever, by the Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em>, the late Queen their mother, or any of them; or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the money of this Commonwealth: or shall bring any false money into this land, either counterfeit or other, like to the money of this Commonwealth (knowing such money to be false) to the intent to <reg orig="merchandize">merchandise</reg>, or otherwise; or if any person or persons shall hereafter <reg orig="falsy">falsely</reg> forge or counterfeit any such kind of Coin, either of Gold or Silver, which is not the proper <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> of this Commonwealth, and yet is or shall be current within the same; or shall bring from the parts beyond the Seas into this Commonwealth, or into any the <pb n="6" /> Dominions of the same, any such false or counterfeit coin of money, to the intent to utter or make payment with the same, within this Commonwealth. Or if any person or persons shall impair, <reg orig="Falsifie">Falsify</reg>, Clip, Wash, Round, <unclear>File</unclear>, and Scale, or lighten any the proper monies of this Commonwealth, or of the monies or coins of any other places allowed, or suffered to be current within this Commonwealth.</p>
<head level="3">Tuesday, January 24.</head>
<p>There is published another Ordinance of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for repealing the penalty of that Act, which <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> men to take the Engagement. Many other things are also under consideration, tending to the ease of the people that desire to live quietly; and <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> if the Dutch have the <reg orig="wisedom">wisdom</reg> to close with this Commonwealth, they will not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> ease themselves (and consequently us) of Taxes, but they and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> may have Commerce; <unclear>yet</unclear> give Laws if need be unto all Europe, though as yet we cannot have the <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg> as at this time fully to assure you hereof; in regard the intelligence thence from doth not hold forth so fully as we, and many of them too, wish and desire, if it may be done with honour and safety.</p>
<p>At the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of the Dutch Deputies which were here, were nine or ten <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> and Agents of several Nations at the Hague, and how far they may assist, or hinder and obstruct the agreement with England, you may easily <reg orig="guesse">guess</reg>; however we hear the States agreed to send another Deputy into England with their Answer, of which you will hear more very shortly.</p>
<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> let it suffice that we understand, that it went so current at Amsterdam and other places that an agreement was made with England, that the Merchants on the Busse leapt for joy, or else to little purpose.</p>
<p>From Plymouth this Post they write, that there was brought in two days before, 3 Dutch Ships which were lately taken prize.</p>
<p>There is nothing more from Scotland, but that they daily increase in their numbers and expect great matters, out of Holland and other parts. In the <reg orig="mean while">meanwhile</reg>, the English are <reg orig="indeavouring">endeavouring</reg> to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them which are now in Arms, who rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to hide themselves in the Mountains <reg orig="then">than</reg> to fight.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>