<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfOcc1">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Perfect Occurrences, Issue 1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Perfect Occurrences</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Message sent from the Citizens of London, to His Highness the Lord Protector, and his coming into the city on Wednesday next; with the great Presents and <reg orig="royall">royal</reg> preparations, for his high and honourable entertainment; and his gracious Resolution, and Act of Grace touching all poor prisoners in Ludgate, Newgate, the Fleet, and <reg orig="else-where">elsewhere</reg>. The further proceeding of Mr. Vavasour Powel in Wales, and Epitaph upon the discontented Itinerants of the Times. The mad Proclamation of Prince Rupert touching the Welsh Mountains, and the last News from the King of Scots. With a new Proclamation from the States of Holland, and sad and <reg orig="woful">woeful</reg> <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from the North of Scotland,</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan. 39. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Feb. 6. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Imprinted at London, for <em>G. Horton</em>, 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p>Hey toss! what an Age do we live in? What our most endeared friends, turn the greatest and implacable enemies? Why! what's the matter Mr. Powel, that after so much favour and clemency vouchsafed from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, you should still persist in your incorrigible <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>; to seduce the people: But seeing 'tis so, I shall present you with an <em>Epitaph</em> upon your Welch Itinerants, and so proceed to other Intelligence.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>An Epitaph upon the Itinerants of these Times.</i></head>
<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Here <em>Propagation</em> lies that did aspire,</line>
<line>like <em>Pharton</em> to set the <em>world</em> on fire,</line>
<line><reg orig="Cry'd">Cried</reg> down <em>Order</em>, and <reg orig="Ministeriall">Ministerial</reg> Call,</line>
<line>And thought to give this Government a fall:</line>
<line>She would have <reg orig="caus'd">caused</reg> the Gentry flock in Swarms,</line>
<line>To beg relief like Cripples without <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>;</line>
<line>And would have made the learned Lawyers plead,</line>
<line>From door to door (poor souls) for Crusts of Bread.</line>
<line>Lament <em>Itinerants</em>! this <em>Trade</em> is gone,</line>
<line>Take up your <em>Tools</em> and <em>Occupation</em>:</line>
<line>Silence in Churches; you have long forgot</line>
<line>Your first Callings, inheritance and lot.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3">Paris <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 29.</head>

<p>The King of Scots has had some consultation with Pr. Rupert, touching the transactions in England: But his Highness hath a design for Scotland, as the traditions of Fame reports, and implores a Commission to carry over all the Welch Mountains, to make Batteries against <reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg>, and the more to facilitate the business, he <reg orig="vowes">vows</reg> to give over his <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> of <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg> in the time of <reg orig="battel">battle</reg>, and that <reg orig="hee'l">he'll</reg> play the man when he's at it, and the Thief when he's at leisure: for which Expedition, his Proclamation, in the Antipodes, runs thus:</p>

<p>All brave and generous spirits, that are desirous to purchase wealth and honour, by adventuring their necks for the <reg orig="infringment">infringement</reg> of their lawful Rights and Liberties, and thereby to make themselves and their posterity slaves:<pb n="2" /> Let them repair to the magnanimous Prince Rupert, late General of the Swallow, and Duke of Plunder-<reg orig="pickroons">picaroons</reg>, where they shall receive such entertainment as followeth, viz Every man to accommodate himself with a horse, which he is to steal where he can find him either in pasture or stable, with bridle and saddle, and all other furniture fit for his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> service, and his own riding; which horse and furniture is to be paid for at his <reg orig="highness">highness's</reg> price, as Welch John paid his Hostess when the Rider <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be knighted by his General for his good service. Secondly that every <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> upon his march, or otherwise, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have free quarters in all places where they come, the best lodging and diet the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> can afford, without a penny pay; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> his Highness doth pass his Princely Word, to see all paid upon the first restoring of every man to his own, or when the <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> Agents upon Earth blind. Thirdly, that every <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> that wants wearing Clothes, Woollen or <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, may lawfully at all times, and in all places, take what they can find, <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> or Clothes, Jewels or Plate, as well from those that cannot spare it, as them that can, <reg orig="Catholicks">Catholics</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> excepted: Nevertheless, his Highness out<pb n="3" /> of his small Zeal to justice, doth oblige himself by his inviolable promise, which he as much values as all the Sack and strong Beer he left behind him in the Royal Fort at Bristol, or all the Land he hath in Asia and America, to see restitution made, when the Protestant Religion he fights for shall again flourish in England, as it did in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Queen <reg orig="Elizabeths">Elizabeth's</reg> sister. And so peace be with <!-- next two words written in large font separate from the rest of the paragraph --> The Queen.</p>

<p>But from our Proclamations in France, we shall proceed to our Occurrences in Sweden: from whence <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> find that the Negotiations of the English, make a very handsome appearance; and that the Queen seems very inclinable to answer our present Overtures: For on the 22 of Decemb. last, the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> had notice from the L. <em>Lagerfield</em>, that the Queen would give him audience on the 23 in the afternoon. And at the appointed day, about an hour after dinner, came two Senators to my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> lodging, with six of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Coaches, to conduct him to his audience: His Excellency met them at the door, and according to the course, gave them precedence to his bed-chamber, where they told his Excellency that they were commanded by the Queen to conduct his Excellency to his Audience, and they did believe the Queen was ready<pb n="4" /> to receive his Excellency. By this time it was dark, but the <reg orig="queens">queen's</reg> <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg> had Torches lighted. All his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> company went with him, whose clothes were rich and comely, and their persons answerable: His Excellency himself was in a plain black Cloth Suit, lined with the same. The Gentlemen of the first degree were all very rich in their clothes of English cloth, handsomely trimmed: Those of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Bed Chamber were likewise richly clothed. The Gent Attendants also <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> and well habited, and his Pages and <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg> came after in their Liveries. In this equipage his Excellency went to the Court; at the first Gate we passed through a lane of <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> of the <reg orig="queens">queen's</reg> guard. After we were alighted out of our Coaches, the Ryx marshal of Sweden, with the <reg orig="Marshals">Marshal's</reg> staff in his hand, met us at the foot of the <reg orig="staires">stairs</reg>; they call him Count <em>Oxenstern</em>, son to the Ryx-admiral, &amp; Kinsman to the Ryx-chancellor of Sweden: The Gentlemen Attendants were first, then those of his Excel chamber: Next, the Gent of the first degree in their order, his Excel. two sons next; after them the Master of the Ceremonies; next him the two Senators, then the Ryx-marshal and his Excellency; after them his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Pages and <reg orig="Lacqueys">Lackeys</reg> on each side of his Excellency with Torches. We went up many <reg orig="staires">stairs</reg> to a large Hall, many people in the way. From thence they led up to the great chamber, where Prince Adolph the grand Master met his Excel. which he never did to any Ambassador before. He gave his Excel. the right hand, and some complements passed between them; his Excel thanking him for his Letters, and for his accommodations in his journey, especially in the places of his Government. He told his Excel. the queen had commanded her Officers to take<pb n="5" /> care for his accommodation. In the next chamber beyond this was a guard of the <reg orig="queens">queen's</reg> <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, with coats richly <reg orig="embroydered">embroidered</reg> with gold. In the next room was the queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, three or four Ladies, and abundance of Lords and Gentlemen of her Court. All his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Gentlemen were admitted into that room, and made a Lane for his Excellency to pass: As soon as his Excellency came into the room, and put of his hat, the queen came two or three steps before her chair. But it was not <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to know her to be the queen, her habit being of plain grey stuff, and made after this manner, a coat down to the ground, and over that a close jacket that cam also to her knees, <reg orig="buttond">buttoned</reg> down with great buttons, with a black Scarf about her neck <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> with a black <reg orig="Ribbond">Ribbon</reg>. After his Excellency had passed his Ceremony, he put on his hat, and called to his Secretary for his credential Letters, which he presented to her Majesty and afterwards spake to her, and M. <em>de la March</em> interpreted into French every sentence his Excellency spake, which his Excellency was advised to do as the constant practice of that Court. Her Maj. was very attentive, and said, she never received so much satisfaction in any Ambassador as in this from England. After his Excellency had ended his speech, she answered him in the Swedish Language, which my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em> interpreted in <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, to this effect,</p>

<p>That her Majesty desired to renew the former alliance, and conclude a firmer Union between England and Sweden.</p>

<head level="3">Scotland <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 28.</head>

<p>The Highlanders are as potent as insolent, and often make incursions upon the Lowlanders; but not without some loss, though to the prejudice of the English<pb n="6" />; for, to speak truth, they have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> taken many Officers and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, but have also besieged one of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>; and Glencarn their General has sheathed his sword in the bowels of an honourable person. But being done in the field in open hostility, and against a grand enemy, the merit of his manhood prevailed against the horror of his parricide, and the crime of his fact was hidden within his <reg orig="valours">valour's</reg> glory.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Beverlin</em> is returned from Holland, and has made his address to his Highness the Lord Protector, signifying, That the States of that Province, and West friezland had a meeting, to consult upon the negotiations and transactions of the late Treaty, and at length came to this result, That they signed the Articles which were sent from England, and his high and mighty Masters desired there might be a cessation of <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> on both sides <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the rest of the Provinces have brought in their ratification. But stay, <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> well known they can swallow Leagues and Treaties as an Ox doth water. But to bring this great Work to a period and conclusion, the States General have sent forth their Proclamations, for calling together the Deputies if the several Provinces, in order to the <reg orig="ful">full</reg> concluding of a peace with England.</p>

<p>The English fleet remain still about <em>Stoke</em> Bay in their old station; and divers of our Canary ships are come into Falmouth after long expectation; The Wetang and the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> hath brought in 2 prizes to Newcastle, some Ordnance, and 100 prisoners: But the Brest men of war do much annoy us, and have taken some ships and Mariners. The Fairfax and the Swiftsure, with many others are going to <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> the Coast of <reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg>; <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> time, for many are come off by weeping cross.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>The Generals at Sea have sent up their Addresses to his Highness the Lord Protector, to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with him; that's no <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>: But the revolting of some of Maj. Gen. <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> Regiment from the present Government, <i>O that is <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> indeed</i>. The sending of a Message to the Lord Protector by the Citizens of <em>London</em>, <i>that's no news</i>; but the coming of his Highness into the City on Wednesday next, with the glorious Diadem, and bright Stars of the Nation, <i>O that's rare news indeed</i>. The adorning of the streets with fine Hangings, as in the Reign of former <em>Kings</em>, <i>that's no News</i>: But to see the bright Star of Sion cast its lustre upon the English Orb, <i>O that's brave news indeed</i>. To see men perish alive in Gaols, <i>that's no news</i>: But to see the poor Captives all set free, <i>O that's pure <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> indeed</i>.</p>

<p>Which <reg orig="restauration">restoration</reg> is now at hand: for our Occurrences from Westminster purports, that his Highness is graciously pleased (out of his abundant clemency toward the lamentable and <reg orig="wofull">woeful</reg> <reg orig="Cryes">Cries</reg> of the deplorable condition of poor languishing prisoners) to pass his Act of Grace, for the restoring of all men to liberty that are not able to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> their Creditors. <i>A most singular and pious Act of Favour and Christianity: For which; let the Name of renowned <!-- next word written in large font separate from rest of the paragraph --> <em>OLIVER</em>, be <reg orig="eterniz'd">eternized</reg> throughout all Ages for the true Assertor of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg> Liberty</em></i>; And indeed, justly may He be termed the Olive leaf, that has restored the Churches of Sion to peace and <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p>It is thought meet that these Occurrences be forthwith printed and published and <reg orig="dispiersed">dispersed</reg> in all Cities, Towns, and Corporations, throughout England, Scotland, Ireland, and Wales.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>