<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfII3">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect and Impartial Intelligence, Issue 3</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">Perfect and Impartial</head>
<head level="1">INTELLIGENCE,</head>
<head level="3">The Affairs in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, And other Parts beyond the Seas.</head>
<head level="3">Together with the Continuation of the History of CAIUS JULIUS <reg orig="CESAR">C&AElig;SAR</reg>.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> May 26</em>, to <em><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> June the 2</em>, 1654.</p>
<hr />

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector hath given out Warrant for issuing of Writs of Summons by the Great Seal of <em>England</em> for a Parliament to be summoned to meet at <em>Westminster</em> upon the third day of <em>September</em> next, and at the day and place of elections, the Sheriff of each County, and the Mayors, Sheriffs, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other head Officers within their Cities, Towns, <reg orig="Burroughs">Boroughs</reg>, and places respectively are to take view of the said Elections, and make <reg orig="returne">return</reg> into the <em>Chancery</em> within twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Elections. No Persons are to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> or to be chosen, that aided, assisted or abetted in the War against the Parliament since <reg orig="Ianu">Janu</reg>. 1641. <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they have been since in the service of the Parliament and found <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg>, nor such have been in the Rebellion of <em>Ireland</em>. And those who are to be elected to serve in Parliament are to be such) as are known persons of integrity, fearing God, and of good conversation.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> hath finished the union with the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, and is coming home by the way of <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The Plot is <reg orig="every day">everyday</reg> by examination discovered more<pb n="1" />clear, two hundred Horse it is confessed did <reg orig="way-lay">waylay</reg> his <reg orig="Hignesse">Highness</reg>, one <em>Wharton</em> in Black-<reg orig="Friers">Friars</reg> should have proclaimed <em>Charles Stuart</em>, who is apprehended, and divers are daily apprehended, one of the <em><reg orig="Ashburnhams">Ashburnham's</reg></em>, and some others are sent to the Tower; I could tell you of apprehending the Lords <em>Montegle, Savage, Cranborn</em>, since released; as also the names of divers this day examined, and who are likely to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, as also one apprehended last night in <em>Holburn</em> in <reg orig="Womans">Woman's</reg> <reg orig="apparell">apparel</reg>, but in short a bloody Plot it was designed. <em><reg orig="Teudore">Tudor</reg></em> this day brought from the Tower to be examined escaped through the House of Office in <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em> Garden, much is <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg> by others, and you will shortly have the particulars. Whosoever can discover any that had a hand in the lately <reg orig="Lybels">Libels</reg> posted about <em>London</em>, will <reg orig="doe">do</reg> an acceptable service, and be well rewarded.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Goldsmiths Hall May 30. 1654.</i></head>

<p>Whereas, in the 28 Article of Agreement betwixt his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <i>the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland</i>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging, and the <i>Lords the States General of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></i>. It is there Ordered and Agreed, that Restitution shall be of all and singular the English Ships and Goods seized and detained within the Dominions of the King of <em>Denmark</em> since the 18 of <em>May</em>, 1652. &amp;c. And whereas in the same Article <em>Edward <reg orig="Winslo">Winslow</reg>, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Russel, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Becx</em>, and <em>William Van der Cruissen</em> are appointed to Arbitrate, <reg orig="Iudge">Judge</reg>, and Determine Indifferency, as well on the part of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as the said States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, the Losses and Damages sustained by the English; let all men take notice that are concerned, that the said Arbitrators by their respective Commissions under the broad <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> of each <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> respectively, met this day at<pb n="2" />Goldsmiths Hall, where the said Commissions were read and the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty, being there present (according to the true intent and meaning of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and the Lords States General of the United Provinces, by the express words of their Commissioners) did administer an Oath unto the Commissioners aforesaid; which done, the Commissioners did enter upon the work, and do hereby give notice thereof to all that are concerned therein, that so they make their several and respective applications to them, sitting at Goldsmiths Hall.</p>

<p><i>Robert Davie Register to the said Commissioners.</i></p>

<p>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 22 May. The Deputies of the Low Saxony are gone home from hence. The Envoys from this City, and from Lubeck to interpose the agreement between the Swedes and the City of Bremen are not yet come back. Those of Bremen do sally out upon the Swedes, having the 19 instant killed and taken some, and brought in 9 horses. The same have brought in both by land and water much munitions.</p>

<p>Naples 26 April. At Ocranie there hath been lately two great Earthquakes.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lords the States General of the United Provinces.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Lords our extraordinary <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>, with the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, have by their Letters written from Westminster the fifteenth instant, among other things given us advice, that his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> had at their desire, found good to put off the time prefixed<pb n="3" />in the thirtieth Article of the Treaty of Peace, Union, and everlasting Confederacy, for the bringing in on both sides, the Claims and pretences concerning the things done in the Indies and other places, mentioned more at large in our Proclamation of the sixteenth of this present, from the twenty eight of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> to the 11 of June next, new stile. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have thought necessary by these to warn all the inhabitants of these Lands, who are any wise concerned therein, to be <reg orig="mindfull">mindful</reg> to send to London within the 11 day of June aforesaid, and deliver to the Commissioners appointed on both sides, all their Claims and Pretences, to be reckoned from the year 1611. to the 28 of May, of the year 1552, new stile <em>inclusive</em>, for the wrongs suffered from the English.</p>

<p><i>Done in the Assembly of the aforesaid Lords States General in the Hague the twentieth of May, 1654.</i></p>

<p>From Dunkirk June 2 new stile. I have no good news to impart unto you at present, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the sad accident which happened at Gravelines upon Thursday last being the 28 of May; about ten of the clock in the forenoon; where the fire having taken to a great quantity in a magazine of Powder blew, up a great part of the Castle, the <reg orig="Covent">Convent</reg> of English Nuns, with many houses <reg orig="adjoynining">adjoining</reg> to it which were all blown up and laid in a heap, and had near taken the other Magazine, where was 400 Barrels of Powder, <reg orig="Granadoes">Grenades</reg>, and other <reg orig="Fire-works">Fireworks</reg> in great quantity.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for the Commissioners sitting at Salters Hall is very near finished, the names are not yet inserted; it is believed some honest and able Lawyers will be added.</p><pb n="4" />

<hr />
<head level="3">CHAP. III</head>

<p>After <em>C&aelig;sar</em> <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg> to foment sedition amongst the <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg> Colonies, the which he could not effect he cometh to <em>Rome</em>, upon his first <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> he set on foot great designs within the City, he conspired with <em>M. Crassus</em>, a man that had been Consul with <em>P. Sulla</em>, and with <em>L. Antronius</em>, (who after they were Consuls elect, stood condemned for suing indirectly and corruptly for that place) to set upon the body of the Senate in the beginning of their year, and that after they had massacred whom they pleased of them, <em>M. Crassus</em> usurp the Dictatorship, and <em>C&aelig;sar</em> be chosen master of the horse, and so when they had <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> the estate at their pleasure, <em>Sulla</em> and <em>Antronius</em> should be restored again to their <reg orig="Consul ship">Consulship</reg>; of this conspiracy <em>Tanusius Geminus</em> maketh mention in his History, <em>M. Bibulus</em> in his Edicts, and <em>C. Curio</em> in his Orations, <em>Cicero</em> seemeth to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> as much in a certain Epistle to <em>Axius</em>, wherein he reporteth that <em>C&aelig;sar</em> established in his Consulship, that Royal government which he plotted, and thought upon when he was Bedile.</p>

<p><i><em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> in this had laid a notable Plot to destroy the Senate, he finding them to be the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> obstruction to his intended <reg orig="greatnesse">greatness</reg>, must destroy them and turn them out of the Senate house; <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg> and Senates are not <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> at the devotion of a Tyrant or Usurper, or by any other ways: therefore <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> must destroy the Senate or some part, a small <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> is easier wrought to the will of a Tyrant <reg orig="then">than</reg> a great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; those whose lives that he intended to spare and continue in the Senate should be but few, and they should be persons qualified with <reg orig="timorousnesse">timorousness</reg>, or else with base corrupt minds that would become <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> and conform themselves wholly to the Will of the Usurper; if he would <reg orig="conive">connive</reg> at their fowling the people: it is likely that if <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> had put in execution this Conspiracy he would have put several necessities upon the remaining part of the Senate to act and do that might justly give cause of discontent in the people, or have <reg orig="imploied">employed</reg> several persons to oppose all<pb n="5" />Acts of justice in the Senate, and have made that famous Chariot to move slowly; by this means have made the people out of love with the Senate, that thereby he might with more ease attempt the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority, by turning the remainder of the Senate out of <reg orig="dores">doors</reg>, and have erected a new Senate or <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> that should be small in number and weak in parts, that thereby he might rule them the better, and be the more comfortable to his Will: <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> in this plot contrives to be Master of the Horse, so that although he drew <em>M. Crassus</em> into the Plot in expectation of being Dictator; yet he knew right well that he as Master of the horse should have command of the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, by whom he might easily remove <em>M. Crassus</em> out of the Dictatorship, and have placed himself in his room.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> did not give the signal upon the appointed time, neither was <em>M. Crassus</em> at the Senate house at that time, <em>Curio</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that this <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Tragedy should have been acted upon <em><reg orig="C&aelig;sars">C&aelig;sar's</reg></em> letting his Gown fall from his shoulders, <em>M. Artorius Maso</em> doth write, that at the same time <em>Cu. Piso</em> should in <em>Spain</em> have raised commotion.</p> 

<p><i>All Authors are silent as to the giving a reason why or upon what reason of State that <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> omitted the putting in execution this <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> intention of his, it is to be supposed and that not without probable ground he refused it, upon the consideration that such an act would render him <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> to the <reg orig="eie">eye</reg> of the people; who rather affect mercy and clemency <reg orig="then">than</reg> cruelty or rigour, and if that he should have done <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to have <reg orig="incenst">incensed</reg> the people, he had been deprived of reaping the benefit of that act of his, if he had committed that treason or cruelty, as to turn the Senate out by killing them, he would have declared that they were unjust, that they were slow in motion, and that the Gods to declare they had no more work for them to do, did not give them hearts to do good to the Commonwealth when indeed <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> was the cause of all.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> incites and stirs up the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> of the Commonwealth to rebel to commit treason, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in disobeying the commands of the Senate; but in tempering them with an inclination to be ready to massacre the Senate, all things are <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> that is done for a Tyrant which are made by him <reg orig="unlawfull">unlawful</reg> to be done, acted, or thought of to be done against him after he hath seated himself in the Throne of his Tyranny, those that do act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against a Tyrant and Usurper, with a weak hand <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> know it to be so he that undertaketh with a strong hand that is able to put in execution his Treason, shall never know what Treason is; <reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg><pb n="6" />who did never commit Treason, acted with that power that he was able to take the head of him off that should call him Traitor.</p>

<p><i>After <em>C&aelig;sar</em> was <em>Aedile</em>, whose office it is to repair the place of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> meetings, feasts, <reg orig="shews">shows</reg>, and the charge of the <reg orig="aquaducts">aqueducts</reg>, ditches, and common shores of the City, and to order the sitting of every Citizen in the <reg orig="Theator">Theatre</reg> according to his dignity as also to judge in cases where on had sold a sickly rotten or unfound beast for the market, he beautified <em>Comitium</em>, which was where part of the people did sit, to hear Orations and to give their voices in matters of great concernment, he beautified the <em>Forum</em> or Market place</i>, the Justice Hall, and the Capitol with fair Galleries, for standing to view <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="shews">shows</reg>, the chasing and baiting of wild beasts, the Stage plays, and solemn fights, he exhibited them jointly with his companion in Office, and also severally by himself, whereby it came to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> that the charges of the solemnities were born in commune between them yet <em>C&aelig;sar</em> alone went away with all the honour, and thanks; neither did <em>Marcus Bibulus</em> his Colleague dissimulate the matter; when he said that the same befell unto him, that befell unto <em>Pollux</em>: <i>A Temple being erected in <em>Rome</em> to <em>Castor</em> and <em>Pollux</em>, the Temple in those times was for breviation of Speech called the Temple of <em>Castor</em> so the honour of <em>Pollux</em> was much <reg orig="lessned">lessened</reg>. <em>Bibulus</em> supposed the same of himself, <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> spared for not cost nor pains to <reg orig="ingratiat">ingratiate</reg> himself with the people, it is popularity that must be <reg orig="helpfull">helpful</reg> to him to lessen the greatness of the Nobility, and to increase his own greatness, he beautifieth places of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> meeting and <reg orig="shews">shows</reg>, he not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> inviteth them to meet and assemble, but presents to them many objects of stately delight to lighten their minds against the Nobility he commeth to them to as <reg orig="councel">council</reg> <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he is rising, after he is risen he expelleth them out of those places, and seeketh not <reg orig="councel">counsel</reg> in the <em>Forum</em> or Market place but of his <reg orig="Cabonit">Cabinet</reg> where nothing is contrived, but how to fasten obedience and servitude upon the necks of the people, where to <reg orig="incamp">encamp</reg> or quarter his forces or erect or strengthen Citadels by fortification that may best keep the people in <reg orig="aw">awe</reg>; he tickleth the people with pleasing plausible works and words: as one would a beast that he intendeth thereby to get him <unclear><!-- approximately 3 characters --></unclear> he have some advantage to cut his throat, the half charges of these expensive reparations, was born by his <reg orig="Collegue">Colleague</reg>; it is frequent that the valour of the <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> is attributed to the General, when he little deserveth it, it is the <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> of many wise Counsellors sometimes to those Princes that deserveth not the name of men but Beasts.</i></p><pb n="7" />

<p>When <em>C&aelig;sar</em> had gained the hearts of the people by these good <reg orig="publick">public</reg> works; he sued to have the Province of <em>&AElig;gypt</em> by an act of the Commons conferred upon him; taking an occasion to make suit for this extraordinary government, for that the <em>Alexandrians</em> had driven their King out of his Realm, whom the Senate had <reg orig="stiled">styled</reg> with the title of a friend; howbeit he could not obtain his suit by reason of the opposition of the Nobles, <i>whose authority he would by all means possibly, infringe, lessen and repair</i>, the victorious monuments of <em>C. Marius</em>, for subduing King <em>Jugurtha</em> the <em>Cimbrians</em> and the <em>Tentons</em>, which before time had been demolished, and cast down by <em>Sylla</em>, he erected and set up again.</p>

<p><i><em>C&aelig;sar</em> might have obtained his suit, had he made use of the authority of the Nobles as well as the Commons, but if he had obtained this suit of the Commons, he would next have sued to the Commons to give their voices an Act to make and declare the power of the Nobility <reg orig="uselesse">useless</reg>, the which thing he <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Upon his sitting upon a Commission for the examination of <reg orig="Murtherers">Murderers</reg>, he reckoned those in the number of them, who in the time of the proscription, had received money out of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Treasury, for bringing in the heads of Roman Citizens; notwithstanding they were excepted by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the law <em>Cornelia</em>.</p>

<p><i>This proscription was in <em>Sylla's</em> time, <em>C&aelig;sar</em> himself was of the number of the proscribed persons, their prosecutors he prosecuteth, contrary to Law; the Tyrant and Usurper valueth not Law, he breaketh them as Reeds, or at least will <reg orig="indempnifie">indemnify</reg> his servants that do break them so that Laws are but Cobwebs to catch the smaller flies.</i></p>

<p>After this he suborned <em>T. Labienus</em>, to indite <em>C. Rabirius</em> of high treason by whose help some years before, the Senate had repressed and restrained the <reg orig="sedicious">seditious</reg> Tribune ship of <em>L. Sauturnius</em>, and he being chosen Judge delegate to pass sentence of the prisoner, so willing he was to condemn him, that when <em>Rabirius</em> appealed unto the people nothing did him so much good as the <reg orig="rigor">rigour</reg> of the rest of the Judges.</p>

<p><i>It is likely they would not allow him the benefit of the appeal; the people might have seen in this what a Tyrant their Patron <em>C&aelig;sar</em> would be in that he would take upon him to judge and be of those that passed sentence against his declared and professed enemy, and also the debarring the prisoner of the benefit of appealing to them, who were to be appealed unto last, as the <reg orig="Supreamest">Supremest</reg> authority of all.</i></p>

<p>The end of the 3. Chapter.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>