<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn232">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 232</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, May. 15. to <em>Monday</em>, May. 22. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> May. 15.</head>

<p>This day from <em>Dalkieth</em>, May 9. thus. Twelve <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of our men of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> are going from <em>Leith</em>. <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> is going towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, <em>Middleton</em> hath sent out <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Commanders for Levies, <em>Drummond</em> to <em><reg orig="Loughtay">Lough Tay</reg></em>, and <em>Glencairn</em> to secure him with 100 horse, Col. <em>Murray</em> to <em>Athol</em>: <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> to <em>Branar</em>, and others to other places; But we shall shortly be among them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath had hard Duties, but the Enemy will not come near him, but gives him the slip among the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in chief of all the Forces in Scotland</i></head>

<p>The Commonwealth of <em>England</em> having used all means of <reg orig="tendernesse">tenderness</reg> and affection towards the People of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the Liberties and Privileges thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much Blood and Treasure) and <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more than their equal proportion with <em>England</em>) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace; Yet divers lewd persons broke in their fortunes, and dissolute in their Lives, are run into Rebellion, and being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Brethren, Tutors, Masters, and People among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder in the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof, I by virtue of the authority to me given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his Council, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are expected in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 days after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next <em>English</em> Garrison, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons freely pardoned, for any Offence, Spoil, or Plunder committed by him or them in this present rebellion (the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.) And I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> declare, that if any Parents, Brethren, or Tutors, who have assisted and connived at any their Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publication hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, to render themselves, and give security as aforesaid, That then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are<pb n="2" /> hereby freely pardoned; But otherwise, then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, shall be imprisoned during the time the said persons <reg orig="doe">do</reg> remain in rebellion. And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion, without the knowledge or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> therefore hereby declare, that the said parish or presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth, to render him or themselves within twenty days after publication hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, that then the said parish or presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned; But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said parish and presbytery, 2 shillings, 6 pence a day for each Horseman, and 10 pence a day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion. And I doe likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person, and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into Rebellion, or attempt so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, and safely to deliver him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English Garrison; and in case of resistance to take such weapons as they can get, and to fight the said person or persons; and if they shall kill any of the said persons so resisting, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive a reward of their good service, all such Moneys, Goods, Horses, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, as the said Rebellious Persons are then possessed of, besides full satisfaction of their pains and travel therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Donald <em><reg orig="Mac-Donald">McDonald</reg></em> Laird of <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and Major <reg orig="Generall">General</reg><pb n="3" /> Dayel. I do hereby therefore Declare, That what such person or persons soever of this Nation, (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said <reg orig="principall">principal</reg> Contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any <em>English</em> Garrison, the said person or persons, so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only be pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> he or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but shall also receive as a Reward of his good service, the sum of Two hundred pounds sterling, for every person so killed or brought prisoner, as aforesaid. And lastly, for the encouragement of all peaceable and well affected people, both <em>English</em> and <em>Scots</em>, I do also hereby Declare, That what <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, or out of the Estates of such as have done the <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, or out of the Estates of the Friends and Harbourers of such <reg orig="Wrong-doers">Wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the Parish, Presbytery, or Shire where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, or give the <em>English</em> Forces such timely notice thereof, that the said <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> may be apprehended by them. And I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby require all Provosts, Bailiffs, and Chief Officers of Head Burghs, in their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Burghs, to cause these presents to be duly Published and Posted up, according to the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me, in writing, under his or their hands.</p>

<p><i>Given under my Hand at <em>Dalkieth</em>, this 4. day of May, 1654. <em>George <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em></i></p>

<p>Whereas the Justices of the Peace in the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties of <em><reg orig="Northwales">North Wales</reg></em> having taken into their due Consideration the great and <reg orig="generall">general</reg> discommodity <reg orig="accrewing">accruing</reg> unto the Inhabitants of the said Counties, by reason of the great numbers of Licenses heretofore usually granted unto <reg orig="severall">several</reg> the native Inhabitants to trade at Drovers and <reg orig="Haglers">Hagglers</reg>, whereby<pb n="4" /> the said Drovers and <reg orig="Haglers">Hagglers</reg> have used sundry undue and crafty means and practises to divert and <reg orig="deterre">deter</reg> all other persons, having Commerce in that kind, from <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> and resorting to the <reg orig="Faires">Fairs</reg>, and Markets of those parts; And whereas the said Justices, for Reformation of these late, and prevention of such like future great and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> abuses, have not only discontinued and refused their Licenses unto such Drovers and <reg orig="Haglers">Hagglers</reg> as formerly were enabled thereby to Trade in this way, but have also caused a just and severe prosecution according to Law, against all others (which were not a few) that presumed to <reg orig="deale">deal</reg>, and have Commerce in those parts as Drovers and <reg orig="Straglers">Stragglers</reg>, without Licenses. It is therefore hereby declared, and made known unto all persons whom it may concern, whether Grafters, Drovers, or Butchers, That they repairing to the Fairs and Markets aforesaid, especially those in <em>Carnavonshire</em>, and <em>Anglesey</em>, may buy what <reg orig="Cattell">Cattle</reg> they please, without the forestalling, <reg orig="regrating">regretting</reg>, or Competition of the said native Drovers and <reg orig="Haglers">Hagglers</reg>, which undoubtedly is no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> to the advantage of the said <reg orig="Drovers~strangers">Drovers strangers</reg> than of the said Inhabitants, many of whom have suffered in their estates, as well by adventuring themselves unadvisedly to deal as Drovers and <reg orig="Haglers">Hagglers</reg>, as by being necessitated to trust and adventure their goods and cattle upon the credit of persons inexperienced, or <reg orig="weake">weak</reg> estates, or dishonest.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 16.</i></head> 

<p>This day the Lord Mayor, with <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Aldermen of the City of London, <reg orig="Dyned">Dined</reg> with his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 20th of May. The preparation of the Enemy in <em>Flanders</em>, doth <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> many that they intend to do some great matter very speedily, in the besieging of some of our <reg orig="Frontire">Frontier</reg> places, but as yet their intent is kept very close, the Garrison of <em>la Bassee</em> doth much disquiet the <em>Lorrainers</em> in their quarters, and thereupon they have removed their being at <em>Lalou</em>, and are now quartered near the River <em>Lis</em>. All things are now preparing<pb n="5" /> for the Kings anointing, which is not done upon the 24 instant as was thought, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said it will be performed upon the 31 instant being Trinity Sunday, the Nobles, both Spiritual, and Temporal, are all preparing to be there present, only the Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em>, who will not by any means be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> to come to the Court, which will somewhat darken that solemnity, what is the reason of his long <reg orig="willfull">wilful</reg> <reg orig="denyal">denial</reg> is not certainly known, but by most men is imputed to the haughty spirit of <reg orig="Madamoiselle">Mademoiselle</reg> his daughter, who driveth on the interests of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and likewise to be revenged of the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>: The Duke <em>de Beaufort</em> who doth now lead a retired life is still blowing the Coals, fomenting that heart-burning which is in the Royal Family: The <em>Catalans</em> having received certain advice from hence, that the Prince of <em><reg orig="Conty">Conti</reg></em> was ready to march towards them, and that with such forces as he should bring with him, <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with those forces that are already in <em>Roussillon</em>, there will be a very considerable Army, which will soon free <em>Rosa</em> from blocking up, and so enter again into <em>Catalonia</em>, where the Spaniards keep a very strict hand over the people of the Country, and having laid very great contributions upon them, they punish severely those that do not bring in their <reg orig="assessements">assessments</reg>, insomuch that a small Town is assessed at five thousand Pistols, as many loads of Corn, and 250 loads of Oats, in default thereof they are to deliver fifty men fit for service who shall be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> where his Majesty shall think fit, which causes the Country throughout to be full of mourning, and heavy lamentations; the news concerning the Prince of <em>Harcourt</em> being fully agreed with the Court doth prove true but in part, he being not yet resolved to leave the Town of <em>Brisack</em>, but <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he is resolved to keep it for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> proceedings of the Law vindicated to be just, &amp;c.</i></head>

<head level="3">Part. IV.</head>

<p><i>For Prevention of making out Writs of Execution against Goods, and outing men of their possessions, and delivering men out of Execution<pb n="6" /> unduly, by such who have not been of Ability or Estate to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the party damnified.</i></p>

<p>Forasmuch as of late years divers indigent persons, being or pretending themselves to be Clerks and Attorneys, have made and sued out in their own or other <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> names many Writs (for which there hath been no <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> ground) <reg orig="retornable">returnable</reg> in superior Courts, for the levying, taking, and seizing of divers <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> goods and <reg orig="chattells">chattels</reg> to very great value, and selling them, or delivering the same to the Plaintiffs or Demandants in such Writs; and for putting honest men out of their lawful possession of divers Lands and Tenements, upon which they have had great crops growing, and divers other goods and chattels upon the same of considerable worth; and for delivering several men out of Prison (who have been in prison for divers great sums of money justly due to the Plaintiff, at whose <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> they have been in prison) and have caused such Writs to be sealed with the Common Seal of such Courts and afterward delivered the same to the Sheriff to whom they have been directed, or sent the same to them by Sharks of small or no estates. And such Sheriffs (finding such Writs sealed with the <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> seals, which would warrant them in the execution of the same) have by virtue of such Writs <reg orig="seazed">seized</reg>, taken, and <reg orig="levyed">levied</reg> divers of such goods and <reg orig="chattells">chattels</reg>, and sold some of the same, and delivered the money thereof made to such Sharks, being Plaintiffs, or <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> authority from them in that behalf, and delivered other part of such goods and chattels to such Sharks, and have put such honest men out of possession, and such Sharks into possession of such Lands and Tenements, who have entered upon such crops, goods, and chattels, and carried away, and wasted and consumed the same, and such Sheriffs also, by virtue of others of such Writs have delivered divers men out of prison, who have been so imprisoned, who have absented and hid themselves, and could never be taken again, but in their <reg orig="sculking">skulking</reg> and rogueing about, have wasted their means and <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> beggars, and thereby such honest men lost just their debts and duties, And when such honest men have sought relief in such Courts for such extremity, they have found<pb n="7" /> no means for any, but against such Sharks who have been of no ability to make any considerable satisfaction or restitution for such mischief, whereby divers honest people have utterly undone, and others have suffered great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>

<p><i>For Remedy whereof, it is proposed to be desired that it may be Enacted</i>, That hereafter <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Clerks of experience and judgement, honesty, and ability in Estates, be and shall be collected, nominated, appointed, and authorized in every of the <reg orig="superiour">superior</reg> Courts, to make or sign Writs of Executions against Goods and Chattels, and for giving possession and <reg orig="seizin">seizing</reg> of <reg orig="Messuages">Messages</reg>, Lands, and Tenements, and <reg orig="cuting">cutting</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> from thence; and all manner of Writs of <em>Supersedeas</em>. And that if any Sheriff or Sheriffs, his or their Deputy or <reg orig="Deputyes">Deputies</reg>, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> or shall receive any such Writ, not so made or signed, and execute the same, and the same after be, or shall be made appear to have erroneously, unrightly, or improvidently issued out of any such Courts; then no matter which he, she, or they, do or shall plead, or give in evidence, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of such Writ, shall <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> him or them in executing of any such Writs, or <reg orig="supersedeing">superseding</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> thereby.</p>

<p>And that every of such Clerks shall (for Writs to be directed to the Sheriffs of Counties distant under 50 miles from <em>London</em>,) keep, <reg orig="signe">sign</reg>, and use a <reg orig="severall">several</reg>, private, particular <reg orig="marke">mark</reg>, or Character by him to be used about such Writs for every 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and of Counties further distant from them, every <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> in every year.</p>

<p>And that every such Clerk shall acquaint and <reg orig="notifie">notify</reg> to every of the such Sheriff, or his Common Attorney in such superior Court appointed, or to be appointed, (requiring the same) once or twice every Term, what every of such <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg>, Marks, or Characters for every of such several and respective times, be or shall be.</p>

<p>And that none of such <reg orig="Sheriffe">Sheriff</reg> be, or shall be (against his will) compelled to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> execution, or act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any such Writ, which shall not be so signed, or have such Mark or Character.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 17.</i></head>

<p>This day was published an Ordinance for continuing an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 31 of <em>May</em> instant.</i></p>

<p>The last Letters from <em>Poland</em> advise us, that the <reg orig="mis-understanding">misunderstanding</reg> that daily increaseth between the <reg orig="Moscovites">Muscovites</reg> and the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> is such, that the first, upon fear of an ill usage for the future, have already forsaken some of those Towns which they possessed in the Province of <em>Ukraine</em>, the General <em>Kimelniski</em> being weary of his new Masters, and doth what lieth in him to free himself from his Engagement to the Muscovite, who have not yet done any considerable action, but remain close in their quarters, being much <reg orig="disheartned">disheartened</reg>, since they hear that the <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em>Poland</em> hath had a very favourable Reception at <em>Constantinople</em>, the great Turk and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, being resolved to maintain the old Treaties and Alliances with <em>Poland</em>; in the mean time our <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Potoski</em>, having a <reg orig="designe">design</reg> to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> some place upon the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> before they knew of his approach, did thereupon march with his Forces to a Town called <em>Flince</em>, where was a Garrison of <reg orig="Cosackes">Cossacks</reg>, who upon the report of his approach with a part of the Army, did forsake the place, and fled to another Town at three leagues distance. This <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> seeing himself disappointed of his ends by bringing in of the Muscovite Army, is now again <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into a new Treaty with the Tartars of Czrjin to come once more to his assistance.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>. There is now daily expected the conclusion of our Diet, the Members thereof having agreed before they dissolve that Assembly, to meet again that time two years, to determine such affairs which could not be agreed upon this Diet, and are of too great consequence to be done in an <reg orig="inferiour">inferior</reg> Assembly.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>. This City, and that of <em>Lubeck</em>, have<pb n="9" /> sent Commissioners to <em>Bremen</em>, to make some overtures for an accommodation between them and the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, in the mean time the circle of lower <em><reg orig="Saxonie">Saxony</reg></em> endeavoureth that the Swedes may cease all acts of hostility in that County.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>, Although by the Treaty of <em>Munster</em> it was agreed that upon the payment of certain <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> of money to the <em>Swedes</em> they should then deliver up unto the Bishop of <em>Munster</em> the strong hold of <em>Wecht</em>, yet hitherto it could not be effected, the <em>Swedish</em> Commander in that place, having received those which were due to that Garrison, and the other <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> agreed upon being sent to <em>Oldenburght</em> to be paid upon the surrender of the place, <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> new difficulties arise which puts the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> in a <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> condition: Our <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> is gone to <em>Kerpen</em> a Castle which he hath lately bought of the Spaniard, for a great <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of moneys.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. From <em>Rome</em>, The Duke <em>de Terranova</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em>Spain</em> in that Court, hath had a long audience of the Pope to whom he made great and high complaints in the behalf of the Master, that he could no longer hide the discontent he hath, by that which is acted here in the person of his Ministers; among other things, that his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> complains that the Card. <em>Colonna</em> was not suffered to make nomination in the Consistory of such <reg orig="Bishops">Bishop's</reg> Sees as were void, &amp; therefore from henceforth he declared, that no benefices within his Dominions should be charged to pay any pension or annuity without his said <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em>. There are two ships lately come, the one from <em>Smyrna</em>, and the other from <em>Candia</em>, whereby we learn that the Turks <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on with great heat about their preparations at <em>Constantinople</em>, where the Ministers of State do so take to heart the carrying on of the <reg orig="warr">war</reg>, and <reg orig="besiedging">besieging</reg> the City of <em>Candia</em>, that to make their Army more terrible and dreadful, therefore each of them doth set out ships at their own Costs; we hear also that they are hard <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to repair the old Fort of <em><reg orig="Lazarretto">Lazaretto</reg></em>, which we had demolished some years since, that so they may the better prevent the relieving of that City by Sea; That<pb n="10" /> three of their Galleys have lately relieved the Town of <em>Canea</em>, General <em>Vssairn</em>, who is Commander in chief of the land forces, had with a party of his men sent a defiance to our Garrison in <em>Candia</em>, but although some of our Officers would have accepted it, yet it would not be granted, but found not to be safe for our men.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em>. Those men of war which our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> had sent into <em>Apuglia</em> to clear that coast from divers Sea-rovers which did much infest it, are now returned, besides those men lately <reg orig="mustred">mustered</reg> in our Arsenal, there hath been 18 Companies more mustered, who have all received some pay, and so with the 22 mentioned formerly it maketh 40, which are all sent into divers places along the <reg orig="Sea-coast">Seacoast</reg> to take their quarters, as also the several Troops of horse, so soon as they are mustered, and have received pay, after the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> of this Kingdom, so that it is esteemed that (besides the Spanish Foot <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> ) it will consist of 45000 foot, and 15000 horse likewise quartered in divers parts of the Sea coast, where they enjoy the same privileges and immunities as is accustomed, and maintained in the same number as they were in the time of the Emperor <em>Charles</em> the fifth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 18.</i></head>

<p>This day in the forenoon Monsieur <em>de Bourdeaux</em>, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em>France</em>, had audience of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at <em>Whitehall</em>, being brought to it in the form and manner accustomed.</p>

<p><em>Paris May 23</em>: The <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of <em>Conde</em> having presented a Petition to the Parliament, that she might have the sequestration taken <reg orig="off">of</reg> her Estate, she had no other answer but that it was taken in the hands of the <reg orig="Atturney">Attorney</reg> General, who carried the same to the Court. The 15 instant the King being at <em>Vincennes</em>, the Queen met him there, and afterwards they were feasted by the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, and so they returned hither. The 16 the Queen sent one of her Gentlemen to joy our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> upon the birth of his young Son. The 17, the King, with his Brother, the Cardinal, and others of the Nobility went to the <reg orig="Arcenal">Arsenal</reg>, where the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> <em>de la Mesteray</em> Master<pb n="11" /> of the Artillery of <em>France</em>, entertained them with a gallant dinner. The 19 the Queen went to visit the late Queen of <em>England</em>, who with her <reg orig="Sonne">Son</reg> the titular King came to visit their Majesties. The 20 the <em>Italian</em> Comedy of <em>Peleus</em> and <em>Thetis</em> was again acted before the Queen, where were present the little Queen, and her three Sons, the Cardinal, and many other persons of quality; The same day was sent from hence the rich hangings, and other house furniture to furnish the King and <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> lodgings at <em>Rheims</em>, where the Master of the Ceremonies is also gone to see that all things be ready and well ordered against his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> coming, Marshal <em>de Turenne</em> is now near his departing from this City, to go to <em>Montcornet</em>, which is the <reg orig="rendezvouz">rendezvous</reg> appointed for the meeting of his army, all the Officers having received special command to repair thither with all speed: We hear from <em>Nancy</em>, that the Marshal <em>la Ferte</em> is likewise ready to march into the field, having also sent order to all his Officers, that forthwith they repair to the several <reg orig="imployments">employments</reg>. Our Fleet at <em>Toulon</em> goeth on, but yet there are things wanting before they can <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Sea, what the design is, is uncertain, some believe they will come to relieve <em>Rosa</em> which wants that very much, and that the same being done, they will proceed upon some other enterprise: We hear from <em>Avignon</em>, that the difference between the Gentry and the Citizens about their election of Consuls, insomuch that the 24 of <em>June</em> next, the day of the election, is like to be very troublesome, if so be that the Pope who hath had a full information of the matter doth not by his authority quell the matters by sending some of the Cardinal of credit among them to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg> all. The Parliament hath met several times about the meeting of their exiled Members: and there it was resolved that from time to time, they should meet at the house of the first President, about the regulating of several offices and places in this <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> and suppressing such as were found burthensome to the <reg orig="publique">public</reg>. The Dukes of <em>Vendosme</em> and <em>Beaufort</em> his son have had a meeting at <em>Surenne</em>, where, after some <reg orig="coference">conference</reg> together they parted, not well satisfied one of the other, the Duke of <em>Vendosme</em> is come to the<pb n="12" /> Court to sign the contract of <reg orig="mariage">marriage</reg> between his eldest son the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em>, with the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> <reg orig="Neices">Nieces</reg>, and so decide some controversies which are now fully ended, here is lately deceased the <reg orig="Counsellor">Councillor</reg> <em>de Brouselles</em>, a man who hath made himself famous during our late troubles.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday May 19, 20,</i></head>

<p>This day was published two Ordinances, the one an Ordinance for Explanation of a former Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for better Amending and Keeping in Repair the Common <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg> within this Nation.</i> The other, An Ordinance for Relief of Debtors in <em>Scotland</em> in some Cases of Extremity. The former of these two being of most <reg orig="publick">public</reg> concernment, here take as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair the Common <reg orig="High-wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation</i>, amongst other things, It is Ordained, That if any <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>, Carts or Carriages wherein any burdens of dead commodities or wares <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> at any time from and after the first day of next <em>May</em>, then next, be drawn upon any such <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>, Roads, or Streets, with above five Horses or Mares, or six Oxen or one Horse or Mare, in any one Cart or Wagon, That then it shall be <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> to or for any Constable or Surveyor of <reg orig="Highwaies">Highways</reg>, or other Inhabitant in any Parish where such <reg orig="Loaden">Laden</reg> Wagon, Cart or Carriage shall pass and be drawn as aforesaid, to <reg orig="distrain">distain</reg> and seize all such supernumerary Horse, Mares or Oxen as he shall find in any such Wagon, Cart or Carriage over and above the number of five Horses or Mares, or six Oxen and one Horse or Mare respectively, and the same supernumerary Horses, Oxen and Mares respectively to <reg orig="detein">detain</reg> and keep, until such Owner or Driver have paid and answered into the hands of the Surveyors of <reg orig="Highwayes">Highways</reg> within the Parish where such <reg orig="Distresse">Distress</reg> and Seizure shall be made, or one of them, the <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of twenty shillings for every such supernumerary Horse, Mare, or Ox. Be it now Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. by and with the<pb n="13" /> consent of his Council, That the said Ordinance or any Clause therein contained, shall not extend to any Carts or Carriages at any time used in the conveying, draught, or carriage of any Ordnance, Timber, or Artillery, of any sort or kind whatsoever, for the use of the Army or Navy, But that such Carts, Draughts or Carriages may be drawn with any number of Horse or Oxen necessary for the Drawing thereof, without incurring any of the Penalties in the said Ordinance mentioned, or without any stop, molestation or disturbance of any Constable, Officer, or other person whatsoever, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Provided that such persons that attend the said Draughts, Carts or Carriages for the use of the said Army or Navy, have some Order or Pass under the hands of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, or the Lord President of his Council, or of the Commissioners of the Admiralty and Navy, or Generals of the Fleet, or other Field Officers of the Army, Commissioners of the Navy, or some <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of a Garrison, or under the hands of some of them, signifying that such Carriages and Draughts are for the use of the said Army or Navy, as is aforesaid.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> <em>April</em> 24, The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em> having happily concluded the Treaty between us and <em>England</em>, is on his way homewards, and all things are now in a <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> at <em>Vpsal</em> for the beginning of the Diet, which is to be upon the first of <em>May</em>, the Queen then <reg orig="its">it's</reg> fully resolved will surrender her Crown and Government unto her <reg orig="Cosen">Cousin</reg> the Prince <reg orig="Palatin">Paladin</reg> <em>Charles</em>, who is to be crowned King of <em>Sweden</em>, his Brother Prince <em>Adolphus John</em>, having laid down his Patent of Lord High Marshal of the Kingdom, and is gone to <em>Stockholm</em>, and from thence to <em>Braburgh</em>, and so the Isle of <em>Oeland</em> to confer with his Brother the future King, who will tarry their till the beginning of the Diet; We hear likewise that the Earl <em>Erard Oxenstern</em> is now appointed to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> as an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> extraordinary into <em>England</em> with a great retinue. Here is lately deceased the Lady <em><reg orig="Fletwood">Fleetwood</reg></em>, late wife of Sir <em>George Fleetwood</em><pb n="14" />, the funeral is appointed in great pomp, the little Queen, and many of the nobility of <em>Sweden</em> are to be present.</p>

<p>To give you an account of some late Letters from <em>Ireland</em> they mention thus: The Nation is <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in as peaceable a condition as ever it was before the late rebellion, an <reg orig="English man">Englishman</reg> having as secure travelling in most parts thereof as in his own Nation, which makes the place more pleasant, and will soon invite many people of the neighbouring Nations to settle their residence in it, when the Taxes are abated, which we hope will be speedily. We hear that the civil affairs of this Nation are to be transacted by additional or other Commissioners, upon new instructions, but the former we are induced to believe, and the rather, for that affairs of this Nation are so well known to these present Commissioners, whose fidelities and ability for the work of that Nation is unquestionable.</p>

<p><em>Dalkieth</em> May 9. The General marches <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> from <em>Dalkieth</em> towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, and from thence to some of our <reg orig="Frontire">Frontier</reg> <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, and so to the fields. The Proclamation you had before, he sends out as a forerunner, which will probably effect something considerable; <em>Middleton</em> continues still in <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> with some broken Regiments, which (as intelligence serves) rather decline than increase in number. <em>Glencairn</em> has made his way over the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, through some obsolete path, with a small party of horse, who purposes, if he can, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and make a Body. Col. <em>Morgan</em> is about <em>Tane</em>, watching opportunities to engage them, if possible.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> May 11</em>, we have as yet little of news, General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> hath yesterday removed his <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> from <em>Dalkeith</em> to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, from whence he intends, after securing of some few passes, to take field: We beat the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg> in all parties that engage, we have lately taken <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Brother and 5 or 6 Officers more, and routed that party, General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> hath hanged two of them already as spies, burnt an Inn in <em>Muscleborough</em> that harboured them, and is resolved to scour them as you may perceive by his Proclamation.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Guernzey">Guernsey</reg> Island</em>, May 12. 1654. The <em>Hector</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> attending without <em>St. Mallo's</em> divers days for conveying the English from<pb n="15" /> thence, who are still <reg orig="deteined">detained</reg> under the arrest, a shallop was sent out of the Town to tell the Capt. that the English should have all freedom, but this was found to be <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> a Decoy, to draw him in, and so not trusted.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Jersey</em> we understand, that some ships of ours lying near St. <em>Mallo's</em>, about 60 of the men (greedy to get fresh victuals) went ashore into the Country, and endeavoured to drive away some cattle, but the Country rising, rescued them, and fell upon the <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg>, and killed several of them, and pursued them to two of our ships which were left ashore by the going out of the Tide. This gave an <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg> to St. <em>Mallo's</em>, who thereupon brought down Ordnance to batter the ships, which they endeavoured to do, but did them little hurt; the Tide coming in, the ships got off, and the <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg> ceased. The Governor of S. <em>Mallo's</em> apprehending this to be a design against the Town, took an occasion to turn out all the English Merchants and seize upon all their houses, wares and goods, and hath made himself Master of what was theirs. The truth of this business is now under Examination, and the French Ambassador hath this week had audience thereupon, the results upon the whole you shall have in my next.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em>, May 18. General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> being now come to the Fleet, it is expected daily Orders will be given for their going out upon some honourable <reg orig="enterprize">enterprise</reg>; since the Fleet coming hither the small <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> dare not be so bold as formerly, by reason that some of our smaller <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are daily sent out as Scouts.</p>

<p>These Easterly winds have brought into this river of Thames this week a great number of <em>Hollanders</em> and <em><reg orig="Zelanders">Zealanders</reg></em> who have brought in good store of their own native Commodities. Great store of Colliers are also expected, as the wind favours, whereof some are already come in.</p>

<hr />

<p>&#x261e; Grammatic&aelig; Latin&aelig; Institutiones Carminibus concinnat&aelig;, Quibus subjiciuntur Commentarioli. Et per totam Syntaxin Regulatim, ipsa <em>Liliana</em> Constructio. Accesserunt <em>Figur&aelig;</em> qu&aelig; s&aelig;pius occurrunt Grammaticales. Isagoge Poetica de Carminum ratione. Tropi &amp; Schemata Rhetorices usiatiora. Opera &amp; Studio Jacobi Shirleii. <unclear>Lonaini</unclear> Excudebat F. I. sumptibus Richardi Lowndes, &amp; apud eum prestant, sub signo Albi Leonis in C&oelig;meterio S. Pauli, 1654.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>