<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn233">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 233</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, May. 22. to <em>Monday</em>, May. 29. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> May. 22.</head>

<p>This day from <em>Scotland</em> by <reg orig="Leters">Letters</reg> <em>May</em> 14, thus. We understand from Col. <em>Cooper</em> at <em>Glasgow</em>, that a party of his of 22 Dragoons coming from the Garrison of <em><reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg></em>, met with a party of the Enemy rambling about the Country, being 60 under command of the Laird of <em>Cairdennis</em> himself with two Cornets, and six more upon the place, took divers horse and men, and the rest fled for it. This is all the action and enemy that hath of late been in these parts; which was indeed<pb n="1" /> very handsomely performed, not one of our men being lost, and but two wounded, which are upon recovery.</p>

<p>From <em>Upsall</em>, April 21. We are now about leaving this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, as we hope: The Negotiation here being brought to a period, only there wants the signing of the Articles, by reason of the absence of the Queen: But her Majesty is upon her Return, and is expected here this night: And I question not, but we shall be dismissed in very few days, and that to satisfaction on all parts.</p>

<p>They are preparing here for the sitting of the next Parliament, which will be the beginning of May. And that my Lord Ambassadors departure may not be too near the Election of the succeeding King, for the avoiding of all exceptions He is resolved to hasten all that possibly he may, out of this Country.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg></em>, May 23. stilo novo. Here are three Ambassadors arrived from the great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em>, one of them is going for <em>France</em>, the other two had Audience the other day; they gave to understand, that the said Duke had resolved to wage war against the King of Poland; and desired leave to buy Arms and Ammunition in these Provinces. They do likewise assure, that they have great quantity of Corn, that in the City of <em>Archangel</em> alone, there is above sixty thousand <reg orig="Tonn">Ton</reg> of Corn ready to be exported. It seems that they will not hearken here to the demand which the great Master hath made here for some Goods which he claims in this Country, as belonging to him; however the maritime Towns, who do not pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>, desire he may have satisfaction given him, for fear their Commerce be not interrupted upon the Mediterranean Sea by the <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> of that Order. We are now taken up with Preparations for our Triumph and Thanksgiving day, which is to be celebrated next Wednesday.</p>

<p><i>A Proclamation by the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>, for prevention of disturbances or breach of the Peace, <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg>, and Confederation, concluded and agreed between His Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>,<pb n="2" /> and the Lords the States General of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>.</i></p>

<p>The States General of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, to all persons to whom these presents shall come, <em>Greeting</em>,</p>

<p>Whereas (to the praise of Almighty God, the advancement of the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> good of the United Provinces, and of every particular person therein) Articles of Peace, Union, and Confederation, are concluded and agreed between his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg> in a Treaty at <em>Westminster</em>, bearing date 5 April Old-<reg orig="stile">style</reg>, 1654. and hath been published both in <em>London</em> and in these Provinces, and all acts of hostility are to cease. We therefore the Lords the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> do hereby warn all people of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>, that they do acknowledge and submit to the said Peace so ratified, and to obey the Ratification in all places without any breach thereof, upon pain of being punished as disturbers of the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Peace, without expectation of <reg orig="Favor">Favour</reg>, or grace, but to be proceeded against according to Justice.</p>

<p><i>Given at the meeting of the States General at the <em>Hague</em>, 7. (alias 17.) <em>May</em>, 1654.</i></p>

<p><em>Jacob Vetch</em>, President <em>pro tempers</em>. <em>N. Ruysch</em>, Clerk to the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>.</p>

<p>From several parts thus. From <em>Stockholm</em>, the Spanish Ambassador hath been sumptuously feasted by the Queen at <em>Vpsal</em>, of whom he hath had his last Audience, and so is upon his departure, but hath received of her Majesty for a present, that which is esteemed worth 8000 Rixdollars. The Lord <em><reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg></em> is to be Lord Treasurer of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Revenues, when she hath divested <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> of her present command and authority. From <em>Warsovia</em>, The General of the <em>Poland</em> Army being <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> with a strong party of his Army in the Province of <em><reg orig="Vkraine">Ukraine</reg></em>,<pb n="3" /> and hearing that one <em>Bohum</em> one of the chief of the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> was in a Town called <em>Kakni</em>, and fled from thence in the night, he forthwith followed after him, but got no more than a tedious and wearisome march, the said <em>Bohum</em> having escaped from them, so being come to a Town called <em>Jakupen</em>, where the Townsmen, with some <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> quartered there, resisted to a furious assault, but at last being overcome, all the Men were put to the Sword, the women and children hardly escaping the fury of the Conquerors, from thence being marched to <em>Homanick</em> where the said <em>Bohum</em> was, they having held a <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> of War, it was not held fit to begin any <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg>, only that the Army should face the Town, and there should be read <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Letters, promising a general pardon to all those that are now in rebellion that would return to their former duty, the same being written in <em>Russian</em> language and characters, that so they might the better apprehend it, but nothing would prevail.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 23.</i></head>

<p>This day was kept a day of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Thanksgiving to Almighty God, according to the Declaration of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, lately mentioned, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, and Mr. <em>Thomas <reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em>, prayed and preached at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> Chapel, where his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and Council were present.</p>

<p>There was a passage inserted in our last concerning some of our English <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> landing in <em>France</em> near St. <em>Malos</em>, which we understand since to be grossly mistaken, and the Reader (to whose hands it hath come) is therefore desired to expunge it the book.</p>

<p>From the Fleet off <em>Aberdeen May</em> 13. Vice Admiral <em>John Lawson</em>, Commander of the <em>Fairfax</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and of this Squadron, hath received Orders from General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> (since his coming into <em>Scotland</em>, after advice and council with the Officers at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and from whence he is going towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>) to ply towards <em>Hoosty</em> Bay.</p>

<p>On the eleventh day of this present <em>May</em>, we discovered a Fleet of Dutch ships, which were about 70 Sail (or more)<pb n="4" /> of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> vessels intended for <em>Greenland</em>, and there Convoy were Rear Admiral <em>de Witte</em> of <em>Amsterdam</em>, and two other men of War.</p>

<p>When we came up with them, they carried themselves very lovingly, and did very <reg orig="chearfull">cheerful</reg> by submission acknowledge the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of <em>England</em> in these Seas, <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> as much to us as could be expected from any <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships, and after a friendly salute passed by, much civility and affection being expressed on both sides.</p>

<p><em>Plymouth Sound 16 May</em>, Sir, Captain <em>John Seaman</em> Commander of the <em>Dragon</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, with the <em>Adventure</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> plying off <em><reg orig="Aldernay">Alderney</reg></em>, they met with a small <em>Frenchman</em>, which had been taken by an <em>Ostender</em> near <em>Bell</em> <reg orig="Iland">Island</reg>; Our Captains being informed that she was laden with English Merchant's goods, they sent her into <em>Weymouth</em> to have that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> further examined. On the 10 instant, plying of <em>Dartmouth</em>, they met with three which belong to <em>Lyn</em>, and upon the desire of the Masters thereof, they convoyed them safe over <em>Murleux</em>, whether they saw them safe, and standing off again, met with 25 <reg orig="Sale">Sail</reg> of Frenchmen which were bound for <em>Rochel</em> to take in Salt, and so on for the bank of Newfoundland, but before they got to <em>Rochel</em> they chased them half a day, but could take but three of them, because they steered so many several courses, while we were upon the chase of them, our men descried another Fleet to the windward, which were found to be <reg orig="thirteeen">thirteen</reg> <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of <em>Holland</em> Merchant ships, with one Convoy in their Company, he saluted ours with three guns, and some expressions of love, and so they passed on their voyage, and ours parted from them, and are now at this present come in here into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> Sound.</p>

<p>From the Squadron in the West, <em>May</em> 13. About 4 days ago two ships belonging to the Dutch sailing from <em>Holland</em> towards <em>France</em> passed by us: at the first when they got the sight of our ships they put up the <em>Holland</em> colours, and sailed on towards us: And so soon as they came near one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which was <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> towards them, they freely took in their <em>Holland</em> colours, and put up a white flag of Peace, which signal of their was answered<pb n="5" /> from our ship, After which they took down their white flag, and again spread their <em>Holland</em> colours, and <reg orig="lowred">lowered</reg> their Topsails on the Cape, and so sailed under our stern. As they passed by they made great expressions of joy for the Peace between their Commonwealth and ours.</p> 

<p><i>The <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> Proceedings in the Law vindicated, &amp;c. Part V.</i></p>

<p><i>For Prevention of pestering the Cities, and charging them and the Countries by begging, indigent people, able to work; and to encourage them to follow their <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> Employments.</i></p>

<p>Whereas divers Actions have been laid to be done in <reg orig="forein">foreign</reg> Counties and places (out of which they were committed) and there <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, and the parties Defendants (to their great trouble, <reg orig="travell">travel</reg>, and charge) compelled to bring divers Witnesses to far and remote places.</p>

<p>And if the Trial of such Action hath been prevented from being in a <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> County, the Defendant therein hath been put to great charges and trouble, in coming and bringing up Witness to the Term, from <reg orig="farre">far</reg> and remote places, to make Oath or Affidavit of the true place; where the cause of such action did arise, and then to move the Court (where such action was <reg orig="commensed">commenced</reg> ) to alter the Visne; which usually hath been granted, if such Defendant hath been provided with such Affidavit the same Term, in which the Declaration of such Action hath been delivered; but not after, to such Defendants great and unnecessary charge; many of such men being very poor, (divers of them dwelling in the remotest places from <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>) and coming to <em>London</em> <reg orig="bare-footed">barefooted</reg>, and <reg orig="bare-legged">barelegged</reg>, and begging on the way going thither, staying there, and returning back to their dwelling, whereby the Countries and Cities have been troubled with, and charged by Beggars, and the necessary <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> of such poor People hindered: which might easily have been prevented by a general Rule or Order for that purpose, and in such Actions or Causes divers times excessive damages have been given by Common <reg orig="Jury-men">Jurymen</reg> in <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>.</p>

<p><i>For remedy whereof, it is proposed to be desired that it may Be Enacted,</i> That all such Actions may be laid in the proper<pb n="6" /> Counties, <reg orig="wher">where</reg> the cause of such Action do, or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> arise, happen or accrue, or else the same to be void, and to be found for the Defendants at the trials thereof, if such Plaintiff at such <reg orig="triall">trial</reg> shall not prove the cause of such action is, or shall be laid to be done; unless the Plaintiff in such Action, before his Declaration thereof filed or delivered in, (to the Officer appointed to filing or keeping such things) do, or shall make appear by affidavit, such Defendants to be very <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg> in the Country where such Cause or Action doth or shall arise, happen, or accrue, or to be there much favoured, or feared, or some other Cause (which concerning such like Actions hath been allowed of by some of the <reg orig="Superiour">Superior</reg> Courts to be sufficient for such purpose) and a true copy <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, and of the Matter which he, she, or they, do, or shall intend to move, to have the same laid out of the Place or County, where the Cause of such Action doth, or shall arise, or happen; and where he, she, or they desire to have the same laid (out of such County, or place, where such Action hath been, or shall be laid) in writing, to the party or parties, Defendant or Defendants, (against whom such action or suit be, or shall be brought) his, her, or their Attorney or Attorneys in the same; And if they, some, or one of them (principally concerned therein) do not, nor shall within 10 days next after contradict, deny, or refuse to consent to the <unclear>same</unclear>, and deliver the matter of such Contradiction, <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> or Refusal in writing to the Plaintiff in such Action, his, her, or their Attorney therein, within 8 days next after the delivery of such Writing to, or for such Defendant or Defendants. And that if such Writing or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> be, or shall be so delivered, then such proceedings may be thereupon, as is mentioned in Propositions concerning Motions and Orders.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 27 of May, 1654. The <em>Lorrainers</em> whom I told you were quartered near <em>la Bassee</em>, are removed further, being between <em>Bapaume</em> and St. <em>Venant</em>, and yet commanded by the E. <em>de Ligneville</em>, by reason D. <em>Francis</em> is not yet come to them, and notwithstanding the <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> Orders of the Archduke, and the aforesaid Duke to live in a peaceable manner, yet they cannot leave their old trade of thieving.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>The Marsh. <em>de la Ferte Seneterre</em> is yet at <em>Nancy</em>, and is gathering all his forces together to take the field with all expedition, and to hasten the matter the more hath appointed 3 <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> to his Army, to such forces as come from the County of <em>Alsatia</em>, at <em>Bourbon</em>, those that are quartered along the river of <em>Aisne</em>, at <em>Tilli</em> on the <em>Mawse</em>, and those from <em>Lorrain</em> and <em>Troys</em> at St. <em>Dizin</em>, the <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> being appointed at <em>Varanne</em> in the County of <em>Clermont</em>. We hear that at last all things are fully agreed between the Court and the E. of <em>Harcourt</em>, and that the agreement was to be signed the 20 of this instant. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. <em>Menehold</em> having notice that the Enemy intended to send their Convoy designed for the relief of <em>Clermont</em> with provisions and ammunitions in small parties, to avoid the better several of parties of ours which are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> sent out for their discovery, carried on their work so wisely, that having gone by private ways, forsaking the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg>, ours missed of them, having only fallen upon the Rear, and taken some few horses. The first President with some <reg orig="Counsellors">Councillors</reg> were this week at the <em>Louur</em> to Petition, about the calling home of their fellow Members which were still in exile, having presented their desires in writing, they made a speech for a further explication thereof; their manner of proceeding was disliked, and therefore had no satisfactory answer. The King is not yet gone from hence to <em>Rheims</em>, by reason that the Archbishop of that City cannot perform the Ceremony of anointing him; therefore Letters are gone from his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> under his Signet to the Bishop of <em>Sorsons</em>, who is Coadjutor of that <reg orig="Archbishoprick">Archbishopric</reg>, to attend his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> there, and to be ready to perform the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> upon the day appointed. The Ambassador of <em>Savoy</em> hath had lately audience of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> there, and to be ready to perform the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> upon the day appointed. The Ambassador of <em>Savoy</em> hath had lately audience of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, to whom he made a long speech concerning the wars of his Country, and what his Master desired concerning the next field expedition. The 24 instant the Cardinal feasted the King at dinner, where was also the Queen, the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Brother, and some Ministers of State; there is a report that the Duke of <em>Vendosme</em> is something out of favour, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said to be concerning some passages between him and the Duke of <em>Beaufort</em> his Son, at their late conference at <em>Surenne</em>.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 24.</i></head>

<p>Upon discovery of a barbarous and blood conspiracy against his Highness the Lord Protector, and to involve this Nation in blood and confusion, divers persons have been this week apprehended in and about <em>London</em>, and committed about it, and some in other parts, the particulars whereof we shall give you more <reg orig="fullly">fully</reg> hereafter, and this day Proclamation was made in <em>London</em> (and the like in other parts) as followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal providences of God in frustrating of their former counsels and <reg orig="malitious">malicious</reg> designs) do appear still <reg orig="restlesse">restless</reg> in their attempts, to involve this Commonwealth in blood and confusion, In order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this Commonwealth, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication hereof, repair to the several houses within their respective parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the Names of all such persons as now do, or did lodge in their respective Houses on <em>Friday</em> night last, being the nineteen of this instant <em>May</em>, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names upon peril of being reputed and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, as <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg> and Partakers in the said Design. Which Lists so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Southwark, and Lines of Communication, are within forty eight hours to deliver to the Lord Mayor of <em>London</em>, and the Bailiffs of<pb n="9" /> <em>Westminster</em> and <em>Southwark</em>, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril. and the said Lord Mayor and Bailiffs are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, immediately after the receipt thereof. And his Highness doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever, lodging within the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the date hereof, without a special License and Pass in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor of the said City of <em>London</em>, or <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Westminster</em> or <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are hereby authorized to give to all such persons concerning whom they shall be satisfied, that they have no ill intentions or designs against the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to none else. And if any such person shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without license obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a Contempt of this his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Command, and be punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em> and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after Publication thereof, to be sent to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Constables as aforesaid, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em>White-hall</em> the 23. of May, 1654.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 25.</i></head>

<p>This following Proclamation was published, as followeth.</p>

<p><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></p>

<p>Whereas by the thirtieth Article of the Peace lately made and concluded between his Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces, It is concluded and agreed, That four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides to meet here at <em>London</em>, upon the eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, one thousand six hundred fifty and four,<pb n="10" /> Old Style, who shall be authorized to examine and determine all the Losses, and Injuries which either allege to have <reg orig="susteined">sustained</reg> from the other, since the year one thousand six hundred and eleven, unto the eighteenth of <em>May</em> one thousand six hundred fifty and two, as well in the <em>East Indies</em>, as in <em>Greenland, Muscovy, Brazeel</em>, or in any other place; the particulars of all which shall be delivered in to the said Commissioners before the said eighteenth of <em>May</em> one thousand six hundred fifty and four. And whereas in pursuance thereof Commissioners are respectively named, viz. <em>John Exton, William Turner</em>, Doctors of Law, <em>William Thompson</em>, and <em>Thomas Kendall</em>, Merchants, on the part of the <em>English</em>; and <em><reg orig="Adryan">Adrian</reg> Van Almonde, Christian Van Rodenbure, Lodovick Howens, James Oysel</em>, on the part of the people of the United Provinces, who not being able to meet so soon as the said eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, It was mutually agreed, That the meeting should be deferred unto the thirtieth of the same <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> of <em>May</em>, and that the particulars of the said Demands on either part may be delivered in at any time before, or upon the <reg orig="thirtith">thirtieth</reg> of <em>May</em> next, and that the same being delivered in before, or upon the said day, should be as effectual as if they had been exhibited upon the eighteenth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid. Which last Agreement his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath Commanded by these presents to be made <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg>, To the end all persons concerned may take notice thereof, and deliver in their Demands unto the Commissioners accordingly. The place of whose meeting is appointed to be at <em><reg orig="Guild-Hall">Guildhall</reg></em> upon the thirtieth of <em>May</em> aforesaid.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> the 24. of <em>May</em>, 1654.</i></p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 30th of May, 1654. New stile. All things are now ready for the anointing of our King, and it is thought that in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> his Majesty will <reg orig="goe">go</reg> from hence, the Earl <em>de Bruston</em> having invited all <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, Residents, and Agents of <reg orig="Forrain">Foreign</reg> Princes to assist at that Solemnity. The 26 instant the Prince of <em>Conti</em> having taken his leave of their Majesties, went from this City, and is now on his way for <em>Catalonia</em>, there to be Commander in chief of the French Army, and the Duke of<pb n="11" /> <em>Candale</em> is to follow shortly after. The 27 the Commissioners for the Cantons of Switzerland had Audience of his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, as also the Earl <em>Riva</em>, <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Minister of the Prince of <em>Parma</em>, being all of them brought to their Audience in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Coaches, and attended by the Earl of <em>Bruston</em>. The same day the late Bishop of <em>Coserans</em> made Oath before his Majesty for the <reg orig="Archbishoprick">Archbishopric</reg> of <em>Toulouse</em>, which the King hath bestowed upon him for his good and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> services to the State: also the same day the Lord <em>Borreell</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> in ordinary for the States of the United Provinces caused several Bonfires, and Wildfires, and great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at and before his house, for the conclusion of the peace between them and the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>The Marshal <em>Granmont</em> being gone to <em>Bayonne</em> had order from the King to see the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, and then to invite him again to come to the Court, that so he might <reg orig="accompanie">accompany</reg> his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> to <em>Rheims</em>, that being done, to complain unto him of his eldest daughter <reg orig="Madamoiselle">Mademoiselle</reg> whom he charged to keep <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Enemies of the State, and to have relieved them with moneys (meaning the Prince of <em>Conde</em> and his adherents) and that in case he would not speedily remedy those faults, he would give order to secure her person and estate: The King is not yet gone, but its credibly reported that he will <reg orig="goe">go</reg> the first of <em>June</em> being <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> next, he is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> first the <em>Compeigne</em>, and from thence to <em>Soissons</em>, and so to <em>Rheims</em>. The Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> is now tampering with the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>de Hocquincourt</em>, that he might once more <reg orig="goe">go</reg> into <em>Catalonia</em> for to assist the Prince of <em>Conti</em> in managing of that war, but he refuseth to <reg orig="goe">go</reg>, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> the reversion of the place of <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Peronne</em> be first granted to his Son. The Duke of <em>Guise</em> is not yet gone, want of money being the main let to hinder his journey; The King seemed to be much discontented at the refusal of his Uncle the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, who hath sent by one of his Gentlemen to desire to be excused for not attending on his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> <unclear>at</unclear> <em>Rheims</em>, which he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he cannot <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, by reason he is not in health.</p><pb n="12" />

<p>From <em>Dunkirk June 2</em> new stile: I have no good news to impart you at present, only the sad accident which happened at <em>Gravelines</em> upon <em>Thursday</em> last being the 28 of <em>May</em>; about ten of the clock in the forenoon; where the fire having taken to a great quantity in a magazine of Powder blew, up a great part of the Castle, the <reg orig="Covent">Convent</reg> of <em>English</em> Nuns, with many houses <reg orig="adjoyning">adjoining</reg> it, which were all blown up and laid in a heap, and had near taken the other Magazine, where was 400 Barrels of Powder, <reg orig="Granadoes">Grenades</reg>, and other <reg orig="Fire-works">Fireworks</reg> in great quantity.</p>

<p><i>At the Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></p> 

<p>Whereas Information hath been given to his Highness the Lord Protector by the Committee sitting at <em><reg orig="Sadlers">Sadler's</reg></em> hall <em>London</em>, appointed to take care of carrying on the business of collections in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, for and towards the relief of the Inhabitants of the Town of <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em> in the County of Wilts, and <reg orig="reedyfying">re-edifying</reg> of the said Town (a great part thereof being lately consumed by a sad and lamentable fire,) That there are divers sums of money collected in divers Parishes, Cities, and Towns Corporate in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em> for the uses aforesaid, which are through <reg orig="remissnes">remissness</reg>, or some other sinister ends, detained in the hands of such as have collected the same, and have not paid them over to such persons as have been appointed by the said Committee to receive them, <reg orig="wherby">whereby</reg> the Charity of good People is abused, and those poor Inhabitants frustrated or delayed of relief intended to <reg orig="shem">them</reg> thereby. It is therefore Ordered by his Highness the Lord Protector and the Council, That all Churchwardens, Collector, <reg orig="Receivors">Receivers</reg>, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, Constables, and other persons who have in their hands any of the moneys collected for the uses aforesaid, do forthwith, upon sight hereof, pay over the same to such person or persons, as Alderman <em>Andrews</em>, Alderman <em>Titchborn</em>, Alderman <em>Ireton</em>, Col. <em>Owen Roe</em>, Mr. <em>Edw. Bushell</em>, Mr. <em>Maximilian Beard</em>, Mr. <em>Greensmith</em>, Mr. <em>Herring</em>, Major <em>Packer</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas <reg orig="Lambe">Lamb</reg></em>, Mr. <em>Wollaston</em>, Mr. <em>Tempest Milnor</em>. Mr. <em>Theophilus <reg orig="Ryley">Riley</reg></em>, Major <em>Wareing</em>, Mr. <em>Asburst</em>, Mr. <em>Strong</em>, Mr. <em>Samuel Wilson</em>, Mr. <em>Robert <reg orig="Barret">Barrett</reg></em>, Mr.<pb n ="13" /> <em>Anthony Dowse</em>, Mr. <em>John Price</em>, Mr. <em>William Kiffin</em>, Mr. <em>Babington</em>, Major <em><reg orig="Bancks">Banks</reg></em>, Capt. <em>Manton</em>, Mr. <em>Bandrith</em>, Mr. <em>Isles</em>, Mr. <em>Lawrence Steele</em>, Mr. <em>William Malyn</em>, Capt. <em>Aldron</em>, Cornet <em>Comeby</em>, being the said Committee at <em>Sadlers</em> Hall, or any five of them, shall appoint and authorize to receive the same; and all the said Collectors, and other Officers and persons before <reg orig="mentio-">mentioned</reg> are hereby required to perform the same accordingly, as they will answer their neglect and contempt at their peril.</p>

<p><i>Ex. <em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday, May 26, 27.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Amsterdam</em> May 25. The <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of <em>Orange</em> with the young P. her Son are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> from the <em>Hague</em> to <em>Honslaerdiick</em> one of their houses, and afterwards are to return to <em>Breda</em>: There is a great preparation made in this City for a day of Thanksgiving for the Peace concluded between us and <em>England</em>; our States Provincial which were parted some days since, are again met to find out a stock for the payment of such <reg orig="summs">sums</reg> as they stand engaged to <em>England</em> for the satisfaction of those Ships stopped at <em>Zund</em> by the King of <em>Denmark</em>. Our Fleet for <em>Greenland</em> is gone to Sea, and a great number of ships are ready to go to <em>France</em>, and other places to the Southward, and two great ships called the <em>Whale</em>, and <em>Hunter</em>, are ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for the <em>East Indies</em>, and for to ease this Province of the great <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> it hath sustained during these late <reg orig="warrs">wars</reg>, our States are about to reduce our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to a lesser number. <em>Minehead</em> May 22, Here are little news in these parts, by reason of contrary winds, we have had but little or no returns from <em>Ireland</em> since this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, besides the <em>Brest</em> <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> still range up and down this <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, but have been disappointed of their expectations: Three days since they chased two Barks in Severn so far up, that it was marvel how they durst to venture, yet at last missed of their intent, and glad to put out again to Sea.</p>

<p><em>Scarborough</em> the same date, This Coat is now well rid of Pirates, whereby we may trade with more security, yet the last week there were again two small <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> of 4 and 6 Guns a piece: We hear by one of our Fisherboats they are of all Nations<pb n="14" />, and pretend to have a Commission under <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>: These two days have <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by a great many ships from the Northward, some of them from <em>Scotland</em>, but the most from <em>Newcastle</em> and <em>Sunderland</em>, laden with Coals for <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Letters from <em>Scotland</em> as followeth, <em>Inverness May</em> 14. <em>Middleton</em> and the rest of his party that remains of those that are run to their own houses, are still in <em>Southerland</em> and <em>Caithness</em>, Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> brigade lies in the Shires of <em>Ross</em> and <em>Inverness</em> blocking them up as formerly; <em>Drummond</em> is about <em><reg orig="Loughtay">Lough Tay</reg></em>, and the Bailiff of <em>Athol</em> is gone to him, to advise concerning the speedy raising of all Gentlemen in that Country (for the Highlanders are <reg orig="noe">no</reg> other) <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> with about 450 horse and foot were lately in the <reg orig="Braies">Brays</reg> of Anguish, forcing men to rise with him: <em>Glencairn</em> we hear is gone South through the <reg orig="Braies">Brays</reg> of <em>Renogh</em>, and from the Hills we understand, the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> foot runs away over the Mountains by thirty and forty in a Company, and are necessitated to eat horse flesh where they <reg orig="goe">go</reg>, provisions being so exceeding scarce in those parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, May 16</em>. Thursday last the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> came hither with part of Col. <em>Okey's</em> Regiment of Horse, his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> Regiment, and four Companies of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> of Foot, we hear nothing of any considerable part of the Enemy being in these parts: only we have Intelligence, That Captain <em>Kympton Hilliard</em> being marched towards <em>Douglas</em>, having Intelligence, That <em>Cardinesse, Forgison</em>, and <em>Wallace</em>, with about 40. of the <reg orig="Rebells">Rebels</reg> were about New Mills, resolved to engage them with 20 of his Troop, and a Sergeant that were with him, but upon a nearer approach found them above 60. ready mounted, and drawn up to receive him; notwithstanding which, he continued his Resolution, and upon his approach the <reg orig="Rebells">Rebels</reg> <reg orig="seem'd">seemed</reg> much to <reg orig="scorne">scorn</reg> the <reg orig="smallnesse">smallness</reg> of his number; but it pleased God so to order it, That after he had received their charge, he fell in upon them, and broke them, <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> <em><reg orig="Cardinesses">Cardinesse's</reg></em> Cornet, and <em>Forgisson's</em> Cornet, and mortally wounded Lieutenant <em>Wallis</em>, <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> two Horses of<pb n="15" /> theirs and took 4. The rest, although <reg orig="disperst">dispersed</reg>, got away being well Mounted. He took 6 or 8 suits of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, being good Backs, and <reg orig="Brests">Breasts</reg>. Most of the Enemy had the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Mark. We had only two wounded, and after two <reg orig="houres">hours</reg> keeping the field, he returned to <em><reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg></em>. The <reg orig="Rebells">Rebels</reg> were marching towards the Hills, but by this means it is supposed they will have no great mind to engage.</p>

<p>This day the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> and Forces march from hence to <em>Cardrosse</em>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Hills, where he will lie in the Fields for some time; <em>Glencairne</em> is come with some Forces into those parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, May 20. Wednesday at night last some Prisoners broke from their place of Durance; But were most of them retaken within two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after. <em>Middleton, Monroe, <reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em>, and <em>Forbes</em>, are in <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> with their broken Regiments; <em>Kenmore</em> <reg orig="remaines">remains</reg> sick in <em>Sutherland</em>, and has been so for this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> past. <em>Glencairne</em> and <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>Drummond</em>, with some Foot and Horse <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at <em>Abersoyle</em>, the most considerable <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> and from the Hills, about 12 miles from <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> is marched that way to observe the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> passes upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg>, and to take some course with them.</p>

<hr />

<p>A brief exposition on the last 50 Psalms, from Psalm 100 to the end, which now makes a <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> work on the whole book of Psalms, by <em>David <reg orig="Dicksen">Dickson</reg></em> Professor of Divinity in <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>: To be sold by <em>Thomas Johnson</em> at the Golden Key in St <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p><reg orig="Metiors">Meteors</reg>, or, a Plain description of all kinds of <reg orig="Metiors">Meteors</reg>, as well <reg orig="Fierie">Fiery</reg> and <reg orig="Ayrie">Airy</reg>, as <reg orig="Warry">Wary</reg> and Earthy: briefly manifesting the causes of all Blazing stars, Shooting stars, Flames in the Air, Thunder, <reg orig="Lightnings">Lightning</reg>, Earthquakes, Rain, Dew, Snow, Clouds, Springs, Stones, and <reg orig="Metalls">Metals</reg>, by <em>W. F.</em> Dr. in Divinity. Exercitatio Scholastica, and Linguam Latinam viam muniens, Both printed and sold by <em>William Leak</em> at the Crown in <em><reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg></em>, between the two Temple Gates.</p>

<p>A <reg orig="Nagg">Nag</reg> <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> 15 May 1654, A brown Bay, with a Star, a snip of one of his ears; branded with a B. and Flower-de-luce upon his near shoulder, 4 years old of stature 14 hands, or thereabouts: If such can be found, to be brought to the <reg orig="Horsshoee">Horseshoe</reg> against <em><reg orig="Sepulchers">Sepulchres</reg></em> Church <em>London</em>, or to Mr. <em>William Roberts</em> of <em>Louth</em> in the County of <em>Lincoln</em>, and they shall be well contented.</p>

<p>Those who desire, may from the <em>Swan</em> at <em>Holborne</em> bridge, upon every <em>Monday</em>, and <em>Friday</em> <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to <em>York</em> in 4 days, or to <em>Newcastle</em> in 6. in the Post hanging Coaches.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>