<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc6">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Diurnall or Occurrences, Issue 6</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg>:</head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="1">OCCURRENCES</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other.</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>June</em>. 5. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>June</em> 12. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, June 5.</i></head>

<p>Leith <em>June</em> 2. Gen. <em>Monk</em> is returned back again to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>; <em><reg orig="Macgriggen">McGriggen</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Macfarland">McFarland</reg></em>, two of the principal <em>Clans</em> in the Hills, have made some overtures of coming in, and to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> to live peaceably; <em>Glencarn</em> is fallen down into the Lowlands, but his Forces are not so considerable as to fight us; <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought that he hath some other inclinations: He and <em>Middleton</em> have had some clashing, and therefore it maybe he will leave him to shift for himself. I told you in my last of the escape of the Earl of <em>Kineuse</em>, and others out of <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> Castle; and there was this remarkable more (which was then omitted,) That <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>. <em>Montgomery</em>, who attempted to escape at the same time, by leaping down, fell, and brake his neck.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3">An Ordinance of his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em>.</head>

<p>Be it declared and ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, That so much of the Act of Parliament of the second of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>, One thousand six hundred fifty one; <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the continuing of the jurisdiction of the Court of Admiralty,</i> or so much thereof as concerns the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> and continuing of the Jurisdiction of the said Court, according to former Acts and Ordinances of Parliament, <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, and is hereby declared to be, and at all times since the 12. of April, <em>anno Dom</em>. One thousand six hundred <reg orig="fiftie">fifty</reg> and one, to have been continued of full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, according to the words contained therein, and the same shall so continue and be, and shall be so in all Courts adjudged to be continued, and of full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, until further order shall be taken to the contrary.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, June 6.</i></head>

<p>The County of <em>Warwick</em> expressed their affections to his Highness and the present Government, as followeth:</p>

<p><i>To his Highness the Lord Protector of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>. The Congratulation of us the Knights, Gentlemen, Ministers, and Yeomen of the County of <em>Warwick</em>.</i></p>

<p>We desire to own and <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> in the good presence of God, which hath gone along with your Highness in all your undertakings; and hath made your Eminency instrumental in the procuring of the deliverance of this poor Nation out of those unhappy and great troubles under which it hath groaned these many years last past, to that great blessing of Peace and quiet which for the present we do enjoy: And we do further with much thankfulness and admiration acknowledge the goodness of God toward us, that when through the preposterous heat of some we were again<pb n="2" /> ready to be plunged into a sea of greater Misery and confusion <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, That then again the Lord did stir you up to stand in the Gap: And hath given us fresh grounds of hope that he hath chosen you out for the Protection and <reg orig="Wellfare">Welfare</reg> of this poor Nation. And whereas it is the duty of the people to strengthen the hands of their <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg>, We have been stirred up <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> to express our resentment of that great, and (we hope) most happy change, tending so much to our establishment and happiness, in that we have a more sure foundation of <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Government held forth unto us, in that he hath already given us a large earnest of that spirit and zeal for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good, which God hath poured upon you in these acceptable beginnings and endeavours for establishing the Magistracy and <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, the Ordinances of God in their power and purity, and the fundamental Laws and Liberties of this Nation, with encouragement of all those that fear God in the three Nations; in the promoting whereof we shall stand by you, and assist your Highness, and ever pray for your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> welfare and prosperity.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A DECLARATION, or Address petitionary to the Lords the States <reg orig="generall">general</reg> of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, by the Princess Royal, and the Princess Dowager, in behalf of the young Prince of <reg orig="Oraunge">Orange</reg>.</i></head>

<p><i>High and Mighty Lords,</i></p>

<p>Her Royal Highness, together with her Highness the Princess Dowager (Mother and Grandmother too) as Guardians of the young Princess Highness; do find themselves under engagement, and out of their Motherly affections bound and necessitated in all due respect to your mighty Highness to declare unto You, that they are informed (to their great wonder and grief) that the Noble, Great, and Potent Lords, the States of <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Westfreezland</em> have taken up a Resolution by which the <reg orig="yong">young</reg> Prince of <em><reg orig="Oraunge">Orange</reg></em>,<pb n="3" /> their Son, and <reg orig="Pupisl">Pupils</reg>, and all that shall descend from him should be excluded from all kinds of Dignities, Office, and Charge, which his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Predecessors did <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> in these <em>Provinces</em>.</p>

<p>Their Highnesses do not know what hath moved them to such deliberation, but this is very apparent,</p>

<p><i>1. That a long and true service hath been performed from the Princess his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Predecessors successively, in which they had hazarded both their blood and lives for this Land.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That their Noble, Great and Potent Lordships have always hitherto <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> inclinations of good affection to the renowned House of Orange.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That the tender and innocent years of the present young Prince is attended with such present education, and considerable interests for the good of this Land, as that it cannot be thought but he will be brought up to tread in the fore-steps of his renowned <reg orig="Fore-fathers">Forefathers</reg>, for the future service of this State.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That there is further hopes of succession from him.</i></p>

<p>And it is hoped that no such Resolution shall be now made to his prejudice, which cannot but leave a remarkable spot both upon his person and his Family. Therefore we do (with all due respect to your mighty Highness) seek, and pray that if you find any such resolution to be under Debate by the States of <em>Holland</em>, that your mighty Highness would be induced that the further Debate of a business of so weighty importance, may be further Debated by none others, Your Mighty Highness <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, and by You so ended, that the Debate thereof may be brought to no further effect. And hereby Your mighty Highness will declare your great Wisdom and Discretion to be praise worthy to the World, and it will be a work very acceptable to all the good people of these <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Signed by the Princess Royal, <em>&amp;c</em>.</i></p>

<p>The Lords Commissioners of the great Seal, came and sat in the Court of Upper-Bench, and acquainted Sergeant <em>Nudigate</em> that his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> looked on him to be a man of Gravity, Wisdom, and Uprightness; and therefore had of his own free motion given his Commission for the making him a Judge of that Court. Then he came up and took his Oath in Court, and took his place in the Bench. The like ceremony was also in the Common-Pleas, of which Court also Sergeant <em>Windham</em> was made a Judge, and Sergeant <em>Popys</em>, one of the Barons of Exchequer.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday</i></head>

<p>The last week we acquainted you with the names of persons of Eminency that were committed to the Tower, about a treasonable Plot and Conspiracy; since which time many others have been taken into custody: some whereof sent to the Tower, and others at Saint <em>James</em> and <em>Whitehall</em>, We shall give you a List of many of them as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>A list of the Prisoners in custody about the Plot daily under examination.</i></head>

<head level="3">In the Tower.</head>
<p>Sir <em>Richard Willis</em>.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilbert Gerhard</em> titular.</p>
<p><em>Jo. Gerhard</em> his Brother.</p>
<p><em>Charles Gerhard</em> his Brother.</p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Ashburnham</em>.</p>
<p><em>William Ashburnham</em> Esq.</p>
<p>Master <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Wiseman</em> Agent.</p>
<p>Mr <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Finch</em>.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Peter Vowel</em>.</p>
<p><em>Tho. Sanders</em> Silkman.</p>
<p><em>Sydney Fotherby</em>.</p>
<p><em>Humphrey Baggaly</em>.</p>
<p><em>Michael Mason</em> a Fensor.</p>

<head level="3">At <reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg>.</head>
<p>Col: <em>Aldridge</em>.</p>
<p>Col: <em>Edw: Villers</em>.</p>
<p>Colonel <em>Phil: Honywood</em></p>
<p>D. <em>Theod: Nandin</em>.</p>
<p><em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> James</em> Apoth.</p>
<p><i>Th. Brown</i>.</p>
<p><i>Jo. Brown</i>.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Alex: Gifford</em>.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Walter Hauford</em>.</p>
<head level="3">At <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></head>
<p><i>Robert Sherow.</i></p>
<p><i>Henry Taylor.</i></p>
<p><i>John Wharton.</i></p>
<p><i>Thomas Barns.</i></p>
<p><i>Nicho Watson.</i></p>
<p><i>William <reg orig="Dod">Dodd</reg>.</i></p>
<p><i>Francis Fox.</i></p>
<p><i>Summerset Fox.</i></p>
<p><i>Thomas Fox.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Brooks.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> <reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></i>.</p>
<p><i>Henry <reg orig="Peirce">Pierce</reg>.</i></p>
<p><i>Francis Newbowl.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Pearsol.</i></p>
<p><i>Henry Barwicks.</i></p>
<p><i>Robert Picket.</i></p>
<p><i><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Andrews.</i></p>
<p><i>Jerem. Ellis.</i></p>
<p><i>Robert Wiseman.</i></p>
<p><i>Thomas Viner.</i></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Harlow</em>.</p>
<p><i>Fane Hake</i>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Paris</em> June 3.</head>

<p>His Majesty having now received the anointing, with the holy <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg> of S. <em>Remigius</em>, is resolved to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself in the head of his Army before his return to this City: They have now besieged the Prince of <em><reg orig="Condies">Condi's</reg></em> Forces in the strong hold of <em>Sterey</em>, and it is thought that it cannot hold out long, for that provisions are wanting; yet it is thought <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> will be attempted for their relief, in regard Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorraine</em> is now in a posture, and holds good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Prince of <em>Conde</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> June 8.</head>

<p>The Writs being issued forth for the Election of Members for another Parliament: his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> and his Council this day agreed upon the form of an indenture between the Sheriff and the Electors of persons to serve in Parliament for Counties as followeth.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>This INDENTURE made the <!-- space blanking out day of the month --> day of <!-- space blanking out a month --> in the year of our Lord one thousand six hundred fifty and four, at <!-- space blanking out a place name --> in the County of <!-- space blanking out a County --> Between <!-- another space blanking out something, maybe a place name --> Sheriff of the County aforesaid of the one part, and <em>C D E F. GH.</em> And divers other persons qualified and capable to elect Members to serve in Parliament for Counties as is prescribed in the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, witnesseth, That Proclamation having been made in every Market-Town in the County aforesaid within ten days after the <reg orig="receit">receipt</reg> of a certain Writ of the Lord <em>Protector</em> to the aforesaid Sheriff directed, and to one part of these Indentures annexed for the Election of <!-- space again blanking something out, probably a number --> Knights, fit and discreet Persons in the County aforesaid, for the Parliament of the said Lord <em>Protector</em> in the Writ aforesaid specified to be chosen, and to be at the Parliament of the said Lord <em>Protector</em> at <em>Westminster</em> in the County of <em>Middlesex</em>, the third day of <em>September</em> next to be held; The aforesaid <em>C. D. E F. G. H.</em> &amp;c. and divers other persons of the County aforesaid, who were present at such Election, freely and indifferently have chosen <!-- again space blanking something out --> <reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg> girt with swords, that is to say, <em>A. B</em> &amp;c. to be in the Parliament aforesaid, as in the said Writ is mentioned who for themselves as also for all the people of the County aforesaid, have full and sufficient power to do and consent unto those things, which in the aforesaid Parliament <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> then and there, by common Consent and Council, happen to be ordained.</p>

<p>Provided, and it is hereby Declared, That the persons so chosen shall not have power to alter the Government as it is now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in one single Person and a Parliament. In witness whereof as well the Seal of Office of the said Sheriff, as also the Seals of the Electors aforesaid, the day, year, and place abovesaid to these Indentures are put and affixed.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobell</em> Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p><i>The Form of an INDENTURE between the Sheriff and the Burgesses and Inhabitants of Burroughs.</i></p> 

<p>The <em>INDENTURE</em> made the <!-- space blanking out a day of the month --> day of <!-- space blanking out a month of the year --> in the year of our Lord one thousand six hundred fifty and four. Between A.B. High Sheriff of the County of the one part, And C.D.E.F.G.H. <em>&amp;c.</em> Burgesses and Inhabitants of the <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <!-- space blanking out a place name --> of the other par, witnesseth, That by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Warrant unto <em>I. K.</em> <!-- space blanking out what probably is a surname --> of the said <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <!-- space blanking out a place name --><pb n="6" /> from the said High Sheriff to him directed, for the Electing and choosing of <!-- space blanking out names or a number --> Burgesses of good understanding, knowledge and discretion for Causes concerning the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> good of this Commonwealth, To be at his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Parliament to <reg orig="be holden">beholden</reg> at <em>Westminster</em>, the third day of <em>September</em> next; We the said Burgesses and Inhabitants there, have made choice and Election of <em>L.</em> and <em>M.</em> to be Burgesses of the said <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <!-- space blanking out a place name --> to attend at the said Parliament according to the <reg orig="tenour">tenor</reg> of the said Warrant unto him the said <em>I. K.</em> directed in that behalf; who for themselves and all the people of the said <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> have full power to do and consent unto those things which in the aforesaid Parliament shall then and there, by Common Council and Consent, happen to be Ordained. Provided, and it is hereby declared, That they shall not have power to alter the Government as it is now settled in one single Person and Parliament. In witness whereof we the parties above-named to these presents interchangeably set our hands and Seals the day and year first above written.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobell</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, June 9.</head>

<p>From <em>Upsal</em> they write, That the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> hath taken his leave of the Queen (having finished the whole Treaty,) and there is great joy that they have made sure unto them such a considerable friend, as they look upon the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> to be; The Lord Ambassador was conducted out of the City by a great number of Nobility, which <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> great respect unto him.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dublin, May 31.</em> 1654.</head>

<p>We are in <reg orig="somwhat">somewhat</reg> a confused posture, yet with our Transplantation, many are gone, but many others play <i>Loath to depart</i>, and many are dispensed with, as particularly one whole Town, <em>Cashel</em>, towards which we had no great obligation upon us: But the Lord by a fire on the 23 instant, hath burnt down the whole Town in little more <reg orig="then">than</reg> a quarter of an hour, except some houses that a few English lived in, which were wonderly preserved being in the midst of the Town. The person that got their dispensation from transporting, died the day before the fire of the Plague, and none else long before nor since, dead or sick of that disease there: The Irish are hatching some mischief as appears by a paper we have found that came from some in <em>England</em> or <em>France</em>, advising the time is not yet for some design, but will be shortly.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, June 10.</head>

<p>Upon a general search throughout the whole City of <em>London</em> and the Suburbs, with the City of <em>Westminster</em>, and the parts adjacent, a great number of suspected persons touching the Plot lately discovered, were apprehended the two last <reg orig="nighs">nights</reg>; some were carried immediately to <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, some to S. <em><reg orig="James">James'</reg></em>; others were laid in the Compters, but the major part were secured in S. <em><reg orig="Giles">Gile's</reg></em>-Church, in the fields, and in <em>Covent-garden</em>. Gen. <em><reg orig="Whaly">Whaley</reg></em> and many other Commissioners and Justices of Peace sit daily in that which was called the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> House at <em>Westminster</em> upon examination of the parties brought before them. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>. <em><reg orig="Digbey">Digby</reg></em> is sent to the Tower; one <em>Cook</em> of <em>Essex</em>, one <em>Bodinham</em> of <em>Herefordshire</em>, and a great number more are secured elsewhere; but we shall forbear the naming of any more at present, because it is a thing that continues still under examination. That we may give a little further satisfaction to those that are earnest in their enquiry what the intention or scope of this design was (according to the best information we can get at present) some of them have confessed the design extended to the cutting of the throats of those that had acted for the Parliament, and the setting fire on <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em> in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places in one instant, and then to <reg orig="proclaime">proclaim</reg> <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>; and several Officers were <reg orig="pitch'd">pitched</reg> upon, who had provided themselves rich <reg orig="Scarffs">Scarves</reg>, some whereof have been produced.</p>

<p>Several persons were apprehended in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg> for <reg orig="Coyners">Coiners</reg>.</p>

<p>Two Soldiers ran the Gantelop in <em>Holborn</em>, and were <reg orig="cashierd">cashiered</reg>.</p>

<p>The L. President <em>Lawrence</em>, the L. <em>Sidenham</em> L. <em>Chamberlain</em>, and the rest of the Council had debate on the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> about Salters Hall for Creditors and Debtors.</p>

<p>An Ordinance under debate for rejecting scandalous Ministers, by Commissioners in every County.</p>

<p>An Ordinance coming forth for continuing a monthly <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> for the Army.</p>

<p>We have lately taken seven prizes from the French, some whereof are come up into the river of Thames.</p>

<p><em>Newcastle</em>, June 4. We hear of no action considerable in Scotland, only we meet with prisoners daily as we send parties abroad. One that came yesterday into this town <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that he heard <em>Middleton</em> and some others of the chief are coming in.</p>

<p>Here is a Fleet of Coals ready to go off, most of them are bound for <em>London</em>, but we hear you press <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> there still.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly come forth that long expected translation of the whole book of <reg orig="Psalmes">Psalms</reg> in meter, by <em>Will. Barton</em> Mr. of <em>Arts</em>, diligently compared with the Original, and to be sold by <em>Francis Eglisfield</em>, and <em>Thomas <reg orig="Underhil">Underhill</reg></em> in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>, and by <em>Francis Tyton</em> at the three daggers in <em><reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Also Mr. <em>Richard <reg orig="Baxters">Baxter's</reg></em> <reg orig="Apologie">Apology</reg>, containing an answer to Mr. <em>Blake</em>, to D. <em><reg orig="Kendals">Kendal's</reg></em> digression, to <em>Moulin</em>, to Mr. <em>Eyres</em>, and Mr. <em>Crandon</em>: Wherein is discussed many great Controverted points in Divinity, of <reg orig="Antinomianisme">Antinomianism</reg> <em>&amp;c.</em> Printed for <em>T. Underhill</em> and <em>F. Tyton</em> and sold by <em>I. <reg orig="Nevill">Neville</reg></em> at the <em>Plough</em>, and <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Barber</em>, at the <em>Lamb</em> in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<p>The second part of the <em>Faithful Counsellor</em>, or <em>Marrow of the Law</em> in English by <em>Will. Shepherd</em> Esq. sold by <em>H. Twiford, Nath. Ekins, T. Brewster, I. Platt</em>.</p>

<p>A thin light bay Gelding, with a star in the forehead, and two feathers on both side the Mane, <reg orig="thorow">thorough</reg> <reg orig="pac'd">paced</reg>, of five years of age, lost on Whitsunday at Sir <em>Richard <reg orig="Kingsmiths">Kingsmith's</reg></em> at <em>Maultshanger</em> in <em>Hampshire</em>: Bring word to M. <em>Francis <reg orig="Burges">Burge's</reg></em>, living at M. <em><reg orig="Prescots">Prescott's</reg></em> in <em><reg orig="Windmil">Windmill</reg>-Court</em>, next Butcher-row, without Temple-Bar, and he shall have forty shillings.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>