<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn217">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 217</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> February. 13. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, February. 19. 1653</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 30</i></head>

<p>This day came a Messenger from <em>Holland</em>, servant to Monsieur <em>Beverling</em> now resident in <em>London</em>, who <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that five of the seven Provinces have signed the Articles for a Peace with <em>England</em>; and that the other two Provinces, viz. Gilderland and <em>Groningham</em> the next day also concurred, and thereupon have sent a <reg orig="Plenepotentiary">Plenipotentiary</reg> power to Monsieur Beverling, there Ambassador in <em>England</em> to make a <reg orig="finall">final</reg> confirmation, and that three extraordinary Ambassadors will be here in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in a full confirmation of the whole. Since this, the said Monsieur <em>Beverling</em> hath<pb n="1" /> had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>Take here also a Letter from <em>Holland</em> of the 16. Feb. <em>Stilo novo</em>, which speaks thus. Many arguings have been to and fro, about the business of Peace; yet the interest of our Country; is like at length to <reg orig="prevaile">prevail</reg> against the corruption of the adverse party; and our necessities and losses taken off the high <reg orig="humor">humour</reg> of the common sort; so that peace will be very welcome, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> generally believed that it will be concluded. <em><reg orig="Zeland">Zealand</reg></em>, on whom the brunt of the War hath chiefly <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg>, stands very much inclined if not more <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em><reg orig="Helland">Holland</reg></em>, though at first they were most eager and forward to the Breach. It is foreseen, what difficulties would befall all sorts of people, should we venture the inconveniences of another <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> conflict; for, another <reg orig="yeers">year's</reg> loss of Free Trade and Fishing were a thing not to be endured, the multitude here not being so easily kept in order, under hardships, as in other Countries. It is said that four or five of the Provinces are willing to end the War, and those that are the most considerable; which will draw on the rest in a little time. By the next we hope we may give some more full Account.</p>

<p>This is certain, the English Royalists in this Country do not like the present Transactions, and many of them are upon removing. The whole family of <em>Orange</em> is much discontented, and all their Party. The Princess <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> and her Son the young Prince, are removing to the Town of <em>Breda</em>, there to manifest a dislike by keeping at a distance.</p>

<p><em>Middleton</em> is departed with about 200 Cavaliers, for the Highlands, having five or six small Vessels to transport his followers and necessaries. This State is sending an Extraordinary to his Majesty of <em>France</em>. The thought of Peace makes our Merchants very pleasant, it being in a manner taken for granted.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> appointed for the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Circuits in <em>England</em> for this Winter Assizes.</i></head>

<p>For the Western Circuit, The Lord chief Justice Roll, and<pb n="2" /> Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Glyn</em>. For Berks, Oxford, &amp;c. Lord Chief <em>St. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg></em>, and Mr. Justice Atkins. For Sussex, Kent, &amp;c. Mr Justice Ask, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Nedligate</em>. For the Midland Circuit, Mr. Baron <em>Thorp</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Peapis</em>. For <em>Bucks</em>, &amp;c. Mr-Baron <em>Nicholas</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Conicrs</em>. For the Northern Circuit, Mr. Justice <em>Hayle</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Windham</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Assizes held by the Judges this Winter in the several Counties, in their Circuits, for the Western Circuit.</i></head>

<p>For Hampshire <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 27 Feb. at the Castle at Winchester, Wiltshire, Wednesday 1 <em>March</em> at New Sarum, Dorsetshire, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 6 <em>March</em> at Dorchester. <reg orig="Summersetshire">Somersetshire</reg>, Wednesday 8 <em>March</em> at Chard. City of <reg orig="Exester">Exeter</reg>, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 13 March at the Guild-hall of the City of <reg orig="Excester">Exeter</reg>. Devonshire, the same day, at the <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> Garden near the City of <reg orig="Exester">Exeter</reg>, in the county of Devon. Cornwall, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 20 <em>March</em> at Launceston.</p>

<p>For the Circuit of Bershire, &amp;c. For Bershire, Tuesday 28. <em>Feb</em>. at Kedding, Dorsetshire, Friday 3 <em>March</em> at <em>Oxford</em>, <reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg>, Wednesday 8 <em>March</em> at <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, The City of <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, the same day at the City of <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, <reg orig="Monmothshire">Monmouthshire</reg> <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 13. <em>March</em> at Monmouth, Herefordshire Wednesday 15. <em>March</em> at Hereford, Shropshire, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 20. <em>March</em> at Shrewsbury, Staffordshire Friday 24. <em>March</em> at Stafford. City of <reg orig="Litchfield">Lichfield</reg>, Tuesday 28 <em>March</em> at the City of <reg orig="Litchfield">Lichfield</reg> Worcestershire, Wednesday 29 <em>March</em> at Worcester. City of Worcester the same day at the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> of Worcester.</p>

<head level="3">For the Circuit of Sussex, &amp;c.</head>

<p>Sussex, Thursday 2 <em>March</em> at East Greenstead, Kent, Munday 6 <em>March</em> at Maidstone, Essex, Friday 10 <em>March</em> at Chelmsford Hertfordshire, Wednesday 15 <em>March</em> at the Town of Hertford. Surrey <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> 27 <em>March</em>, at Southwark.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">For the Midland Circuit.</head>

<p>For Northamptonshire, Friday 24 Feb. at the Castle of Northampton, <reg orig="Warwickshirs">Warwickshire</reg>, Tuesday 28 Feb. at Warwick, The City of Coventry, Leicestershire Friday 3 March at Leicester, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Leicester, the same day at the <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Leicester, Derbyshire, Tuesday 7 March at Nottingham Town of Nottingham, the same day at the Town of Nottingham, Lincolnshire, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 13 March at the Castle of Lincoln, Lincolnshire, Rutlandshire, Friday 27 March at Okeham.</p>

<head level="3">For the Circuit of Berks, &amp;c.</head>

<p>For Buckinghamshire, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 27 Feb. at <reg orig="Alisbury">Aylesbury</reg>. Bedfordshire, Wednesday 1 March at the Town of Bedford, <reg orig="Huntingtonshire">Huntingdonshire</reg>, Friday 3 March at the town of Huntington. Cambridgeshire, Monday 6 March at the Castle of Cambridge, Norfolk, Wednesday 8 March at Thetford, Suffolk, <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 13 March at Bury St. Edmunds.</p>

<head level="3">For the Northern Circuit.</head>

<p>For Lancashire, Tuesday 7 March at Lancaster, Yorkshire, Tuesday 24 March at the Castle of York City of York the same day at the Guild-hall of the same City.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Febr. 9.</i></head>

<p>Yesterday a party of twenty five Horse from Rodsew, came over the Ford, and came very near the Castle of Dunbarton, before our Horse there took the alarm; but very seasonably twelve mounted and gave them a very stout charge, and took the Lieutenant who did command the party, and two more, all of them are sorely wounded, the Lieutenant being run through the body, and not like to live: there was another of their party run through the body, who forsook his Horse, and took the River, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought was drowned, not (being seen to come out) and three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before, Colgrain being pot valiant, was <reg orig="vaporing">vapouring</reg> with another of their Officers on the other side of the River, and one of Captain <reg orig="Thomsons">Thomson's</reg> men shot him through the thigh.</p>

<p>Lieutenant Col. Cotnell is this day marched forth hence with 600 Foot, 40 Dragoons, and 100 Horse into the Isle of Leven.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 18. of Feb. 1654. By Letters from <em>Perguan</em> we hear that the Plague is very hot in <em>Barcelona</em>, that many of the chief of that City are fled thereupon, and their admission into some Villages, having brought infection thither, therefore it hath through a great fear into the Country, and those that came out now from that City, are refused entertainment wheresoever they come.</p>

<p>The Marshal de Hocquincourt having left that Country, is come hither; and now gone for <em>Picardy</em> to be again Governor of <em>Peronne</em>, having left the Command of the forces in <em>Rousillon</em>, in the hands of <em>Dom Joseph Marguerit</em>.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>There is the old imposition of the <em>sol per liver</em> set again, upon <reg orig="forraigners">foreigners'</reg> goods that come from <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Countries. One of the Masters of the Requests was commanded this week to depart from this City, and not to return till further order: there is a report that the Regiments of the <reg orig="Guardes">Guards</reg> and the Switzers, and that their number shall be much increased, that so they may be at hand to serve upon any occasion.</p>

<p>One of the Gentlemen belonging to the Duke of <em>Mercorur</em> hath been here, and is sent again to his Lord with all speed, that he may come to Court without delay.</p>

<p>The Governor of St. <em>Menehold</em> finding that the Castle of Vienna not far instant from him, did much annoy him, had therefore made way to get some intelligence in the place, and thereupon sent a party, who came <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the place in the middle of the night; but no sooner were they come, but they were discovered, and those of the Castle shooting upon them with great and small shot, forced them to retire faster <reg orig="then">than</reg> they were come.</p>

<p>The Prince of Conti being come to this City, the great talk is about his <reg orig="Mariage">Marriage</reg>, and that by great a <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> from his new <reg orig="Unckle">Uncle</reg> he shall go to command the French Army in Catalonia: and that the Duke de Candale, who is to marry the other niece shall command the Army in <em>Savoy</em> the next Summer.</p>

<p>From <em>Upsall</em> in Sweden Jan. 11. The absence of the great Chancellor of Sweden was one cause why my Lord Ambassador has for some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> been at a stand. Now things will be put to an issue; and so much the rather, because of the late change which hath fallen out in England, which we hope will prove for the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> of God, and the good of our native Country. It is extraordinary well resented here by the <reg orig="Quee">Queen</reg> and her Servants, who were much pleased, that the Credentials came so soon from his Highness the Lord Protector, to my Lord Ambassador, and the Queen hath received them with all satisfaction.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>From <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>, Although the Emperor did seem at the first to give consent to the relieving and assisting of the Elector of Cullen: yet it hath not produced any greater effect <reg orig="then">than</reg> to send letters to the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> Leopoldus; and the Duke of Lorrain to desire them to forbear using any acts of hostility in the Country of Liege: and appointed Commissioners for the sums of money they are to have upon the surrendering of those places they hold in the Empire, in the mean time several Electors do excuse themselves of paying any part of these monies upon several reasons: especially the Prince Elector, and the Elector of <reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg>: there are yet much business to do at the Diet, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> not like to have any good issue, by reason that the Commissioners from Hungaria are very instant with his Majesty Imperial to come into their Country to be present at the Diet to settle the Affairs of that Nation.</p>

<p>From Cullen the differences are not yet agreed between us and our Elector, who will not relate anything of his high demands, and therefore we are now but in a tottering condition.</p>

<p>The Committee for claims for land in Ireland, taking into consideration some special occasions intervening at Grocers Hall London, the 9th day of this instant <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> of Feb: 1653. (being the day formerly appointed for the Lottery of <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>) and to the end sufficient notice may be given to all the Adventurers for lands in Ireland respectively, have thought fit and ordered, that the first day for drawing of Lots for the<pb n="7" /> several <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg> allotted to the Adventurers, shall be on the Thursday the 23 of Feb: to begin at eight of the clock in the Forenoon of the same day; and all persons concerned therein, are desired to take notice thereof accordingly.</p>

<p><em>William Tibbes</em> Cleric.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg> and clearing of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Debts, <em>&amp;c.</em> sitting at Worcester house in the Stand, being lately informed that divers persons in several counties do abuse the people, by summoning them to certain places for drawing up <reg orig="claimes">claims</reg>, and taking unreasonable Fees for the same, under the pretence of their Order and Authority for so doing; the said Commissioners therefore declare, that they have given no such Authority to <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg>, but leave all people to their own will and <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> for drawing up their claims, and delivering them in either by themselves or others as they shall think fit. And do also give notice to such persons who have thus pretended such authority from them, that they are <reg orig="sencible">sensible</reg> of the wrong done to them and the people, and in due time shall let them understand it.</p>

<p>All Christians may meet at Dr. <em><reg orig="Chamberlains">Chamberlain's</reg></em> in White-<reg orig="Friers">Friars</reg> every third day called Tuesday, from two to four in the afternoon, to learn or teach truth, observing the <reg orig="reer">rear</reg>, 1 Cor. 14. 29. to 33.</p>

<p>One Anne Burch, <reg orig="alis">alias</reg> Neale a Maid, about 16 years of age, born at Liddington in Rutland, she did <reg orig="weare">wear</reg>, in case she hath not changed her Apparel, a <reg orig="darey">dairy</reg> colour, or a sad red colour Cloth <reg orig="Wascot">Waistcoat</reg>, with 3 Laces about the skirts, and 3 up before of each side, brown coloured hair, of a fresh countenance, she went away out of Holborn the 23 of November, 1653. If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> can bring tidings of her to Mrs. Price, at the Tennis Court in Holborn, they shall have 20 shillings for their pains.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday February 15.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris February</em> 21. The last Letters from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> advise us, That one called <em>Dureteste</em> (lately one of the Commissioners for that City in <em>England</em>) having attempted to return home without a pardon from the King (he being excepted of the <em>Amnestia</em>) was arrested near <em>Libourn</em>, and carried prisoner to <em>la Reole</em> where that Parliament sits now, and there being brought to trial, he was condemned to be broken on a Wheel as the manner is, his head to be set on the top of the Tower near the Elm house, and a <reg orig="Piramide">Pyramid</reg> to be erected, his Sentence to be there affixed as a memorial to posterity: His <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> hath bestowed upon the Earl <em>de Navailles</em> the place of <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em><reg orig="Phillipsburgh">Phillipsburg</reg></em>. This week was celebrated the marriage of the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquise</reg> of <em>Baden</em> one of the Princes of the Empire with the Princess <em>Louyssa</em> daughter to the Prince <em>Thomaso</em>, her brother having performed the Ceremony in the absence of the Bridegroom. This week their Majesties with the Cardinal went to see the Fair of <em>St Germains</em>. There hath been some differences in this City between the Jesuits and the rest of the <reg orig="Clergie">Clergy</reg> concerning a <reg orig="Bull">Bill</reg> of the Popes, which doth invest them of more power than they can lawfully demand, or the rest of the Clergy suffer to be with honour. We have received an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from <em>Beffort</em>, whereby we hear that the Earl <em>de la Suze</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of that place finding that his long resistance was but in vain, and that there was no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg> of any relief from the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, is at last come to a composition, and thereupon agreed upon Articles of which you shall have the Sum by the next. The Duke <em>de <reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> is still at his house near <em>Blois</em>, and will by no means come to the Court. The Duke <em>de Beffort</em> is in the same mind; the Cardinal being earnest that he <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> up the reversion of the place of Admiral, which he would give to the Duke of <em>Mercocur</em>. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is still close Prisoner, and there is an overture of a agreement but nothing done yet.</p><pb n="9" />

<p><em>Chester</em>, Feb: 14. We hear from <em>Dublin</em> that the Lord Protector was proclaimed there the 2. instant after a long pause, many Officers absent, and the <reg orig="Herauld">Herald</reg> at arms did officiate in a side black <reg orig="cloack">cloak</reg>. In the North of <em>Ireland</em> he was proclaimed long before. The only work now in agitation, is transplanting the <em>Irish</em> into <em>Connaught</em>: Some ten <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg> were lately <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by the Tories, and had such quarter as those desperate Caitiffs expect themselves, which will make them more wary hereafter not to go about that work without a guard; long will it be before those Vermin will be totally destroyed.</p>

<p><em>Dublin</em>-Castle, Feb: 1. I thank you for yours weekly; we have here little to return, only that Articles have lately been made with Col. <em>Murtogh O Brien</em>, in the behalf of all the Tories in <em>Munster</em>, for their transportation into <em>Flanders</em>, a Copy whereof I send you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>. The Lord Protector hath been proclaimed in <em>Limbrick, Chonmell</em>, and <em>Tredagh</em>, and this day, after a long Pause, in this place; but now the Bells are ringing, Cannons, and small shot roaring, and the acclamations of the people speak <reg orig="alowd">aloud</reg> their satisfaction of the present Government.</p>

<p><i>Articles of Agreement made and concluded on between Major <em>Peter Wallis</em>, and Captain <em>Thomas Coakely</em>, on the one party; and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, in the behalf of himself and party on the other side.</i></p>

<p>1. That Col. <em>Mortagh O Brien</em>, with all such of his party as will adhere unto, and engage with him to be transported into <em>Flanders</em> for the service of the King of <em>Spain</em>, in that Army <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> the Prince of <em>Conde</em> is General, do lay down their arms, with such Stores of ammunition, and such other habiliments of War, without <reg orig="imbezlement">embezzlement</reg>, as is hereafter expressed in this Article, by Wednesday the 25 of this instant <em>January</em>; (<em>viz</em>.) Those of the County of <em>Cork</em> at <em>Myallow</em>, and <em>Mackrompe</em>; those of the County of <em>Kerry, Limbrick, &amp;c</em>. in the respective Counties where now they are, except what is hereafter excepted; to Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em> one Case of Pistols, to every <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg><pb n="10" /> of his party one Case of Pistols, and to all other commissioned Officers their Swords only.</p>

<p>2. That license be granted to the said Col. to transport himself, and as many of his party, as well of the <reg orig="Clergie">Clergy</reg>, as others that do adhere unto him, and will engage with him for the service aforesaid; and also of all others protected persons, with such others that have been in arms, as are willing to engage with the said Col. to be transported as aforesaid, submitting themselves to the trial of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, according to the instructions of the Authority of this Nation; allowing the persons so submitting the benefit of the explanation of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, as is set down and annexed to the Articles made with the Lord <em>Munkery</em>.</p>

<p>3. That the said Col. be allowed Commissions for such numbers as he shall produce at the Waterside, according to the Establishment of the Prince of <reg orig="Condie's">Condi's</reg> Army, and likewise to every private <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> six shilling each man at their going on shipboard, or twelve shillings each man when they arrived in <em>Flanders</em>.</p>

<p>4. That the said Col. do produce at the Waterside at the Harbour of <em>Kingsale</em>, to be shipped in order to their transportation, upon, or before the 14th day of <em>February</em> next ensuing, as many of his party as are now in arms in the County of <em>Cork, Kerry, Limbrick</em>, and <em>Waterford</em>, as do adhere unto him, and will engage with him in the aforesaid service; and also of all such other persons as do adhere unto him, and engage with him as aforesaid.</p>

<p>5. That Free-quarter be allowed the said Col. and all such of his party as do adhere unto him, and engage with him, and lay down their arms as aforesaid, from the time as their so laying down arms, until the time of their Transportation, according to direction from Col. <em>Phair</em>, or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, or of any other <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> authorized thereunto. And the benefit of quarter to be allowed to all such of the Clergy, and other protected People, and such as have formerly been in arms that <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere unto the said Col. and engage with him from the time of their so adhering and engaging as aforesaid, Provided<pb n="11" /> that they, and every of them, content themselves with such ordinary Diet as the Country usually allows themselves.</p>

<p>6. That eight <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time be allowed to rally and draw together all such of his said party now in the County of <em>Cork, Kerry, Limbrick</em>, and <em>Waterford</em>, as do adhere unto him, and will engage with him for the service aforesaid without molestation or prejudice from any Forces or Garrisons, under the pay of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and likewise free quarter to all such of the said party in the respective Counties if they desire it where they now are, and their <reg orig="thorow">thorough</reg> fare from County to County, in order to their laying down of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> as is before appointed; provided the said Colonel and every of the said party forbear all Act and Acts of hostility against the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> their forces and Garrisons; And all persons whatsoever under the protection of the Commonwealth, provided also that the said Col. or any other of his party take not any prey or preys nor offer any other violence to the protected people in the respective Counties after the date of these Articles, and the knowledge thereof communicated unto them: And in case any prey be taken by the said Col. or party after the date of these Articles, before the knowledge thereof be communicated as aforesaid, in that case the prey or preys so taken to be restored to the Owners, all but what is disposed of to the necessary relief of the <reg orig="partie">party</reg> or parties so taking the said prey or preys; the like restitution to be made for any other violence or injury done or committed by any of the said party after the aforesaid date of the said Articles.</p>

<p>7. That the said Col. and all such others of his party as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere unto him, and engage with him, as aforesaid, be freed and acquitted from all personal arrears for debt, or claims of that nature, and from all manner of molestation, for any prey or preys taken, or any Act or Acts done or committed by him, or every of them since the year 1640 but as is excepted and provided also this extend not to the exempting of any of the Goods and Chattels of any of the aforesaid persons so <reg orig="adhearing">adhering</reg> and engaging, as<pb n="12" /> aforesaid from making satisfaction for any just debts for which any of the said persons may be convicted by due course of Law.</p>

<p>8. That the said Col. and all others of his <reg orig="partie">party</reg> as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere unto him, as well the Clergy, as those that have been in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, with such other protected persons as shall so adhere and <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him, as aforesaid, as also all such of the said <reg orig="Cols">Col's</reg>. Party as shall lay down their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, as aforesaid, be <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> and admitted to dispose of their goods and Chattels to their best <reg orig="advantag">advantage</reg> within the aforesaid time of their transportation.</p>

<p>9. That all such of the said <reg orig="Cols">Col's</reg>. party as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere and engage to transport themselves and did not, be forgiven the forfeitures of their bonds to themselves and their sureties: and also that none of the said <reg orig="Cols">Col's</reg>. party are now under his command be admitted to stay in this Nation, or to dispose of themselves without his license.</p>

<p>10. That the said Col. or any of his party so adhering and engaging, as aforesaid, be admitted to recover any of his or their goods left in custody of any protected persons, which said persons have not discovered the said Goods to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next adjacent Garrison before the signing hereof.</p>

<p>11. That the said Col. be admitted to transport himself into <em>Flanders</em>, as aforesaid, with fifteen hundred Irish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and in case the said Col. cannot produce at the Water side the whole number by the time appointed, the said Col. then to be allowed to depute an Officer to stay behind, who shall be <reg orig="quallified">qualified</reg> with power to <reg orig="rallie">rally</reg> and raise so many as may make up the said number, which number so raised, to be transported, as aforesaid, be allowed the benefit of these conditions in all particulars, provided the said Officer or Deputy produce the said number of men at such Ports, and at such times as he shall be thereunto appointed by Col. <em>Phair</em>, or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them after the <unclear><!-- There is just a blank space here, lasting approx. 9 characters --></unclear> of <unclear><!-- a similar blank space, again approx. 9 characters --></unclear> next ensuing, provided also that the said Col. or Officer enter sufficient security to the said Col. <em>Phair</em> or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, that the said Officer, or any such as shall be raised or rallied in order<pb n="13" /> to their transportation, as aforesaid, Act not any thing during before the time of their transportation, to the prejudice of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, their Forces or Garrisons.</p>

<p>12. That the Wives of all such of the said <reg orig="Colls">Col's</reg>. Party be allowed to enjoy the benefit of the Act of Qualification equally with the Wives of others in protection.</p>

<p>13. That all such of the said <reg orig="Colls">Col's</reg>. party to whom the charges of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> may extend, be allowed 16 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time to state their cases in writing, and receive the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of Officers thereupon; and also eight and forty hours after the knowledge of the opinion of the said <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> is communicated unto the party so concerning, to dispose themselves for their own security (if they desire it.)</p>

<p>14. That the Articles be conformed and allowed of by his Excellency the Lord General.</p>

<p>15. That for the performance of these Articles, sufficient Hostages shall be given upon signing hereof.</p>

<p>16. In testimony whereof, we do hereunto interchangeably set our hands and seals, the 12th of January 1653.</p>

<p><i>Signed, sealed and delivered in the presence of us, Tho: Mosse, Fr: Cartret, Nathaniel Child.</i></p> 
<p><i>Mortogh O Brien</i></p> 

<p>Veral Copia.</p>

<p>From <em>Antwerp</em> we hear, that by the last post from <em>Madrid</em> they had intelligence how the Plate Fleet from West-<reg orig="India's">Indies</reg> with great store of silver was arrived at Cadiz, yet not in that quantity as hath been seen in former years; that much about the time of their arrival the Fleet bound for Terra firma had likewise set sail from Cadiz also to sail for the West-<reg orig="Indias">Indies</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday February 17.</i></head>

<p>Dalkeith, Feb. 11. The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> is the greatest part of News here at present; <em>Kenmore</em> with his Body of about 2000 of those wild people, is now at <em>Kildranning</em>, an House of the Earl of <em>Mar's</em> in <em>Murrayland</em>: they have been very quiet of late, and is peace with the 7 Provinces be concluded, they<pb n="14" /> are not like to be very <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>: Most of <em>Wogan's</em> party (now he is gone the way of all flesh) are contriving to get as well out of <em>Scotland</em> as they came into it.</p>

<p>We do daily <reg orig="snapp">snap</reg> divers of the Enemy in small parties; a Lieutenant of Col. <em>Fairfax's</em> Regiment with 12 <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg>, took 4 of <reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg> own Troop, and 8 Horse, and one Lieutenant Rutherford who commanded them, narrowly <reg orig="escap'd">escaped</reg>; <em>Glencairn</em> hath sent out a Proclamation, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Fire and Sword to all those that do not comply with him in sending in their Levies. Mr. <em>Jo. Goodwin's</em> 17 Queries are reprinted at <em>Leith</em>.</p>

<p>On Sunday last 4 of Col. <em><reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg></em> Regiment and 2 of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> going from <em>Drummond</em> Castle for St. <em><reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg></em>, were set upon by about 50 of the remains of Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs'</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> horse, who took 3 of them, killed 2 and the other escaped. There is a considerable party of the Enemy in those parts around <em>Conrie</em> who are very active, since the drawing of the horse Northwards, but upon the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in of the 2 Regiments from England, our horse will be placed so as to meet with them at all turns. Col. <em>Drummond</em> is certainly got to the Enemy with further Instruction from <em>Charles Stuart</em>, from whom he is sent to see in what posture they are, and whether so considerable as to protect him, in case he should come to them this Summer. He tells them, that his Majesty strained hard to send them over a ship with ten thousand arms, which is cast away upon the Coasts of Ireland; though I am apt to think it is the same ship that was driven from the Coasts of <em>Loughaber</em> to <em>Killebeggs</em>. There is nothing come since my last from the North.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday February 18.</i></head>

<p>This week several persons were apprehended in <em>London</em> upon a Plot against the Lord Protector and the present Government, whereupon they have been examined, (but we must forbear the particulars at present) 11 of them were this day sent close prisoners to the Tower, concerning whom more by the next.</p>

<p>From <em>Newcastle</em> the 13 of February. There are yet many ships here laden with coals, and some of other commodities, but by<pb n="15" /> reason of these Easterly winds cannot get out of the <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> over the Barr. We hear by a small Vessel come two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since from Holy Island, that a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> man of war set out from <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> hath brought in two Dutch prizes, the one of 200 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, and the other 150, laden with <unclear>bait</unclear>-Country Goods; also that of late there hath been some <reg orig="Shipwrack">Shipwreck</reg> about these Rocks which lie of that Island.</p>

<p>From <em>Bristow</em> the 15 of January. The high hopes that are conceived (now at length) of a firm peace with <em>Holland</em> have filled all these parts with gladness, in regard of the <reg orig="prevalency">prevalence</reg> of the Dutch to bring the <em>French</em> in with them; howsoever we could with these Western parts better guarded with Men of War, having here suffered most. The common Peoples talk is of a blazing star, which the judicious have thought to be occasioned by a conjunction of <em>Saturn</em> and <em>Venus</em> to be seen very clearly not long since. As for <em>Ireland</em>, the Tories we beat are given in <!--?rep in orig or typo??-->in a List by <em>Morough O <reg orig="Brian">Brien</reg></em>, upon composition to be transported for <em>Flanders</em>, <reg orig="quietnesse">quietness</reg> there would make our trading and their lands much more considerable.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is extant three excellent and pious treatises, viz. 1. The complaint of a sanctified Sinner. 2. The triumph of a true Christian. 3. The great mystery of <reg orig="Godlinesse">Godliness</reg> opened. In sundry Sermons upon the whole 7, 8, and 9 chapters of the Epistle to the <em>Romans</em> wherein that great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> of the doctrine of Election and Reprobation is fully and clearly handled by that <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servant of Jesus Christ Mr. <em>Edward Elton</em>, B. D. and late Preacher of the Word at <em>Mary Magdalen Bermondsey</em> near <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>The tempestuous Soul calmed by Jesus Christ, being the extract of several Sermons preached by <em>Anthony Palmer</em> Pastor of the Church at <em>Bourton</em> on the water in <em><reg orig="Glocester-shire">Gloucestershire</reg></em>. These two are to be sold by <em>Edward Brewster</em> at the <em>Crane</em> in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p>A white Mare and a black <reg orig="Nagg">Nag</reg> lost out of <em><reg orig="Hide-Park">Hyde Park</reg></em> about <reg orig="Candlemasse">Candlemas</reg> last the Mare about 10 or 11 years old, 13 <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> high, and paceth, Flea-bitten about her head, and her back somewhat rising, the Nag black, and about 13 hands high also and <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear>, whosoever shall bring, or give notice of them to Mr. <em><unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear></em>, at the Red <em><reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg></em> in Dairy-lane, shall have 4£ for their pains.</p>

<p>Tuesday last the 14 of Feb. <em>John Twistleton</em> Esq. had his Stable broken open, and 4 large light bay stone horse stolen out with these marks, viz. a white blaze down his face, 3 white feet, and a wenn of the <reg orig="bignesse">bigness</reg> of a <reg orig="Wallnut">Walnut</reg> growing transparent between his eyes, and a black main, and a black tail bobbed. If any shall bring tidings of him to Mr. <em>Smith</em> a Corn Chandler at the ship in Smithfield they shall be well contented for their pains.</p>

<p>Wednesday the 15th day of this present February, A little <reg orig="Christal">Crystal</reg> Box and a <reg orig="Christal">Crystal</reg> cover fixed with <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> and shutting like a watch, was lost in St James Palace or the old Spring Garden, if any will bring it to Mr <em><reg orig="Perryn">Perrin</reg></em> Goldsmith at the golden bottle in Cheapside, or to <em>Ralph Harlow</em> the Porter at Wallingford house next Whitehall shall be well contented for restoring this Box.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>