<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc03">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Diurnall or Occurrences, Issue 3</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="1">OCCURRENCES</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em>. 15. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em> 22. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 15.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> 8. May. General <em>Monk</em> is gone from hence to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, at his coming to this <reg orig="citie">city</reg> here was a great appearance of Officers of the Army, and the Magistrates of the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> went to meet him on horseback in their rich robes, and brought him into the <reg orig="citie">city</reg> in great honour and <reg orig="renowne">renown</reg>, they came up to the great Cross, which was adorned with rich hangings, and there was proclaimed his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector in great state by sound of Trumpet and Drums beating; After this the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Officers had a great dinner which was prepared for them at the charge of the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg>, and the full consummation of this Solemnity concluded in very gallant fireworks at night; General <em>Monk</em> hath also set forth this Declaration following.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3">A DECLARATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander chief of all the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>The Commonwealth of <em>England</em> having used all means of <reg orig="tendernesse">tenderness</reg> and affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody war) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the Liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much Blood and Treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more than their <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> <reg orig="propotion">proportion</reg> with England) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace; Yet divers <reg orig="leud">lewd</reg> persons, broken in their fortunes, and dissolute in their lives, are run into Rebellion, who being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Brethren, <reg orig="Tuitors">Tutors</reg>, Masters, and people among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to Rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in Peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof.</p>

<p>I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, do declare, that all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within twenty days after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned, for any offence, spoil or plunders committed by him or them in this present Rebellion, (the killing of any person in clod blood only excepted.)</p>

<p>And I do Declare, that if any Parents, Brethren, or <reg orig="Tuitors">Tutors</reg>, who have assisted or connived at any of their Sons, Brothers<pb n="2" /> or Pupils now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publication hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers or Pupils, to render themselves and give security, as aforesaid, that then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are hereby freely pardoned; But if otherwise, then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, shall be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion.</p>

<p>And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion, without the knowledge or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth; I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby Declare, That if the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth, to render him or themselves, within twenty <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after Publication hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the said Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned, but if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said Parish or Presbytery, two shillings six pence a day for each Horseman, and ten pence a day for each footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their ordinary Sesse, out of the said parish or presbytery, which the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> is hereby authorized to levy and receive <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, during the time the said persons shall so continue in Rebellion.</p>

<p>And I do likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person or persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into Rebellion, or attempt so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, and safely to deliver him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and fight the said person or persons; and if they shall kill any of the said persons so residing, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive as a reward of their good service, all such<pb n="3" /> Moneys, Goods, Horses, and <reg orig="Cloths">Clothes</reg>, as the said Rebellious persons are possessed of, besides full satisfaction for their pains and <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em> and the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Donald <reg orig="Mac-Donald">McDonald</reg></em> Laird of <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and Major General <em>Dayell</em>;</p>

<p>I do hereby therefore Declare, that what person or persons soever of this Nation (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said <reg orig="principall">principal</reg> contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any English Garrison, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only <reg orig="bee">be</reg> pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but also shall receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of two hundred pounds sterling for every person so <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And lastly, for the encouragement of all peaceable and well-affected people, both English and Scots, I do also hereby Declare, That what <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done to their persons, goods or <reg orig="Geer">Gear</reg>, for their good affection to the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>, the same shall be again repaired out of the Estates of such as have done the <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, or out of the Friends and harbourers of such <reg orig="wrong doers">wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the Parish, <reg orig="Prebsytery">Presbytery</reg>, or Shire where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said Offenders, or give the English Forces such timely notice thereof, that the said offenders may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> apprehended by them.</p>

<p>And I do hereby require all Provosts, <reg orig="Bailiffes">Bailiffs</reg>, and chief Officers of Head burghs, in their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Burghs, to cause these presents to be duly published and posted up, according to the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me, in writing, under his or their hands.</p>

<p><i>Given under my Hand at <em>Dalkeith</em> this 4 day if May 1652.</i></p>

<p>GEORGE MONK</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 16.</head>

<p>An Ordinance came forth by his Highness the Lord Protector, for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act of Parliament for relief of Creditors and <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> Prisoners <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 31. of May instant.</p>

<p>An Ordinance also <reg orig="past">passed</reg> for the relief of poor Creditors in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> in <em>Germany</em> 28 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> is in person<pb n="4" /> here at the <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg>. The Prince Paltsgrave is also come hither and hath had audience, but the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> makes strict propositions to him, for the spreading and increase of the Roman <reg orig="Catholique">Catholic</reg> Religion, and that he should raise a yearly sum of money to be paid to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> towards his <reg orig="domesticke">domestic</reg> <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg>; and further that all things should be performed which were agreed &amp; concluded on in Assemblies touching the affairs of <em>Bohemia</em>.</p>

<p>By Letters out of <em>Flanders</em> thus; we hope now to be eased of that great burden that has been long upon us by reason of the insolentness of the Army commanded by the Duke of <em>Lorraine</em>, and since the imprisonment of the Duke, they have been more <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> before, but now they are to be called away to assist the Spaniard in his war against the French, it is supposed they will be more <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> to the Spanish interest <reg orig="then">than</reg> before.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 17.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Civill">Seville</reg></em> 10 May. The concluding of peace <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> we hope will produce such effects that the English Merchants there shall not suffer so much for the future as they have done in times past, or else that they will be brought to make satisfaction for all the <reg orig="wronges">wrongs</reg> and injuries they have done us for divers <reg orig="yeares">years</reg> past, contrary to the Articles betwixt <em>England</em> and them, and for satisfaction herein, I shall give you some few particulars.</p>

<p>1. The Farmers use to value our goods, and force us to pay what <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> they please.</p>

<p>2. All the Canary Islands are rented by one Farmer, who forceth the English to pay, 2, 3. and 4 times <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> for one and the same goods when they send them from one Island to another to sell them.</p>

<p>3. They <reg orig="vsually">usually</reg> <reg orig="keepe">keep</reg> ships in the Harbours, before they suffer them to discharge their goods after they arrive, and it is long before they will dispatch them when they would depart, and cause the Masters to pay twenty shillings each time for their boats that carry them aboard the ship.</p>

<p>4. They put Prizes upon our provisions and Commodities, and it oftentimes happens that they will not suffer us to sell them but to those of their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>. And by the <reg orig="Brasse">Brass</reg> moneys we have lost 300000. sterling, which we are forced to receive after <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have sold our goods for Plate, so that we <reg orig="loose">lose</reg> our principals by a forced violence and <reg orig="deceipt">deceit</reg>.</p>

<p>5. The Informer hath a third part of any goods confiscated; and the suit is followed at the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> charge, neither are they condemned in any Costs when the sentence goes for the English and the Judges of the Admiralty, <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>, <reg orig="Baylies">Bailies</reg>, and witnesses are oftentimes sharers of honest <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> goods.</p>

<p>Much more of this nature might be related, but let this suffice for the present.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 18.</i></head>

<p>Paris 12. May. The <reg orig="foraigne">foreign</reg> <reg orig="Ambassanors">Ambassadors</reg> here have had a meeting with Card. <em>Mazarine</em> in order to the carrying on of a general peace. The Prince of <em>Conde</em> hath had new Propositions sent to him for an agreement since his <em>effigies</em> were hanged up in this city; and his brother <em>Conti</em>, who is now in great favour, <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> to be an effectual Mediator between his brother and the Court. A small sum of money hath been allotted <em>Charles Stuart</em>, but it was so <reg orig="smal">small</reg> a pittance, that he is like to have occasion to make new addresses for more before he can get out of this country. It is said here that upon the beating up of drums in some of the remote parts of this Nation, many desperate persons that knew not how to subsist came to be listed, and the report goes that they are sent to Scotland.</p>

<p>Amsterdam 13. May. There hath been some discontent in these parts by the house of <em>William</em> of <em>Nassaw</em>, and all that are that way allied and affected. They pretend they knew not of one or two of the Articles of peace till they were concluded and published, (and indeed none were obliged to acquaint, or consult with them about it) <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> conceiving what was done <reg orig="wil">will</reg> conduce to the good and profit of both Commonwealths, we do here and at other places keep strong guards, for that Count <em>William</em> his calling his Army to a general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and some discontented persons who have gone lately to visit the young Prince of <em>Aurange</em> have uttered very high word, yet do they seem rather to proceed from abundance of affection, then judgment, valour, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that may add life, nerves and sinews to a new war.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday May 19.</i></head>

<p>The Messenger returned from <reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. Col. <em>John Lilburn</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he is well and in health in the Castle at <em>Jersey</em>, but the Keeper (as by Law he might) refused to return him back hither upon sight of the first <em>Habeas Corpus</em>.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>A gallant part of our Fleet are gone Northward, to prevent further supplies coming into Scotland to the Enemy, and <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> that coast of <reg orig="Pickerons">Picaroons</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Our next main <reg orig="designe">design</reg>, 'tis thought, will be to help the Venetians against the Great Turk, for that he is the common Enemy of all <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>; and as he is making himself stronger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, so doth he <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself more insolent, &amp; cruel, and hath <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the Venetian Ambassador in close prison, not so much as <reg orig="rendring">rendering</reg> a reason for it, or intending to have any further treaty or capitulation with the Duke of Venice.</p>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> sate in Council at <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg> with the <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear> of the Lords of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Council. Gen. <em>Pen</em> is now with the Fleet.</p>

<p>The summons for <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> another Parliament against the third of September next are already prepared, and in due time <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be issued forth by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>You cannot but by this time understand that which will please you; that (blessed be God) my Lord Ambassador is come to a good conclusion of his <reg orig="busines">business</reg> here: For, when by Letters from <em>England</em> we understood the state of your Treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>, it being in such condition that the affairs in this place could have no reflection upon it, it was then high time for his spirits, and put on the business more than formerly; which took so good effect, that in fourteen days after this beginning we were come to a full agreement; and now there remains nothing but the signing and sealing of the Articles, which I presume will be done upon the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> return hither, she is gone to see her Mother, and to meet with the Prince Royal, her Successor, to confer about the great business of her Resigning of the Government; we look for her to be back again the next week, in the mean time my Lord Ambassador is forced to make a longer stay.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 20.</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector received a Letter from General <em>Monk</em>, whereby he signified, that he was advanced a <reg orig="daies">day's</reg> march beyond <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> towards the Highlanders, and that he doubteth not (by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> assistance) to give a good account of that business in a short time.</p>

<p>Yesterday the Denmark Ambassador had another conference with the Lord Protector, and a Committee of persons of Honour are appointed to capitulate further of the great Affairs of State, betwixt this Commonwealth and the Kingdom of <em>Denmark</em>.</p>

<p>On Thursday last the French Ambassador and his Followers were nobly entertained by the Lord Protector at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</p>

<p>It is resolved, that the next Term shall be kept at the usual place at Westminster, &amp;c.</p>

<p>The last Letters from Upsal say, That the Articles of Peace between that Crown and the Commonwealth of England are <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>, and ready to be signed and sealed. By the next you are like to hear, that her Majesty is returned again to this City, and that the formality of signing the said Articles will be consummated.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for the sale of the Honours, <reg orig="Manours">Manors</reg>, Lands, &amp;c. belonging to the late King and Queen &amp;c. sit again at Worcester House, on Tuesday <em>May</em> 30.</p>

<p><em>Rochel</em> 14. May. We have news that the English Fleet the last week at their <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> on the <reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg> were 150. <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>. Our fears are great here in France; (as our preparations daily manifest) some are of opinion you <reg orig="wil">will</reg> rather revenge an injury done farther off, and steer your course to <em>Ligorn</em>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> fall upon your next neighbours first. That which most amazeth us is, that you impress more men, and put your whole Fleet in so high a warlike posture: We are informed you have <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> mortar-pieces, great numbers of spades, pickaxes, <reg orig="wheel-barrowes">wheelbarrows</reg>, and other things necessary for land-service.</p>

<p><i>Whereas by a late Ordinance concerning the <reg orig="Highwayes">Highways</reg>, no Carts, <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>, &amp;c. are to travel with above five horse a piece: It is provided by the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that the said clause shall not extend to draught horses for Ordnance, Ammunition, &amp;c. but that so many horses may be used for the affairs of the Army as shall be needful.</i></p>

<p>This Week the Packet Boat coming for England from beyond Sea was taken by the <reg orig="out-lying">outlying</reg> Pirates abroad, some of the Passengers English were <reg orig="drown'd">drowned</reg>, and those that were saved were <reg orig="stript">stripped</reg> to the skin, and the next morning, the Masters one woman, and two more, had pieces of broken <reg orig="Sailes">Sails</reg> given them to cover their nakedness, and put into an old <reg orig="Coale">Coal</reg> Boat to shift for themselves.</p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>