<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc168">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 168</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The Audience of the French Ambassador before His Highness the Lord Protector at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>; together with his Speech and Addresses made to his Highness by the said <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, in behalf of his Master the Most Christian King of France; together with some Propositions concerning Peace. With the Proceedings touching the Treaty with the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>. Several Prizes taken at Sea. The raising of men in Scotland by Gen. Middleton, Glencarn, Seafort and Athol, and their moving Westward. Letters from Ireland. And news from several other parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em>, March 22. to <em>Wednesday</em>, March 29. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>March 22</em>.</i></head>

<p>We could tell you this week how far you are like to be eased of the Excises, <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, the <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg> <reg orig="Assesments">Assessments</reg>, and other taxations, but we have not room enough at this time; therefore for <reg orig="brevities">brevity's</reg> sake, take in the first place, the Copy of an Ordinance of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for the Continuation of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, and several other Ordinances of his Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, which in order take as followeth.</p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for <unclear>Continuation of an</unclear> Act of Parliament, intituled, an Act for the Continuation of the Customs, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> 26 of March in the year, 1653.</i></head>

<p>Be it ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That one Act of Parliament, intituled, <i>An Act for the continuation of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 of March, 1653.</i> and all powers and clauses therein contained, be, and are hereby continued, and shall, and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 26 day of March in the year of our Lord, 1658. And be it further ordained, that the Commissioners of the Customs shall not hereafter make repayment of half <reg orig="Subsidie">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported, which have been, or hereafter shall be sold unto, or in the possession of any <reg orig="Shop-keeper">Shopkeeper</reg> or Retailer of the said commodity, or any such goods where the property, form, or nature of the commodity once imported, is any wise altered, mingled, amended or confounded. And be it hereby further ordained, That the Commissioners of the Customs for the time being shall have and receive upon every 20 shillings <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> clear unto the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> upon their account such salary of Poundage as is or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for Regulating the Customs, or any other thereunto authorized by his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, March 23.</head>

<p>This day was published the Ordinance appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, and is to this effect.</p>

<p>Whereas for some time past hitherto, there hath not been any certain course established for the supplying vacant places with able and fit persons to preach the Gospel, by reason whereof not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the rights and titles of Patrons are prejudiced, but many weak, scandalous, popish<pb n="2" />, and ill-affected persons have intruded themselves, or been brought in, to the great grief and trouble of the people of this Nation, for remedy and prevention whereof, It is ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that every person, who shall from and after the 25 of March instant, be presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Lecture in England or Wales, shall, before he be admitted into any such Benefice or Lecture, be judged and approved, by the Persons hereafter named, to be a person, for the Grace of God in him, his holy and unblameable conversation, as also for his knowledge and utterance, able and fit to preach the Gospel; and that after the said 25 of March, no person, but such as shall upon such approbation be admitted by the said persons, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Lecture, having a constant stipend legally annexed and belonging thereunto, or take or receive any such Benefice as aforesaid, or the profits thereof, And be it further ordained, That Francis Rous, Esq. Dr. Thomas Goodwin, Dr. John Owen, Mr. <reg orig="Thankfull">Thankful</reg> Owen, Dr. Arrowsmith, Dr. Tuckney, Dr. Horton, Mr. Joseph <reg orig="Caryl">Carroll</reg>, Mr. Philip Nye, Mr. William Greenhil, Mr. William Strong, Mr. Thomas Manton, Mr. Samuel Slater, Mr. William Cooper, Mr. Stephen Marshal, Mr. John Tombes, Mr. Walter Cradock, Mr. Samuel Faircloth, Mr. Hugh Peters, Mr. Peter Sterry, Mr. Samuel Bamford, Mr. Thomas Valentine of Chaford, Mr. Henry Jessee, Mr. Obadiah Sedgwick, Mr. Nicholas Lockier, Mr. Daniel Dyke, M. James Russel, Mr. Nathaniel Campfield, Robert Tichburn Alderman of London, Mark Hildsley, Thomas Wood, John Sadler, William Goff, Thomas St. Nicholas, William Parker, and Edward Cresset<pb n="3" /> Esquires, be constituted and appointed Commissioners for such approbation and admission as is abovesaid, and the said Commissioners or any five or more of them met together in some certain place in the City of London and Westminster, as his Highness shall appoint, are authorized to judge and take knowledge of the ability and <reg orig="fitnesse">fitness</reg> of any person so presented, and to grant admission to such Benefice or Lecture by an instrument in writing under a common Seal to be appointed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>Provided always, That no person who shall tender himself, or be <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> for approbation as aforesaid, shall be concluded by any Vote of the said Commissioners which shall <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> in the Negative as to his approbation, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> nine or more of the said Commissioners be present at such Vote.</p>

<p>And it is further ordained, That all Patrons of any Benefices that are now void, shall within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> next after the five and twentieth of this instant March, and of any Benefice that shall hereafter be void within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> next after the avoidance of the same, Present unto the said Commissioners, or any five of them, some fit person to be admitted, and for default of such Presentation within that time, the Presentation or that turn shall devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg>, That in case the Patron be disturbed to present unto such Benefice, and thereupon within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the avoidance of such Benefice a <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> be commenced for the recovery of such Presentation, and notice thereof in writing left with the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them or the Register, that then such notice shall be as effectual to prevent the lapse, as where the <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> was heretofore commenced against the Bishop or Ordinary.</p>

<p>And it is further ordained, That during the vacancy of such place by reason of such <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg>, the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them have hereby authority to sequester the fruits and profits thereof for supplying of the place with an able Preacher, by the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, to be nominated and approved of as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And forasmuch as many persons since April 1. last past, have been placed in such Benefices, and <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Lectures, It is hereby ordained, That in case such person shall not before the 24 of June next, obtain approbation and admittance in the manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, then such person or persons as have right thereunto, shall or may present<pb n="4" /> or nominate some other fit and able person to such place.</p>

<p>And in default of such Presentation within two <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the said 24 of June, or within six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> after the place became void, the Presentation for that turn shall likewise devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>And for the better satisfaction of the said Commissioners touching the godly and unblameable conversation of such persons as are to be admitted into any place as aforesaid, It is further declared and ordained, that before any admittance of any person as aforesaid, there shall be brought to the said Commissioners, or any five of them, a Testimonial or Certificate in writing, subscribed with the hands of three persons of known godliness and integrity, whereof one at least to be a Preacher of the Gospel in some constant <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> place, testifying upon their personal knowledge, the holy and good conversation of the person so to be admitted; which said certificate shall be duly <reg orig="Registred">Registered</reg> and filed. And it is also Declared, That the penalty for or in respect of the not subscribing or reading the Articles mentioned in the Act of the 13th year of Queen Elizabeth, intituled, <i>Reformation of Disorders in the Ministers of the Church:</i> or for not producing such Testimonial as in the said Act is required, shall from henceforth cease, and be void.</p>

<head level="3">Friday, March 24.</head>

<p>An Ordinance was published for continuing the Act for laying an imposition upon Coals, towards the building and maintaining ships for the guarding the Seas, to be in force until the 26 of March, 1655.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for passing Custodies for Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance for continuing the Act of impressing of Seamen to be of force until Novemb. 1. 1654.</p>

<p>From Milford Haven, March 18. There is arrived this week from Ireland three Vessels laden with Irish Commodities, and brought over some few passengers; they say little for news from thence, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Country in many parts want people to till the ground, that the Tories, and others of that <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> crew are very near all <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg>, there being <reg orig="onely">only</reg> very small parties remaining on foot, but dare not to stand to any engagement with such parties of ours as are sent to destroy them, and so clear the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> of them, upon the least report that they hear of our men approaching they presently run into the Woods and Bogs where there is little or no access to them. We have been little troubled of late with any <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, one <reg orig="onely">only</reg> was seen the beginning of this week to the westward of the Isle of Lundy; but upon the report<pb n="5" /> made him by a fisherboat, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> appointed to keep these Seas was in pursuit, he immediately went away and left this channel, sailing towards the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end; he hath about 6 guns and 60 men, being a Dutch Vessel, but a singular good <reg orig="sailer">sailor</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> March 25.</head>

<p>From Scarborough March 20, Since that the Fleet of Colliers bound for the Southward hath passed by, there hath not sailed this way many ships, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a few bound for Newcastle, Berwick, and the Frith in Scotland; two days since two Dutch Freebooters were seen about Fylie Bay, and seeing nothing to prey upon, they went about Flamborough into the Bay, and seeing nothing ready to be <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg> up, they sailed into the sea, and were seen this evening hovering about the mouth of Humber.</p>

<p>Leith, March 18. There is no account yet come of the Highlanders great <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be about Wednesday last in Badgenoth, in order to which all their forces are drawn Northwards, where they will arm those that want, and <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to raise Sutherland, <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg> and <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>, and so drain the Country of all the sensible men they can get together, though I suppose when that is done they will not be able to keep them, without coming into the Lowlands, which if they once become more numerous they will attempt.</p>

<p>By another Letter further thus: Seaforth hath raised his number to 700. and the last general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of them all they spake themselves to be 7000 armed, but have no monies, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> are fed with great hopes of sums to come out of Germany, and that the titular Duke of York is to bring from thence an additional supply of men under his conduct, and on this depends the great expectation of <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg> arrival among them. In the interim they march towards our borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p><pb n="6" />

<p><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> morning about three of the clock the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg> with the Dutch letters going from Southwark towards Dover, was <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> and broke open by Thieves within a mile of S. <reg orig="Georges">George's</reg> Church, which they did as supposed upon hopes to find money, but finding none, broke open all the Letters that were in packets, and throwed them on the ground, and turned the man back again.</p>

<p>From Dover thus. We hear of several Prizes lately taken by our fleet, and by private men of War. The archest <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> that belonged to the Brest men of War, was lately taken in the west, and brought into Plymouth. It is a large vessel, and hath very good good guns; she stood not long before she had five foot water in the Hold. As I was writing, a private man of War brought in a Dutch prize, wherein is a good quantity of Wine and other commodities of value. We have many Merchants ships newly gone forth to sea, some for the Canaries, others for <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, and some for other parts.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, March 27.</head>

<p>Monsieur de Neufuille the French <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> attended with several Coaches, was this day brought in his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> own Coach through the City to Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg> house at Westminster; <reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> he is to have audience of his Highness.</p>

<p>Letters from France represent, that the titular King of Scots is very sorry for the taking of Capt Beach, which hath also <reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> the rest of that crew with such fear, that they dare not venture again into the narrow, but are all going to Toulon to serve the King of France. An Order was issuing for banishing Prince Rupert out of France upon the Killing and wounding some of the Marquis of <reg orig="Plessis">Plessis'</reg> men, but is since demurred upon. The <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> army is marched more Northward <reg orig="then">than</reg> before, they say their King <reg orig="wil">will</reg> marry <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> daughter, and that Queen of Sweden will marry the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> son.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, March. 28.</head>

<p>The French Ambassador (of whom we made mention before) had Audience this day by his Highness the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> -house at Whitehall, where stood a Chair of State, and His Highness by it. The Ambassador is a man of eminency in France, having the advantage of a very large Revenue, as an Ornament for his natural endowments, and <reg orig="shews">shows</reg> himself to a true Monsieur, that he made three low Congies to his Highness the Lord Protector at his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up to make his Speech or Oration to him, which was partly congratulatory, wherein he wanted not words to demonstrate the <reg orig="joyes">joys</reg> of his Master, and how happy he apprehends the people to be, that are under so good, so able a Governor; with whom that <i>Most Christian King</i> desireth to enter into League and Confederacy. He therefore in the first place doth desire a Treaty for a free Trade and Commerce, and that acts of hostility may cease, with some other things, which will be yielded to, if it may be done with Honour and Safety to the Nation.</p>

<p>We should here give you the copies of several Letters from Scotland; but wanting room, we must leave out the circumstances (which will stuff up two sheets, and <reg orig="onely">only</reg> fall upon the chief substance of them all, viz.</p>

<p>The Earl of Glencarn, the Lord of Kenmore, Major General Middleton, the Lord Seafort, the Earl of Athol, and the rest, have raised whole Shires, or forced them to leave their habitations; yet we hear they want Arms for the one half of their men, and Saddles for very many of their horses, and their horses also want growth. They fancy to themselves great matters, viz. That a great supply both of men and money is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of Germany, That their titular King will be suddenly in Scotland to head their Army, and that the titular Duke of York will be there also. They press on Westward, although for the present they are able to do little except to rob and plunder. That which makes us most of all admire, is, why Middleton, Monro, and others, which have the repute of knowing men, and good <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, should hazard themselves upon this account, except there be more in <reg orig="then">than</reg> we yet see, or can find out at present.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>