<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn230">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 230</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, May. 1. to <em>Monday</em>, May. 8. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg></head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> May. 1.</head>

<p>This day from <em>Dalkieth</em>, April 27. 1654. Here is yet no News from Col. <em>Morgan</em>. These parts are now more quiet than formerly, and certainly exemplary Justice upon some, and sending others of the Rebels to <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, will something tame these <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> people. Yesterday Captain <em><reg orig="Malcombe">Malcolm</reg> Rogers</em>, who was Agent between <em>Charles Stuart</em> and <em>Glencarne</em>, was executed at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, being <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, found guilty, and condemned by a Court Marshal for a Spy. He confessed that he killed one of our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> (pretending himself to be a Merchant) between <em>Christorphin</em> and <em>Edinburgh</em>.</p>

<p><em>Leith 25 April 1654</em>. There hath been little happened since General<pb n="1" /> <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> arrival here, Col. <em>Morgan</em> with his Brigade, lieth still at <em>Dingwall</em>, and the Enemy under <em>Middleton</em> in <em>Sutherland</em> most of their forces being lately drawn from all parts towards the North; so that there are not so many <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> parties in the Lowlands as formerly, only some few in <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em> and <em>Galloway</em>. A party of about thirty (which are under the English Capt. Lieut. to <em>Kenmore</em>, came about four days since so Provost <em><reg orig="Marburnies">Marburnie's</reg></em> house near <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em>, which they burnt, and many goods. The Provost got to a little old Tower, which himself with half a dozen more held out against them. The Tories endeavouring to storm it, they killed two English, and two more, and so secured themselves.</p>

<p>From <em>Dublin, April</em> 15. The General Council hath proceeded so far, as to resolve to cast lots who shall be in each province. The General Officers are fallen in <em>Munster</em>. A Letter owning the Government of the Lord Protector is also signed unanimously, and to be sent by Officers of quality. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> feared the Lands will fall short of satisfying the whole Arrears, and therefore the standing Army who have Arrears due since <em>June</em>, 1649. are content to take but two thirds at present, leaving the other as a pawn for their Brethren who have Arrears due before 1649 until either more can be found upon an exact survey (for as yet we compute only by the <reg orig="grosse">gross</reg>) or that more be got from <em>England</em>, and then take in their pawn again.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The ancient Proceedings in the Law further Vindicated to be just, &amp;c. <em>part 2</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>For preservation of many debts from to sing by <reg orig="mis-understanding">misunderstanding</reg>, and partly by the nicety of the exposition of the Statute of Limitations.</i></head>

<p>Whereas a good Law was made in the time of the reign of <em>James</em> late King of <em>England</em>, for the avoiding of divers frivolous <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> without specialty (which above six years after the debt or demand hath <reg orig="accrewed">accrued</reg>, have been brought and prosecuted for debts and demands satisfied before the <reg orig="commensing">commencing</reg> of the same, and sundry persons thereby compelled to make further satisfaction, or composition of such debt or demand: And whereas also of late various opinions have been about the interpretation or exposition of that Statute, or Law;<pb n="2" /> some holding opinion, that an action ought to be <reg orig="commensed">commenced</reg> by an original Writ, bill or plaint only, and that original proceeding by Writs original issuing out of the Chancery, or bills, or plaints in Courts of records and none other, and that the saving of any Action, Debt, or Demand from losing, for not proceeding according to that Statute, ought, only to be upon such original <reg orig="proceding">proceeding</reg>: And others have been of opinion that Writs of <em>Latitat</em>, Bills of <em>Midds</em>. and such other Writs have been sufficient for so saving such Actions and demands; but with this, that the prosecution for the same must be upon these Writs and none other.</p>

<p>And many other (whose advice hath been adjudged, not consonant or agreeable to the Letter of that Statute) have been of opinion, that <reg orig="commensing">commencing</reg> of any Action, or <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> in the Chancery or any other Court, or demand of the same within six years next after the debt or demand hath <reg orig="accrewed">accrued</reg>, or <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> hath been of sufficiency for the preservation of such debt, or demand; upon which last opinion very many have depended, and many others (who have had multitudes of just and due debts and demands owing and due to them without specialty, have not been of ability to <reg orig="commense">commence</reg> <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> (by reason of the great charge thereof) within those six years for most part of the same, by which means many just debts and demands have been totally lost by honest Creditors, and they thereby utterly undone: And their unreasonable <reg orig="Debitors">Debtors</reg> (after those six years expired) becoming of ability to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the same, or being so before, and concealing the same (till the expiration of those six years) have met such their Creditors in their poverties, and laughed at, and jeered them to their faces, and have not paid, or satisfied to them <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> for the same, or made them any promise in that behalf, but have utterly refused so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>: And many others have <reg orig="commensed">commenced</reg> and prosecuted very many <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> (within the years mentioned in that Statute) against multitudes to the <reg orig="Utlawry">Outlawry</reg>, and some to further proceedings, and been at great change thereabouts, some to their further undoing, most of those so prosecuted against continuing and dying <reg orig="insolvant">insolvent</reg>; whereby much good money hath been thrown away after bad,<pb n="3" /> and many Courts of this Nation perplexed and troubled with multitudes of <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> in vain.</p>

<p><i>For Remedy whereof, and saving to the People the Debts and Demands which so have been, or may be lost, It is proposed, to be desired, that it may be Ordained, or a Law be made.</i></p>

<p>That any person or persons, Creditor or Creditors, may at any time (within 12 months next ensuing, or within 6 years after the cause of any Action or <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> shall <reg orig="accrew">accrue</reg>, arise or happen to, or for him, her, or them,) cause an action, bill, plaint, or Declaration (as much cause do, or shall require) to be drawn for any Debt or Demand, (which hath been, is, or, shall be due, or owing to him, her, or them, without specialty) and deliver, or cause a true Copy in writing of the same to be delivered to him, her, or them, which <reg orig="doe">do</reg> or shall owe such Debt, or be liable to, or for such Demand; or leave such Copy at his, her, or their Dwelling, or Habitation, or last place of abode, with some there, (if any be) with a Note, or Writing, requiring him, her, or them, to give an Answer, Confession or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg>, at some Place certain, within 5 miles next to the place, where such Copy be, or shall be so delivered or left.</p>

<p>And that if such person, or persons, to, or for whom such Copy, Note, or Writing be, or shall be delivered, or left, do not, or shall not at such place before-mentioned deliver to, or leave for such person or persons, by whom, or by whole direction, such Copy be, or shall be delivered, or left a Confession, Answer, or <reg orig="Denyal">Denial</reg> to the same in writing (signifying whether or not the matter in such Copy, or any part thereof, and how much were, be, or shall be true) within 8 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after such Copy be, or shall be so delivered, or left, then may he, she, or they, (by, or by whole direction such Copy be, or shall be so delivered, or left) bring, or commerise and prosecute, his, her, or their Action, or <reg orig="Suite">Suit</reg>, for, or concerning the same Matter in, or to be in such Action, Bill, Plaint, Declaration or Copy, and proceed upon the same at any time, and in any Court, and the same be good and available in Law, to all intents and purposes, for the recovery and obtaining of the Debts or Demands as be, or shall be in such<pb n="4" /> Action, Bill, Plaint, or Declaration. <i>The residue of this is to come out with the <unclear>electoral part at</unclear> the next, there being not place sufficient for it here.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 2.</i></head> 

<p>This day came forth this following Proclamation.</p>

<head level="3">BY THE LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<p><i>A Proclamation by his Highness, concerning a Cessation of all acts of hostility between the Commonwealth of England, and that of the United Provinces, and their respective People, and the restitution of all things taken and seized upon by either party, after the 4th of this instant <em>May</em>.</i></p> 

<p><em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging: Whereas the Commissioners appointed by us to Treat with the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the United Provinces, and the said Ambassadors, by way of Explanation of the third of those Articles of Peace, lately concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Netherlands, and for removing all questions and differences which may arise thence from, have agreed and concluded the following article, viz. [That whereas in the third of those Articles of Peace, Union and confederation made, established, and promulged between the <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Lords the States General of the United provinces, it is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges and Damages, which either party hath sustained by the other since the 18 &amp; 28 of May, in the year 1652. shall be taken away and forgotten, in such manner as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other, for, or upon occasion of any the aforesaid Injuries, Charges, and Damages, but that there <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> a present abolition of all and every of them until this present day. And all actions for the same shall be held and reputed void and null, excepting such depredations as shall be committed by either side in these Seas after the space of 12 days, and in all other places on this side the Cape St. <em>Vincent</em>, after 6 weeks, and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> Sea, and to the <em>Equinoctial</em> Line after 10 weeks, and beyond the Equinoctial Line, after the space of 8 Months, or <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places.] And whereas certain questions may possibly arise about the<pb n="5" /> fore rehearsed words, which may <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> occasion of debates and disputes, the said Lord Protector and the said States General, to the end all manner of <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> and difference may be removed, which might arise by reason of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the aforesaid Article contained, Have unanimously accorded and agreed, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> by these presents publish an declare to all and singular their People and Subjects respectively. That immediately after publication of the Treaty of Peace, which is already done, all Acts of hostility shall immediately cease in all places expressed in the said Article, and in all others wheresoever. And that all depredations, damages, and injuries which shall be done or committed by one party against the other, after the fourth day of this instant <em>May</em>, in all places whatever, mentioned in the foresaid Article, or elsewhere, as well on this side the Line as beyond, shall be accounted for. And all things taken or seized after the abovesaid fourth of <em>May</em>, shall be restored without any form of <reg orig="Processe">Process</reg>, as also damages growing by occasion thereof. And to the end this Agreement and Article may be better known, both parties shall publish the same within their respective Territories and Dominions, and straitly charge and command as well their ships of War, as others, whether in Port, or at Sea to observe the same.</p>

<p>Wherefore we having considered what is agreed as aforesaid, have confirmed and ratified, as we <reg orig="doe">do</reg> confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same by these presents, which we have caused to be published, that all persons concerned therein may take notice thereof. And we <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby straitly charge and require all ships of War, and others, either belonging to the State, or to any particular persons set forth upon private Commissions, or otherwise to observe the said agreement. And to the end none may pretend ignorance herein. The Commissioners of the admiralty are hereby required to give effectual notice hereof to all the ships of this State, either at Sea or in Port, within these Dominions or elsewhere. And the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty are also by virtue of these Presents, forthwith to call in upon their several securities given in that Court, all such ships as have been set forth upon private<pb n="6" /> Commissions against the united Provinces, or the People thereof. Given at <em>Whitehall</em> this first of <em>May</em> in the year 1654:</p>

<p><i>In <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> whereof as well the Lords Council of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as the Ambassadors extraordinary of the States General have signed these Presents with their own hands. Done At <em>Westminster</em> the 28 of <em>April</em>, old style, in the year 1654.</i></p>

<p>H. <reg orig="Lawwrence">Lawrence</reg> <em>Pres</em>. H. Beverning <unclear>Kt</unclear>.</p> 
<p>Gilb. Pickering. Wil. <unclear>Nieupoort</unclear>.</p>
<p>E. Montague. Alan P. <unclear>Tongestall</unclear>.</p>
<p>Walt. Strickland.</p>

<p>The Articles of Peace between <em>Holland</em> and us, being now published at large, we will <reg orig="referr">refer</reg> you to the original printed by order of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>There is also another Copy of the Articles published, translated out of a Dutch copy, wherein there is one grand Omission in the 12th Article, which is the Reader is desired to take notice of, <em>viz.</em> After the words, <i>That they may trade in any Goods or Commodities that they please, and to Import and Export the same as they please,</i> These words are left out, <i>And saving <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> all and singular the Laws and Ordinances of either Commonwealth respectively.</i></p>

<p><i>To his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></p>

<p><i>The humble Representation of the Justices of the Peace, chief Officers of Corporations, Ministers of the Gospel of the County of <em>Salop</em>, and of the Grand Jury at the Assizes held at Salop the 20 of March, in the year 1653.</i></p>

<p><i>Humbly <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg></i></p>

<p>That we cannot but with all <reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> of heart call to remembrance the late eminent actings of the Providence of God among us, in his Ordering our Wars, and Ordaining our Peace for us; And that after such variety of changes, which have passed over us, and with them so many fears, which have so deeply sate upon the hearts of many of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people. We have such assured hopes of a settlement of these Nations in Truth and <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg>, by the exercise of the declared Government; wherein consisting the present support of our Religion,<pb n="7" /> and Laws. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> cannot but acknowledge it as a great Mercy of God, that so suitable a Remedy should be so suddenly <reg orig="applyed">applied</reg> to our growing Maladies; and that our hopes after many years patient attendance upon other Instruments (when almost swallowed up in the multitude of our too just fears) are now revived, and recovered from so <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> a condition, by the raising up of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in this juncture of time, and affairs, so seasonably to be our Ruler, who have been so successfully our Leader, God having already put upon you as much of the Honour of our Peace, as men of the hazard of our wars, and we trust farther about to honour you (and you Him) with doing as much at the Helm of our Government, as in the Head of our Armies; In bringing to effect those great things, for which the Faithful in these Nations have from the beginning of our troubles continually contended with God by earnest prayer, and long with their <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> vast <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of blood, and treasure; Your Self being made the Steward for laying out a far greater part thereof than any other, that best knowing the price, you might best value the purchase, and be most tender of any new <reg orig="intrenchments">entrenchments</reg> upon those precious concernments, the Redemption whereof has cost so dear.</p>

<p>We have very strong <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg>, Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath already under consideration from our common good, more than probably we know well how to request: We shall therefore in general commend only to your best of care those two comprehensive Interests, Religion, and Justice; The two great Ordinances of God, for the due exercise of the one, and execution of the other, Magistracy and <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, together with the fruitful Nurseries of both these (as well as <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Ornaments to the Nations) our Universities, and <reg orig="Innes">Inns</reg> of Court. In your <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> pursuance of which so <reg orig="publick">public</reg> concernments, the faithful in these Nations will follow you with their prayers, the Lord here them for you, and follow you with good: And we among the thousands of our <em>Israel</em> who make the like Addresses to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, faithfully serve you, and with you our Generation in our respective stations, who have subscribed our Names.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday May 3.</i></head>

<p>Paris the 6 of May, 1654. By the last Letters from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> we hear, that two small Biscaya <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> which used to haunt about our River, and had taken divers Barks going and coming to us, fearing a storm, ventured to come too <reg orig="farr">far</reg> in, and having sent some men on shore to steal Sheep, the Country took the <reg orig="alarum">alarm</reg>, thereupon they gathered in a competent number, and forced the Thieves to leave their prize; and being close pursued, forced them to swim aboard to save their lives, and word being sent to <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, there came down two small vessels well manned and armed, who having secured the Bar all the night to prevent the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> escape, set upon them early in the morning, and after some little dispute they were taken, the men being all sent prisoners to the Castle <em>de Buch</em>, and the vessels carried up to the City, although the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, his Arms have been defaced from his house in this City, although the Pr. Of <em>Conti</em> his brother did use all means possible to prevent the same, but could no way prevail; there is a great falling out between <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his <reg orig="Cosin">Cousin</reg> <em>Rupert</em>, upon the selling of the Guns belonging to the <em>Swallow</em>, and they are come to very high words about it, and though some have endeavoured to make them friends, it cannot yet be brought about. The new Italian <reg orig="Comedie">Comedy</reg> doth so much take the <reg orig="Courtiers">Courtiers'</reg> minds, that they can hardly be satisfied thereof, so greedy they are of it, insomuch that they make it a good part of their <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>, here is a great want of moneys, insomuch that the chief work at Court is to find out some <reg orig="monys">moneys</reg>, by reason that the field expedition goeth on but slowly, and the Spaniard is like to be out with his forces long before us. Their Majesties with the King's Brother, and the Cardinal, went upon Tuesday the 5th instant with many Nobles to <em><reg orig="Fontainbleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em>, where they are to remain for a time: we hear that the King is to go to <em>Rheims</em> by the latter end of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> to his consecration, and that from thence he will go into <em><reg orig="Picardie">Picardy</reg></em>, and take a view of his Armies, others believe he will return from thence to this City. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> hath been visited by the Duke his brother in the Castle of <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em>, where he still remaineth a close prisoner,<pb n="9" /> and little hopes of any <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>. The Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> is still at his house near <em>Blois</em>, and intends to come to Court notwithstanding all their <reg orig="sollicitations">solicitations</reg>: The Commissioners for the Protestants have had at last an answer to their demands, which is very plausible, and full of gallant language, but when it cometh to the execution, as to that point which concerneth their privileges, there will the reality of it appear.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. From <em>Naples</em>, There hath been a general muster here of all the new Levies, which are far short of what was expected, there being not above twenty two Companies, the Duke <em>del Sesto</em> was there as their General, there hath been lately cast a great number of <reg orig="brasse">brass</reg> pieces of Ordnance, whereof one part is to be sent into <em>Catalonia</em>, and the rest to be put into some of our Castles. Our old Archbishop Cardinal <em>Filomarini</em> hath again received a command not only to depart the City, but likewise to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> out of the Kingdom, which is found so much the more strange, that our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> at his coming, that he ought not to fear <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> during his Government. From <em>Rome</em>, The Lady <em>Lucretia Barbarina</em>, contracted to the Duke of <em>Modena</em>, being come to take her leave of the <em>Pope</em>, who presented her with a <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of Diamonds, worth 15 hundred pounds sterling, went out of the City with a very great number of followers among others were the Cardinals <em>Barberini</em> her Kinsmen, with the Cardinals <em>Collona</em> and <em>de Este</em>, who having brought her on her way about three miles left the Cardinal her Brother to bring her to her intended Husband, who is to meet her at <em>Lorretto</em>, and there the Nuptials are to be consummated by the Cardinal <em>Facchinet</em>. From <em>Venice</em>, There is no further news from <em>Dalmatia</em> but the confirmation of that sad disaster happened to the General <em>Delfino</em> in that design he had against <em>Clim</em>, which hath proved so fatal to those of our side. The <em>Bashaw</em> is now on his way to <em>Constantinople</em>, and doth carry with him all the prisoners, which are near one thousand, and intends to present them to the great Turk as a great <reg orig="Trophie">Trophy</reg>, and a badge of his great victory upon the Christians. From <em>Milan</em>, News being come to our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of the arrival of some of the new Levies, thereupon he hath<pb n="10" /> sent some Officers, who are to bring them to their quarters, and provide them with necessaries for their <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, there are likewise more forces arrived from <em>Germany</em> and the <em><unclear><reg orig="Grisons">Grison's</reg></unclear></em> Country. Moreover the last Letters from <em>Naples</em> assure us, That the men lately raised there for us will soon be here, the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> having given order that forthwith they be shipped and sent hither, in the mean time our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> with his Lady is going upon some certain journey of Devotion to <em><reg orig="Montecarllo">Montecarlo</reg></em>. From <em>Genoa</em>, Besides the ships cast away by storm mentioned the last week, there are yet more we hear are cast away about <em>Scicilia</em>, who were laden with rich goods, whereof we hear one to be English, and the other Dutch, which losses are fallen very heavily upon some of our Merchants, the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> being valued to above one million of gold: The Waters likewise have done much harm in the plain Country, many Rivers have overflown their <reg orig="Bancks">Banks</reg>, and done very much harm. From <em>Turin</em>, The Marshal <em>de Grancey</em> having used all care possible to put his Army in a good condition, which according to the List which we have seen is to be of 330 Companies, and 120 <reg orig="Troopes">Troops</reg> of Horse, besides the 3 thousand Irish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> who are quartered in the Province of <em>Daufine</em>, with the like number of French <reg orig="wich">which</reg> are appointed for the recruiting of divers Regiments; whereof the Officers have lately received moneys at <em><reg orig="Lions">Lyons</reg></em>, for the putting of the same in execution, besides the Duke of <em>Savoy</em> his forces, and the thousand men more which are to be levied for the recruiting of them; all these <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together will make an Army considerable, and so strong, that we shall not fear much the high threats of the Enemy: There hath been a Proclamation made through all the quarters, <reg orig="injoyning">enjoining</reg> all Officers, and then are to march in the field as soon as the train of Artillery is ready.</p>

<p><em>Texel</em> April 25. Five men of War are ready to fall towards <em>Brazil</em>, and three others to <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> towards our Freebooters to call them in, Here is a gallant Fleet of Merchant ships of about <unclear><!-- approx. half a line --></unclear> <em>Spain</em> and other places.</p><pb n="11" />

<p>The 22 instant those <em>Galliots</em> that went to Sea from hence the day before, were driven in again by three English Freebooters, who took one of them. The 23 in the morning a fleet of our Merchant ships and men of War went to Sea.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em>, March 31. My Lord Ambassador presses very earnestly to have conclusion of his long attendance, and he had audience both <reg orig="to day">today</reg> and yesterday. The Queen seems now to be in good earnest to lay down her Crown. She did discharge last week most of all her Servants and Retinue, and hath reserved to <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> a very <reg orig="thinn">thin</reg> Court. This is a mystery we yet understand not. She professes here desires of Solitude and Retirement; and some others say, The Debts grew so high, that she was, as it were, forced hereunto. But whether any other secret thing is couched under it, Time will discover.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday May 4.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 9th of <em>May</em>. The fourth instant <em>Dom Francisco Cotinbo</em> Portugal Ambassador, had audience of the King, to whom he made a relation of a great victory which the <em>Portugal</em> forces had obtained in <em>Brazil</em> against the <em>Hollanders</em>, how they had taken the <em>Recif</em>, and other places yet held by the <em>Hollanders</em>; the same day the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <em>Palavicini</em>, who is come hither as a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister from the State of <em>Genoa</em>, being brought into the Court by the Earl <em>Bruston</em>, had likewise audience of his Majesty. The last news from <em>Flanders</em> advise us, that <em>la Bassee</em> is well provided with men, and other warlike materials fit for their defence, and do not fear much the <em>Lorrain</em> forces, although they quarter but 3 miles from that Town. The discontents are still very great in this City, there being daily private meetings, notwithstanding they are so strictly forbidden; this week were found several papers affixed to the corners of streets, with this Title, <i>To the good Subjects, and true servants of his Majesty</i>, the <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> being thus, That they were not to hope for any peace, whilst that <em>Mazarin</em>, <em>le Tellier</em>, and <em>Servient</em> did bear much sway, and some four days since there was an assembly of about 400. who in the night went through the streets, crying, <i>No Mazarin, no Tellier, nor Servient</i>, and the Provost with his guard come to suppress them, they <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> fell to blows, there being divers slain and <pb n="12" /> wounded on both sides: the last week was seen over this City a Comet, the tail been turned towards the North, which by many is taken as a portender of greater miseries than any we have yet seen; in the meantime <em>Dom Joseph de Marguerit</em>, chief Commander for <em>Roussillon</em>, hath received Order to depart speedily, and to return into that Province, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> credibly reported, that the Marshal <em>d' Hocquincourt </em>shall again command those forces in <em>Roussillon</em>, as <reg orig="Leiut">Lieut.</reg> Gen. under the Pr. Of <em>Conti</em>. We hear also that the Duke <em>de Guise</em> is to depart from hence to <em>Toulon</em>, and so to prosecute his design, which hath been driven by him these many <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, and the <em>Marq; du Plessis Bellieure</em> is to be his <reg orig="Leiut">Lieut.</reg> Gen. It is not long since that the Duke <em>d' Espernon</em> making <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> for the recovering of one hundred and fifty thousand livers, which he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he hath disbursed for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, it was answered him, that the Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em> being out of purse many millions disbursed for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> use, he was to be satisfied in the first place; and thereupon the Cardinal having made a motion about the marriage of the Duke of <em>Candale</em> with one of his Nieces, the said Duke <em>d' Espernon</em> replied, He desired some time to be advised therein, to whom the Cardinal <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg>, That he would likewise take time never to speak to him any more, that he kept his Kinswoman for a greater match, and the like lofty language, whereupon the business was quite broken off, but since I hear it is renewed again: We are here still led along with vain hopes of peace, which is of no other use than to make the people part with their money more freely. We hear from <reg orig="Barcelon">Barcelona</reg>, that <em>Dom John d' Austria</em>, who was <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> from thence to go to <em>Madrid</em>, had been countermanded, and returned to that City, having had express order to <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> all the moneys that are in the Treasury of <em>Montserrat</em>, and to bring it to <em>Barcelona</em>; from whence he hath lately sent a circular press command to all the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> to live peaceably, and after an exact discipline, and to such as shall be disorderly the Officers to punish them, and moreover giveth leave to the people in case they receive any wrong, to stand upon their own defence, and seek to preserve their lives and estates, and of their families, to their uttermost power.</p><pb n="13" />

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday May 5, 6.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Allicant April 10 stilo nova</em>. As for news in these parts, The <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg> who intended to have gone to <em>Madrid</em>, being forbidden by an order from the King to advance further, is now expecting a fair wind to return home, as also (we hear) he at <em>Madrid</em> is to go home likewise, there are extraordinary preparations in hand for Sea and Land service in <em>Catalonia</em>, as it is thought, and in the <reg orig="Dutchie">Duchy</reg> of <em>Milan</em>: <em>Dom Juan de Austria</em> is now on his way back for <em>Catalonia</em>, and hath with him 300 pieces of Eight Rialls plate, with bills of exchange for a greater sum, the Count <em>de Ognate</em>, late <reg orig="Vice-king">Vice King</reg> of <em>Naples</em> is made President of the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> for <em>Italy</em>; and a small <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> come from <em>West-Indies</em> with the two Plate Fleets adviseth, That he had left them on their way sailing both in <reg orig="Companie">Company</reg>, and that they make account to be at <em>Cadis</em> about the middle of <em>June</em>, and were very rich. The Plague being now quite ceased at <em>Barcelona</em>, there will be Proclamation made thereof, that so the neighbouring Countries may no more forbear from coming thither. From <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em> <em>May</em> 9, The 4th instant about 4 in the afternoon the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em> went out of this City in his Coach, and some 40 more followed him, most with 6 horses, to meet the Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em> three miles from hence upon the way to <em>Louuain</em>, and so both their <reg orig="Highnesse">Highnesses</reg> <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> this City together about eight of the Clock, and the said Duke with his two Sons were brought into the Palace where they have the chief lodgings, and are tended and served with all the honours and the state that can be. The 6th <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> here the Lord <em>Francis Verrelien</em>, Baron <em>de Genes</em>, who for the space of above <reg orig="fourty">forty</reg> years had served his <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Maj. in divers honourable <reg orig="imployments">employments</reg> both Politick and Military, wherefore the Country is very much grieved for his death.</p>

<p>We had from <em>Scotland</em> by several Letters, as followeth. <reg orig="Innernesses">Inverness</reg> April 19. The Enemy remains still in <em>Southerland</em> and <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, there is great clashing among their Grandees; <em>Glencairn</em> and Sir <em>George Monro</em> fought a duel, and Sir <em>George</em> his right hand was almost cut off, the other was wounded in the head: Two days after the Lord <em>Athol</em> and <em>Glengarry</em><pb n="14" /> appointed field, but it was taken up by the rest of the Officers, the quarrel begun about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> in place: There was also a falling out betwixt Forbes, Kenmore, and <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>: <em>Middleton</em> hath sent <em>Glengarry</em> with 500 foot into the West, its supposed to force the people there and in the Western Islands to rise, for the <em>Loughabrians</em> refuse to rise until they receive command from <em>Argyle</em>, or his Son <em>Lorn</em>; Col. <em>Morgan</em> marched to <em>Tain</em>, and saw the Enemy but could not come at them for want of Boats, the water being broad and very impetuous, he is now come back to <em>Dingwell</em> to quarter. <em>Middleton</em> was very angry with <em>Glencairn</em> and the rest for marching into <em>Southerland</em> without orders, for he would have had them stayed in <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> to have kept open the <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, which they durst not <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, for fear of the Horse and Foot (from this Garrison) falling into their quarters.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> April 25.</em> Intelligence was brought from the North on <em>Saturday</em> last, and met General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> at <em>Dalkeith</em>, that Middleton had tired out <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> and <em>Sutherland</em> and himself too, and was making his way through the Hills, places supposed <reg orig="unpassable">impassable</reg>, to avoid engaging us, Wherefore <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> that has fought out opportunities for that purpose; is like to be disappointed. The quarrel between <em>Glencairn</em> and <em><reg orig="Monro">Monroe</reg></em> (which you had particulars of in the last) has <reg orig="occasiond">occasioned</reg> further difference amongst them, so that many of them are at Daggers drawing <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>. The name of General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> is very formidable to them, who is now making all possible preparations to visit them.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith April 25</em>. Things are very quiet in these parts, <em>Middleton</em> and <em>Morgan</em> are yet in the same posture in the North, <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> numbers <reg orig="doe">do</reg> rather decrease than increase, many daily <reg orig="goe">go</reg> from him as others are flocking to him, and amongst the rest the <em>Loughabrians</em>. The Lord <em>Craighall</em> one of the Judges died at <em>Edinburgh</em> this day.</p>

<p>From <em>Cowes</em> in the Isle of <em>Wight</em> May 4. A Bark being come hither out of <em>France</em>, advises, That in her way homewards she met two of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, who near the <em>Conquet</em> had met about 10 sail of small <em>French</em> ships, and had taken 5 of them, and were<pb n="15" /> in pursuit of the rest, being about 2 leagues from them, and very likely to take them. The Brest <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> are very rife abroad, and have of late taken an English ship bound home from <em><unclear>Morlack</unclear></em>, laden with <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> going for <em>London</em>. Yesterday our Fleet was under sail in <em>Stoaks</em> Bay and put forth to Sea, we conceive they are <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> for the Downs, there are yet some remaining in <em>Portsmouth</em>, which will soon be ready to follow the main Fleet.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em> the same day. Here are arrived a great number of our <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, and the rest is expected <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, this being the place (<reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said) for the general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>. Here are yet many <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships, who will not venture to Sea without a strong convoy, until the Letters of <unclear>Mart</unclear> be called in, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> is expected here on Tuesday next, or sooner.</p>

<p>To close up this week we had further the <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> news of the agreement between the Queen of <em>Swedland</em> and our Ambassador the L. <em>Whitlock</em>, as by Letters from <em>Vpsal</em> April 8. whereof one in the words following, <em>Sir</em>, I sent unto you about a for night since, but having very little news in that letter, I was <reg orig="resolv'd">resolved</reg> to make you amends in this, (though in a few words) by acquainting you that our Treaty with the Qu. of <em>Swedland</em> is concluded, and the next week to be <reg orig="sign'd">signed</reg> I hope as well to the advantage of the Nation, as the particular satisfaction of my L. Ambassador, who (by the time you can receive this Letter) will be advancing homewards, I hope that after our attendance here in a very hard winter, our tedious <reg orig="journies">journeys</reg> and voyages backwards and forwards, and bringing home with us the Alliance of so considerable a people as <em>Swethland</em> may be to <em>England</em>, we shall find a general <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg>, at least by our friends.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is <unclear>by way</unclear> reprinted with Additions, that Excellent <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of Cases of Conscience practically resolved, containing a Decision of all the <unclear>prime pal</unclear> Cases of Conscience, being of daily concernment, and continual use: Written by Dr. Hall, Bishop of Norwich, and are to be sold by <em>Francis Egglesfield</em>, at the <reg orig="Marygold">Marigold</reg> in St. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p>Also a book of much use to all practitioners in <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>, entitled, An new and Brief Introduction to <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg>, both for Song and Viol; never before printed: and are to be sold by <em>John Playford</em> at his shop in the Inner Temple.</p>

<p><em>Animal Corantum Secundi <unclear>inm.</unclear></em> On, The Second <reg orig="Horn'd">Horned</reg> Beast, Containing an Answer to Mr. <em>Tho: Gataker's</em> Envy, produced in the Postscript of his Discourse Apologetical. Printed for <em>William Larnar</em> at the <reg orig="Black-mores">Blackmore's</reg> head near Fleet-Bridge.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>