<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title> Perfect Diurnall Occurrences, Issue 2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg>:</head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="1">Occurrences</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other.</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em>. 8. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em> 15. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<p>By Letters from <em>Deale</em> dated May 6. thus: About forty <reg orig="sayle">sail</reg> of our Fleet are come up this way, and ride before this town, and most of the rest of the Fleet we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> are coming after in order (as we understand) to a general <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, but a Squadron is gone either towards the Isle of <em><reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg></em>, or S. <em>Males</em>, for we hear of some affronts offered to the English there by the French; and it is admitted how they dare to do it, as the affairs of <em>England</em> stand in this juncture of time: but it may the great ones will not <reg orig="owne">own</reg> it: Many vessels that have been trading abroad daily come home, and many Merchant-men are laden and going forth.</p>

<p>From <em>Upsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em> April 8. Now we are able to give you a satisfactory <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> negotiations there; for a firm peace is concluded in the behalf <em>England</em> with the Queen of<pb n="1" /> <em>Sweden</em>, which is as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> resented here as it can be acceptable to <em>England</em>: The Articles are <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>, and are within few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> to be signed, sealed, and delivered to both parties. The Queen looks upon this business as a thing crowneth the rest of her actions, that so great a work should be accomplished just at the laying down of her Crown. The persons commissionated to treat and conclude with my Lord were the Lord <em>Chancellor</em>, and his second son Count <em>Erich</em>. The <reg orig="successe">success</reg> having thus answered the expectation of our coming hither, we shall have little to do but wait for orders to call us back. Upon the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> resigning her government she is to take possession of the Isle of <em>Orland</em>, and other revenues which were given to the Crown, and all other estates which she gave by way of gratuity to Courtiers and <reg orig="Favorites">Favourites</reg> are to return unto her: she hath already resigned unto her the isle of <em>Oesel</em>, which is worth 100000. livers a year. The Prince <em>Palatine</em>, who is now to be crowned, is a man of great judgment and valour. Here is an army of thirty thousand able <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and forty gallant men of war, but the <reg orig="designe">design</reg> they are to go upon is kept very secret.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 9.</head>

<p>By a Merchant ship newly come home we are <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that many ships have been lately cast away by storm, whereof one was a Dutch Merchant ship of great value, coming from <em>Lubon</em>, having in her fifteen <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of gold, which was cast away upon the Sicilian sea. The French are preparing what men of war and <reg orig="gallies">galleys</reg> they can for the relief of <em>Rosa</em>, a port-town besieged by the Spaniard.</p>

<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, that the articles of peace ratified by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector are come safe to the States General, and that they are proclaimed there, at which the Merchants expressed great joy, and the States General have appointed a day of thanksgiving for this happy peace, and there is great preparations for feasting, and make bonfires that day.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Le Brun</em>, (the Spanish Ambassador at the <em>Hague</em>) and his Secretary have signified to the States, that he hath order to negotiate the affairs of State there, and complained that the Hollander doth prejudice the Spanish trade in the <em>East Indies</em>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance came forth touching the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, That all goods and merchandize mentioned in the book of Rates for the Customs (except Bullion, Corn, <reg orig="Victualls">Victuals</reg>, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, Ammunition, Ordnance of <reg orig="Brasse">Brass</reg> or Iron, and <reg orig="Wooll">Wool</reg>, exported or imported, which are not in the said Rates of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> before or otherwise charged) shall hereafter<pb n="2" /> pay <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> after the rate of five pound <em>per cent</em>. to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant or Importer; and that from March 25. last the revenue of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> shall be but one Receipt, and brought into one <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Revenue.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, May 10.</i></head>

<p>This day was ordered to be printed a Declaration of his Highness the L. Protector for setting apart a day of thanksgiving, which <reg orig="followes">follows</reg> thus.</p>

<p>A Declaration set forth by his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> for a day of Thanksgiving for the peace with <em>Holland</em>, and for the the late seasonable Rain.</p>

<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings, in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the <reg orig="out stretched">outstretched</reg> arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment and wonder. Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter, and they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, and indeed the dispensations of the Lord have been as if he had said, <em>England</em> thou art my <reg orig="first-born">firstborn</reg>, my delight amongst the Nations, under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us.</p>

<p>The Lord having added another Link to this golden Chain of his loving <reg orig="kindnes">kindness</reg>, by giving us a Peace with our Neighbours the <em>United Provinces</em>, (<reg orig="wherby">whereby</reg> he hath not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> stopped a great issue of blood, but We trust also given us hearts to unite Our blood and strength for the mutual defence of each other) <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>

<p>It is therefore thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23. of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, and for the thankful Acknowledgment of this blessing of Peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other blessings.</p>

<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg>, and did cause the Beast of the said field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into the expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord imparted this mercy to us, did any amongst us <reg orig="fore.know">foreknow</reg> it was coming, was it not stirring upon hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy <em>&amp;c</em>.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>This day begun the Sessions in the <reg orig="old Bayly">Old Bailey</reg> whereof more hereafter.</p>

<p>Since Lieutenant <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Lilburne</em> was carried to the Isle of Jersey, his friends sued forth a <em>Habeas Corpus</em>, and sent at away by a messenger, who took shipping at <em>Weymouth</em> about a fortnight since (as he intimated to some friends here in <em>London</em>) since which they have heard nothing from him; yet is not Lieutenant <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> <em>John Lilburne</em> <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> or executed, as was <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> reported.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 3 May</em>. General <em>Monk</em> hath had meetings with a Council of Officers, and we are in preparations against the forces from <em>England</em> come, to be ready to march into the Field after Col. <em>Morgan</em>, who hath so frighted the Enemy in the Hills, that they durst not venture to come out, but have found a way through the Hills to get Provisions, which we wonder how they came by. <em>Middleton</em> hath, we hear, sent a Messenger to the Islands, to double their Guards. Some Scotch Towns have made stay of a few passengers, but not considerable: We have taken a few Country people that were going towards the Hills. There hath been great <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in the North of <em>Scotland</em>: There hath been lately no considerable actions, but two or three small skirmishes with parties.</p>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> is with the Fleet in the Downs; Letters from <em>Spain</em> and <em>France</em> both say they are <reg orig="afaid">afraid</reg> of them. General <em>Pen</em> is near ready to return to the Fleet.</p>

<p>The business of the Law goes on apace, which will be to the great ease of the Nation in regulating the course of the Law, that it may be with much Justice, Ease, and Speed.</p>

<p>The Dutch have had Peace proclaimed, and a day of Thanksgiving kept.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Collonel">Colonels</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> quarters at <em>Dingwell</em> in the North of <em>Scotland</em>, thus, we are more wearied by often <reg orig="alarums">alarms</reg> and watching <reg orig="then">than</reg> with fighting, for though the enemy brag and boast high, yet they rather make choice to stay with their <reg orig="maine">main</reg> body in the <reg orig="mountaines">mountains</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> stand to the hazard of a <reg orig="Battell">Battle</reg>. <em>Middleton</em> hath bestirred him since his coming into Southerland, and told <em>Glencarne</em> to his face, that if himself had not been there they had been all lost before this. The best intelligence we can gather of them is very doubtful, for the ordinary sort are so extremely ignorant that<pb n="4" /> they cannot, and the better sort so maliciously cunning, that they will not inform us.</p>

<p>On Sunday last a party of theirs met another of ours at a place called <em>Dumgith</em>, where they had a short skirmish, in which we killed <reg orig="foure">four</reg> of the Enemy, and took nine prisoners, one whereof <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that their Officers told them, that they expected very suddenly a considerable number of <reg orig="forraigne">foreign</reg> Forces to come over to them. We hear that General <em>Monk</em> is upon his march on this side <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with us, his coming may prove very seasonable, for certainly if the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> numbers are so great as is reported, they will be forced by hunger <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to forsake the mountains, and either fight us or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> by us, and then we should be sure to make them fight before they get back again. The late differences amongst their chief Officers are not quite salved up yet, neither have they yet completed their Levies. By the next it's probable you will have more of action, but this is all all at present from <em>Dingwell May 7. 1654.</em></p>
<p>Your Friend and Servant, <em>J. H.</em></p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> May 11.</head>

<p>An Ordinance came forth for doubling further upon, and finishing the sale of Deans, <reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg> and <reg orig="Chapters">Chapter's</reg> lands, and of <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories Glebe Lands, &amp;c. wherein it is ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the consent of his Council, That over and above the sum of three hundred thousand pounds appointed to be borrowed upon the security held forth by a late Act of Parliament, and over and above the sum of one hundred and twenty thousand pounds more borrowed upon the security held forth in two other Acts. The sum of twenty thousand pounds shall be further borrowed upon the security of such of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg> respectively exposed to sale by the said Acts, by way of doubling<pb n="5" /> the like sum or sums as shall be due to any person or persons. Body <reg orig="politike">politic</reg> or Corporate, for any money, plate, horse, arms, or other things advanced upon the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Faith, or which hath been at any time allowed by any Act or Ordinance of Parliament to be doubled, together with the interest upon such <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Faith debts after the rate of 8. <em>per cent</em>. <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the stating of such debts and interest, by the persons named and appointed in and by an Act for sale of several lands &amp; estates forfeited to the Commonwealth for treason. In relation to which doubling, the Trustees, Treasurers, Registers, <reg orig="Accompants">Accountants</reg>, and all other Officers concerned therein, are required to proceed according to the directions of the Acts of Parliament in like case made and provided.</p>

<p>Provided also that where any purchaser or purchasers, his or their assign or assigns shall tender any Bills or Receipts by this Ordinance made applicable for payment of any second <reg orig="moity">moiety</reg>, other <reg orig="then">than</reg> such Bills or Receipts, as by his or their contract ought to have been applied thereunto: the <reg orig="partie">party</reg> or parties so <reg orig="tendring">tendering</reg> such Bills or Receipts, shall defalk so much more in value, as shall countervail the interest incurred by his or their elapsed time. For which second <reg orig="Moities">Moieties</reg>, as also defalcations as aforesaid, the said <reg orig="Treasurrers">Treasurers</reg>, or one of them, are hereby authorized to give such purchaser his or their receipt or acquittance and re-conveyance accordingly.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday May 12.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris 14</em>. May new stile. The Commissioners for the Protestants have waited long on the Court, and can get no answer of their complaints except some promises at large that their just grievances <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be redressed in due time; but for the present the Court is wholly given to pleasure. His Majesty is to go from <em><reg orig="Fountainbleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em> the next week, and great preparations are making for him to go <em>Rheimes</em>, against the day of his Coronation. <em>Charles Stuart</em> and the Duke of <em>York</em><pb n="6" /> came yesterday to the Palace <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg>, from taking their pleasure in the country. A Messenger is arrived here from <em>Scotland</em> which talks of high matters, glorying much at <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> success since his going thither. And now here is a hot report that the <em>Stuarts</em> will be gone out of <em>France</em> very shortly.</p>

<p>From <em>Doway</em> 12. May. The Spanish Forces are come into these parts, which makes us sufficiently miserable, by their plundering and <reg orig="forraging">foraging</reg> the country. Some say they have a <reg orig="designe">design</reg> against <em>Bassee</em>, now the French have drawn all their Forces towards the sea side for fear of the English.</p>

<p><em>Francis</em> Duke of <em>Lorraine</em> is come to <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em> with his two sons, and was very nobly received by the Archduke <em>Leopold</em>, who gave unto him the upper hand, and allotted him the chief lodgings at the Court. The Officers of the Army are invited to the Court to be acquainted with this their new General, and after that he will <reg orig="repaire">repair</reg> to the Army, and <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to get the love of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Portsmouth</em>, 11. May. Here are seven or eight of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, which are to hasten after the <reg orig="maine">main</reg> Fleet, which is gone towards the Downs. There came unto this Port a Merchant ship bound for <em>London</em>. The Skipper <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he was in great danger to be taken by the <em>Brest</em> men of war, which lose no time, but the scouting up and down about the West of <em>London</em>, and very lately <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> a Merchant ship belonging to <em><reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg></em>, we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that at S. <em>Malos</em> there was some <reg orig="grosse">gross</reg> affronts offered to the English Factors, and others, and that some were imprisoned, but by the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> command to the Governor, all things are now quiet there.</p>

<p>At <em>Rochel</em>, 5. new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are making ready, and great preparations are all along upon the French Coast. Their Garrisons filled with <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and their Castles and Magazines supplied with <reg orig="Amminition">Ammunition</reg> and victual, as if they expected nothing but a sudden war.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday May 13.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg></em> 8. May. Some Merchants have letters thus. Since the publication of the Articles of Peace with <em>England</em>, and order given for the departure of the Royal Party (according to the time limited in and by the said Articles) they and the vulgar sort of the <em>Aurange</em> Party begin to spurn and kick, <reg orig="indeavouring">endeavouring</reg> to stir up, if possible, dissention amongst <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, but the States have committed some to prison, and issued forth very strict orders against any that shall disturb the present peace.</p>

<p>There was lately a fire in one of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> houses, which is conjectured to be kindled by some of the <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Party. There is <reg orig="newes">news</reg> here that at S. <em>Malos</em> one or more Englishmen have lately been assaulted and slain by the French, and that the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> goods are made stay of.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Redding">Reading</reg></em> 12. May. This week were committed to the Town <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>: nine persons (men and women) who are charged with witch craft, they were apprehended within two or three miles of <em>Okingham</em>, where they were making merry and exercising feats of activity in several shapes.</p>

<p>The Lords of the Council sit every day very close at <em><reg orig="White-Hal">Whitehall</reg></em> upon great and weighty affairs.</p>

<p><reg orig="Foure">Four</reg> Forests are to be sold for the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Dublin</em> 6. May. All things here are very quiet, eight and ten of a Company are drawn out and sent Northward to be transported into <em>Scotland</em>. The Native Irish are drawn together in <em>Conaingh</em>.</p>

<p>This day the Sessions in the <reg orig="old Baily">Old Bailey</reg> ended, seven persons received sentence of death, <em>Downs</em> and <em>Smith</em> were found guilty of <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> half Crowns shillings &amp; sixpences of several stamps, <em>viz</em>. K. <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em>, K. <em>Charles</em>, and the States. The rings were good silver, but the middle course and base metal. 'Twas proved that when some did speak of the money, <em>Downes</em> said these words, <i>We do make it:</i> and at another time <em>Smith</em> said, <i>I do make it</i>. So the best evidence was out of their own mouths. He that <reg orig="ript">ripped</reg> off the lead off S. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church, as well as took down the scaffolds is fined 1200. pound, and adjudged to perpetual imprisonment. The rest that be condemned are for robberies of several sorts.</p>

<p>A lone house in <em>Tuthil</em> fields was lately robbed, all the goods clean carried away, and the woman almost killed.</p>

<p>Reader take notice. That (for thy ease and satisfaction) the sum of the whole <reg orig="weeks">week's</reg> intelligence is <reg orig="comprized">comprised</reg> in this one sheet.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>