<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn213">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 213</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> January. 2. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January. 9. <em>1653</em></i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 2</i></head>

<p>We cannot let <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, for more <reg orig="generall">general</reg> satisfaction, (especially in the Country) what was this day published, of <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Government of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector; to this effect following.</p>

<p>1. That the Supreme Legislative Authority of this Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, shall be, &amp; reside, in one person, and the people assembled in Parliament; The style of which person shall be, <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</p>

<p>2. That the exercise of the chief magistracy and administration of the government over the said Counties and Dominions, and the people thereof, shall be in the Lord Protector, assisted with a Council; the number whereof shall not exceed 21. nor be less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 13.</p>

<p>3. That all Writs, Processes, Commissions, Patents, Grants, and<pb n="1" /> other things, which now run in the name and <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of the Keepers of the liberty of <em>England</em> by authority of parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> run in the name and <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of the Lo: Protector from whom, for the future, shall be derived all magistracy and <reg orig="honors">honours</reg> in these 3 nations; and shall have the power of pardons, (except in case of murder and treason) and benefit of all forfeitures for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> use; and shall govern the said Countries and Dominions in all things by the advice of the Council: and according to these presents, and the laws.</p>

<p>4. That the Lord protector, the parliament <reg orig="siting">sitting</reg>, shall dispose and order the Militia and Forces both by sea and land, for the peace and good of the three nations, by consent of parliament, and that the Lord protector, with the advise and consent of the major part of the Council, shall dispose and order the Militia for the ends aforesaid in the intervals of parliaments.</p>

<p>5. That the L: protector by the advice aforesaid shall direct, in all things, concerning the keeping &amp; holding of a good <reg orig="corrspondency">correspondence</reg> with foreign Kings, princes, &amp; States; and also with the consent the major part of the Council have the power of war and peace.</p>

<p>6. That the laws shall not be <reg orig="altred">altered</reg>, suspended, abrogated, or repealed, or any new law made, nor any tax, charge, or imposition laid upon the people, but by common consent in parliament, save only as is expressed in the 30 article.</p>

<p>7. That there shall be a parliament summoned to meet at <em>Westminster</em> upon the 3 day of Sept. 1654. and that successively, a parliament shall be summoned once in every third year, to be accounted from the dissolution of the preceding parliaments.</p>

<p>8. That neither the parliament to be next summoned, nor any successive parliaments, shall, during the time of five months, to be accounted from the day of their first meeting, be adjourned, prorogued or dissolved without their own consent.</p>

<p>9. That as well the next, as all other successive parliaments, shall be summoned, and elected in manner hereafter <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; That is to say, the persons to be chosen within England, Wales, the Isle of Jersey and Guernsey, and the Town of <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg> upon Tweed to sit &amp; serve in parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and not exceed, the number of 400. The persons to be chosen in Scotland, to sit in parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be &amp; not exceed the number of 30. &amp; the persons to be chosen to sit in parliament for Ireland, shall be, and not exceed the number of 30.</p>

<p>10. That the persons to be elected to sit in parliament from time<pb n="2" /> to time for the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> counties of England, Wales, the Isles of Jersey and Guernsey, and the Town of <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg> upon Tweed, and all places within the same respectively, shall be according to the proportion and numbers hereafter <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>.</p>

<p><i>But these numbers, for wanting room, we must omit.</i></p>

<p>The distribution of the persons to be chosen for Scotland, and Ireland, and the several counties, cities, and places within the same, shall be according to such proportions and number, as shall be agreed upon, and declared by the Lord protector and the major part of the Council, before the sending forth of Writs of Summons for the next parliament.</p>

<p>11. That the summons to parliament, shall be writ under the Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> of England, directed to the <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg> of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Counties, with such alteration as may <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> with the present government, to be made by the Lord Protector and his Council, which the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg>, shall <reg orig="seale">seal</reg>, issue, and send abroad by Warrant from the Lord Protector. If the Lord protector shall not give Warrant for issuing of Writs of Summons for the next parliament, before the first day of June 1654. or for the <reg orig="Triennall">Triennial</reg> parliaments, before the first day of August in the third year, to be accounted as aforesaid, That then the <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg>, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg>, for the time being, shall, without any Warrant or direction, within seven <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the said first day of June 1654. seal, issue, and send abroad Writs of Summons (changing therein what is to be changed as aforesaid) to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, for summoning the parliament, to meet at <em>Westminster</em>, the third of September next; and shall likewise within seven <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the first day of August, in every third year; to be accounted from the dissolution of the precedent parliament, seal, issue, and send abroad <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Writs of Summons changing therein what is to be changed, as aforesaid, for summoning the parliament to meet at Westminster the fixt of November in that third <reg orig="yeare">year</reg>: That the said <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Sheriffs shall, within ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the receipt of such Writs as aforesaid, cause the same to be proclaimed and published in every Market-Town within his County, upon Market days thereof, between Twelve and Three of the clock; and shall then also publish and declare the certain day of the <reg orig="weeke">week</reg> and month for <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> Members<pb n="3" /> to serve in parliament for the Body of the said County, according to the Tenor of the said Writ, which shall be upon Wednesday five weeks after the date of the Writ, and shall likewise declare the place where the Election shall be made; for which purpose he shall appoint the most convenient place for the County to meet in, and shall send precepts for elections to be made in all and every City; Town, Borough, or place within his County, where Elections are to be made by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of these presents, to the Mayor, Sheriff, or other head Officer of such City, Town, Borough, or place, within three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Receipt of such Writ or Writs, which the said Mayor, <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg>, and Officers respectively are to make publication of, and of the certain day for such Elections to be made in the said City, Towne, or place aforesaid, and to cause Election to be made accordingly.</p>

<p>12. That at the day and place of Elections, the Sheriff of each County, and the said Mayors, Sheriffs, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other head Officers within their Cities, towns, Boroughs and places respectively, shall take view of the said Elections, and shall make return into the Chancery within 20 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the said Elections of the persons elected by the greater number of Electors, under their hands &amp; seals, between him on the one part, and the Electors on the other part; wherein shall be contained, That the persons elected shall not have power to alter the government as it is hereby <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in one single person and a Parliament.</p>

<p>13. That the Sheriff who shall wittingly and willingly make any false Return, or neglect his duty: shall incur the penalty of 2000 Marks of <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> English <reg orig="mony">money</reg>; the one moiety to the Lord Protector, and the other moiety to such person as will sue for the same.</p>

<p>14. That all and every person and persons, who have aided, advised, assisted, or abetted in any war against the Parliament, since the first day of Jan: 1641 (unless they have been since in the service of the Parliament, and given signal testimony of their goods affections thereunto) shall be disabled, and be <reg orig="uncapable">incapable</reg> to be elected or to give any Vote in the Election of any Members to serve in the next Parliament, or in the three succeeding Triennial Parliaments.</p>

<p>15. That all such, who have advised, assisted, or abetted the rebellion of Ireland, shall be disabled and incapable for ever to be elected, or to give any Vote in the election of any Member to serve in Parliament; as also all such who do or shall <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> the Roman <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</p>

<p>That all Votes and Elections given or made contrary, or not according to these Qualifications, shall be null and void; And if any person who is hereby made <reg orig="uncapable">incapable</reg>, shall give his Vote for Election of Members to serve in Parliament, such persons shall lose and forfeit one <reg orig="years">year's</reg> value of his <reg orig="reall">real</reg> estate; and one full third part of his <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> estate, one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the Lord Protector, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to him, or them who shall sue for the same</p><pb n="4" />

<p>That the persons who shall be elected to serve in Parliament, shall be such (and no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> such) as are persons of known integrity, fearing God, and of good conversation, and being of the age of 21 years.</p>

<p>18 That all and every person and persons seized or possessed to his own use; of any estate real or personal, to the value of 200 l. and not within the aforesaid exceptions, shall be capable to elect members to serve in Parliament for Counties.</p>

<p>19 That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal, shall be sworn before they enter into their Offices, truly and faithfully to issue forth and send abroad Writs of Summons to Parliaments at the times, and in manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; And, in case of neglect or <reg orig="failer">failure</reg>, to issue and send abroad Writs accordingly, he or they shall for every such offence be guilty of High Treason, and suffer the pains and penalties thereof.</p>

<p>20 That in case Writs be not issued out, as is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, but that there be a neglect therein, 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the time wherein the same ought to be issued out by the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal, that then the Parl: shall, as often as such <reg orig="failer">failure</reg> shall happen, assemble and be held at <em>Westminster</em>, in the usual place, at the <reg orig="prefixt">prefixed</reg>, in manner and by the means hereafter expressed; that is to say, That the <reg orig="Shrieffs">Sheriffs</reg> of the several and respective Counties, <reg orig="Shrievedoms">Sheriffdoms</reg>, Cities, Boroughs and places aforesaid, within <em>England, Wales, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, the Chancellor, Masters and Scholars of the Universities of <em>Oxford</em> and <em>Cambridge</em>, and the Mayor and Bailiffs of the Borough of <em><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em> upon <em>Tweed</em>, and other the places aforesaid respectively, shall at the several Courts and places to be appointed as aforesaid, within 30 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the said 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, cause such Members to be chosen for their said several and respective Counties, <reg orig="Shrievedoms">Sheriffdoms</reg>, Universities, Cities, Boroughs, and places aforesaid, by such persons and in such manner, as if several and respective Writs of Summons to Parl: under the Great Seal, had issued and been awarded according to the Tenor abovesaid: That if the Sheriff or other persons authorized, shall neglect his or their duty herein; That all and every such Sheriff and person authorized as aforesaid, so neglecting his or their duty, shall, for every such offence, be guilty of High-Treason, and shall suffer the pains and penalties thereof.</p>

<p><i>That the Clerk called The <em>Clerk</em> of the <em>Commonwealth</em>, in Chancery for the time being, and all others, who shall afterwards execute that Office, to whom the returns shall be made, shall for the next Parliament, and the two succeeding Triennial Parliaments, the next day after such return, <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> the names of the several persons so returned, and of the places for which he and they were chosen respectively, unto the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who shall peruse the said Returns, and examine whether the persons so elected and returned be such as is agreeable to the qualifications, and not disabled to be elected, and being approved by the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to be persons not disabled, but qualified as aforesaid, shall be esteemed a Member of Parliament, and be admitted to sit in Parl. and not otherwise.</i></p><pb n="5" />

<p><i>22 That the persons chosen and assembled in manner aforesaid or any <unclear>50</unclear> of them, shall be, and deemed the Parl: of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>; and the supreme legislative power to be and reside in the Lord Protector, and such Parl: in manner herein <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>23 That the Lord Protector, with the advice of the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, shall at any other time <reg orig="then">than</reg> is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, when the necessities of the state shall require it, summon Parliaments in manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, which shall not be adjourned, prorogued, or dissolved without their own consent, during the first 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> of their sitting, and in case of future War with any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> State, a Parliament shall be forthwith summoned for the advice concerning the same.</i></p> 

<p>24 That all Bills agreed unto by the Parl: shall be presented to the Lord Protector for his consent; and in case he shall not give his consent thereto, within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after they shall be presented to him, or give satisfaction to the Parl: within the time limited, that then, upon declaration of the Parl: that the Lord Protector hath not consented nor given satisfaction, such Bills shall <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> into, and become Laws, although he shall not give his consent thereunto; provided such Bills contain nothing in them contrary to the matters contained in these presents.</p>

<p>25 That <em>Philip</em> Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em>, <em>Charles Fleetwood</em> Esq; <em>John Lambert</em> Esq; Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em> <reg orig="Barronet">Baronet</reg>, Sir <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Wolsley</em> Baronet, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em> Bar: Ed: <em>Montague</em> Esq; <em>John Desborow</em> Esq; Sir <em>Walter Strickland</em> Esq; <em>Hen: Lawrence</em> Esq; <em>Wil: Syndenham</em> Esq; <em>Philip Jones</em> Esq; <em>Rich: Major</em> Esq; <em>Fran: Rous Phil: Skippen</em> Esqs, or any 7 of them, shall be a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for purposes <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in this writing: and upon death or other removal of any of them, the Parl. shall nominate 6 persons of ability, integrity, and fearing God, for every one that is dead or removed, out of which the major part of the Council shall elect two, and present them to the Lord Protector, of which he shall elect one.</p>

<p>26 That the L. Protector and the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> aforesaid, may at any time before the meeting of the next Parl: add to the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> such persons as they shall think fit; provided, the number of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> be not made thereby to exceed 21. and that the <em><reg orig="quoram">quorum</reg></em> to be proportioned accordingly by the L. Protector, and the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>27 That a constant yearly revenue shall be raised, <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> &amp; <reg orig="establisht">established</reg> for maintaining of 10000 Horse and Dragoons, and 20000 Foot in England, Scotland and Ireland, for the defence and security thereof, and also for a convenient number of ships for guarding of the Seas; besides 200000 <em>per annum</em> for defraying the other necessary charges for administration of justice, and other <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government.</p>

<p>28 That the said yearly revenue shall be paid into the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Treasury, and shall be issued out for the uses aforesaid.</p>

<p>29 That in case there shall not be cause hereafter to keep up so great a defence at Land or Sea, but that there be an abatement made thereof; the <reg orig="mony">money</reg> which will be saved thereby shall remain in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service and not be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to any use but by consent of Parl: or in the intervals of Parl: by the Lord Protector and major part of <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<p>30 That the raising of money for defraying the charge of present extraordinary forces both at Land and Sea, in respect of the present wars, shall be by consent in Parl: and not otherwise; save only that the Lord Protector, with the consent of the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for preventing the disorders and dangers which may otherwise fall out both at Sea and Land, shall have power until the meeting of the first Parl: to raise money for the purposes aforesaid.</p>

<p>31 That the Lands, Tenements, Rents, Royalties, Jurisdictions and Hereditaments which remain yet unsold or <reg orig="undisposed">indisposed</reg> of by Act of Ordinance of Parl: belonging to the Commonwealth, (except the Forests and Chafes, and the <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> and Manors belonging to the same: the Lands of the Rebels in Ireland, lying in the 4 Counties of Dublin, Cork, Kildare and Katerlaugh or the Lands forfeited by the people of Scotland in the late Wars: and also the Lands of Rapists and Delinquents in England, who have not yet compounded) shall be vested in the Lord Protector: To hold, to him and his Successors, Lord Protectors of these Nations, and shall not be aliened, but by consent in Parl: And all Debts, Fines, Issues, Amerciaments, Penalties and Profits, certain and casual, due to the Keepers of the Liberties of England, by Authority of Parliament, shall be due to the Lord Protector, and be payable<pb n="7" /> into the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Receipt, and shall be recovered and prosecuted in his Name.</p>

<p>32 That the Office of the Lord Protector over these Nations, shall be Elective, and not Hereditary; and upon the death of the Lord Protector, another fit person shall be forthwith elected to succeed him in the Government, which Election shall be by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> upon the death of the Lord Protector, shall assemble in the Chamber where they usually sit in <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and having given notice to all their number, of the cause of their assembling, shall, being 13 at least present, proceed to the Election; and before they depart out of the said Chamber, shall elect a fit person to succeed in the Government, and forthwith cause Proclamation thereof to be made in all the 3 Nations as shall be requisite: And the person that they, or the major part of them shall elect, as aforesaid, shall be; and shall be taken to be Lord Protector over these Nations of England, Scotland and Ireland, and the Dominions thereunto belonging: Provided, that none of the Children of the late king, nor any of his Line or Family, be elected to be Lord Protector, or other chief Magistrate over these Nations, or any Dominions thereunto belonging.</p>

<p>33 That Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> Captain General of the Forces of England, Scotland and Ireland, shall be, and is hereby declared to be Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, for his life.</p>

<p>34 That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the Great Seal, the Treasurer, Admiral, chief Governors of Ireland and Scotland, and the chief Justices of both the Benches, shall be chosen by the approbation of Parliaments, and in the intervals of Parl: by the approbation of the major part of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, to be afterwards approved by the Parliament.</p>

<p>36 That the Christian Religion, contained in the Scriptures, be held forth and recommended as the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Profession of these Nations, and that as soon an may be, a provision less subject to scruple and contention, and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present, be made for the encouragement and maintenance of able and painful Teachers, for instructing the people, and for discovery and confutation of Error, <reg orig="Heresie">Heresy</reg>, and whatever is contrary to sound Doctrine: And that until such provision be made, the present maintenance shall not be taken away nor impeached.</p><pb n="8" />

<p>36. To the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> profession held forth, none shall be compelled by penalties or otherwise, but that endeavours be used to win them by sound <reg orig="Doctrin">Doctrine</reg>, and the example of a good conversation.</p>

<p>37. That such as profess faith in God by Jesus Christ (though differing in judgement from the doctrine, worship, or discipline <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth) shall not be restrained from, but shall be protected in the profession of the faith, and exercise of their religion, so as they abuse not this liberty, to the civil injury of others, and to the actual disturbance of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> peace on their parts: provided this liberty is not extended to Popery or Prelacy, nor to such, as under the profession of Christ, hold forth and practise licentiousness.</p>

<p>37. That all Laws, Statutes, and Ordinances and Clauses in any Law, Statute and Ordinance to the contrary of the aforesaid liberty, shall be esteemed as null and void.</p>

<p>39. That the Acts and Ordinances of Parliament, made for the sale or other disposition of the Lands, Rents, and Hereditaments of the late King, Queen and Prince, of <reg orig="Arch-Bishops">Archbishops</reg> and Bishops, <em>&amp;c</em>. Deans and Chapters, the Lands of Delinquents, and Forest Lands, or any of them; or of any other Lands, Tenements, Rents and Hereditaments belonging to the Commonwealth, shall no way be impeached or made invalid; but shall remain good and firm: And that the securities given by Act and Ordinance of Parliament for any sum or sums of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, by any of the said Lands, the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, or by any other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Revenue; and also the securities given by the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> faith of the Nation; and the engagement of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> faith for satisfaction of debts and damages, shall remain firm and good, and not be made void or invalid upon any presence whatsoever.</p>

<p>40. That the Articles given to, or made with the Enemy, and afterwards confirmed by the Parliament, shall be performed &amp; made good to the persons concerned therein. And that such appeals as were depending in the last Parliament, for relief concerning <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> of sale of <reg orig="Delinquents">Delinquent's</reg> Estates, may be <reg orig="heatd">heated</reg> and determined the next Parliament, Any thing in this writing, or otherwise to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>41. That every successive Lord Protector over these Nations shall take and subscribe a solemn Oath, in the presence of the Council, and such others as they shall call to them, That he will<pb n="9" /> seek the peace, quiet, and welfare of these Nations, cause law and justice to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>, and that he will not violate or infringe the matters and things contained in this writing, and in all other things will to his power, &amp; to the best of his understanding, govern these Nations, according to the Laws, Statutes, and Customs.</p>

<p>42. That each person of the Council shall, before they enter upon their trust, take, and subscribe an Oath, that they will be true and faithful in their trust, according to the best <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg>; and, that in the election of every successive Lord Protector, they shall proceed therein impartially, and do nothing therein for any promise, fear, favour or reward.</p>

<head level="3">The Oath taken by His Highness Oliver <em><reg orig="Crowel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector.</head>

<p><i>Whereas the major part of the last Parliament (judging that their sitting any longer, as then constituted, would not be for the good of this Commonwealth) did dissolve the same, and by a writing under their hands, dated the twelfth day of this instant <em>December</em>, resigned unto Me their Powers and Authorities; And whereas it was necessary thereupon, That some speedy course should be taken for the Settlement of these Nations upon such a Basis and Foundation, as, by the blessing of God, might be <unclear>lacking</unclear>, secure Property, and answer those great Ends of Religion and Liberty, so long contended for, and upon full and mature Consideration had the Form of Government hereunto annexed, being satisfied that the same, through divine assistance, may answer the Ends <reg orig="afore-mentioned">aforementioned</reg>: And having also been desired, and advised, as well by several persons of Interest and Fidelity in this Commonwealth, as the Officers of the Army, to take upon Me the Protection and Government of these Nations, in the manner expressed in the said Form of Government, I have accepted thereof, and hereby declare my acceptance accordingly. And do promise in the presence of God, That I will not violate, or infringe the matters and things contained <reg orig="therin">therein</reg>, but to My Power, observe the same, and cause them to be observed; and shall in all other things, to the best of my understanding, Govern these Nations according to the Laws, Statutes and Customs, seeking their Peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>.</i></p>
<p>O. <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg></p> 

<p><em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Captain General of all the Forces of this Commonwealth, and now declared <em>Lord Protector </em>thereof, did this 16 of <em>Decemb. 1653</em>. sign this Writing, and solemnly promise, as is therein<pb n="10" /> contained, in presence of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Commissioners of the Great Seal of England, who <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> the same Oath, and of the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of <em>London</em>, divers of the Judges of the Land, the Officers of State and Army, and many other persons of Quality.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday and Wednesday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 3, 4</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> December</em> 29. The Enemy (for now we must call them so) still go on with their levies in several parts of the Hills, and will be numerous, do what we can to prevent them; though I see not how they can keep together in a body which <reg orig="conjoyned">conjoined</reg>, The Country not being able to bear them: <em>Kenmore</em> lies up towards the the Bray of <em>Mane</em>, and in the Glens that way, within the, Hills near Woods and Rivers, and all along in several fast places from <em>Lough Tay</em>, towards the Brays of <em>Stermont</em> and <em>Angus</em>.</p>

<p>Lieut. <em>Whitmore</em> of Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Regiment went up lately into the Hills, and took 40 Sheep and 5 Cows, which Sir <em>Mungoe Murtah</em> their Quartermaster General sent forth of the Highlands to be kept near his own house, Sir <em><reg orig="Mungoes">Mungoe's</reg></em> man, and one horse of the Laird of <em>Lenes</em> (who took Capt. <em>Townsend</em> and Capt <em>Scroop</em>) but the Rider <reg orig="escapt">escaped</reg>: Yesterday a party of the <em>Tories</em> met with 4 of Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons near <em>Levingston</em> house, about 10 miles from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, whom they barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, one of them fled into the House for safety, but the people would not protect him, but left him to the cruelty of those Villains. A party of our Dragoons from the Bray of <em>Maine</em>, fell upon the Enemy, <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> one, wounded three, and four horses: I cannot think there is a pack of more unmerciless Rogues in the world, than those now gathered together in this Country, and many of them were at <em>Dunbar</em>, and <em>Worcester</em>, and had liberty given them through our too much lenity.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em> the same date thus. Major <em><reg orig="Bramstones">Bramstone's</reg></em> party had light upon Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> upon <reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> last, had not an old K. near <em>Pebbles</em> sent him notice of our parties coming thither, he being then at the Kirk of <em>Atterick</em> very sore wounded, yet upon hearing of their approach, marched towards the Hills, his number being then made 70 horse by the occasion of one Capt <em>Steward</em> with 20 horse, our men took two more of them who were in the former fight, and one <reg orig="Mosse">Moss</reg> Trooper.</p><pb n="11" />

<p>The Enemy have now a Garrison in <em>Roldew</em> about ten miles from <em>Dunbarton</em>, from whence they came commanded by one <em>Colgrave</em>, with about 80 Foot last week to <em>Dunbarton</em>, and in the dead of the night took two of the Bailiffs and other principal men of the Town to the number of 36, whom they threaten to keep till they send them in 4 horsemen and 37 Footmen for their Levies.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors taking their leave at a long conference at Whitehall yesterday; this day they sent their goods a Shipboard, and went themselves in the afternoon by Barge to <em>Gravesend</em>, there to take shipping for <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p>No farther news from Sea, but that General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> rides with our Fleet about the Channel, and Gen. <em>Blake</em> is gone down to the <em>Hope</em> to look after the rest of the Fleet, who are near ready also to set out, besides those two Ships mentioned formerly taken by the Dutch near the Lands end being homeward bound from <em><reg orig="New-England">New England</reg></em>, there are two more safely arrived in this River coming from the same Country, and laden with Masts, and great store of <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg> skins, and the like commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday January 5.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> January 10. 1654. <em>stilo novo</em>. The last news from our Army in <em>Alsatia</em> imply, That the Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em> hath invested <em>Beffort</em>, and is now making his Lines of Communication and other works belonging to a siege, there hath been several pieces of Ordnance drawn out of <em>Nancy</em>, which are on the way, and will come to the <reg orig="Leagure">Leaguer</reg> as soon as any Batteries will be raised for to plant them upon; the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <em>de Vxelles</em> is to be Lieutenant General, and is expected there with three thousand men. This design hath much <reg orig="allarmed">alarmed</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so much the more, since the yielding up of the strong Castle of <em><reg orig="Phillipsburgh">Phillipsburg</reg></em>, which was taken by a <reg orig="surprizal">surprisal</reg> without the loss of one man: the manner thus, The Deputy <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> being gone a hunting with some of the high Officers of that Garrison, notice being given to one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> creatures, he embraced with alacrity that occasion, and being come into the place, he so prevailed upon the Garrison, that he became Master of the place, and this Deputy <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> being come in the Evening, knowing not what had passed, found the Bridge <reg orig="drawne">drawn</reg> up, and entrance <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> him; whereupon he was forced to retire speedily. The Duke <em>d' Amville</em> being sent by the King to <em>Blois</em>, to try once<pb n="12" /> more whether he could <reg orig="prevaile">prevail</reg> with the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, and so bring him <reg orig="againe">again</reg> to the Court, returned back this week, and the report is at Court, that he hath brought a very good Answer, and that he will be shortly in this City: but others are of a contrary opinion. The Duke <em>de Guise</em> is still going on in his preparations for his intended design for <em>Naples</em> against the next Spring.</p>

<p>The States assembled in <em>Provence</em> are now sitting at <em>Bagnolls</em>, where the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and the other Procurators are also gone: they do sit daily, and hope to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> many abuses, and <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> grievances which do much burthen the People there. The Commissioners appointed to draw out the charge of high Treason against the Prince of <em>Conde</em> have met several times, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> said that it is finished, only it wants to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg>: News is come that the Prince hath surprised a little Town and a Castle in <em>Champagne</em> and plundered the Country <reg orig="pittifully">pitifully</reg>; two days since the King with his brother and the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> went to a place called the <em>Plain of Madrid</em>, near the City where the Regiment of the Guard was drawn in <em>Batalia</em>, and a List being brought to his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, it was found to consist of above 6 thousand men fit for service.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday January 6, 7</i></head>

<p><em>Warwick <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 4 1653. This last Saturday Mr. <em>Bulstrode</em> one of the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> of <reg orig="North-wales">North Wales</reg> came hither by a special Commission of Gaol delivery, he heard the Sermon early on <em>Monday</em> morning, and went directly from thence to the Hall, where there was a very great appearance, and a very able grand <reg orig="Iury">Jury</reg>, there hath not been a greater Gaol known these many years: there is five men and one woman condemned to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>, seven likewise burned in the hand, and two men (that would not plead) to be pressed, the <reg orig="Iudge">Judge</reg> used his endeavours to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to plead, telling them what a sad condition they would bring themselves into; but the resolute Villains were resolved to die in their <reg orig="wickednesse">wickedness</reg>, I will assure you the <reg orig="Iudge">Judge</reg> carried the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> very well, and gave the Country a great deal of satisfaction: he spake something in his charge in relation to the late Government, he said that it was now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon such a Basis as was like to conduce much to the <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg> of all good people; he gave strict orders to the grand <reg orig="Iury">Jury</reg>, that if they heard<pb n="13" /> any that were Perturbers of <unclear>thus</unclear>, that they should not fail to bring them to the bar of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>, and a great deal more to the same effect.</p>

<p>There came Letters of the Lord <em>Whitlock</em>, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> Novemb. 18. his voyage and reception there, as followeth. We began to set <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> from <em>Gravesend</em> Novemb. <em>6</em>. but the wind coming too much into the North, and being not able to get clear of the lands that day, we were enforced to cast Anchor near <em>Quisborow</em>; The next day the wind standing fair we set sail again, and made a very large course, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> about noon the day after, at which time the wind turned full against us, so that we were afraid, that we should have been necessitated to put into <em>Yarmouth</em> Road. But the wind favoured again for a little time, and we made forwards, yet it was not long ere we were very much becalmed; and so we were exercised with uncertainties of winds until the 12 instant, when there came a very fair wind, which carried us on with full sail, so that on the 14 instant at night we cast Anchor on this side the <em>Scagen</em>, and we came on the 15th betimes in the River. As we came along our ship met with some <em>Holland</em> Fishermen, and boarded one of them, but my Lord Ambassador willing to pass peaceably over the Sea, released it again, which did exceedingly overjoy them, who had been undone in his own thoughts before; yet the Elizabeth, being one of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> home some of our Company, staying behind to bring up one of the <reg orig="Baggage-ships">Baggage ships</reg>, met with a small Dutch Caper, and boarded it, and brought it along with them. We were not altogether without rough and stormy weather, especially the last night, when we anchored at the <em>Scagen</em>, insomuch that we were afraid we should have lost one of the Baggage ships, which was but very slenderly provided with Tacklings, yet (through the goodness of God) we are all come safe, and there is none sick among us, nor <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> lost; As soon as ever we were come into the River, being weary of the Sea, we made <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to the shore, so that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Magistrates of the Town could not be ready to give us that solemn reception as they intended. The next day the three Presidents, with the Magistrates, came to salute my Lord in a very <reg orig="handsom">handsome</reg> Equipage, and one of them made a Speech to him in <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, wherein he acquainted his Lordship, That they had received positive commands from the Queen to demonstrate all respects to<pb n="14" /> the <em>English</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, whom she had received notice would arrive here in a short time; and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> desired his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> excuse, that they were not prepared to give him a more pompous entertainment at his first landing. Afterwards the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> came to give his Salutation, which he performed with great demonstrations of civility, and respect. And indeed they are very ready to accommodate us in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>, and to give us all possible help and assistance in our intended journey towards the Court. The Queen is at present at <em>Vpsalia</em>, but we are uncertain whether she intends to reside there all this Winter; <reg orig="Tis">It is</reg> supposed that she may return again to <em>Stockholm</em>, there dying but two of the sickness the last week; our journey thither will be very tedious and <reg orig="chargable">chargeable</reg>; and we now begin to find by experience, That those that are employed upon such solemn Missions into so barren a Country, must needs be <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> with a very large purse. After that we have refreshed <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, and rested our horses here for a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, we shall begin our journey, having already sent Letters to the Court of his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> arrival; we must be <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to carry all our baggage by Land; the Presidents of the City after consultation had amongst themselves giving us this advice, which will be a very vast charge.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Gottenburgh, Novemb.</em> 18. 1653.</head>

<p><em>Weymouth</em> 2 <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 1653. A <em><reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg></em> Vessel went Saturday last of this Harbour homewards, but the same night a very great storm rose at Sea, and brought the ship back again upon our Coast, <reg orig="wher">where</reg> she was cast away in the <em>West-bay</em> between <em>Portland</em> and <em>Ratberry</em> all the men being cast away but the Shipman and two Passengers that were <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> going over to <em><reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg></em> or <em>Guernsey</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven the 2 of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>. There are several Vessels here bound for <em>Ireland</em> but stayed here by reason of the contrary winds; we have not of late heard any news from thence: The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> are still plying about the Isle of <em>Bundy</em>, and often come into the Severn mouth, where sometimes they catch some of our small Vessels.</p> 

<p>There is nothing more from our Fleet, but that part of them are about <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> and other places to the Westward, some lie out towards the Coast of <em><reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg></em>, to try if they can meet the <em>Brest</em> men of War, who have now got good ships, and have considerable strength at Sea.</p><pb n="15" />

<p>This week is arrived the Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em> consisting of about 40 sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg>, <reg orig="thred">thread</reg>, &amp;c. Therein come likewise 5 ships from the <reg orig="East-land">East land</reg>, as also one from <em><unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear></em> with Currents but has yet not come up the River.</p>

<p>The Dutch Commissioners, whom we mentioned before to be gone to <em>Gravesend</em> in order to take shipping for <em>Holland</em>, have not yet set sail but remain there, and have made some farther application to his Highness and his Council, which whether or no it will occasion their <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> back again to make an absolute agreement, a short time will discover.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Letters from <em>Holland</em> yesterday we had the certain Intelligence, That upon Tuesday last was seven night they had about <em>Amsterdam</em> a most <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> Thunder, Lightning, and Tempest, (as about the same time we had by other Letters was the like at <em><reg orig="Pembrook">Pembroke</reg></em> in <em>Wales</em>) and by this Thunder and Lightning there were about 500 Houses burnt and destroyed in and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Amsterdam, besides above 40 <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> Ships sunk in the Texell, and many other great Damages, the particulars whereof you shall have further by the next, when a more Exact <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg> comes.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is published an Excellent piece of <reg orig="Chronologie">Chronology</reg>, intituled <em>Calamus Mensurans</em>, The Measuring Reed, or Standard of Time, Containing an Exact Computation of years of the world, from the Creation to the destruction of <em>Jerusalem</em>, By <em>John <unclear>Stern</unclear></em>. Printed for <em>John Williams</em> at the Crown in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p><em>Hymen's Preludes</em>, or Love's <reg orig="Master-piece">Masterpiece</reg>, being the first and second part of that is much admired Romance, <reg orig="intitled">entitled</reg> <em>Cleopatra</em>; by <em>R. Loveday</em>: Also, the <unclear>Anal<!--6 other letters --></unclear> Exercises of Dr. <em>William Harvey</em> Professor of <reg orig="Physick">Physics</reg>, and Physician to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty, Concerning the motion of the Heart and Blood: both Printed for <em>Richard Lownds</em> at the White Lion in <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Churchyard.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>