<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc174">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 174</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The General <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of the English and the Dutch Fleets, and the service to which they are designed with all expedition. Certain Letters touching the proceedings of the enemy in Scotland. The raising of an army of 330 Companies, and 120 Troops of Horse. The last intelligence from <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, and the Duke of York. The concluding of a firm and lasting peace between England and Sweden with her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> absent. The last news out of Holland, and from several other parts.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> May 3. to <em>Wednesday</em> May 10. 1654.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, May 3.</i></head>

<p>This day <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Prides">Pride's</reg> Regiment (being about twelve hundred men marched from London to Barnet, in order to their long march for Scotland.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> from the King of Portugal had audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The Articles of Peace agreed upon betwixt his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the States General of Holland, came this day out in print, they are 33 in number, and so long that they cannot be contained within this sheet.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>By Letters from our Fleet at Stokes Bay, it was advertised, that Gen. Pen was come unto them, and that there would be a general <reg orig="Randezvouze">Rendezvous</reg> of the Fleet upon the Downs very speedily.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday May 4.</head>

<p>The Ambassador from the King of Denmark intimated to his Highness the Lord Protector, that he had Letters credential from the King his Master, &amp;c. whereupon His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> appointed a day to give him audience, and yesterday he came to Whitehall in his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> coach, attended by Sir Oliver Fleming Master of the Ceremonies; his Highness <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> forth, the Ambassador congratulated him in his place of Government, and seemed to acknowledge it a happiness that so much of the differences were taken up by the Treaty with the Dutch, and hoped all would conduce to a happy peace, to the advancement of the Protestant religion, and stopping the effusion of innocent <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>. This appears very fair, but he had something more of State affairs, which he imparted in writing unto his Highness, and will afterwards be taken into consideration.</p>

<p>The Yeomen of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Guard <unclear>wait</unclear> by turns <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, Mr. Ingoldsby, brother to Col. Ingoldsby, is made Captain of the Guard.</p>

<p>Many Arms are ordered to go for Ireland, the ship that carries them lies at Bulls Key in St. <reg orig="Katherines">Katherine's</reg>.</p>

<p>The East India Company have ordered that there shall be a general Court the tenth day of this instant May; at which time they are to consult in this time of peace, on the best ways they can for the advance of the East India trade.</p>

<p>Deal, May 4. We understand by a vessel that is come hither, that General Pen is come to the fleet with some private instructions from his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and that<pb n="2" /> within a few days there will be a general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> of our fleet upon the Downs: <reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> the narrow seas will be quiet and without danger of any acts of hostility betwixt the Hollanders and us (the Articles afterwards being in force) and if any Freebooters or <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> do appear, we shall take a course to sweep the English Coasts of such guests.</p>

<p>Leith 1 May. We have little of action but what you have heard already, for the enemy avoids a general <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> in hopes to make themselves stronger: But when they hear that England and Holland are <reg orig="ageed">agreed</reg> many will fall off from them: in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> some discontented persons, as well <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> as others, have <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> away to them, for which they may have time to repent hereafter.</p>

<p>A small Hoy went lately from hence for London, with goods and rich furniture belonging to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> May 5.</head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and her <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <reg orig="Protectresse">Protectress</reg> will go <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to Hampton Court.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for Approbation and Trial of Ministers at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> sate this day in debate of Presentations, and <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> they will sit upon Augmentations.</p>

<p>From Cows in the Isle of Wight May 4. A Bark being come hither out of France, advises, That in her way homewards she met two of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, who hear the Conquet had met about 10 sail of <reg orig="smal">small</reg> French ships, and had taken 5 of them, and were in pursuit of the rest being about 2 leagues from them, and very likely to take them. The Brest <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg> are very rife abroad, and have of late taken an English ship bound home from Morlex, laden with <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> going for London.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>An Additional Ordinance for the <reg orig="Exise">Excise</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance of the seventeenth of March last, intituled, <i>An Ordinance for continuing the Excise</i>, it is next after the rates therein specified, generally declared and provided, <i>That other goods and Merchandizes (except <reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg>, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of <reg orig="Brasse">Brass</reg> or Iron imported or to be <reg orig="imgorted">imported</reg> ) not specified or therein rated, should pay after the rate of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, according as the same are charged by the book of rates, for the Customs to be <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> by the first buyer one shilling.</i></p>

<p>Be it ordained, and it is hereby Ordained and declared by his Highness, with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That the said Clause be null and void, and instead thereof, be it hereby ordained and declared, That all other goods and Merchandizes mentioned in the book of Rates for the Customs, except <reg orig="Bulloin">Bullion</reg>, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron, and wools of sheep) imported or to be imported which are not in the said Rates of Excise, before or otherwise charged, shall hereafter pay excise after the rates of five pounds <em>per centum</em>, to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant or Importer, and the same is to be collected accordingly.</p>

<p>And to the end the whole receipts of the Excise may be the better reduced into one Cash, and the charge and number of Officers thereby retrenched, It is hereby ordained by authority aforesaid, That from and after the 25 of March last, the Revenue of the Excise shall be but one Receipt, and so <reg orig="accompted">accounted</reg> for, and that all receipts and <reg orig="accompts">accounts</reg> heretofore taken or kept of any payments of Excise or new Impost, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any additional Act, Ordinance, or Order of Parliament, and designed to any separate uses or uses whatsoever, shall from thenceforth cease, and be void, and be brought and reduced to one general Cash and <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> Revenue. Provided <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg>, that the <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> of all Fines and Forfeitures, imposed and received since the 25 of March last, or that hereafter shall be imposed and received, shall be still kept in an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> apart, and be paid out towards the <reg orig="mainteance">maintenance</reg> of <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, according to Ordnance of Parliament of the 13 of July 1647.</p>

<p>And it is hereby, for the further relief of <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, Ordained, That from and after the said 25 of March last, there shall be, out of the general Cash and Revenue of the Excise, allowed<pb n="4" /> the certain yearly sum of 26260 l. to be paid weekly by equal proportions out of the said <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Receipt unto such person or persons as is, are, or shall be appointed thereunto by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and be <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for <reg orig="imploying">employing</reg> and disposing thereof to the use aforesaid. Which said yearly sum of 26260 l. is to be in lieu of all and every sum and sums of money assigned by any Act, Ordinance or Order of Parliament out of any the receipts of the Excise, for relief of the said <reg orig="Widdows">Widows</reg> and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, other <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> of Fines and forfeitures before excepted; and the present Commissioners of the Excise, or any three of them, shall have power from time to time to issue out all moneys, either delivered over unto them, by the Commissioners preceding them, or which hath, or shall be received by them since the 25 of March last, according as they are or shall be directed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, or by Authority thereof. And the said Commissioners for Excise, and their Sub-Commissioners are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to make <reg orig="repaiment">repayment</reg> of the Excise to any person whatsoever, for any goods imported upon the exportation thereof, in such sort as the late Commissioners might have done before the 25 of March last, It appearing unto them, that the duty of the said Goods have been fully paid; any former Clause, Article, or Provision to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, May 6.</head>

<p>By Letters from Holland it is advertised, That there is great joy at the proclaiming of the peace between England and them, and that the States have sent out orders, for the calling in of Freebooters, and above two hundred sail of Merchants men are going to trade abroad.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Madrid</em> we hear, that the Spaniard is making great preparations for war, the same Letters that say their West India Fleet is very richly laden and expected at home the middle of June next.</p>

<p>The Letters from <reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg> say, that Francis Duke of Lorrain came to that City on the 4th of May, and after three days feasting and royal entertainment by the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> Leopoldus he set forward on his journey for Flanders.</p>

<p>Dalkeith Apr. 25. Things are very quiet in these parts, Middleton and Morgan are yet in the same posture in the North, <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> numbers do rather decrease <reg orig="then">than</reg> increase, many <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> go from him as others are flocking to him, and among the rest the Loughabrians. The Lord Craighall one of the Judges died at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> this day.</p><pb n="5" />

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, April 25. Intelligence was brought from the North on Saturday last, and met General <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg> at Dakeith, informing, that Middleton had <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg> out <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg>, and Southerland and himself too, and was making his way through the Hills, places which we supposed unpassable, to avoid engaging us: Wherefore <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan, who hath taken all opportunities he could lay hold on for that purpose, is like to be disappointed. The quarrel between the Earl of Glencairn, and Sir George Monroe (of which I doubt not but you have already had the particulars) hath occasioned further difference and many divisions amongst them, so that many of them are at Daggers drawing <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>. There was also great strife between Sir Arthur Forbes, the Lord Kenmore and Glengary: General Middleton hath sent Glengary with 500 foot into the West; his design is, as it is supposed, to force the people there and in the Western Islands to rise, for the inhabitants of Loughaber do refuse to rise, until they receive command from the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of Argyle, or his son the Lord Lorn. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan marched to Tain, and saw the Enemy, but could not get to them, for that he wanted Boats, and the water being broad and very impetuous; so that he is now come back to Dingwel to quarter. Middleton was very angry with Glencairn and the rest for marching into Southerland without Orders, for he would have had them slayed in <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>, to have kept open the <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>. But the naked truth of the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is, they durst not stay, fearing lest our horse and foot, which were not then far from them, should fall into their quarters.</p>

<p>Some Letters from Holland say, That the Royal party boast much of the good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> which Middleton hath had in Scotland, that of late there had been a great fight, wherein Middleton was crowned with victory, having<pb n="6" /> killed <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Morgen">Morgan</reg>. They also report, that a Spanish man of War hath seized upon an English Merchant ship, and carried her into Dunkirk.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 8.</head>

<p>From Portsmouth May 3. This day our Fleet was under sail in Stokes Bay and put forth to sea, we conceive they are gone for the Downs, there are yet some remaining here, which will soon be ready to follow the main fleet.</p>

<p>From Deal May 4. Here are arrived a great number of our <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, and the rest is expected <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, this being the place it is said for the general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>. Here are yet many <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, who will not venture to sea without a strong convoy, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the Letters of Mart be called in, General Pen is expected here on Tuesday next, or sooner.</p>

<p>To close up this week we had further the welcome news of the agreement between the Queen of <em>Swedeland</em> and our <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> the Lord Whitlock, as by Letters from Upsal April 8. whereof one in the words following. Sir, I sent unto you about a fortnight since, but having very little news in that letter, I was resolved to make you amends in this, (though in a few words) by acquainting you that our Treaty with the Queen of Swedeland is concluded, and the next week to be signed, I hope as well to the advantage of the Nation, as the particular satisfaction of my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, who (by that time you can receive this Letter) <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be advancing homeward, I hope that after our attendance here in a very hard winter, our tedious <reg orig="journies">journeys</reg> and voyages backward and forward, and bringing home with us the alliance of so considerable a people as Swedeland may be to England, we shall find a general welcome, at the least by all our friends.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, May 9.</head>

<p>This day we understood that about twenty Pinks and small ships are newly come into the River of Thames, with <reg orig="severall">several</reg> sorts of Merchandize, we have also a great number of Merchant men, going out some for the Canaries, others for <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> and other parts. <reg orig="To morrow">Tomorrow</reg> we hear that our fleet keep their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs, and the Dutch <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> near the Texel. The Brest men of war have done some late prejudice to us in the West, they rage exceedingly now, for that they think their time is short, we hear that a squadron of our Fleet are to sail Northward, to prevent the coming over into Scotland to the enemy, any arms, ammunition, or forces.</p>

<p>Admiral Van Trump is yet with his Squadron about the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>. You will shortly hear of some design, that the gallant Fleets of these high and considerable Commonwealths, will fall upon some honourable action.</p>

<p>By Letters from Newcastle it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that a great fleet of Colliers, are laden coming away for London.</p>

<p>The last Letters from Paris say, that <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and the Duke of York are yet there, the news of the peace with Holland makes their friends backwarder in supplying them <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever they were; neither is the difference between <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and Rupert taken up yet; Cardinal de Retz remaineth a close prisoner at <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>, we hear of an English Merchant ship cast away by storm <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <reg orig="Sicilia">Sicily</reg>.</p>

<p>The Marshal de Grance hath raised an army of 330 foot Companies, and 120 Troops,</p>

<p>Several Letters to Merchants and others confirm the intelligence, that a firm and lasting peace is now concluded betwixt England and Sweden.</p>

<p>The Articles will not be published before the Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> Whitlock is returned into England, which if the wind serve may be about a <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> or six weeks.</p>

<p>There is not any news yet of any such great fight in Scotland, as some have reported, for the enemy keep up in the hills and places <reg orig="inaccessable">inaccessible</reg>, where our men cannot come at them for the present, but if they would come out and fight a quick period would be put to that business.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>