<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc172">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 172</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The making stay of our English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships by the Governor of St. Mallo's. And the taking of 300 Chests of <reg orig="mony">money</reg> on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> last. The heads of the Ordinance of Grace and Pardon to the people of Scotland, and the names of 30 Dukes, <reg orig="Marquesses">Marquises</reg>, Earls, Lords, and Knights, who are excepted of having any benefit of the said pardon. The late actions between Col. Morgan and Gen. Middleton. The proclaiming the Articles of Peace between England and Holland. The great joy at the Court in France, and the late Qs. going from thence. With several transactions of his Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> April 19. to <em>Wednesday</em> April 26. 1654.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>April 19.</em></i></head>

<p>This Monsieur de Grave, who is the resident here in England, from the Duke of Guelders had Audience from the Lord Protector, there was then present divers Lords of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, the chief Secretary of State (his other attendants) at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, when the Resident first came up to speak to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> he congratulated him in the Place wherein he is, and after that imparted some matters of State, which is not yet fit to be communicated to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>The chief part of our intelligence for many weeks together, hath been to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the people of this Commonwealth concerning the Treaty betwixt England and Holland, which you <reg orig="wil">will</reg> discern to be fully ended and brought to a period, if you read this <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> Ordinance or Proclamation.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas a Peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and the States General of the United Provinces of the Low Countries. And whereas it is agreed, That the publication thereof shall be made on both parts on Wednesday next being the six and twentieth of this instant April; from which time, restitution is to be made of all Ships that shall be taken on either side, after twelve days within these Seas, and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. Vincent, after six weeks; and from thence within the Mediterranean sea, and to the &aelig;quinoctial, after the space of eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: which several places were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this Commonwealth, and to all others whom it may concern, <reg orig="with in">within</reg> the Dominions thereof; to the end they may have warning, to provide for their own safety, and not to expose their Ships to danger within the several and respective times aforesaid.</p>

<head level="3">W. <reg orig="Iessop">Jessop</reg> Clerk of the Council.</head>

<head level="3">Thursday April 20.</head>

<p>Dalkeith, April 13. 1654. On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning last a party of 40 of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemies'</reg> horse, or more, came in view of our <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Kilcrooch, and passed by it. Lieutenant,<pb n="2" /> Hunt that commanded there, drew out with a party, but could not overtake them, till they were got to Aberfaste, took 7 prisoners, 11 horse, 20 Cloaks, and many Cloak-bags full of plunder, which the Enemy scattered the better to make their escape: We rescued two prisoners which they had brought out of the borders of Cumberland to the hills; Lieut. Col. Irwin commanded, and brought up the Rear. The Lords Forrester and Dudhopp are in Athol, but bring no further advantage to their party, <reg orig="then">than</reg> their persons and attendants. Since the two defeats given to <reg orig="Mac Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg> party, he is gone away, being much suspected by some of that party, that he hath betrayed his party to us, which makes many of their Officers begin to capitulate, and to desire terms to come in. The 9 instant Col. Morgan was at Dingwel in Ross, <reg orig="with in">within</reg> a mile whereof the Enemy must march, or else engage, otherwise go such a way as never horse went, over Hills and Rocks. Their number is 4000 horse and foot, ours about 2200, our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are very hearty, and wish nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> an Engagement.</p>

<p>Inverness, April 16. The Enemy in Caithness have endeavoured all they could to raise that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>; but the people are backward in <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with them, fearing lest the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> which is at Sinclair Castle, commanded by Cap. Langrish, of Col. <reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg> Regiment, should punish their <reg orig="forwardnesse">forwardness</reg> after <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> march out of <reg orig="Caithneis">Caithness</reg>, wherefore for their encouragement, Maj. Gen. Dyal with a party of foot, and 100 horse is ordered to sit down before it for the taking it in, which is conceived will not easily be achieved by them, the place being naturally strong, and a vessel within these few days being sent from hence with 3 <reg orig="moneths">month's</reg> provision and ammunition; so that they are, with what they had in store, well provided for at least six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>The <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> about Ruthen is at present free from the enemy; the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Ruthen Castle, Capt. Hill of <reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg> Regiment, carried thirty horse load of necessaries for his <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>. Col. Morgan marched from this place on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, he having drawn a party of foot out of this <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those forces he brought from Aberdeen, so that he lies with about eleven or twelve hundred Horse and Dragoons, and a considerable party of Foot, betwixt the Enemy, and the <unclear>Passes</unclear> they must needs march through, if they intend to move out of this North corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, or otherwise break or disband those Forces they have gathered, there being no way left them to avoid meeting with <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan, but through such inaccessible bounds, as it is impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their foot, it being exceeding Mountainous, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> they are in will not long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a few days will give us an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of some Action betwixt him and Middleton; what the <reg orig="successe">success</reg> will be the Lord Knows, in whose hands are all the corners of the earth.</p>

<p>By another <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> dated April 17, thus. We have little news here but <reg orig="whats">what's</reg> in expectation. Morgan and Middleton have continued at an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> distance from each other for some days past, and 'tis conceived that the little Colonel hath some advantage of him in respect of ground and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> endeavour by all means to engage him, though his number at present be much <reg orig="inferiour">inferior</reg> to his. In the <reg orig="mean while">meanwhile</reg>, there is many dissolute persons from several parts run to the Enemy. One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that convoyed ammunition and some <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships hither, in her return off from Dunbar was confronted with 7 Dutch ships, and after a hot skirmish boarded, and carried away; two light Vessels that went with her made their escape, and brought the news to Leith.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> April 21.</head>

<p>Plymouth April 16. Wednesday last Captain Potter Commander of the Constant Warwick (who three weeks since brought in Beach) did bring in hither another of the Brest <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, viz. The Bridget <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a small vessel of 4 guns, but one of the neatest things, and the best Sailor that hath been known. Beach and Jones say (who are now together lamenting their <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>, and bemoaning their misfortune as they call it) that Captain Potter hath taken two of the principal <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that belong to Brest.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>Tuesday last the Portsmouth, Middleborough, and Falmouth <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> met with 48 sail of <reg orig="French men">Frenchmen</reg> upon their own Coast, 24 of them were ships of force, and the other great vessels all bound for the New found land; there was an hot fight for the space of five hours in which time there were three of the best ships sunk, but most of the men which were alive saved by our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, there are four taken, one of which is brought in hither, the other three are brought in at Foy, they have nothing in them but provisions and some salt. I cannot learn of any men we have slain, but some wounded, neither have we sustained much damage in our shipping.</p>

<p>Further from Paris April 25. In answer to yours concerning the little Queen, and her son the <unclear>titulary</unclear> King of Scots, thus much at present; Three days since she went from hence, having two days before taken her leave of the King and Court, there went with her, her two sons, Pr. Rupert, and some others, in all about 12 Coaches; some say she intends for Orleans, others to the Duke her brother at his house near Blois. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> gone to convoy her on her way, and to return, but not yet quite to leave France as reported.</p>

<p>Deal, April 21. This afternoon is arrived here the <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> who doth return into Holland to carry to the States General the ratification of the peace, signed and sealed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, which upon signification of their receiving, will be suddenly proclaimed both in England and Holland. There is brought into this Road three Dutch prizes, whereof one was a ship bound for the East Indies, and the other two of good value: there is also brought into Harwich two Dutch prizes, which came from Norway, and some <unclear>Busses</unclear> we hear are taken by a private man of war, and carried into Yarmouth, having some fish in them, but not fully laden.</p>

<p>By an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from the Fleet riding in Stokes-Bay, it is advertised, That 100 sail of lusty men of war, viz. 50 English, and as many Dutch, are designed for the <reg orig="Straights">Straits</reg>, the Indies, and Levant Seas; and that valiant General <reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg> is to be <reg orig="commissionated">commissioned</reg> for this famous enterprise, on the English part; It is likewise said, that young Tromp is to go Admiral over the Dutch Fleet <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> as aforesaid. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, and till further Order from his Highness and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, our Fleet ride at anchor in Stokes Bay.</p>

<p>It is certified from Venice, that the General Delfino hath received a defeat by the Turks in Dalmatia, at the siege of Clim; but the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> not so great as was at first reported.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> April 22.</head>

<p><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector taking into consideration, how much it might conduce to the glory of God, and the Peace and welfare of the people of this whole Island, that after all those late and unhappy wars and differences, the people of Scotland should be united with the people of England, into one Commonwealth: For perfecting of which union, it is ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That all the people of Scotland, and the Isles of Orkney and <reg orig="Shethland">Shetland</reg>, and of all the Dominions and Territories belonging unto Scotland, are and shall be, and are hereby incorporated into, constituted, established, declared and confirmed one Commonwealth with England, and in every Parliament to be held successively, thirty persons shall be called from, and serve for Scotland.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, that all the people of Scotland, <em>&amp;c.</em> be discharged of all Fealty, Homage, Service and Allegiance, which is or shall be pretended due unto any of the issue and posterity of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> late King of England.</p>

<p>And also Saint <em><reg orig="Andrews">Andrew's</reg></em> <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> from henceforth is to be born in the Arms of this Commonwealth, as a <reg orig="badg">badge</reg> of this Union.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained that all Forfeitures, Escheats, Simple, or of life, rent Bastardy, and last heir, which heretofore Escheated, Forfeited, and fell to the King, Lords of Regality, or other Superiors, shall from henceforth fall Escheat, and forfeit to the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth for the time being.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> April 17.</head>

<p>From Paris they write, that there hath been great store of Masking and Plays at Court of late, which being now<pb n="6" /> over, they begin to go forward with businesses more <reg orig="sollid">solid</reg> and in particular in that touching the grievances of the Protestant Princes, and to put some money (promised) into <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg> Pocket, then he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he will be gone from them.</p>

<p>The Queen of Sweden seems to hold her resolution to resign up her Crown, and the Treaty goeth on fairly touching the affairs with England.</p>

<p>By Letters out of Flanders it is certified, that the Duke of Lorrain is still kept in custody by the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg>. The Army which was under his command are yet in their quarters, Duke Francis of Lorrain the second Brother, is <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> expected there, to take upon him the command of that Army which his Brother had, and then no doubt he will be courted very high by both the Spaniard and the French.</p>

<p>From France thus. The <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> de St. Geniez, field Marshal in his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Armies is come to <reg orig="Phillipsburgh">Phillipsburg</reg> where he is to be <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, the former Commander having resigned him the place according to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Orders thereupon. We hear from Flanders that the <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of Cullen, and the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> Leopoldus, have had a meeting at Louvain, tarrying there about two days; the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> at his departure, presented him with some rich <reg orig="Tapistry">Tapestry</reg>, and four of the best horses. We have by Letters from Sedan, that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <unclear>Jamers</unclear> having made a design with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Mouson to beat up the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters at Witton in the Province of <reg orig="Luxenburgh">Luxemburg</reg>, they carried their on so gallantly, that the several Troops there quartered, were for the most part slain, and the rest taken prisoners with a company of Spanish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, who were left for the guard of that Town.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, April 25.</head>

<p>An Ordinance of Pardon and free Grace to the people of Scotland, came this day out in print. It is something long, and therefore the Heads will be the more acceptable to such as cannot go to the price to purchase it at all.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Some Heads of the Ordinance of Grace and Pardon to the people of Scotland.</i></head>

<p>I. That all persons of the Scottish Nation, of what degree or quality soever they or any of them are, (except the persons in the said Ordinance excepted) shall be, from and after the first of May, 1654, freed, acquitted, and discharged of all Forfeitures, Pains, and Penalties whatsoever, for any matter or thing by them committed or done, by Sea or Land in relation to the late War.</p>

<p>II. The Persons, and Estates excepted out of this Ordinance, are these, <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart eldest son of the late King, James Stuart, James Duke of Hamilton, William late Duke of Hamilton, John Earl of Crawford Lindsey, James Earl of <reg orig="Callender">Calendar</reg>, the Earl of Kelly, John Earl of Lawderdale, John Earl of Lowdon, the Earl of Seaforth, the Earl of Athol, Viscount Kenmore, the Lord Lorn eldest son of the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of Argyle, Lord Machlin, Lord Montgomery, George Lord Spynie, Lord Cranston, Lord <reg orig="Sincleer">Sinclair</reg>, Thomas Dalyel, John Middleton, James Viscount Newburgh, Lord Bargany, Sir Thomas Thomson, James Edmeston Laird of <unclear>Womat</unclear>, Lord Napier, William Earl of Glencarn, James Lord Mordington.</p>

<p>III. All persons are excepted out of this Ordinance, that have been at any time since the first of May, 1652. or now is in Arms in Scotland, against this Commonwealth, saving the benefit to such persons, as can claim any by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of Articles of War.</p>

<p>This day we had news from St Mallo in France, that the Governor hath made stay of all the English Merchants there.</p>

<p>A man come from Rye yesterday, affirmed, that about <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the last week a ship was brought prize in thither, laden with 300 Chests of Money, besides great quantity of Sugars, Nutmegs, and other Spices; so that Sugars were sold, some for 3 d. some 4d. the pound, and Nutmegs, some for 2 d. some for 3 d. the hundred, &amp;c.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop 1654</em>.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>