<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc165">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 165</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The Conferences and Speeches between his Highness the Lo. Protector, and the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> from the States General of Holland. Another fight in Scotland, between a party of the English, and some of the L. <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> forces, and the number <reg orig="disperced">dispersed</reg> and taken prisoners. Several prizes taken at Sea. Letters from Ireland of the L. <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg> arriving there. An <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> from the K. of Denmark. The Last Letters out of France and Sweden. An Ordinance of his Highness the L. Protector &amp; his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. News from the Assizes at Salisbury, and variety of other intelligence from several parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> March 1. to <em>Wednesday</em> March 8. 1654.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, March 1.</head>

<p>An <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> (or <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Messenger from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> of Flanders, had Audience before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector; he spake much in relation to Trade, but nothing affective, as to the concluding of a Peace with Holland: The whole matter of his Credentials are to be taken into further consideration.</p>

<p>This day came Letters from Scotland, touching the whole proceedings between the English and the Highlanders, which we had in a Letter from Mr. Hill, Secretary in chief to <pb n="1" />Col. Morgan, who is Commander in chief of the English forces in the North of Scotland.</p>

<head level="3">SIR,</head>

<p>Thought good to acquaint you, that Col. Tho. Morgan, Commander in Chief of the forces in the North of Scotland, understanding of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> approach within 24 miles of this Town, he drew forth about 1100 horse, dragoons, and foot, and upon the 9 instant after a very hard march, met with the forces under the <reg orig="comand">command</reg> of Glencarn and Kenmore, about the number of 1400 horse and foot: where after a short dispute, upon most base ground, he put them to a retreat, and forced them to a very strong <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg>, which 40 resolute men might have kept against 4000. yet so cow'd were the enemy, that in a short time Providence ordered it so, that we recovered the <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg>, and in time put them to the rout, pursued them through such invincible <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> (as were the truth of them related, would be imagined incredible) which never English men marched over before that time: there was about 120 of the enemy slain, 17 taken prisoners, about 80 <reg orig="hors">horse</reg>, most of their Arms, all their Ammunition, Bag and Baggage, all which the Lord was pleased to carry on with great facility to us, for there was not so much as one man of ours wounded, and we had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 2 horses slain: there was indeed one of Captain <reg orig="Merimons">Merimon's</reg> troop shot through the head by one of his fellow <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> accidentally before the Engagement. The next day, having intelligence that the enemy had possessed a strong house called Kildrummy, where the Earl of Marr dwelt, who afterwards pretended he was <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by the enemy; yet so just are Scotchmen, that now they begin to appear in their colours, they through our lenity being grown to such a <reg orig="heighth">height</reg>, as that they make good their old Character, Turks and Scots coequal.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>We marched thither and summoned it, an account you may have in the annexed passages between the commander in chief, and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, as also the Articles for the surrender: after the said Garrison was reduced, we marched to our winter quarters to this Town, where we was <reg orig="welcommed">welcomed</reg> with news from Johnstons, that col. Daniel with a considerable party out of Johnstons, and Dundee, resolved to make an attempt upon Dunkel, being informed that there was a considerable party of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> horse in that Town, and that Athol, and Forbus had <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> a <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> of about 60 persons in an old House in that place, and had victualled the same well for two <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p>

<p>Upon Wednesday the 15 instant by break of day col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg> forlorns fell into Dunkel with their Scouts, having <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> a quarter of an hour too short of <reg orig="surprizing">surprising</reg> the Town; and for their escape they were beholding to the <reg orig="nearnesse">nearness</reg> of the Hills; yet as quick as they were we took 40 of their horses, and after 1 hour and a half won the house, gaining room after room, in which time they were reduced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> upon terms for life, their number with those that were taken belonging to their horse, is about 120 and 4 or 5 killed, besides what is wounded, the enemy looking on, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Daniel</em> blew up the house, and carried the prisoners to Johnston.</p>

<p>Upon <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> night being 17 instant, was one Captain Thompson, and <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> Col. <reg orig="Ramstes">Ramstes'</reg> <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> came down with 5 or 6 more into the Lowlands to plunder horses, and <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Hellen, <reg orig="Lievt.">Lieut.</reg> to Major Bramston, having intelligence thereof marched forth with 7 more Dragoons with him, out of the <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> of Thornston, and after he had pursued them ten miles through the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, catched them about 5 in the morning, killed one of them, and brought the rest prisoners to Dunotter Castle.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>Sir, these blows are very seasonable, for the enemy were very high, and <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> all with fire and sword, that would not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. I am apt to <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> that the peace with the Dutch will vanish like smoke, though notwithstanding these Brushes they give out high language, and say that they resolve to gain their credit. I hope to hear from you and remain,</p>

<p>27. Febr. 1653. <em>Your affectionate Nephew;</em></p>

<p><em>I.H.</em></p>

<head level="3">Thursday March 2.</head>

<p>From Paris we hear that the strong garrison of Beffort is surrendered to Marshal de la Ferte, the Defendants had conditions to march away to <reg orig="Luxenburgh">Luxembourg</reg>. Here is talk of sending another <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> for England; his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> (your Lord Protector) is looked upon here as a person very considerable; if the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> comes not very speedily, the Credentials of the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> that is in England already <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be renewed.</p>

<p><i>An Order passed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for reviving the <reg orig="Iurisdiction">Jurisdiction</reg> of the County Palatine of Lancaster, and for holding an Assizes there: to this effect.</i></p>

<p>That all <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> and Jurisdictions belonging to the County Palatine of Lancaster, and the inhabitants <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, be, and are hereby revived and continued, as fully and amply to all intents and purposes, as the same were at any time before the tenth day of October last. And that all actions as well real as personal, and all other actions <reg orig="mixt">mixed</reg> or otherwise, Pleas, Precepts, Writs, <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg>, Demurrers Recognizances, Fines, Recoveries, and all other proceedings, matters and things, of what nature or quality soever, now depending in any Court within the said County Palatine, or there commenced or prosecuted since the said tenth day of October, shall be and stand revived, continued, and of full force and effect in the Law, to all intents, constructions and purposes. And that all <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg>, Pleas, Demurrers, and proceedings on every such Action, Actions, <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg>, or Plaints, which were there depending the said tenth day of October last, or commenced or prosecuted there at any time since, shall stand good and effectual, and be proceeded in according to the Laws of the Nation, and the proceedings used within the said County Palatine of Lancaster.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>And it is further Ordained, that Matthew Hales one of the Justices of the Court of Common Pleas at Westminster, and Hugh Wyndham <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at Law, shall be Justices of Assizes, and <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>-delivery within the said County Palatine; and that the said Justices, or either of them shall and may act, do and perform all matters and things, as well concerning Criminal as Common Pleas, and all other Pleas and <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg> whatsoever, in such manner and form as any other Justice or Justices of Assizes at Lancaster have usually acted, done and performed at any time heretofore, and the Commissioners for keeping the Seal of the said County Palatine of Lancaster hereafter named, is hereby authorised and appointed to issue forth to the said Justices, for the execution of the premises, such Commission or Commissions as in such cases have been heretofore in the said County Palatine used and accustomed. And that Thomas Fell Esquire, be, and is hereby made and appointed Commissioner for keeping of the Seal of the said County Palatine of Lancaster, and shall have all such powers as any <reg orig="Chancellour">Chancellor</reg> or Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County Palatine hath formerly lawfully used and exercised concerning the same, till further Order.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> March 3.</head>

<p>This day the Lord Newport and Yongstal the two <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> extraordinary from the States General of the united Provinces, came from Gravesend to London attended with many rich Barges, and at their landing there attended his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coach, and many other rich Coaches to the number of 60 Coaches, all with 6 horses a piece, in which Coaches the said <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, their attendance, and many English Lords and Gentlemen, rode through the city to Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his house in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard, which was trimmed up very stately for them.</p>

<p>From Flanders they write, that the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> doth yet retain in custody the Duke of Lorrain, neither are all his plundering and thieving Regiments able to rescue him out of the Castle wherein he is now a prisoner.</p>

<p>From Milford Haven the 28 February: Here are some lately come from Ireland, who telleth us no more as for news, but that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Montagne</em>, there are great numbers of Irish ready to take shipping for Flanders, to serve the King of Spain, but yet there are still small parties of Tories, who lie lurking in the woods and <reg orig="Boggs">Bogs</reg>, and do much disquiet the peace of <pb n="5" />the Country, which is still in great want of people to inhabit those parts. The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is safe arrived in Ireland. From Deal the 2 of March two days since all the Merchants ships as were here, and in Dover Road set sail, having a fair wind to go for France, and other parts to the Southward; also several convoys to bring them to their distinct places, there hath been likewise <reg orig="som">some</reg> of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> here, but are gone all again Westward, where we hear our Fleet rides still near St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, by the Isle of Wight.</p>

<p>This afternoon the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> had Audience given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, the <reg orig="Roome">Room</reg> was richly hung with hangings, and a rich chair of State set for the Lord Protector, and Chairs on the one side for the <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, the entertainment was stately, and gallant, and the subject of this Audience was partly Congratulatory to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and to declare the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of their <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to make and settle a firm peace, and to <reg orig="renue">renew</reg> the old friendship which hath been for many years between the two Nations: And that to this purpose their Superiors the 7 United Provinces, do all of them agree and consent to the agreement or peace between us and them, which they, their <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> extraordinary, are <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>; desiring a speedy Cessation of arms, and that all acts of hostility may cease on both sides, so that undoubtedly, some few circumstances being considered on, all will be concluded, and a peace fully <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, as we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be able to give you further the particulars by the next.</p>

<p>There is also an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> we hear landed from Denmark, to make application to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> upon the <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of the Dutch Treaty, his name is <em>Williamson</em>.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, March 6.</head>

<p>It is confirmed by Letters this day from Scotland, that <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> our horse are in the Northern parts of that Nation, Sir Arthur Forbs, who is again recovered of his wounds, is marched Southwards, to see what parties he can find <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg>, or what booty he can get about <reg orig="Lenox">Lennox</reg>, or Tivesdale.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Earl of Glencarn is in the North, and not daring to hazard all his strength on the uncertainty of one <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, doth divide his forces into <reg orig="severel">several</reg> parties, that he might thereby be enabled to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the importunity of their bellies, and encourage or enforce the <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> to <reg orig="encrease">increase</reg> their Levies; the fiery Crosses have had their run, and whirled from place to place in several <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>, but to no effect. It is <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> indeed to consider what an impression any thing supernatural hath in all ages left in the minds of the common <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>: to demur therefore from the Levying of new forces, it hath been reported wheresoever the Recruits are to be raised, That a Gentleman in the County of Fife had a Vision, in which he was admonished by a young man, with all speed to <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> himself to Glencarn his kinsman, and to acquaint him with the anger of God to fall on him and all his forces, if they pursued such destructive courses. The Gentleman disobedient to the Angel on the first night, was struck dumb the second, because he <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> not his voice as he was commanded. This report hath  been of more efficacy to trouble the Levies, and discourage the old <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> of Glencarn, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the certain arrival of our Regiments, and of 3 ships laden with Tents, <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> &amp; all manner of provisions both for life &amp; death.</p>

<p>Mr. Feak, and Mr. Vavaser Powel have made their addresses for their liberty; some Ministers have been with them, and advised them to be sensible of their mistakes.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, March 7.</head>

<p>By Letters from Newcastle it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that a Fleet of Colliers are lading there, and almost ready to set sail for London, but they make the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> because they have hopes that peace will suddenly be proclaimed throughout England and Holland, in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> many Freebooters and <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> do ply up and down upon the Northern Coasts, they took a small English vessel lately.</p>

<p>The English Fleet rideth near to the Isle of Wight, and many more lately manned and victualled are newly come unto them; we hear that a squadron are designed for the Irish seas, to clear those Coasts of the Brest men of War, which have done some great mischief thereabouts lately.</p>

<p>The Letters from new Sarum say, that this day seven night my Lo. Chief Justice Rolls, and Mr. <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> Glyn, came into the City attended by the Sheriff, and many Gentlemen of the Country, the next day being the first of March the Assizes began there, and his Lordship made a very learned speech to the great satisfaction of the Country, under the present government.</p>

<p>His <reg orig="HIghnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have met again in order to the perfecting of the peace betwixt the two Commonwealths of England and Holland, and many sweet Speeches have been made by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as also by the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>, both at their first audience at the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house and since, and it is thought the Articles will suddenly be sealed.</p>

<p>The Letters this Post from Scotland make mention, that by reason of the <reg orig="coldnesse">coldness</reg> of the season, and the great store of snow lately fallen in the Northern parts, Col. Morgan returned back (from pursuing the enemy) to Aberdeen, but a party of ours have had another <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> with a party of about 60 of <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> horse they fought at the first very stoutly, but soon turned their backs and fled to save themselves, in this fight we took one <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> and about 20 more prisoners, their main design at the present is to rob and spoil what they can, and therefore divide themselves into divers small parties.</p>

<p>Further from Ireland thus: upon Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>, Col. Hewson, and other Officers coming to Dublin, the Lord Deputy Fleetwood and the rest of the Officers there, congratulated their coming safe over the boisterous sea (which was very tempestuous during some part of their passage) and they declared a great deal of joy and satisfaction as in relation to the present Government under the Lord Protector.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>