<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc5">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Diurnall or Occurrences, Issue 5</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg>:</head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="1">OCCURRENCES</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em>. 29. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>June</em> 5. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 29.</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector signed his Warrant for issuing forth of Writs of Summons for another Parliament, to begin the third of September next, none are to be chosen, or presume to be Electors, that aided, assisted or abetted in any war against the Parliament, since Jan. 1641. With this proviso that they have not since given sufficient satisfaction of their integrity by their service for the Parliament, neither are any such to be chosen or Electors, who had any hand in the late Rebellion in Ireland.</p>

<p>A motion hath been made already this <reg orig="Terme">Term</reg> for another <em>Habeas Corpus</em> for <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Col. <em>John Lilburn</em> in the upper Bench, but not granted for the present.</p>

<p>A great debate was had by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Council about the reviving of the Ordinance for continuing the Commissioners of the Admiralty,<pb n="1" /> and navy, according to the most exact and serviceable way for the Commonwealth that hath been known.</p>

<p>There is another Ordinance under consideration for the casting out of scandalous Ministers, <i>many are already under that notion put by.</i> Something is offered against a Minister in <em>Essex</em>, which chargeth him in matter of Doctrine, and other things scandalous. Also that he instigated another which he admitted into the pulpit to call the Parishioners (in his way of Preaching) Rogues and <reg orig="Rascalls">Rascals</reg>, &amp;c. And being complained of to himself, he said that he would preach them all out of the Church, since which reviling Speeches few have come to hear him, and being marrying of a couple, he uttered many very lascivious words.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May. 30.</head>

<p>From <em>Ireland</em> thus; There hath been a great noise about the setting out of the Lands here which are allotted to the English, as if we got great profit by it, but who <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> whether we shall live to receive any; although we need not <reg orig="feare">fear</reg> but if the taxes were mitigated, there would <reg orig="soone">soon</reg> be Planters to improve the earth, all which we hope will be accomplished in a short time, for we are told his Highness the Lord Protector will take such a course, that we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not much longer pay the full fourth part of our Estates both real and <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, which hath for some time been exacted in this Country.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector and his Council set forth an Ordinance for the preservation of the works and <reg orig="draines">drains</reg> of the great <reg orig="Levell">Level</reg> of the <reg orig="Fenns">Fens</reg> in <em>Lincolnshire</em>, &amp;c. Giving power to the participants to levy the taxes usual for <reg orig="repaireing">repairing</reg> the same, and such as wilfully destroy the works in any place are to be accounted and adjudged felons.</p>

<p>This day the Commissioners appointed by the Articles of peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> to treat and determine about the business of <em>Amboina</em> (and other thing mentioned in<pb n="2" /> the said Articles) meet at the place appointed, which is <em>Guildhall London</em>; unto which place they were accommodated by the Lord <em>Strickland</em> and others of his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> Council, and after their Commission was read, the Commissioners desired to know whether it might not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> enlarged to the giving of them power to treat and debate the business in some other place, if they should see cause; and it was answered that his Highness and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> should be moved to grant them liberty to <reg orig="adjorn">adjourn</reg> to some other place for a time, if it were thought convenient.</p>

<p>Letters this day confirmed a report we had before that the Covent and part of <em>Gravelin</em> was burnt. The Matron and three Nuns are said to extinguish in the fire.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, May. 31.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>Goldsmiths-Hall, May 30 1654.</i></head>

<p>Whereas in the 28 Article of agreement betwixt his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions <reg orig="therunto">thereunto</reg> belonging, and the Lords the States General of the <em>United Provinces</em> of the <em>Netherlands</em>; it is ordered and agreed, that restitution shall be made of all and singular the English ships and goods seized and detained within the Dominions of the King of <em>Denmark</em>, since the 18 of <em>May</em>, 1652. And whereas in the same Article <em>Edward Winslow, James <reg orig="Russel">Russell</reg>, John Becks</em>, and <em>William Vandererussni</em>, are appointed to arbitrate, <reg orig="Judg">Judge</reg>, and determine <reg orig="indefferently">indifferently</reg> as well on the part of his Highness, as the said States General, the losses and <reg orig="dammages">damages</reg> sustained by the English; Let all men take notice that are concerned, that the said Arbitrators by their respective Commissions under the broad Seal of either Commonwealth respectively met this at Goldsmiths Hall, where the said Commissions were read, and the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty, being there present (according to the true intent and <reg orig="meaining">meaning</reg> of his Highness, and the Lords the<pb n="3" /> States general of the united Provinces, by the express words of their Commissions) did administer an oath unto the Commissioners aforesaid; which done, the Commissioners did enter upon the work, and do hereby give notice thereof to all that are concerned therein, that so they may make their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective applications to them sitting at <em>Goldsmiths Hall</em>.</p>

<p><i>ROBERT DAVIE, Register to the said Commissioners.</i></p>

<p>Several <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> have been spent upon examination and finding out the depth of the plot; <i>Tudore the quondam</i> Apothecary (who was at the first apprehended) being brought again from the Tower to Whitehall to be examined, pretended occasion to go to the house of office in the garden, and having the advantage of a low water made an escape: but some others have <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg> much of the <reg orig="designe">design</reg>, and that one <em>Wharton</em> on <reg orig="Blackfriers">Blackfriars</reg> should have proclaimed <em>Charles Stuart</em>, and that a party of horse did <reg orig="way-lay">waylay</reg> his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> as he was top return from Hampton Court, but by providence coming back by water, their intentions were frustrate. Since our last divers persons of eminency have been apprehended amongst whom the Lord <em>Mountegle</em> (a letter to whose predecessor was a means to discover the great Gunpowder plot) as also one <em>Ashburnham, Savage</em>, and <em>Cranborn</em>. <em>Ashburnham</em> is sent to the Tower, others are released, and some still upon examination.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 1.</i></head>

<p>From Amsterdam thus. Some of your Newcastle Coals and some ships of provisions which we wanted are come hither out of England to a good market, and all things are quiet, except the tongues of some discontented persons which can hardly be tamed. We hear there is a Messenger <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg> from the States General with a message to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of England, &amp;c. The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is not known, but it is conceived that it is to intercede for some little qualification of the Article touching the extirpation of the family of <em>Aurange</em>.</p><pb n="4" />

<p><i>A Summary of the desires of all honest prisoners that are desirous to pay their just debts, as the same was presented by Captain <em>Roger Prichard</em> to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, on the prisoners behalf, and also to Judge <em>Atkins</em>, and Baron <em>Thorp</em>, and Mr. <reg orig="Attorny">Attorney</reg> <em>Prideaux</em> to whom it was referred by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who desire that as many of them as shall be thought fit, may be inserted in the new Ordinance.</i></p>

<p>1. That the late Act for the relief of Creditors and poor prisoners, be absolutely nulled and repealed, or set aside for the incompetence of the Judges, and sundry inconveniences <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, and that care be taken to elect fitter men in the new, and that no inroad be made therein, contrary to the ancient and known laws of the land, the benefit whereof the prisoner claims as his birthright, as well as others.</p>

<p>2. That the badge and brand of Bankrupt be omitted in the new Ordinance <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> it be upon such as were adjudged Bankrupts, by former Statutes, and that there be a course to make all men pay their debts as well as prisoners.</p>

<p>3. That 6 <reg orig="months">month's</reg> time be also therein allowed prisoners at least, to seek out their own chapmen with liberty in the mean time, especially to all such as shall find sufficient security to the Gaoler, or some Judges of record to pay their debts, for which they stand charged in execution, or to return to prison at six <reg orig="moneths">month's</reg> end.</p>

<p>4. That prisoners for contempt have the same liberty, giving security, to answering, or refusing to be examined then upon security, to answer or to be examined with time, or to return at six <reg orig="moneths">month's</reg> end to prison, there to remain till they shall answer or be examined or perform the decree, this is desired because many are <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> and brought into prison unjustly upon this account.</p>

<p>5. That poor prisoners be forthwith discharged upon their Oaths, especially such as shall find security to return again at 6 <reg orig="months">month's</reg> end, during which time the Creditor may inquire of their estates, and secure the same, if any be found and have the same among them, and then to be quite discharged, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they forswear themselves, <reg orig="til">till</reg> they shall get estates.</p>

<p>6. That <reg orig="Out-lawries">Outlawries</reg> be not pleaded <reg orig="againg">against</reg> prisoners for debt, and that they may be discharged of course putting in Bail to answer the suit.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>7. That where a <reg orig="prisoners">prisoner's</reg> whole estate is to be sold, a 4 or 5. part be preserved for wife and children (it being <reg orig="Haberdashers">Haberdasher's</reg> <reg orig="Halls">Hall's</reg> mercy) and that none be sold under 20. <reg orig="years">year's</reg> purchase.</p>

<p>One Colonel <em>Cromwell</em> (of alliance to his Highness the Lord Protector, whose command is in Holland, and came lately over) was entertained by the Dutch Ambassadors at their house in Channel Row.</p>

<p>Plymouth 19. May. Above 20. empty <reg orig="vessells">vessels</reg> of the French are sent in hither by some of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, which came hither to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> these seas of <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>.</p>

<p>From Sweden thus. We can now assure you that the Articles of Peace are signed and sealed between the Commonwealth of England and her Majesty, and the L. <em>Whitlock</em> is on his way home. The Diet begins forthwith, and then her Majesty <reg orig="resignes">resigns</reg> government, and according to the best intelligence, intends to go to the Spaw, and being delivered of the burthen of government, may happily have leisure to communicate her affection to <reg orig="foraigne">foreign</reg> Princes: some think she is inclined to marry with some person of eminent birth, though his fortunes be low, in regard she hath a very large maintenance, and yet refused to <reg orig="harken">hearken</reg> to the overtures made in that kind in behalf of the King of the Romans, eldest son to the Emperor of <reg orig="Germanie">Germany</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday <reg orig="Iune">June</reg> 2.</i></head> 

<p>There hath been a report of some differences lately about Northampton and <reg orig="elswhere">elsewhere</reg>, but upon examination it amounts <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to private <reg orig="duells">duels</reg>.</p>

<p>Paris 28. May. His Majesty of France was crowned at Rheimes, in was solemnized in great state and more ceremony, there was a great appearance of Dukes, <reg orig="Marquesses">Marquises</reg>, Earls and Lords both spiritual and temporal; the chief ceremony did of right belong to the Archbishop of Rheimes, but in regard of his indisposition the <reg orig="annoynting">anointing</reg> was performed by<pb n="6" /> the Bishop of Soissons, assisted with three more Bishops, the whole particulars you will have by the next. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is gone to take upon him the command in Catalonia, and his brother <em>Conde</em> intends to take the field very suddenly. The Duke of <em>Orleans</em> was not at the Coronation, being overswayed by his daughter, who is now under restraint for holding correspondence with the Enemy. The Duke of <em>Vendosme</em> is also out of favour, and discharged of his office, so that it is not yet known who will be high Admiral. There is a kind of grudge that some English and some of other Nations do get into the highest places at Court. The little Queen and others of that family were at this coronation, but P. <em>Rupert</em> is gone into <reg orig="Germanie">Germany</reg> to his Brother.</p>

<p>S. <em>Johnstons</em> in <em>Scotland</em> 27. May. Sir, I know that fame hath large wings, and as it flies swift, so doth it make a great noise, and oftentimes vanisheth; and thus we <reg orig="looke">look</reg> upon what you may have from some reports, and what the Enemy will at last make of all their great undertakings here, when once we can but get them upon an <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> engagement. For though we find many of them well mounted and armed with swords, Pistols, Back, <reg orig="Brest">Breast</reg>, and <reg orig="headpeeces">headpieces</reg>, yet but twenty of ours routed a party of sixty of theirs the other day <reg orig="neere">near</reg> <em>Douglas</em>, and <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> and killed six of them, therefore let them boast of their numbers as much as they please, it nothing frighteth us; Indeed whilst they keep in parties we must of necessity undergo the harder duty, but in a short time I believe you will <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that they are driven <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> together. The General is advanced to <em>Kilsey</em>, and intends to march towards <em>Abersoyle</em>, where we understand most of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> forces are, he lately made an attempt upon the County of <em><reg orig="Argile">Argyle</reg></em>, but was repulsed with some loss by the inhabitants, and the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> is come to General <em>Monke</em> to give an account thereof. Twenty Gentlemen in Galloway that were in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> are come in to us.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, June 26.</head>

<p>By another Letter dated at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> 26 May. Gen <em>Monk</em> hath set considerable guards upon 3. most eminent passes <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <em><reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg></em>, where our parties appearing early in the morning, took six of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> Scouts, and <reg orig="alarum'd">alarmed</reg> <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> Brigade, Lieut. <em>Goffe</em> commanding a party of ours met with a party commanded by Capt. <em>William <reg orig="Forester">Forrester</reg></em>, kinsman to the Lord <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Forester</em>, with a greater party, resolved to charge the enemy: the enemy drew up into a body which Lieut. <em>Goffe</em> perceiving, commanded his men (being about 50.) to give the enemy a thorough charge, and his Frontiers not to give fire <reg orig="til">till</reg> they came within pistol shot of the enemy, who came galloping down a hill, and gave fire at 20. <reg orig="yards">yard's</reg> distance, which gave us such advantage, that we took the Captain, six prisoners more, and put the rest to flight. They talk of a large appearance of their new levies. <em>Middleton</em>, who carries the name amongst them, and takes on him to be (as it were) a <reg orig="fore-runner">forerunner</reg> of their great <em>Diana's, Charles Stuart</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>. 'Twas thought that the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> of <em>Argile</em> would have <reg orig="staied">stayed</reg> in our quarters, but it's thought he goes within few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> to his own country, where possibly he may do better service <reg orig="then">than</reg> he can <reg orig="elswhere">elsewhere</reg>.</p>

<p>We shall in due time give you better satisfaction <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been yet, touching the late plot against his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the present Government, as also of the substance of a Letter found in Mr <em><reg orig="Ashburnhams">Ashburnham's</reg></em> pocket, wherein <em>Charles Stuart</em> was mentioned, with a list of those now in custody at <em>Whitehall</em>, S. <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em>, and other places besides the Tower: but in regard it may prove injurious to some that are innocent, if they should be but of the same name, we forbear till a perfect distinction be made of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parties.</p>

<p>Debate was had upon certain Propositions made by the French Ambassador, as also upon some papers from the Ambassador of the King of <em>Denmark</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Deale</em> they write, that the <em><reg orig="Beares">Bear's</reg> Paw</em>, and divers other Merchant ships are <reg orig="out-bound">outbound</reg> for <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em>, and thence to the <em>Barbados</em>, and that a great part pf our Fleet is yet on the Downs.</p>

<p>We had this day <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of consequence from several other parts, of which we have room <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to give you the heads, viz. The Squadron in the North have taken a Barque with provisions &amp; some ammunition going to the Enemy. The <reg orig="Leters">Letters</reg> also say, that in the West we have taken two small <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> and a <em>Brest</em> man of war. Some of the English which went out of <em>Ireland</em> are landed in the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>