<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn216">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 216</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><em>From Monday</em> January. 23. to <em>Monday</em>, January. 30. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em>, January 23.</head>

<p>This day from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his Council was published an Ordinance, Declaring what offences, and no other, shall be adjudged <reg orig="High-Treason">High Treason</reg>, within the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; And for better notice to all, take this <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg> as the chief <reg orig="heads">head's</reg> thereof, <em>viz</em>. It is declared, and shall be adjudged <reg orig="High-Treason">High Treason</reg>, <i>If any compass or imagine the death of the <em>Lord Protector</em> for the time being. If any shall write, print, openly declare, preach, teach, or otherwise publish, that the <em>Lord Protector</em> and the People assembled in Parliament, are not the Supreme Authority of this Commonwealth.</i><pb n="1" /> If any shall declare (as aforesaid) <i>That exercise of the chief Magistracy, in these dominions, is not in the <em>Lord Protector</em> assisted with his Council. Or that the said Authority or Government is tyrannical, usurped, or unlawful. Or that there is any Parliament now in being, or that has any continuance, or any Law in force for continuing <unclear>the</unclear> Parliament, which is hereby declared to have been dissolved 20 <em>April</em> 1653. and shall be adjudged, and taken so to be. Or if any shall in any wise endeavour to stir up, or raise force against the <em>Lord Protector</em> or present Government, for subversion or alteration thereof, and shall declare such endeavour by any open deed,</i> it shall be adjudged <em>High Treason</em>.</p>

<p>Also these following offenders and offences, are to be adjudged within the compass of <em>Treason, viz</em>. All endeavours of any mutiny (not being a member or members of any of the armies) and to make <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> disobedient in any of the forces. All inviters and procurers of Invasion from abroad upon any of these Dominions. All adherers to any forces of the common Enemies. All plotters for surrender of any City, Town, Fort, <reg orig="Magazin">Magazine</reg>, Ship, <em>&amp;c.</em> All counterfeiters of the great Seal, or of the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> Manual, Privy Signet, or privy Seal of the <em>Lord Protector</em> for the time being. All proclaimers or promoters of the pretended right of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, or any of that family, to the government of this Commonwealth, or any of the dominions thereto belonging. All Corresponders and Intelligencers with him, his mother, his brother James Stuart, or any of them. All Counterfeiters, Clippers, Diminishers, Falsifiers of <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, for gains sake. All Importers of false <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>, <em>&amp;c.</em> together with their counsellors, aiders, and abetters, are to be taken, adjudged and executed as Traitors. <i>Provided, that nothing in this Ordinance as touching the <reg orig="Monys">Moneys</reg> and <reg orig="coyns">coins</reg> aforesaid, shall extend to make any corruption of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, to any heir of any offender, or to the prejudice of any wife of such offender. Provided <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg>, that no person shall be prosecuted for any offence here mentioned, unless the prosecution be within one year after the offence committed.</i></p>

<p>These offences afore-named, and no other, are to be adjudged <em>High Treason</em>, not withstanding any former Act or Statute, <em>&amp;c.</em><pb n="2" /> Provided nevertheless, and it is declared to be the true intent &amp; purpose of this Ordinance, that the Laws made in the reigns of <em>Queen Elizabeth</em>, and King <em>James</em> against the Pope and See of <em>Rome, Jesuits, Seminary Priests, and Professors of the Polish Religion</em>, shall stand in full force and virtue. All abetters of the Pope's <reg orig="Iurisdiction">Jurisdiction</reg> in England, all procurers and promoters of <reg orig="Bulls">Bills</reg> from the Pope to absolve People from their obedience to this Government, or to move any to promise obedience to any other Price or power whatsoever.</p>

<p>Lastly all Jesuits, Priests, &amp;c. born in any of these Dominions, who have taken or shall take orders by authority derived from the See of <em>Rome</em>; and shall afterwards be found within this Commonwealth. These Offenders aforementioned shall be adjudged and executed as <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance for repealing several Acts and Resolves of Parliament for taking the Engagement <em>viz</em>. That the Act of the second of <em><reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 1649<em>, for subscribing the Engagement</em>: And certain Orders, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <em>Resolves touching the subscribing to an Engagement, &amp;c.</em> And all and every Clause, Branch, Article and Sentence in them, and every, or any of them contained, shall from and after the nineteenth day of January in the year of our Lord 1653. stand, and be absolutely repealed, and <reg orig="adnulled">annulled</reg>; And that all and every Clause, Branch, Article, Proviso, or Sentence contained in any other Act, Ordinance, Resolves or Order of Parliament, whereby the said Oath or <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> is directed, and appointed to be taken and <reg orig="adminstred">administered</reg>, and all and every the penalties, losses, incapacities, disabilities, and forfeitures for not taking or subscribing the same, shall from and after the said nineteenth day of <em>January</em> in the year of our Lord 1653. as to so much only (and no more) as concerneth the said Engagement, and the penalties, losses, incapacities, <reg orig="dissabilities">disabilities</reg>, and forfeitures, for not taking and subscribing the same; be, and are hereby utterly repealed, and made void, &amp;c.</p>

<p>From aboard the <em><reg orig="Saphir">Sapphire</reg></em>, Letters this day from Capt. <em>Heaton <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 20 came as followeth. The 16 instant about 27 leagues<pb n="3" /> from <em><reg orig="Vshant">Ushant</reg></em>, we spake with one of <em>Ostend</em>, who <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the Thursday before he came out of <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, in company with 40 Hollanders, and 20 others homeward bound; They kept the French shore, but had no Convoy; for a ship of 34 guns on whom they depended grounded upon the Pole head <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> out, and the sunk on the 17 at two in the Afternoon with the wind at East. As we <reg orig="plyed">plied</reg> <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> the Channel about 16 leagues South from <em><reg orig="Scily">Scilly</reg></em>, we met with four <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that bore the English Ensign, and the old <reg orig="Unicorn">Union</reg> <reg orig="Iack">Jack</reg>. The greatest was a ship not much unlike the <em>Nonsuch</em>, only somewhat shorter, with a <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Head, a Rampant <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, with a <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Crown in her Stern, and a <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> streak, as hath the <em>Lanrell</em>, this we suppose was <em>Beach</em>. The three smaller did weather us a Saker shot, and the other half a shot, as he <reg orig="past">passed</reg> he fired one gun; though four to one yet they could not bear up, They standing in the Northward we tacked in their <reg orig="wacke">wake</reg>, and kept them company till night drew his curtain. All this day it was so much wind and sea, that we could not safely open a top sail.</p>

<p>On the 18 instant we hailed with the Lizard, thinking to find him, and met with 16 of our Merchant ships outward bound, whom I saw 20 leagues to the Westward. On the 19 at noon we met with the <em>Middleborough</em>, and with her a supposed prize. And the last night we fell with a pretended Dover-man. But the whole company are French save one <em>Rob. Hopkins</em> of <em>Dover</em>, both which Vessels laden with wine we have sent into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> by the <em>Middleborough</em>, and are ranging where we can best imagine, to clear the Coast and Channel of the <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>. The aforesaid <em>Rob. Hopkins</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That on Saturday lat, there came out of St. <em>Martins</em> in his company a ship of 26 Guns that came from the West-Indies, and with him nine more, which are gone on the back-side of <em>Ireland</em>, for they steered West from <em>Alleronne de Baies</em>. They further say, That they look for a Fleet of 200 sail from <em>Holland</em> which are to come round.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 14.</i></head>

<p>Further from <em>Dalkeith</em>, January 19. The chief Body of the Enemy is now fallen into <em>Murrayland</em>, where they are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in levying their Sess, and intend to <reg orig="debarre">debar</reg> correspondence between <em>Aberdeen</em> and <em>Innerness</em>. Col. <em>Morgan</em> is drawing all the forces of the Northern parts together to attempt their driving out thence: <em>Athol</em> was lately in <em>Strathardle</em>, where he <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> all men to rise, and got together about 500, who had not <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> long with him, but 300 departed without leave. Whereupon he gave liberty to all but 60 to be ready upon occasion. The Enemy I am confident were no gainers by the loss of Captain <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> party from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, he that commanded the first party (supposed to be Col. <em>Wogan</em>) was slain and many of his men. The party consisted of <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> English, being 30, and about 40 of Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> his men that were beaten in the South, and the other were Major <em>Mercers</em> men that belong to <em>Athol</em>: <em>Wogan</em> and his men stood valiantly to it, otherwise we had totally routed the Scots. Lieut. <em>Caleb Leigh</em> is certainly killed.</p>

<p><em>Lieth</em> Jan. 17. The Enemy are part in <em>Badgenoth</em>, and part in the Laird of <em>Grants</em> Bounds. The party that Col. <em>Morgan</em> drew from <em>Aberdeen</em> toward <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Innerness</reg></em> could not get over <em>Spey</em>, the waters were so high. The <em>Boggy-geith</em> is a very <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> Garrison, the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> of <reg orig="Huntlies">Huntley's</reg> Lady being removed to <em>Strathbogie</em>. The Enemy are much startled at <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> revolt, and think there is a greater <reg orig="designe">design</reg> in the same than is yet apparent. There is to be a great meeting of all the Clan <reg orig="Camphell">Campbell</reg> in <em>Argyle</em>, it is said to offer some proposals to the Commander in Chief. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> yet lies wounded in some part of <em>Monteith</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 25.</i></head>

<p>On Thursday lat <em>Athol</em> and <em>Lorn</em> were at the house of <em>Balloch</em>, near <em>Lough Tay</em>; since which <em>Athol</em>, is very sick, and in <em><reg orig="Weems">Weem's</reg></em> Garrison, and <em>Lorn</em> pretends his Father is not <reg orig="reconcileable">reconcilable</reg> to him, whereupon he goes not home. The 14 instant Capt. <em>Crese</em>, Captain Lieut. to the Col. <em>Okey</em>, with a party from St <em>Johnstones</em> fell into the Quarters of about forty of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg><pb n="5" /> Horse about <em>Stabengham</em>, near little <em>Dunkel</em>, under Lieut. Col. <em>Ramsey</em> took ten prisoners, and sixteen horses and killed two on the place.</p>

<p>But a party of Capt <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> Troop from <em>Drummond</em> had not so good <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, for the Lieut. being sent out with a party of thirty horse to rescue some sheep taken by the Enemy near the Garrison, pursued so far as to rout them, but another party of 60 Horse, and 100 or 200 foot lying in <reg orig="Ambuscado">Ambuscade</reg>, our men made a very difficult retreat, in which the Lieutenant, the Cornet, and two Troopers were killed, and seven Troopers. Divers of the Enemy were killed, and amongst the rest <em>Wogan</em> (as is supposed) he and the English with him giving the first charge.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> the 28 <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>. By Letters from <em><reg orig="Marseillis">Marseilles</reg></em> thus. About eight days since an English ship being taken by the <em>Hollanders</em> and brought into that Port, the English Merchants caused it to be <reg orig="seased">seized</reg>, as laying a just claim to it, but the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> being put to debate it was carried on the <em><reg orig="Hollanders">Hollanders'</reg></em> side and the ship delivered to them again, provided that they should neither sell ship or goods there, but carry it <reg orig="else where">elsewhere</reg>: and the next day another English ship bound for that City <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> near the Islands the <em>Hollanders</em> would have gone out to take her, but were prevented, and stayed until the ship was safe in the Harbour: One of our private men of war having lately surprised a ship of <em>Genoa</em> within the command of this City upon pretence <pb n="6" />that he was laden with <em>Spanish</em> goods, it was ordered by our Magistrate the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> should be examined, and speedy justice done to the Plaintiffs,</p>

<head level="3">An advertisement from the Lieutenant of the Tower.</head>

<p><i>At the desire of the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em><reg orig="Cleaveland">Cleveland</reg></em> now Prisoner in the Tower, I do hereby give notice to all persons <reg orig="alleyed">allied</reg> in blood or acquaintance to the said <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg>, That his Lordship hath been lately <reg orig="inform'd">informed</reg> of a certain Impostor or Cheat, who under the cloak of friendship, and a pretence of serving his Lordship, hath made very unworthy addresses to divers persons of quality in the said <reg orig="Earle's">Earl's</reg> behalf to borrow money for his relief, and to supply his occasions in the Tower, and have counterfeited the said <reg orig="Earle's">Earl's</reg> hand and seal for such lewd purposes: And because a vizard is proper for such practitioners, he goes sometimes under the name of <em><reg orig="Bucke">Buck</reg></em>, sometimes <em><reg orig="Brathwayt">Braithwaite</reg></em>, and <em>Butler</em>; and that by this means he hath obtained several <reg orig="summes">sums</reg> of money from several persons who are deluded by his Knavery; and although the Lieutenant (at the desire of the said Earl) hath granted many Warrants for the apprehending of the said person, yet it hath hitherto been his fortune to escape.</i></p> 

<p><i>The Earl of <em><reg orig="Cleaveland">Cleveland</reg></em> desires, this may be <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> known, that this Villain's proceedings may be prevented for the future, and also that it may be believed, that when the said <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> hath any occasion to use money, it hath been his custom <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> to use such honourable means of procurement as are suitable with his degree and honour.</i></p>

<p><i>The like abuse hath been <reg orig="offer'd">offered</reg> by the same person to the Lord <em>Grandison</em> also, a Prisoner in the Tower, which he likewise desires to be made known.</i></p>

<p><i>This Cheat had been <reg orig="practis'd">practised</reg> since the first publication, and therefore the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em><reg orig="Cleaveland">Cleveland</reg></em> desires it may be <reg orig="re-printed">reprinted</reg> for further caution.</i></p>

<p>The Adventurers for lands in <em>Ireland</em> are desired to take notice, That since the Committee for Claims sitting at Grocers-hall directed one penny (upon every pound adventured) to be paid Mr. <em>Turner</em> or some other by their order; The Lord Protector with the advice of his Council hath otherwise ordered the payment<pb n="7" /> of the same, as appeareth by his Order, the Copy whereof ensueth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday the 26 January, 1653.</i></head>

<head level="3">At the Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</head>

<p><i>Whereas by and Order of the Council of State at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> of the 2. of <em>July</em> last, It was Ordered, that one penny in the pound (which amongst other things, by Order of the said Council of the first of <em>June</em> last authorizing the Committee for clearing <reg orig="claimes">claims</reg> at Grocers-hall to receive the said penny upon the pound, of, and from every Adventurer) should be paid unto such person or persons at the Committee of Adventurers (who are <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> by the body of Adventurers) should nominate and appoint for that purpose, as by the said Order of the 2. of <em>July</em> (amongst other things therein contained) may at large appear. It is now thought fit, and so Ordered by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice of the Council, That the said Order of the 2. of <em>July</em> last, and every clause therein <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, to all intents and purposes, shall stand; and is hereby ratified and confirmed; Any Act, Order, or Vote made to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding: And it is further Ordered, That the said Committee for <reg orig="cleering">clearing</reg> the claims at <em>Grocers-hall</em>, shall not deliver out any Certificate to any of the said Adventurers for their respective allotments of land, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> they are satisfied by a <reg orig="noat">note</reg> under the hand of the Treasurer already appointed, or to be appointed by the said Committee of Adventurers, that he hath received the said penny upon the pound, according to the said Order of the Council of State of the 2. of <em>July</em> last, which every Adventurer is hereby <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> and required to pay accordingly.</i></p>

<p>Ex. <em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>The said Adventurers are farther desired to take notice that Mr. <em>George Almary</em> living at the lower end of old Jury is the Treasurer appointed by the Committee of Adventurers to the purpose aforesaid.</p>

<p>The Reader is also desired to take notice, <i>That one <em>George Carter</em> born in the Parish of <em>Bucklebury</em> in the county of <em>Berks</em>, the son of <em>Simon Carter</em>, his Father being dead, there is an Estate fallen to him, if it be possible he may hear of it, and discover himself betwixt this and Easter next, he hath been absent about sixteen years since his Friends had any Intelligence of him.</i></p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday, <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>, 26. 1654</i></head>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 31. of <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 1654. Stilo nov. The <reg orig="Counsellour">Counsellor</reg> Monsieur du Groissy Foueguet, after one years imprisonment was set at liberty, but upon condition that he shall leave his <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>, and be <reg orig="Exil'd">Exiled</reg> to Venice during the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> pleasure. The other Counsellors likewise who had been <reg orig="Exil'd">Exiled</reg>, are now called home, and sit again in Parliament as formerly. They write from Perpignan, that they are in a very good condition, that now Rosa being well provided with all manner of Provisions and Ammunitions, doth not fear any attempt of the Spaniards, who are now all gone into their Winter-quarter: <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg>, the Spanish Garrison at Villafranea doth <reg orig="doe">do</reg> much harm in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, insomuch, that our Forces to prevent further <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> are forced in this hard time of the <reg orig="yeare">year</reg> to march into the Field, to try if they can bring in that Garrison, or at least block them up, so that they do no further mischief. The last <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from the Leaguer before Biffort <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the Marshal <em>de la Ferta</em> was come thither with two thousand foot, and one thousand horse, that the Trench being open, they had made a great Progress, and the Mine was near finished under the great Bastion, that the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> had turned several places without the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg>, and <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> the Besiegers to his uttermost, to make any advantage by <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> left about the Town, yet the place is very close besieged, and there being little hope of any considerable strength to relieve it, its thought the Besieged will be forced to make their Agreement in a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The difference between the States and the Parliament of <reg orig="Brittannie">Brittany</reg> is not yet decided: both parties having sent Commissioners to the Court, to <reg orig="maintaine">maintain</reg> their cause: The Price of Conti is not yet come, and it is conceived that he doth expect the event of that <reg orig="Processe">Process</reg> followed so eagerly against his Brother. The Protestants in Languedoc remain yet unsatisfied, having as yet obtained nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> Court language, which they will not accept in payment of so many gross injuries received from the Papists.</p><pb n="9" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 16.</i></head> 

<p>Monsieur <em>Beverlin</em>, one of the Dutch Commissioners that lately went hence returned the last night, and had this day Audience. He <reg orig="affirmes">affirms</reg>, that the Province of <em>Holland</em>, the leading and greatest <reg orig="Provinc">Province</reg>, have declared their consent to the Articles lately agreed upon with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>; and within very few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> there will be Deputies from the rest of the Provinces, declaring their assent, (but some question Zealand) as also Ambassadors from Holland, to see the confirmation hereof on our part.</p>

<p>This day Mr <em>Feake</em> and Major <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em> (who were yesterday taken into custody) were examined before the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, and stand committed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 27. 1654.</i></head>

<p>Further from Upsaliah in Sweden by letters Decemb. 30. of the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, his Honourable Reception, Audience, and his Speech to the Queen, as followeth:</p>

<p>We are now at Upsaliah, where the Queen resides by reason of the <reg orig="Sicknesse">Sickness</reg> being at Stockholm. We came from <reg orig="Gottenbergh">Gothenburg</reg> the 29. of Novemb. And came to Upsaliah the 20. of December, where my Lord was entertained with very much respect, and on the three and twentieth day my Lord had Audience, where the Queen heard him with as much Gravity and Majesty as to my apprehension might be composed in a Woman, if not any man; Besides, I have heard my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> (who hath had private Audience twice since) commend her to be the <reg orig="accutest">acutest</reg> woman that ever he met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and to be admired for her knowledge in <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg>; And that she is so well acquainted with the Transactions of States, far beyond what he was able to conceive she had; here is very great hopes of the accomplishing the business my Lord came hither about the Queen having declared such readiness and freedoms to treat with my Lord concerning it: There is here now resident from <reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg>, France, Holland, Denmark, and Russia. Concerning the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, I cannot <reg orig="finde">find</reg> as yet so great difference between it and England as was reported: We have here Frost and Snow, and I think not very much colder <reg orig="then">than</reg><pb n="10" /> frost and snow in England: but in other things there is a great <reg orig="deale">deal</reg> of difference, for there is hardly a Commodity in England but would <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> as much more here; nothing that as yet I <reg orig="finde">find</reg> plenty here, but Wood, Pitch and Tar.</p>

<head level="3"><i>His Excellency the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> Speech to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>.</i></head>

<p><em>Madam</em>, By Command from my <reg orig="Superiours">Superiors</reg>, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England, I do with all respect salute your Majesty, which had been sooner done, if by extraordinary accidents and engagements in the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of three Nations with no few <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> <reg orig="Divertions">Diversions</reg> it had not been retarded. And although the Commonwealth of England are not encouraged to send abroad, when they reflect upon the barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places; yet your Majesty perceives that from your Government neither our Masters nor their Servants have the least suspicion of any such entertainment: but we who are here present <reg orig="doe">do</reg> gratefully acknowledge our experience of the contrary, and of much Civility to our nation.</p>

<p>My business is to communicate with your Majesty in matters relating to the common good, which is of so great weight that it admits of no hopes of <reg orig="successe">success</reg> without his <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> blessing, who by small means can bring great things to pass; the confidence whereof, with my submiss to the judgement and commands of my Superiors hath given me this honour of being in your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence.</p>

<p>Whom, I shall not weary with many words or expressions beyond meaning; I am not sent hither for that cause, and it is as different from my own spirit, as contrary to the practice and commands of my <reg orig="superiours">superiors</reg>, from whom and from their servant according to the English reality, your Majesty will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> all manner of <reg orig="plaine">plain</reg> ness and truth in our <reg orig="transections">transactions</reg>, Our deliverances &amp; preservations, whereof we have been eye-witnesses, have been so near to miracles, and such monuments of infinite rich mercy and love from heaven, that<pb n="11" /> we should <reg orig="sinne">sin</reg> against them if the least guile or unfaithfulness should infect our conversation.</p>

<p>It is not my work to paint out my <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, or to draw black lines upon any, though our adversaries, neither shall I take upon me to mention the excellencies of your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> person and government, or of your People, and <reg orig="Countreyes">Countries</reg>, lest I should injure any merit; and because I speak to those whom God hath favoured with the enjoyment of great mercies, the increase and continuance whereof is heartily desired by my <reg orig="superiours">superiors</reg>, and by me their servant.</p>

<p>I shall not <reg orig="inlarge">enlarge</reg> my discourse with observations, concerning both Nations, of their likeness in Language, Manner, and war like dispositions, Arguments more natural <reg orig="then">than</reg> artificial for a nearer union; but this I may not omit, the fruits whereof I have tasted: the present happy Government under your Majesty, which remembers unto us those blessed <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of our Virgin Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, under whom above 40. years the people enjoyed all protection and justice from their Prince, and she all obedience and affection from her people.</p>

<p>May this and more be the portion of your Majesties and your Successors, nor had it been lost in those who followed Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, though <reg orig="forraigners">foreigners</reg>, but through the extremity of their own ill Government.</p>

<p>When attempts were made to ravish from us our highest interest, the Orthodox Religion and just liberty, the defence whereof undertaken by King <em>Gustavu Adolphus</em>, your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Royal Father of blessed memory, in his <em>German</em> Expedition, for the Protestants relief, was in him most honourable and successful, and surely for us was most just and necessary, and alike crowned with gracious success by the Almighty.</p>

<p>For the extirpation of both which, by force which had long been endeavoured otherwise <em>Auxiliaries</em> were provided, and afterwards a war raised, which first appearing in Scotland; but there diligently resisted, and the <em>English</em> refusing to be instrumental against <em>Scotland</em> for those ends, the storm was then blown over.</p>

<p>In <em>Ireland</em> it rose so hideously, that 200000 poor Creatures Men, Women and Children, besides what the War devoured,<pb n="12" /> were in clod blood barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, for no other reason, but because they were Protestants, and Commission <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> for it.</p>

<p>In <em>England</em> the fire brake out in all parts of it, from one corner of the land to the other, not a place, not a Family free from the rage of our decennial, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> civil War, and yet after so much blood powered forth, we <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God we live, and after so many devastations, a stranger passing through our Country can hardly espy the steps of it, or good God hath given us in <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and all the adjacent Isles and Territories of the Commonwealth, a full and happy peace.</p>

<p>In all appeals to him, whereof we have seen many, he was pleased still to <reg orig="ditirmine">determine</reg> for the Parliament, and after these, and eight tenders and treaties of peace, wherein we received the <reg orig="denyal">denial</reg> from our adversaries, it pleased the <reg orig="gratious">gracious</reg> and all disposing hand of God for the good of <em>England</em>, to change the Government thereof.</p>

<p>Nevertheless the same common <reg orig="intrest">interest</reg>, which first begat former <reg orig="allyances">alliances</reg> and confederacy between the two Nations, do still continue and oblige both to desire the good of each other.</p>

<p>Whereunto they seem the more engaged, because we cannot <reg orig="finde">find</reg> that in any age there hath been a declared war between them but a constant intercourse of friendship and amity with <reg orig="mutuall">mutual</reg> Offices of kindness out of which great profit and happiness hath redounded unto both.</p> 

<p>These things being considered, with the affairs of <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>, and especially of the neighbouring Princes and States, through divine Providence in such posture and condition, as to give greater opportunity, and lay stronger Obligations upon both Nations; to entertain a nearer union and correspondence <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore, whereby the <reg orig="Commerse">Commerce</reg> and <reg orig="Tranquility">Tranquillity</reg> of both may be preserved and provided for, with respect also to the common interest of and concernment of the true Protestant Religion. And you <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> having by your late <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers to England signified your <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> inclination and willingness by all good <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> to conserve &amp; <reg orig="encrease">increase</reg> the ancient good understanding<pb n="13" /> between these States, upon these and other weighty considerations, and to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how acceptable the former overtures of your Majesty have bin, the Parliament have thought fit by me to make tender unto your Majesty of the friendship of the Commonwealth of England, and to let you know, that they are not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> ready to renew and preserve inviolably that amity and good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> which hath hitherto been between the two Nations, but are farther willing to enter into a more strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> and union (then but as yet been) for the good of both.</p>

<p>And in such way as shall be held requisite, I shall be ready more particularly to <reg orig="comunicate">communicate</reg> what I have in charge for this purpose. Thus far the Speech.</p> 

<p>There were two men this day set in the Pillory in Smithfield, the one a Carpenters servant, for beating and abusing his Master and <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg>, the other for <reg orig="Perjurie">Perjury</reg>, and had his <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> nailed to the Pillory.</p>

<p>Between three and four of the clock this afternoon part of the Body of <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Church (but not the Steeple) at the great South <reg orig="doore">door</reg> <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> down, there being divers Children about the time playing in the Church <reg orig="neare">near</reg> the place, but we hear as yet not of any killed, but one or two sorely hurt.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Jan. 28. 1654.</head>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em>, Jan. 22. There is little since the last engagement of our party near Drummond, I cannot yet <reg orig="learne">learn</reg> who they were that were <reg orig="slaine">slain</reg> on the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> side, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one Captain <em><reg orig="Ker">Kerr</reg></em>, and another eminent man, who they said was the second brave man of their Forces, very many of them wounded. The <reg orig="maine">main</reg> body of them still continue in <reg orig="Murray-land">Murrayland</reg>, between <reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg> and <reg orig="Aberdene">Aberdeen</reg>. The which instant a party of 300 foot, under Lieutenant Col. Heniet of Newark, and 100 Horse, commanded by one <em><unclear>Imebinrole</unclear></em> came into Dunbarton Town, stayed about an <reg orig="houre">hour</reg>, and went thence: At their last going away before this, the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> was pasted up upon the <reg orig="Market-Crosse">Market Cross</reg>, those expressions in it, Our <em>Ancient Old Enemy, the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of England</em>; And Our grand Enemy <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the <reg orig="bottome">bottom</reg> of their <reg orig="Designe">Design</reg> to destroy the English, and is a very good invitation for them to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg><pb n="14" /> with them: if their Plots be laid no deeper, we hope they will not be able to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> us much hurt. We <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that Col. Humphries gallant Troop of Dragoons are on the Borders, and some other <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> for our supply, which is welcome <reg orig="Newes">News</reg>; and now we shall be able to meet with the Enemy at all turns.</p>

<head level="3">A Proclamation</head>

<head level="3"><i>William Earl of Glencairn, Lord <reg orig="Kilmares">Kilmare's</reg> Commander in chief of his Majesties forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>For as much as to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service and advancement of <em>our ancient old Enemy</em> the Kingdom of <em>England</em>, who by their <reg orig="perfideous">perfidious</reg> practise, and all unlawful means, still pretending the good and advancement of the Protestant Religion, has <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> the reducement and enslaving of us, our predecessors and Country to their subjection. Many pretended Countrymen of several qualities, within the shires of Dunbarton, <reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfew">Renfrew</reg>, and other adjacent places upon the South side of <unclear>Farth</unclear> are not ashamed to bring in, sell, and deliver to several Officers of Garrisons belonging to the said grand enemy, the whole serviceable Arms, and other offensive weapons, they either have, or possibly can acquire, whereby his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> in most parts of the said shires, are greatly impeded far contrary to our natural Countrymen, inhabiting the Northern shires, who by their good example, laying to heart the bleeding condition of this their native <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, do all unanimously take up Arms, and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with us for relief, and recovery thereof, we do therefore by these presents, <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> and declare, that whatsoever person or persons of whatsoever quality, within any of the said shires of Dunbarton, <reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfew">Renfrew</reg>, or places adjacent, shall upon whatsoever pretence after publication hereof, presume to sell, give or deliver up to any belonging to the said common enemy, any serviceable Horses or Arms, to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service or levies of Horse or Foot, <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon any of them, that the whole good and <reg orig="gein">gain</reg> of the person or persons disobeyers of this our Command (without respect of any) shall be sequestrate, and confiscate for the use of any whosoever can first apprehend them, for <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with, and effectuating whereof these presents shall be an <reg orig="irreducable">irreducible</reg> warrant, and ordains publication hereof at the Market <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of Dunbarton; whereby they, nor none inhabiting the Shires of <reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg>, or places adjacent, pretend ignorance hereof. Given at Weims this 22 of December 1653. <em>sic subscribiter</em>.</p>

<p><i>Glencairn</i></p><pb n="15" />

<p>By Letters from <em>Falmouth</em> thus. Here are several ships come into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, being wind bound, and intending for <em>London</em> and those parts with the first opportunity, those that were here, whom we formerly mentioned are all now gone out with these Easterly winds: there are many Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, who lie still between the Lands end and the Isles of Scilly, and makes it very dangerous to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> without a Convoy. Some of the Brest French Pirates (we hear) have lately taken two small Barks of this Country, and sent them home. They have we hear lately among them above 20 Sail of Men of War out, whereof one hath 36 Guns, and 200 Men, other about 24 and 20 Guns, but most of 12. and under. From West Cowes in the Isle of Wight. Our Fleet is still riding <reg orig="neer">near</reg> St <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point, ready upon the least notice of any appearance of the Dutch to set sail and encounter with them, if a peace ensue not. We have no other Prizes brought in of late, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a French Bark laden with <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, Cloth, Paper, and other French Goods. Yesterday came in the 8 <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> sent out to ply in the Channel, and the day before eight others were sent to scout in their rooms.</p>

<hr /> 

<p>The Continuation of Artaminis, or the Grand Cyrus that excellent new Romance, written by that famous wit of France Monsieur de Studery Governor of Nostredame, and now englished by F. G: Esquire. Printed for Humphrey Moseley, at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Arms in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg>, and Tho: D.ing at the George in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>.</p>

<p>The Marrow of Ecclesiastical History, contained in the liver of the <reg orig="Fathers">Father's</reg> Schoolmen, <unclear>first</unclear> Reformers and modern Divines which have flourished in the Church from <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> time to this present. The lively Effigies of most of them cut in Copper. The second Edition enlarged in most of the Lives, with the addition of <unclear>4</unclear> Lives which were not in the former. By Sam Clark of <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg> Fink London, Printed for Will: Reybould at the Unicorn in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p><unclear>Reliqui&oelig;</unclear> Wotionieme, or a collection of Lives, Letters and Poems, &amp;c by the curious Pen of Sir Henry Wotton, now published with large Additions, sold by H. Marriot, G. Bedell, T. <reg orig="Garthwait">Garthwaite</reg>.</p>

<p>A learned <reg orig="Peece">Piece</reg> called Examen Acundennaram, by John Webster, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> a more profitable and practical way of all Arts and Sciences, and for the further advancement of Learning: The strait Gate or narrow way leading to life by H. Heere Master of Arts, delivered in several Sermons.</p>

<p>Divine <reg orig="Essayes">Essays</reg> by <reg orig="Isaack">Isaac</reg> Pennington Junior, sold by Edw. <unclear>Calvert</unclear>, at the Blackspread Eagle at the west-end of <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>.</p>

<p>A Pearl Necklace being one Rope, with a black twopenny <reg orig="Ribbin">Ribbon</reg> either end, in a white <reg orig="woodden">wooden</reg> Box, writ thereupon three <unclear>Dosse</unclear> of Pearl left betwixt York and Wetherby about the 17th of Jan. last. If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> shall <reg orig="finde">find</reg> the same and deliver it at Wetherby to Mr. Will: Tomson, at the sign of the Crown there, or at London to Mr. Bernard Morden Merchant, at his House in great Woodstreet, he shall have three pounds for his pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>