<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn225">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 225</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, March. 27. to <em>Monday</em>, April 3. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg></head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> March 27.</head>

<p>This day the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Bourdeaux</em> from the King of <em>France</em> was entertained (as before ordered) and brought from Tower-Wharf, where he landed, through the City to <em>Westminster</em> in great State by about 50 or 60 Coaches. The first was the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> rich Coach wherein was the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, and five or six of his chief Gentlemen attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of Ceremonies, 10 of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Pages in Liveries, and the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Pages with his Liveries.</p>

<p>Next the French Ambassadors own rich Coach with other of his Gentlemen in it, that are come from <em>France</em> to attend the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>Then went the chief Coach of the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, with the chief of the <em>Portugal</em> Gentlemen in it, and the Coachman and Postillion riding in Crimson Velvet coats, laid thick with rich silver lace.</p>

<p>After them followed about 20 more with 6 horses a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of the Coaches of the English Nobility and Gentry, The foremost of which was the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> second Coach: And then about 12 with four horses a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>, and last of all some 20 Coaches with two horses a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>.</p>

<p><i>From Italy and parts adjacent, and first from Naples thus</i>: The Duke <em>de Andria</em>, and the Lord <em>Caraffa</em> his Brother, have been this week imprisoned, the first in the New Castle, and the second in the Vicaria, the subject being for some abuses done to a Spanish Officer. We hear from <em>Palermo</em>, the Duke <em>del Infantado</em> the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of <em>Scicilia</em> is now much better than he was, there being great hopes of his recovery from his dangerous <reg orig="sicknes">sickness</reg>. From <em>Rome</em>, There issued out an Order from the Pope, which was sent to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Pamfilio</em> (who is still near <em>Tivoli</em>) That from henceforth he use not the name or arms of <em>Pamfilii</em>, and to take anew the name of <em>Astali</em>; likewise not to intermeddle with the managing of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> affairs in the Church Dominions, as heretofore, the same being taken from him, as also all prerogatives which he enjoyed as one of the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Nephews; There is lately fallen here and about this City an extraordinary Snow, which in a short time came<pb n="2" /> to be of a foot thick, being much <reg orig="wondred">wondered</reg> at, in regard the Spring was near at hand. From <em>Venice</em> thus, We hear from <em>Constantinople</em> that they have taken up for their service twelve Ships, <em>English</em> and <em>Dutch</em>; That a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister is sent into <em><reg orig="Barbarie">Barbary</reg></em> with Moneys and express Order that all Shipping fit for service might be made ready to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the <em>Turkish</em> Army at the <em>Dardanelles</em>: And we have from <em>Candia</em>, that the General Bashaw having intelligence that some of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> people near <em>Suda</em> had relieved that <reg orig="strong Hold">stronghold</reg>, that thereupon <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in an <reg orig="outragious">outrageous</reg> manner he had destroyed them all with fire and sword, and likewise a conformation from <em>Candia</em> of the taking <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Vessel's">Vessels</reg> laden with provisions going to relieve <em>Canea</em>. From <em>Turin</em>, The French forces do live very peaceably in their winter quarters, not giving any occasion of discontent to the Country where they quarter, those that are about <em><unclear>Tbiolli</unclear></em> and <em>Cisterna</em> do the same, and are kept upon a very strict <reg orig="disciplin">discipline</reg>. From <em>Milan</em>, The new Levies go on with all diligence, and we hope will be ready timely for the next <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> Expedition. The Commissary Gen. of the Artillery, with the <em>Mastre de Campo</em>, and some other high Officers, are ready to depart for <em>Madrid</em> about their particular affairs; we hear from <em>Madrid</em>, that there are great preparations intended for the next Expedition, and to carry on the work the Impost was raised on <reg orig="severall">several</reg> commodities, &amp; amongst others on <em>Tobacco, Wool</em>, and <em>Salt</em>, that their Majesties were in perfect health, being sometimes there, and <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> at the <em>Escurial</em>, to take the fresh air.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>From the <em>Hague</em>, March 27. The last Thursday were brought in here a Pink sent for that purpose Letters of the 20 instant from the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors now in <em>England</em>, whereby we hear they give advice to the Lords States, that the Treaty of Peace was not yet concluded, but that preparations for Sea were made there in all <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, the occasion thereof was unknown to them, which caused some <reg orig="suspitions">suspicions</reg> and jealousies amongst the said Lords States; Insomuch that the Vice-Admiral <em>Ruyter</em>, and the Scout by night <em>Tromp</em> with other Captains received orders to resort presently to <em>Amsterdam</em>, which they did accordingly <em>Wednesday</em> morning, as also several Messengers were dispatched to the Counsels of the Admiralties. The Lieut. Admiral, the Lord Van-<em>Opdam</em> was likewise commanded to come from <em>Brabant</em> where he was hither.</p>

<p>And yet we cannot understand by the Letters come from <em>London</em> the night between the 20 and 21 that any difficulties should have arisen wherefore the Treaty should not go on, so that it is believed that the same may have a good <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, and that those preparations made there may be for some other design. We have very little certainty of the Scottish Affairs, It is presumed that <em>Middleton</em> is arrived in <em>Scotland</em> to gather what forces he can to restore the titular King his Masters fortune. Last night a Pink hath been by the Lords States dispatched from Scheveling into <em>England</em>, though he be but stirring up humours to a <reg orig="Boyl">Boil</reg>, which without question will break this Spring.</p> 

<p><i>A List of the several Prizes taken by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance</em> and <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> since February 1653.</i></p>

<p>March 2. taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot <reg orig="hoy">Hoy</reg>, whose Mast being shot by the Board, she was burnt.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the <em>Assurance </em><reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Hope</em> of <em>Hous-down</em>, burthen 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p>Taken then also by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em>, the <em>Claus</em> of <em>Hous-down</em>, burthen 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p>March 14. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Moremaids">Moremaid's</reg></em> Boat, the Fortune of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, burthen 32 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, wherein were many Barrels of Fish, and 6 of Salt, with about 40 empty Cask.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the <em><reg orig="Newcastles">Newcastle's</reg></em> Boat, the Skell-fish of<pb n="4" /> <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, with Fish, Salt, and some empty Cask.</p>

<p>Taken the same day also by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat, the <em>Plumpart</em> of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, burthen 30 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise.</p>

<p>March 12. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the Providence of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, burthen 28<reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading.</p>

<p>March 17. Brought by the Lee of the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> and her Boat sent on board, and afterward run on board by the Newcastle, who broke her head and Boltsprit, and forced the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat off, <em>viz</em>. the <em>Fortune</em> of <em>Dels-haven</em>, burthen 200<reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Brandy wine, French wine, Prunes, &amp;c.</p>

<p>March 18. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, burthen 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>.</p>

<p>March 19. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, two Scotch Vessels, the one laden with Beef, Flower, Train <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Deer-skins, and Sugars, the other had only Ballast. Both of them were going for <em>Holland</em>, having been first taken by a private man of War belonging to <em>Enchuysen</em>, but thus recovered.</p>

<p>March 27. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the <em>Wakeing Bay</em> of <em>Enchuysen</em>, and with her eight Guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable, 12 Picks, ten Muskets, eight Pistols, and a Boat with four Oars.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 28.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em> March 21. The Lord <em>Ray</em> hath sent to <em>Skelco</em> for Arms for his men, <em>Seafort</em> was expected the 10 instant within five mile of <em>Crabsdale</em>, with his Men, Sir <em>Geo. Monroe</em> and <em>Middleton</em> were then in <em>Stranraver</em>, and to meet <em>Seafort</em> and <em>Ray</em> at <em>Inra</em> with their whole force, where also <em>Glengary</em> with his rabble are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, and so force <em>Sutherland</em> and <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> to rise. It is reported that since <em>Middleton</em>, a Lord is landed with some Men and Arms.</p>

<p>The Garrison of <em>Lewis</em> have made slaughter of the Country people that <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Seafort</em>, and they have also slaughtered some of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the old Natives <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with our men<pb n="5" /> against the rest of the Country: so that the divisions cause great devastations in those parts. Those of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniels's</reg></em> Regiment which quartered in the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Logie</em>, have found 22 new Muskets, 9 Firelocks, 11 Swords, 9 or 10 sets of <reg orig="Bandaliers">Bandoliers</reg>, three quarters of a barrel of Powder, and 13 bundles of Match, they were close made up in an Wall, and found out by accident. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> is again from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and divers parties in these parts stealing Horse, which the wit of man cannot prevent, the Country are so false, and yet cannot but see, that all that those people from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> can <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, is to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> them, rather than injure the English, against whom they pretend their chief quarrel.</p>

<p>The Commander in chief hath apprehended and confined some who discover themselves addicted to the other Party; one of them being Mr. <em>Knox</em> at <em>Kelsay</em>, partly for praying for the pretended King, and declaring his affection to the Rebels that are in arms against us, and partly for somewhat of correspondence.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em>, the 16th of March, 1654. From <em>Warsovia</em>: The main <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> now in agitation at the Diet, is about the finding out of considerable <reg orig="summes">sums</reg> of money towards the raising of new Regiments for the strengthening of our Army against so potent an adversary, and never more need than at present, in regard that the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of <em>Russia</em>, among other our Enemies, is now in the field with an Army of two hundred and fifty Thousand men, which yet he doth not <reg orig="thinke">think</reg> sufficient, but also, after many <reg orig="sollicitations">solicitations</reg>, hath received the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> into his protection, their General having in their name acknowledged him for their Lord and <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, this work being thus brought about chiefly by the <reg orig="Patriark">Patriarch</reg>, who doth wholly dispose of him and his Army by his <reg orig="Counsell">Council</reg>: and for security on the <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> part of their Fidelity, this <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> hath put three places into the hands of the <em>Muscovites</em>, and commanded all the Province of <em><reg orig="Vkraine">Ukraine</reg></em> to be in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> upon the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in of the <em>Russian</em> Army. We hear from <em>Riga</em>, That the said <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath removed all the Strangers that had any Office in his Army, upon <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg> that they<pb n="6" /> might prove false to him; and that he hath already taken many Prisoners out of the Province of <em>Smolensko</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>: The Assembly meets here twice of a day upon <reg orig="hastning">hastening</reg> the conclusion of Affairs, by reason the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath now declared he will be gone by the latter end of April: That main point concerning Justice being at last agreed upon. The <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of St. <em>Amour</em> hath been some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in this City, where having had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Conferences with the <em>Spanish</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, he is gone to <em>Vienna</em>, there to invite the Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em> to come and command the <em>Lorrainers</em> during the detention of the Duke <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> his Brother.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>: Notwithstanding the many fair promises which were made to our Commissioners at <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> by the Diet, yet are <reg orig="wee">we</reg> in <reg orig="continuall">continual</reg> fear that all the preparations made by our Elector do only aim at this City; and therefore this City is resolved to stand upon its <reg orig="owne">own</reg> defence and to have some forces on foot for their preservation: in the mean time to keep us in hopes of peace he lets us have a free Trade on the Rhine, and we hear he is expected at <em>Boone</em> in a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The <em>Lorrainers</em> are now quite gone out of the County of <em>Liege</em>, and the Archduke <em>Leopoldus</em> hath promised he will take care that County shall be free of <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 2 of March, 1654. There hath been a great dispute about the choosing of a new Bishop for this Diocese, the Dean and Chapter having proceeded to the election of an Archbishop, as soon as the other was deceased, and by reason that the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> was his Nephew, and had the reversion, <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> the place is fallen to him, as being his due, which is much displeasing to the Court, and therefore would have the Election to be null. The King went on the 21 instant to the Parliament, all the Chambers being assembled there, the Chancellor caused the <reg orig="processe">process</reg> against the Prince of <em>Conde</em> to be read, and order was passed for the speedy prosecution thereof. The 23 there marched out of this City ten Companies of Foot <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and the French guards, and four Companies of,<pb n="7" /> <em>Switzers</em> who are sent to recruit the Garrison of <em>Arras</em>, and are to be commanded by the Baron of <em>Vauturneux</em>.</p>

<p>The Marriage between the Duke of <em>Candale</em> and one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces is yet <reg orig="delayd">delayed</reg>, and some will have it be broken off: There is much discontent among the Protestants in <em>Languedoc</em> for their hard usage by the Parliament at <em>Tholoze</em>, where there is no justice to be had for them upon any cause, but continually are paid with delays, or flat denials. We hear from <em>Perpignan</em> that the <em>Spanish</em> Horse had left their Quarters in the County of <em>Lampourdan</em>, and were <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to the Plain of <em>Vrgel</em>, that so they may protest those who are appointed for the demolishing of all the fortifications of several Towns and Castles in the Province of <em>Catalonia</em>, which is to be done <reg orig="spedily">speedily</reg> according to an Order from the Counsel of <em>Spain</em> come to that purpose unto <em>Dom John d' Austria</em>, the intent being to reserve only <em>Barcelona</em>, and some 9 Towns more fortified, and to slight the Works of all the rest: The Count <em>de Harcourt</em> is now again upon a Treaty with the Court, having delivered <em>Tanes</em> Castle to the Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em>, he likewise sent one of his Gentlemen to the Court, who in his name hath made submissions and promises of future obedience to his Majesty, as also to carry Letters to his Brother the Duke <em>d' Ellouf</em> to carry on that Treaty, and a full power to end the same, and make a speedy conclusion; but news being <reg orig="spred">spread</reg> this morning that the said Duke was deceased, might be a means. Yesterday the 27, the King with many attendants went to the Parliament to see their proceedings in the <reg orig="Processe">Process</reg> against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, the Presidents and <reg orig="Counsellors">Councillors</reg> being all present in their ordinary Habit, and this Morning the King goeth thither again to be present at the pronouncing of the Sentence against him all the Chambers being assembled, and the Presidents and Counsellors to be in their Scarlet Gowns: The Cardinal hath so much tempered with the Marshal <em>de Hocquincourt</em>, that he hath prevailed so much as to draw him from the frontiers from <em>Peronne</em>, and is now to come to this City, many fair promises being made him, not only of security for his Person, but likewise for great preferment upon his compliance.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 29.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Bourdeaux</em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had <reg orig="publique">public</reg> audience in the Banqueting house in <em>Whitehall</em>, which was richly hung with hangings, and a great number of people present. The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> was carried in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and with him some of the Council, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, attended by divers of the Nobility and Gentry in the Coaches of the <em>Portugal </em><reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, and the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, and the Nobility and Gentry of <em>England</em>, above forty Coaches, most with six horses a piece.</p>

<p>Being come to <em>Whitehall</em> he was received by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, who was with his Council at the upper end of the Banqueting house, and after several <em>Congies</em> each to other, the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> made a speech to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> answer and salutings, he returned back again. A Committee of the Council is appointed to Treat with him.</p>

<p>From <em>Bristol</em> March 27. Yesterday, a new <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> was launched here for the Lord Protector and the Commonwealth, and another of the 3 Rate is raising on the Stocks.</p>

<p>The sufferings of this City of late from the <em>Brest</em> men of war have been great; scarce a week, but one ship or other of this Port hath been taken by them.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em> thus. We hear from <em>Stockholm</em> that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> having visited here Mother at <em>Nicoping</em> is again returned to <em>Ypsal</em> to be present at the great assembly of the <reg orig="Senatours">Senators</reg>, which is now to begin, and among other things which are to be debated in order to what shall be done at the next Diet, that which concerneth the affairs now in hand between <em>England</em> and them is to be discussed, and after some days the Queen intends to go to the Copper Mines, and there to remain until the beginning of the Diet: Our last Letters from <em>Poland</em> advise us, that as yet they have not any tidings of the arrival of their <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, but only that having escaped several dangers, he was fairly on his journey, and they hoped in a few days to hear of his arrival: The Country doth continue in great fears for the great preparations they see made in<pb n="9" /> <em>Muscovia</em>, where they have got together above two hundred and fifty thousand men, with the which they threaten to enter the Country by three <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> at once. We hear likewise that one <em>Zuischi</em>, who heretofore was arrested at the request of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of <em>Russia</em> in the City of <em>Lubeck</em>, and since that carried to <em>Moscow</em>, (which is the chief City) being brought to his Trial, was put to the Rack ordinary, and extraordinary, had his head cut off, and his body thrown upon a dunghill without burial, his Charge was, for having assumed to himself the Title of a Prince of <em>Moscovia</em>, which he was not, but a counterfeit. The general Diet is not yet concluded at <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>, although the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> doth <reg orig="presse">press</reg> very much that they should speedily put a period to it, his presence in <em>Hungaria</em> being very necessary for the speedy <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> of many things which are out of order, and to provide for the preservation of the Country against the Turkish invasion, which is much feared this next Spring, the Turks appearing very strong upon the Border. The Dukes of <em>Luneburgh, Holstein, Brunswick</em>, and <em>Meckleburgh</em>, who were met at <em>Hamborough</em>, are all returned homewards, having had first <reg orig="severall">several</reg> conferences, about making a defensive league between them. The Earls of <em>Welphalia</em> have been received Princes at the Diet, and so taken their place upon the fourth Bench, in the Chamber of Princes. The Earl of <em><unclear>Groesfelt</unclear></em> having returned thanks to the Company in a grave Speech for having admitted them into their Honourable society. The Earl of <em>Soremburgh</em> who was sent by the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> to <em>Rouxelles</em>, is now on his way homewards, not having given to the Elector of <em>Cullen</em> such a satisfaction as he expected, he doth go on in his Levies, and intends to quarter them in some part of <em>Westphalia</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday March 30.</i></head>

<p>This Day his Highness the Lord Protector, with advice of his Council, passed an Ordinance for Relief of Persons that have acted in the service of the Parliament, to this effect. That whereas many good and necessary Acts, Ordinances, and Orders of Parliament have heretofore been made for the encouragement, Indemnity, and saving harmless of such persons<pb n="10" /> as have in any sort either by Sea or Land Engaged, or Acted, or Commanded to be done, any matter or thing whatsoever by Authority, or for the service or benefit of the Parliament; And Committees having been appointed to take care therein, and that Justice should be done accordingly, the Power of which Committees being determined, and so no course settled for parties grieved, His Highness, having a continued and lively sense of such <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> undertakings &amp; hazards for the service of the <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> in times of eminent danger and extremity, And being willing that full remedy should be provided for their safety, Doth, by and with the Consent and advice of his Council, Declare, Establish and Ordain, That all and every the said Acts, Ordinances, and Orders of Parliament, and every Article, Clause and Sentence in them, or any of them contained, shall stand, remain, and be in full force, effect and virtue, and be put in practice and execution, and be pleadable and made use of in all Courts of Justice, as fully and absolutely, to all intents and purposes, as if the same had been now particularly made for such purpose.</p>

<p>And further Ordained, That where any person that ought to have been <reg orig="Indempnified">Indemnified</reg>, by the true meaning of the said Acts and Orders of Indemnity, hath any Judgement or Verdict already obtained against him at Law, for any matter or thing for which he ought so to have been <reg orig="indempnified">indemnified</reg>, by whereof he is disabled to plead his matter of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg> before the said Judges before mentioned, that then in every such case, upon complaint exhibited before the Barons of the Exchequer, setting forth his case, and <reg orig="alleaging">alleging</reg> such matter for his <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, as that Court shall judge sufficient; and also give in such security, as the said Barons shall approve of, to pay Cols unto the party molested or drawn so in question before the said Barons, in case he shall not prove the suggestion of his said complaint.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That nothing in this Ordinance be construed or understood to revive the power of the said Committees in any the former Ordinances or Acts of Parliament named, so as to enable the said Committees to <reg orig="intermedle">intermeddle</reg> in the execution<pb n="11" /> of any the said Acts or Ordinance. <i>As see further by the Act is <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> printed.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Leghorn</em> March 10 1654 <em>stilo novo</em>: We hear by a Ship from <em><reg orig="Barbarie">Barbary</reg></em> with Corn, that the Turkish Agent being come to <em>Tunis</em> hath pressed or taken up all the Galleys and Ships fit for service, and intends to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> the same at <em>Algier</em> and <em><reg orig="Tripali">Tripoli</reg></em>, in his coming hither he met two small Turkish Pirates, who being come up to him, and viewed him on both sides, not finding him a fit match to fight with, they tacked about and left him: This morning is come a report that the French <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> had met with two English Merchant ships, and after a long fight had taken them, both homewards bound, but by reason those that brought the news vary much, therefore little credit is given to it till there comes further confirmation.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em> the 27 of Febr. 1654. <em>S.N.</em> All the actions of our great Queen, are so many wonders, and continual effects of her Royal virtues, and of the <reg orig="greatnes">greatness</reg> of her incomparable courage, but some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since in special she did give such proof thereof, that the same may be called the Crown of all her other actions, seeing it doth manifest to the world how this admirable Princess hath set <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> above the Crowns, under which men commonly do seek their satisfaction and glory. The 23 of this instant she having summoned all the Senators of the Land, they all made their appearance, except 9. who were out of the Land upon <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>; there this Princess did declare unto them the design she had to leave the charge of the Kingdom, and to that end that she was resolved to go to <em>Nicoping</em> to confer with the Prince <em><reg orig="Palatin">Palatine</reg></em> of <em>Sweden</em> her Cousin, having sent him Letters to invite him thither, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to accept the charge of the Kingdom, and the managing of the State affairs; this Prince is the same who was heretofore Generalissimo of the <em>Swedish</em> Armies in <em>Germany</em>, concluded first a peace with the Duke <em>Picolomini</em>, and in the year 1650 at the Coronation of the Queen, was there declared heir apparent to the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, and by the <unclear>States</unclear> Commonalty acknowledged so, having made their Oath of Allegiance to him, as unto their future King, after the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> death; we<pb n="12" /> are expecting with great impatience the event of that generous and unthought of resolution. Yesterday, the 26, her Majesty had a mask danced in the behalf of the Earl <em>de <unclear>Montecuuth</unclear></em>, General of the Horse to the Emperor, where were present the English and Spanish Ambassadors, with many of our Senators; the beginning of this Mask was of an exquisite harmony of voices, and instruments, to sing some <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Poems, composed first by an <em>Italian</em>, called <em>Albertus Vimino</em>, in honour of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, in the midst of it was a splendid, and Royal collation of <reg orig="Sweet-meats">Sweetmeats</reg>, and other Rarities, and at the end of the Mask was brought by the Earl of <em>Todta</em> a rich Collar, and being laid near the Queen, there was a cushion laid at her feet, then having called to her the Earl of <em>Montecaculli</em>, and with her own hands invested him of that new Order of Knighthood called of <em>Amarantha</em>, and first instituted by her Majesty, who holding both his hands, did make him then promise, that he would truly and faithfully keep and observe all the statutes of that Order: during all this Ceremony the <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg> both vocal and instrumental, and among other rare pieces then sung, was one made in <em>Italian</em>, whereof all the verses ended thus, <em>Long may live Amarantha.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday March 31, and Saturday April 1.</i></head>

<p>An Ordinance also passed for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, Intituled, <em>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</em>; which being of so general concernment, take as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas upon perusal and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, Intituled, <em>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners</em>, many Doubts and Difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorized for Sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such Explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges, authorized in and by the said Act, several inconveniences and mischiefs would grow, not only to the said Creditors and Prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended<pb n="13" /> to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles, and suits in Law, and Equity; For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: And whereas many of the said Prisoners have offered really to endeavour the satisfaction of the said Creditors, if some further time may be given for that purpose; Be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the Sale or Disposition of any the Estates Real or personal, of any of the said Prisoners, or of any other person or persons whatsoever mentioned or intended in or by the said Act; nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act; or of any the powers or authorities given by the same, until the 20 day of <em>April</em> next. And be it further ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Acts or things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by virtue, <reg orig="color">colour</reg>, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said 20 day of <em>April</em>, shall be utterly void, null, and of none effect; saving only that it shall and may be <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> for the said several and respective Judges that have bailed or let out any Prisoners upon Sureties or otherwise, out of Prison (which Prisoners are to appear again at a certain day before the said Judges, and are not absolutely discharged by any Order of the said Judges, <i>as see further by the Act.</i></p>

<p>Paris April 1, 1654. All the discourse at present is concerning that which was acted in the Parliament on <em>Saturday</em> last, when all the Chambers being assembled, and every Member in their Scarlet Gowns, the King then came, and being sat in his bed of Justice, they proceeded in the <reg orig="busines">business</reg> of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, his sentence being read, which containeth, That for being found guilty of high Treason, and Rebellion, against the King his Lord and Liege, he was to put to death, and that so soon as he should be apprehended, his Sentence to be executed, his lands and goods all forfeited to the Crown; in regard of his quality he is not to be executed in <reg orig="Effigie">Effigy</reg>, and as touching the manner of his death the Parliament would not determine<pb n="14" />, but left it to his Majesties pleasure: The Prince of <em>Conti</em> was not then in Town, but had taken an occasion to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to <em>Chatilli</em>, as some believe, because he would not be present at the condemnation of his Brother, which he could not have excused if he had been in the City: The Treaty of the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> goeth on apace, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought will be finished within 10 days. The Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> is not a little troubled because he can not finish the Marriage of he two <reg orig="Neeces">Nieces</reg>, for when it was thought quite done, it was found further off, and very little hopes of the Treaty with the Cardinal <em>de Rets</em>, who doth still remain a close Prisoner in the Castle of <em>Vicennes</em>.</p>

<p><em>Edinburgh</em>, 25 <em>March</em>. The Commander in Chief having issued forth a Proclamation, Requiring all <reg orig="Burroughes">Burroughs</reg> and other parishes to secure all <reg orig="suspitious">suspicious</reg> persons, or otherwise to give intelligence of them to the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present Government, and proceeded against accordingly: <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Towns have been lately found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a Court Marshal for the same. The last week the parish of <em>Liberton</em>, two miles from <em>Edinburgh</em>, for harbouring 15 of the Enemy by the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving Intelligence of them, and the Tories at their going away stealing 15 Horses, the parish was for that offence fined 200 l. <em>sterling</em>, the person in whose House they were concealed, <reg orig="sentenc't">sentenced</reg> to Imprisonment during pleasure, and the House where they were harboured to be <reg orig="raced">raised</reg> to the ground, and a pair of Gallows to be built there. There are divers other parishes who are <reg orig="summon'd">summoned</reg> in to Court Marshals upon the very same account, who will suffer for it. It is hoped this course will in time <reg orig="compell">compel</reg> the <em>Scots</em> not to give any Entertainment unto the Tories, but give notice of them, wherever they shall come, otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>

<p>The 21 instant Col. <em>Cooper</em> with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em>, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of <em>Leven</em>, where about 300 of the Enemy quartered (about 4 in the morning) took <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg></em><pb n="15" /> Trumpet, and 35 other Prisoners, and narrowly missed <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Newarke">Newark</reg></em>, who were both there; They killed 12, whereof of them (as the Enemy <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> ) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 Horse, and some Arms, totally scattered the whole party, and returned without any <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>

<p>This week Capt. <em><reg orig="Ortan">Orton</reg></em> Commander of the <em>Sun</em>, and Capt. <em>Bilburn</em> of the <em><unclear>Vnton</unclear></em> came into <em>Lieth</em> Road, from <em>Lewis</em> and <em>Oikney</em>, and brought three Companies of Col. <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> Regiment, and therewith a particular relation of the late infall of the Earl of <em>Seafort</em> into <em>Lewis</em> Island, much to the same purpose formerly related.</p>

<p><em>Dublin</em> March 18. Since the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> departure for <em>England</em> we have nothing further of news, but that about 1200 <em>Tories</em> are shipped away from <em>Limbrick</em>, and 1700 more are ready for transportation which renders the whole Nation more free, than in times of the greatest peace this Land hath enjoyed.</p>

<p><em>Plymouth</em> Fort, March 24. The news this place affords is, the Commander of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a Dutch prize, which hath no loading, only some few barrels of Pitch, &amp;c. This week the <em>Paul</em>, a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met with a <em>Plushen</em> man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> in the Channel of 15 Guns, who after 5 hours fight took her, and this day brought her in hither, we lost not any man in the fight, but sustained some <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> in Masts, Sails, and Rigging; the Enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and the ship much torn, she hath some silver in her, and some small quantity of Wines.</p>

<p>Great have been the Expectations and hopes of a Peace and Union between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> upon this last Treaty, which we have <reg orig="severall">several</reg> weeks mentioned, and we can now safely assure you, that the Articles of Peace, both in relation to them <em>Denmark</em>, are absolutely concluded on, and for a full confirmation (undoubtedly) will be signed and sealed by Commissioners on both sides, before the publication of our next.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>