<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn215">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 215</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><em>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> January 16. to <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em>, January 23. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 16.</i></head>

<p>This day from <em>Scotland</em> we had these papers following, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>A Letter from the Earl of <em>Glencairn</em> to the Governor of <em>Badgenoth</em> Castle, and his answer thereunto. Together with a Letter from the Governor, to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</p>

<p><i>For my <unclear>honoured</unclear> Friend</i>, Cap. <em>John Hill</em>, Governor of the Castle of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</p>

<p>SIR, I have sent a Letter of yours directed to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>, wherein you have expressed so much <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> to your <reg orig="un just">unjust</reg> Masters from whom you are trusted, that it makes me conceive, if those principles of yours were rightly founded upon the warrantable grounds<pb n="1" /> of legality, you might yet redeem your former failings, and those principles of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> which now are darkened in you, being out of their true Channel, may shine eminently, when unclouded, from under those fatal <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and snares wherein many gallant spirits in this age are <reg orig="insnared">ensnared</reg>. Thus much I have conceived it fit to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> you, that I might undeceive you in some opinions, upon which I find you ground your Arguments in your Letter to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>: As first you look upon your Commonwealth (as you call it) as one firm and <reg orig="fixt">fixed</reg> Government, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>, there is at this instant no such thing in <em>England</em>, that power which was lately called a Parliament, being by the Trustees again resigned in <reg orig="Cromwells">Cromwell's</reg> hands, and now none <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg> what Government he will pitch on; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> what may be conjectured from his former actings, he is like to frame such an one (if possible) which will rather maintain such an interest, <reg orig="then">than</reg> prove any <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> comfortable to the ruined and oppressed people of <em>England</em>. Another ground you go upon in your Letter, that this Army now of foot by his Majesties Command, for him and his long oppressed <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> delivery, will soon evanish. It seems the distance you are at in this remote place, admits you not right information; you may indeed look upon this as the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> work, returning the abused spirits of all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Subjects, to<pb n="2" /> their duty to their King and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>; for now most of all <em>Scotland</em> are in Arms, and many gallant <em>English</em> are already in Arms, and have marched through the greatest part of <em>England</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces in this Kingdom; (besides what is doing in <em>Ireland</em>) all Christian Princes are arming against those you now serve, and ere long will bring a flood of strangers upon them, if the Lord do not bring them to prevent their <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> by a timely submission to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> most just command. I have given you this right view of the present condition of Affairs, because I have been informed of your gallantry, that when you reckon betwixt God and you alone, and deals impartially with <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg>, you may do <reg orig="your self">yourself</reg> that right to <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> that <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> God hath given you in the most approven way by him, wherein if you <reg orig="finde">find</reg> I can serve, you may freely command your friend and Servant,</p>

<p><i>Decemb. 30. 1653. Glencairn.</i></p>

<head level="3">For the Earl of <em>Glencairn</em></head>

<p>My Lord,</p>

<p><i>I received yours by your Trumpet, wherein you have put <reg orig="your selfe">yourself</reg> to much <reg orig="labor">labour</reg>, to convince me of the <reg orig="orroniousness">erroneousness</reg> of my principles, and of my blindness for want of information; the truth is I see not so far as I desire, but the more I see, the more I discover of the unwarrantableness of your proceedings, given about to disquiet the peace of the Country, and to devour that little which the poor people have left them, upon pretence of a King, which I assure you I have disowned, and will still disclaim: And whereas you are pleased to inform <unclear>me</unclear> of the greatness of your Army, and of many who daily appear for you in <em>England</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, I am apt to believe, that were you so powerful as you speak, your Lordship might have had far better quarters in the Lowlands; but were you ten times the number which you are, it should not cause me to own that power which you call Kingly, or to betray that trust committed to me by my just Masters, the deliverers under God, of the poor oppressed and <reg orig="inslaved">enslaved</reg> people of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and <em>Scotland</em>, from regal Tyranny and bondage, but shall through the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> assistance approve <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> faithful to them, while called by the name of <em>John Hill</em>.</i></p>

<p>Ruthven Castle, 30. Decemb. 1653.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">For the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</head>

<p><i>Gentlemen,</i></p>

<p>For as much as I believe you will be summoned to come in to the Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>, Lord <em>Lorn</em>, and others now come into the Country to its <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, (<reg orig="what ever">whatever</reg> they pretend to the contrary) to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in their unwarrantable &amp; headlong designs, to the destruction of our own peace and welfare: I desire you to look back to your Engagements to those (who though of another Nation) never dealt so hardly with you as these do: I see the destruction of many of them eminent, who are <reg orig="Murtherers">Murderers</reg>, <reg orig="theeves">thieves</reg>, Drunkards, Swearers, Whoremongers, <reg orig="Headdy">Heady</reg> high-minded, proud and yet <reg orig="beggers">beggars</reg>, disobedient to honest and good Parents, Trucebreakers, Bankrupts, and lawless persons; and generally such as the Scripture excludes from Heaven, and think you, can these men prosper? All that they pretend is for a King, but their intent is to strike at the power of godliness, and that lust might <reg orig="raign">reign</reg> <reg orig="uncontroled">uncontrolled</reg>; and judge you, if they could do no more for their great <reg orig="Idoll">Idol</reg> when personally present with them, at such time as they had the general concurrence of this Country, and some of other Nations, what they are now likely to effect for him with this handful of men Beasts; and indeed, I cannot but much wonder, that your young Master, who is the son of so good a <em>Father</em>, should concur with these Birds of Prey to defile his own Nest, and with these Caterpillars to eat up and destroy those people that have their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> upon him, but surely if he be a man that hath any spark of grace or honesty, he will rather die <reg orig="then">than</reg> suffer these men so to wrong and abuse his own innocent people; but certainly, if he do otherwise, destruction will be his portion: I do again require you, as you tender your own good, to give no concurrence with these men; which if you do, it will undoubtedly prove your <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, (as I have formerly and more at large declared to you;) but if you carry out <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> honestly according to your <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg>, you may expect <reg orig="stedfast">steadfast</reg> friends to stand by you, when these like <reg orig="chaffe">chafe</reg> are blown away with the <reg orig="whirl wind">whirlwind</reg> of destruction; and this I must tell you, that when you first obliged <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> to us, those your Engagements were in your own apprehension, either lawful or unlawful; If lawful you are strictly <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> to perform them, and God will require an account <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>; if unlawful <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> guile be at your doors for it: I leave these things with you, desiring you to ponder them seriously, your Friend and Servant, <em>John Hill.</em></p>

<p><em>Rutvurn Decemb.</em> 31. 1653.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Jan: 17</head>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em>, Jan: 17. <em>stilo nov</em>. We are here very apt to believe a peace, because it is a thing exceedingly desired all over these Lands: And there is the more hope, because all things are very still and <reg orig="calme">calm</reg>, both at sea and land: And we have added to all our conceits the like out of <em>England</em>, by the way of <em>Flanders</em>; from whence Letters say, that there was not much difference between the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at their parting. Some things have been communicated from them to the States General, which take up a great part of their time in consultation, but nothing can be certainly known yet of the event, because it depends upon their <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> present Resultation: But we <reg orig="ghesse">guess</reg> things may go well, because men are not high in Discourse (as formerly) against <em>England</em>, besides we observe little talk of a war, or of a desire to it. Thus we live by <reg orig="ghesses">guesses</reg>. The Princes about us are loath to see two such formidable <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> in so <reg orig="neare">near</reg> a Conjunction, especially now that <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em> are united under one Head, and that a wise and, an active one too; and therefore they bid high in hope to keep open the breach; of whose <reg orig="feares">fears</reg> and jealousies the States here will be able to make many an <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> use, and <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> them up to their own conditions, as they shall see cause.</p>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em>, Jan. 7. The Supplies are safely and timely arrived here, for the encouragement of our Forces in this Nation, where <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg> look with no <reg orig="plaesant">pleasant</reg> face, by reason of the great devastations, <reg orig="spoiles">spoils</reg>, and devourings made by the <em>Highland</em> Locusts, who have been swarming and pilfering up and <reg orig="downe">down</reg> in all parts. And now they are very active in their Levies.</p>

<p><reg orig="Doubtlesse">Doubtless</reg>, the enemy have been fed and <reg orig="heightned">heightened</reg> with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary hopes and promises; and so may be more considerable <reg orig="then">than</reg> is believed, as to matter of resolution; but how to accomplish <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of moment, as yet is not seen: but great men <reg orig="doe">do</reg> still flock to them.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>As this week the Commander in <reg orig="Chiefe">Chief</reg> hath received an account of the flying out of young <em>Montross</em>, and <em>Charles</em> Lord <em><reg orig="Gourdon">Gordon</reg></em>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> brother to the late Marquis of <em>Huntley</em>, and Chief of that Clan, who are gone in to the enemy.</p>

<p>By Letters from Dublin in Ireland was certified; that Lieu: Gen. Fleetwood and the Commissioners are at Dublin; That the Lord Musgrave is to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> the beginning of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>; That all is very quiet in Ireland, save some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties of <reg orig="Torie">Tory</reg>, which are chiefly about the County of Carlow, where they lately fell upon and wounded some of the <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>; and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> sometime where they dare venture, and <reg orig="flie">flee</reg> away again with their prey presently.</p>

<p>An Ambassador from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> was this day to congratulate His Excellency the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Lesleboue Long</em>, to whom is added Mr. <em>Sadler</em> are the Masters of Requests for Petitions that are to his Highness.</p>

<p>Dover, 13 <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 1653. We have <reg orig="severall">several</reg> ships out in several parts, for securing the English Merchants in and out, which makes us now to hear little of the Brest men: And our Fleet with Gen. <reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg> in the Channels is ready for action, if the Dutch do not agree. The French are not a little troubled to hear there is such probability: But there was a sad accident befell the Protestants in France, the last Sunday; for so soon as the Exercises were done at Charington, the place where the Protestants meet, about two Leagues<pb n="6" /> from Paris, many of them were cast away in a Boat <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> home towards Paris. It <reg orig="seemes">seems</reg> there useth to go a Passage-Boat between Paris and that Church, to carry those that cannot well go on foot so fane, and return with them when the Ordinances are over: and this Boat returning with them on the lat Sunday, there being in it <reg orig="abount">about</reg> and hundred persons, and of them divers were whole Families; so soon as they were in the Boat almost, it being but newly put off, near a Mill which was then going, they were by the stream forced under the Mill; which <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to near it, did suck them in, and about sixty of them are drowned; and amongst them two Lords, sons of that pious Protestant <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg>, the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of <em>Mirambo</em>, and others of quality.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Francford">Frankford</reg></em> the 7. of <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 1654. The Duke of Simmeren having ended those differences between him and the Prince Elector; having taken his leave from the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and the Nobles, is gone homewards. The Diet at <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg> begins now to act upon <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, and in the first place they have agreed that the new chosen Princes of the Empire shall from henceforth sit in the Princes Chamber, and have power to Vote: And is concerning the <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of money promised the D: of Lorrain for the evacuation of his Forces out of the Empire, and the quitting of those places which are as yet <reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> by him, although there is an agreement of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, the Princes and other Nobles, yet the States are very backwards, and <reg orig="finde">find</reg> many difficulties to put the same in execution; and so this business with many others who are yet undecided doth put the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> to no small anxiety, being daily solicited by the States of Hungaria to be present at their Diet, which is to begin the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> at Presburgh; the <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> occasion being for the Election of a new Palatine, and so end the differences lately sprung up between the Protestants and Papists; upon that subject we have news that the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of Russia hath declared open <reg orig="warres">wars</reg> to the King of Poland, and that he is marching with a powerful Army towards Smolmsko, with an intent to besiege it, having sent another Army into Russia-alba, consisting of 40 thousand men, whereof the one half is of his Subjects being all<pb n="7" /> under the Command of the High-Dutch Officers: and one third Army sent to the <reg orig="reliefe">relief</reg> of the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, which doth put the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of Prustia and Moravia into an excessive <reg orig="feare">fear</reg>, seeing themselves already so much <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> by the Tartars and <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em>, Jan. 21: 1654. <em>stilo nov.</em> By the last Letters from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, we have <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, that this Winter season hath caused the Spanish ships to forsake their <reg orig="Rivers">River's</reg> mouth: which thereby is become free, but as yet we have little trading here, which doth make us suffer much: We are expecting here daily our Ambassador which was at Rome, whom we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> to be gone from thence by land to Florence, and so is to <reg orig="imbarque">embark</reg> at Lerio: And as concerning the new Minister to succeed him, there is yet no certainty, there being three in nomination, but as yet none agreed upon: The Knight of Ctequi is now gone into Picardy, there to raise some forces which are to be Commanded by the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Sidon, and these are to be employed for the <reg orig="reliefe">relief</reg> of the Leigers, who have of late been visited by the Prince of Conde, and the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> Forces, who have <reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> themselves of two small <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>, and thereby have got power to quarter themselves therein; the <reg orig="Coantrey">Country</reg> having endeavoured to oppose them, but came by the worst in the encounter.</p>

<p>Forasmuch as many persons have <reg orig="Claimes">Claims</reg> depending at Worcester-house upon the last Bill for sale of <reg orig="Delinquents">Delinquent's</reg> Estates: It is thought necessary to publish and give notice that all persons who have any <reg orig="Claimes">Claims</reg> there depending upon that Act, do bring the same unto a hearing before the last day of this present <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>, for that the Commissioners for removing Obstructions have not power to hear any Reports upon <reg orig="Claimes">Claims</reg> after that time. And the great cause concerning Sir <em>Arthur Haslerig</em> and the Commonwealth about the Estate of Mr <em>Cuthbert Collingwood</em> of Eslington in the County of Northumberland is appointed to be heard on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 30 day of January instant, before the said Commissioners for Removing Obstructions sitting at Worcester-house.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday January 18.</i></head>

<p>The <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador's Brother was by an Order of the Council removed back from the Tower to Newgate, the Sessions now sitting in the <em><reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg></em>; but upon several grounds, and the Petition of the <em>Portugal</em> Merchants, his Trial was put off <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the next Sessions.</p>

<p>The Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> from the several Garrisons and Regiments have been very unanimous in signing the Establishment and Engagement to the Lord Protector, as certified by their several addresses to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, whereof take one, as followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>. Our Lord General.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The humble Address of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army.</i></head>

<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services, wherein through the blessing of God upon the <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg> and <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> of your Highness, we have in some measure been Instrumental in our places to free the Commonwealth from its enemies: So we now cannot but above all worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations after all the shakings which have been in the midst of us, set up upon its true and proper Basis and Foundation, and thereby brought into a <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of rest and safety. The sense whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your Highness, and the whole Nation at this time when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment by inclining you to accept of the Government and Protection of this Commonwealth; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the people, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We judge it highly incumbent upon us to make our humble address unto you, and to declare, That we shall not only be obedient unto you in the performance of Your great Trust, in the performance of Your great Trust, but in our places most faithfully and diligently. To the hazard of our Lives, and whatsoever is near and dear unto us, be serviceable unto you in the station<pb n="9" /> God hath placed you against all opposition: Not doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you, so You will to the utmost of your power and endeavours, lay forth <reg orig="Your Self">Yourself</reg> for the Glory of God, and the Good of this People amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of Faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take this <reg orig="boldnesse">boldness</reg> most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> Your Highness more especially to spread the wing of Your Protection, and to account of them as the apple of Your eye; which You continuing to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, We are confident their Father which is in Heaven will be unto you a Buckler and a Shield, and an exceeding great reward, which is, and shall be the prayer of</p>

<p><i>Your Highness most humble, and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servants.</i></p>

<p><em>Dalkeith <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 14. <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencary</em> with their forces marched by the way of <em>Strathspey</em>, and <em>Glencarn Lane</em>, <em><reg orig="Mac. Aldney">McAldney</reg></em>, and some of <em><reg orig="Mac. Griggers">McGrigger's</reg></em> men, with the rest of the gang (<em>Athol</em> being left behind) marched by the head of <em>Badgnoth</em>, and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> their forces within three miles of <em>Ruthven</em> Garrison. Upon their approach <em>Glencarn</em> sent a Letter to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Castle, inviting him to come in to his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> forces, and telling him, That all <em>Scotland</em> was up in Arms, and many had marched through <em>England</em> top <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them: To which, he received a very resolute and ingenious answer from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> Cap: <em>Hill</em>; and it was not probable his Lordship had so great an Army, when he could provide no better quarters for them. After they had been a while in <em>Lorne</em>, there fell a discontent between <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Lorne</em>, about the men of the Country, <em>Lorn</em> saying, They being his men, he ought to have the ordering and disposal of them, as the Earl of <em>Athol</em> had of his; but <em>Glencarn</em> told him, that he took up the Rents of the Country, the men were the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> of <reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg>. After many high words, <em>Glencarn</em> offered to draw his Sword, and <em>Lorne</em> went away in a great rage, swearing, That rather than he would see his own people abused by <em>Glencarn</em>, he would lose his life, and thereupon drew to the other side of the water with some<pb n="10" /> of <reg orig="Mac.Griggers">MacGrigger's</reg> then, and about sixty horse with him: This difference hath put the Country to a stand, who otherwise would have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with Lorne; so that some of them are fled to <em>Innerness</em>, and other parts, to secure themselves. Parties of Horse, and Posts are directed every way, for the apprehending of <em>Lorne</em>, The Enemy take up all the Horse they can find in the Country.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 19</head>

<p><em>Paris <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 24, <em>stilo novo</em>. The last news from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg> advise us, that the States of that Province were still at variance with the Parliament, whom they accuse to attempt against the Royal authority and the good of the Country, and moreover complain of other abuses, thereupon ordered that their grievances should be drawn out in <reg orig="writting">writing</reg>, and Commissioners appointed to carry them to the Court; The Parliament have likewise raised a sum of <reg orig="moneis">monies</reg>, and have appointed Commissioners to go to the Court, and make their humble Remonstrance to the King upon that Subject: This week the Parliament having order to come to the <em><reg orig="Louur">Louvre</reg></em>, went there by a select number of them; the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was concerning Rents and moneys due upon the <reg orig="Town-hall">Town Hall</reg>, but after a long debate they went home again, having got more of discontent than money: The City of <em>Piriguex</em> having of late submitted to the King, and thereupon sent their Commissioners to the Court, they had the first audience, where there was a great many Protestations made on their parts, and so were paid again in the same <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg>: The Prince <em>Thomaso</em> of <em>Savoy</em> hath obtained the eminent place which the Prince of <em>Conde</em> had at Court, although it had already been promised to another by the Cardinal: The great Mask, or Ball is not yet <reg orig="compleated">completed</reg>, and therefore expectations is still to see it, being a thing will spend many Crowns in gold and silver; it is said here that the Cardinal will carry the King to <em>Chanille</em> (a house formerly belonging to the Duke of <em><unclear><!-- approx. 12 characters --></unclear></em>, but by the late King given to the Prince of Condi) to take possession thereof, as falling to him by way of confiscation, but others will not have it so, but tell us of divers<pb n="11" /> matches between the great ones, whereby they affirm that things will look of another hue, but seeing the Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> cannot as yet be drawn into come to the Court, there are very small hopes of any conclusion of those matches, the preparations go on for the consecrating of the King at <em>Rheims</em> the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. The letters from <em>Naples</em> advise us, that the Cardinal of <em>Savelli</em> having remained there some time, and being visited by our new <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> is gone to <em>Salerna</em>. The <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> is to go in state within a few dayes to the high Church, it being a <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> at the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of new <reg orig="Vicekings">Vice kings</reg>, to ride thither in a stately manner: The new <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> hath taken a great distaste at the Prince of St. <em>Severo</em> at his return from <em>Apuglia</em>, the occasion of it being for <reg orig="entring">entering</reg> the City with above one thousand to attend on him, and thereupon hath commanded him to remain as prisoner into his own house.</p>

<p>From <em>Rome</em>: The Cardinal <em>Trivultio</em> (who doth now act for Spain in the absence of their <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>) had audience of the Pope this week, which did continue near two hours.</p>

<p>From <em>Genoa</em> there is no other, than that the late <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of <em>Naples</em> was gone from thence with 4 Galleys, but having met with <reg orig="foule">foul</reg> weather they were forced to return thither again.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em>: The Senate hath again issued orders for the <reg orig="hastning">hastening</reg> of the Fleet, which is thought will be ready in a short time to go to Sea, and likewise care is taken that the land forces may be in a <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg>, both of them being to the greater than it hath been hitherto since the War between the Turks and us: The Commander <em>Barbarigo</em> hath concluded the contract of twenty men of war in <em>France</em>, and besides some Dutch Merchants have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> to furnish ten besides four English ships: so that all things are in a good <reg orig="forwardnesse">forwardness</reg> against the next Spring: We hear from our Army in <em>Dalmatia</em> that the <em>Morlacks</em> were gathered in a body of about fifteen hundred men,<pb n="12" /> with an intent to break in the Country of <em>Albania</em>, but that great abundance of Snow being fallen: they were forced to remain in their old quarters.</p>

<p>Nothing yet from <em>Holland</em> but what is expressed by private Letters, that the States would within 6 days an answer for an absolute agreement with <em>England</em>, as also <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> their Deputy Monsieur <em>Barrel</em> in <em>France</em>, that the States have agreed to the English Propositions for peace.</p>

<p>From <em>Dartmouth <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. 12, The <em>Hector</em> hath brought in a ship hither, which hath in her 3000 Cheeses, the ship is of <em>Amsterdam</em>, and took in her Lading at the <em><unclear>Else</unclear></em>. There is a private man of War hath brought in a ship of <em><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg></em> laden with Herrings, and Holland Cheeses, and about 10 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of Pepper, and some Cloves.</p>

<head level="3">Friday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 20.</head>

<p>This day further from Scotland came as followeth. These parts <reg orig="afforde">afford</reg> no news, the Enemy is preparing to make ready for the season of the year, and do the utmost this Winter to promote their design, and do send into our quarters their Warrants for their levies, but dare not come themselves to see performance, only in the night do sometimes come and steal horses, and at sometimes carry away some men, you may by the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> see their Warrants, and what the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of this place Col. Cooper is constrained to do to counterwork them, or else the people would be too willing to answer their expectations, no more but that I am Sir,</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg> <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 12 1653.</i></head>

<p><em>William</em> Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>, Lord <em>Kilmarrs</em>, Commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of <em>SCOTLAND</em>.</p>

<p><i>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to us by His Majesty for <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> of Forces, Horse and Foot, for suppressing the Common Enemy within this Kingdom, we <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby require you, and every of you, within the Shires of <em><reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg></em> and <em>Renstrew</em>, upon sight hereof, to send forth for His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service (forth of every Thousand pounds rent within<pb n="13" /> your said Shires respectively, one sufficient well-mounted man, with Pistols, and other Furniture, and weapons belonging thereto, and to deliver the same at <em>Rosdew</em>, to Lieut. Col. <em>George Maxwell</em>, Lieut. Col. <em>George Herriot</em>, and Captain <em>James Cunningham</em>, or any having their Orders for that effect; certifying all persons of whatsoever quality, within the said Shires respectively, that doth either refuse or delay to give obedience to this Order, and Commands, they shall be taken notice of, and proceeded against as <reg orig="disloyall">disloyal</reg> Subjects, and <reg orig="profess'd">professed</reg> Enemies to the present Expedition; whereas by the contrary we do hereby oblige <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to protect and defend against all Enemies whatsoever, all such as shall willingly put forth their several proportions of the foresaid Horse <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg>. And whatsoever Horse, or any other Goods shall be taken from <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> of them, so protected, in any disorderly manner, shall not only be restored again, but the person or persons <reg orig="offendors">offenders</reg>, shall according to the quality of the offence, at the sight of the party offended, be severely punished, to the terror of others; And ordains this to be published at every Headborough, or Parish Church, within the said Shires respectively, That every Heritor, and others therein contained, pretend no ignorance of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>. Given at <em>Garth</em>, the 23 of <em>December, 1653</em>. Sicsubscributer, <em>GLENCAIRN</em>.</i></p>

<p>For the whole Noblemen, Gent: Heritors, and others, Inhabitants within the <reg orig="Shrefdoms">Sheriffdoms</reg> of <em>Ayre</em> and <em>Ransrew</em>,</p>

<p><i>We expect your answer at <em>Rosdew</em> the 6 of <em>January</em>, 1654.</i></p>

<p>This from Col. <em>Cooper</em> upon the aforesaid Paper to the Noblemen, Gentlemen, &amp;c. of <em><reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg></em> and <em>Randsrew</em>, as followeth.</p>

<p>Having seen a Paper, subscribed <em>Glencairn</em>, directed to the Noblemen, Gentlemen, Heritors, and all others within the Shires of <em><reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg></em> and <em>Renfrew</em>, Commanding them to set <reg orig="fort">forth</reg> horses furnished for war, with sufficient Riders thereon, and to bring in the same to <em>Rosdew</em>, and to deliver them to such persons as shall be there to receive them. And lest <reg orig="bigg">big</reg> words should fright some, and <reg orig="subtill">subtle</reg> <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> delude others into obedience of the same Papers, to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> not only of the persons so yielding, but to the apparent hazard of the peace and welfare<pb n="14" /> of the said Shires, and the inevitable mischiefs that will ensue; These are therefore to require all Noblemen, Gentlemen, Heritors, and others in the said Shires of <em><reg orig="Ayre">Ayr</reg></em> and <em>Renfrew</em>, to refuse obedience to all such Commands, and not in the least by <reg orig="ayding">aiding</reg> and assisting to the said <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, directly or indirectly, nor to hold any correspondence with the said <em>Glencarn</em>, or his <reg orig="associats">associates</reg>, now in Rebellion against the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, as they would not be held and deemed <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Enemies, and proceeded against as such with the utmost of extremity. And lest any should pretend ignorance in the same, the Sheriffs of the respective Shires are required to take special notice, that copies hereof may be sent to every Church within the said Shires to be published. Given under my hand at <em>Glasgow</em>, this 5th of <em>January</em> 1653.</p>

<p><i>THO: COOPER.</i></p>

<p>We hear by a Ship come from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, and also many ships this week come from <em>Dunkirk</em>, of ten of our Merchant men come safely to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> laden with all Eastern commodities, and five of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> convoy to them, who have also homewards bound made several prises upon the Coast of <em>Norway</em>, which will be in <em>England</em> very shortly.</p>

<p>All persons are desired to take notice that the Committee for claims for lands in <em>Ireland</em> have appointed Thursday the ninth of <em>February</em> 1653, for Adventurers to draw lots at Grocers-hall <em>London</em> for <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>, and that all persons who intend then to draw lots, do before that day pay their pence.</p>

<p><i>William Tibbs</i></p>

<p>From Milford <reg orig="haven">Haven</reg> the 16th of January. Some <reg orig="Vessells">Vessels</reg> come lately from <em>Ireland</em> bring news, that all things there are much at one: only that the <em>Tories</em> in <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> parties do much mischief, endeavouring to gather up a body of an Army, and of late some encounter was between a party of ours and them, but they were forced back again into the <reg orig="boggs">bogs</reg>, their great Sanctuary, with some loss. The Plague is not yet ceased, but remaineth in many parts, but not so violent as formerly.</p>

<p>From the Isle of Wight thus. General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> is still riding<pb n="15" /> with the Fleet without St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point; some of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> are passed by to the Eastward, as convoy to 12 <reg orig="sailes">sails</reg> of Merchant ships, for the <reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg> the winds favouring them, <unclear>these</unclear> eight <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> sent to cross the Channel are come in again, and have brought with them two Dutch prizes; there is another party <unclear>sent</unclear> out in their Head.</p> 

<p>By Letters of a later date from Scotland they write, That the Highlanders increase in their Levies, and confirm, That the young <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> of <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> and <em>Huntley</em> are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with them. Also a Letter from <em>Aberdeen</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That 17 Dutch ships are arrived in <em>Scotland</em> with 1500<reg orig="Forreigners">Foreigners</reg>, and <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and 200 Horse.</p>

<p>There is nothing as yet further from <em>Holland</em> to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> their agreement to the Treaty of Peace, what ever reports be. General <em>Blake</em> is again gone down to the Fleet, whom we understand will be in <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> to put to Sea (according to Orders) very shortly.</p>

<p>Letters further from <em>France</em> speak of an <reg orig="Imbargo">Embargo</reg> to be put upon all our English <reg orig="shippes">ships</reg> in their ports for the present.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly published an <unclear>express</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> Mr. <em><reg orig="Baxters">Baxter's</reg></em> <unclear>Aphouldnes</unclear> of <unclear><reg orig="Iustification">Justification</reg></unclear>, with a <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> of <unclear><reg orig="Iustification">Justification</reg></unclear> by <reg orig="neer">near</reg> grace from all the Popish and Armenian <unclear>Sophisanes</unclear>, by which the Author labours to ground it on <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> works and <reg orig="righteousnesse">righteousness</reg>: wherein you have his <unclear><reg orig="Aphocismes">Aphorisms</reg></unclear> repeated and <unclear>confused</unclear>: By <em><unclear>John Crander</unclear></em> Minister of the Gospel, sold by <em>T. Brewster</em> at the <unclear><!-- 1 character --></unclear> Bibles <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="church-yard">churchyard</reg>, and <em>L. <unclear>Chipaus</unclear></em> at the Crown in <em>Popes-head Alley</em>.</p>

<p>A piece <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, Observations on the present manners of the English, briefly <unclear>anaromizing</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> by the dead, with an <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> detection of the <unclear><!-- approx. 14 characters --></unclear> both <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> <em>Richard Whitlock</em> Dr. in <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, late of <em>All-Saints</em> College in <em>Oxford</em>. <unclear>Also the</unclear> Tragedy of <em>Alphons</em> as <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> of Germany; written by George <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear>, both printed for <em>Humphrey <reg orig="Mosely">Moseley</reg></em> at the Princes Arms in St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>-<reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<p>A brown bay <reg orig="fillie">filly</reg>, with a bald face, and two <reg orig="whitefeet">white feet</reg> behind, her far eye is a whale eye, a little dale backed, about fourteen <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> high, she will be two years old the next <unclear>grasle</unclear>, she was <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> upon Friday the 6th day of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> in the Evening. If any one can bring <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of her to Mr. <em>John Smith</em> at <em>Kegworth</em> in the County of <em>Leicester</em>, or to <em>Thomas <unclear>Alney</unclear></em> at the sign of the Sun in Newgate-Market in <em>London</em>, he shall be well rewarded for his pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>