<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn215#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 215#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> January. 30. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, February. 6. 1654</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 30.</i></head>

<p>The last week we gave an account of the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> first audience, and speech to her Majesty of <em>Sweden</em>, what further passed and was then omitted (wanting room) of her Majesties present Reply to the Lord Ambassador, and some other transactions, take now as followeth.</p>

<p><i>After my Lord Ambassador had done his speech, the Queen answered him presently in the Swedish Language, which my Lord <em>Lagerfield</em> interpreted in <em><reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg></em>, to this effect, That she esteemed it a very great <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> that the Parliament had been pleased to send an Ambassador to her, especially a person of his Excellencies condition, and that she <reg orig=" her self "> herself </reg> would take care during<pb n="1" /> his abode here, that not the least injury should be offered either to him or to his Company; and that she hoped in her Government there should be no cause or doubt of the contrary; That as his person was very acceptable to her, so was the business which he had imparted; in the transaction whereof she should manifest the affection she bore to the Commonwealth, and her desire not only to renew former <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between them, but to enter into a <reg orig="nearar">nearer</reg> union <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore; that she was glad of these blessings which the Commonwealth had received in their peace and settlement; and <reg orig="wisht">wished</reg> the continuance thereof to them. She thanked his Excellency for his civilities to her, and for his acceptance of such entertainment as the place would afford; and that she was sorry it was not answerable to his quality, and to the respect she bore to the Commonwealth whom He served; but desired he would take it in good part, and told his Excellency he was very <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> to her Court. After she had done, his Excellency spake to her Majesty in <em>French</em>, that there were two of his Sons, and other Gentlemen in his Company, that much desired the <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg> of kissing her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> hand, if she pleased to permit it; which she readily did to those whom His Excellency appointed, which were 18. After that Ceremony passed, the Queen spake to his Excellency in <em>French</em>, desiring him to excuse the ill treatment by the way in his journey, those places far off not being furnished for entertaining such a person as His Excellency was, and so attended. She was likewise sorry that this place would not afford such accommodation as were fit for His Excellency,<pb n="2" />
and <reg orig="wisht">wished</reg> she might have entertained Him at <em>Stockholm</em>, where it would have been better. His Excellency <reg orig="ansuuered">answered</reg>, that He <reg orig="uuas">was</reg> sorry for the occasion of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> remove from that place, and that he had received many <reg orig="favors">favours</reg>, both in his journey, and here by her Command, for which he returned thanks to her Majesty, and would acquaint the Parliament therewith. She then excused her Habit, saying she had been ill, which cause her to put <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> into the <reg orig="dresse">dress</reg> of her Chambers, in which she chose to appear thus <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg>, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to disappoint his Excellency of audience; and that she hoped they should have time and opportunity enough to discourse together. His Excellency then took his leave of her Majesty, who was very civil and courteous to him, and to all his Company.</i></p>

<p>His Excellency was brought back to his Lodging with as much ceremony as He went to Court. The Ryx Marshal and the two Senators supped with his Excellency, it being the custom for such to be at the last meal that Ambassadors are entertained at by the Queen. At supper those Senators told his Excellency it was their manner in this Country for them to begin a Health to the Superiors of the Ambassador, and to himself; but they understanding that it was against his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> principles, either to pledge or begin any health, they did therefore forbear, and not out of any disrespect, either to his spectators or himself.</p>

<p>The next day in the morning being Saturday, his
Excellency<pb n="3" /> sent to visit the Spanish Resident, who had sent twice to him before, and also his Coach to accompany him to Town. In the afternoon he came himself to visit his Excellency, and made many Protestations of his readiness to serve the Commonwealth of England, to whom he knew his Master did bear a great respect.</p>

<p>On Monday the twenty sixth afternoon my Lord had private audience for above two hours, with the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, no person else with them.</p>

<p>On the 29 his Excellency was admitted again to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence, with whom he was alone <reg orig="neer">near</reg> 3 hours together It was his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> wonder, to hear a Lady discourse so of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> affairs, and of the interests of all the States and Princes of Christendom, which such <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> and judgment as she did.</p>

<p>His Excellency hath been visited by both the Spanish and French Agents, and by the Ryx <unclear>Hoffuraster</unclear> of Denmark, by the Ryx Marshal of Sweden, by Court Tole, Monsieur Vanderlain, and Mr. Bond Senators, Court Tort, and Monsieur Banniere. Some of their visits his Excellency hath already required.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Dalkeith</em> Jan. 21.</head>

<p>The 19 instant Col. <em>Daniel</em> Governor of St. <reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg> having intelligence that the enemy were in or about Dunket, sent out 100 Dragoons under the command of Cap. Lieut. <reg orig="Ashly">Ashley</reg> of Col. <reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg> Regiment, who came very <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Town undiscovered, and the Forlorn fell in with two of their scouts, they made some resistance at the <reg orig="Barracado">Barricade</reg>, but our few Dragoons beat them thence, <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> the Town, and <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> 6 or 7 at the entrance: Our Forlorn went in the mean time to the other end of the Town, and pursued them that (upon the <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg>) got away towards the Hills and passages betwixt the Town and Blaire, and there were seven of them <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>; many had the states mark and most of <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> Troopers made Footmen, they brought 50 Horse with them, and 7. prisoners of <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> Regiment, also many <reg orig="Carabins">Carbines</reg>, Cloaks, Boots, and other things belonging to them, and had they<pb n="4" />
not escaped to the woods and crags which are at the very <reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg> end, there had been more in our custody. Athol was there himself, and <em>I</em> believe this will be a great obstruction to his Levies. he had about 100. or 150 Foot with him, most of whom got to the Hills, the Horse pursued them about two miles beyond the Town, a <reg orig="vvounded">wounded</reg> There <reg orig="vvas">was</reg> one of Col. <reg orig="Tvvistletons">Twistleton's</reg> <reg orig="ovvn">own</reg> Troop killed, some of the prisoners confess the Wogan <reg orig="vvas">was</reg> run through the shoulder at Drummond, and lies at Weims. Captain <reg orig="Kilsmores">Kilsmore's</reg> Lieut: and Captain <reg orig="Ker">Kerr</reg> did kill each other, both of them at one instant firing together at 4 yards distance with both their Blunderbusses, and fell both from their Horses <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg>.</p>

<p>Mr. Feake and Mr. Simpson were this day carried prisoners to Windsor Castle.</p>

<p>By Letters from Cap. Mill aboard the Falmouth <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, came as followeth.</p>

<p>The 16 instant the <em>Paul</em> Middleburgh, and we were altogether, the 17 day we having 3 several chases lost each other, and have not met to this day.</p>

<p>The 18 instant I fell foul with 4 Brest men of War, of which Beech was one, with his flag in his main top, which gave chase to 4 small Vessels bound for Rochel from Barstable, laden with Herrings and Coals, with which men of War I did engage some six hours, some 25 Leagues southwest of <em>Scilly</em>, and put them to flight, and saved those small Vessels from their hands.</p>

<p>Yesterday I fell foul of one Smith of Brest, which had with him a Vessel of Plymouth, (One Parret Master) bound for <reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg>, which he had in <reg orig="poslession">possession</reg> four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, which said Vessel I did redeem, and took in him 17 French men belonging to the said Smith, which said Vessel of Plymouth, I have this day sent thither.</p>

<p>Also this day I came up with 9 stout Merchant ships of France, which came from <reg orig="Marsilles">Marseilles</reg>, bound for St. Mallow, but could do no good on them.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, Ian. 31. 1644</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> we hear, that notwithstanding the Amnistia (or general pardon granted to the City, there hath been many of the Citizens, which have suffered some by imprisonment, others in their Estates, and some with their lives; in the <reg orig="meane">mean</reg> time there is but little Trade; although the Plague doth now afflict, and <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the Seas are more free, a <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Trade cannot be expected of any consequence. From Provence we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that the States of that Province assembled at Bagnelle is broke up, having determined to maintain some regiments of foot for the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> service, and some considerable sums of money is by them granted for the <reg orig="paiment">payment</reg> of the <reg orig="Souldierie">Soldiery</reg>. From St Menehould, there is a strong party sent by the Governor towards the Counts of Liege; and the Irish that were here are also sent thither, the same being upon certain information, that the Prince of Conde, and the Duke of <reg orig="Lorrains">Lorrain's</reg> forces, intend to settle themselves there. The Earle of Merib is gone from <reg orig="Cleremont">Clermont</reg> to <reg orig="conferre">confer</reg> with the Prince of Conde, and to know what he is to trust to, seeing that the Spring being near at hand he is fearful of a Siege, being already <reg orig="bestraightned">bestraightened</reg> in some sort, which maketh their Provisions and the Ammunitions somewhat scarce: The Castles of Nienna and Landres being likewise blocked up; which doth hinder much their <reg orig="reliefe">relief</reg> and supplies from their friends, which is within a little distance of Stanay. The third instant, arrived to this City the Duke of Longueville who went the next day to the Court, and very well received of their Majesties. The same day the King and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> went to St Maur, and there took the pleasure of hunting, and being gone to some other places, returned thither the fifth day: The Prince of Condi is not yet come and in regard there hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> so many words spoken about it; therefore we shall say no<pb n="6" /> more at present. There is nothing from Catalonia at present, both parties being gone to Winter-quarters, nothing for matter of action can be expected <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the spring be come.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From several parts</i></head>

<p>From Regensburgh: The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> being earnestly solicited by the Agent for the Elector of Cullen hath thereupon sent an Order to those Princes and State of the Empire that are <reg orig="neare">near</reg> him, that they <reg orig="doe">do</reg> without delay assist him with such Forces, and Ammunition, as they have now on for, for the expulsion of the Lorrain, and other <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> Forces who have of late made great devastations in the <reg orig="Countie">County</reg> of Liege: and those that have not any forces, to assist them with monies. The Swedish <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <reg orig="shewes">shows</reg> great discontent, by reason that contrary to the <reg orig="pretention">pretension</reg> of that Crown, the Town of Bremen hath been received into the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> of the Free <reg orig="Citie">City</reg>, which they pretend to be a great prejudice and detriment to their <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg>. From Worsania; Upon many Letters passed between the King of Poland, the Tartars and Cossacks at last a Treaty hath been agreed upon on both sides appointed to meet at Kannineck, where after many Propositions made on both sides, it is certainly reported, that they are come to an agreement, whereof at present we can not give you any particulars. From <reg orig="Strasburgh">Strasbourg</reg>; The <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg> of Beffort goeth gallantly on, and is thought the besieged will in short time be brought to a surrender. The Elector of Cullen not being satisfied<pb n="7" /> with such <reg orig="faire">fair</reg> promises as are made to his Agents at Ratisbone; doth therefore threaten in case he hath not a speedy <reg orig="reliefe">relief</reg>, to crave the assistance of a <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> Prince, and to that end there hath been some meeting with the French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, who doth not omit to <reg orig="imbrace">embrace</reg> that occasion for the furtherance of that occasion.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith, 26. <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. One troop of Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Dragoons being relieved, are <reg orig="goone">gone</reg> after him in the North; from whom we have not heard since he marched from <em>Aberdeen</em>. The Regiments in Scotland <reg orig="doe">do</reg> well approve of the New Government in England, and the Officers generally send in their Addresses, to be sent to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to that purpose; only some few of Maj. Gen. <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, <reg orig="chiefely">chiefly</reg> of the Welch Troop, the Quartermaster, and some <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are gone off towards England, and the Chaplain to the Regiment. There was a Shallop built up, and <reg orig="foure">four</reg> Guns put into her, to secure Trade in the River Clyde, and prevent the Highlanders falling into Renfrewshire, which they often did before; but there being present no other considerable Vessel to assist, (as we expected) three of four days <!--??-->agone one Lieutenant Col. <em>Harriet</em>, with some Boats from the Loughs in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> the <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg>. A Lieutenant of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg> Regiment, and seven or eight other (most Officers) were lately taken <reg orig="neare">near</reg> Falkirk, by a party, and carried to the Hills. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Humphreys">Humphrey's</reg> Troop is come to Musleborough: We expect the other two Regiments.</p>

<p><em>Newcastle, 28 <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. The Wetwang, and the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> have each of them brought in hither a prize, 2 Dutch Capers of 6 Guns a piece, and 100 prisoners, 50 in each. We are here full of Dutch prisoners.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 30 <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg></em>. This morning news is come from Dartmouth, that a great <reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg> is put on shore, having on board her <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one dead man, being killed by a shot, the rest of the Company forsaking her. Some Canary ships arrived at Falmouth, and 4 ships from Mallago at this Port.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday February 1.</i></head> 

<p>The Lord Protector and his Council have passed an Ordinance, appointing a Committee for the Army, and Treasurers at War, with full power and authority in full and ample manner, to all intents and purposes, as the former Committee had. The Names of the Committee are these following, <em>viz. John <reg orig="Clerck">Clark</reg>, Edward Cludd, Richard Lucy, Rich: Horseman, James <reg orig="Philips">Phillips</reg>, Edward Gill, John Hildesley, Jervas <reg orig="Bennet">Bennett</reg></em>, Esquires; Captain <em>Adam Baines</em>, or any three more of them; And <em>John Blackwell</em> the younger, and <em>Richard Dean</em>, Esqs; to be Treasurers at War.</p>

<p>Ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and the Council, That <em>Tho: Rand, William Palmer, Robert Yarborrow, Nehemiah Rawson, William Harvey, William Welby</em>, Esquires, and the Mayor of Lincoln for the time being, be added to the Commissioners for the <reg orig="Monethly">Monthly</reg> Assessment within the County of Lincoln.</p>

<p><em>Philip Stansby</em> for the County of <em>Dorset</em>. The Mayor of <em>Banbury</em> for the time being, for the County of <em>Oxon</em>; And <em>Christopher Peircebay</em>, Esquire, and Sir <em>Robert Berwick</em>, Knight, for the County of <em>York</em>.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <em>London</em> having invited his Highness the Lord Protector to Dinner, on such a day as his Highness would please to appoint, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath nominated Wednesday next to be the day for that purpose, and great Preparations are now already making for that Feast.</p>

<p>We have had nothing from <em>Holland</em> since Monsieur <em>Bevering</em> came the last Week, and Reports the consent of the Province of <em>Holland</em> to the terms agreed on, He is very confident the other Provinces will likewise accord, and send their Deputies to that purpose hither speedily. In the mean time our Fleet are putting out to Sea, and there are already gone out from <em>Portsmouth</em> above 50 stout men of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> with General <em>Penne</em>, and General <em>Blake</em> is gone out with about 20 more to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with them, and more are sitting apace daily.</p><pb n="9" />

<p>A Declaration to his Highness the Lord Protector, from the Generals at Sea, and Commander of the Fleet, as followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>For his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The Declaration, with the humble <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> of the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the Fleet, by them severally subscribed.</i></head>

<p>That these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, having been for some years like the Bush which burned, but is not consumed: And though the Nations round about us stand gazing on to see us made a desolation, as well as a hissing unto them; yet we are hitherto by the mighty power of the Lord, and his wonderful outgoings amongst us, made rather and astonishment in our preservation, than a reproach, by our <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and devastation.</p>

<p>In which great work of the Lord, we acknowledge with <reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> Your Highness hath been a glorious Instrument; and hath undergone many hardships, and <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of all that was near and dear unto you, even to life <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, and understanding by Providence Your Highness is <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with, and hath accepted of the protection of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in the Government thereof.</p>

<p>We hope that the Lord intends a settlement of Peace to these poor distracted Nations; and that <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with all the People of the Lord shall enjoy and partake<pb n="10" /> of the same under Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> protection, according to the Rule of the Lord Jesus. And therefore we have thought it necessary as a duty incumbent on us to declare, that we shall willingly be obedient, and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to your Highness, in performance of Your great Trust, and also in the utmost hazard of our Lives, (with what else is near and dear unto us) be serviceable unto You, in the station the Lord hath placed You, against Yours, and the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Enemies in our <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places, and capacities, during our employments.</p>

<p>And having good testimony of Your great Affection, and earning Bowels after the <reg orig="weale">weal</reg> of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> People, we are <reg orig="imboldened">emboldened</reg> and encouraged in all humility to make this following <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg>.</p>

<p>That Your Highness will be pleased to have a more special eye of favour unto them above all others, in regard they are near and dear unto him, who is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, even our Lord Jesus. For which cause he is not ashamed to call them Brethren; And do humbly apprehend that their Privileges will be Your Privilege. And to count of them as of your greatest Jewels, which will <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> turn to your great advantage.</p>

<p>And hereby you will for time to come not only engage their hearts unto You, who in times past have not stood at a distance from You, But Your Highness<pb n="11" /> will also engage the great Jehovah, Your and their Father to be a refuge, shield and defence unto You as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as an everlasting rest for You, when all the storms of this Commonwealth shall cease, which is, and shall be the unfeigned prayers of,</p> 

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> most humble and faithful Servants,</i></p>

<p>Signed by the Generals and the several Commanders present in the Fleet.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday February 2.</i></head>

<p>Paris 7th of February 1654. <em>stilo novo</em>. There is a great alteration now made in the perception of the Taxes and Imposts, there being new Offices made, and new Officers created, where old ones are put out of service: And among many remarkable things, it is to be <reg orig="wondred">wondered</reg>, that many Protestants are admitted to places of some honour, and more profit. There is now at present in this City the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> his <reg orig="Secretarie">Secretary</reg>, and one from the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>Seneterre</em>; therefore now a Treaty is in hand concerning the Agreement between the Court and the said Earl touching <em>Alsatia</em>, there hath been some <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> made in it, but nothing agreed upon. During this Treaty the siege of <em>Beffort</em> goeth on with as much gallantry as may be expected, considering the season, and the great opposition of the Besieged, who neither spare valour or labour in the defence of that place. The Marshal <em>la Ferte</em> is daily seen in the Trenches, thereby to animate the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>; so that it is expected in a short time you will hear of the surrender of that place. The great preparations made at <em>Toulon</em> goeth on, and it is variously reported to what intent it is; for some will have it for to get the mastery of the Seas in the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>; others will have it only in part that way; and the other part to be sent to the aid of the Venetian State; but some who do think themselves wisest, believe that it doth <reg orig="runne">run</reg> upon the old design for <em>Naples</em>; and for a confirmation of the same, it is observed that the Duke of <em>Guise</em> doth make money at all hands, having sold and pawned such things whereby to raise a very considerable <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of<pb n="12" /> moneys, and we do hear that he is to go from hence within this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> <unclear>as out</unclear> of this more by the next. The Pope seemeth to be very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the making a general peace between us and Spain, and the other Allies, and to that end we are told of an extraordinary <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg> that is now on his journey hither; another being also sent into <em>Spain</em>: Our <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from <em>Rome</em> is to be here the next week, and now all things are ready for the dancing of the great Ballet, which will be between this and Shrove Tuesday and for the consecrating of the young King it will not be so soon as was expected.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. From <em>Rome</em>, The <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg> which is to go for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> hath been consecrated <reg orig="Patriarke">Patriarch</reg> of <em>Jerusalem</em>, and is commanded to make himself ready to depart from thence to <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>. He is to make overtures of Peace between the two <reg orig="Crownes">Crowns</reg>, that so there may be a general peace in <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>, and that in case he findeth any inclination in those two Princes, that then he will further it to the uttermost, and speedily sent two <reg orig="Legats">Legates</reg>, the one in <em>France</em>, the other in <em>Spain</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em>, There are very great preparations making for the <reg orig="Cavalcate">Cavalcade</reg> of our new <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg>; and the Nobility and Gentry make vast <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg>, that they may be seen in a gallant Equipage on that day, which is therefore put off to a longer time; that so those that are to be there, may not pretend to have too little time. Upon the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> complaints made by the Citizens, of some wicked persons, who daily committed many areas great <reg orig="Insolencies">Insolences</reg>, and after that take Sanctuary in the Churches and Convents; therefore the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> hath sent to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Trivultio</em> (who doth now in the vacancy of <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> act for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>) that he may complain of it to the Pope, who thereupon hath sent Letters to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Filomarini</em>, That he may no longer protect such Rogues, but that he may suffer them to be delivered into the hands of Justice, there to answer for those <reg orig="hainous">heinous</reg> crimes whereof they stand charge.</p>

<p>From <em>Venice</em> thus, We have received Letters from <em>Constantinople</em><pb n="13" /> by way of <em>Ragusa</em>, which advise us, That the Great Bashaw being returned there with 30 Galleys, was at first well received by the Great Turk, and his <reg orig="Counsell">Council</reg>, but <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to give an account of his Summers Expedition, he was found guilty in many respects, for not having discharged that Trust reposed in him; and thereupon was condemned to die, which was executed accordingly. They <reg orig="doe">do</reg> prepare great Forces to be landed in <em>Candia</em>, to try if they shall after many <reg orig="years">year's</reg> wars become Masters of that fair Island: We are likewise making very great preparations both by Sea and Land, and to that end, no cost is spared to make it ready with all speed possible.</p>

<p><em>Rotterdam</em> the first of <em>February</em>. Our Country here is full of joy for the peace we conceive will now be certainly concluded with your <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, since we hear that the Lord <em>Beverning</em> is sent into <em>England</em> with the ratification of the Province of <em>Holland</em>, in the mean time that the rest of the Provinces are to meet to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same likewise, which will be <em>March</em> first as our Occurrences tells us before they can all get together. We are no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> overjoyed to hear that the Treaty is so <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> decided as they say it is, to the great honour of our Provinces, and the reputation of our Commissioners, and to the good liking and content of the States General, who are met at the <em>Hague</em> about it, to come to a final conclusion. But yet there are many honest and faithful Patrons amongst us, that are of the opinion it were <reg orig="bet ter">better</reg> to prosecute the War with vigour against <em>England</em> and that the labour and the <reg orig="successe">success</reg> we should have had would in the end have been more honourable and profitable, than what we can expect from this Treaty of Peace.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday Feb. 3, 4.</i></head>

<p>All Adventurers for Lands in <em>Ireland</em> are desired to take notice, that the day for drawing of Lots for Baronies (being formerly appointed to be on Thursday the 9th of this instant <em>February</em> 1653.) is now by the Committee for Claims for Lands in <em>Ireland</em> (in regard of some special occasions <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters with "ning" on the end --></unclear>)<pb n="14" /> ordered and appointed to be at Grocers hall London, on <em>Thursday</em> the 23 instant <em>Feb</em>. and to begin at 8 of the clock in the forenoon of the same day.</p>

<p><i>Will. Tibbs, Clerk</i></p>

<p>Newcastle Feb. 1. For news we have very little, only that which we suppose you have heard of, The intercepting a great many Letters that came from the <reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg> <reg orig="Cavaleers">Cavaliers</reg>, to the Malignant party here, but they were by a person of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> sent up to his Highness. The truth is, there is such continual meetings of the <reg orig="Cavaleers">Cavaliers</reg>, that any may judge without the intercepting Letters, they have great <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> in hand; Here is much doings about the Quakers; they were at a place called <em>Hasington</em> Sabbath day, and as they were speaking to the Minister, the Country people fell upon them, and abused them very much, almost killed one or two; but going out falling upon their knees, seeking to God to forgive them, saying, they knew not what they did, and afterward speaking to them, many of the people were so convinced of the Evil they had done in beating of them, that returning back to the residue of the people that was on the Green in the Town, begging to accuse one another, as the occasion of beating those Men who had done them no hurt, nor opposed the Minister till he had done, and the Minister being earnestly pressed to go and discourse with them, and he refusing, this discourse went so high, that the Townsmen generally went to go by the Ears, and did so exceedingly beat one another, that such a fight hath not been seen. There was very few that went home without their faces or head broken.</p>

<p>From the Isle of <em>Wight February</em> 3. Our Fleet hath now set sail, and put to Sea from St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point</em>, they are divided in three Squadrons, but are not at so great distance but that upon any occasion they can soon <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> into one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> body, there being Scouts appointed, who are to give notice upon any appearance of the Enemy.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal, February</em> 2. Here are little news at present; a good number of Ships bound to the Southward, as also for several Ports of <em>France</em>, are gone from hence and from <em>Dover</em>. The French <reg orig="Pikeroons">Picaroons</reg> do still haunt about these parts,<pb n="15" /> and are often seen, and as soon as any of our ships set sail to give them <reg orig="chace">chase</reg>, they get their own Coast before he can come up to them, there being two at present who are riding in <em>Calice</em> Road,</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Feb. 1.</em> Col. <em>Morgan</em> marching from <em>Aberdeen</em> with 14 Companies of Foot, and 8 Troops of Horse and <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg> towards the Enemy, <em>Glencairn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> the same day went out of <em><reg orig="Murryland">Murrayland</reg></em> towards the Hills, they burnt all the Lord <em><reg orig="Lothans">Lothan's</reg></em> land (the Lord <reg orig="Brodies">Brodie's</reg> uncle) because he kept his house out against them in the late infall into the Earl of <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> quarters at <em>Dunkel</em>: There was <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> one Capt. <em>Robertson</em>, one Capt. <em>Hunter</em>, (a young Laird) who attended <em>Athol</em>) the Laird of <em>Baillachan</em>, Maj. <em>Mercer</em> run into the Body with a Tuck, and through the Arm; <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed he will not live; there were about 20 more slain and <reg orig="deperatly">desperately</reg> wounded. The 23 instant <em>Athol</em> had a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of the Country at a place <reg orig="call'd">called</reg> <em>Catrane</em> 2 or 3 miles Northeast from <em>Dunkel</em> but had very slender appearance. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> and <em>Wogan</em> lie ill of their wounds at <em>Weems</em>, <em>Wogan</em> is not likely to recover. Col. <em>Hume</em> with about 16 more out of the <em>Merch</em> or <em>Berwickshire</em> are this week gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those in the Hills.</p>

<hr />

<p>PANTHEOLOGIA, or the <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> of practical Divinity <reg orig="practiz'd">practised</reg> in the Wilderness, and delivered by our Saviour in his Sermon on the Mount, being observed on the 4, 5, 6, 7. Chapters of St. Matthew. By Tho. White Minister of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> word at Anne Aldersgate, London. Printed for Joseph Cranford at the sign of the Ph&oelig;nix in St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p>The Holy Order, or Fraternity of Mourners in Sion, whereunto is added songs in the Night, or <reg orig="Chearfulness">Cheerfulness</reg> under Affliction, By J. H. B. N. Printed for Nath. Brooks at the Angel in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg>.</p>

<p>The false <reg orig="Iew">Jew</reg>; being a true Relation of one Thomas Ramsey, who came from Rome, and was baptized at London, and afterwards baptized at Hexham by Mr. Tillam, but found at Newcastle to be a <unclear>Cheat</unclear>: sold by R. Tomlins at the Sun in <reg orig="Py">Pie</reg>-corner: Also an Answer to the false <reg orig="Iew">Jew</reg>, intituled Banners of Love; Written by Tho. Tilham, newly published, and sold at the sign of Sir <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Oldcastle in <reg orig="Py">Pie</reg> -corner.</p>

<p>One bay Nag, with a little star in the forehead, about fourteen handful high, which goeth wide behind, hath all his paces, about eight year old. And one <unclear>sorrel mare</unclear> with a <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> in the forehead, about fourteen handful high also, which trotteth, and five years old, both <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> (on Monday night <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 30 last) from Mr Radbrook Minister of Solihull in Warwickshire, who so shall bring news of them or either of them to John Saywell <unclear>Stationer</unclear> at the <reg orig="Grey-hound">Greyhound</reg> in little <unclear>Brixton</unclear> without Aldersgate, London, or the party from whom they were <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg>, shall have good satisfaction.</p>

<p>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order</p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>