<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn229">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 229</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg> </head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, April. 24. to <em>Monday</em>, May. 1. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, at the <reg orig="Faulcon">Falcon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe-lane">Shoe Lane</reg> </head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> April. 24.</head>

<p>This day was published the Ordinance (formerly mentioned) for uniting <em>Scotland</em> into one Commonwealth, and under one Government with <em>England</em>, and runs thus, That in every Parliament to be held successively for the said Commonwealth, thirty persons shall be called from, and serve for <em>Scotland</em>. And for the more effectual preservation of this union, and the freedom and safety of this Commonwealth so united, it is ordained that the people of <em>Scotland</em> and <em><reg orig="Sethland">Shetland</reg></em>, and of all the dominions and territories thereto belonging to be discharged of all fealty, homage, service and allegiance, pretended to be due unto any of the family of the <em>Stuarts</em><pb n="1" />, who are by this Ordinance disabled to hold or <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> the Crown of <em>Scotland</em>, or to have the name, <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, title, or dignity of King, or Queen of <em>Scotland</em>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Ordained also, that the said office, <reg orig="stile">style</reg>, dignity, power and authority of King of <em>Scotland</em>, and all right of the three Estates of Scotland, to assemble in any general Convocation or Parliament, and all Conventional and Parliamentary authority in <em>Scotland</em>, as formerly established, be abolished, made null and void. And that the arms of <em>Scotland</em>, <em>viz.</em> St. <em><reg orig="Andrews">Andrew's</reg></em> Cross, be received into, &amp; born henceforth in the arms of this Commonwealth, as a badge of this Union, and that all the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> seals, seals of office, and seals of bodies civil or corporate, in <em>Scotland</em>, which heretofore carried the arms of the Kings of <em>Scotland</em>, shall henceforth, instead thereof, carry the Arms of this Commonwealth.</p>

<p>No greater rate for Excise and Custom are to be imposed upon any goods transported between <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, but they are to pass with the same privileges, as goods passing from port to port, or place to place in <em>England</em>, Also all goods which by any law are prohibited to be transported out of <em>England</em>, are by the same law prohibited to be transported out of <em>Scotland</em> to any <reg orig="foraign">foreign</reg> parts. The like rule also for importation, and upon the same penalties.</p>

<p>Ordained likewise, that all Cesses, <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Impositions, and Taxations whatsoever, be <reg orig="levyed">levied</reg> henceforth <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> from the whole people of this Commonwealth so united.</p>

<p>All dominion of Tenures and Superiorities importing servitude and Vassalage, are also abolished in <em>Scotland</em>. Concerning which more at large, and the other particulars before abbreviated, you are referred to the printed Ordinances themselves.</p>

<p>A second Ordinance, intituled <i>An Ordinance of Pardon and Grace to the people of <em>Scotland</em>,</i> the sum whereof is to this effect, That from and after the first day of <em>May</em> 1654. all persons shall be acquitted, for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> done by Sea or Land, in relation to the late war, or any <reg orig="preceeding">preceding</reg> wars between the two Nations, but the same shall be put in perpetual oblivion, and their estates be discharged from sequestration. From the benefit of this Ordinance these following persons are Excepted, <em>viz.</em> <em>Henrieta Maria</em><pb n="2" /> late Queen with her two Sons <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> and <em>James Stuart</em>, <em>James</em> and <em>William</em> late Dukes of <em>Hamilton</em> deceased, <em>John</em> Earl of <em>Crawford Lindsey, James </em>E. of <em>Calender</em>, E. <em>Marshal</em>, E. of <em>Kelly</em>, <em>John</em> E. of <em>Lawderdail</em>, <em>John </em>E. of <em>Lowdoun</em>, E. of <em>Seaforth</em>, E. of <em>Athol</em>, Visc. of <em>Kenmore</em>, L. <em>Lorne</em>, eldest Son of the Marq. Of <em>Argile</em>, L. <em>Macklin</em>, eldest Son of the E. of <em>Lowdpun</em>, L. <em>Montgomery</em> eldest Son of the E. <em>Eglingroun</em>, <em>George</em> L. <em>Spynie</em>, L. <em>Cramston</em>, L. <em>Sinclecre</em>, Thomas <em>Daliel</em> late Major Gen. of the Foot in the <reg orig="Scotish">Scottish</reg>, John Middletoune late Lieut. Gen. of the Army, <em>James</em> Viscount <em>Newburgh</em>, L. <em>Bargany</em>, Sir. <em>Tho. Thomson</em>, <em>James <unclear>Edmerton</unclear></em> Laird of <em><unclear>Womar</unclear></em>, L. <em>Napier</em>, <em>William</em>, E. of <em>Glencairn</em>. These persons are excepted, and estates confiscated wholly; save that some part is <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon the wives and children of some of them, out of their respective estates.</p>

<p>A third Ordnance, for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Estates of the several Excepted persons in <em>Scotland</em>, in the real and actual possession and <reg orig="seizin">seizing</reg> of Sir <em>John Hope</em> of Graighall, <em>William Lockard</em> the younger, Esq; <em>Rich: Sabonstal</em> and <em>Edw: Siler</em> Commissioners at Leith, Lieu. Col. <em>Wilks</em>, deputy governor of <em>Leith</em>, <em>David Barkley</em> Esq; <em>Jo: Harpar</em> Advocate, and the survivors and survivor of them, their heirs and assigns, for certain uses and purposes in the said Ordinance expressed, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the sale, disposition and conveyance thereof, or of such part thereof as shall be requisite for the purposes aforesaid, as is therein directed, and the remainder to he use of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his successors, for the benefit of the Commonwealth.</p>

<p>Also an Ordinance for erecting Court Barons in <em>Scotland</em>, but of these further by the Ordinances themselves printed at large.</p>

<p>Also there is published an Order concerning the peace with <em>Holland</em>, as followeth.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Wheras">Whereas</reg> a Peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the States General of the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces of the Low Countries. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof shall be made on both parts on Wednesday next, being the 26. day of this instant <em>April</em>; From which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after twelve <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, within these Seas; and in all other places on this side the Cape of <em>St. Vincent</em>, after 6<pb n="3" /> weeks; and from thence, within the <em>Mediterranean</em> sea, and to the &AElig;quinoctial line, after 10 weeks; and beyond the &AElig;quinoctial, after the space of 8 months: Which several spaces were so limited, to the intent convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this Commonwealth, and to all others, whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof; To the end, they may have Warning to provide for their own safety, and not expose their ships to danger, within the several and respective times aforesaid.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 25.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dalkeith</em> April 20 thus. Col <em>Morgan</em> is marched from <em>Dingwel</em> towards <em>Tain</em> with all his Brigade: On Thursday last there marched one thousand Foot over the hills above <em>Braban</em> towards <em>Sutherland</em>, which <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed are the <em>Loughaber</em> men which will add to the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> strength, which was before 4000 Horse and Foot. There was a quarrel between Sir <em>George <reg orig="Monro">Monroe</reg></em>, and the Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>, for plundering of and abusing the Laird of <em>Fowlis</em> (<em><reg orig="Monroes">Monroe's</reg></em> Brother) who was extremely abused by them, which rise so high, that they appointed to fight a combat, and accordingly on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day was eight days, in the morning they mounted and rid to the place appointed, and because <em>Monroe</em> would fight on Horseback, he took his Pistols with him, But <em>Glenclairn</em> bid him put away his Pistols, and they would fight only on Horseback with their swords. In which combat <em>Monroe</em> had his right hand almost cut off, and a cut in the Forehead, <em>Glencairn</em> was likewise cut in the head. There was also a quarrel between <em>Athol</em> and <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> about <reg orig="precedency">presidency</reg> of place, and a field appointed, but the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was taken up by the Commanders.</p>

<p>Our small Garrisons near <em><reg orig="Sterlin">Stirling</reg></em> have this week fallen with <reg orig="successe">success</reg> into the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> quarters, and brought away prisoners, and amongst the rest a party from <em>Bubannon</em> marched into the Parish of <em>Strablain</em>, where Capt. <em>Cunningham</em>, and Capt. <em>Edmiston</em> were levying of horse and foot, took Capt. <em>Cunningham</em>, and narrowly <reg orig="mist">missed</reg> Capt. <em>Edmiston</em>. General <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> intended to be at <em>Berwick</em> this night, and is expected here on Saturday.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation by the Commander in chief of all the forces in <em>Scotland</em></i></head> 

<p>Whereas (amongst other things) by Proclamation of the 27 <em>Sept</em>. 1653. All Magistrates and Officers of Burghs and Parishes, and all other persons whatsoever, are required to secure, or give intelligence of all suspected persons, travelling through or abiding within their bounds or jurisdictions, as in and by the said Proclamation more particularly is expressed: Notwithstanding nothing to this time hath been effectually done, but on the contrary, divers Rebels, as well considerable numbers as Spies, have been, and still are frequently <reg orig="permited">permitted</reg>, &amp; <reg orig="suffer'd">suffered</reg> to march through, &amp; abide in any Burgh or Parish within the quarters of our Army unquestioned, as if no rebellion were, who thereby take opportunity not only to get intelligence, but also to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> many loose persons to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in rebellion, and commit frequent robberies and barbarous <reg orig="murthers">murders</reg>, and other outrages upon the persons, goods, and <reg orig="geer">gear</reg>, as well of Scots as English. These are therefore strictly to charge and command, that no person or persons, of what degree or quality soever (not being a member of the English Army) do presume after publication hereof, to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> above five miles from his and their respective abodes and habitations, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> he or they have first obtained a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> from <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, or the Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em> for the time being, or from the next chief Officer of the English Army, or the Judge Advocate of the Army (of whose circumspection and care in parting with the said passes to persons well affected, or upon good caution, I nothing doubt) which said <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> is to be signed and sealed with my hand and seal, conform to the hand and seal hereunto subscribed and affixed, or the hand and seal of the Commander in chief for the time being, and subscribed by the said Officer from whom it shall be obtained, with his name, together with the time and place of his subscription (except he or they make it appear he or they are upon their ready way to the next chief Officer for obtaining the said <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>) under the pain of being adjudged, deemed, and taken as Enemies in Rebellion against the peace of the Commonwealth, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly. And all Magistrates and Officers, and all other persons whatsoever within Burghs or Parishes, are hereby<pb n="5" /> strictly required, that if any person or persons (except as before is excepted) and not being Members of the English Army, shall contrary hereunto presume to march, travel, <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through, or abide in any Burgh or Parish without a Pass as aforesaid, the said Magistrates, Officers and parishioners of such Burgh and Parish are hereby required to secure them, if they shall be of strength sufficient, and them safely keep, until notice be given to <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, the Commander in chief for the time being, or the next adjacent Officer in chief of the English Forces (any of whose Orders theranent is duly to be observed) under the penalty of 20 pounds sterling, &amp; such further punishment, according to the quality of the offence, as to a Court Marshal to be held for the <reg orig="head-quarters">headquarters</reg>, or any other inferior Court Marshal, before whom the matter shall be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be thought just; And whensoever any party of the Rebels which now are, or hereafter shall break forth into Rebellion, or any other person not having a pass, as aforesaid, shall march or travel, into or through any Burgh or Parish; and if the Burgh, Parish and Inhabitants of the said Burgh, and parishioners of the said parish, and every individual person thereof, are hereby strictly charged and required, to take care that such expedient be found out amongst themselves, that upon the first entrance of such Rebels, or persons not having a pass, as aforesaid, whether they make stay or not, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> to take care that with all possible speed, one or more persons, mounted on as good a horse as at present may be had, or otherwise a nimble Footman, to post away with all possible speed to the next and <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> forces of the English Army, wheresoever they shall happen to be, and give true Intelligence to the Officer or Officers thereof, of their number, and who commands them, so near as may be, under the like penalty of twenty pounds sterling, and such farther punishment, according to the quality of the Offence, as to a Court Marshal, to be held for the <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg>, or any other inferior Court Marshal of the Army, before whom the matter shall be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, shall be in like manner thought just.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and seal at <em>Dalkieth</em>, the 7 if April, 1654.</i></p>

<p>R. LILBURNE.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>From <em><reg orig="Roterdam">Rotterdam</reg></em>, April 24 <em>stilo novo</em>. On the 14 of this Month arrived an Express at the Hague, with Letters from our <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors in England to the States General, wherein they advise that the Peace was wholly finished and concluded, That the business of <em>Denmark</em> was determined, and the States General to be responsible for One hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling, That the ships detained in the Sound, should be restored within Fourteen <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after that those should arrive there who were to receive them, and that the Damages shall be appraised by the first of May, by four Persons. Upon this good News the States of Holland adjourned yesterday; leaving their Order and consent with the States General to sign the Ratification. A few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Articles of the Treaty of Peace were signed on both sides, being sent over two several <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, by two of the Gentlemen of the Lords Ambassadors, who <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> at the Hague to the great contentment and joy of all the honest men in these parts, which were no sooner read, but presently Ratified by the States General, and the Ratification sent away for England immediately. So that now we no longer doubt of this blessed Peace, which hath kept us in <reg orig="suspence">suspense</reg> thus long together; however our <reg orig="Criticks">Critics</reg> will not pardon the remissness of our Governors, for making such slow preparations, when their <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> arm so vigorously.</p>

<p>The Lord Lieut. Admiral <em>Opdam</em> is at present at the Hague, with the <reg orig="Vice-admiral">Vice Admiral</reg> <em>Witte Wittesen, Ruyter</em>, and <em>John Evertson</em>, with several other <reg orig="Sea-Captains">Sea Captains</reg>, who have received order from the States General to furnish their ships with all things necessary with all speed. The <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> for the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships to be at <em>Goree</em>, and no ship is to be suffered to go to Sea, <reg orig="til">till</reg> the peace be published: and much variety of Opinions here passeth upon the great Preparations of the English, and the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> they have in hand with their great Fleet.</p>

<p><em>Paris April 29, stilo novo</em>. The last letters from <em>Perpignan</em> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, That the Earl of <em>Merinville</em> Commander in chief of the French forces in the County of <em>Roussillon</em> hath of late relieved <em>Rosa</em>, by the way of <em>Lampourdan</em>, which hath somewhat amazed the Spaniards, who did not expect any such thing, and thereupon<pb n="7" /> are drawn back into <em>Catalonia</em>, which doth so much incense the <em>Catalans</em>, and chiefly along the coast near <em>Blanes</em>, and <em>Palamos</em>, who are daily at odds with the Spanish soldiers, and often from words they fall to blows, many being slain on both sides in those quarrels. From <em>Aras</em> we hear, that the <em>Lorrain</em> forces are quartered in the villages along the River <em>Deulle</em> between the rivers of <em>Lis</em> and <em>Lile</em>, yet this doth in no wise <reg orig="afright">affright</reg> the Earl of <em>Broglio</em>, <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Bassee</em>, who finding himself in a good condition, hath therefore sent back the Regiment which had been sent to reinforce his Garrison.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> with those forces under this command, having passed the <em>Mawse</em> the 20 instant upon the bridge of <em>Mouzon</em>, and so are gone to quarter in <em>Champagne</em>, where they were before to march. The 24 instant the King, with his Brother, and many other Lords saw the Regiment of guards drawn out in the field, where they were trained in the Plain near the Wood called the Wood of <em>Bollen</em>. The same day the <reg orig="Counsellour">Counsellor</reg> <em>Bouchet</em> one of our Parliament being dead in this City, was buried in the <reg orig="Abby">Abbey</reg> of St. <em>Victor</em>, to whom he hath bequeathed his library which doth consist of above 7 thousand Volumes, upon this condition, That they shall suffer thrice in the week all persons to come and have the use of those books. The Court is still <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in the acting of their Comedies, and other like play games, the new <em>Italian</em> <reg orig="Comedie">Comedy</reg> being played some 5, or 6 times over. The Commissioners for the protestant Churches are very importunate with the Cardinal to get an answer unto their demands, but as yet no real satisfaction. Marshal <em>Turenne</em> is not yet gone, moneys being short doth put back all Martial affairs. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> is still a close Prisoner in the Castle of <em>Nantes</em>. From <em>Brussels</em> we have, that the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> hath received special orders from <em>Madrid</em> to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> on <reg orig="spedily">speedily</reg> in the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of the Earl of <em>Bassigni</em> and the Baron <em>Mercy</em>: And we hear from <em>Dunkirk</em> that <em>Mortagh O' Brian</em> with some Irish was arrived there, according to the agreement made with the English in <em>Ireland</em>, and are marched up towards the <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg>, that so they may serve in this field expedition.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday April 26.</i></head>

<p>This day the Peace between <em>England</em> and the united Provinces, was by sound of Trumpet solemnly proclaimed; first, in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> Court, in presence of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Council, Afterwards the <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at Arms, Heralds, and other Officers appointed, were received at <em>Temple Barr</em> by the Lord Mayor, and there proclaimed from thence to the <em>Old Exchange</em>, where it was proclaimed in these words following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation of the Peace made between this Commonwealth, and that of the united Provinces of the Netherlands.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, considering how necessary it is, not only to preserve Peace and quiet at home, but as far as in him lies, to live in amity and Friendship with his Neighbours; Hath by the blessing of God, with the advice of his Council, made and concluded a Peace, Union, and confederation to continue <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>, between this Commonwealth of the one part, and that of the United Provinces of the Low Countries, of the other part, their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories, Places, and People by Sea, Land, Fresh waters, or elsewhere, by which the peace is agreed, That all Enmity, Hostility, Discord and War between the said <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their People, and Subjects, shall cease, and all injuries and wrongs, whatsoever done since the 18 and 28 of <em>May</em> 1652, shall cease and be forgotten, except such <reg orig="Depradations">Depredations</reg> as shall be committed on either side, in these Seas, after twelve days, from the date of these presents; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks; and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> Sea, and to the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line, after ten weeks; and beyond the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line, after the space of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, or <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places, and that the People and inhabitants of each party respectively, of what condition or quality soever they be, shall treat each other with love and friendship, and may freely and securely come into, and<pb n="9" /> <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through each others Countries, Towns, Villages, and Precincts, and there stay and abide, and from thence depart again at their pleasure, without any <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> or molestation, and likewise trade and have commerce, and generally do use and exercise all other things (observing the Laws and Customs of each place respectively) as freely, fully, and securely, as they might have done in time of Peace. Whereof all Persons whatsoever, in these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, are to take notice, and conform themselves accordingly.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 26 of April, 1654.</i></p>

<p>O. P.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em> the 24 of March, 1653. On Tuesday last my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> and Count <em>Erick</em> had a meeting, to the debate of the Articles of <reg orig="Vnion">Union</reg>: at which time Count Erick did <reg orig="exhibite">exhibit</reg> several Articles on the behalf of Sweden, some whereof were such, that his Lordship can by no means consent unto. Yesterday, his Excellency went unto the Queen to deliver his exceptions, and the reasons why he cannot admit of some of these Articles proposed to him, and the Queen seemed to be satisfied therein. But this day Count <em>Erick</em> came again unto my Lord, and was very earnest that those might be admitted, but his Lordship is as earnest to exclude them. Yet I have <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg>, that the Queen will find some expedient to reconcile all, and will <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> up things into a harmony and agreement. The great talks here are made of the Coronation of the new King; and preparations are made thereunto; so resolved is the Queen to <reg orig="resigne">resign</reg> up the Government. <em>Piemontelli</em> the Spanish Resident suddenly takes his leave to return home. Count <em>Monte Cuculli</em> went away last week.</p>

<p><i>The ancient proceeding in the Law vindicated to be just, before abuses and corruptions crept in, And the removal of the Abuses, &amp;c. Proposed, and intended Weekly, or more often, to be published in several parts.</i></p>

<p>Whereas divers troublesome persons, being Rectors or Incumbents of some Rectories or Vicarages, have of late<pb n="10" /> years brought divers things in one Libel in the Court Christian, and have there complained of divers things of several natures, some proper for such Courts to hear and determine, and some not; whereby such persons have greatly vexed their Neighbours, and put them to great charges in suing for prohibitions, and yet no cost by Law can be given, either for the Plaintiff or Defendant in such prohibition, for whomsoever any Verdict passeth in the same, or if any be non-suit in the same.</p>

<p><i>For Remedy whereof, it is desired that it may be Enacted,</i></p>

<p>That if either party, Plaintiff or Defendant, in prohibition shall be either non-suited, or have a Verdict given against him in the same, that then costs shall be given against him for the other party, Plaintiff or Defendant therein, in like manner as costs use to be given in actions of debt, trespass, and upon the case, and other actions.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday April 27.</i></head>

<p><em>Paris</em> May 2. 1654. <em>stilo novo</em>. The 25 instant two <reg orig="Counsellors">Councillors</reg> of the Parliament went from hence to <em>Chantilli</em>, and <em>Montmorencie</em>, two places formerly belonging to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and according to the Sentence lately given against him, did there declare those Houses and Castles to be reunited to the Crown, and <reg orig="accordngly">accordingly</reg> did take possession of them. The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> was no sooner come to the Castle of <em>Nantes</em>, but that within two days after, and for several <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> following he was complimented, by the Dean and Chapter, and by all the Courts of Judicature in that City, he was also visited by the D. of <em>Brissac</em>, and others of the Nobility &amp; Gentry of the Province; nevertheless the Marshal <em>de la Mesteray</em> doth narrowly look over all his actions, and of those that visit him. There are great complaints made against the Parliament at <em>Rennes</em> by most of the Gentry of that Province; this being occasioned by one <em>Marbeuf</em>, who sitting there upon the reversion of a <reg orig="Presidents">President's</reg> place, hath lately offered some great abuses to a Gentleman of quality, who was <reg orig="solliciting">soliciting</reg> a <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> in that Court for some Pupils, whereof he is the guardian.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> of <em>Jametz</em> and <em>Mouzon</em> having a design to<pb n="11" /> rifle the small Town of <em>Verron</em>, came thither in the night, and having plundered it, carried away the chief men prisoners to make them pay a ransom. The Chancellor hath this week sent for the Parson of St. <em>Paul</em>, to declare unto him some Order from the Court about a <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> which had lately happened in his Church: The Parson answering he could not obey it, an Officer was sent to him with an Order from the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> whereby he is <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> to depart the City within 24 hours, which he did accordingly.</p>

<p>There hath been of late great troubles in this City among the people, by reason <reg orig="off">of</reg> the great imposts laid upon them, and although that imposts upon all <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg> which was so much <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> against be taken of; yet there are many other new ones which are little better, some fortifications are to be made at the Castle of <em>Vicennes</em>, and the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Guards have received order to be in a <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> for a march about the 10th. of this instant; it is variously spoken that whether the King shall <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to the Army or else to be crowned, as it was intended. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is now near ready his departure for <em>Catalonia</em>, and the Duke of <em>Vendosine</em> is going to the water of <em>Bourbon</em> to recover his health, and by reason that money is very scarce at Court, and therefore the new intended Levies cannot <reg orig="goe">go</reg> forward as it was expected, thereupon a great many vagrants and idle persons about this City are taken up and made fit to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to the Army, besides a great number of men which is to be furnished by divers Towns and Villages near to this City, that so, if it be possible our Army may be able to take the field by the end of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>. Two <reg orig="Counsellours">Counsellors</reg> of the Parliament being exiled last week the occasion as yet not being known, the Parliament sat in extraordinary for to readmit them again, but the first president being ill, the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was differed till another day. This week we have also received Letters from <em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfort</reg></em>, who advise that the <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> at the Diet at <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> was deceased lately. The Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorrain</em>, and his two Sons are this day expected to be at <reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Dover</em> the 25 of <em>April</em> 1654. Yesterday in the evening came<pb n="12" /> this Road a private man of war being a <em>Morget</em> hoy of 6 Guns, and about fifty men, who having found in the <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg> a Dutch ship coming from the <em>West-Indies</em> that had been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent by the <reg orig="tediousnesse">tediousness</reg> of the voyage, did of a sudden clap them aboard, and after little dispute became Masters of her, and brought her along with them, the ship is said to be of great value, for besides plate, whereof several Letters say there is a good quantity, the Ship will be found full of other rich commodities, which will prove very beneficial to the takers when it comes to be judged prise.</p>

<p>From <em>Italy</em> and parts adjacent. From <em>Naples</em>, our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> seeing that the new Levies in <em>Germany</em> will not much increase his Army, after he hath sent those which he doth intend to <em>Catalonia</em>, and <em>Milan</em>, hath given out a Commission for the raising of a new Regiment of Foot, which is to be commanded by the Duke of <em>Tremoli</em>, who is declared <em>Mastre de Campo</em>, he is in the mean time <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to provide all our Maritime places whereof all the <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> have been removed, to prevent any intelligence which they might have with strangers. The <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of <em>Gallicano</em> seeing that no accommodation could be made between her Husband &amp; she, hath therefore resolved with <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> to enter into a <reg orig="Cloyster">Cloister</reg>. The Duke <em>d' Andria</em> and his Brother, who have been for some <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> close prisoners are now set at liberty. The Lady <em>Lucretia Barberina</em> having taken her leave of the Pope and all the great ones at Rome, is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> from thence with the Prince of <em>Palestrina</em>, and some other Nobles to <em>Modena</em>, where she is to be solemnly married to the young Duke. The Pope having received Letters from the Lord <em>Massina</em>, that the King of <em>Spain</em> refused to receive him as his <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg>, hath therefore sent him Letters with Orders to return again. From <em>Venice</em>: The Senate having received the news of the defeat of some of our Forces in <em>Dalmatia</em> which was done by a party of 5 thousand Turks, who lying in an <reg orig="Ambuscado">Ambuscade</reg> took ours at advantage, but with this moderation, that the <em>Morlacks</em> and our Men did carry themselves so gallantly that above<pb n="13" /> 18 hundred of the Turks were slain on the place, and many wounded, the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> on our side being little more than two thousand, and to repair this <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> new orders are issued out for the raising of more forces who are speedily to be sent thither.</p>

<p>From <em>Milan</em>: Our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> seeing that those forces which are promised him by the <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of <em>Naples</em> do not yet appear, hath therefore made a new Contract with the <reg orig="Commandour">Commander</reg> <em>Precivallo</em> of <em>Luca</em>, for the raising of a thousand <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, which are to be brought unto him about the middle of <em>May</em> next, and seeing that he is in <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> of the Duke of <em>Modena</em>, who hath now lately put a small Army in the field, therefore he hath sent the Duke <em>de Sesto</em> to <em>Cremona</em>, and <em>Trin</em>, that he may seen all the Fortifications to be in good order, and the places well furnished with all necessaries, for fear of a surprisal by the said Duke.</p>

<p>From <em>Genoa</em>: Two Galleys of <em><reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg></em> are arrived in this Port, to victual, and furnish themselves with all necessaries for the service in the <em>Levant</em>, being appointed to serve the Venetian, and another likewise which being at <em>Leghorn</em> is to be ready also to go along with them.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>. The K. of <em>Denmark</em> hath been to visit the new Church of <em>Alvenaux</em>, and the next day went back to <em>Gluckstadt</em>. The Gen. <em>Koningsmarck</em> hath at last <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> the town of <em>Bremerburgh</em>, and likewise the Fort which is near it. From <em>Munster</em>, The Swedish Commissioner <em>Hofslater</em> is come to this City to receive from our Bishop, 135000 Rix-dollars, being so much left unpaid to this day by the upper Circle of the Rhine, which being effected, they are to <reg orig="conveen">convene</reg> of a certain <reg orig="summ">sum</reg> for the Evacuation of the strong hold of <em>Weckt</em>.</p>

<p>This Day the Dutch Ambassadors Resident in <em>London</em>, were feasted by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at <em>Whitehall</em>, and very great Entertainment was made for them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday, April 28, 29</i></head>

<p>From <em>Leghorn</em> the 2. April 1654. The last news we have in these parts is, that by a Vessel come hither with silks from <em>Messina</em> we hear, that there hath been of late a great <reg orig="Shipwrack">Shipwreck</reg> upon that coast, where about 16 sails have been cast away, all<pb n="14" /> being lost except a few men saved, besides many others cast away in these Seas: By a vessel come from <em>Alicante</em> we hear, that they are raising of men in the Kingdoms of <em>Valentia</em> and <em>Arragon</em>, which are to be sent part for Dukedom of <em>Milan</em>, and partly for <em>Catalonia</em>, and by reason that we hear the Plague hath began again at <em>Barcelona</em>, as also at <em>Malaga</em>, therefore, by the command of such Officers as are appointed to look to that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, those ships that come from those parts are to tarry 40 days at some distance from this Port. The <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> of Naples having sent some men of war upon the coast of <em>Apuglia</em> to clear the same from the French, whereof it was much infested, have done according to their Order, and so have forced them towards <em>Sicily</em>.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 20. There is yet no considerable News from the North, that I can understand; for <em>Middleton</em> with his forces is drawn into <em>Sutherland</em>, betwixt whom, and our Forces, there is a Navigable River, not passable but by Boats, and those the Enemy has drawn to their own Banks. In many parts of the Country there is all possible Endeavours used to carry on their Levies, and not a few desperate persons continue their recourse to them. There has been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Officers and others of them gathered up lately, and committed to safe Custody. In some of their pockets has been found a paper, called <em>Glencairn's</em> Declaration, <reg orig="stuff'd">stuffed</reg> with many expressions that carry little consistency with their Course. I may possibly help you with a Copy by the next.</p>

<p><em>Inverness</em>, April 14. I can <reg orig="adde">add</reg> nothing to my last, yet would not omit writing to you by this Post. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> is at <em>Dingwell</em> with his Forces. The Enemy still North of him, and past getting out of that Country without either engaging or dispersing their own force, <em>Badgenoth</em>, and other parts of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> are quiet.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Milford-haven">Milford Haven</reg></em> April 24. As for news in these parts, it doth afford little. The last vessels come from <em>Ireland</em>, brought with them <reg orig="severall">several</reg> passengers, which tell us no further, save only that the Tories who remain hid in corners, are as ready as ever to do mischief, but that they want strength, and so narrowly looked after, that they are presently suppressed, and driven into<pb n="15" /> their dens: as for other matters all things are quiet over the Country, as they are likewise in these parts.</p>

<p>From <em>Falmouth</em> the same day, All the news at present is, that we are expecting to hear the peace proclaimed between us and the Dutch, that so some course may be taken to <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> this coast of so many <reg orig="Pyrating">Pirating</reg> Rogues, who have for a long time much annoyed us, and do the same now, though not so bad as formerly, they do no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> about <em>Bristol</em>, and so along that <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>. One of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> lately chased two <em>Brest</em> <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg> even to their own doors, but being got among the Rocks, our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> durst not venture after them, and so gave them over; here are several Ships bound to several parts to the Southward, who are <reg orig="onely">only</reg> expecting a fair wind to proceed on their voyage.</p>

<p><em>Portsmouth April</em> 27. Our Fleet is still riding in <em>Stoakes Bay</em>, and most of those ships which are come in to victual, and be new fitted for the Sea are gone out, and the rest will be ready by the week. We are in a <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> of expectation of General <em>Pen</em> from <em>London</em>, and then upon his arrival we doubt not but this Fleet will be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon some honourable design, which I hope will prove for the good of this Nation.</p>

<hr />

<p>&#x261e; HEPTAMERON, or, The History of the Fortunate Lovers; Written in French by the most virtuous <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> <em>Margaret de Valoys</em> Queen of <em>Navarr</em>; Now Englished by R. C. Master of Arts, Printed by F. L. for <em>Nath. Ekins</em>, at the sign of the Gun, by the West-End of St. <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>. &#x261c;</p>

<p>We are once more desired to mention Mr. <em><reg orig="Isaack">Isaac</reg> Playford</em>, Student and Practitioner in <reg orig="Physick">Physics</reg> and <reg orig="Chirurgery">Surgery</reg>, resident in <em><reg orig="Kingstreet">King Street</reg></em> in <em>Covent <reg orig="Gaeden">Garden</reg></em> near the sign of the Golden Fox, at Mr. <em>Wells</em> his house, to let the Nation understand that he can make the Antidote called <em>Orivetan</em>, so much renowned all over <em>Europe</em>, which is a remedy for most diseases incident to Men, Women, and Children, <em>viz</em>. For prevention of <reg orig="Poyson">Poison</reg>, the Plague, the Small Pox, Palsies, or Convulsions, and divers other diseases not here mentioned. If you please to repair to him, you may have Printed Bills for Directions how to use them, he having it always ready by him.</p>

<p>There was <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> from <em>Good Eastone</em> in <em>Essex</em> the 21 of <em>April</em> 1654 being Friday, A Bay stone horse about 6 years old, four white feet, a white star in his <reg orig="forhead">forehead</reg>, <reg orig="grisled">grizzled</reg> in the face, a white slip upon his Nose, with hair standing up right upon the top of his Buttock, where he hath formerly been <unclear>towelled</unclear>. Also a short Horse about 14 hand high. And a black brown Gelding about 14 hand high, 5 year old and lean, with a white <reg orig="starr">star</reg> in his forehead, and a white foot behind. Whosoever shall send or give notice of such Horses to one Mr. Bagley next door to the White Hart in St. <em>Gyles</em> the Fields <em>London</em>, or to the Bell at <em>Chelmsford</em> in <em>Essex</em> they shall have forty shillings for their pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>