<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc156">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 156</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, the Navy at Sea, and other transactions of, and in relation to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> Decemb. 28. to <em>Wednesday</em> January 4. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, Decemb.28.</head>

<p>This day the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> Brother was removed from Newgate to the Tower of London.</p>

<p>From Bristol thus, A squadron of the English under the command of Capt. Martin with some <reg orig="Hamburghers">Hamburgers</reg> and Swedish ships, and committed them to the care of Captain Crispin to convey them to Plymouth; and Captain Martin is gone further to seek out the Brest men of War which ply about the Lands end, and upon the coast of <reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg>.</p>

<p>The Letters from Scotland advertised, that Glencarn and Kenmore is marched with some broken forces towards the North, to meet with some Arms and Ammunition which they expect from Holland, or elsewhere. The news of the late Revolutions in England are well resented by the English Army, who unanimously declare That they will assist the Lord Protector.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>By Letters from Holland, Decemb. 26. We are at a great stand, what to expect concerning the Treaty with England, most are of opinion upon the receipt of the last Letters from England, that our <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> will return home <em>reinfecta</em>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> Chonu urgeth hard for a near Alliance with this State, and hath offered already very fairly if we will break with Spain. It is said that we shall have of the French six thousand men, three or four millions yearly towards the defraying of the charges of the war, and thirty good ships to join with our fleet. If it be so that we break with you, 'tis probable that France and we may strike up the bargain.</p>

<p>Our defensive League with the Prince of Liege doth not hold (and happily the fault is not on our side) insomuch that all our Troops, both Foot and Horse, are retired to their old <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> again. The Lorrainers being fairly returned <reg orig="before hand">beforehand</reg>, who hereupon with some of the Condees and Spanish under that notion, have besieged a small City belonging to Liege, which they press sore, but have been as yet but rudely entertained, it is to be feared that they will carry it with some others in that Country, and so put the whole country round under contribution.</p>

<p>Our whole Country is now full of discourses of the Treaty with England, if it break, this State will <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to make a diversion in Scotland, by lending assistance to the Highlanders, and it is said that Prince Rupert is to go <reg orig="Generallissimo">Generalissimo</reg> into that Country; but if both States do agree, as is much desired, no doubt but the triumph will be greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> that for the Spanish accommodation.</p>

<p>The Treaty between the Count of Harcourt and the Duke of Lorrain, we hear is far advanced, and it is not <pb n="2" />doubted but that Brisack will change Master, and the whole Province of <reg orig="Elsas">Alsace</reg> lost to the French.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday Decemb. 29.</head>

<p>Dalkeith 22 Decemb. A party of Cap. <reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg> took Cap. Stuart, and four more, killed three, besides divers other taken by parties in other places, among which Lieut. Col. Patwick Hay, Lieut. Col. Cambal, the Laird Lugton, Cap. Crichton, and others of quality. Yesterday Cap. Hart pursued Sir Arthur Forbs from Borthwick Bray, where he was at <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, traced them by the snow, routed them, took 65 horse, 16 prisoners, killed divers, few escaped without wounds. Sir Arthur Forbs and Major Erwin, his Major, both wounded and fled. We had one slain, and 16 wounded. Glencarn and most of their heads, are with 500 horse, and many foot, passed to the North, over the skirts of Bays William, 3 miles in the Mere and Tividale. Middleton sent a letter to Glencarn, that col. Drumond was 26 November, <reg orig="imbarked">embarked</reg> from the Brill with 1500 <reg orig="Valuntiers">Volunteers</reg> of divers Nations. The titular Scots King also sent a letter to Glencarn, dated 12 November, telling him, That the Kings of France and Denmark, the Duke of Brandenburgh, the Emperor, and princes of Germany, are not willing to assist him with men, but have assured him of a large proportion of Arms, Ammunition and monies, and that he would <reg orig="bee">be</reg> with them immediately after the receiving of Drumond and his forces, whose <reg orig="Head-quarters">Headquarters</reg> are to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> at Loughern, the most fortified place in the Highlands.</p>

<p><em>The 21 of December</em>, the bailiffs of the Town of Yarmouth, received the Proclamation to proclaim the Lord Protector, with an Order for publishing it in that Town, and the 22 day accordingly it was proclaimed in a solemn <reg orig="maner">manner</reg> in four places of this Town. The Bailiffs and <pb n="3" />Aldermen in Scarlet, and 48 in their Gowns. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and some of the Officers also accompanied them; and as soon as the Proclamation was published, the great guns in the Town and Forts were fired. The <reg orig="generallity">generality</reg> of people there, are very well satisfied.</p>

<p>The like Letters same from Bristol, <reg orig="Exceter">Exeter</reg>, Salop and many other places, much to the same purpose.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> it is advertised, that Captain <em>Crispin</em> with the Assistance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, is come hither, he was in a storm near Scilly, but afterward sailed Eastward of <unclear> For</unclear> Bay, he hath been with cap. <em>Hatfel</em> and went from thence about the 10 instant, and hath been a great check to the Brest men of War, after which he with the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> that went out with him, on the 16 instant anchored in <reg orig="conquet">conquest</reg> road, where the boats were sent to fetch of two vessels, one laden with wine from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>, the other light, and there were then in the same place near 30 sail more, two of which were supposed to be men of war, who with the rest hauled close under the houses, which were lined with what <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> that country could afford, with which (it being half <reg orig="ebbe">ebb</reg>)they beat off our boat, but by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> providence without <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to us; the <reg orig="Non-such">Nonesuch</reg> boat going in with a small Gun ours also returned with them, and attempted to set the said vessels on fire, but could not make way for our boats, so that Cap. <em>Crispin</em> was constrained to fire out of his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Town, and upon the vessels, against whom he made about two hundred and thirty great shot, which in sight of our men did the enemy very much spoil; the enemy made use of <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one Gun, which they did keep playing all the time at our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> we did beat them from it.</p>

<p>That afternoon we discovered a ship of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> playing in towards Brest, and the <reg orig="Non-such">Nonesuch</reg> sailed after <pb n="4" />her, and the evening took her, she being a great Holland Fly-boat of eight guns, laden with wine from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, Decemb.31.</head>

<p>The Spanish Ambassador sent lately to the Lord Protector, to acquaint his Highness that he had something to tender to his consideration, and would be very ready to attend his Highness when he would appoint the time; and the next day was the time appointed: at which time he congratulated his Highness in his new place of Government.</p>

<p>We have not had any news from Ireland of late considerable, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the last Letters say, that about 60 Tories were lately seen in a party, and about 30 in another, within 30 miles of Kilkenny. It seems their chiefest time is in the Winter; for by the swiftness of their feet, and the advantage of long and dark nights, they use to filch and steal away the <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> from the English.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 2.</head>

<p>This day was extant the Government of this Commonwealth by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> especial <reg orig="commandement">commandment</reg>. Many of the Heads I have already exhibited; I shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> add, That the Parliament sitting, his Highness shall dispose the Militia by Sea and Land by their consent, and shall order it in the Intervals of parliament, by the consent of the greater part of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. That the raising of <reg orig="Moneys">Monies</reg> for the <reg orig="Warrs">Wars</reg> shall be by consent of Parliament, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Lord Protector shall have power until the meeting of the next Parliament, to raise Money for the present service, and to make Laws and Ordinances for the welfare of the Nations with the consent of the greater part of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. That a Parliament being chosen of four hundred persons, sixty of them <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be deemed the Parliament of England &amp;c. and the Supreme Legislative Power is to reside in the Lord Protector and such a Parl.<pb n="5" /> The Parliaments are not to be adjourned, or dissolved without their own consent during the first three months of their sitting, and in case of future War with any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Nation, a Parliament shall forthwith be summoned for their advice concerning the same. That a constant yearly Revenue <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> for the maintaining 10000 Horse and Dragoons, and 20000 Foot in the 3 Nations, for the security of them, and a convenient number of ships for guarding the Seas, and two hundred thousand pound yearly to defray the necessary charges for the <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government, which Revenue is to be raised by the Custom, and such other ways as the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> shall think fit. That in case there needs not so great a defence either at Land or Sea, that an abatement be made, and the money saved to be kept in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service. That the Land, <unclear>Rents</unclear> and Royalties yet unsold or indisposed by Parliament belonging to the Commonwealth (except the <unclear>Forests</unclear>, <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg>, and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> belonging to the same, and some Lands forfeited in Ireland and Scotland, and the Lands of some Papists and Delinquents in England) be vested in the Lord Protector to hold to him and to his Successors. That the Christian Religion contained in Scriptures be held forth, and that a provision less subject to scruple, and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present be made for the <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> of painful Teachers, and confusion of Errors, and that to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Profession held forth none shall be compelled by penalties, and that all such as <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> Faith in God by Jesus Christ, though differing in judgement from the Doctrine <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth, shall be protected in the profession of the said Faith and exercise of their Religion, so as they abuse not this liberty; provided it extend not to Popery or Prelacy.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>The Oath taken by His Highness <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Major part of the last Parliament, (judging that their sitting any longer as then constituted, would not be for the good of this Commonwealth) did dissolve the same, and by a Writing under their hands, dated the twelfth day of this instant December, resigned unto me their powers and Authorities: And whereas it was necessary thereupon, that some speedy course should be taken for the speedy settlement of these Nations upon such a basis and foundation, as (by the blessing of God) might be lasting, secure Property, and answer those great ends of Religion and Liberty, so long contended for; and upon full and mature consideration had on the Form of Government hereunto annexed, being satisfied that the same (through Divine assistance) may answer the Ends aforementioned: And having also been desired and advised, as well by several persons of Interest and Fidelity in this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, as the Officers of the Army, to take upon Me the protection and Government of these Nations in the manner expressed in the said Form of Government, I have accepted thereof, and do hereby declare my acceptance accordingly. And do promise in the presence of God, that I will not violate or infringe the matters and things contained therein; but to my power observe the same, and cause them to be observed; and shall in all other things, to the best of my understanding, Govern these Nations according to the Laws, Statutes and <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, seeking their Peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">O. <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg>.</head>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, January 3.</head>

<p>From aboard the Marmaduke <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> it is certified that we have a very gallant Fleet of near 80 sail already fitted, and upon the Downs, or gone forth in service. Two Dutch prizes were brought in last Friday, and one small French vessel. We have a squadron gone Westward, and some towards Harwich, besides Scouts which ply up and down; 16 sail more are in the Hope, which we expect shortly. Some Seamen and others have lately been punished for criminal offences.</p>

<p>Letters from Holland say, that they are building 30 more new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which will be ready to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> about the beginning of February, when (they say) their whole Fleet <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> come forth: they do what they can to maintain Trade abroad, and say, if the Treaty with England break off, it will prove a very hot summer. Middleton hath sent some Skellums to Scotland, gathered up of several nations. The Agents for <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart speak against his going thither, till he see if they will stand a field fight. Many here are for peace, and many against it; they also speak of great divisions in England. There is speech of a new Declaration <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> forth of the States of the United Provinces, of which more hereafter.</p>

<head level="3">Thus you have an Account of</head>

<p><i>A new Declaration of the States of Holland; the Agitations there for carrying on the war with England, and the <reg orig="Intrest">Interest</reg> of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> in Scotland. Some proceedings of his Highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; with the <unclear>Plan</unclear> form of Government now established in England, Scotland and Ireland; with his Highness Oath thereupon. The bold attempts of the Highlanders in Scotland against the English, with the taking of several prisoners. And variety of Intelligence from Sea.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>There is published five new plays in one <reg orig="vollum">volume</reg> <i> viz. The mad couple well <reg orig="matcht">matched</reg>; The Novella; The Court Beggar; The City Wit; and the <unclear>Damoisella</unclear>: <em>all written by</em> Richard Brown. A collection of those excellent Letters to several persons of Honour: <em>written by</em> John Donne <em>sometimes Dean of</em> St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <em>London. Likewise</em> a Poem called the <reg orig="Shepheards">Shepherd's</reg> Oracles, delivered in certain <unclear>Eglogues</unclear>: <em>by</em> Francis Quarls. And the Poems of John Donne <em>sometimes Dean of</em> St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <em>London</em>; with Elegies on the <reg orig="Authors">Author's</reg> death:</i> to which is added divers Copies under his own hand never before printed. All which are to be sold by <em>John Sweeting</em>, at the <reg orig="Angell">Angel</reg> in Popes-Head Alley.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>