<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc158">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 158</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The consultations in Holland upon the return of their Ambassadors out of England. The removal of the King of Scots from Paris, and the Determination of Major General Middleton, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Massey, and other English. The late actions of the Highlanders in Scotland. The falling down of <em><reg orig="Mahomets">Mahomet's</reg></em> Tomb, and a strange Miracle <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> thereupon, in the presence of many hundred people. The proceedings of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, With variety of choice Intelligence from several other parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> January 11. to <em>Wednesday</em> January 18. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, January 11.</head>

<p>From Falmouth thus. The French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, and the Dutch <reg orig="Free booters">Freebooters</reg> increase every day, they have taken two small vessels of ours lately, and another vessel which belonged to Bristol. We are glad to hear that some part of our fleet is <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> this way, upon the first sight whereof, these desperate Rogues will fly further off. Notwithstanding in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, they will continually be actuating of more mischief.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>From Deal thus. The fleet is now gone Westward from the Downs plying too and again upon the Road betwixt England and the coast of France. Many ships are going from England to the Barbadoes and other parts, I hope they shall have good convoys with them.</p>

<p>Scilly Jan. 2. The Elias <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come safe into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, and brought us six months pay which we were in arrears, other news this place affords not.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday January 12.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Lime</em>: we hear by a Barque come from <reg orig="Britania">Britannia</reg>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroon">Picaroon</reg> near Ushant, gave him chase, and followed so close, that he forced him to run aground on the nether side of the Bay of Camaret, and by reason of his shooting hard at him made the Country to come down to the water side; it happened that some shot did make execution on the shore, there being four killed and wounded; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the Country being all <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg> thereby, could not fetch her off; but ours put to sea again, to clear from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>

<p>By several other Letters from Scotland, which contracted speak to this effect: The Highlanders continue their stealing and plundering of their own Countrymen that will not rise with them, or pay the Contribution money that they lay upon them, though I am confident many have not <reg orig="wherewithall">wherewithal</reg> to subsist, paying likewise their <reg orig="Assessements">Assessments</reg> for the maintenance of the English Army: but when Major General <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, Commissary General <reg orig="Whaleys">Whaley's</reg> Regiments of Horse, with Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> Regiment of Foot, (which we hear are upon their march) are come into us, we doubt not but to send this Heathenish and plundering enemy, so far back into the Highlands, as that they shall not dare to <pb n="2" />approach the Lowlands, whereby to do the inhabitants any considerable prejudice.</p>

<p>How the Highlanders are able to keep horse and man, is <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be imagined, all their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> being upon <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, and his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> with the Dutch for money and Arms; but a peace with Holland (which we hear is in a very probable way for a very speedy conclusion) disperses them to their several mountainous habitations, without ever drawing the sword against them, and then the Lords and Chieftains amongst them may expect a liberal reward of Justice, for doing their Master such rebellious service, which hath been, and is destructive to the generality of Scotland, that a few <reg orig="moneths">months'</reg> continuance will bring them to the sad condition of the Irish, that have been forced to eat the <reg orig="corps">corpse</reg> of their deceased friends after many <reg orig="days">days'</reg> interment; yet are not the people of Scotland very much to be <reg orig="pittied">pitied</reg>, in regard they will <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> give notice to any of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> when any party of the enemy marcheth through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might be the better preserved from their violence and cruelty, <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather to be willingly destroyed by them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> be treacherous (as they call it) to their own <reg orig="Countrey men">Countrymen</reg>: Some Arms they pretend are lately landed for the enemy in Scotland, but this is more to encourage their forced and naked party, <reg orig="then">than</reg> otherwise considerable.</p>

<p>Paris Jan. 17. 1654. By Letters from Perpignan, we hear that the Spanish army are quartered in and about Giron, although the plague doth rage much there still; one party is gone about Palamas, and the Field Marshal de Serra hath an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> Order from Don John d'Austrin, to take care that the country be not oppressed by the quartering of the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, but to keep them in a strict discipline.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>From Alsatia, we hear that the Marshal de la Forte is come before Beffort, where the lines are near finished, and the Ordnance within a <reg orig="days">day's</reg> journey of the place, but on the other side, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Town intends to defend it gallantly; which to effect, and for his better <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> he hath commanded all the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> adjacent to bring in their corn, and all other the like provisions which are necessary for him. The 15th instant the Provost and Eschenins of this City went to the Lawne, where they had audience, the subject being about those monies due to the Citizens upon the Town house. The next day Prince Rupert arrived from Nantz, to this City. The same day returned here from Catalonia, the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquis</reg> du Plessis Belliere, who hath been for many many years an eminent Commander in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army: there is little news at present, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> great preparations are made here for the <reg orig="solemnizing">solemnising</reg> his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> consecration the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>.</p>

<p>From Champagne we hear the Irish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were at St. <reg orig="Meneholds">Menehold's</reg>, are gone from thence to Chaalons, there remaining no more but those companies of Switzers, who were there at the reduction with the Regiment of Dambrole, and six companies more who upon agreement between the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and the Townsmen, are jointly to have the guard of the City, there being an equal number of the town with the <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, to watch day and night: Those of Clermont have not of late made many inroads, the reason we <reg orig="here">hear</reg> is because many desert the place.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Jan. 13.</head>

<p>General Blake, and General Monk are now at <reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg>, General Pen in the Swiftsure, doth ride as Admiral of the fleet. The Fleet is at Spice head, not far from Portsmouth. Some part of them are sent out to ply between Portland and the Lands end, and over upon the Coast of France, to suppress the French <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg>, and those of Holland who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to them.</p>

<p>Three thousand Irish, under the command of the Spaniard, are brought up towards Galizia, who being all old <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, do something trouble the Portugal, fearing they may put a stop to the progress of their successes. The Irish in France boast that these in Spain will take an opportunity to come unto them: They do boast also, but no man <reg orig="beleeveth">believeth</reg> them of a great victory which lately they have got in Ireland.</p>

<p>The <unclear>Dict</unclear> is not yet concluded in Germany, there being new differences between the Prince Elector and his Uncle, about the enjoying of some Lands, which each pretend to be theirs.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>The Dutch to their late griefs have wisely added one day of solemn sorrow, and this (on the beginning of the last week) was observed in a day of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Humiliation to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg>, or divert the anger of the Almighty. Their preparations at sea are great: Nothing is yet done as to the Answer which the Deputies brought from England, and nothing can be done till there be a general meeting of all their States, but it appears their inclinations are for war: But nothing doth more startle them, then the celerity, industry, and magnanimous resolution of the English.</p>

<p>The loss which the Dutch received by the late fire and Tempest is said to be greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> was at first reported, both in houses, and ships; the hearts of the people are exceedingly overwhelmed with sadness at this desolation.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, Jan. 14,</head>

<p>From Gottenburgh, November the 29. After that Captain Welsh had landed the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> Whitlock, he put to sea again, and met with two Hollanders riding at the Scah, the one of four hundred, the other of three hundred and fifty <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, laden with Wheat, <reg orig="Rie">Rye</reg>, Wool, and Planks, of both which he took the charge, and brought them away with him, and by storm was forced to come a little way within this Port for shelter, but remained without the command of the Forts.</p>

<p>The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> was earnestly pressed to send for the Captain, and to discharge the Prizes, but answer was returned, That it was conceived a matter not appertaining either to himself, or to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Officers to meddle with, and <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg>, that the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Ports would not be denied to any English man, who had commission by Authority of Parliament, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> here to shelter himself against storms; that the conflict had been upon the high Sea, between the English and Dutch, who were enemies: For these reasons, his Excellency the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> refused to do anything in it.</p>

<p>This day some of Captain Welsh his men <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to this Town, were <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> and brought before the Landtsher, who examined them, and sent his Major to the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, to know whether he would own the Captain; whereupon his Lordship returned this Answer. That he did not own him, as one who did not believe had had a Commission by Authority of Parliament: Whereupon the men were dismissed. But our English people have the more trouble here, and the less favour, because the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Admiral is a Hollander.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The Swedes of Gottenburgh report that the King of Denmark is much troubled that they affronted our Nation by their ships being <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg>, and blames evil counsel for it. De Wit (when last in the Sound) <reg orig="indeavoured">endeavoured</reg> to comfort him with a cordial of their great Victories obtained against us at sea, giving him a List of 22 sail of our ships sunk, and 8 taken, boasting much of their putting us still to flight. But that <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> own subjects are now able to inform him that the Hollanders, and not we are still the flying party, and that one day, one <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, fought with, and routed their fleet, and men of war, and the next day made her way (the Lord helping us) through three of their ships coming to avenge their quarrel, the least of which (as to countenance) exceeded the Ph&aelig;nix.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, January 16.</head>

<p>There is a story lately printed in Spanish, whether it was penned for truth, or <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for delight I leave to the belief or credit of such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hear of it, and the thing is briefly this.</p>

<p>Upon a day dedicated by the Turks unto <em>Mahomet</em>, there was a great meeting at the Church or Temple called <em><reg orig="Mecha">Mecca</reg></em> where his Tomb, or iron Chest did hang at the top or roof of that building, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> of a Loadstone which was fixed there, and when people were in the midst of their heathenish worship or adoration, in an instant the said Chest did fall down to the ground, and (if the story lie not) the ground forthwith opened and received it into the bowels of the earth in the sight of many hundred spectators, and out of the same place came flashes of fire, and a great smoke for the space of one quarter of an hour, after which the ground closed up again.</p>

<p>From the Fleet thus. We have 50 lusty ships which have met already in one <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>; the <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> will speedily be made ready at Portsmouth; the Rainbow is going <pb n="6" />from Chattam; the <reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg> is already set forth from thence, she was seen yesterday morning beyond the Castle. Four lusty ships more are going from Chattam, and there are ten ships more at the Hope <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> under sail, amongst which are the Lion and the George. The Resolution, which hath carried <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> so stoutly during all these wars with Holland, is now going to be equipped at Chattam. We shall have speedily abroad 100 gallant ships, enough not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to daunt the Hollanders, but peradventure the whole world,</p>

<p>Letters are received from Portugal, informing, that the Spaniards have driven from the Portugals 1200 head of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>, the Portugals who were in a gallant body of about one thousand horse, fell upon the Spaniards who were 1500, and maintained the charge with so much resolution, that they utterly routed the Spaniards, and followed the pursuit to close, that many gallant Commanders fell upon the Spanish party, 300 Spaniards were killed on the place, and 400 taken prisoners, and about 800 horse: It is said that on the <reg orig="Portugals">Portugals'</reg> side, there was no officer slain but one Major <reg orig="onely">only</reg>.</p>

<p>I have seen some letters from Scotland differ something from those in print, for they make mention that the Highlanders are not altogether so barbarously <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> towards those they have taken. The greatest part of them had rather take <reg orig="ransomes">ransoms</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> take away lives, and yet this is not so much out of mercy, as necessity, their miserable condition <reg orig="perswading">persuading</reg> them to use all arts to preserve themselves. It is certain that in their Levies they do miserably oppress their own Countrymen, that they now extol and commend the protection of the English, which before they murmured at, &amp; this intelligence being more <unclear>quick <reg orig="then">than</reg></unclear> ordinary did not a little conduce to the captivity of the L. Kinoul, and the routing of his seventy horse.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, January 17.</head>

<p>From Holland we understand, that the Dutch Deputies that were in England, are safely landed, though as yet not come unto <unclear>the</unclear> Hague, yet are every hour expected. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Orange party leap for joy, and say, Nothing will now be concluded on with England.</p>

<p>The French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> at the Hague is in great esteem; and it is said here, that the titular King of Scots intends suddenly to remove from Paris, but unto what place he goes next, is not yet known. Yet Middleton, Massey, Bunce, and other English are yet here, though they have had many invitations by the Highlanders of Scotland. It is conceived they will not hazard themselves in person upon such a slender Engagement, as that is looked upon by the more <reg orig="sollid">solid</reg> sort of people to be.</p>

<p>The late great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> that happened at Amsterdam by Thunder and Lightening, with great Storms and Tempests, is some <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> to the present Undertakings; and great <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> is made to amend and repair the shipping which received prejudice therein. Two small English Vessels were lately brought into Zealand, which were taken in the North. Their great Fleet is almost in a readiness, Men and Provisions are shipping as fast as may be; yet many are very desirous to have Peace with England, saying, That they shall all be undone if the Wars continue; and if they seal not to the Articles with England, you may expect a Declaration shortly.</p>

<p>Several prizes are brought into Portsmouth, and other Ports, by part of our Fleet. Two of our Scouts chased six Dutch ships, but they being near unto Harbour, escaped; yet not without some damage, for we gave them several <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>.</p>

<p>The Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> sit <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> in consultation upon the weighty affairs of this Nation.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="newes">news</reg> further from Scotland, is, That the Enemy finding the English forces to increase, and to be active in pursuing them, and have taken many of their men lately, They begin to contract themselves nearer together, and say, that they have a great design on foot to go Westward, and do their great matters. But if we once meet with them out of their Dens and <unclear>Fastnesses</unclear>, we doubt not but to <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> their Designs, and make them pay dear for the mischiefs which they have already done.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>