<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn211">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 211</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Decemb. 19. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Decemb.26. 1653</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Decemb. 19.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dalkeith</em> 13 <em>Decemb</em>. came as followeth. The Enemies dispersing themselves into several parts, is confirmed, They are now <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to reduce their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> into form, by laying the same equally upon all the nearest Parishes to the Hills; but their demands so high, That <reg orig="its">it's</reg> impossible that the Country (though willing) should be able to bear them. We have information, that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise and force Men, Horses, and monies in the South, and will have something from the borders of <em>England</em>, where he intends to make some inroads, unless prevented, which is the<pb n="1" /> more probable by that information from <em>Durham</em>, That 20. Horse well mounted went through that Town on Tuesday last by break of day, and the like number, (amongst which Col. <em>Wogan</em> is reputed to be) lay at <em>Peblis</em> on Saturday night last; and the last Sunday morning some of their royal plunderers met with the Post-boy (going with <em>London</em> letters) near <em>Haddington</em>, took away his Horse and letters, and the poor Coat, Belt, and twenty pence in money.</p>

<p>A party of Horse being from a Garrison of ours at Dublain the other night took one Major <em><reg orig="Murrihead">Murrayhead</reg></em> a prisoner at War (and for whom security was given) going to the Hills, they do much encourage their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> by a report, That their King is come into Holland, and that Col. <reg orig="Drumand">Drummond</reg> is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 1500 <reg orig="Volunteeres">Volunteers</reg>, Arms, and Ammunition, and that the Dutch have now left treating with the English: with all which they have a Post to be come from their King.</p>

<p>From old <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em> the same date with the former thus. Captain <em>Lisle</em> being in his quarters at old <reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg>, in the County of Anguish, received intelligence, upon Friday the ninth of this instant, about 8 of the clock, that there was a Regiment of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> Horse quartered within 8 or 9 miles of him; of which Regiment the Lord of Kinnoole is Colonel, and one David Ramsey Lieut. Col. Upon which intelligence, he forthwith sent to Col. Rich his own Troop to meet him, with all convenient speed that might be, at <reg orig="Brichin">Brechin</reg>, being a place where past of Major <reg orig="Bramstones">Bramstone's</reg> Dragoons are quartered, and in the way to the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, and they meeting according to order, he and they, with part of Major <reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg> Dragoons and 12 Foot-<reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, which he mounted out of his own quarters of old <reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg>; about 4 of the clock in the morning, marched out of <reg orig="Brichin">Brechin</reg>, and in the break of the day, fell into the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, where by the providence of God, there was taken two Captains, one Cornet, one Quartermaster, a <reg orig="Corporall">Corporal</reg>, and twenty private <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and about 40 Horse, and some Arms; for the Captains before they would be taken, suffered the House to be fired<pb n="2" /> about their ears, so that there was divers Arms lost in the fire: there was 3 killed, and thanks be to God this was done without any hurt on our side, save only there was one man wounded by a shot in the thigh: the Lord of Kinnoole, and Lieut. Col. Ramsey, with about 30. of their <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> being quartered in a very strong stone House, by that means escaped from us. And by that time Cap. Lisle was in his quarters upon Saturday at night, there came Orders from Col. <reg orig="Morgin">Morgan</reg>, that he with his Troop should meet <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Morgin">Morgan</reg> near Thornton the next morning early, which accordingly he did, where met likewise Col. Rich his Troop, Major <reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg> Troop of Dragoons, and a commanded party of Foot of about 30. in number from Dunotter Castle. And with this party we marched 6 or 7 miles into the Highlands, and again fell into the Lord of <reg orig="Kinnooles">Kinnoole's</reg> quarters, where we took about 7 or 8 prisoners, and about 18 Horse, killed one, and rescued the Lord of <reg orig="Egles">Egle's</reg> <reg orig="sheriffe">sheriff</reg> for that part of the Country, whom they had taken prisoner from his own House the day before, Kinnoole and Ramsey themselves very hardly escaping, the whole Regiment totally dispersed; but our Horses were so spent, and the way so <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>, because steep Rocks, and dangerous bogs, and night coming on, that we were constrained to leave off the pursuit.</p><pb n="3" />

<p><i>A List of the prisoners taken in the Lord <em><reg orig="Kinnooles">Kinnoole's</reg></em> Regiment.</i></p>

<p>Cap. Michael Belford Gen. <reg orig="Bruse">Bruce</reg> J. Braud</p>
<p>Cap: Wil: Blare J. Macklane G. Mat. Donald.</p>
<p>L. J. Ramsey Wil: Fife Ar: Walle</p>
<p>Cornet Wil: Grier D. Cuttinangus J. Paterson</p>
<p>George Flike David Lanson Wil: Fumiston</p>
<p>J. Martin Jem. Gardner Alex Goodley</p>
<p>Francis Sharp Rob. Swan Hen. Man.</p>
<p>David Ramsey</p>

<p>These were taken upon Saturday the 10. of Decemb. 1653. with 40 Horse, by Cap. <em>Edmund Lisle</em>.</p>

<p>This day his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, was proclaimed by sound of his Trumpet in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard at Westminster, at the old Exchange, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other places in London: Divers of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>, and the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen in their Robes; together with three <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, with their Maces, and the Heralds in their Ornaments, attending. The tenor of the Proclamation was as followeth. By the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> a Proclamation</p>

<p><i>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, by a <em>Lord Protector</em>, and successive <reg orig="treiennal">triennial</reg> Parliaments, is now established; and whereas <em>Oliver Cromwell</em>, Captain-<reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of all the Forces of this Commonwealth, is declared <em>Lord Protector</em> of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof: <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make publication of the Premises, and strictly to charge and command all and every person and persons, of what quality and condition soever, in any of the said 3 Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all <reg orig="Shrieffs">Sheriffs</reg>, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, and Officers, whom this may concern, are required to cause this <em>Proclamation</em> to be forthwith published in their respective Counties, Cities, Corporations, and Market-Towns, to the end, none may have cause to plead ignorance in this behalf</i></p>
<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em> the 16 day of Decemb. 1653</i></p><pb n="4" />

<p>We gave you the last week an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> of the manner of the <reg orig="Installment">Instalment</reg> of the Lord Protector, some further of the frame and constitution of the Government now established, (so much enquired into) this may be added, That we shall have Triennial Parliaments, and the first to begin on the third of Septemb. Next, and so from 3 years to 3 years.</p>

<p>That Parliaments shall be chosen by the people, according to certain qualifications set down in the said Parchment.</p>

<p>That the time of their sitting shall be for five <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p>

<p>That such Laws as shall be agreed on in Parliament, shall be presented to the Lord Protector for his assent; which if it not be obtained within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, then those Bills shall <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> notwithstanding, and become Laws in full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>.</p>

<p>Strict provision is made also for the succession of Parliaments, the management of Elections, and of Returns to be made by the several Sheriffs of the persons elected.</p>

<p>That the Lord Protector shall govern with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, the number of whom shall not be <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> thirteen, and not exceed twenty one.</p>

<p>That all Writs, Process, &amp;c. shall issue forth in the name of the Lord Protector; That Articles of War shall be made good, That the Ministry of the Gospel shall be maintained, and the present way of their maintenance continued, till some other way more convenient shall be found out and provided.</p>

<p>All Magistracy to be <reg orig="detrived">derived</reg> from him, all hours to be conferred by him, Peace and War to be made by him, and the Militia by Sea and Land to be ordered by His Highness, and the major part of His <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><em>Thuesday Decemb.</em> 20</head>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> Dec. 6.</em> The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em> safely arrived at <em>Gottenburgh</em>, Nov. 15. where he <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in expectation of an Answer to certain Letters of his, which he had sent to the Queen. The Dutch here say that the treaty with you in England will come to nought, and that you will thereupon go together by the ears more fierce <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever: certainly that people mean nothing for they in all these parts hold up their violent malice against England, and have Letters constantly out of their own Country, which augment their disaffection abroad, and <reg orig="shew">show</reg> what temper the rest are of at home.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> Nov. 2. S.V. The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> arrived here upon the 15 instant with all his retinue; they are a gallant company consisting of at least 50, or 100 persons; he is yet here, and I suppose will stay yet not 10 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, till he get the answer of those Letters he sent to Court since he came hither; he came a shore the same day he arrived here, so that the Magistrates here had no opportunity to receive his Lordship as they intended, but having <reg orig="bin">been</reg> <reg orig="extremly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> unto him since, which he doth himself <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg>; The convoy which came along with the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships are yet here, which will now get the good company of the Ph&oelig;nix and Elizabeth <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg>, which came with my Lord over. By Letters from Stockholm I have that there was three <reg orig="Hollands">Holland's</reg> Fly-<pb n="6" /> <reg orig="boates">boats</reg> laden with great Guns for Holland. I have acquainted his Excellency with it, and doubt not but some course will be taken for the interception of the same.</p>

<p>From Madrid the 10 of Nov 1653. The King hath been <reg orig="forneer">for near</reg> a <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> at the Escurial but is returned this week back to this City in perfect health; There hath been lately a great alteration made at Court among the great ones who have been renounced from their places of authority, and exchange made one for the other. By the last Post arrived here from Biscay; we hear that our Fleet which was in the River of <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, is safely arrived into St. Scbustians.</p>

<p>This week died in his Lodgings at Court, the Earl de Figneyro Lord Steward to the Queen. We hear from Leghorn by Letters of the 22 last past, that 36 <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> of Naples, to whom was <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> two great Dunkirk men of War had met with some French Merchant ships, and after a great fight had seized upon them, and carried them into Portolongow.</p>

<p>From Scarborough the 12 of Decemb. 1653. the last week a private man of War brought in a Dutch prize into Burlington Bay, where having not remained long, he sent her up to Hull, the ship is of burthen about 150 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, her loading for the most part Nantes Wines, with some Vinegar: there hath passed before this Town the last week a good number of ships, who sailed to the Northward, the most part<pb n="7" /> being bound to Newcastle, and the rest for <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg>, and Scotland: we have not been of late troubled much with the Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, neither do I hear that they have done us any harm of late in these parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Francfort">Frankfurt</reg></em> the 10th of Decemb. 1653. We hear from <em>Vienna</em> thus. That the Earl de Bouchaim, Lieut. Gen. for the Emperor in <reg orig="Hungaria">Hungary</reg>, is come back from thence in that City, having first visited all the <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> places of that Kingdom, and left them in a very good condition able to resist the Turks, who have not made any invasion since the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> thither of some high Dutch Regiments.</p>

<p>From <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>. This week deceased here the Earl of Losenstein, one of the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> privy <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>: the <em><unclear>Diett</unclear></em> is not yet ended, there being so many businesses in agitation, that either it must yet continue a long time, or else leave many things undecided till the next Diett, chiefly, that great point concerning the Duke of Lorrain: some of the States of the Empire finding many difficulties in point of security, about the payment of the first hundred thousand Rich Dollars.</p>

<p>Dom John de Borgia Ambassador in Ordinary for Spain, is gone from hence, taking his journey for Flanders.</p>

<p>The King of Denmark is still at <reg orig="Coppenhagen">Copenhagen</reg>, and hath lately sent more ships to the Sound, for the better preservation of that place from any <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> invasion.</p>

<p>The difference between the Elector of <em>Cullen</em>, and that City, is not yet ended, which is great prejudice to that City, by reason the said Elector doth wholly stop their trading upon the Rhine; but there are mediators <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> for reconciling of both parties, if it may be done upon reasonable <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg>, which as yet seemeth to be difficult, time will produce more.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday December</em> 21.</head>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector</head>

<p>A Proclamation of his Highness, with the consent of his Council, for continuing all Persons being in office for the Execution of <reg orig="Publicke">Public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, until his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> further Direction.</p>

<p><i><em>Oliver, Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, considering, that whereas the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, is invested and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council, And left thereupon the <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and ordinary course of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> in the Commonwealth (if <reg orig="remedie">remedy</reg> were not provided) might receive Interruption, His Highness in His Care of State, and <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg> thereof (reserving to future consideration the reformation and <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> of any abuses of Misgovernment, upon better knowledge taken thereof) is pleased, and doth hereby expressly <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, declare and ordain, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, who have power until the meeting of the next Parliament to make <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force until Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, That all persons who on the tenth day of this instant <em>December</em> were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of <reg orig="Iudicature">Judicature</reg>, or Office of Authority, <reg orig="Iurisdiction">Jurisdiction</reg> or Government, within this Commonwealth, shall be, and shall so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and places<pb n="9" /> respectively as formerly they held and enjoyed the same, and not otherwise, until his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which respect or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>, and all Proceedings of what nature soever, in Courts of Common Law, <unclear>&amp;</unclear>, or in the Court of Admiralty, or by Commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purpose is the same were on the said to tenth day of this instant <em>December</em>, until further Order given by his Highness therein, And that in the mean time (for preservation of the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of <reg orig="Iustice">Justice</reg>, and for Safety of the State) all the said Persons, of whatsoever Place, Degree, or Condition, may not fail every one severally according to his respective Place, Office or Charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all Duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them, whilst the former Government was in being.</i></p>

<head level="3">Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 21 of December, in the year of our Lord, 1653.</head>

<p>Those of His Highness Council already chosen, and which now fit in the old Council Chamber at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, are these so <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg>, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>Major General <em>Lambert</em> Colonel <em>Peter Jones</em></p>
<p>Major Gen. <em>Desborough</em> Colonel <em>Mountain</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Henry Lawrence</em> <em>Rich: Major</em>,</p> 
<p>Sir <em>Charles Worsley</em>, <em>Walt: Strickland</em>, Esq;</p>
<p>Colonel <em>Sydenham</em>,	Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>,</p>
<p><em>Francis Ross</em>, Esquire. Major Gen. <em>Skippon</em>,</p>
<p><em>Philip</em> Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em>, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>.</p><pb n="10" />

<p>By the last Letters from <em>Naples</em> thus. The Earl of <em>Castriglio</em> our new Vice-king is arrived from <em>Sardinia</em> to <em>Pesilippo</em> with his Lady, and a numerous train of followers, and being landed was brought to the Palace belonging to the Duke OF <em>Fruelia</em>, who had caused it to be made ready for him; and the same day sent his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Letter to the Earl <em>de Ognate</em> late Vice-king, who is now preparing to <reg orig="imbark">embark</reg> and <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>Genoa</em>: There was lately taken in this City many <reg orig="theeves">thieves</reg>, who used to do much hurt every night by killing and breaking open houses; being brought to their trial, two were condemned to be hanged, 5 to be whipped, and two sent to the Galleys during life. From <em>Venice</em> thus: We hear from <em>Levant</em> by way of <em>Otranto</em>, that the great <em>Vizir</em> had sent an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> to <em><unclear>Vissam</unclear> Bashaw</em> to command him to return home, and with many fair promises, that after some conference with him of what is most convenient to be done the next Summer upon the grand Design they have had for many years to conquer <em><unclear>Candia</unclear></em>; this being done he is to be sent thither again: but he dispatched away the <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> with Letters, wherein he desireth to be excused, and this Vessel being taken by a French man of War, the letters were found, and the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> discovered. We hear from <em><reg orig="Corfou">Corfu</reg></em> that the Turks intend to send twenty two men of War into our Gulf, thereby to spoil our trade, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> us much mischief, which to prevent, the General <em>Delfino</em> in <em>Dalmatia</em> hath sent a squadron of Ships and Galleys to oppose them at <em>Casilenovo</em>, thereby to secure those parts from foreign invasion.</p>

<p>From <em>Turin</em>: The Enemy hath his <reg orig="Head-quarters">Headquarters</reg> at <em>Gattinara</em>, and most of their Army is gone to Winter quarters, their being only a party of horse left to observe our motion, which is but slow; the condition of our Army and the season not permitting either of us to undertake any considerable action, which we must refer till the next war.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday December</em> 20.</head>

<p><em>Paris December</em> 21. The last Letters from <em>Lyons</em> do confirm unto us the great division <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> lately in <em>Avignon</em> between<pb n="11" /> the Gentry and the Citizens, both parties being very much <reg orig="inraged">enraged</reg> one against the <unclear><!-- approx. 12-14 characters --></unclear> Court of <em>Rome</em> intended to have sent thither one of the Cardinals to have ended the <reg orig="Controversie">Controversy</reg>, but upon deliberation it was resolved, that the <reg orig="Arch-bishop">Archbishop</reg> who commands there in chief for the Pope, shall have a power to hear both parties, and to put an end to all controversies, he having a full and strong Commission sent him to that purpose. We hear from <em><reg orig="Marseillis">Marseilles</reg></em>, that there is a great preparation at <em>Toulon</em> for a Fleet to be ready against next <em>March</em>; those men of war who were gone out with Letters of Mart being all commanded to come in by the next month; in the mean time great store of Bisket is providing, a great quantity of Arms and Ammunition, so that it is like to prove some great enterprise, the common report goeth that it is to relieve <em>Rosa</em>; but there is no need of so great preparations for that work, but it is more probable that this project is carried on, to begin a new War in the kingdom of <em>Naples</em>. The Duke of <em><unclear><!-- approx 8 characters --></unclear></em> is waiting with much impatience fro the <reg orig="Comming">Coming</reg> of the King in our parts, which is not like to be sooner than <em>February</em> next. From <em>Bordeaux</em> we hear little: the Plague doth still continue there, but many write that it is not so violent as formerly: they see with mournful eyes, the new raising of the two <reg orig="yoaks">yokes</reg> which the Court pleased to lay upon their necks by the rebuilding of the two Castles: they have as yet little or no trade, the Spanish men of war being still about the mouth of the river: The Court is here very merry after their great <reg orig="successe">success</reg> this last Summer; the Prince of <em><reg orig="Conty">Conti</reg></em> is still expected but not come as yet: The Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> is also at his house, and no means can prevail with him to draw him to the Court: The Duke of <em>Beauford</em> hath been there lately, but is gone from thence now: The Chamber <em>Ardenn</em> hath not of late done <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>: our Archbishop doth continue to be sick: The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> remaineth close prisoner, and not well in health.</p>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em> December 19 thus. The people in these Lands say the Treaty hath been long in hand with <em>England</em>,<pb n="12" /> that they fear nothing will come of it. It will be a difficult point to bring all the Statesmen here to agree about it, being all divided in Interest and opinion; some looking towards <em>France</em>, others towards <em>Spain</em>; some wedded to the <em>Orange</em> party and <em>Charles Stuart</em>, and think to support themselves by lending a shoulder to that broken Family. Some few also there are who are good Patriots, and they but few, who know, <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg>, and desire an Union with <em>England</em>, as the great Interest of their Country, but can do nothing, because <reg orig="over-powred">overpowered</reg> and <reg orig="out-numbred">outnumbered</reg> in all <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg>. The truth of things, and the offers made by <em>England</em> to incorporate both Commonweals into one, are kept from the knowledge of the People, or else misrepresented to them, as if thereby <em>England</em> intended only to <reg orig="becom">become</reg> Masters of themselves, their wealth, and their Trade and so the <em>Bouteseus</em> here do blast all belief of those Advantages that might come to the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces by such an Incorporation; which would be a matter of so much consequence to Religion, and of Terror to the Popish party, that it is no wonder if all the Jesuits in <em>Europe</em>, (who are said to have a notable influence in the Dutch Council) employ all their Wits and Insinuations to hinder it. And therefore it is often beaten into the ears of the great ones here a <em>Coalition</em> (as the term is) with <em>England</em>, would soon take down the dignities of these <em>Hoghens Moghens</em>; so that rather than part with their High and Mighty Titles, they seem more ready to sacrifice Religion, and the Interest of the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> people, as the price of their ambition. It will and must be said so, and this people will at length understand it, if their Lords do neglect those great Advantages, which you in <em>England</em> have <reg orig="offer'd">offered</reg> them by his Treaty. Which God bring to a good issue, if not yet concluded.</p>

<p>What to think of it here, we cannot tell; for, great Preparations are going <reg orig="one">on</reg> here still. Much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> here is at the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, and much Talk about them. <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> said, that some Supplies of Arms and Ammunition have been let go from hence, or that they shall go. If true, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> no good sign; nor can I tell what to think of the great preparations in hand<pb n="13" /> in this Country against Spring, no less than thirty new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> now laid on the Stocks to be added to the former 30 already built. The whole Navy of old and new together, will be, they say, above 100 sail: besides, they will <reg orig="labor">labour</reg> to hold up their Reputation in the <em>Levant</em>, by Lording it that way this next Summer: for, young <em>Tromp</em> is to go out of hand with 12 men of War to the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, and they have their eyes <reg orig="every way">everyway</reg>, both at home and abroad, when activity portends more than ordinary Resolutions for Action.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday and Saturday Decemb.</em> 23,24.</head>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, <em>Decemb</em>. 18. Affairs here seem troublesome, though the Highlanders have for <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> divided themselves, conceiving it for the present more for their accommodation and design, than in a body; <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> territories is the West, <em>Glasgow</em>, and Marshes; Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> and <em>Ramsey</em> the <unclear>Breas</unclear> of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> in <em>Angus</em> and <em>Mearnes</em>; Earl of <em>Athol</em> in <em>Athol</em> and those Clans above St. <em>Johnstons</em>; <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Glengary</em> towards the North parts about <em>Innerness</em>; and thus this new purloined Royal Army have disposed their Quarters; but a party of Horse from Hence with Col. <em>Morgan</em>, somewhat disturbed their Levies, in <em>Angus</em>: for they have taken about 40 men, and 60 horses, and had unregimented <em>Kinnoule</em>, if the hills had not been friend to a few.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith December</em> 17 thus: The Enemy is departed from the hithermost parts of <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em>, and gone to <em>Kirkmichel</em> in order to their march Northwards; as I am informed <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarn</em> are both there and their force reported to be 500 Foot and 500 Horse, but those that gave me information that saw them, affirm they are not half that number, they lie under very many discouragements, and every place is eaten up where they come:, that they are forced upon often removals; and now provision of Mutton and Beef begins to decay: I hear they intend for the North, that their quarters upon the Lowlands, may be more assured and broader, where they expect the Landing of foreign forces, Ammunitions and money from their <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, and the States of <em>Holland</em>.</p><pb n="14" />

<p><em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> doth nothing considerable; the people refuse to raise his men according to command, one that saw him and his <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he hath not got above 40 foot, and Major <em>Mercer</em> is there with about 60 horse.</p>

<p>Capt. <em>Elsemore</em> of Col. <em>Riche's</em> Regiment, sent out a party the other day from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, who took one Capt. <em>Stewart</em> who had a Commission from <em>Lorne</em> to raise Forces, and four others, and <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> three on the place: The Marq; of <em><reg orig="Huntly">Huntley</reg></em> died last week at his House of <em><unclear>Bogy-geith</unclear></em>.</p>

<p><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg> December 19. A private man of War, we have Intelligence hath brought into Holy Island two Dutch vessels coming from the East Country both being about one hundred and fifty <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burthen, laden with Pitch, Tar, and the like commodities.</p>

<p>From Falmouth the 19 instant: There are many Ships in this Harbour which are now all gone to their several intended Ports: The Dutch are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts, so that it is very hard to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> by the lands end without a good Convoy: they have we hear taken a Sip of London coming from New-England, laden with Masts, Beaver Skins, and the like commodities. Here have been some of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships to wash and tallow, and to take in fresh water, but they <reg orig="ar">are</reg> all at Sea again, there remaining none at present in this harbour.</p>

<p>From <em>Deale</em> the 23. We have news this day that some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken some Beclanders belonging to <em>Calice</em>, who were bound for <em>Roan</em> and <em>Cane</em> in <em>Normandy</em>, laden with divers sorts of commodities, and carried them into <em>Stoaks</em> Bay, where we hear that General <em><reg orig="Monke">Monk</reg></em> with his Squadron was about 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since: Those ships lately gone from hence bound<pb n="15" /> for <em><unclear>Pean</unclear></em> are safely arrived there, and their Convoy is returned back.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Scotland, Dec.</em> 19. The Enemies disperse themselves into several parts is confirmed; they are now <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to reduce their Levies into form, by laying them upon all the nearest Parishes to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, but their demands so high, that it is impossible the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> (though willing) should be able to bear them. We have information that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all his endeavours to raise and force men, horses, and monies in the South, and intends to make some Inroads into the borders of <em>England</em>, unless prevented; which is the more probable from the information from <em>Durham</em>, That 20 horsemen well mounted, and armed with pistols and swords went through that Town on Tuesday last by break of day amongst them a person of Quality. The same number and <unclear>party</unclear> lay at <em>Pellis</em> on Saturday night last, and with them Col. <em>Wogan</em>, formerly a Cap. of <reg orig="Dragoones">Dragoons</reg> in the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> Army. Thursday night last Lieutenant <em>Whitmore</em> going with a party towards the Hills took one Major Morehead (a prisoner of War and yet upon parole and security) well mounted and armed, going to the Enemy, as himself <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg>. They do much hearten their party, that their King come is come into <em>Holland</em>; that Col. <em>Drummond</em> is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>, Arms, and Ammunition; and that the Dutch have left off treating with the English: <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> which they feign a Post came lately from their King. On Friday morning last, a party of these Royal Pilferers met the Post-Boy going from <em>Leith</em> with Letters for <em>London</em>, and near <em>Haddington</em> <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> his Horse and Letters and some money, so that now it will be uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy.</p>

<hr />

<p>If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> hath found a big Red Letter-Case, with an Order from the Trustees at Drury house, and other writings therein belonging unto one Mr. Lloyd, lost on Tuesday the 20. of this instant, let them give notice unto Mr. Thomas Jones a Girdler at Chancery lane end, or to Mr. Thomas Hartley <reg orig="house-keeper">housekeeper</reg> at Drury house, and they shall have satisfaction for their pains, with thanks.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and entered according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>