<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn223">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 223</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> March. 13. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></i>, March. 20. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, March 13.</i></head>

<p>We had from <em>Scotland</em> this day by several Letters as followeth.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith 9 March</em>, Since <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing, the Enemy go on to their <reg orig="Rendezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which will be about <em>Straithspey</em> the 10 or 11 instant; they give out (to encourage the Country) that Middleton hath 3500 foot, and 500 Horse, but the people know the contrary. There was besides Captain <em>Johnson</em> (who was killed before Blair Castle) one Cap. <em>Scot</em> shot in the back, not likely to recover and Lieut. <em><reg orig="Erwins">Erwin's</reg></em> Horse killed under him. The enemy do rather diminish <reg orig="then">than</reg> increase; very many through dislike, either of their Quarters<pb n="1" /> or Service; do run from them. An order is issued forth, if any go down to the Lowlands, without a party, they are to be brought back, and suffer for it. The Lowland men would fain be at home, the Highlanders are so barbarous towards them, that if they catch any Lowlandmen apart from the rest, they presently take all away from them <em>Athol</em> and <em>Forbs</em> are yet in <em>Glenlyon</em>, but they are forced to remove every night. A party of horse from St. <em>Johnstons</em>, on <em>Tuesday</em> last, took a Sergeant, and another of his men. The main body of their forces, is yet in Bagnoth; <em>Middleton</em> is gone towards the Lord <em><reg orig="Reays">Reay's</reg></em> Bounds. The unhappy disaster of the two Troops, you have the particulars of before.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, march 7. A party of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Forces Horse and Foot, came the last week and faced <em>Blair</em> Castle, the Governor Captain <em>Witter</em> sent out a party within protection to skirmish with them: whereupon one Cap: <em>Johnston</em> and two more with him, charged up to our men on horseback, but himself and one more were killed, then all came up, whereupon our men retreated, they <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> off their two dead men, and buried the said Captain with Col. <em>Wogan</em> at the Kirk of <em>Kenmore</em>. His death is much lamented amongst them, being very stout, but in this business he was too fool hardy: we had either one or two shot. There have of late been some private overtures made from some in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg><pb n="2" /> of some proposals which would probably much allay the present distempers without any harsh corrosives, which though I have hinted before, yet since nothing is done tending to satisfaction in any of them, I shall again inculcate, 1. Te sequestration that was upon many (and of little or no advantage to the State) made many desperate, and so to be removed. 2. That personal Arrests might cease, and Creditors contented to take all their lands and goods, for satisfaction, or to cease prosecution till there be ability to pay: the want of this makes others desperate. 3. That such as were <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of fortune had <reg orig="past">passed</reg> the prime of their time in Wars, and were void of Callings, or <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>, might be considered to be transported to some Prince or State in amity with the Commonwealth for they are; born and they must be kept, or will have a <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg> as long as they can get it. If these things were put in Execution it would prevent many from going to them, and bring off many from them.</p>

<p><i>A Narrative of the sad accident that befell the Troops at the <em>Lanker</em>, in <em>Scotland</em>, published to prevent the misreports that perhaps some <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> spirits will be ready to make of it.</i></p>

<p>On the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day Feb. 19. 1653. Captain <em>Mason</em> being at <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, upon which he forthwith marched<pb n="3" /> with 80 of his Troop, whose approach the Enemy discovering left the Town, betaking them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>; Captain <em>Mason</em> in pursuit took a Cornet and two more, the rest (their horses being fresh, and his almost weary with the march escaped) Capt. <em>Mason</em> quartered in the Town that night, and about four in the morning Captain <em>Palmer</em> came there with his party, having also had intelligence of the enemies being there, and knowing nothing what was done, took Captain <em><reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg></em> Troop to be the Enemy, and a Scotchman one of the <reg orig="Dragoons">Dragoon's</reg> Scouts, being violently charged by Captain <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> men, who he thought to be the enemy, declared the spirit of a Scotchman by saying that he was for the King, to save his life, by which <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> he lost it.</p>

<p>The whole party then <reg orig="endevoring">endeavouring</reg> to enter the Town, but the Guard repulsed them, upon which Captain <em>Palmer</em> drew out a party of 20 to fire the Guard house, by which time Captain <em>Mason</em> had got 30 or 40 of his horse together, and with them beat out Captain <em><reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg></em> party, which they took to be the Enemy, they pursued in the evening, but at the Towns-end Captain <em>Palmer</em> met them with the whole party, and fell upon them, both sides still judging each other to be the enemy, in which unhappy engagement six were slain of both parties and eight wounded, of which Captain <em>Palmer</em> is one hurt.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> March. 14.</head>

<p><em>Amsterdam</em> March. 14. Here is much discourse of the great Preparations made for Sea by you in <em>England</em>, which causeth the State to be very quick in theirs, yet here is all hope of Peace, and the affections of men seem ripe for it, expecting to hear of it very <reg orig="suddainly">suddenly</reg>, especially the Merchants. Our neighbour States and Princes wonder much at the great number of ships that are to be equipped on either side, and therefore if a Peace be, must needs say, it was not Necessity but Reason that made it.</p>

<p>The French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, Monsieur <em>Chanas</em> hath been labouring very hard at the <em>Hague</em>, to put on the Interest of his Master, so as that it may not be left<pb n="4" /> to stand or fall by <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, when the Conjunction between both the <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg> shall be <reg orig="compleated">completed</reg>. The Spaniard will (it is said) be put to play a new Game before he thought of it. This Peace, if it prove so, is a hinge upon which all the affairs of Christendom, must have a new Turn. The Popish party frown at it, and talk of a Conjunction too between the Emperor, Spaniard, and I know not who, it may be they may think on the <em><reg orig="Steuarts">Stuarts</reg></em>, if any good may be done against <em>England</em>, upon the score of that Family. It seems, by the working of Affairs, as if there would be a Confederacy against the <em>Reformed Religion</em>, though (perhaps) it shall be managed upon other pretences.</p>

<p>An <em>Eastland</em> Fleet of about 150 Sail hath brought home the great necessaries of this Country.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> the 18 of <em>March</em> 1654. <em>Stilo novo</em> from <em>Perpignon</em> we hear that the Commander in chief <em>Merinuille</em>, who was left by the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>d' Hocquinon</em> to command the French Army, having notice that the Enemy had some <reg orig="designe">design</reg> upon <em>Castillon</em>, a place near <em>Rosa</em>, is marched with some Forces to prevent their <reg orig="designe">design</reg>, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> reported in <em>Catalonia</em>, that the Count <em>de Ognate</em> late Vice-King of <em>Naples</em>, is to come thither to be their Vice-king. From <em>Alsatia</em> by the last Letters, that the Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em>, having received <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Orders from the Court, to take in all the small places in <em>Alsatia</em>, and so march to <em>Brisack</em> and block it up, thereby to reduce the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em>, and <reg orig="compell">compel</reg> him to accept those conditions, which are set down in those papers sent him from the Court, hath marched with his Forces thither, and taken in <em>Ensisheion Guemer</em>, <em>Alkris</em>, and Saint <em>Creux</em>, and having disposed all things for the <reg orig="besiedging">besieging</reg> of <em>Thanes</em>, given the command of the Army to the <em><reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> de Castelnan</em>, and by permission from the Court is retired to <em>Nancy</em>, there to refresh himself of those great labours he hath suffered in the field this last Winter.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>This new Commander having set the siege in a forwardness, began to work cunningly with the besieged and having taken in one of the <reg orig="Subburbs">Suburbs</reg>, which was fortified with a Moat, and a good number of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to guard it, two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the Trench being open, and he upon some action, was shot through the arm near the elbow, and the wound so dangerous, that he is forced to be carried into <em>Nancy</em> to the great grief of the Army, who nevertheless became Masters of the Town 8 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after, and the Castle being now open, a Treaty we hope will take effect.</p>

<p>The 14 instant Dom <em>Joseph Marguerit</em> Governor of <em>Catalona</em>, Dom Francis <em>de Montpalan</em> Abbot of <em>Bagnoles</em>, and Dom <em>Francisco de Calno</em>, Field-Marshal Commissioners for <em>Catalonia</em> and <em>Kussillon</em>, had their first audience at Court, being very graciously received by the King, to whom the Abbot made a learned Speech, wherein he represented to the life the sad condition of those Countries, and what heavy and long pressures the people had been under these many years, humbly praying that some speedy and effectual relief may be sent into those parts which might give some ease to their present griefs, and prevent greater evils, which without that will necessarily ensue.</p>

<p>The King hath made them many great promises, and the Cardinal likewise, whom they visited the next day, and had likewise a very long conference with him, now their whole attendance is to procure<pb n="6" /> that relief and assistance in effect, which they have only in words, and do intend to spare no pains for the attaining of it.</p>

<p>Upon <em>Thursday</em> next two of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces are to be married, the one to the Duke of <em>Candale</em>, the other to the Marshal of <em>le <reg orig="Millerays">Milleray's</reg></em> Son.</p>

<p>The <em>Dutch</em> Ambassador here hath spoken several times to the Cardinal, on the behalf of the Protestants, that they may be redressed in what they desire of his Majesty; and that some effectual Order may be speedily taken to prevent all further complaints. Furthermore, that his Majesty would be pleased to cause to be made good unto them, all that his Royal <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> hath vouchsafed to allow unto them, and all what hath been granted them by the King and his Predecessor.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and His Brothers are still here, but are resolved not to stay long, having no encouragement given them at this Court, where they do much desire a peace with <em>England</em>. And our great expectation is to hear that Monsieur <em>de Bourdeaux</em> had very near finished the Treaty between France and England, with the Lord Protector; wherein we make no doubt but the said Monsieur <em>de Bourdeaux</em> will be able to give content to his Highness in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that can in justice be demanded of this Crown.</p>

<p><em>Fromfort</em> on the Main the 8th of March 1654. We have by letters from <em>Poland</em>, that the Lord <em>Bleganowsk</em> who is sent as Ambassador to <em>Constantinople</em>, notwithstanding all the <reg orig="Ambuscadoes">Ambuscades</reg><pb n="7" /> which the <em>Tarlures</em> had laid to entrap him, had happily gotten his way without meeting any opposition, being now near to his <reg orig="journies">journey's</reg> end: yet the Country is in much fear, being like to see a very great invasion by the <em>Musconite</em>, who as the report goeth, hath near two hundred thousand men: with the which he intends to enter the Country by several places, his pretence for doing is, that he demands the City of Smolensk, and the Dukedom of Semery, which he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, hath been by open violence taken from him, and the more to strengthen his side, he doth <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to draw the <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg> to him.</p>

<p>The Diet is newly begun, but as yet nothing can be said in any relation to it.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>. The time that the Emperor hath set for the closing up of the Diet, being near expired and they finding it to be impossible to end their business within so short a time, have thereupon made their humble addresses to his Majesty, that he will be pleased to give them yet an additional time for that purpose, to which the Emperor hath answered, that the affairs of <em>Hungaria</em> were of that consequence, and required such a speedy <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg>, that he could not tarry a longer time: therefore they should find out some speedy way to conclude the whole business.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>: Since the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of the French forces into the Country of Liege, the Spaniards and the Lorraigners have wholly left it; but having first plundered, and then fired divers small Towns, among whom is one belonging to the Countess of Schwartzenburgh.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Marstrick">Maastricht</reg></em>. Although the Lorrainers be quite gone from the Country of Liege, and are now quartered around Diest, yet the Elector of Cullen will not lay down his arms till such time he hath good security, that no such invasion shall be made for the future, and that the <reg orig="Authours">Authors</reg> of the mischief shall give satisfaction towards these losses sustained.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday March</em> 15.</head>

<p>This day the Commissioners from the Lord Protector and the Dutch Commissioner <unclear>have had</unclear> a conference <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> Abraham Williams in order to the <unclear>finish</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> the Power. The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> this day was to <unclear>confer the Reports of the</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> which were <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> on both sides and <unclear><!-- approx. 20 characters --></unclear>, A final Close (<reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed) will be within a few days.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> March 11. About three day since the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and the <em>Constant Warwick</em> being together <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear> with the <em>Brest</em> Man of War commanded by Captain <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> Admiral of their <reg orig="Pyratick">Piratic</reg> crew which lurk in <em>Brest</em>. <unclear>Others are with him</unclear> two Prizes which he had newly taken, but perceiving them our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the Prizes and was afterwards <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> by night coming on. The same being <unclear>of</unclear> the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and the Constant<em> Warwick</em> <unclear><!-- approx. 15 characters --></unclear> Company; and it fell out about Midnight that <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> moving about, lighted on the Constant <em>Warwick</em> all alone, which before he came near, he took to be a Merchant <unclear>Man</unclear>, and went on with an intent to board him, but the Warwick <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> who he was, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> he was the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and for <em>Whitehall</em>, but the <em>Warwick</em> suspecting him, <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> him <unclear>stand</unclear> off. The <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake and seeing the <em>Warwick</em> to be a Man of War, he presently made away; but the <em>Warwick</em> being a good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg> made after him, and kept company with him all night. About 6 in the morning <em>Beach</em> began the fight firing three Guns, which were answered by the <em>Warwick</em>. The encounter lasted till 2 a clock in the Afternoon, at which time <em>Beach</em> and his Men called for quarter, and had it. He had 5 foot water in the hold when he <reg orig="yeilded">yielded</reg>; he had 200 men, 20 whereof were killed, his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is a gallant new Vessel, <unclear>with</unclear> 42 Guns whereof but 30 were mounted. There are taken aboard with him 9 Captains besides himself, &amp; divers Gentlemen who are all Prisoners. This is that Beach, the ring leading Pirate, who hath done our Merchants so much mischief this Winter that he lived like a Prince at Brest; for which 'tis like <unclear>he will</unclear><pb n="9" /> receive his reward, being brought in hither with the rest of his Companions.</p>

<p>From <em>Dover</em>. March 9. By a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Barque come this morning from <em>France</em>, we hear that a great Fleet of Dutch Merchantmen, consisting of about 140 Sail, are gone to the Westward, sailing close by the French coast. And having a fair wind, <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> like they may <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> without any interruption from our Fleet, who are (we hear) still near St Ellen's point: this Dutch fleet have a Convoy of about <unclear>60</unclear> Sail of Men of War, (as they say) but they are to be divided, the Merchantmen being bound to several Ports and Countries.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em>, the 15. of February, 1654. Our <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> made his <reg orig="Cavalcate">Cavalcade</reg> upon the 12th instant, and was sworn after the accustomed manner, this being performed in the great Church of St. <em>Laurence</em>, in the presence of the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg>, of our Archbishops, and most of the Nobility and Gentry, and in his return to the palace he was saluted with all the Ordnance in the Castle of this City.</p> 

<p>From <em>Rome</em> the 23 ditto. There hath passed nothing more of late concerning the business of the Cardinal <em>Pamphino</em>, save only that some of his <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> servants are apprehended and sent to prison: There was likewise Order given to have apprehended his Secretary, but he having notice thereof, escaped out of this City, and fled to his Master. There hath been Proclamation made by the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of this City, that all manner of persons presume not to carry about them any pistols, or such like armour, by day, upon the forfeiture of all their Estate, and to be sent to the Galleys, nor by night, upon pain of death; none having the Privilege but only the Shires who are a certain number appointed for the Guard of the City:</p>

<p>The Duke <em>de Terra Nova</em> is arrived in this City from <em>Marino</em>, and hath made his Entrance with a great number of Coaches; he is to be here as ordinary <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>.</p><pb n="10" />

<p>From <em>Venice</em> the 24. ditto: We hear this week by way of <em><unclear>Smyria</unclear></em> of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> at <em>Constantinople</em>; which advises us, That the Bashaw of <em>Buda</em> being lately called home from his Command of those parts, was chosen Captain <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Fleet, being better entertained than he of <em><reg orig="Rhodez">Rhodes</reg></em>, who was no sooner come but his person and all his Estate was secured, which his <reg orig="sonne">son</reg> hearing, laid hold of all those <reg orig="choise">choice</reg> things which he could come at, and is fled in a Galley into <em><reg orig="Barbarie">Barbary</reg></em>. There are great Preparations to be made against <em>Candia</em>, and <em>Dalmatia</em>, both by Sea and Land, and out State on their part neglect nothing requisite for their defence.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday March</em> 16.</head>

<p><em>Paris</em>, the 21. of March, <em>stilo novo</em>. The putting down of those Officers called the Elect, doth not in any way prove to the case of the people, although so pretended; for in <reg orig="liew">lieu</reg> of them are to be created other Officers, which, though appearing under other shapes, do give notice of a worse evil than the first, and prove more burdensome to the people. The whole <reg orig="Bodie">Body</reg> of this University, have again made some Addresses to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg>, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> their complaints concerning the laying of a new <reg orig="Taxe">Tax</reg> upon all sorts of Paper, which they <reg orig="shew">show</reg> will turn much to their prejudice, by a great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to the Printers, and others, who have relation to that profession: The answer was, That the matter should be taken into consideration, and with all speed be taken off, though the common opinion is, that there will be only moderation used, in regard the <reg orig="Taxe">Tax</reg> is very high. The Cardinal hath now well nigh finished part of his work, having consummated the matches between the Duke <em>de Candale</em>, and the Marshal <em>de la Mesteray</em> his <reg orig="Sonne">Son</reg> with two of his Nieces, which was done this week. The Court doth now begin to <reg orig="stirre">stir</reg> for the recruiting and new ordering in a military posture their Armies; and to that end the Marshal <em>de Turenna</em> is gone into <em><reg orig="Picardie">Picardie</reg></em> to set the work forward. Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em> is at <em>Nancy</em>, and<pb n="11" /> is said to be sick, which is more caused, by reason be is now under the displeasure of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg>, form having (as I am informed) gone beyond his Commission in his late Treaty with the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> <em>de Harcourt</em>, which is distasted by the Cardinal: It was expected that the Court should <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to <em><reg orig="Fontaine-bleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em> this week, but now the report goeth, that it is put off till after the Holydays. The Cardinal and his Creatures are much troubled to see that nothing can <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> the Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em> to come to the Court, they taking was a main <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> to the carrying on of their great designs: The Prince of <em>Condi</em> we hear is come from <em><reg orig="Brassels">Brussels</reg></em> to <em>Louuain</em>, and from thence to <em>Rocroy</em> having by the way taken a view of his Army into the several quarters, intending, if possible, to take the field by the beginning of the next month, and now the Earl <em>de la Susa</em> with divers Commanders and the Garrison in <em>Beffort</em> will much conduce to the furtherance of the Works.</p>

<p>From <em>Vpsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, February 10. We are yet expecting the good hour of dismission, which will not be too suddenly: though I hope we shall be ready to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> away by that time the weather will give us leave. The Chancellor is an old Statist, and he makes excuses and delays, till he see what the issue will be of our Treaty with the Dutch. Neither can I blame him, for according to that, it will be necessary to guide their answers unto our proposals. This afternoon my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, and the Chancellor have had another meeting; there is a very fair <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> between them: but, according to the <reg orig="policie">policy</reg> of State, I suppose, as yet there passes only discourse between them, and nothing is drawn up unto a head, he being willing to see, whether there is likely to be a Peace, or a continuation of War with the <em>Hollander</em>. There is an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> come from <em>Russia</em>, he that was here before is gone into <em>Denmark</em>; 'tis <reg orig="talkt">talked</reg> of that the Duke of <em>Moscovia</em> will make a War with the <em>Pole</em>, and therefore he Courts these neighbouring Princes.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> Feb. 27. These are from <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg> in Scotland of several dates came to my hand as followeth. About eight days<pb n="12" /> since <em>Middleton</em>, with Sir <em>George Monro</em>, the Lord Napier, one called Major General <em>Dial</em>, and <em>Lodowick Drummond</em> in a small Hoy from <em>Holland</em> put into <em>Garmouth</em>, which is a the mouth of <em>Spey</em>, and is the place where <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> landed, but understanding we had Garrisons near that place put to Sea again, and about twelve of the Clock at night landed at the Ferry of <em>Vnes</em> in <em>Sutherland</em> with about fourscore Men, as we have notice; they sent about ten load of Arms to <em>Auchness</em>, and themselves are gone towards the shire <em>Assine</em>, they give out another Vessel is to meet them in <em><unclear>Strathcavern</unclear></em>, but they speak not of any men, he hath since summoned all the Gentlemen and Heritors of <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg>, Sutherland</em>, and <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>, to come in unto him, and hath appointed a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> to be this day in the <em><unclear>Brays</unclear></em> of <em>Sutherland</em>. He hath forbidden the Sheriff of Sutherland to act any more in the names of the Keepers of the liberties of England, or in the name of <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector, but <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he will give him a Commission to act by as Sheriff. <em><unclear>Seaford</unclear></em> hath raised 600 men, and is gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, but the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> <em>Glencairn</em> and the rest sustained by Col. <em>Morgan</em>, and that by Col. <em>Daniel</em>, I doubt not but allays their courage, and his landing with so inconsiderable a party both in number and <reg orig="demeanor">demeanour</reg> will not a little dishearten their Comrades, who always made <reg orig="shew">show</reg> of expecting great Matters by <unclear>him</unclear>.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em> March 6. In my last I gave you an Account of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing in <em>Sutherland</em>, there is since a Vessel come for him into <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> whether he is gone to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> all he can to craw the Gentlemen of that Country into an <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> with him, which we hear they are backward in, notwithstanding he gives out great words, and talks of diverse Vessels with Arms to come to him: <em>Seaford</em> is endeavouring all he can to get some of his men together to meet him, the Country generally <reg orig="disrellishes">disrelishes</reg> their proceedings, by the next I may have an occasion of enlarging.</p><pb n="13" />

<head level="3"><i>Friday and Saturday March 17, 18.</i></head>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em> the 20th of March, stilo novo. Here is returned from <em>England</em> one of the Pilots who was commanded to wait upon the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, who brought news of their gallant Reception by the Lord Protector. About four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since arrived here two Pilots who had gone over with General <em>Middleton</em> into <em>Scotland</em>, and brought word, That he was landed there with those men he had with him, most of them Reformadoes, One hundred and fifty Barrels of Powder, and arms for some Thousand men: We hear also by one lately come from <em>Amsterdam</em>, That their Freebooters have lately taken some Colliers homeward bound, who straying from their Convoy and the main Body of the Fleet, were soon taken, and carried away: The common Report here is, That the Peace is made between you and us, which is generally wished for among the people.</p>

<p><em>Dalkieth</em>, March 14. Upon <em>Middleton's</em> landing in <em>Sutherland</em> he sent summons to the Gentlemen of <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em>, <em>Sutherland</em> and <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> to give him a meeting at his <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be the last of <em>February</em>, (at the place where <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em> was formerly overthrown) upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Southerland</em>, and their to send in their Levies of men and Horse: When <em>Middleton</em> came <reg orig="ashoare">ashore</reg>, he writ to the Sheriff of <em>Sutherland</em>, Requiring him not to <reg orig="keepe">keep</reg> any more Courts in the name of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>: <em>Seafort</em> hath gotten<pb n="14" /> 600 of his men together again, and is gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>. There was brought in the <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> with <em>Middleton</em> 300 Barrels of powder, 1000 Snaphance-firelocks, and as many Pikes, Muskets, and Pistols, as made in all 5000. Arms, which, with two Brass Field-pieces, were <reg orig="lodg'd">lodged</reg> in the Castle of <em>Skelbo</em>, which is <reg orig="secur'd">secured</reg> by Major <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Dyell</em>, and one Major <em>Watson</em> with Six or Sevenscore men; <em>Glencairn, Kenmore, Glengary, <reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em>, and <em>Forbes</em> with their Rabble, intended their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> as on this day 24 Miles from <em>Aberdeen</em>, from Whence Col. <em>Morgan</em> is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> forth to <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> with them.</p>

<p><em>Scilly</em>, March the 12th. A small Vessel of <em>Topsam</em> that came from S. <em>Sebastians</em> and commanded by Cap. <em>Stafford</em>, who had a Commission for a <reg orig="privat">private</reg> Man of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg>, brought in hither a French Prize of 30 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Iron, <reg orig="Licquorice">Liquorice</reg>, &amp;c. But the News which will be most acceptable to many, is the bold attempt, and good success of Captain <em>Potter</em>, Commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, who on Saturday last in a single encounter, mastered, and took as prize, the <em><reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> James</em>, commanded by Captain <em>Beach</em>, chief Admiral of <em>Charles <reg orig="Steward's">Stuart's</reg></em> <reg orig="Pickaroons">Picaroons</reg>, and hath brought him into this Port; the Fight continued Eight hours, and then <em>Beach</em> <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> for Quarter: <em>Beach</em> had 39 Guns, and 200 men, the <em>Constant Warwick</em> had about 130 Men, and 32 Guns, which indeed was an Eminent service; The Captain commends both his Officers and Seamen for standing close by him, but especially his Lieutenant, for his Judgement and Valour in that <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> service; <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <em>Potter</em> lost but two men, and <em>Beach</em> about twenty men; <em>Beach</em> <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> aboard the <em>Warwick</em>, demanded of Captain <em>Potter</em>, the way and manner of performing his Articles, <reg orig="clayming">claiming</reg> it his promise to set him <reg orig="ashoare">ashore</reg> in France; at which Captain <em>Potter</em> being startled, told him, he never heard of such demand, and to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> <em>Beach</em> therein, commanded <em>Beach</em> aboard again his own <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg>, and to fight it out; but <em>Beach</em> refused the same: Such eminent services merit more than ordinary <reg orig="Incouragement">Encouragement</reg>.</p><pb n="15" />

<p><em>Beach</em> and his Crew are since brought into <em>Plymouth</em>, and close Prisoners there, till further Order for their <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>, which will be speedily.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for appointing Commissioners for approving o Ministers throughout the Nation, is <reg orig="past">passed</reg> by the Council. Also an Ordinance for disposing forfeited Estates in Scotland; and tow other Ordinances for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Customers and Excise, which will be forthwith published.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Harwich</em> we understand of a Dutch Ship of Four hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, <reg orig="Tarre">Tar</reg>, Masts and Iron, to a great value, brought in thither, taken by a private man of war.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly published an excellent piece of Mr. <em>Tho. Brooks</em> Preacher of the Gospel at <em>Margarets</em> <unclear>Fishstreet</unclear> Hill, intituled, Heaven on Earth; or a serious discourse touching a well grounded Assurance of <reg orig="Mens">Men's</reg> everlasting <reg orig="Happinesse">Happiness</reg> and <reg orig="Blessednesse">Blessedness</reg>. Discovering the Nature of Assurance, the possibility of attaining in the Causes, Springs, and degrees of it, with the resolution of several weighty Questions. Printed for <em>John Hancock</em> in Popes-head Alley.</p>

<p>There is newly published a curious new plain and exact map of England, Wales, Ireland, and Scotland, the which is <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> called the <reg orig="Travellers">Traveller's</reg> guide and plain <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> Map because both it and all other Maps are made plain and <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> by directions therein given, whereby <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> may know the way, situation, and distance of any place therein, with a description <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the temperature of the Airs, Nature of sails, and the Commodities thereof, as also a brief <reg orig="Chronologie">Chronology</reg> of all the remarkable passages and actions that have happened therein ever since the long Parliament began November the 3, 1640, to this present, both by Sea and Land, they are not only necessary for ornament of every mans house, but for all occasions and persons, and of small price, and are to be sold by <em>Robert Walton</em> at the Rose and Crown at the West end of St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>.</p>

<p>A black Mare with a blaze down her face, five years old, fourteen <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> high at least, <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> all, the near foot behind lately shaved, not quite cared of the scratchings, some white on her <reg orig="hinde">hind</reg> feet, but one hath more white than the other, with a black half checked Bridle, and sad <reg orig="colourd">coloured</reg> saddle, <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> out of a Stable at <em><unclear>Bonce-bridge</unclear></em> near <em>Peterborough</em> <unclear><!-- approx. 2 characters --></unclear> of March in the night. If any can give notice of her to Mr. <em>Hall</em> at the Fox in Watlin street London or to Mr <em>King</em> of <em>Bottlebridge</em>, they shall 20 shillings for their pains.</p>

<p><i>Licensed and Entered according to Order.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>