<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfII1">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Politick Commentary, Issue 1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">A Politick</head>
<head level="1">COMMENTARY</head>
<head level="2">On the Life of</head>
<head level="2">Caius July C&aelig;sar,</head>
<head level="3">Written by CAIUS SUETONIUS TRANQUILIUS.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">CHAP. 1.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>C&aelig;sar</em> in the 16 year of his age lost his father <em>Lucius C&aelig;sar</em>, who died suddenly at <em>Pisa</em> in <em>Italy</em>; and in the year following being elected <em>Flamen Dialis</em> (which was the great Priest of <em>Jupiter</em>) he cast off <em>Cossutia</em> (a Gentlewoman born, but very wealthy affianced unto him during his Childhood; and espoused <em>Cornelia</em> the daughter of <em>Cinna</em>, four times Consul, <i>(the which without question was, that he might have the assistance of <unclear>his</unclear> father in law, to back him in his great attempt)</i> who bare unto him soon after, his daughter <em>Julia</em>: neither could he be forced by any means, by <em>Sylla</em> the Dictator, to put her away: whereupon being deprived of his dignity, losing the Dowry in the right of his wife, and forfeiting all his heritages descended unto him from his lineage and name, he was reputed one of the contrary faction; insomuch as he was constrained to hide his head: and albeit the Quartain Ague hung sore upon him, to change almost every night his starting holes, wherein he lurked; yea and to redeem himself with a piece of money out of the Inquisitors hands that made search for him: <i>you may perceive that this was the cause that <em>C&aelig;sar</em> was of a contrary faction to <em>Sylla</em>, who chastised <em>C&aelig;sar</em> out of a religious pretence, the better to <reg orig="cloke">cloak</reg> his enmity to<pb n="1" /> <em>C&aelig;sar</em>, who he much feared might one day overtop him in his usurpation. At this time may be discerned, that the Roman Commonwealth was declining in <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, for that the Inquisitors took Bribes: it is a fit time for Tyrants and Usurpers to thrive, when a Commonwealth is degenerated in <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> seeketh a particular good, and not a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good, else such Weeds would be pulled up before they grow too <reg orig="bigge">big</reg>.</i></p> 

<p><reg orig="Whilest">Whilst</reg> <em>C&aelig;sar</em> was in this exile, the religious Vestal-Virgins mediate for his liberty, and that he may be received into favour. by the mean of <em>Marcus Aurelius</em>, and <em>Aurelius Cotta</em>, his near kinsfolk, and allied unto him, he obtaineth pardon of <em>Sylla</em> after much denial; who when he granted the request of those <reg orig="worshipfull">worshipful</reg> persons, said, Go to my Masters, take him to you, since you will needs have it so: but know <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, that he whose life and safety you so much desire, will one day be the overthrow of the Nobles, whose side you have taken with me.</p>

<p><i><em>C&aelig;sar</em> did very cunningly in this, that he <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> the Vestal Virgins, whose charge it was to keep the holy fire that it went not out. In those days Religious Orders had a great influence over the greatest in power: since that those in power have by them had great power over the people, they have not esteemed of Religion any further then a Cloak.</i></p>

<p><i>But here <em>Sylla</em> prophesieth of <em>C&aelig;sar</em> that one day he should destroy the Nobility. There might a great question arise, Whether that the end of <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> or <em>Sylla</em> was the better. <em>Sylla</em> he striveth to defend the Nobility! It is probable that the Nobility did at that time Tyrannize: for if they had not discontented the people, there had been no footing for <reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> to undertake what he intended.</i></p>

<p><i>Certain it is, that the Commonwealth at that time would not have suffered so much, if <em>Sylla</em> had prevailed, for that his assistants were a rich Nobility; as it did when <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> made <reg orig="him self">himself</reg> Lord of Empire, for that his assistants were all poor and hungry, who raked and scraped more <reg orig="then">than</reg> those that were already full would have done.</i></p>

<p><i><em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> made use of the discontents of the people as a footstep to ascend, together with pretending to ease them from servitude: he <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> he attained the Empire, pretended all that he did to be in favour of the people, which begot in them the more <reg orig="Willingnesse">Willingness</reg> to assist him. A people are <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> deceived by these two Vizards, viz. pretence of Liberty, and Religion.</i></p>

<p>C&aelig;sar being restored to liberty, doth go to the wars in <em>Asia</em>, in the<pb n="2" /> Domestical Retinue of <em>Thermius</em> the Pretor: by whom being sent into <em>Bythinia</em> to levy a fleet, he made his abode with King <em>Nicomedes</em>, by whom it was supposed he suffered his body to be abused: after which, at the taking of <em>Mitylian&aelig;, Thermus</em> honoured him with a <reg orig="Civik">Civic</reg>: Garland: <i>which was an Ornament that <reg orig="Generalls">Generals</reg> of the field were honoured with. It was made of Oak-leaves bearing Mast: it was also an honour that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> had that saved the life of a Citizen of <em>Rome</em>, for which <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> was honoured with it. This was the first undertaking of <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> in the wars: he being one of the Domestical Retinue of <em>Thermus</em> the Pretor. The Roman young Gentlemen were <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> trained up in martial affairs: in the same manner, to attain <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg>, did attend the Generals, &amp; Lieut. Generals of armies in their Pavilions, and were as their familiar companions. After this, he was a <reg orig="souldier">soldier</reg> under <em>Servilius Isauricus</em> in <em>Cicilia</em>, but it was not long: he conceived that to attain the Empire it must be by Arms, therefore it was requisite that he should attain to the experience of arms</i>; he left this undertaking, hearing of the death of <em>Sylla</em>, in hope of the new dissention that was set on foot by <em>M. Lupidius</em>, he returned in all <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to Rome. <i>This dissention was occasioned by <em>Lupidius</em>, being a Consul, who went about to alter the Laws and Acts that <em>Sylla</em> had established: the which kindled a new civil war.</i></p>

<p>For all this, he did forbear to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Lupidius</em>, though <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was often thereunto solicited; <i>For that <em>Lupidius</em> was of a variable and <reg orig="unconstant">inconstant</reg> disposition, and for that then was not a fit time for him to attempt what he intended: the Commonwealth could then have been <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and quieted with <reg orig="smal">small</reg> forces: his design was to increase the troubles of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and put a necessity on the Commonwealth to make use of great forces to allay the troubles thereof.</i></p>

<p><i>So that his design was to pretend the service of the Commonwealth, and so obtain the conduct of those Forces, by which one day he might fasten obedience, or his intended servitude, upon the Commonwealth <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> with the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Arms he made himself Lord of the Commonwealth.</i></p>

<p>Howbeit, when that the discord, occasioned by <em>Lupudius</em>, was appeased, he judicially accused for extortion <em>Cornelius <unclear>Dolobbly</unclear></em>, a man who had been Consul, and had triumphed.</p>

<p><i>In this he took an effectual course to his rising, to remove out of his way those that might <reg orig="bee">be</reg> hurtful to him, or hinder him in his intended usurped <reg orig="Tyrannie">Tyranny</reg>.</i></p><pb n="3" />

<p><i>When one that is in power is accused for injustice, if he that accuseth be in any sort <reg orig="powerfull">powerful</reg>, or in any credit with the people, his Authority is soon <reg orig="weakned">weakened</reg>, and <reg orig="after wards">afterwards</reg> brought to a Bar to receive the sentence of death, by him that not only jumps into his place, but also cloatheth himself with his iniquity also; and by this means disquieteth the Commonwealth, doth the same and worse and pretends that the State of the Commonwealth necessitates him thereto; if any should say otherwise, he is made a <reg orig="Traytor">Traitor</reg>, and a seditious person: <reg orig="hee">he</reg> being now at the top is the only person to judge of the necessities of the Commonwealth; Who <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he was rising, made every man the Image. He who helpeth him, whilst he is obtaining what he aimeth at that medleth with <reg orig="every thing">everything</reg>, though accounted never so sacred is esteemed for a <reg orig="publike">public</reg> -minded man; but he that medleth, after he hath obtained the Empire, is accounted a <reg orig="busie-body">busybody</reg> and a dangerous person.</i></p>

<p><em>C&aelig;sar</em> faileth in his attempt against <em>Dolobblla</em>, who was found not guilty, and acquitted, by which <em>C&aelig;sar</em> received much disgrace; he to avoid the hatred of the people, for his accusing so honourable and worthy a person, determineth to <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> to the City of the Rhodes, where he intended to learn the Art of Oratory under <em>Apollonius Molon</em>, the most renowned <reg orig="Rhetotician">Rhetorician</reg> in those days.</p>

<p><i>People are usually carried away with a good opinion of those that have <reg orig="successe">success</reg> in their attempt: to <unclear><reg orig="tryrinise">tyrannise</reg> </unclear>, with a disesteem and hated of those that have ill <reg orig="successe">success</reg>; of <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> had cast <em>Dolobblla</em> he had gained reputation, his not casting of him brings a disrepute upon himself; if <em><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg></em> had failed in his attempt of the Empire, he had been brought to a Bar and lost his head as a Traitor, but he not failing, bringeth his legal opposers to the same place and punishment that himself deserved.</i></p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Treason never prospers, what's the reason.</line>
<line>Cause when it prospers, none dares call it Treason.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p><i><reg orig="Cesar">C&aelig;sar</reg> faileth in his accusation, therefore suffereth disgrace; perhaps it was for want of being a good Orator; for <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> the best judgements and quickest wits are none the best Orators, but to supply that defect he undertook to learn that art, to add his other good parts, which he intended to <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> to an evil end and purpose: he intends to rise by the people, in his rising to make <reg orig="musick">music</reg> to their ears, by fair words and promises inviteth them to expect Liberty, instead thereof behold Slavery.</i></p>

<p>The end of the first Chapter.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="2">Perfect and Impartial</head>
<head level="1">INTELLIGENCE,</head>
<head level="3">Of the Affairs in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, And other Parts beyond the Seas.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em> May 16. to <em>Tuesday</em> May 23, 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation of General <em>Monk</em> published in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his Highness, and his Council, do declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> within twenty days after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the Governor of the next English Garrison, and give good security for his, or their future peaceable living, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and is hereby in his and their persons freely pardoned, for any offence, spoil, or plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion, (the killing of any person in cool blood only excepted,)</p>

<p>And I do declare, That if any Parents, Brethren, or Tutors who have assisted or connived at any of their sons, brothers or pupils to render themselves and give security, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publication hereof, cause their said sons, brothers or pupils, to render themselves and give security, as aforesaid, that then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are hereby freely pardoned; But if otherwise, then the said Parents, brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion.</p>

<p>And in regard divers persons who are now in rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion, without the knowledge or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish of Presbytery where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth; I do therefore hereby declare, That if the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, that then the Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned; But if otherwise, I do hereby impose<pb n="5" /> upon the said Parish, or Presbytery, two shillings six pence a day for each Horseman, and ten pence o day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their ordinary Sesse, out of the said Parish or Presbytery, which the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg> is hereby authorized to levy and receive <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, during the time the said persons shall so continue in Rebellion.</p>

<p>And I do likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into rebellion, or attempt so to do, and safely him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>; and in case of resistance, to take such weapons as they can get, and to fight the said person, or persons, and if they shall kill any of the said persons so resisting, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive as a reward of their good service, all such monies, goods, horse, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg>, as the said rebellious persons are then possessed of, besides full satisfaction for their pains and <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Donald, <reg orig="Mac Donald">McDonald</reg></em> Lord of <em>Glencary</em>, and Major Gen: <em>Dayell</em>.</p> 

<p>I do hereby therefore Declare, That what person or persons soever of this Nation (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any English <reg orig="garison">garrison</reg>, the said person or person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be pardoned for <reg orig="anything">any thing</reg> he or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but also receive a reward of his good service, the sum of 200 hundred pounds sterling for every person so killed or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And lastly, for the <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> of all peaceable and well affected people, both English and Scots, I do also hereby declare, That what damage shall be done to their persons, goods or <reg orig="geer">gear</reg>, for their good affection to the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>, the same shall be again repaired out of the estates of such as have done the damage, or out of the estates of the friends and harbourers of such <reg orig="wrong doers">wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the Parish, Presbytery, or Shire where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said Offenders, or give the English forces such timely notice thereof, that the said Offenders may be apprehended by them.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>And I do hereby require all Provosts, Bailiffs, and chief Officers of Headburghs, in their several Burghs, to cause these presents to be duly published and posted up, according to the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me, in writing under his or their hand.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand at Dalkeith, this 4 of May, 1651:</i></p>

<p>George Monk.</p>

<p>Col. Venables, and Col. Ingolsby are come from Ireland, and have presented their addresses from the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> there, to the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>General Blake being come to Town from the Fleet, he with the Lord Mayor, and some of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> dined this day with the Lord Protector, General Pen is with the Fleet in the Downs, the Northern squadron that convey the Coals will shortly be there, God willing, the Brest men are out, and do mischief upon the Western coasts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The substance of the <reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg> Propositions to the States of Bohemia assembled 13 April, 1654.</i></head>

<p>1. That they use their utmost <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> for the propagating of the Romish <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</p>

<p>2. That they <reg orig="selebrate">celebrate</reg> the Feast of S. <em><reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg></em> as the rest of the Patrons of the Kingdoms used to do.</p>

<p>3. That they pay a considerable sum to the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> for the maintenance of his <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> Officers, <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, Residents and Attendants.</p>

<p>4. That they pay their proportion for maintenance of the frontier places of <em>Hungaria</em>.</p>

<p>5. That they continue the maintenance of the Imperial Forces quartered in that Kingdom, and pay those which his Majesty shall disband.</p>

<p>6. That they suffer not the importation of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> salt without paying the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> Customs and Duties.</p>

<p>7. That they neither suffer the importation, nor in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> the use of the bad Turkish wool.</p>

<p>8 That they shall incessantly cause the River of Elve to be made navigable as far as this Town.</p>

<p>9. That they perform whatsoever hath been agreed on in former Assemblies touching the other Affairs of the Kingdom.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>On <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> was published an Ordinance intituled, <i>an Ordinance for the explanation of an Ordinance formerly published</i> intituled <i>An Ordinance for the mending of <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg></i>, which was that no Cart or Wagon should be drawn with more then six oxen and an horse: or five horses to exceed that number penalties are provided therein: Now it is provided by the <reg orig="afore mentioned">aforementioned</reg>, that it shall not extend to the drawing of Ordinance for the Army, or Timber for the use of the Navy: and such Draughts as have a Pass under the Lord Protector, or the President of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, or the Commissioners of the Navy, or under the hand of the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Gettenburgh</em> by Letters of the 24 <em>April</em> thus. The Lord <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> hath finished the Treaty with the Queen of Sweden, and the Parliament there is to sit the first of May, and Oxenstern is to be sent <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> into England, with a great attendance.</p>

<p>From Dalkieth Gen. Monk hath published his Declaration, and Middleton continueth still at <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg>.</p>

<p>From Jersey by Letters that some of <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> of the English Navy, went ashore near St. Maloes, where some of the Country rise upon them and slue some of them.</p>

<p>From Deal, several Hollanders and <reg orig="Zelanders">Zealanders</reg> are come upon the Coast to Trade.</p>

<hr />

<p>Reader, thou mayest wonder that in this discourse, I should undertake to prove <em>C&aelig;sar</em> a Tyrant and a Usurper, my Author <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> little better of him in these words, <i>and for that he assumed the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority and altered the Laws of his Country; the Gods as a just reward due for his so doing, permitted him to be slain in that sort he was</i>, I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not <reg orig="comit">commit</reg> treason against him in my undertaking, I am told he is dead long since; I have much <reg orig="wondred">wondered</reg> oftentimes to read of Flatterers, that have to those in power said, Sir you are like <em>C&aelig;sar</em>; when it would better <reg orig="becom">become</reg> them to be like <em>Timolion</em> at <em>Corinth</em>: to be like <em>C&aelig;sar</em> is in effect to say they deserve to be killed by <em>Brutus</em> as he was: by this <reg orig="smal">small</reg> work thou shalt see the picture of all Governments and Governors: if they be just and good thou mayest see how far they differ, thou mayest judge colours by their contrary, and if not contrary how near they are one unto another comparing, the lives of 12 <em>C&aelig;sars</em> I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> go through in the like manner, as is here undertaken in this on sheet: it shall perform the work intended in the <em>Observations on <reg orig="Aristotles">Aristotle's</reg> Politicks</em>, the which <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> within 3 <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> be published Observations on the first book <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> without news. Of this work one chap. of the Commentary in one half sheet and the news of these times in the other half sheet, shall be published on upon Tuesday, and another on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> weekly: the which thou mayest <reg orig="seperate">separate</reg>, and they will be two distinct Histories.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em> printed, and are to be sold by <em>R. Moon</em>, at the 7 Stars in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>:</p>
 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>