<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc162">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 162</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>Another Messenger with Letters from Holland, concerning the concluding of the peace between England and them, and the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of Deputies with the Ratifications thereof. An Ordinance of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, concerning Delinquents and their Estates. Several ships taken at Sea. The proceedings of the Army in Scotland, against the Highlanders, with their bold attempts, and the prisoners lately taken. With variety of other intelligence from several other parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> February 8. to <em>Wednesday</em> February 15. 1654.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, February 8.</head>

<p>The Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> (the day before had under consideration certain Letters and Credentials presented by two Agents from the Isle of Amiland in Holland, desiring, that they may be esteemed as Neuters.</p>

<p>They have many fisher boats belonging to that place, and some shipping, the names whereof they presented in writing, and certain marks, so that none may be deceived, but know them from any other. They plead that they have <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> been held a free State <pb n="1" />(having not, as they say, been subject to any <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>) and desire that they may be esteemed so for the time to come.</p>

<p>This being the day appointed for the entertaining of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector in the City of <em>London</em>, it was done in a very magnificent manner: The streets from <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall to Temple Bar were railed on both sides the way, and the <reg orig="Rayls">Rails</reg> covered with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg>, with store of great Flags and Streamers, bearing the Arms of the respective Companies: The 24 Companies in their Liveries about 11 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>, took their places within the <reg orig="Rayls">Rails</reg>, the Lord Mayor and Aldermen in their Robes, on Horseback went to meet his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> at Temple Bar: His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> came in his Coach from Whitehall, and in the Coach came along with him Major General Lambert, and the Lord President of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>: The Life Guard marched before him, and the <reg orig="Heraulds">Heralds</reg> followed, the Foot Officers were bare on each side his Coach, and 12 <reg orig="Foot men">Footmen</reg> in rich Liveries, two Pages before bare, General Whaley led up all the field Officers bravely mounted, and Commissary General Reynolds brought up the Rear, the Lord Mayor and Aldermen received His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> at Temple Bar, where his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> alighted out of his Coach and took horse: he was in a musk coloured suit richly <reg orig="imbroidered">embroidered</reg> with Gold: The Lord Mayor delivered up his sword, which was speedily <reg orig="re-delivered">redelivered</reg> to his Lordship, who rid bare before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall, where the Recorder made a congratulatory Speech: his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and Officers were royally entertained, the Lord Mayor sitting on his right, and the Lord Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> on his left hand, the rest that <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> at his Table were of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> and Officers of the Army: After dinner his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> was conducted into an upper Room, and there entertained by <pb n="2" />the Lord Mayor with a sumptuous banquet, this being done his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> knighted the Lord Mayor, and afterwards departed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Mr. <reg orig="Recorders">Recorder's</reg> Speech to the Lord Protector, upon Wednesday the 8 of February, 1653. being the day of his <reg orig="Highneess">Highness'</reg> Entertainment in London.</i></head>

<p>May it please your Highness, my Lord Protector, it hath been observed by some, That when Samuel offered sacrifice, he therefore reserved the shoulders for Saul, that he might know what was the weight of Government: the consideration of which made Maximilian affirm, That none who knew how heavy Diadems were, would stoop to take them up. <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> are like the Heavenly Bodies, much in veneration, but never in rest; and how can it be otherwise expected, when they are not made for themselves, or their own glory, but for the safety and good of Mankind: as in the natural, so in the civil world, great things being ordained to serve the less: We see the Sun by its beams serving the eye of the meanest <reg orig="Flie">Fly</reg>, as well as of the greatest Potentate. The Supremacy of <em>Satus Populi</em>, was the conclusion of the twelve Tables, and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be a prevalent <reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg> until the end of the world.</p>

<p>By thus much my Lord, you may perceive the dark side of this leading Cloud of Government; but if God vouchsafe assistance from those shoulders upon which the Government is laid, and put under his everlasting Arms, you <reg orig="wil">will</reg> see the bright side also, and thence receive encouragement. This support he is pleased to give, by letting Rulers know he is the Author of their power, and that from him they are to expect their Rule. The designation of Government, as to forms and persons, is an <reg orig="humane">human</reg> institution, and mutable, as things that are made, but Government itself<pb n="3" />, abstractly considered in its pure original, is of a divine Offspring, and can with no less difficulty be shaken, <reg orig="then">than</reg> those Vestigias, which being as relations tell us, upon the tops of some mountains, above the Clouds, can be disordered by wind and tempest, And for the Rule, the word, or reason of God in the Divine understanding, is the eternal Law of all things. But this being too deep a Well for <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> Bucket to draw out of, it pleased his infinite Goodness to let fall a <reg orig="Rivolet">Rivulet</reg> from this Source into the Creature; which leaving an impression in <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> understanding, we call the Law of Nature: But man having this honour, presently became of no understanding; his mind being clouded with passions and sins, had soon need of superadded helps, which God gave him by those other Laws fit for Government, and still gives a spirit for the framing such Municipal Laws, as are according to his will, and suitable to the good of the people. But when this was done, the best Laws without a Government, were no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> as the Sword behind the Ephod; and therefore Moses in his time, and other <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> in their time, must be as walking Laws, and Administrators of Justice.</p>

<p>We may conclude, my Lord, your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath experimented both these <reg orig="incouragements">encouragements</reg>, as being the spectator of some, and the subject of other great Revolutions which have happened in this Age, and Land of wonders: And not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> know, that the most high rules in the <reg orig="Kingdomes">Kingdoms</reg> of men, disposing them to whom he pleaseth; but also, that its not sufficient with the Princes of the Nations, to exercise dominion, which is the common Image of God, except there be also a share in the peculiar Image of his righteousness and holiness; they being Gods indeed, and after a peculiar manner, to whom the reason, or word of God so comes.</p>

<p>My Lord, there is one help more in Government, which God is pleased often to add to the rest, which is the giving in of the affections of the people, the solemnity of this day, wherein the Citizens of this great City appear in their several Companies, as so many Cities within the City, speaks much to this; they leave it to other Nations to salute their Rulers and Victorious Commanders, with the names of <em>C&aelig;sares</em> and <em>Imperatores</em>; and after Triumphs, to erect for them their <em><unclear>Arcus</unclear> Triumphales</em>: But if I mistake not, their end this day, is not any such outward pomp or glory, but that those who have been delivered together, might <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> together; and to <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> their desires, that the civil Sword might be as prosperous for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> ends, in the hand where it is placed, as the Military Sword hath been in the same hand.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>This City seldom goes along in <reg orig="publick">public</reg> actions: it was anciently called by <em>Stephanides</em>, the heart of the nation; and if the heart be in a <reg orig="Politick">Politic</reg> consideration, as it is in the natural, it will communicate life and spirits into the other members, by which means the whole body may unanimously contribute their <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to oppose the common enemy, and after all our distractions, see the Nation established upon the firm Basis of peace and <reg orig="righteousnesse">righteousness</reg>, which is the end of Government, and shall now be the end of my further troubling Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, Febr. 9.</head>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for the better ordering and disposing of the Estates under Sequestration.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector; by and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, that Josias <unclear>Bainers</unclear>, Edw. Winslow, Rich. Moor, Joh. Upton, Edw. Cary, and Rice Williams, Esq. Or any four of them, be, and are hereby constituted and ordained Commissioners for the managing, ordering, and disposing of the Estates of all Delinquents now <reg orig="sequestred">sequestered</reg>, or which shall be adjudged Delinquents, upon cases now depending, and of all Estates now under Sequestration for Recusancy. And that the said Commissioners, or any four of them, shall from and after Febr. 10. 1653. have power, and are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to manage, order, set, let, or dispose of all and every the said Estates, during such time as the same shall remain under Sequestration. Provided, no Lease thereof to be granted, exceed the term of one year: And that the whole Rents, Revenues and Profits of the said Sequestrations and <reg orig="Sequestred">Sequestered</reg> Estates, shall be paid in at <reg orig="Goldsmiths">Goldsmiths'</reg> Hall, to the hands of Rich. Sherwin and John Leech, Esqs. who are hereby constituted and appointed Treasurers of the said <reg orig="Receit">Receipt</reg>. And the said Commissioners are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> and required to call all Commissioners for Sequestrations, Treasurers, Receivers, and other persons employed by the former Commissioners for compounding, in the several Counties, to an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> for all and every sum and sums of money in their, or any of their hands, of the said <reg orig="Sequestred">Sequestered</reg> Estates, or any of them.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> February 10.</head>

<p>From Holland we hear; that the outward face of the affairs there, carry the countenance of resemblance of peace with England, and they talk of sending away another messenger, with an account how far all the Provinces have proceeded.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>Some Letters make mention of some <reg orig="shipwracks">shipwrecks</reg> by reason of the high winds at Sea on the 4 and 5 of this present <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>. The Irish taking advantage of the winter season, play their pranks in some parts of that Nation, but they may be shortly met with. </p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> February 11.</head>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Mackworth, <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the Town of Shrewsbury, is made one of his Highness <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. New Judges will very suddenly be made to ride this next Circuit.</p>

<p>There was little news this week from France, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some say the Prince of <unclear>Conti</unclear> is come in, and <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart is not yet gone from Paris; the titular Duke of York, hath been shrewdly shaken with so sore a spirit as an Ague, and is not yet rid of it; many young Lords of the Kingdom, both of the one religion, and the other do daily come to visit him. The Protestant Nobility have of late <reg orig="beene">been</reg> much respected, and preferred by the King of France, the Cardinal Mazarini no <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> repining at it.</p>

<p>By Letters from Scotland thus. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Daniel hath done good service not far from St. Johnstons, and taken nine Troopers well mounted, their Cornet being killed upon the place. Glencarn hath sent a terrible Letter to the Scots Troop in our Army, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> them with the utmost extremities, for the injuries received by them, and for the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of his Captain Lieutenant, who is his kinsman so ruinous is his resolution, that whosoever of their own nation, will not deliver up their men and horses to serve him in the war, are to have their families and themselves imprisoned, and their houses burned with unquenchable fire.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> February 13.</head>

<p>From Portsmouth they write, That our Fleet is yet near S. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> points, yet many Scouts are abroad. The Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath brought into Burlington, a Dutch man of War; this ship did usually <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> on that Coast, going and coming: The Captain and other Officers are carried to York <reg orig="Goal">Jail</reg>.</p>

<p>Letters from Holland do make mention, that they even make themselves sure there of a Peace with England, to which the sending back of some prisoners of which we had taken, and the continuance of our Fleet at St. <reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point, which might have <reg orig="allarum'd">alarmed</reg> them, doth make them to presume the more of it. I am informed of a Letter which advertiseth of seven ships gone lately with Arms from Holland to the Highlanders, but I much doubt the truth of it, by reason of the present overtures, and the hazard they should run by so doing. I made mention before of some ships taken by the Dutch from us: we have taken this week 17 ships from them, 11 whereof, some being Merchants, and some men of war, are very considerable.</p>

<p>It is further certified from Holland, that although the most of the Provinces have consented to the Articles of Agreement for the peace between England and themselves, yet Friezland stands off, and all the rest are under a cloud of <reg orig="Jealousie">Jealousy</reg>; for their <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are making ready with all the speed that may be, in which the Shipwrights by a strict command are so prophanely diligent, that they do work on Sunday, and all their whole Fleet will be ready to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth within these three weeks at the furthest. It is reported, that the Lord Brederode, and the Lord Opdam their Admiral, were to be sent hither, but the former hath excused himself by reason of his great age.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, February 14.</head>

<p>There is another Messenger come from Holland, who speaks very confidently of Peace, and <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That within a matter of 14 days, Deputies will be here from the respective Provinces; further affirming, that the Province which was most averse, hath now consented to the Articles which came from England, <i>This is good news if true at the last</i>. But there is yet some cause to doubt, if we consider, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> how they have served us before, but how they have played their game often in their Treaties with Spain.</p>

<p>On <reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> night last, or rather on Sunday morning about three or four of the clock, (the watch rising too early) Mr. Hancock at the Greyhound Tavern in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>, was robbed of about 50 pound in Plate, and himself wounded in his bed. There were 9 or 10 of the Thieves, who all escaped at the present, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable Justice will overtake them.</p>

<p>There came Letters from some part of our Fleet, which <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that we have taken two French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, and a Dutch vessel laden with salt and other commodities.</p>

<p>The Letters this last Post from Scotland say, that the Lord Athol and <unclear>Seafort</unclear>, are joined together with their forces, and that they make many bold attempts upon the English, and the English are as gallant as may be in daring them to fight; but what is done by the Highlanders are properly deeds of <reg orig="darknesse">darkness</reg> and are principally executed in the night, yet do we <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> take many of them, and shall shortly drive them further off and hunt them out of their Dens into the Rocks and Mountains for shelter; we have parties go out <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> to find them out, twenty prisoners were brought into St Johnstons the 5 of this instant, which is all at present that we have from thence.</p>

<p>From several parts beyond the seas we hear, That the Turkish Fleet at Constantinople is retreated; the General Bashaw having made his peace, by presenting the young <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> a young Virgin of extraordinary beauty. The Diet at Regensburgh is <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> upon the examination of the Oath given to the new King of the Romans, and regulating of the privy <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, that of the Empire, next, to regulate the Courts of Justice, and so to conclude the Diet.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>