<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn210">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 210</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p>From <em>Monday</em>, Decemb. 12. to <em>Monday</em>, Decemb.19. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em> Decemb. 12.</head>

<p>This day by Letters from <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, Dec 2. <em>Glencairn</em> and the rest removed from their Fastness in <em>Monteith</em> towards <em>Broad-Albin</em> Tuesday last, upon an <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg> given them by a garrison of ours 8 or 19 mile hence, <em>Lorn</em> &amp; <em>Kenmore</em> are certainly at a great difference, and some <reg orig="conteste">contest</reg> <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> <em>Glengary</em> and <em>Glencairn</em> for the Chief Conduct, <em>Glengary</em> looking upon himself as the better <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, and stouter Man; they talk of setting up the <reg orig="Stantart">Standard</reg> at the Head of <em>Lough Tay</em> very shortly; and then they will go on very hotly with their Levies; in the mean time the Commander in Chief is using all possible ways for the securing the Forces here, and putting them into such<pb n="1" /> a posture as may oppose the Enemy, and that no means may be left unattempted for preventing the Country from <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with this rude rabble, he hath <reg orig="conveened">convened</reg> the Gentlemen of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> shires in these parts, some of which have subscribed the enclosed Engagement under hand and seal, and the Gentlemen of this shire have generally engaged also, That neither themselves, nor any of the People under their power, shall or will act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to the prejudice of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, or their Forces, nor any way aid, assist, or correspond in persons, <reg orig="Councells">Counsels</reg>, Advice, or any other means, the Highlanders, and others now in arms, or who hereafter shall be in arms against the Commonwealth! By this course the greatest part of the Gentlemen are engaged in Honour, not to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with or assist this party, which is the most probable way to prevent this growing <reg orig="evill">evil</reg>.</p>

<p>I do hereby oblige me, my Heirs, Executors, That I shall and will live peaceably under the Command of the Commonwealth of England, and that I, or any other under my Command, shall not act directly or indirectly to the prejudice of the Commonwealth aforesaid, in <reg orig="ayding">aiding</reg> and assisting the Highlanders, and others now in <reg orig="armer">armour</reg>, and who hereafter shall be in <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> against the said Commonwealth in person, <reg orig="Councell">Counsel</reg>, Advice, <reg orig="Meanes">Means</reg>, or any other manner of way whatsoever, under the penalty of forfeiture of Life and Estate, And to be proceeded against as the Parliament of the Commonwealth, and those, <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> by them shall appoint; <em>In Witnesse</em> where of I have subscribed the same at the 28 day of <em>November</em>, 1653.</p>

<p>By the last from <em><reg orig="Stockholme">Stockholm</reg></em>: The Queen with all her Court is now at <em>Ypsall</em>, and from thence her <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> doth intend to visit the Copper Mines: The Lord high Treasurer and other nobles being newly returned hither of their <reg orig="visite">visit</reg> to the Prince <em>Pulatine</em> Heir of this Crown. From <em>Warsovia</em>: The common report<pb n="2" /> that the Enemy was within ten leagues of our Army hath proved false, it being no more but a design of the <em>Tartars</em> and <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em> to relieve the old Hospodar <em>Basiliw</em>: and the King upon a survey of his Army, hath found the same to be <reg orig="fourty">forty</reg> five thousand strong, besides the Gentry and Volunteers; and by the relation of some prisoners, the <em>Tartars</em> but of ten thousand, whereof the most were horse, who were at the command of the old Hospodar aforesaid. From <em>Vienna</em>: The Earl of <em>Bouchaim</em> commander in chief of the Imperial Armies in <em>Hungaria</em> is come back to this City, but first he has secured all the <reg orig="frontiere">frontier</reg> places in that Country. From <em>Regensburgh</em>: The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath made known to the <reg orig="Diett">Diet</reg> upon several Articles; but nothing hath as yet been agreed upon concerning the differences that yet remain with the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>. From <em>Cullen</em>: We have been for many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> disturbed in our trade by our <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg>, who doth still go on in stopping the free passage of the river. The <em>Lorrain</em> forces do begin again their old trade, and so to plunder about <em>Aquisgranum</em>, but we hear the City of <em>Liege</em> is seeking to oppose them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday December 13</em>.</head>

<head level="3"><i>Advertisements to the Garrisons, and Navy, &amp;c</i></head>

<p>The Parliament on <em>Saturday</em> last returned the Debate upon the Report made from the Committee of Tithes, which is as follows:</p>

<p>1. That it be represented to the Parliament as the best way for ejecting ignorant, <reg orig="prophane">profane</reg> and scandalous Ministers; that Commissioners be sent from hence into all the Counties, divided into six circuits (besides <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>) three Commissioners into each circuit, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with four or six in every County (and each Riding in <em><reg orig="Yorkeshire">Yorkshire</reg></em> to be as a County) and that in every County the said persons or five of them (two of the Commissioners sent from hence being always present) be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to eject all Ministers (of that County) that are not of good behaviour, and holy in conversation, or that are not apt and able to teach, or in teaching hold not forth the faithful<pb n="3" /> Word; or be not <reg orig="dillgent">diligent</reg>; or labour not in the Word and Doctrine, or be greedy or <unclear><!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> and be also <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to settle god <unclear>!-- approx. 10 characters --></unclear> persons to preach the Gospel in all void places, <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> two or three Parishes together, so that none be above three miles from the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> meeting place.</p>

<p>2. That it be presented to the Parliament, That Dr. <em>Arrowsmith</em>: Colonel <em>Goff</em>, Major <em><reg orig="Hains">Haines</reg></em>, Mr. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Owen</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas <reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em>, Mr. <em>Ben</em> of Dorchester, Mr <em>Fairclough</em> the elder, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, Mr. Caryl, Mr. <em>Stephen Marshal</em>, Mr. <em>Worthington</em>, Mr. <em>Turner</em>, Mr. <em>Tomes</em>, Mr. <em>Martin Holbeck</em>, Mr. <em>Cradock</em>, Mr <em>Jessey</em>, Mr. <em>Arthur Barnardiston</em>, Mr. <em>William Greenhill</em>, Colonel <em>Campfiell</em>, Mr. <em>Dyke</em>, Mr. <em>Stalham</em>, may be sent Commissioners by three in a circuit for ejecting and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> Ministers, according to the Rules prescribed.</p>

<p>3. That all such as are or shall be approved for <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Preachers of the Gospel in the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> meeting-places, shall have and enjoy the maintenance already <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> by Law, and such other encouragement as the Parliament already hath appointed, or hereafter shall appoint: And that where any scruple payment of Tithes, the three next <reg orig="Iustices">Justices</reg> of the Peace, or two of them, shall upon complaint call the parties concerned before them, and by the <reg orig="Oathes">Oaths</reg> of <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> Witnesses, shall duly apportion the value of the said Tithes; to be paid either in money or Land, by them to be set out according to the said value, to be held and <reg orig="injoyned">enjoined</reg> by him that was to have the said Tithes; and in case such approved value be not duly paid or enjoyed according to the order of the said <reg orig="Iustices">Justices</reg>, the Tithes shall be paid in kind, and shall be recovered in any Court of Record.</p>

<p>4. That upon hearing and considering what had been offered to the Committee touching propriety in Tithes, of Incumbents, Rectors, Possessors of Donatives or propriate Tithes. It is the opinion of this Committee, and resolved to be reported to the Parliament, that the said persons have a <reg orig="legall">legal</reg> propriety in Tithes.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>The House having spent several days in debate of the whole Report, and especially of the first of the four parts thereof; and the Question being put, That this House doth agree with the first Clause of the Report, it passed in the Negative, And the House adjourned till Monday morning. When meeting, it was moved in the House, That the sitting of this Parliament any longer as now constituted; will not be for the good of the Commonwealth; and that therefore it was requisite to deliver up unto the Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Cromwell</em> the Powers which they received from him; and that Motion being seconded by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Members, the House arose, and the Speaker with many Members of the House, departed out of the House to <em>Whitehall</em>, where they, the greater number of the members sitting in Parliament, did by a writing under their hands resign unto his Excellency their said Powers, and Mr. Speaker attended with the Members, did present the same to his Excellency accordingly.</p>

<p>His Excellency the Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Cromwell</em> and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers met this day, at which meeting, some things were transacted in order to a <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the Government of this Nation for the future, whereof more anon.</p>

<p><em>Newcastle, December</em> 3. There have been some Malignants at Fairs Northward, who have bought Horses, and marched in small parties two or three together, towards <em>Scotland</em>. Col. <em>Woogan</em> was in <em>Northumberland</em>, and some others with him, at a Fair there, and are gone towards Scotland. It seems some men are of that desperate fortune, that they will venture upon anything. Indeed those that are there have gotten something by Robbing, but they may chance pay as dear for it as other Rogues.</p>

<p><em>Berwick, December</em> 2. On Wednesday last there was a part of about 16 or 18 horse of the Enemies at a town called <em>Chernside</em>, within four or five miles of <em>Berwick</em>, and there being a Fair there, divers <em>Berwick</em> men, and other Gentlemen went thither about their
<reg orig="businesse">business</reg>; and they were seized upon, their<pb n="5" /> horses, and best of their
<reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg>, moneys, and what could be taken from them they were stripped of, and then let go again. A party of them also seized on two <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that went along towards that place to assist the Collectors in the gathering of the Sesse, they were disarmed, and then discharged, those horsemen that thus plunder are exceeding well mounted; they have taken <reg orig="severall">several</reg> good Horses out of the Marsh; the Gentleman which commands them is said to be one <em>Meldrum</em>. There are also about 140 horse in the Marsh, and in <em>Tividale</em> under Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, raising both men and money.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> the 17th of <em>December, new stile</em>. By the last Letters from <em>Languedoc</em> we hear the glad news of the relieving of <em><unclear>Kosa</unclear></em> in the County of <em>Roussillan</em>, where our Convoy being <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> without any opposition of the Enemy: thereupon our General resolved to fight with them wheresoever he met with them, and hearing by some of our Scouts that they were <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to meet us, being <reg orig="onely">only</reg> on the one side of the River: thereupon the Lieutenant <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> with the main <reg orig="bodie">body</reg> of the <reg orig="Armie">Army</reg> <reg orig="foarded">forded</reg> over, and fell upon the <reg orig="Enemie">Enemy</reg> with so much heat, that they routed them, having slain upon the place four hundred men, and taken Eleven hundred prisoners, whereof a great many Officers, with all the baggage that was in those Quarters.</p>

<p>From St. <em>Menebold</em> we hear, That the Ordnance which was upon the five Batteries that were at the Siege of this place, have been all safe got up into this Town, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one which <reg orig="sunke">sunk</reg> into a Ditch, and so is like to remain <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the next Summer.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> from <em>Marseilles</em> that there is a great preparation of Ships and other Vessels at <em>Toulon</em>, towards the prosecuting of the great <reg orig="designe">design</reg> of the new Conquest of <em>Naples</em>; the Duke of <em>Guise</em> is very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in furthering the same enterprise: it beloveth those that are concerned therein, to <reg orig="susse">suss</reg> those flames before they are too much kindled: there is also preparations made of Land forces about <em><reg orig="Lions">Lyons</reg></em>,<pb n="6" /> where is the general Rendezvous of <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear>: The divisions grow higher in <em>Avignon</em> <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> the Gentry and the Citizens, and generally those parts are much disquieted: only we are put in hopes that by the approach of the Court the next Spring, that all our <reg orig="heavie">heavy</reg> <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg> will be taken off, or at least much lightened.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Orleans</em> is still at his house near <em>Blois</em>, and will not at any rate be invited to return to the Court. The 13th instant the King with all the Court, and the chief of this City went to the <reg orig="Cathredall">Cathedral</reg> Church, where was sung the <em>Te Deurn</em> for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> safe return, and the taking of the town of St. <em>Menebold</em>.</p>

<p>This Evening the <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> brother made escape out of Newgate, but is since retaken, and he with others close prisoners in Newgate, in order to their <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg>.</p>

<p>This also was published from the Council of State, <em>viz</em>. The Council of State taking notice of the Tumultuous and Barbarous Actings at the <em>New-Exchange</em> in the <em>Strand</em>, in the County of <em>Middlesex</em>, upon the 21 and 22 of <em>November</em> last past. The same being accompanied with the drawing of Swords, discharging of Pistols, and such other high <reg orig="Misdemeanors">Misdemeanours</reg> as are scarce to be <reg orig="paralleld">paralleled</reg> by the actings of any persons living under the protection of a Civil Government; and which, in the effects thereof, produced not only a very great and notorious violation of the <reg orig="Publique">Public</reg> Peace but also the murdering of one, and the assaulting, wounding, and affrighting of many other of the people of this Nation, pursuing their ordinary callings and occasions: And for as much as the said <em>Exchange</em> is a place of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Resort and Trade, the Council have therefore thought it necessary hereby to declare their resentment of those proceedings, and their just displeasure against the same. And as they intend <unclear><!-- approx half a line --></unclear> the Offenders to the intent the like evils may be better prevented in time to come, they do hereby strictly <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> <unclear>in the charge</unclear>, That no person or persons of what quality soever, do presume at the said <em>Exchange</em> or any other like <reg orig="publick">public</reg> place, to occasion,<pb n="7" /> encourage or abet, any <unclear>tumultuous</unclear> meetings or <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> of the Civil Peace, by drawing there or in any other such place any Sword or other weapon, discharging, presenting, or teasing any Gun or Pistol, or firing of Powder in <reg orig="Granadoes">Grenades</reg>; or in any otherwise whatsoever. Of which command it will be expected, That all persons whatsoever, take notice, and demean themselves accordingly, upon peril of being reputed and dealt withal as disturbers of the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Peace, whereof a very strict account shall be taken. And all Justices of the Peace and other <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Ministers, are required carefully to perform their duties in this behalf <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear> also to use their endeavour, to prevent and restrain all immodest and <reg orig="unhandsom">unhandsome</reg> <reg orig="demeanors">demeanours</reg> of such as shall resort to the said <em>Exchange</em>, that so not just cause of offence may be given to sober minds, nor <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> there acted <reg orig="dishonorable">dishonourable</reg> to Religion or the Nation. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Thurloe</em> Sec.</p> 

<p><i>All persons who are Adventurers for lands in <em>Ireland</em> are desired to take notice, That the Committee for Claims for lands in <em>Ireland</em> have appointed Thursday the 12 of <em>January</em> next <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, to be a day of Lottery at <em>Grocers-hall</em> <em>London</em>, both for Provinces and Counties, and Thursday the 19 of the same <em>January</em> to be a Lottery for Counties for all such Adventurers who have made their choice in Provinces: and after the said 19 of <em>January</em> the said Committee intend to sit three mornings in a week, viz. <reg orig="Tuesdayes">Tuesdays</reg>, <reg orig="Thursdayes">Thursdays</reg> and <reg orig="Saturdayes">Saturdays</reg>, for preparing Certificates for such Adventurers as have, or shall, by that time draw for their Lotts.</i></p>
<p>W. Tibbs</p>

<p><unclear>Whereas it ere</unclear> was one <em>Anthony <reg orig="Knoles">Knowles</reg></em>, aged about <unclear>70</unclear> <reg orig="yeers">years</reg>, a <unclear>Western</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear>, that did live in the City of <em><unclear>Kilkenny</unclear></em> in Ireland, before the Wars, in the year 1645: It is desired that the said <em>Anthony <reg orig="Knoles">Knowles</reg></em> be now living, and may be found, that then there be speedy <unclear><reg orig="setled">settled</reg></unclear> thereof given unto Mr. <em>George Woodford</em> at the Rose and Crown in <unclear>Church-lane</unclear> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <unclear>Doyghen</unclear> in London and upon certain intelligence thereof, the <unclear>person</unclear> that gives it shall have 40 shillings for his pains, and the said <em><reg orig="Knoles">Knowles</reg></em> be well <reg orig="recompenced">recompensed</reg>: it being for no other end or purpose but to <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> his knowledge in a <unclear>state now depending</unclear> in <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear>.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday, Decemb</em>. 14</head>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Excester">Exeter</reg>, Decemb</em>. 7. We have intelligence that the Hound, a Man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> of the States, hath sent into <em>Plymouth</em> a ship belonging to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and bound home from <em><reg orig="Lisborn">Lisbon</reg></em> with salt and sugar, burthen 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>; and that Captain <em>Marten</em> Commander of the <reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg>, who with some other <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> and ships, doth ply in the mouth of the <reg orig="channell">channel</reg>, hath sent into <em>Plymouth</em> two ships, who pretend of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, and bound thither, the one is <reg orig="foure">four</reg> hundred<reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, 14 Guns; the other 100 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, both laden with Sugar and <reg orig="Oyles">Oils</reg>, to a great value.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth Decemb</em>. 9. For News here is little, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> there was a Frenchman brought in this day, that hath two &amp; twenty Fats of Bever, and some pot-ashes, which came from <em>Canady</em>.</p>

<p>Another since the former from <em>Plymouth</em>, intimates a sad accident <reg orig="befaln">befallen</reg> one of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships called the <em>Sussex </em><reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, which was blown up by her own powder, and about 50 men. She was a gallant <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Rotterdam Decemb.</em> 12 <em>stilo novo</em>. This week affords little, all our gaping being after the Treaty; for want of <reg orig="stuffe">stuff</reg> I will <reg orig="entertaine">entertain</reg> you this <reg orig="weeke">week</reg> with <reg orig="aery">aerie</reg> fancy of some of the great Ones here of the <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> party, who are dividing the <reg orig="Brares">Brare's</reg> skin before the beast be killed; They suppose that <em>France</em> and <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> may at length agree, and that then they will some reflections upon your growing Commonwealth; and will so order the matter, that the D. of <em>Lorain</em> shall exchange his Country for <em>Ireland</em>; the Prince of <em>Condi</em> is to be made King of <em>Scotland</em>; and he of great Britain to be content with <em>England</em> alone; and thus will these three Entitles be provided for, and that power which remaining united doth now prove so formidable to all its neighbours will by this <reg orig="Tipartite">Tripartite</reg> division be <reg orig="rendred">rendered</reg> <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> considerable. In the mean time <em>Middleton</em> is making all the <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> he can to transport from hence great store of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and Ammunition into <em>Scotland</em>, to the assistance of the Highlanders,<pb n="9" /> who have declared for <em>Charles Stuart</em> (as we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg>) and want nothing but <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> to beat the English out of <em>Scotland</em>, who are not able to keep the field; but are <reg orig="faine">fine</reg> to <reg orig="keepe">keep</reg> in their Garrisons, where for want of <reg orig="materialls">materials</reg> the Highlanders can do no good upon them; and if you and we do not agree, we shall furnish them with enough from hence to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> you work at home. Here is a general report that our Commissioners are returning from England, and that there is no <reg orig="likelyhood">likelihood</reg> of a peace, and that you are making great preparations for the war, which causeth the like here.</p>

<p>Yesterday the <reg orig="Corps">Corpse</reg> of that courageous Sea commander <em>John Van Galan</em> was to be <reg orig="buired">buried</reg> at Amsterdam in great state, by order of their high and mighty Lordships. <reg orig="Tis">It is</reg> said that the framer of our <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> ship here, hath <reg orig="out-sript">outstripped</reg> his <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> in <reg orig="nimblenesse">nimbleness</reg>, and is run away; though it be yet but said so, I fear it will prove so in the end.</p>

<p>The marching of our Troopers towards the Lorainers hath caused them to withdraw from off our Borders, once again.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday Decem</em>. 15.</head>

<p><em>Paris Decemb</em>. 20. 1653; the main work to do now at Court and in this City is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in making great preparations for the keeping of their great Feast of the Nativity of our Saviour, which beginneth the next <em>Thursday</em>; The King <unclear>smee</unclear> his return with his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, hath been <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> in the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Winter Quarters for the Army, which is not quarter in Villages as formerly, thereby to become burthen some to the people, but they are to be quartered in the <reg orig="frontiere">frontier</reg> <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>, where some allowance will be made <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg> for their lodgings and firings, and care taken that the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> might receive their pay to buy provisions for their <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>. The <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> de <em>Foucauld</em> and others, who lately are returned into the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Obedience, came to this City, this being done by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the <em><unclear>Ammistia</unclear></em>, therefore they were presented to His Majesty, who received their thankfulness,<pb n="10" /> , and other submissions The last Tuesday arrived here the Marquis of <em><unclear>Viguabo</unclear></em>, to bring the particulars of the Defeat given to the Spaniards in <em><unclear>Rousillon</unclear></em>, which you have heard in my last, the design of his Majesty to go into <em>Prounce</em>, continueth still, it being <reg orig="easierly">easily</reg> followed by the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, who worketh his own ends therein, as well as the good of the Kingdom, which he doth so much pretend; this doth something thwart the project of the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador, who for many months since hath <reg orig="droven">driven</reg> on the design of making a Match between the King and his <reg orig="masters">master's</reg> daughter, with whom he proffers to give many millions of <reg orig="golde">gold</reg>. The Protestant party in Languedoc and other Countries <reg orig="adjicent">adjacent</reg>, are in expectation of a <reg orig="favorable">favourable</reg> answer to be given to their many and great <reg orig="grivances">grievances</reg> lately brought from them by the Baron of <em>Rou-vigni</em>, who (as I hear) hath presented them, but as yet no answer returned to them, but was promised fair to have it within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The common report is, that the Chamber Alders shall be put down, it being very much exclaimed against, and I- hear not they have done or acted <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of late: Our Archbishop is still very sick, and also his Nephew the Cardinal <em>de Retz</em>, who doth yet <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> a close prisoner, by reason that the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> will not be able to bend him to his Italian <reg orig="humor">humour</reg>. The News from <em>Alsatia</em> are various, some will have the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em> to have made his agreement with the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, for<pb n="11" /> the delivering up Brisack, and other places under his Command to him, but others affirm this to be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a plot of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> to spread such reports, thereby to render him odious to the King and the whole nation.</p>

<p>By the last news from <em>Naples</em> thus: The vice King having notice that the Earl of <em>Castriglio</em> our new vice King was arrived at St. <em>Poselippo</em> with his Wife, and a great Train sent one of his high Officers, to <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> him, and make him the usual complement: the next day he was visited by the Cardinal <em>Filmarini</em>, with the rest of the Nobles, both spiritual and temporal: The Duke de Tirranova, who is to be Ambassador in ordinary at Rome, is also come to this City.</p> 

<p>From <em>Venice</em>: The Turkish Army is partly at Delo, in the <reg orig="Archipelag">Archipelago</reg>, and the remainder at <em>Scio</em>; and the General Bashaw being commanded from the supreme power at Constantinople, to come thither with his Fleet, he hath made his excuse, and sent it by an express in writing.</p>

<p>From <em>Milan</em>: The <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> de Carnelne our Governor, having agreed to a conference with the General of the French Army: there being agreed between both parties, a cessation of all acts of hostility: which being ended, our said Governor came to this City, being accompanied with all the high Officers of the Army; and having returned back to the Army, will have a special care to observe the motions of the French Army.</p>

<p>From <em>Turin</em>: We have news at present, that the Cardinal <reg orig="Macchiavelli">Machiavelli</reg>, and of the <reg orig="Arch Bishop">Archbishop</reg> of Feimo. The Senate is now preparing a Palace for the reception of the <reg orig="Counte">Count</reg> de Ognate, late vice King of Naples: but yet his coming is not certain, by reason that his Secretary hath sent letters, that he intends to take shipping at Leghorn, and so go directly for Spain.</p>

<p>There hath not passed of late any considerable action between both Armies.</p><pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><em>Friday &amp; Saturday</em> 16 &amp; 17. Decemb.</head>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Decemb. 9. thus. Since my last Intelligence is come, that Kenmore is marched into the South with some few Foot, and sevenscore Horse, <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> is gone into his own Country with 80 Horse, to keep in the Castle of Blair, that so he may with more liberty take up his Levies there. Kinoule is to raise a Regiment in Barchlaush, and Cooper in Angus &amp; Ramsay (who lately brought sevenscore Horse to them, and is returned again) to be his Lieut. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>. Lane not yet come to them, some jealousies lie upon him, that he is not so forward as he might. <reg orig="Mac naughton">McNaughton</reg> is also somewhat could in the work, so that <reg orig="ne">no</reg> help is come from them as yet.</p>

<p>Glencairne hath sent out Warrants to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Towns, for very great proportions of Cloth, Boots, <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, <em>&amp;c</em>. He sent for as much Cloth as would <reg orig="cloath">clothe</reg> 150 Foot <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>: together, with as much <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> and <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg> as will furnish the same number, each of them with two shirts and a pair of <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg>, and fifteen hundred pound Scotch <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, threatens them, that if they delay to give obedience, he will exalt the same by force.</p>

<p>The last week a party of fourscore of these broken people, took away 7 or 8 good Horses from the Earl of <reg orig="Weems">Weem's</reg> house in <reg orig="Fyfe">Fife</reg>, and a party of 4 Rogues came into the Laird of <reg orig="Womats">Womat's</reg> House 3 or 4 miles from Leith, and <reg orig="stob'd">stabbed</reg> an Englishman, who was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by the Commissioners to gather in the Rents of his <reg orig="Coal-pits">Coal pits</reg> by which we may perceive what usage we might expect, if we were at their mercy.</p>

<p>By a letter intercepted from one of their own party thus. All our <reg orig="Commission'd">Commissioned</reg> Officers are going now to their several Localities for Levies (which was not till now determined upon) both of Horses and Foot the Earl of <reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses in Perthshire, and the whole Foot thereof: Kinoule hath the Horses of the shire of Angus and Mernes: Glengary is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses out of <reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg>, Sutherland, <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg> and Murray, and to be Commander in chief of the Foot <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> there.<pb n="13" /> Kenmore is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> the Horses of the shire of Aberdeen. Col. <reg orig="Blakader">Blackadder</reg> of Tulliallen is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> in a part of the shire of Fife, Sir Mungo Murray left us two nights, being discontented for not getting <reg orig="Locallity">Locality</reg> on the North side of Forth, he was and is Gentleman Quartermaster, and is again reconciled, and is to have <reg orig="Sterlingshire">Stirlingshire</reg> for a <reg orig="Locallity">Locality</reg>, for <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> the Horses there.</p>

<p>We are now about 1000 good well armed resolute Foot, and 500 Horse, the Riders are singularly good, they and the Horses are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> ill equipaged, Saddles and Bridles that are good, are rare here, I have sent you a purse-penny. I <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> that there be not a word of the other, this is all, I remain,</p>

<p>Pool Decemb. 9. Here hath not presented any intelligence worthy of your <reg orig="cognizance">cognisance</reg>. About 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since, Captain Green Commander of a private man of War, brought into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> a prize, pretending to be of Dunkirk, she hath about 114 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of French Wine on board, came from <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg>, the Master is a Scotchman, put in as is supposed, for colour only, which with other circumstances, give great expectation, that she will prove a prize.</p>

<p>This day the same Captain Green hath brought in another Vessel, called the Gront pot, she <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> <reg orig=" her self "> herself </reg> of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, the Masters name is Steven van Collen, she hath about 70 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of French Wine and some Ginger, its believed she will also prove prize.</p><pb n="14" />

<p>From Dover the 14 Decemb. we hear by one come this morning from Deal, that Gen. Monk and his squadron were safely <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg> into the Downs: there are several ships gone by this week, bound for London, some come from the Canaries <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with wines, and one from Masago, whose loading is all fruit: there is a Dutch <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with wines, taken by a private man of War, belonging to London, whose loading is all White wines.</p>

<p>The late Parliament having upon the dissolution delivered up the power which they received from his Excellency at their first sitting by a writing under their Hands and Seal, his Excellency thereupon called a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, and advised with other persons of Interest in the Nation, how this great burthen of governing <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, with the Armies therein, and Navy at Sea <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> by whom; who after several <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> seeking of God, and advising therein. It was resolved that a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of godly, able and discreet persons should be named, consisting of 21. And that his Excellency should be chosen <em>Lord Protector</em> of these Nations. In pursuance thereof, several persons of <unclear>eminence</unclear> and worth, are already made choice of to be of the said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> which are not fit to be mentioned at this time. And on Friday last his Excellency came down to Westminster, and was installed <em>Lord Protector of the three Nations</em>, the manner whereof was thus.</p>

<p>His Excellency about one of the clock in the <reg orig="after noon">afternoon</reg> came from <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em> to <em>Westminster</em>, to the Chancery Court, attended by the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seale of England, Barons of the Exchequer, and judges in their Robes, after them, the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> Aldermen, and Recorder of the City of London, in their Scarlet Gowns; then came his Excellency attended with many of the chief Officers of the Army,<pb n="15" /> a <reg orig="chaire">chair</reg> of State being set in the said Court of Chancery, His Excellency stood on the left hand thereof uncovered, till a large writing in Parchment, in the nature of an Oath, was read; there being the power with which his Excellency was invested, and how His Excellency is to govern the three Nations, which His Excellency accepted of, and subscribed in the face of the Court, and immediately hereupon sat <reg orig="downe">down</reg> covered in the said <reg orig="chaire">chair</reg>; the Lords Commissioners then delivered up the Great Seale of England to His Excellency, and the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> his Sword and Cap of Maintenance, al which His Excellency returned <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> to them again: The Court then rose, and His Excellency was attended back as aforesaid, to the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg>-House in White-Hall, the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> uncovered, carrying the Sword before the Protector all the way, and coming into the Banqueting House, and exhortation was made by M. <em>Lockier</em> after which the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg>, Aldermen, and Judges departed.</p>

<hr />

<p>Upon the 13 of Decemb. instant, there was <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> out of the Stable of Mr. <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> at the Swan in Bartway in the County of <unclear>Harsford</unclear>, a <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> <unclear><reg orig="Bey">Bay</reg></unclear> <unclear><!-- approx 8 characters --></unclear> 15 handful high with white upon one of his Feet behind, a brand on his near shoulder, scarce to be seen, with <unclear>very</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 12 characters --></unclear> upon one side <unclear>of his face</unclear>, about 7 years of age: <unclear>If any man shall who</unclear> give notice of him to Mr. Charles Everard at the <unclear>Starry</unclear> in <unclear>Lumber street</unclear> London, or to Mr. <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear>, at the sign of the Hogs Head in <unclear>Norwich</unclear>, he shall have <unclear><!-- 3 characters approx. --></unclear> for his pains or if he bring the Horse to either of the aforementioned places shall have five pound.</p>

<p>Tow Mares lost from <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> in <unclear>Ayr</unclear> upon Thursday at night being Decemb. 16. The one being a sorrel with two feathers in her neck and a saddle spot of the far side and two <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear>, one on the <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> of, and the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> to the <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> <unclear>high</unclear>, with a <unclear>bit</unclear> of white on the fore leg behind next the foot-lock. The other being a <unclear>hey</unclear>, with a black <unclear>list</unclear> down the back, <unclear>bob</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> and <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> <unclear>the near side</unclear>, if you hear of any such, send word to Mr. Edw: East, Watch-maker, dwelling in <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> against S. <unclear>Drastaxs</unclear> Church in Fleet-street. And you shall have 20 sh for your pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>