<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiurn218">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Perfect Diurnall of Passages, Issue 218</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">The Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg></head>
<head level="2">OF SOME</head>
<head level="2">PASSAGES and PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="3">Of, and in relation to, the</head>
<head level="2">ARMIES</head>
<head level="2">IN</head>
<head level="2">ENGLAND, IRELAND, &amp; SCOTLAND.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Licensed according to the direction of the late Act for Printing.</head>
<hr />
<p><em>From Monday</em> February. 6. to <em>Monday</em>, February. 13. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>Francis Leach</em>, And <em>E. Griffin</em> in the <reg orig="Old-baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Beginning Monday</em>, February 6</head>

<p>This day came an Ambassador from the Great Duke of <em>Tuscany</em> to to congratulate his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>Two Agents also made their <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> to his Highness, from the Lord of the Isle of <em>Amiland</em> in <em>Holland</em>, about 9 English miles long, and some 3 or 4 broad, having upon it about 450 houses, to desire that they may be esteemed as Neutrals; and they have brought with them credentials, and a List of the Names of all their ships and Fisher boats, of which only four are Merchant ships, the rest Fisher boats belonging to that Island, and they have delivered in also the marks of the said ships, that so none may deceive us by<pb n="1" /> seeking for protection in their names, and they desire to be accounted as a Free state, having not been hitherto subject (as is pretended) to any Country.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> 4 <em>Febr</em>. Our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> towards the Lands-end have done very good service of late in relieving sundry vessels and <unclear>ships</unclear> that were taken by the <em>Brest</em> men. A ship of above a hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> with some Iron guns in her, was stranded not far from <em>Dalkeith</em>, whose lading was Salt, and French built; she is <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> by the Vice-admiral of this County for a wrack. A <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> stories are raised, (and daily discoursed of) upon the poor people, that go by the name of Witches in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, I think 20 are already committed, as suspected, and more are daily detected; but the Lord deliver us from <reg orig="blood-guiltiness">blood guiltiness</reg> in this kind, our Manufacture here hath a quick vent upon the hopes of peace with the <em>Dutch</em>. I am glad to hear the <em>Swedes</em> are so <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> to us, and hope, that if they be hearty, we may chastise the <em>Danes</em> and <em>Dutch</em> <reg orig="incase">in case</reg> they juggle with us.</p>

<p> <em>Dalkeith</em>, 31 <em>Jan</em>. Sir upon the march of Col. <em>Morgan</em> from Aberdeen, the enemy <reg orig="hastned">hastened</reg> their march out of <em><reg orig="Murriland">Murrayland</reg></em> towards <em>Ross</em>, and the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, so that Col. <em>Morgan</em> returned back to <em>Aberdeen</em>, but Major <em><reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg></em> Cornet with a party of that Regiment, took <em>Glencarn's</em> Captain Lieutenant, and 5 Horsemen, and sent them to <em>Innerness</em>. There being a small party of Scotchmen who have formerly done good service in a smaller party, the Commander in chief gave them encouragement to raise about 40 horse, with which they have more advantage to come upon the enemy by their Scotch tone, than our Forces have. Saturday last this party fell upon the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> guards, upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Angus</em>, and killed the first Scout, and went on and charged a guard of theirs, and killed 3 or 4, and then fell into another quarter, took a Captain Lieut. and a Cornet, and 150 others prisoners, with 20 horse, and killed 9 or 10, and 2 or 3 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before Cornet <em><reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em> (who is Cornet to that party) sent in a Captain and another Horseman prisoners to <em>Dundee</em>, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> much resolution in the several charges given the Enemy.</p>

<p>By the last Letters from <em>Stockholm</em> thus: A <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Minister is<pb n="2" /> come hither from <em>Muscovia</em>, having a Train of about Twenty persons; his chief Message is to give her Majesty notice, how the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> his Master doth intend to declare open Wars against <em>Poland</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Warsovia</em>: At last there is an agreement made between this Crown, and the <em>Tartars</em> and <em><reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg></em>, the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg>, in regard there is no security for the performance of the same, there being no deeds passed between the two parties, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> verbal promises; which doth make many fear this to be but a plain dissimulation. <reg orig="Neverthelesse">Nevertheless</reg> the King is come to this City, and hath given order for the Army to take up their Winter quarters.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>: The Diet is now <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> upon the examination of the Oath given to the new King of the Romans, and likewise to regulate the Privy <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, and that of the Empire: next, to regulate the Courts of Justice, and so come to the conclusion of the Diet.</p>

<p>From <em>Cullen</em>: Our Commissioners are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> upon a Treaty with those of our Elector, but as yet nothing can be effected, which doth put us into great fears, by reason that our Trade remaineth stopped; and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed, that as soon as he hath cleared the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> of <em>Liege</em> from the <em>Lorraine</em> and Prince of <em>Conde</em> his forces, that he will then fall upon us, and make us yield to his demands.</p>

<p>From <em>Liege</em>: We expect daily the <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of <em>Cullen</em> our Prince, who coming with considerable forces intends to <reg orig="expell">expel</reg> all <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> forces from these parts, and to fight them, <reg orig="incase">in case</reg> they will abide his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em> thus: The <reg orig="Viceking">Vice King</reg> hath given Audience to one who was sent from the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Milan</em>: His Message being after some complements passed upon his new Admission, that he would further that supply which he is to have of men and money, towards the maintaining of the <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> in that Country against the French and Savoy forces; There is in the mean time great preparations made for his <reg orig="Cavalcate">Cavalcade</reg> (or riding in State) <reg orig="thorough">through</reg> this City: He hath likewise<pb n="3" /> sent to <em>Gaerta</em> to view all the places which are to be fortified, or else that they have any fortifications to be made in that County, there is likewise two hundred <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to be sent with all speed for the supplying of the Garrisons which we hold in <em><reg orig="Toscanie">Tuscany</reg></em> also there are several pieces of broken Ordinance brought from <em>Catalonia</em>, and there are some new cast which are to be sent thither.</p>

<p>From <em>Rome</em>. The Pope seemeth to be very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> to bring the Crowns of <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em> to an agreement, that thereupon might follow a general peace, and to that end he expects an answer from the two <reg orig="Nuntio's">Nuncios</reg>, that so if there be any overture made, he may send two Legates <em>a Latere</em>. From <em>Venice</em>. We have received a confirmation of the retreat of the Turkish Fleet at <em>Constantinople</em>, where the General <em>Bashaw</em> hath made his peace though for a while he was under a cloud: The report is, that having presented to the young <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> a young Virgin of an extraordinary beauty, who is of the Greek Nation, that thereupon he is received into favour, and the young maid like to be his chief <reg orig="favorite">favourite</reg>: Our General doth continue his best <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> in preventing the relief of <em>Canen</em>, having lately taken one ship and two others who fled, that were commanded to relieve it at their peril, being laden with provisions and ammunitions.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday February 7</i></head> 

<p><em>Paris February</em> 11. By an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> come from the <em>Leagure</em> before <em>Beffort</em> we have, that the work doth go on gallantly notwithstanding the <reg orig="rigor">rigour</reg> of the season and the strong resistance of the <reg orig="besiedged">besieged</reg>, hitherto there hath been no shot made upon the Town, by reason that we had certain intelligence, that as soon as we should begin to batter the Town they would set it on fire: thereupon it was resolved that the main work would be to undermine the Castle, and so by that means get the possession of the Town; the Minors having got over the Counterscarp have begun to undermine one of their Bastions, but by reason they work upon the Rock where they find little earth, therefore it will not be finished as soon as was expected; The<pb n="4" /> <reg orig="Besiedged">Besieged</reg> do throw abundance of stones from the Wall thereby to spare their shot, of which they have no great plenty, and the Marshal <em>la Ferte</em> was hurt with one of them as he was in the trench.</p>

<p>The Marshal <em>de Hocquincourt</em> having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> all things as well as the present condition of the County of <em>Rousillon</em> will permit: and left the command of the Army unto the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> <em>du Plessis</em>, the Lieutenant General, is returned again into these parts, and two days agone arrived to this City; yesterday he went to Court, and there did give an <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> to the King of all what passed during his abode in <em>Catalonia</em> and <em>Roussillon</em> the King <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> him a very gracious countenance, and its said he is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> the next week to <em>Peronne</em>, to take again the command of that place.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. <em>Menehold</em> hath now near finished his work for the repairing of the fortifications of that Town, he doth daily send out parties, who do often meet with some of the Prince of <em>Conde</em> his forces, and sometimes get the better, and othertimes do come short home: The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em> was marched out upon a design to have <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> <em>Stevay</em>, and a strong Castle hard by it, but there was notice given timely to the <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> of those places, and thereupon they were frustrate of their intentions.</p>

<p>From aboard the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> at <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 31. I gave you an account of the taking of the <em>Dorgord</em> of <em>Flushing</em>, the 26 instant, and the recovering the Patrick of <em><reg orig="Leverpool">Liverpool</reg></em> from the <em>Brest</em> men of War on the 27th. On the 28 standing over from <em>Scilly</em>, we chased a <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, which we understand by our prisoners aboard, was made for Cap. <em>James Dillon</em>. The old <em>Warwick</em> being between the shore and us, and we plying large, that he should not <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> between the shore and us came up with him before us. He was under the command of the Mount before our ship came up, and ran so near the shore, that we durst not go near him, by which means he ran very near <em><reg orig="Pensance">Penzance</reg></em> Key, and there anchored. The old <em><reg orig="Warwicks">Warwick's</reg></em> boat taking her, found her to be one of St <em>Malo's</em> coming from <em>Faro</em>.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>The Middleburgh went to the Lands-end, and I intended to follow, but did not; very little <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> made us stand off two or three leagues farther than ordinary, which brought us (the 29 in the morn) within sight of four ships of St. <em><reg orig="Maloes">Malo's</reg></em> coming from <em>Marseilles</em>, bound for <em>Newhaven</em>, viz. the St. <em>Martin</em> with 18 Guns and 44 men, the St. <em>Hellena</em> with 14 guns, and 32 men, the <em>Protection</em> with 12 guns and 32 men, and the <em>Francis</em> with 38 men and 10 guns, laden with <em>soap, <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, cotton</em>, &amp;c. with whom we came up about one <reg orig="aclock">a clock</reg>, and fought them <reg orig="til">till</reg> the <reg orig="Sun-set">Sunset</reg>. The St. <em>Martin</em> and St. <em>Hellena</em> had both yielded, but we had none of our men aboard; it beginning to be dark, and we being ready to board the <em>Protection</em>, whom we had well paid with shot, bethought <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> that we should lose the other two in taking her, and so <reg orig="cleered">cleared</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with much ado, and stood to the other, who being secured, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> were bearing for the other yet untaken; but these two ships we had taken were so much disabled, as we were forced to keep by them to save them from sinking, and sent our Carpenter aboard to stop leaks, and men to fit the Rigging, the Admiral not being able to bear sail, which occasioned the losing the other two. Our ship suffered in Hull, Masts, Rigging and Sails <em>viz.</em> in the <reg orig="main-mast">mainmast</reg> 3 shot, the <reg orig="top-mast">topmast</reg> 2, in the head of the <reg orig="fore-mast">foremast</reg> one, in the <reg orig="mizen-mast">mizzenmast</reg> 2, our <reg orig="fore-yard">foreyard</reg>, and <reg orig="mizen">mizzen</reg>-yard made unserviceable; we had several shot between wind and water; but the worst loss is 5 of our men killed, and 19 wounded, some of whom have lost their limbs.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>From <em>Bristol</em>, Febr. 4. 1654. Since my last some of our <em>Candiz</em> ships are arrived, and bring notice that the rest are in <em>Ireland</em>, having made our land a month since, but by contrary winds forced and kept there, which is very good news to our <reg orig="Marchants">Merchants</reg>, who had almost given them up for lost; it being eight weeks since they set sail from <em>Cadiz</em>; some of them have brought a Dutch man of about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with salt, which they took a little off that Port as they put homewards. The <em>Brest</em> men of war of whom I wrote you in my last have since taken two Vessels of <em>Milford</em>, of which we had notice this day, and about the time of the taking of the former, they took three ships, one of eighteen Guns, another of twelve, laden with Lead and Red Herrings, who pretended themselves of <em>Amsterdam</em> and <em>Sweden</em>, being Dutchmen, but had <reg orig="Cocquets">Coquets</reg> from North <em>Yarmouth</em>, the Seamen being Dutch, and indeed the commodities English, it is a shame that these Rogues should be permitted thus to rob our Fleet, and that such Cow ships are <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> Westward, whereto all ships make, that are bound for <em>England</em>. One of <em>Bristol</em> <reg orig="shippes">ships</reg>. Of which I wrote you last was taken half a League from <em>Scilly</em>, and though one of our ships pursued them thence 48 <reg orig="houres">hours</reg>, as the Master of that ship which was taken, since hath informed me, and the <em>Brest</em> man of War of 38 Guns towed her, yet could not reach her.</p>

<p>By Letters from the <em>Hague</em>, February 6. <em>stilo novo</em>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> shall not much longer now detain you or <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with the Expectations of Peace between <em>England</em> and these Provinces; this I can assure you, the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of <em>Holland</em> and <em>West-Friezland</em> do unanimously <reg orig="concurr">concur</reg> to a Peace, and the same we understand of <em>Zealand</em>, and the Province of <em>Virick</em>. They of <em>Friezland</em> upon the interest of the <em>Orange</em> party broke up abruptly their meeting about it; but what will be done upon the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Meeting of the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of all the Provinces at the <em>Hague</em>, which is appointed to be 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hence, which will be the last of January upon the English <reg orig="Accompt">Account</reg>, a short time will discover.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>But I am verily <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> there will be a sudden agreement to a peace, which will be the more <reg orig="hastned">hastened</reg>, because they cannot believe that the Lord <em>Beverling</em> will prevail with the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, for a Cessation of Arms, until there be a Conclusion; for there are so many ships both to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> out, and also to come in, and in such danger that they are necessitated to hasten a dispatch.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador here, made many addresses and large offers to have the War continue with <em>England</em>, and that the French King would contribute in all things to half the charges; but that being weighted, it was thought not to countervail the losses they must necessarily suffer; and not to answer their expectation, which is <reg orig="gettting">getting</reg> of wealth, which must be by an open trade, and thereupon the French offers were refused.</p>

<p>Yet the Ambassador makes often addresses to the States, but what is done is kept still very secret, only they call it a congratulation of their peace with <em>England</em>; but if it be about that, I suppose it is either to see if it may be hindered, or to get as good terms for <em>France</em> as may be in it.</p>

<p>However we still go on preparing new ships of War <reg orig="every day">everyday</reg>, the Workmen never <reg orig="seasing">ceasing</reg>, <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> <reg orig="daies">days</reg> and all, for dispatch of the work with all possible speed.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Newport</em> is at <em>Amsterdam</em>. It was under consideration upon the agreement to the Peace to have sent the Lord <em>Bedrode</em> General of the Land forces to be the Ambassador either alone, or the Lord <em>Vpdam</em> Vice-Admiral of their Navy with him, but the Lord General (because of his age) seems to decline it, but what will be concluded by the States General at their meeting four days hence, I shall <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> unto you by the first opportunity.</p>

<p>If there be not a conclusion of Peace truly I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not know what they will <reg orig="doe">do</reg>; The <reg orig="Meerchants">Merchants</reg> are undone, The Fishers cannot work, The Poor can have no <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> nor <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>; And there must needs be a very great hubbub and distraction.</p><pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday Febr. 8.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>Mr. <reg orig="Recorders">Recorder's</reg> Speech to the Lord Protector, upon Wednesday the 8. of Feb: 1653. being the day of his Highness Entertainment in <em>London</em>.</i></head>

<p>May it please your Highness, my Lord Protector, it hath been observed by some, That when <em>Samuel</em> offered sacrifice, he therefore reserved these shoulders for <em>Saul</em>, that he might know what was the weight of Government: The consideration of which made <em>Maximilian</em> affirm, That none who knew how heavy Diadems were, would stoop to take them up. Governors are like the Heavenly Bodies, much in veneration, but never in rest; and how can it otherwise be expected, when they are not made for themselves, or their own glory, but for the safety and good of Mankind as in the natural, so in the civil world, great things being ordained to serve the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg>: We see the Sun by its Beams, serving the eye of the meanest <reg orig="Flie">Fly</reg>, as well as of the greatest Potentate. The supremacy of <em>Salus Populi</em>, was the conclusion of the twelve Tables, and will be a prevalent <reg orig="Maxime">Maxim</reg> until the end of the World.</p>

<p>By this much my Lord, you may perceive the dark side of this leading Cloud of Government; but if God vouchsafe assistance from those shoulders, upon which the Government is laid, and put under his everlasting Arms, you will see the bright side also, and thence receive Encouragement, This support he is pleased to give, by letting Rulers know he is the Author of their power, and that from him they are to expect their rule. The designation of Government, as to forms and persons, is an humane institution, and mutable, as things that are made, but Government <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, <reg orig="abstrectively">abstractively</reg> considered in its pure Original is of a divine <reg orig="Off spring">Offspring</reg>, and can with no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> difficulty be shaken, <reg orig="then">than</reg> those <reg orig="Vestigias">Vestiges</reg>, which being as relations, tell us, upon the tops of some Mountains,<pb n="9" /> above the Clouds, can be disordered by wind and tempest. And for the Rule, the word, or reason of God in the Divine understanding, is the eternal Law of all things. But this being too deep a well for <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> Bucket to draw out of, it pleased his infinite Goodness to let fall a <reg orig="Rivolet">Rivulet</reg> from this source into the Creature; which leaving an impression in <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> understanding, we call the Law of nature: But man having this <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, presently became of no understanding; his <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> being clouded with passions and sins, had soon need of superadded helps, which God gave him, by those other Laws fit for Government, and still gives a spirit for the framing such Municipal Laws, as are according to his will, and suitable to the good of the people. But when this was done, the best Laws without a Government, were no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> as the sword <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg> the ephod; and therefore <em>Moses</em> in his time, and other Governors in their time, must be as walking Laws, and Administrators of justice.</p>

<p>We may conclude, my Lord, your Highness hath experimented both these encouragements, as being the spectator of some, and the subject of other great Revolutions which have <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in this Age, &amp; Land of wonders: And not only know, That the most high rules in the Kingdom of Men, disposing them to whom he pleaseth; but also, that <reg orig="its">it's</reg> not sufficient with the Princes of the Nations, to exercise dominion, which is the common Image of God, except there be also a peculiar image of his righteousness<pb n="10" /> and holiness; they being <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> indeed, and after a peculiar manner, to whom the reason, or word of God so comes.</p>

<p>My Lord, there is one help more in Government, which God is pleased often to add to the rest, which is the giving in of the affections of the people, the solemnity of this day, wherein the Citizens of this great City appear in their several Companies, as so many Cities within the City, speaks much to this; they leave it to other Nations to salute their Rulers and Victorious Commanders, with the names of <em>Casares</em> and <em>Imperatores</em>; and after Triumphs, to erect for them their <em>Arcus Triumphales</em>: But if I mistake not, their end this day, is not any such outward pomp or glory, but that those who have been delivered together, might <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> together; and to express their desires, that the Civil Sword might be as prosperous for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> ends, in the Hand where it is placed, as the Military Sword hath been in the same Hand.</p>

<p>This City seldom goes along in <reg orig="publick">public</reg> actions: it was anciently called by Stephanides, the heart of the Nation; and if the Heart be in a <reg orig="Politick">Politic</reg> consideration, as it is in the natural, it will communicate life and spirits into the other Members, by which means the whole body may unanimously contribute their desires and <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to oppose the common enemy, and after all our distractions, see the Nation established upon the firm Basis of peace and righteousness,<pb n="11" /> which is the end of Government and shall be the end of my further troubling Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>This being the day appointed for the Entertaining of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector in the <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> of <em>London</em>, it was done in a very magnificent manner: The streets from <em><reg orig="Grossers">Grocers'</reg></em> Hall to <reg orig="Temple-barre">Temple Bar</reg> were <reg orig="rayled">railed</reg> on both sides the way, and the <reg orig="Rayles">Rails</reg> covered with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg>, with store of great Flags and Streamers, bearing the Arms of the respective Companies: The 24. Companies in their Liveries about 11 a clock, took their places within the <reg orig="Rayles">Rails</reg>, the Lord <reg orig="Maior">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen in their Robes, on <reg orig="Horse-back">Horseback</reg> went to meet His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> at <reg orig="Temple-bar">Temple Bar</reg>; His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> came in his Coach from Whitehall, and in the Coach came along with him Major <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Lambert</em>, and the Lord President of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>: The Life Guard marched before him, and the <reg orig="Heraulds">Heralds</reg> followed, the Foot-officers went bare on <reg orig="aach">each</reg> side his Coach and 12. Foot-men in rich Liveries, two Pages before bare, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Whaly">Whaley</reg></em> led up all the field Officers bravely mounted, and Commissary <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Reynolds</em> brought up the Rear, the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> delivered up his sword which was speedily redelivered to his Lordship, who rid bare before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to Grocers Hall, where the Recorder made a congratulatory speech: his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and Officers were royally entertained, the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> sitting on his right, and the Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> on his left hand, the rest that sate at his Table were of his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> and Officers of the Army: After dinner his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> was conducted into an upper Room, and there entertained by the L. <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> with a sumptuous Banquet, this being done his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> knighted the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg>, and afterwards departed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday.</i></head> 

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector hath appointed certain <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> every week to receive Reports from the Masters<pb n="12" /> of Requests of Petitions presented to them, and to give Answers.</p>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Mackworth</em> Governor of <em>Shrewsbury</em> is added to the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>; of the Lord Protector Master Recorder Steel, Mr. <em>Newdigate</em>. M. <em>Twisden</em>, M. <em>Maynard</em>, and M. <em>Hugh Windham</em> are made <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at Law; <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Hales</em> sits now one of the <reg orig="Iustices">Justices</reg> of the Common Pleas, and other new <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg>, tis conceived will be suddenly made to ride this next.</p>

<p><em>Paris</em> the 14. of <em>February</em>, 1654. The Duke <em>de Longueville</em> is gone from hence with all his attendants to his house that is between Roan, and this. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is at last come to this <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> with a great <reg orig="Traine">Train</reg>, and much Nobility and Gentry to accompany him, he doth <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the house of <em>Condy</em>, but its said he will not <reg orig="retyre">retire</reg> there very long, but is to remove into another house which is to be made ready for him: the marriage between him and one of the Cardinal his Nephew being wholly agreed upon, it is daily expected when it will be solemnized, some think it will be <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, there are more projects <reg orig="inhand">in hand</reg> at Court for the raising of great sums of money, and amongst other projects a great Tax is to be levied upon all the <reg orig="Merechants">Merchants</reg> strangers throughout the Nation, and that it will be much like to that which was <reg orig="mised">missed</reg> in the year of our Lord, 1637: which proved very heavy to many at that time; this <reg orig="worke">work</reg> being done, there are great Taxes to be raised upon all those that have any considerable states either <reg orig="reall">real</reg> or personal, whether they dwell in Towns, or in the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>: the reason of the working thus; it is in regard they have so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> drawn the substance of the poor, that in great many places they can neither pay the whole Tax nor part thereof: The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Retz</em> remaineth still a close Prisoner, and no probability of his <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg> without he <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> to the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> his demands. Our <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> from <em>Rome</em> is expected here on <em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em> next, he is this night to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at <em>Estampes</em>. This week there hath been a large debate in the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> concerning the affairs between us and <em>England</em>, and it was resolved that an <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> in extraordinary<pb n="13" /> should be sent into England, but yet I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> who shall be the man, only two are in nomination, <em>viz</em>. the Marshall <em>de Clerambant</em>, and the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> <em>de Arpason</em>, by my next you will know further.</p>

<p>The Kings consecration is not to be done yet, but is put off for a longer time, and the common opinion is, it will not be till next May.</p>

<p>The Duke of Guise is now near ready to go from hence, but not to go for Naples, but rather to go into the County of Roussillen, there to be Commander in chief in <reg orig="lew">lieu</reg> of the Marshal de Hocquincourt lately come from thence.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> &amp; Saturday Feb. 9. 10.</i></head>

<p>Chester Feb. 4. By late Letters from Dublin we hear, that things thereabouts at present are very quiet: the Irish of late have had a general Fast, the occasion is not known, but to themselves; some few desperate <unclear>Tories</unclear> are yet doing mischief in Munster, and some <reg orig="sculking">skulking</reg> in Nicklow made shift to snap some dozen <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>, but what quarter was given them we hear not certainly, no further news at present.</p>

<p>Sears Castle Feb. 5. The other day the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> brought into Burlington Bay, a small Dutch <reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg> of <unclear><!-- a number, probably of 2 digits --></unclear> Guns and 50 men, which about 12 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> took some Colliers on this Coast as they were coming and going for Coals, the Captain and men are sent to the Goal at York.</p><pb n="14" />

<p>From Falmouth 6th thus. Here are still many ships here, who are bound for London and other parts to the Eastward of this place; all those that were here being gone some for Ireland, and others for Portugal, Spain and West Indies, we have not heard lately any news from Ireland, only by way of Barnstable, we hear that the Irish Rebels would again be stirring, and to that end are gathered into small bodies: with the which they have lately done us some mischief, this winter season being very <reg orig="advantagious">advantageous</reg> to them, and is a means that those Rogues cannot be <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg> so soon as is to be wished. From Cowes in the Isle of Wight Feb. 8. Our Fleet doth still ride near St <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point upon <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last, there passed by this Island near 30 sail of ships, which come all from the Strait Spain and Portugal, and <reg orig="Biscain">Biscayne</reg>, and are for the most part bound for London, as we are informed by a small Vessel who came along the Channel in their Company, that a private Man of War hath brought into two prizes, the one a Dutch Ship, of a considerable bigness, and the other a French Vessel, which ride between this place and Yarmouth.</p>

<p>From Deal the 9th of Feb, there hath passed through this Road several ships this week, which came from the Southward, and are all bound for London: there hath been very high winds lately, which have made some wrack upon the Coast of France about Calice, Bullein and those parts, among others a Dutch man of War, of a good strength, who rid in <em>Calice</em> Road, was beaten upon the shore, broken in <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, many of the men drowned, only a few saved: there are very few ships at present in this Road, this North and Easterly winds having carried them all away.</p>

<p>These ships <reg orig="afore mentioned">aforementioned</reg> are all safely arrived in the River of Thames. Also several prize ships, whereof five Dutch prizes with French Wines, one ship with Currants, and about ten other Dutch prizes are expected every Tide.</p>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> Feb. 6. thus. The enemy at their late being in Badgenoth, got 3 men from every 4 Ploughs in that Country, (except one near the water) but many of them returned back<pb n="15" /> the Laughabec men, did plunder much when the enemy was in <reg orig="Murriland">Murrayland</reg>, and then left them: the greatest part of <reg orig="Lelentarnes">Lelentarne's</reg> forces are at Strathspey near the Land of <reg orig="Gyants">Giants</reg>, who will (as is said) keep out his house against them, having taken in men and provisions to that end.</p>

<p>The 38. instant, about 36 Horse came into the Coast of Gowry, to Sir Peter Hayes House called Meginch, they did break his outer Court, and demanded his Horses, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> to burn his Corn otherwise; but he firing out then, they ran away, but two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> a great party came and burnt about 600 l. sterling in Corn: also the Earl of <reg orig="Luihtgowes">Luihtgowe's</reg> Corn for not delivering his Horses.</p>

<hr />

<p>A history of New England, from the English planting in the year 1628 till 1692. their form of Government civil, military, and <reg orig="ecclesiastick">ecclesiastic</reg>. Their wars with the Indians, their troubles with Gorlonish, their manner of Gathering Clunches, with the names of their Governors, Magistrates and Ministers.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> prayer unclasped, with a vindication of it, against all Schismes and <reg orig="Hereticks">Heretics</reg> called Enthusiasts, or Fratriciffs. By James Harwood, B.D. and are to be sold by H and G. Everden, at the Gray hound in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Church yard.</p>

<p><unclear>Cusia</unclear> Polic&aelig;, or the Apologies of several Princes justifying to the world their most eminent actions by the strength of reason, and the most exact Rules of Policy, written in French by the <reg orig="Acurate">Accurate</reg> Pen of Monsieur de Scudery, Governor of Nostredame, and now faithfully rendered into English; with the figures of many Emperors &amp; Kings.</p>

<p>Also Danes, an excellent new Romance written in Italian, by Gio: Francisco Loredano, A Noble Venetian in four Books translated into English, by Sir Aston Cockain Boch printed for Humphrey Moseley, at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Arms in St. <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p>An excellent and long expected Book, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, Jus divinum ministern Evangelici, or the divine right of the Ministry of England. Made by the provincial Assembly of London. Also the second part of spiritual refining, or a Treatise of sin, by Mr. Anthony Burgess. Also Mr. Rich. <reg orig="Bixters">Bixter's</reg> answer to Mr Aires, concerning the justification of Infidels: together with a brief account of Mr. <reg orig="Crandons">Crandon's</reg> Book.</p>

<p>The chiefest points of the Christian Religion being questionwise proposed, resolved by pertinent answers, taken word for word out of the holy Scriptures, without either consequences or Content. By John Biddle Master of Arts, are to be sold by Rich: Moon at the 7 Sparte near the great North door in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p>A brief exposition of the Prophecy of <em>Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, <reg orig="Habakuk">Habakkuk</reg></em>, and <em>Zephaniah</em>, by <unclear>Hutcheson</unclear>, Minister at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and are to be sold by Raph Smith, at the Bible in Cornhill, near the Royal Exchange.</p>

<p>A Bay Gelding with a black main &amp; a black <reg orig="bobd">bobbed</reg> tail, a white Ring about either <reg orig="eare">ear</reg>, is Hawk nose, he hath had the fashion the <reg orig="neer">near</reg> hind leg, a little white upon one of his hind feet, above 14 hand high, very well paced, &amp; about 8 or 9 years old, stole out of the Meadhw between Hereford and Wales, out of Mr. Roberts ground <unclear>to</unclear> on Sunday night the 5th of Feb. 1653. If any man bring tidings of the same Horse to his Henry Atkinson, a Stationer at Staple Time Gate, or at Mr. <reg orig="Roberts">Roberts'</reg> house at Hertford, they shall be rewarded for their pains.</p>

<p><i>This is licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to Order.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>