<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc177">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 177</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>

<head level="3">Containing these <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> particulars.</head>

<p><i>The sumptuous manner of Crowning and Anointing his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> the most Christian King of France, at the City of <em><reg orig="Rhemes">Rheims</reg></em>; in the presence of the titular King of Scots, and the Dukes, Marquesses, Earles, and other of the Nobility there assembled The burning of the English Nunnery at <em>Gravelin</em>, and a great part of the Town. General <reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg> driving the Scots up into the <reg orig="Mountaines">Mountains</reg>. The taking of divers prisoners, and further preparations for action on both sides. The daily proceedings of his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> and his Council, and a transaction of <reg orig="Maritine">Maritime</reg> affairs.</i></p>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Wednesday</em> May 24. to <em>Wednesday</em> May 31. 1654.</p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Wednesday, <em>May 24.</em>.</i></head>

<p>A Dangerous Plot being discovered against the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> set forth this Proclamation following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal Providences of God in frustrating of their former counsels and malicious designs) do appear still <reg orig="restlesse">restless</reg> in their attempts, to involve this Commonwealth in <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> and confusion. In order whereunto divers of them<pb n="1" /> have lately repaired to London, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this Commonwealth. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> with the advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> charge and command, that for the better discovery of persons ill affected to the Peace of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of London and Westminster, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Southwark, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication hereof, repair to the several houses within their respective Parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of names of all such persons as now do, or did lodge in their respective houses on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> night last being the 19. of this instant May, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg>, are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them a true List of all such names, upon peril of being reputed and dealt withal as Complices and <reg orig="Pertakers">Partakers</reg> in the said designs. Which list so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of London and Westminster, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of Southwark and Lines of Communication, are within 48 hours to deliver to the Lord Mayor of London and Bailiffs of Westminster and Southwark respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril.</p>

<p>And the said Lord Mayor and Bailiffs are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, immediately after the receipt hereof. And his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever, lodging within the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten days after the date hereof,<pb n="2" /> without licence and <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor of the said City of London, or Bailiff of Westminster or Southwark respectively, under their respective hands and seals, which pass the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark respectively, are hereby authorized to give to all such persons concerning whom they shall be satisfied that they have no ill intentions or designs against the Commonwealth, and to none else. And if any such person <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without licence obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a contempt of this his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> command, and punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of London, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster and Southwark respectively, are to cause this proclamation forthwith, after publication thereof, to be sent to the several Constables as aforesaid, and to require and demand from an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> 23 May.</i></head>

<p>Paris 16 May 1654. The King goes this day towards Rheins in order to his Coronation, it is thought that he will make three days journey of it, and after that some time <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be spent before all the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, which are summoned to appear, do come thither, yet it is probable that by the next we shall give you a full account of the whole solemnity.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday May 25.</head>

<p>A Proclamation was this day published in the name of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, touching an Article of the agreement between his Highness, and the States of the United Netherland Provinces, which followeth in these words.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by the thirtieth Article of the Peace made and concluded between his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces, it is concluded and agreed, That four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides, to meet here at London, upon the eighteenth day of May one thousand six hundred fifty and four, old stile, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be authorized to examine and determine all the losses and injuries which either <reg orig="alledge">allege</reg> to have received from the other since the year, 1611. unto May 18, 1652. as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> in the East-Indies, as in Greenland, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brazeel">Brazil</reg>, or in any other place; the particulars of all which shall be delivered in to the said Commissioners before the said 18 May, 1654. And whereas in pursuance thereof Commissioners are respectively named, viz. John Exton, William Turner, Doctors of Law, William Thompson, and Thomas Kendal Merchants, on the part of the English, and Adrian Van Almonde, Christian Van Rodenbure, Lodowick Howins, James Cysel, on the part of the people of the United Provinces, who not being able to meet so soon as the said 18 of May, it was mutually agreed, That the said meeting should be deferred unto 30 day of the same <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> of May, and that the particulars of the said Demands on either part, may be delivered in at any time before, or upon the 30 of May next, and that the same being delivered in before, or upon the said day, should be as effectual as if they had been exhibited on the 18 of May aforesaid. Which last agreement his Highness hath commanded by these presents to be made <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, to the end all persons concerned may take notice thereof,<pb n="4" /> and deliver in their demands to the Commissioners accordingly. The place of whose meeting is to be at <reg orig="Guild-hall">Guildhall</reg> upon the 30 of May aforesaid.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 24 of May, 1654.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from Amsterdam it is certified, That the <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of Orange with the young Prince her son, are gone from the Hague, to a Country house called <em>Honstaerdiick</em>, and after some stay there, they intend to go to Breda. There was great moan made and wringing of the hands by the meaner sort of women, at the passing away of the young Prince. The States General do sit again at the Hague, and are consulting how to lessen their charge by reducing part of their <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>. Their Greenland Fleet is gone to Sea.</p>

<p>From Bristol they write that the Brest men of War are very often seen upon that Coast, and the last week two of them came seeking of prey, quite up into the mouth of Severn, but found none that they durst venture on.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> May 26.</head>

<p>By several Letters from Scotland as followeth, <reg orig="Invernesse">Inverness</reg> May 14. Middleton and the rest of his party that remains of those that are run to their own houses, are still in Southerland and <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Brigade lies in the Shires of Ross and Inverness blocking them up as formerly; Drummond is about <reg orig="Loughtay">Lough Tay</reg>, and the Bailiff of Athol is gone to him, to advise concerning the speedy raising of all Gentlemen in that Country (for the Highlanders are no other) <reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg> with about 450 horse and foot were lately in the <reg orig="Braies">Brays</reg> of Anguish, forcing men to rise with him: Glencairn we hear is gone South through the Brays of Renogh, and from the Hills we understand, the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> foot runs away by 30 and 40 in a company, and are necessitated to eat horse flesh<pb n="5" /> where they go, provisions being so exceeding scarce in those parts.</p>

<p><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> May 16. Thursday last the General came hither with part of Col. <reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg> Regiment of horse, his own Regiment, and four Companies of Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> of Foot, we hear nothing of any considerable part of the enemy being in these parts: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> we have intelligence, That Captain Kympton Hilliard being marched towards Douglas, having intelligence, That Cardinesse, Forgison, and Wallace, with about 40 of the <reg orig="Rebells">Rebels</reg> were about New Mills, resolved to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them with 20 of his Troop, and a Sergeant that were with him, but upon a nearer approach found them above 60. ready mounted, and drawn up to receive him; notwithstanding which he continued his resolution, and upon his approach the Rebels seemed much to scorn the <reg orig="smalness">smallness</reg> of his number; but it pleased God so to order it, that after he had received their charge, he fell in upon them, and broke them, killed Cardinesses Cornet, and <reg orig="Forgissons">Forgisson's</reg> Cornet, and mortally wounded <reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. Wallis, killed two horses of theirs, and took 4. The rest, although <reg orig="disperst">dispersed</reg>, got away being well mounted; He took 6 or 8 suits of Arms, being good Backs, and <reg orig="Brests">Breasts</reg>, most of the Enemy had the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Mark. We had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> two wounded, and after two hours keeping the field, he returned to Air. The Rebels were marching towards the Hills, but by this means it is supposed they will have no great mind to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg>.</p>

<p>This day the General and forces march from hence to Cardross, near the hills, where he will lie in the fields for some time; Glencairn is come with some Forces into those parts.</p>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> May 20. Wednesday at night last some prisoners broke from their place of durance; but were<pb n="6" /> most of them retaken within two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after. <em>Middleton</em>, Monro, Athol, and Forbs, are in Caithness with their broken Regiments; Kenmore remains sick in Sutherland, and hath been so for this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> <reg orig="past">passed</reg>. Glencarn and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Drummond, with some foot and horse lie at Abersoyl, the most considerable pass to and from the hills, about 12 miles from <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>, General Monk is marched that way to observe the several passes upon the Brays, and to take some cause with them.</p>

<p>Another Fleet of Coals came into the river of Thames from Newcastle.</p>

<p>The Letters from Leith advertise, that the English squadron which are gone to the Northward, have taken two of the French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> which had done much mischief upon that Coast. They also say that General Monk hath had a <reg orig="randezvouz">rendezvous</reg> near <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>, and that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Prides">Pride's</reg> Regiment was expected to come up unto them.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, May 29.</head>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for the preservation of the Works of the great Level of the Fens.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the <reg orig="dreining">draining</reg> of the great Level of the Fens, extending <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> into the several Counties of Northampton, Norfolk, Suffolk, Lincoln, Cambridge, and Huntington, and the Isle of Ely, or some of them;</i> William Earl of Bedford, <reg orig="Perticipants">Participants</reg> and Adventurers are thereby <reg orig="impowered">empowered</reg> to <reg orig="drein">drain</reg> the said Level which is done accordingly, and so adjudged and to have for their <reg orig="recompence">recompense</reg> the proportion of 95000 Acres, which is also set out and assigned; In and by which Act there is not a full remedy provided to enforce the payment of Taxes, which shall be laid and assessed in order to the preserving of the said Level; For remedy whereof, and also for providing of all ways and means conducing to the preservation thereof; Be it ordained and established by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the consent of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That upon any Tax or Taxes to be made or laid, in pursuance of the said Act, that it shall and may be <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> for any person or persons, by any Warrant under the Hands and Seals of any five or more of the said Adventurers or Participants of the said 95000 Acres (having 500 Acres a piece) not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to distrein upon the said Lands which are or shall be in arrear for such taxes, but in case of non-payment by the space of thirty days after the tax so in arrear, to <reg orig="sel">sell</reg> the distress or distresses so taken, and the moneys arising by such sale or sales, to be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> as well to the satisfying<pb n="7" /> of such Arrears of Taxes as to the payment of 2 s. in the pound for the Taxes so in Arrear, to the use of the said Earl, Participants and Adventurers, their Heirs and Assigns, for defraying Charges occasioned in and about such distresses and sales, <reg orig="rendring">rendering</reg> <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> the surplusage upon such sales, above the said arrear Taxes, and two shillings in the pound aforesaid, if any be, to the owner of the distresses, demanding the same.</p>

<head level="3">Tuesday, May 30.</head>

<p>The news passeth <reg orig="currant">current</reg> upon the Exchange, that there lately happened a great fire at Gravelin, which burned down the Covent of English Nuns, and a considerable part of the Town. This fire is said to begin rather by accident <reg orig="then">than</reg> of negligence.</p>

<p>The Letters from France <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, That the King is now crowned at Rheins, and all the ancient ceremonies were then used, attended with as great pomp and state as hath <reg orig="hither to">hitherto</reg> been heard of. <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart and his brother the Duke of York were there. Before their going from Paris, Cardinal Mazarine made a Royal Feast for his Majesty and his Nobles.</p>

<p>Many great robberies attended with most horrid and inhuman <reg orig="murthers">murders</reg>, have lately been committed in several parts of this Nation.</p>

<p>General Pen is yet about the Downs with the Major part of our Fleet; but it is said, that a squadron will shortly be designed for the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>.</p>

<p>There is not any Letters as yet this week from Upsal in Sweden, but it is verily <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg>, that the Articles of Peace are signed and sealed and that the Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> Whitlock is on his journey again for England.</p>

<p>This week a ship was brought into Plymouth, wherein are many rich commodities, she is a French Bottom, and <reg orig="its">it's</reg> thought will prove prize.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of his Highness the Lord Protector sit very close, having before them many things of great concernment, which we hope will all conduce to the good of this Commonwealth, and more particularly those things propounded concerning the Law (which in <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> is good) and the regulating the Courts of Justice.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> and approbation of Ministers, sit on their usual days at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, there have been many brought before them, which have not been approved of.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>E. Alsop 1654</em>.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>