<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc164">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 164</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>The arrival of the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> at Harwich, for perfecting the Peace with England. The Proclamation of the Earl of Glencarn, General of the Highlanders, for the levying of Horse and Foot, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Fire and Sword to the disobedient: The taking of <unclear>Kildrumy</unclear> by Col. Morgan. The further proceedings of the Lo. <reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg> Treaty with the Queen of Sweden. Strange news from Germany. The last intelligence from <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, touching his travel from Paris. The selling of several prizes taken at Sea. With variety of other Intelligence from several parts.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> February 22. to <em>Wednesday</em> March 1. 1654.</head>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, February 22.</head>

<p>Some Addresses were made to his Highness the Lord Protector, in the name of many Ministers of the County of Leicester wherein they acknowledged the goodness of God in the late variations and remarkable productions of his Providence, and most especially for the seasonable rescue that hath been lately given to the greatest concernment of Church and State, and they do esteem it as a large improvement of that mercy, that His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> was inclined to take that protection of these shattering Nations in so dangerous and troublesome <pb n="1" />a constitution, when almost spent with the tempestuous violence of contrary winds, and waves, which conspired to threaten a common wrack and <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>; and they hope, that the God of Order will so protect his Highness in defending the Faith, and encouraging the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg> of Jesus Christ, as shall declare to the world his special approbation of his Noble and Just intentions in these his great undertakings: And further they humbly beg, that Religion and Learning may flourish, and the work of the Lord made to prosper in the hands of the Ministry of Christ in these Nations under the hands of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness'</reg> protections, Long and Happy Government.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, Febr. 23.</head>

<head level="3"><i>The Copy of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> Proclamation, for the bringing in of levies in Scotland, as followeth.</i></head>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased his Majesty to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of Scotland, for opposing the common enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his justice hath permitted to overcome, and be the instrument of <reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on, but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we would turn to him by unfeigned repentance. And to the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that none of his <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> subjects may pretend ignorance; and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires and Parishes and head Burghs by open Proclamation, that every one may make his several proportions ready to be <pb n="2" />delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under our hand wheresoever the aforesaid Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, ties of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of Honour, will move to their Duty, may be proceeded against with fire and Sword, unworthy to be looked upon as Scotchmen, to the <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> of all false-hearted Traitors, who by their Treacheries and Rebellions against their <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> King, and his just power and authority, hath drawn on the deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon the three Kingdoms.</p>

<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore horses hath been brought forth from any well-affected person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said horses hath been taken, that they shall meet and <unclear>stent</unclear> themselves equally, for bearing equal <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, and resound the persons from whom any horses hath been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of horses now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries, out of every thousand pound of rent: and the proportion of foot, every third man; and what Dragoons are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one Dragoon. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes, where no Burghs are, the Provost and Bailiffs of Burghs to proclaim this at the Market <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as they will answer the contrary upon their highest peril. Given under our hand the 1 of <em>Feb.</em> 1653. <em>Sic Subscribitur</em>, Glencairn.</p>

<p><i>God save King <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> the <em>II.</em></i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Febr. 24.</head>

<p>Several Letters from Paris make mention, that the Scots King is going from thence with his attendants; but it is not certainly known unto what place he goeth, some giving out that he is for Germany, and others for Holland.</p>

<p>From Dalkeith, Febr. 18. About four days since, Col. Daniel with a party of Horse, Foot, and Dragoons, together with the conjunction of another party from Dundee, in all about 1000, marched towards Dunkel, where the enemies most considerable quarters was, and where they had newly established a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Lord <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> House, near the Church. And upon Col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg> approach (the Lord Athol and Sir Arthur Forbs having intelligence, retreated to the hills, and left <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and some few to defend the Church) those in the Church durst not stand, but fled to the House; which our men attempted, and got under the walls with Pickaxes, and other <reg orig="instrumants">instruments</reg> that were in readiness, and in short time got into a part of the House without the loss of one man; and having slain <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 3 of the enemy, the rest <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> quarter, and had it granted, yet notwithstanding unworthily began to resist a <reg orig="litttle">little</reg> which quickened our men the more; and then the enemy cried out amain, they would accept of the terms granted. In the house we took two Lieutenants, one Ensign with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> colours, Sir Arthur Forbs his own Quartermaster, two <reg orig="Sarjeants">Sergeants</reg>, two Cornets, and an hundred and nineteen private rogues, together with eighty Muskets and Bandeleers, some Firelocks and Swords, about sixteen pound of powder, as also five and twenty troop horses, and fourteen or fifteen case of pistols, with much Meal, Malt and Oats, which not having convenience to carry away, we set fire to a barrel of powder and those provisions, and blew up them and the House together. About five days <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg>, one of late <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg> men with three of his best horses, got his Landlord to help him water them, and run away with them to Blaire Castle, one of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, which makes the English less trusted by Athol and the <!--tories??-->Teries. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan hath also removed the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Kildrummy; and many of those Horsemen he routed at his engagement with valiant Glencarn (the great Patron, or rather <reg orig="spoyler">spoiler</reg> of his <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>) running to Athol near Dunkel, he translated them to foot. Col. Morgan at his late engagement, with the enemy at Cromar, killed 120, and took 27 prisoners with all their Ammunition, and most of their Arms, and about 80 horse, in all which we lost not one man.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>From Upsall in Sweden Jan. 10. We have very great probability (God favouring the undertaking) to accomplish what we came hither about, and to return within, or a little time after the time limited, which was six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: My Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> carries on <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> with a great deal of <reg orig="wisedome">wisdom</reg> and discretion and is highly approved <reg orig="off">of</reg> by the <reg orig="Queeen">Queen</reg>, and Grand Chancellor who bears great power here, we were a little at a stop upon the new change of Government in England, for my Lord was forced thereby to begin again, and had a new Commission sent him from my Lord Protector, but the Queen received his new Credentials with all <reg orig="willingnesse">willingness</reg>; and now business goeth forward at least in appearance fairer then before; the Queen seeming to have very great respect to my Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> Feb. 25.</head>

<p>This day the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="Bayly">Bailey</reg> ended. There was condemned 3 men and one woman, which robbed Mr. Hancock at the Greyhound Tavern in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>, and wounded him. One Mrs. <em>Beard</em> was also condemned for Witchcraft, and some others for Robbery.</p>

<p>Every day this week, was expected the <reg orig="arrivl">arrival</reg> of the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg>; but it seems the winds have been so contrary, that it hath not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> caused their passage the longer, but they are forced (as we had this day intelligence( to put in either at Harwich or Colchester.</p>

<p>Further by Letters from France it is thus certified: The titular K. of the Scots hath lately been sick of a cold, but is now pretty well recovered. His mother is altogether in her devotions at Chaloons; on Ash wednesday last she took her ashes from the hands of Mr. <em>Philips</em>, who was sometimes her Confessor in England.</p>

<p>It is also confirmed, that the Duke of Lorrain being arrested by the authority of the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg>, was brought to Antwerp, where he is kept close prisoner in the Castle; many of his menial servants are also arrested, and distributed into several Prisons: It is said that he endeavoured to betray the Prince of Conde and his Army to the King of France.</p>

<p>By divers Letters from beyond the seas, it was this day confirmed that the Pope endeavouring to bring his <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> hairs with peace to the grave, doth labour with all his power to work a reconciliation betwixt his two sons the most <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg>, and the most Christian Kings; and this mediation by Agents of undoubted knowledge and Authority, hath already in a fair way advanced <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>It is certified from Germany, that in some parts thereof the ground hath been almost covered with innumerable sorts of Mice of several complexions, which have devoured the <reg orig="grasse">grass</reg> in the fields, and the grain in the barns, so that they conceive, that this Plague is not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a Forerunner of <reg orig="dreadfull">dreadful</reg> Famine, but also of a new War; to the apprehension of which, they have been terrified with a Blazing Star, not much unlike unto that which was beheld all Europe over, a little before the German Wars began.</p>

<p>Take this from the Hague Febr. 20. This day Mr. Stocker, sent by the Protestant Cantons in Switzerland to mediate a Reconciliation between the two Commonwealths of England and the untied Provinces, who hath formerly resided long at London, is arrived here. The Freebooters <em>de Haen</em> hath brought in three <reg orig="shigs">ships</reg> taken upon the coasts of Scotland, two laden with coals, and a Flute laden with salted Salmon and other Goods. The last Sunday arrived here an express from London, with Letters from Lord Beverling, to the Lords States General.</p>

<p>Letters from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that they begin to conceive great hopes of the Treaty between England and Holland, and are much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at the good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of that Negotiation. There are great preparations made by Sea in Denmark. We hear from Brandenburgh that over against Leatzer, there hath appeared in the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg> a star of an extraordinary <reg orig="bignesse">bigness</reg>, with many shining streams round about.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Febr. 27.</head>

<p>This day being the <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> delivery at Newgate, three men and one Woman was hanged in Fleet-street, and five at Tyburn: Those who suffered in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>, were some of them that had broken there into the Greyhound Tavern<pb n="6" />, robbed the house, and desperately wounded the <reg orig="Vintener">Vintner</reg> <reg orig="himsel">himself</reg>; the Robbery was attended with such circumstances of aggravation, that it was thought fit they should be made exemplary by losing their lives in the same place where the Robbery was committed. Letters make mention of other great Robberies at <reg orig="Maydenhead">Maidenhead</reg>, and others at Salisbury: Fifteen <reg orig="Highway men">Highwaymen</reg> have been lately taken and brought to Bedford <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>. There was exhibited this last Sessions, a Bill against a <reg orig="Counsellour">Councillor</reg> for corruption, which was nine yards long, and a foot broad.</p>

<p>I have this morning seen a Letter which informs, that the Dutch <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> are landed at Harwich: It is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> that very speedily they will be at London; Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg> house in the <reg orig="Pallace-yard">Palace yard</reg> is prepared for them.</p>

<p>The Gentlemen and Heritors of the Shire of Argyle had lately a meeting with the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquis</reg> thereof at <unclear>Innerara</unclear>, where they resolved not to join with those people now in Arms; but to be ready at 24 <reg orig="hours">hours'</reg> warning to oppose them. The business of the Lewis was thus; Normand mac Cloud with 4 or 500 men landed in Lewis Island, and after 3 or 4 days staying in some inaccessible places of the Isle, fell upon our <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who lay in Sternway out of the Fort, and killed 12 of them; but a party out of the Fort beat them thence, relieved the remainder of the men, removed the Goods into the Fort, and burned the houses.</p>

<p>It was also this day advertised, that the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> and the constant Warwick, had rescued the <reg orig="Samaritane">Samaritan</reg> of Bristol, and a Pink belonging unto Plymouth, which were both taken by Captain <em>Beach,</em> who was <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to leave them, and had much to do to escape himself, but a companion of his, an old Picaro was taken in the <reg orig="Samaritane">Samaritan</reg>, and is now held in the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg>.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, Febr. 28.</head>

<p>Wednesday the first of March, is sold by the Candle at the Prize Office, the ship called the <em>White Cat</em>, with all her Tackle; and a large parcel of <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> Wine.</p>

<p>From Lieth in Scotland thus. Since the late Rout given to Glencarn and Kenmore near Aberdeen, we hear that Glencarn is endeavouring to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> (with those broken forces which were left) with Athol and Seafort. We hear that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan hath taken the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Kildrumy; SO that you may see these Warriors for their King, have but cold <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, and yet the Lowlands prove too hot for them.</p>

<p>The Letters from Amsterdam speak two more <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> to be sent away for England, and the Merchants are <em>Cap a pee</em> in hopes of gallant times, when the Peace is Proclaimed betwixt them and England. Others that are <reg orig="byassed">biased</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> by the Orange party, are full of discontent; and if they do conclude a Peace with England, it is thought some new differences will fall out here: But what matter is it for that, if we can trade without danger or fear to any part of the world?</p>

<p>The Letters from the West do make mention of the taking of one of the Brest men of War, and a Merchant ship by the English.</p>

<p>Our Fleet is plying up and down in the Channel and many prizes are lately brought in. The Fleet increaseth <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>, by the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in of others that are fitted out; and the Dutch have made themselves as strong as they can also.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is newly published an excellent Treatise, intituled, <em>The <reg orig="greatnesse">greatness</reg> of the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg> of <reg orig="Godlinesse">Godliness</reg>,</em> opened in several Sermons, by <em><unclear>Cuthbeart</unclear> Sydenham</em>, Teacher to a Church of Christ in <em>Newcastle</em>, sold by <em>Richard Tomlins,</em> at the Sun and Bible near <em>Pie-Corner</em>, and by <em>William London</em> Book seller in <em>Newcastle</em>.</p>

<p>Tuesday Febr. 21. Richard Luckin of Dives Hall in the County of Essex, Esquire, was robbed of 700 l in money, 4 or 5 slit silver Spoons, marked with R.E. one silver preserving Ladle, punched with 4 <reg orig="rowes">rows</reg> of holes; and a Rapier with a <unclear>Russeted</unclear> Hilt, and a black Horse-haired Handle; it had no Scabbard. The Thieves, one of them was a slender man, a thin face, <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of pockholes, a white close coat: another was a strong set man, with a cast upon his eye; his <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> were a liver coloured coat and breeches. Another was a fair haired man in a loose white <reg orig="horsemans">horseman's</reg> coat girt to him. If any can give notice of the goods or persons or any of their company, to Mr. Beachams a Goldsmith, at the Rose in Cheapside, they shall have 3 l. for their pains.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>