<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfDiOcc4">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Diurnall or Occurrences, Issue 4</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect <reg orig="Diurnall">Diurnal</reg>:</head>
<head level="2">OR,</head>
<head level="1">OCCURRENCES</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">Certain Military Affairs in order to the</head>
<head level="3">Armies, in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="2">WITH</head>
<head level="2">Variety of the transactions of other</head>
<head level="2">NATIONS.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em>. 22. to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, <em>May</em> 29. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3">Printed for <em>F. Coles</em>, dwelling in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg></em>.</head> 
<hr />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> May 22.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> May 18. General <em>Monk</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> yesterday from hence to <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>, where the two Regiments which came last into Scotland are to meet him. Col. <em><reg orig="Prides">Pride's</reg></em> Regiment (we hear) are within two or three <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> march. The Enemy is stirring about in parties, and do most miserably rob and plunder the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> where they come, but in a short time we shall drive them <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> together. Four persons have been <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> for Spies since Gen. <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> coming into this country.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Another Letter from Scotland.</i></head>

<p>Col. <em>Cooper</em> having occasion to send his wife and his Lieut. Col to the garrison of Ayr sent a convoy of 22. Dragoons with them: the Dragoons returning back met a party of the enemy ranging about the country, being 60 horse under the command of the Laird <em>Cairdennis</em><pb n="1" />, who charged and routed them, killed the Laird <em>Cairdennis</em> himself, with two Cornets, and nine more upon the place, took divers horse and men, the rest fled. This is all the action done of late in these parts, we lost not a man, two were wounded, but are upon recovery.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday May 23.</i></head>

<p>Upon the discovery of a <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> <reg orig="designe">design</reg> against his Highness the Lord Protector, and this Commonwealth for involving the same again in <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, divers persons were apprehended, and some sent to the Tower. And for the better discovery of such persons as had any hand in that <reg orig="designe">design</reg>, his Highness set forth this Proclamation following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal Providences of God in frustrating of their former counsels and malicious Designs) do appear still restless in their Attempts, to involve this Commonwealth in blood and confusion. In order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this Commonwealth. His Highness with the advice of his Council, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> charge and command, that for the better discovery of persons <reg orig="il">ill</reg>-effected to the peace of this Commonwealth, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westm</em>. <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication hereof, repair to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> houses within their respective Parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as now do, or did <reg orig="lodg">lodge</reg> in their respective Houses on Friday night last being the 19. of this instant <em>May</em>, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they<pb n="2" /> have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names upon peril of being reputed and dealt withal, as <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg> and Partakers in the said <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>. Which List so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and Lines of Communication, are within 48. hours to deliver the Lord Mayor of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Southwark</em>, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril.</p>

<p>And the said Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliffes">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the receipt hereof. And his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever lodging within the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the date hereof, without a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Licence and <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor of the said City of <em>London</em>, or <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, or <em>Southwark</em> respectively, under their respective hands and seals; which <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the said Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em> and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are hereby Authorized to give all such persons, concerning whom they shall be satisfied that they have no ill intentions or designs against the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to none else, And if any such person shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without licence obtained as aforesaid, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be reputed a Contempt of this his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Command, and be punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after Publication thereof, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent to the several Constables as aforesaid<pb n="3" />, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon. <i>Given at Whitehall 23 May.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, May 20.</i></head>

<p>A Proclamation was this day published in the name of his Highness the Lord Protector, touching an Article of the agreement between his Highness, and the States of the united Netherland Provinces, which <reg orig="followes">follows</reg> in these words.</p>

<head level="3">BY THE LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<p>Whereas by the thirtieth Article of the Peace lately made and concluded between his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces, It is concluded and agreed, That four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides to meet here at London, upon the eighteenth day of May, one thousand six hundred fifty and four, old style, who shall be authorized to examine and determine all the losses, and injuries which either allege to have received from the other, since the year one thousand six hundred and eleven, unto the eighteenth of May one thousand six hundred fifty and two, as well in the East Indies, as in Greenland, Muscovy, Brazeel, or in any other place; the particulars of all which shall be delivered in to the said Commissioners before the said eighteenth of May one thousand six hundred fifty and four. And whereas in pursuance thereof Commissioners are respectively named, viz. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Exton, William Turner</em>, Doctors of Law, <em>William Thompson</em>, and <em>Thomas Kendall</em>, Merchants, on the part of the English; and <em><reg orig="Adryan">Adrian</reg> Van Almonde, Christian Van Rodenbure, Lodovick Howens, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Oysel</em>, on the part of the people of the United Provinces, who not being able to meet so soon as the said eighteenth day of May, It was mutually agreed, That the said meeting should be deferred unto the thirtieth of the same <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> of May, and that the particulars of the said Demands on either part may be delivered in at any time before, or upon the thirtieth of May next, and that the same being delivered in before, or upon the said day, should be as effectual as if they had been exhibited upon the eighteenth day of May aforesaid. Which last Agreement his Highness hath Commanded by these presents to be made <reg orig="publike">public</reg>, to the end all persons concerned may take notice thereof, and deliver in their Demands unto the Commissioners accordingly. The place of whose meeting is to be at <reg orig="Guild-Hall">Guildhall</reg> upon the thirtieth of May aforesaid.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> the 24. of May, 1644.</i></p><pb n="4" />

<p><em>Dublin</em> 14 May, Knowing not what Lands belong unto us towards the satisfaction of our arrears, the <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> thing we want is a way to improve the same to the best advantage; and if any of our own Nation English would come over with a little money in their <reg orig="pocketts">pockets</reg>, they might (for ought we know) improve it to as much advantage, as if they made a journey to the East Indies; <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are all at peace and quietness here, and three or <reg orig="foure">four</reg> together may <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> a hundred miles an end if they will with a bag of money upon the end of a Pike <reg orig="staffe">staff</reg>. The greatest danger which hath appeared of late is at Sea, where the French <reg orig="Pickerons">Picaroons</reg> or <em>Brest</em> men of war are very active, and (as we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> ) have lately taken a ship going from hence for <em>England</em>, but there is a ship lately come into our ports from <em>London</em> laden with <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition.</p>

<p>The Irish are not all come into <em>Conough</em> as yet, but Proclamation is made that such as are not already come in shall lose the <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> which was formerly granted, and lie under censure of <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of life and Estates if they come not in at, or before the first of June.</p>

<p>Paris, 23. May 1654. The 8 instant the Princess of Conde petitioned the Parliament to have the sequestration taken off from her estate, but they <reg orig="refus'd">refused</reg>, and <reg orig="refer'd">referred</reg> the business to the King.</p>

<p>The 15. day Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> sumptuously feasted the King, Queen, the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> brother and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Grandees at the <em>Bots de <reg orig="Vicennes">Vincennes</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday, May 18.</i></head>

<p>The examinations of divers persons have been taken about the plot against the present Government before spoken of, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons remain under commitment, the names of some of them are these. <em>Gilbert Gerhard</em> Esquire, formerly an Officer for, and knighted by the late King; <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Gerard</em> brother to the said Sir <em>G. Gerhard, Humphrey <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em><pb n="5" />, Secretary to the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marques</reg> of Dorchester, otherwise called the Earl of Kingston, <em>Sidney Fothersby, Thomas Teudor, <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Jones</em> an Apothecary, Mr. <em>Hill</em>, Mr. <em>Brown</em>; A Drapers man in <reg orig="PAULS">PAUL'S</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>, a Milliners man in Cheapside <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Old Change, and some others.</p>

<head level="3">A Letter from the Squadron in the West.</head>

<p>Sir, About four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since two ships belonging to the Dutch sailing from Holland towards France passed by us: at first when they got sight of our ships, they put up the Holland colours, and sailed on towards us: As soon as they came <reg orig="neer">near</reg> one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, they took in their Holland colours and put up a white flag of peace, which signal of theirs was answered from our ship. After which they took down their white Flag, and again spread their Holland colours, <reg orig="lowred">lowered</reg> their <reg orig="top-sails">topsails</reg> on the cape, and so sailed under our stern. As the Dutch passed by they made great expressions of joy for the peace between their Commonwealth and ours. The Lord in mercy give us all hearts to in prove these great providences which his <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> is pleased to dispense towards us poor worthless ones, and help us to seek after that peace which hath eternity written in it.</p>

<p>May 13. 1654.</p>

<p>Plymouth Sound 16 May, 1654. Sir Captain <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Seaman</em> Commander of the Dragon <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, with the Adventure <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, plying off Alderney, they met with a small Frenchman, which had been taken by an Ostender <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Bell Island; Our Captains being informed that she was laden with <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> goods, sent her into Weymouth to have that business further examined.</p>

<p>On the 10 instant, plying off Dartmouth they met with three Barks which belong to Lyn, and upon the desire of the Masters they convoyed them safe over Murleux, whither they saw them safe, and standing off again, met <reg orig="witth">with</reg> 25 sail of Frenchmen, which were bound for Rochel to take in salt,<pb n="6" /> and so on for the bank of Newfoundland, but before they got to Rochel they chased them half a day, but could take but three of them, because they steered so many courses: while we were upon the chase of them, our men descried another Fleet to the windward, which were found to be thirteen sail of Holland Merchant ships with one convoy in their company, he saluted ours with three guns, and some expressions of love, and so they passed on their voyage, and ours parted from them, and are now at present come into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> Sound.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, May 19.</i></head>

<p>The Letters this Day from <em>Holland</em> advertise, that the mouths of the averse party are pretty well <reg orig="stopt">stopped</reg>, and pacified, and the States have set forth this ensuing Declaration.</p>

<p>The States General of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, to all persons to whom these presents shall come, <em>greeting</em>.</p>

<p>Whereas (to the praise of Almighty God, the advancement of the general good of the united Provinces, and of every particular person,) Articles of peace; Union, and Confederation, are concluded and agreed between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and the States General of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>, that they do <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> and submit to the said peace so Ratified, and to obey the Ratification in all places, without any breach hereof; upon pain of being punished as disturbers of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> peace, within expectation of any favour or grace, but to be proceeded against according to justice.</p>

<p>Given at the meeting of the States General at the <em>Hague 7. (alias.) 17 May, 1654</em>. <em>Jacob Vetch</em> President <em>pro tempore</em>.</p>

<p><em>N. Ruyseh</em>, Clerk to the States General.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, May 17.</i></head> 

<p>A Son of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Salisburies">Salisbury's</reg></em> and some other persons of eminency are in question touching the plot before mentioned. We shall <reg orig="forbeare">forbear</reg> to name them all, for that they stand upon their vindication.</p>

<p>The Constables of London made a return of the names of Lodgers, according to the Proclamation before recited.</p>

<p>The Treaty goes forward with the French Ambassador.</p>

<p>From Amsterdam 16. May. We are here at quiet, and all parties pretty well satisfied. Our Merchants put out to sea as fast as they can, there is gone forth above 200. sail since the peace with England was concluded. Many commodities are come hither from England which we much wanted. The <reg orig="newes">news</reg> that now troubles some Merchants upon the Burse is the taking of a ship richly laden &amp; bound for the East Indies a little before the concluding of the peace, that she is already made prize and delivered at London: she is valued very high, and extraordinary well victualled with all kind of provisions for 200. men for two years.</p>

<p>From <em>Jersey</em> thus. <reg orig="Lievt">Lieut</reg>. Col. <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Lilburn</em> is well and merry, he hath a faire Chamber (which was once Mr. <em><reg orig="Prins">Prin's</reg></em>) and the <reg orig="benifit">benefit</reg> of the Leads to walk in, The Messenger which brought the <em>Habeas Corpus</em> to the Governor, was received with civility, and had the <reg orig="Governors">Governor's</reg> <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> to carry him <reg orig="backe">back</reg>. Part of our fleet met with about thirty <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of Hollanders upon this Coast on the 12 of this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> and the Dutch gave us the ancient respect of Lowering their Top, and as they came <reg orig="neere">near</reg> one another they <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> large expressions of joy and friendship.</p>

<p>All remarkable in the Letters out of Scotland by this Post is this. Gen. <em><reg orig="Monke">Monk</reg></em> had a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neere">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em>, <em>Middleton</em> is said to be gone out of Southerland to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> with Athol. We have taken a kinsman of the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em><reg orig="Seafords">Seaford's</reg></em> and three Lords of the tribe of <em>Glencarn</em>. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> brother whom we <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> about 10 days since is like to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> for a <reg orig="Spie">Spy</reg>: two were hanged upon that <reg orig="accompt">account</reg> the last week. Last night our Scouts brought intelligence, that they heard a party of the Enemy was marched Westward. We are now driving on for action.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is lately published a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Tract <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>The <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> censure upon Recusants that refuse the Sacrament of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Supper</i>, by <em>Thomas Marshall</em> Minister of the Gospel, to be sold by <em>Francis Coles</em> in the <reg orig="old Baily">Old Bailey</reg>.</p>

<p>Another Book called <i>Waters of March, drawn forth in two <reg orig="funerall">funeral</reg> Sermons</i>, by <em>Henry Hibbert</em> Pastor of <em>Trinity</em> Church in <em>Kingston</em> upon <em>Hull</em>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Post hanging Coaches do now go upon every <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Wednesday, and Friday from the <em>Swan</em> at <em>Holborn bridge</em> to <em>York</em> in <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and go to <em>Newcastle</em> in six.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>