<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PerfAcc161">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>A Perfect Account, Issue 161</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">A Perfect Account</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">The daily Intelligence from the Armies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Navy at Sea.</head>
<head level="3">Containing these ensuing particulars.</head>

<p><i>A description of the great Feast made for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall London. Divers Letters intercepted from the Highlanders in Scotland, directed to their friends in the North of England with some orders of the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. Letters from our Fleet at sea. And Van <reg orig="Trumps">Trump's</reg> conducting out 200 sail of Merchants ships towards Spain, Portugal, and other parts. The beheading of the great Bashaw, and some proceedings of the States of Holland, and the other Provinces. The taking away the ships at sea, and letters from Ireland.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Wednesday</em> February 1. to <em>Wednesday</em> February 8. 1654.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>Beginning Wednesday</em>, February 1.</head>

<p>From the North we understand by Letters that a squadron of the Dutch men of war are gone Northwards, and young Trump's said to be their Admiral. It is thought they expect some Merchant ships home that way, and are conducting others out.</p>

<p>Three Dutch prizes are lately brought into Newcastle, and one into Lieth in Scotland, yet are there many <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> and Freebooters <reg orig="too">to</reg> and fro upon these coasts, and on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last they took an English vessel laden with salt and other commodities.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have passed an Ordinance, appointing a Committee for the Army, and Treasurers at War, with full power and authority in full and ample manner, to all intents and purposes, as the former Committee had. The names of the Committee are theses following, <em> viz. John Clerk, Edward Gludd, Richard Lucy, Richard Horseman, James Philips, Edward Gill, John Hildesley, Jervas Bennet</em> Esquires; captain <em>Adam Bains,</em> or any three or more of them; and <em>John Blackwell</em> the younger, and <em>Richard Dean</em> Esquires, to be Treasurers at War.</p>

<p>Ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, That <em><unclear>Tho</unclear> Rand, William Palmer, Robert Yarborow, Nehemiah Rauson, William Harvey, William Welby,</em> Esquires, and the Mayor of Lincoln for the time being, be added to the Commissioners for the <reg orig="Monethly">Monthly</reg> Assessment within the County of Lincoln.</p>

<p><em>Philip Stansby</em> for the county of <em>Dorset</em>; the Mayor of <em>Banbury</em> for the time being for the county of <em>Oxon</em>; and <em>Christopher Piercehay</em> Esq. And Sir <em>Robert Berwicke</em> Knight, for the county of <em>York</em>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, Febr. 2.</head>

<p>A Declaration to his Highness the Lord Protector, from the Generals at sea, and <reg orig="Comanders">Commanders</reg> of the fleet, as follows.</p>

<p><i>For his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. The Declaration, with the humble Address of the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the Fleet, by them severally subscribed.</i></p>

<p>That these Nations of England, Scotland and Ireland, having been for some years like the Bush which burned, but is not consumed: And though the Nations round about us, stand gazing on to see us made a desolation, as well as a hissing unto them; yet we are hitherto by the mighty power of the Lord, and his <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> outgoings<pb n="2" /> amongst us, made rather an astonishment in our preservation, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a reproach by our <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and devastation. In which great work of the Lord, we acknowledge with thankfulness your Highness hath been a glorious instrument, and hath undergone many hardships, and hazard of all that was near and dear unto you, even to life <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>; and understanding by Providence your Highness is <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with, and hath accepted of the Protection of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in the Government thereof; We hope that the Lord intends a settlement of Peace to these poor distracted Nations; and that <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, with all the People of the Lord shall enjoy and partake of the same under your <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> Protection, according to the rule of the Lord Jesus. And therefore we have thought it necessary as a duty incumbent on us to declare, That we shall willingly be obedient and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to your Highness, in performance of your great Trust, and also in the utmost hazard of our lives (with what else is near and dear unto us) be serviceable unto you, in the station the Lord hath placed you, against your and the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> enemies in our several places and capacities, during our employments. And having had good testimony of your great affection and earning bowels after the weal of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people, we are emboldened and encouraged in all humility to make this following Address.</p>

<p>That your Highness <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be pleased to have a more special eye of favour unto them above others, in regard they are near and dear unto him, who is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings even our Lord Jesus. For which cause he is not ashamed to call them Brethren; And do humbly apprehend, that their <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> will be your <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg>. And to count of them as your greatest jewels, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> doubtless turn to your great advantage. And hereby you will for time to come, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> engage their hearts unto <pb n="3" />you, who in times past have not stood at a distance from you; but your Highness will also engage the great Jehovah, your and their Father be a refuge, shield, and defence unto you, as well as an everlasting rest for you, when all the storms of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> shall cease, which is, and shall be the unfeigned prayers of,</p>

<head level="3"><i>Your Highness most humble and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servants.</i></head>

<p>Signed by the Generals and the several Commanders present in the Fleet.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, Febr. 2.</head>

<p>Paris, the 7th of February, 1654 <em>stilo novo</em>. There is a great alteration made in the perception of the Taxes and Imposts, there being new Offices made, and new Officers created, where old ones are put out of service: and among many remarkable things, it is to be <reg orig="wondred">wondered</reg>, that many Protestants are admitted to places of some honour, and more profit: There is now at present in this City, the Earl of Harcourt his secretary, and one from the Marshal Seneterre; therefore now a Treaty is in hand concerning the Agreement between the Court and the said Earl touching Alsatia, there hath been some progress made in it, but nothing agreed upon. During this Treaty, the siege of Beffort goeth on with as much gallantry as may be expected, considering the season, and the great opposition of the besieged, who neither spare valour nor labour in the defence of that place. The Marshal La Ferte is daily seen in the Trenches, which very much doth animate, and encourage the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>; so that it is expected in a short time you will hear of the surrender of that place.</p>

<p>The great preparations made at Toulon goeth on, and it is variously reported to what intent it is; for some will have it for to get the mastery of the Seas in the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>; others <reg orig="willl">will</reg> have it <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in part that way; and the other part to be sent to the aid of the Venetian State but some who do think themselves wisest, believe that it doth run upon the old design for Naples; and for a confirmation of the same, it is observed that the Duke of Guise doth make money at all hands, having sold and pawned such things whereby to raise a very considerable sum of moneys, and we do hear that he is to go from hence within this <reg orig="Moneth">Month</reg>: but of this more by the next. The Pope seemeth to be very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about making a general peace between us and Spain, and the other Allies; and to that end, we hear of an extraordinary <reg orig="Nuntio">Nuncio</reg> that is now on his journey hither, another being also sent into Spain: Our <pb n="4" /><reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> from Rome is to be here the next week; and now all things are ready for the dancing of the great <reg orig="Balet">Ballet</reg>, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be between this and Shrove Tuesday: and for the consecrating of the young King, it will not be so soon was expected.</p>

<p>The last Post from Scotland, brings this further intelligence; That on the 23 of January, Athol had a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of the Country at a place called Cairane 2 or 3 miles Northeast from Dunkel but had very slender appearance. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> and <em>Wogan</em> lie ill of their wounds at Weems, <em>Wogan</em> is not like to recover: <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Hume</em> with about sixteen more out of the <em>Merch</em> or <em><reg orig="Berwickeshire">Berwickshire</reg></em>, are this week gone to join with those in the Hills; and that the enemy having advertisement that <em>Morgan</em> was marched from <em>Aberdeen</em> with 14 Companies of Foot, and 8 Troops of Horse and Dragoons towards them <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> the same day went out of <em>Murra
yland</em>, towards the Hills, and burnt all the Lord <em><reg orig="Lothams">Lotham's</reg></em> land (the Lord <em><reg orig="Brodies">Brodie's</reg></em> Uncle) because he kept his house out against them in the late infall into the Earl of <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> quarters at Dunkel: There was killed one Capt. <em>Robertson</em>, one Captain <em>Hunter</em> (a young Laird who attended <em>Athol</em>) the Laird of <em>Baillachan</em>, Major <em>Mercer</em> run into the body with a Tuck, and through the arm; <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed he <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not live, and about 20 more slain and desperately wounded.</p>

<p>There came likewise further intelligence from the Navy, certifying that our Fleet hath now set sail, and put to sea from St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helen's</reg> point</em>, they are divided in three squadrons, but are not at so great distance but that upon any occasion they can soon <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> into one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> body, there being Scouts appointed, who are to give notice upon any appearance of the enemy.</p>

<p>From Venice thus, We have received Letters from Constantinople by way of <em>Ragusa</em>, which advise us, That the great Bashaw being returned there with 30 Galleys, was at first well received by the great Turk and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, but <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to give an account of his <reg orig="Summers">Summer's</reg> expedition, he was found guilty in many respects, for not having discharged that Trust reposed in him; and thereupon was condemned to die, which was executed accordingly. They do prepare great Forces to be landed in Candia, to try if they shall after many <reg orig="years">years'</reg> wars, become Masters of that fair island. We are likewise making very good preparations both by Sea and Land, and to that end, no cost is spared to make it ready with all speed possible.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><reg orig="Satturday">Saturday</reg> February 4.</head>

<p>The last Post from Newcastle brings intelligence, that there is little news in those parts, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the intercepting a great many Letters that came from the Scottish Cavaliers to the Malignant party here, but they were by a person of honour sent up to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>. The truth is, there is such continual meetings of the Cavaliers, that any may judge without the intercepting they have great designs in hand. Here is much doings about the Quakers, they were at a place called Hasington on a Sabbath day, and as they were speaking to the Minister, the Country people fell upon them, and abused them very much, almost killed one or two; but going out falling upon their knees, seeking to God to forgive them, saying, they knew not what they did, and afterwards speaking to them, many of the people were so convinced of the Evil they had done in beating of them, that returning back to the residue of the people that was on the Green in the Town, begging to accuse one another, as the occasion of beating those men who had done them no hurt, nor opposed the Minister till he had done, and the Minister being earnestly pressed to go and discourse with them, and he refusing, this discourse went so nigh, that the Townsmen generally went to go by the Ears, and did so exceedingly beat one another, that such a fight hath not been seen. There was very few that went home without their faces or head broken.</p>

<p><em>From Deal February the 2.</em> Here are little news at present, a good number of ships bound to the Southward, as also for several Ports of France, are gone from hence, &amp; from Dover. The French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> do still haunt about these parts, and are often seen, and as soon as any of our ships set sail to give them chase, they get their own coast before he can come up to them, there being two at present who are riding in Calice Road.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the <em>City of London</em>, have <reg orig="solemnely">solemnly</reg> invited His Highness the Lord Protector and the <em><reg orig="Councel">Council</reg></em> to taste some of their <em>City</em> Delicates, and his Highness hath nominated Wednesday next to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> set apart for that purpose, and great preparations are already making for the reception of his Highness and his attendants.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, Febr. 6.</head>

<p>From <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> we understand, that two of our men of War, chased three Brest men of War, upon the coast of France, but being near unto Harbour, they got away from ours, though not without much difficulty, for we gave them many <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, and came near to the boarding of one of them.</p>

<p>We had also from some part of our Fleet intelligence, that a Fleet of about 200 sail of Dutch Merchantmen, are gone very lately, they are bound for <em>Spain</em> and for Lisbon in <em>Portugal</em>, but if any of our Fleet meet with them, their journey may be shortened.</p>

<p>This day came more Letters from Scotland, which <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>; that since the late fight betwixt the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. Johnstons, and a party of the Highlanders, whereof you have had a true Relation before, the said <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> sending forth a party to clear the Coast of the Enemy, they met with another party of <em>Athols</em> men of about 60 horse and Dragoons, and after a sharp conflict we killed four, wounded many, took above twenty prisoners, and put the rest to flight.</p>

<p>Upon complaint made to the Vice King of Naples, that some wicked persons daily commit <reg orig="out-rages">outrages</reg> and take to Sanctuary to secure them from the Law, he writ to Cardinal <em>Trivultio</em> to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> his Holiness thereof, who returned answer, that such offenders should no longer be protected, but brought to punishment.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3">Tuesday, February 31.</head>

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of London having invited His Highness the Lord Protector to dinner at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocers'</reg> Hall; and Wednesday being the day appointed, the several Companies of the said <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> had warning from the said Lord Mayor to meet at Guild-Hall in their <reg orig="Gownes">Gowns</reg>, and from thence to place themselves according to their superiority in the streets, stretching themselves as far as Temple Bar, to attend His Highness coming by through the City, and for his entertainment there is as great preparations as hath been known for any Feast of late times; I could give you some particulars thereof, but that I love not to anticipate the Intelligence properly belonging to that day whereon it happeneth.</p>

<p>From the <reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg> we hear of Ships going forth to trade for <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> and other parts. Several Merchants ships are also come home, and will shortly be in the River Thames. They also hear by some Ships, that we have taken several prizes from the Dutch since the going forth of our Fleet to Sea.</p>

<p>From Holyhead thus. The <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> on this Coast have done much mischief of late, and taken a small vessel or two which used to trade for Ireland, one Capt. Price came into this harbour the last week, and brought in with him a small Irish vessel, she had little in her, but some of the men in her say, that she was a kind of Passage boat, and went often betwixt Ireland and France, she is light and nimble, and could creep in at a small Crick and go away undiscovered.</p>

<p>We have little news out of Ireland, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the present government is <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the Officers of the Army, and for the generality It is already signed by the major part of them.</p>

<p>Here is a great noise of the insurrections of the Highlanders in Scotland, the report is that they <unclear><!--approx 8 characters--></unclear> exceedingly, but they which are most knowing in these affairs make little of it knowing that they will not stand in the day of <reg orig="battell">battle</reg>, and their <reg orig="principalls">principals</reg> so weak, that there is few knowing men that will hazard themselves upon that account.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London,</em> Printed by <em>E. Alsop</em> 1654.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>