<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PolInform01">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Politique Informer, Issue 1</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The <reg orig="Politique">Politic</reg></head>
<head level="1">INFORMER.</head>
<head level="3">COMMUNICATING,</head>
<head level="2">The Mysteries of State, to the People of Great <reg orig="BRITTAIN">BRITAIN</reg>.</head>

<p>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 23 of January, to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 30 of January. 1654.<!-- final digit corrected by hand (by Thomason?) to 3 i.e. 1653--></p>

<p>I hope no <reg orig="juditious">judicious</reg> <reg orig="States-man">Statesman</reg>, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Citizen, will rashly or unadvisedly censure me, before they have seriously perused and read me over: Had not the Gentlemen that formerly writ this Pamphlet, <reg orig="walkt">walked</reg> in forbidden paths, he had been unacquainted with the miseries of a Prison, and might with safety and security have published his acute Informations, as well as other with toleration vent their dull Intelligence; and whether it was his weakness or wilfulness, We not dispute; But give me leave to tell him, the Revolutions and Changes which this Commonwealth hath sustained, ought not to be questioned by every Subject; for private men, who know little of, or converse little with State transactions and affairs, are not competent Judges, when the observation of the letter of the Law is of a dangerous and <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> import to the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> safety; but rather such persons whose daily residence is in the <em>Mount of State Negotiations</em>, who by the advantage of the ground where they stand, may very reasonably be conceived to be in a full capacity perfectly to discover and understand on what hinge the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> interest and safety turneth, and what means and <reg orig="interposures">interposers</reg> are most promising for their procurement, promotion, and establishment; for the reason or end of the Law, ought in all cases to be preferred before the Letter; nor hath any Law whatsoever any binding force, further <reg orig="then">than</reg> the execution<pb n="1" /> of it, or subjection unto it, is consistent with the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> safety and good: This is apparently made out to us in Scripture, <i>2 Sam. 2. 10</i>. we read that eleven of the twelve Tribes of <em>Israel</em> did side with the House of <em>Saul</em> against <em><reg orig="Davids">David's</reg></em> advancement over them, being for a time highly unwilling and discontented that he should be their King; yet afterwards flourished under his Government like a green Bay-tree, and saw many years of prosperity and Peace. <reg orig="Therfore">Therefore</reg> such <reg orig="persons">persons'</reg> sin against an express <reg orig="commandement">commandment</reg> of God, who under what pretext soever, shall openly dictate disobedience unto those Powers, which God (whether in Judgement or in Mercy) hath most justly placed and appointed over them.</p>

<p>The Rise of all Monarchies and States hath been as much by their policy as strength, these are not to be separated, where either of them is wanting, there is little hopes of that <reg orig="States">State's</reg> advancement. This his Holiness the Pope of Rome is not ignorant of, who fearing lest the two Protestant Estates of England and Holland should accord, endeavours to mediate a peace between France and Spain, not that he aims at the title of <reg orig="Peace-maker">Peacemaker</reg>, but hopes by that means to obstruct the Treaty, and advance Popery; indeed it <reg orig="behooves">behoves</reg> him to bestir his stumps, for if the two Sea thunderers agree, it is hoped they will make all <em>Italy</em> to tremble, and the very <reg orig="Wals">Walls</reg> of <em>Rome</em> to shake.</p>

<p>There hath been notable tampering at the <em>Hague</em> by the Agents of <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> <em>Princes</em>, to obstruct our proceedings, and some false <em>Scots</em> have been forward to thrust their fingers into the <reg orig="pye">pie</reg>, though as yet to little purpose; but it is an old saying, <i>Ill egging makes ill begging</i>: This ensuing Letter will discover somewhat of their <reg orig="designes">designs</reg>.</p>

<p><i>SIR,</i></p>

<p>There is brought into Flushing two Virginia prizes, the one of 18, the other of 11 pieces of Ordnance, laden with Tobacco, Sugar, Indico, and <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg> -wool, taken near the English Channel, and two other prizes are brought into the <reg orig="Vlie">Ulie</reg>. There are divers ships come from the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>, and two hundred are expected from France; also some East-India ships are come likewise into the <reg orig="Vlie">Ulie</reg>, and the whole Fleet is said to be within sight of Land, but to our great grief we hear that four or five of them are stranded, and the goods like to<pb n="2" /> be lost. He that takes and <em>Eele</em> by the <em>Tail</em> hath but slippery hold, and however the Dutch pretend <em>Peace</em>, their actions <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the contrary; for in <em>Zealand</em> they are setting forth 20 new ships of War, of 150, 136 to 130 foot long, and from 30 to 38 foot broad. There are divers <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> come hither from several Princes, and it is feared, will rather <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to obstruct, <reg orig="then">than</reg> promote peace with England. Middleton hath lately received a Letter from Glencarn, giving him notice that he hath made himself Master of <reg orig="Sterlingshire">Stirlingshire</reg>, and of the Northern quarter of Scotland, and that they <reg orig="onely">only</reg> want the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> presence, and some more Arms and Ammunition. The Deputies of the States arrived here yesterday from England, and thereupon the Lord States assembled this day, and the Deputies made report of these Negotiations; it is said that the English would exclude the King of Denmark in the Articles, and therefore that point remained undenied, till the ratification of the Articles.</p>

<p>The Zealanders are as inveterate as ever, and will not <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of the peace, but do persist for war; they say there that the English will not have a Peace <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they buy it at a dear rate, and with ready money; which the Zealanders look upon as a peace that will be dishonourable, <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>, <reg orig="disadvantagious">disadvantageous</reg>, and not lasting: but we that are Merchants must pray and desire peace, for if these miserable wars continue, we shall be quite undone for want of trade, which is the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> support of these countries.</p>

<p>I have sent you here <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>, a Narrative of a paper printed at Haerlem, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> <i>Peace, or true news of the Peace concluded between the United Provinces, and the Commonwealth of England.</i> The substance whereof being contracted is to this effect, <em>viz</em>. First, That the Deputies of Holland by the dissolution of the last Parliament, and the transferring the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the said Commonwealth of England to <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector, had been interrupted three days in their Negotiation. 2. That on the third of January, 1653, they treated very close with the English Commissioners at Whitehall, and the eight very near perfected the Treaty, which was not brought to a full end because of some difficulty. 3. Thereupon the Lordships (as they had done sometimes before) declaring to be desirous to return home, and demanding a <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> to that effect, it was granted them the ninth day, and they being gone to <unclear>Gravesend</unclear>, the said Treaty hath there <unclear>being resumed</unclear> in hand by the English, and all<pb n="3" /> the Articles renewed, whereupon the Allies and Confederates were comprehended in it. And that the fourteenth the Peace was there agreed on, concluded and signed, God Almighty be praised; being a great blessing for the Protestants throughout <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>. 4. That afterward the Lord Deputies of Holland, after many loving <reg orig="imbracements">embracements</reg>, went the 16 into a ship appointed for them and ready to set sail, and their Lordships arrived in the Mase the 21, and about noon arrived at Schiedam, from whence they came that evening to the Hague, where, upon their coming, and the report they have made of the peace concluded, and of all the circumstances, there hath been great rejoicing. 5. That the 22 the States sent Letters to all the Towns and Burroughs concerning this great and good <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, that every one might be informed thereof. 6. The time will not yet give me leave (good <reg orig="Country men">Countrymen</reg> ) to afford you more particulars of the Treaty; I shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="adde">add</reg>, that the Lords States <reg orig="wil">will</reg> speedily call for a meeting, to agree, <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, and approve the said Articles of Peace. God grant it.</p>

<p><i>Hague, Jan. 22 stilo novo, 1654.</i></p>

<p>I shall not stand to dispute the truth of that contained in the aforesaid Letter, but it pleases God to be as favourable to us as he hath <reg orig="beene">been</reg> within this eight or ten days, they will be glad to embrace <em>peace</em> upon any <reg orig="termes">terms</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes lately taken from the Dutch.</i></head>

<p>A Vessel from New-Haven, forced on shore upon the French coast by the Diamond.</p>

<p>An Holland Virginia Merchant ship run on board and sunk by the Ruby <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>A prize of Wines taken by the Middleborough, is brought into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>.</p>

<p>A Dutch Merchant ship richly laden, sunk upon the coasts of France, upon a chase.</p>

<p>A French man taken by Captain Heaton, laden with Wines, sent into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>.</p>

<p>Two Dutch ships sunk near the coasts of Norway.</p>

<p>A <reg orig="Fly-boat">Flyboat</reg>, called the Spotted Oxe, an Holland Merchant ship coming from <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, laden with Wines, of 140 Lasts, taken by the Captain Hide, sent into Dartmouth.</p>

<p>A Dutch Merchant ship taken upon the coasts of Scotland.</p>

<p>One Dutch ship sunk, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, near the Pole head.</p>

<p>A Dutch Flute belonging to Monnickedam, taken near <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>.</p>

<p>A small Vessel called the Hope of Campheir, with Deal boards and ballast, brought in by the Expedition.</p>

<p>Another ship coming from Dantzick, belonging to the same place.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>The noble Reception of His Excellence the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> by her Majesty of <em>Sweden</em>, deserves to be recommended to posterity; And that succeeding Generations may record as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> the <reg orig="Vertues">Virtues</reg> of this royal Queen, as the Victories of Her <reg orig="Heroick">Heroic</reg> Father, I have here inserted the Copy of a Letter from a Gentleman of quality belonging to the Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, now at the <em>Swedish Court</em> in <em>Upsalah</em>.</p>

<p><i>SIR.</i></p>

<p>I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give you an account of our journey from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> to <em>Upsalah</em>, which hath been very long and difficult, yet our God hath brought us lately the last night. We went out of <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> on Wednesday the 29 of November. The Magistrates came solemnly to take their leaves, the Citizens were in Arms in the <reg orig="Market-place">Marketplace</reg>, and the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> upon the Works, as we passed they gave us several Volleys of small and great shot. The first night my Lord <em><reg orig="Lagerfields">Lagerfield's</reg></em> Secretary met us from the Court, whither he posted to give the Qu. notice of our arrival, and she sent him back to attend my Lord in his <reg orig="journy">journey</reg>, and to see that we had accommodation, which was a great assistance to us in our journey. Our his Train consisted of 83 saddle Horses, 2 Coaches, and about 60 <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg>, few of them carrying not above one Trunk a piece, being very <reg orig="smal">small</reg>, and drawn with one horse apiece, being brought in by the Country at the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> command, as every stage. The fifth <reg orig="days">day's</reg> journey we came to a City called <em>Scazez</em>, and the tenth day Mr. <em>Andrew Potley</em> met us by the way, and one Mr <em>Lily Chrone</em> a servant of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, who was sent to visit my Lord in his journey. The 11 days journey we came to <em>Erbrow</em>, where we met with Letters from England. The 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> journey we came to a City called <em>Westraaz</em>, and from thence went to a Town called <em>Eucopin</em> within 4 leagues of <em>Upsalah</em>; At night Letters came from the Grand Master of the Ceremonies to Mr. <em>Lily Chrone</em>, signifying that the Queen and her Nobles were amazed at his Excellencies being advanced so far in so short a time, that Her Majesty was disposed to receive him with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary respect and honours, and could not make preparation accordingly in so short a time, therefore desired him to repose there till <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, whose commands my Lord obeyed.</p>

<p>Tuesday morning we went from thence to <em>Upsalah</em>, the Weather continuing <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hard; Half a league before we came to Town, the Master of the Ceremonies met his Excellency, and told him that the Queen had sent him to congratulate his safe arrival, and to conduct him to <em>Upsalah</em>: About a quarter of a league from the Town, two Senators met his Excellency, that is, two of the Council of State, they spake in the Swedish tongue, to the same effect as the Master of Ceremonies, as their Interpreter told us; My Lord answered them in English, that the respect which her Majesty did bear to the Commonwealth of England, appeared in the honourable reception of him their servant, which he desired to acknowledge with thanks to Her Maj: They then brought his Excellency into a rich Coach of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, where the two Senators and<pb n="5" /> Master of the Ceremonies sate with him. There were divers other Coaches of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, with the Spanish Agents, and many <reg orig="Noblemens">Noblemen's</reg> Coaches, in all eighteen, every one with 6 horses, and a great many of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> servants on Horseback, they brought his Excellence to his lodging and then left him; the Rooms of Entertainment and four or five Bed Chambers were furnished with the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Hangings and Beds, the Bed in his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Chamber richly embroidered with gold; About half an hour after came in a Gentleman of the Bed-chamber to my Lord, and told his Excellency that the Queen had sent to see how he did after his journey, to bid him welcome, and my Lord returned his thanks to Her Majesty: then Mr. <em>Laggerfieldt</em> was sent to see if we wanted any accommodations and to take care that we might be supplied: Afterwards the Master of the Ceremonies desired of his Excellency a Copy of his Credentials, which he had ready and gave to him, who carried them presently to the Queen, and left them with her, and returned back to accompany his Lordship to supper. In a Lobby next to the <reg orig="with drawing">withdrawing</reg> Room, is a constant guard of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, beyond that a very fair Room, which was very well furnished, with a great deal of Plate, and many <reg orig="waxe">wax</reg> Candles in it; two Tables were plentifully <reg orig="furnisht">furnished</reg>, one of his Excellence, the other for his Steward, and over his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> Seat hung a Canopy of State. About the middle of Supper the Master of the Ceremonies began a health to his Lordship, which he denying to pledge, some high words passed between them; but it was afterwards moderated, and they are since reconciled. The Queen hath appointed his Highness <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> to be speedily audited; and then you shall have the Copy of Her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Answer.</p>

<p><i>Upsalah, Decemb. 22.</i></p>

<p>Take this from Scotland, The Enemy is much <unclear>startled</unclear> at <reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg> revolt, and think there is some design in it, Col. <reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg> Cap. Lieutenant fell into their quarters near Dunkel took 10 prisoners, 16 horses, and killed two on the place. But a party of Capt. Elsmore were not so <reg orig="successfull">successful</reg> his Lieutenant being sent with 30 horse to rescue some sheep taken by the Enemy, pursued them, and recovered their prize; but returning were <unclear><reg orig="Ambuscadoed">Ambuscaded</reg> </unclear>, and had an intricate retreat; the Cornet, one Corporal, and two Troopers were killed, and 7 taken; but divers of the Enemy lost their lives, amongst the rest Col. Wogan is supposed to be one, who charged first with the English. The Spring comes on apace, and then our forces will take the field, and soon quell these insolent fellows. We have there at the least 20 <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> Regiments, which for satisfaction of the curious I shall here nominate.</p>

<p>General <reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Penwicks">Penwick's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Riches">Riche's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Fairfaxes">Fairfax's</reg> Col. <reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Overtons">Overton's</reg>, that which was Major General <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Alureds">Alured's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Daniels">Daniels'</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Cobbets">Cobbet's</reg>, Col <reg orig="Salmons">Salmon's</reg>, Col. <reg orig="Thomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg>, part of Col. <reg orig="Sandersons">Sanderson's</reg>, the Company at Dunbarton, besides going to Scotland, Major General <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, Commissioner <reg orig="Whalleys">Whaley's</reg>, part of Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg>.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his Right Honourable <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, set forth an Ordinance declaring, That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be high Treason for any person (not being an Officer, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg>, or Member of the Army) to plot contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the stirring up of any mutiny in the said Army, or if any person shall invite or assist any <reg orig="Forrainers">Foreigners</reg> invading England, Scotland, or Ireland, or if any person shall plot, contrive, or <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the betraying or yielding up any City, Town, Fort, Ship or Vessel, belonging to this Commonwealth, or if any person shall <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg> or imagine the death of the Lord Protector for the time being, or if any person or persons shall maliciously or advisedly either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector, and the people in Parliament assembled, are not the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> authority of this Commonwealth, or if any person or person whatsoever, shall proclaim, declare, publish, or <reg orig="any way">anyway</reg> promote <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, eldest son to the late King, or <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em> one other of his sons, or any other the issue or posterity of the said late King or any other person or persons, claiming by, from, or under him or them, or either or any of them, or any of the Dominions to them, or either of them belonging; or if any person or persons shall give, keep or hold any intelligence whatsoever, by Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart</em>, the late Queen their mother, or any of them; or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the money of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: or shall bring any false money into this land, either counterfeit or other, like to the money of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (knowing such money to be false) to the intent to merchandize, or otherwise; or if any person or persons shall hereafter <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> forge or counterfeit any such kind of Coin, either of Gold or Silver, which is not the proper <reg orig="coyn">coin</reg> of this Commonwealth, and yet is or shall be current within the same; or shall bring from the parts beyond the Seas into this Commonwealth, or into any the Dominions of the same, any such false or counterfeit copy of money to the intent to utter or make payment with the same, within the Commonwealth. Or if any person or persons shall Impair, <reg orig="Falsifie">Falsify</reg>, <unclear>Clip, Wash, Round File</unclear> and Scale, or lighten any the proper monies of this Commonwealth, <unclear>or false</unclear> monies or coins of any other place allowed, or suffered to be current within this Commonwealth.</p>

<p>Some persons are already apprehended for breach of this Ordnance, doubtless they were afraid they should lost their <em>Turn</em>, they might have made less haste, for I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> <reg orig="they'l">they'll</reg> <reg orig="finde">find</reg> cold entertainment at Paddington.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>The dejected Cavaliers in the Netherlands, though they have empty purses, yet they are full of Inventions to advance their <em><reg orig="Deer">Dear</reg> <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg></em> interest; and have reported throughout the United Provinces, <i>That the Scots have taken the City of Aberdeen and 2000 Horse from the English</i>; and feign the story thus. <i>That the English having gathered from Aberdeen and other <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> a great number of Horses intended to fall upon the <em>Highlanders</em>, who were met in a very considerable Body; these latter having warning thereof, and being acquainted with the Country; did cut the way to the English, insomuch that they were forced to march through a <reg orig="Morasse">Morass</reg> ground, where the Horses stuck fast, and they were forced to <reg orig="flye">fly</reg> to <em>Aberdeen</em> a foot back, to which place the <em>Highlanders</em> <reg orig="persued">pursued</reg> them, and afterward forced the Town.</i></p>

<p><em>Mazarin</em> <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> the Machiavel in the French Court, and hath <reg orig="prevail'd">prevailed</reg> so far with the King, that his brother Cardinal, <em>de Retz</em>, is commanded to be kept close prisoner, and cannot procure a mouthful of fresh <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, though he should pawn his <em>Cap</em> to purchase it. <em>Conte</em> is making his peace with the King, and <em>Conde</em> hath a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time to come in, which if he refuse, his Estate is to be sequested, and he proclaimed Traitor, and to be executed (<i>if they can catch him</i>) without further <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg>. The <em>Rentiers</em> in <em>Paris</em> grow numerous, and their discontents high; and there is a Proclamation published, prohibiting all persons to meet in or about the City or Suburbs, to fight with any manner of weapons, or to throw stones at one another; and the King of <em>France</em> hath caused some English ships to be arrested and stayed.</p>

<p>There is a Declaration signed unanimously by the Officers of the English <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, who protest to live and die in defence of the present Government.</p>

<p>There are divers Dutch ships come into Vlie and the Texel from the <em>Straits</em>, and some prizes have been brought into Flushing by the Dutch Freebooters. General <em>Pen</em> rides with the English Fleet without St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point and hath sent divers <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> <reg orig="East-ward">Eastward</reg>, to convoy 12 <reg orig="Merchant-men">Merchantmen</reg> into the <reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg>. Those eight <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> formerly sent out to <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> the Channel, are returned again, and have brought in with them two Dutch prizes.</p>

<p>There happened a very sad accident on Friday last, part of the <reg orig="in-side">inside</reg> of the ancient, famous and Metropolitan Church of St <em>Paul</em> in London fell down, to the ground, which so amazed the Inhabitants near it, that they thought there had been a general Earthquake: As yet it is not certainly known how many were killed and <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> buried under the stones and rubbish; report speaks of four of five, but not knowing it to be certain, I refer you till my next for further in Information.</p>

<p>The printed Government gives much satisfaction to out friends in <em>Scotland</em>, and is <reg orig="Re-printing">Reprinting</reg> at <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em>, and the Officers of every Regiment are signing Representations of their approbations hereof; divers of which are already sent in, and the rest will be speedily read; in which they declare to live and die with His Highness.</p>

<p>Published according to Order.</p>
 
<p><i>London, printed by Robert Wood. 1654.</i></p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>