<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="PolInform02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Politique Informer, Issue 2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The <reg orig="Politique">Politic</reg></head>
<head level="1">INFORMER.</head>
<head level="3">Wherein is Represented;</head>

<p><i>The Agreement of the States of <em>Holland, Zealand, Gelderland</em>, and <em>West-Frieslandt</em>, concerning the sending over Deputies to the Lord Protector of <em>England</em>, to desire a Cessation of all further Hostility, till the Articles of Peace are ratified; And a Declaration of the Council of the Admiralty thereupon. A great Victory obtained by the <em>English</em> against the <em>Highlanders</em>, the total routing of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> New Levies near <em>Dunkel</em>, with the taking of 50 horse, and many prisoners, and forcing the rest to <reg orig="flye">fly</reg> into the Woods and <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. General <em>Glencarn's</em> blocking up the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Burgy</em>, with 1200 foot, and 300 horse, besides Dragoons; and the taking of divers <em>English</em> Officers by the Enemy. The last Letters from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, informing of the true state and condition of our Fleet, of several fights between some of the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> and the <em>Brest</em> men of War, and of divers Prizes brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, Falmouth</em> and <em>Newcastle</em>; With the proceedings of the L. Protector and his Council.</i></p>

<p>From <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan. 30, to <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Febr. 6. 1654.</p>

<p>In these lamentable <em>Times</em> [when the <em><reg orig="Divel">Devil</reg></em> and his <em>Agents</em> seek to <em>Work</em> our <em>destruction</em>] 'tis a hard thing not to meet with a <em>sad Subject</em>, and yet it is more difficult to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> a <em>true one</em>. For, the world is so full of strange News and different Opinions, that every man carries a several party in his own bosom; And he that thinks to write to please all, had need to have as many hands as <em>Argos</em> had eyes, and those fitted with all the variety of fancies as either Wit or Invention can possibly bring forth: Now that I may<pb n="1" /> avoid the Character of so strange a Monster, I shall <reg orig="onely">only</reg> apply <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> to the truth of Intelligence, and then if any are displeased the quarrel is not worth the owning: And that <reg orig="every thing">everything</reg> may appear in its naked colours, and the present posture of Occurrences <reg orig="shew">show</reg> themselves in their proper and bare existence, I shall refer the Reader to the subsequent matter.</p>

<p>We have received Information from Holland, that the Dutch Merchants were drunk with joy, that the peace was agreed upon, and therefore with all expedition made ready their ships of trading; but the Lords States considering their might some danger accrue, if they should put to Sea before the Articles were ratified on all sides: Commanded this ensuing Declaration to be printed and published.</p>

<p>A DECLARATION</p>

<p><i>By the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at Amsterdam.</i></p>

<p>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Admiralty residing at Amsterdam, To all those before whom these presents shall come, Greeting.</p>

<p>Let it be known, that it being conceived, thought, and apparent, that upon the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Deputies of this State from England, to make report how far the Treaty there is by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> grace and favour effected, some Merchants and Masters of Merchants ships, upon presumption of a Cessation of hostility have been so forward as to have brought out their ships and goods, and have beyond their hope suffered <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>; We have found good, and resolved to give warning to all and every one whom it concerneth, as also <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> is warned by these presents; That the former hostility doth yet continue, and that it is not fit nor convenient that <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> should in regard of the Treaty, think <reg orig="him self">himself</reg> secure, before upon the continuation of the Negotiation, there shall be a Cessation of the aforesaid hostility proclaimed.</p>

<p><i>Acted in the Assembly of the said <reg orig="Cunncel">Council</reg> of the 26 of January, 1653---4.</i></p>

<p>F. HERBERTS.</p>
<p>DAVID WILDT.</p>

<p>From Copenhagen it is certified That the Dutch Fleet which were beaten in there again by some English <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> from <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, are resolved to Winter there. The City had suffered much by a late fire, had not the King and Court bestirred themselves to quench it, which <reg orig="onely">only</reg> consumed two or three houses. They hear every day of the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> great respect to the English Ambassador, which increaseth their fears and jealousies, and now they seem more afraid <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, that the Dutch will leave them in the <reg orig="bryers">briers</reg>. But they may comfort themselves in this, That they have not much wool to lose.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector hath consulted with his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, about the regulating of the Laws of this Nation, and particularly of the Chancery, for the general good of the Nation. Also an Order is appointed to be drawn up by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, for propagating of the Gospel in the Northern Counties of England.</p>

<p>Mr. Feak, and Mr. Simpson are likewise committed prisoners to Windsor Castle. And another also was set upon a wooden horse at Tower-hill, and had his ears cut, for forging of an Order in the name of the Commissioners of the Navy, to <reg orig="cousen">cousin</reg> the State of nine pounds.</p>

<p>Some Aldermen of the City of London, have this Week made several Addresses to his Highness the Lord protector.</p>

<p>And there is published an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance appointing a Committee for the Army, and Treasurers at War.</i></p>

<p>The last Letters from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, that a great Flemish ship put on shore at <em>Dartmouth</em>, having <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one dead man aboard her, some Canary ships are safely arrived at Falmouth, and 4 ships from Malago are come into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>. The Wetwang and the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, brought two Dutch Capers of 6 Guns apiece and 100 prisoners, into Newcastle And some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken two ships with the Haven of Brest. The <reg orig="Sea men">Seamen</reg> with an unanimous consent, have presented a Declaration to his Highness, with an Address subscribed by the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the fleet. Wherein they acknowledge their thankfulness, that the Lord hath preserved his highness from many eminent dangers, and understanding he hath accepted of the protection of this Commonwealth, declare they will be faithful and obedient to his highness, in performance of their trust, and also that in the utmost hazard of their lives they will be <reg orig="service able">serviceable</reg> unto his highness in the station that the Lord hath placed him.</p>

<p><em>Conde</em> refuseth to come in to the King of <em>France</em>, and his Brother <em>Conti</em> <reg orig="enclines">inclines</reg> to the marriage with <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>. The titular King of <em>Scots</em> hath with prince <em>Rupert</em> and others of his council, been several times deliberating about weighty <reg orig="affaairs">affairs</reg>, and his friends report, that Gen. <em>O' Brian</em> hath got a body in <em>Ireland</em> of 4000 foot and 1000 horse, and doth fence the Castle of <em>Dingle</em> by the <reg orig="sea side">seaside</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Zealand</em> is come Information, That their States are gone to the Hague to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in confirmation of the Treaty with England. That the Assembly at the Hague is dissolved till the 20 of Febr. next, and that they desire a Cessation with England, till the<pb n="3" /> rest of the provinces have ratified the Articles of peace. The French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> hath audience, but his propositions are kept secret.</p>

<p>It is verified from <em>Scotland</em>, that all the English Regiments there (except some few of Major General <reg orig="Harisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, and those chiefly of the Welch Troop) do well approve of the New Government, and the Officers generally send in their Addresses, to be presented to his Highness to that purpose. There was a Shallop lately built up, and four Guns put in her to secure Trade in the River <em>Clyde</em>, and to prevent the <reg orig="High-landers">Highlanders</reg> falling into Renfrewshire, but one Col. Harriot came with some Boats from the Lough in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> and secured her. And they took also a Lieutenant of General <reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg> Regiment and 7 or 8 other Officers near Falkirk, and <reg orig="caried">carried</reg> to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. Colonel <em><reg orig="Humphreys">Humphrey's</reg></em> Troop is come to Musleborough, and they covetously expect the other two Regiments.</p>

<p><i>The Copy of another Letter from Dalkeith, dated Jan. 25.</i></p>

<p><em>Sir</em>, The 19 instant, Col. <em>Daniel</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of St. Johnstons, having intelligence that the Enemy were in and about Dunkel, sent out 100 horse and 100 dragoons under the command of Lieutenant <em>Ashby</em>, of col. <em><reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg></em> Regiment, who came very near the Town undiscovered, and the forlorn fell in with two of their Scouts, they made some resistance at the Baracado, but our few dragoons did beat them thence, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> six or seven at their entrance into the town. And when the rest were <reg orig="entred">entered</reg>, our forlorn <reg orig="persued">pursued</reg> them that upon the alarm got away to the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> and passages betwixt the town and Blair, where they <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> seven more, and bestowed upon most of the rest the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> mark. They totally <!--dispersed??--><unclear>dispierced</unclear> <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> new Levies, dismounted all his Troopers, and brought fifty horses and many prisoners, with good store of plunder. <em>Athol</em> was there himself, with about 150 foot, who escaped to the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>. The horse <reg orig="persued">pursued</reg> them above two miles beyond the town, and wounded many; but being eager in the <reg orig="persuit">pursuit</reg>, and the Woods within two or three yards of the passage, when they <reg orig="knockt">knocked</reg> them of their horses they would creep into their thickets and secure themselves. Captain <em><reg orig="Elsemores">Elsemore's</reg></em> Lieutenant and captain <reg orig="Ker">Kerr</reg>, did kill each other, both of them firing at more <reg orig="then">than</reg> four yards distance with their <reg orig="blunderbushes">blunderbusses</reg>, and fell from their horses immediately. It was a seasonable mercy both to <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg> their height upon <em><reg orig="Drummonds">Drummond's</reg></em> business, and also to<pb n="4" /> lay a discouragement upon that <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> people. There was one of <reg orig="collonel">colonel</reg> <reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg> own troop killed, and some of the prisoners confess, that col. Wogan was run through the shoulder at Drummond, and lies now at Weyms. The <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> are now in Elgin, Glencarn with about 1200 foot and 300 horse besides dragoons. They have <reg orig="blockt">blocked</reg> up Burgye, which is a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of ours. Kenmore is at Forres, and keeps his Guards upon the River Findern to scour the passage from <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>; but colonel Morgan advanced towards them the 20 instant, with 14 companies of, and eight troops of horse and dragoons.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em>, Jan. 27.</p>

<p>The forces of the Duke of Lorain are about Liege, and commit all <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> of hostility, insomuch that no body can travel thereabouts; whereupon the Elector commanded out a party against them, who fell upon them about the town of Thuyn, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> 500 of them. Whereupon the Duke of Lorain proclaimed open wars against the said Elector, and hath taken the castle of Orsey, where many Bores and country people had fled for refuge, he found there two or three hundred horses, and took 750 pistols from the Bores.</p>

<p>The 18 of Jan. Captain <em>Mill</em>, commander of the Falmouth <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>, fell foul with four Brest men of War, of which <em>Beech</em> was one, with his flag in his main top, which gave chase to four <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels bound for Rochel from Barnstable, laden with herrings and coals, with which men of War he engaged <reg orig="sixe">six</reg> hours, some 25 leagues southwest of Scilly, and put them to flight, and saved those <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels from their hands. Afterwards he fell foul upon one <em>Smith</em> of Brest, which had with him <unclear>Partets</unclear> Vessel of <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> bound for <reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg>, which he had in possession four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, which Vessel he redeemed and took seventeen Frenchmen in him belonging to the said <unclear>Smith</unclear>, and sent them to Falmouth. And the 23 he came up with nine stout <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships of France, which came from Falmouth. And the 23 he came up with nine stout Merchants ships of France, which came from Marseilles, whom he fought a while with, but night approaching they all gave him the slip, and escaped.</p>

<p>The two Generals are still in Stoakes Bay, from whom there is come a confirmation of the prizes lately taken, and likewise an account of what Squadrons they have sent out.</p>

<p>There is one <em>Orton Brooker</em> hath obtained Licence to dig in some suspected places for Treasure long hid.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>Concerning the State Transactions in <em>Sweden</em>, <reg orig="betweene">between</reg> the <em><reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg></em> most Excellent Majesty and the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> for the Commonwealth of England, this ensuing Letter will certainly inform you.</p>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>We are now at <em>Upsalah</em>, where the Queen resides by reason the Plague is at <em>Stockholm</em>. My Lord was entertained with very much respect, and on the 23 of December my Lord had Audience; and the Queen heard him with as much Gravity and Majesty, as to my apprehension might be composed in a Woman, if not in a man; and my Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> having had twice private Audience since, commendeth her to be the acutest Woman that ever he met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and to be admired for her knowledge in <reg orig="publike">public</reg> affairs, knowing the transactions of State far beyond his expectation. Here are several <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> come to reside from <em>Spain, France, Holland, Denmark</em> and <em>Russia</em>: And though they endeavour to obstruct my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> proceedings, there is very great hopes of effecting the business his Excellence came hither about, the Queen having declared such readiness and freedom to treat with my Lord about it. For the Queen told my Lord, that she esteemed it a great honour, that the Parliament had been pleased to send an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> to her, especially of his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> condition, and that she <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> would take care, during his abode there, that not the least injury should be offered to him nor his company. And further said, that in the transaction she would manifest the affection she bore to the Commonwealth, and that she not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> desired to renew former <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> between them, but to enter into a nearer Union <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore.</i></p>

<p>Upsalah. Jan. 1654.</p>

<p>There came also to my hand a Pamphlet, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>Strena Vavasoriensis, A <reg orig="New-Years">New Year's</reg> <reg orig="guift">gift</reg> for the Welch-Itinerants;</i> Or, <i>A <em>Hue-and-Cry</em> after Mr. Vavasor Powel.</i> Wherein the Author, after he had touched upon those places of Scripture (which with <reg orig="infinit">infinite</reg> others <em>Powel</em> wrested and <reg orig="mis-applied">misapplied</reg>) then he proceeded upon his <em>Seditious</em> and <em>Invective Accusations</em>. And <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg>, that first <i>Powel abused the honourable Council</i>, and called their Proclamation, <i>A Libel</i>. Secondly, <i>That He basely traduced the Commanders, Officers, and Soldiers of the Army</i>; nay (their Wives and families escaped not the lash [<i><reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> my <reg orig="Authuor">Author</reg></i>] of <em>his Tongue</em>; and told the <em>Sword-men</em> in <em>General</em>, That <i>the Spirit of God<pb n="6" /> was departed from them, that heretofore had been precious and Excellent men, and that their <em>Parks</em>, new <em>Houses</em>, and gallant <em>Wives</em></i> (that which indeed all men are subject to <reg orig="doat">dote</reg> upon (perhaps he spoke experimentally) <i>had <reg orig="choaked">choked</reg> them</i>. Thirdly, <i>That they had all revolted from the Lord, and left his people Fatherless</i>. Fourthly, that <em>Powel</em> also abused His <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <i>Chaplains, whom he said had thousands a Year to set up this New Government</i>; All which, the Author ingenuously and learnedly confuted, and wished, that if the Chaplains had their thousands, it might me multiplied to ten thousands; which wish I second, and am confident that no honest <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> man but will do the like, <i>That not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they, but all other deserving men may be rewarded according to their deserts.</i></p>

<p>After this he printed his <em>Hymn</em> at <em>Christchurch</em>, with the <em>Antiphone</em> thereunto, a true Copy of which I have <em>verbatim</em> inserted.</p>

<head level="3">His Hymn at Christ Church, 18 Decemb, 1653.</head>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>To Christ <em>our King</em>, let us praise sing,</line>
<line>Who is our Saviour dear,</line>
<line>Who is our <em>Protector</em> and our Rock,</line>
<line>Who will come and soon appear</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>To humble his, and try their hearts,</line>
<line>And make them clean and pure,</line>
<line>To set his Kingdom upon Earth,</line>
<line>Which ever shall endure:</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line><reg orig="Hast">Haste</reg> Lord, come quickly down,</line>
<line>Thy Saints do wait and pray,</line>
<line>And men would fain, if they knew how,</line>
<line>Thy Prophets kill and slay.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His Saints <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> reign with him on <em>Earth</em>,</line>
<line>And <em>Great Ones</em> then shall bow,</line>
<line>The Battle, and the <reg orig="Battle-Ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>And men of War shall know,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>That he will arise, and he will rule,</line>
<line>And their power will fall,</line>
<line>And Christ our <em>Great Commander</em>, He,</line>
<line>Shall be our <em>General</em>,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>But they shall live, and eke stand up,</line>
<line>And give their Testimony,</line>
<line>Against the Monarchs of the Earth,</line>
<line>That sit, and reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3"><i>The <em>Antiphona</em> thereunto</i></head>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>The <em>Devil's</em> your King, his praise you</line>
<line>His Spirit leads you here, (sing,</line>
<line>Who is your <em>Protector</em>, and your <em>Rock</em>,</line>
<line>And in you doth appear.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>'Tis he exalts and lifts your hearts,</line>
<line>To make you his most sure,</line>
<line>To set his Kingdome upon Earth,</line>
<line>Which shall not long endure:</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His Saints shall reign with him in Hell,</line>
<line>And to him they shall bow,</line>
<line>The Battle and the <reg orig="Battle-ax">Battleaxe</reg>,</line>
<line>And men of War do know,</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Though he be up, and his doth rule,</line>
<line>Yet his Power will fall,</line>
<line>Since <reg orig="Sathan">Satan</reg> your good Master, He</line>
<line>is your great <em>General</em>.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>The Lord will come in his due time,</line>
<line>His Saints for to preserve,</line>
<line>And all your lying Prophets slay,</line>
<line>Who from his Word do swerve.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>His Word <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, his <em>Saints</em> shall live,</line>
<line>To give their Testimony</line>
<line>Against false Teachers of the Earth,</line>
<line>Who strive to reign on high.</line>
</stanza>
</poem><pb n="7" />

<p>The States of Holland, Zealand, West-Friesland, Gelderland, Utrecht, and the rest of the United Provinces have agreed to send over their Deputies to his Highness the Lord Protector, to entreat that there may be a Cessation of all manner of hostility, till the Articles of Peace be fully agreed upon, and signed on both sides. Some are of opinion, that the Peace will come to nothing, and ground their reasons upon the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> favouring of the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, who it is feared endeavours to obstruct the Peace with England, being animated thereto by the titular King of Scots, and his Agent now at the Hague. They have <reg orig="dissolv'd">dissolved</reg> their General Assembly till the 20 of February, some think on purpose to protract time, and delude us. It is very well known the Dutch are very cunning Gamesters, and know how to play their Cards upon all advantages; but I would wish them likewise to be honest, and play altogether upon the square; for they have but one <em>Tromp</em> now left, and if we take that, 'tis not all the Kings in the Pack that can redeem their lost Game.</p>

<p>It is confidently reported, that on Thursday last the River of Thames <reg orig="ebb'd">ebbed</reg> and flowed three times in one day, the like hath not happened since a little before the death of the old Earl of Essex, who was beheaded in Qu. <em><reg orig="Elizabeths">Elizabeth's</reg></em> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. This with the fall of the South part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church (which I mentioned in my last) is adjudged by some to portend some further alteration or change in England; I shall not presume to predict the event of things, but leave them for time to discover: Hoping that the Lord who hath done such wonderful things for the preservation of His people in this Nation, will not now leave us to be a prey to our Enemies.</p>

<p>On Friday, a <reg orig="Bark">Barque</reg> laden with Corn, having some small quantity of Gunpowder in her, and having <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a Boy of about 13 years of Age aboard her, he accidentally fired the Gunpowder, and blew up the <reg orig="Bark">Barque</reg> and himself in it.</p>

<p>It is informed from <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>, that the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and the Imperial Cities, have (notwithstanding the Protestation of the Swedes to the contrary) admitted the City of Bremen into the number of the Imperial <reg orig="Townes">Towns</reg>, as it hath been before; whereupon the Swedes have declared that they will not lose their claim upon the said City, but will make it good whensoever they have opportunity. The Elector of Cullen and the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> Mons. <em>Vantorse</em>, having made the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> acquainted with the hostile invasion of the Lorainers into the Dominion of Liege, it hath been concluded between the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and the said Imperial Towns, that they shall assist the said Elector, and force the Larainers out of the land. There are 600 foot and 300 horse already sent from Trevers, to the assistance of the aforesaid <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg>.</p>

<p>The Irish <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the town of <em>Armen</em> <unclear>is in</unclear> Brabant, had a plot against the said town, but the same being discovered, 18 of them were seized upon and committed to custody.</p>

<p><i>Licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> according to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by R. WOOD, 1654.</p> 
 
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>