<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState228">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 228</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 2 of <em>February</em> To Thursday the 9 day of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 2. February.1653.</i></head>

<p>Letters from <em>Windsor</em> say that Mr. <em>Feake</em>, and Mr. <em>John Simpson</em> came thither on the Monday night before, brought by some Messengers of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, and no other company with them. The Governor is not <reg orig="wel">well</reg>, but they were received prisoners there, where the old Judge <em>Jenkins</em>, the Welsh Judge, is also prisoner.</p>

<p>They have sent Letters to their Churches to keep close together and wait upon God. They say now at <em>Windsor</em> that it is good to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <i>wise as Serpents</i>, as well as to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <i>innocent as Doves</i>.</p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector had the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> touching Sir <em>John Lenthall</em>, and the prison whereof <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was late <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, under consideration.</p>

<p>The Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have passed an Ordinance which was this day published, appointing a Committee for the Army, and Treasurers at War, with full power and authority in full and ample manner, to all intents and purposes, as the former Committee had. The names of the Committee are as followeth, <em><reg orig="viz">viz.</reg></em>, <em>John Clerk, Edw. Clud, Rich Lucy, rich. Horsman, James Philips, Edward Gill, John Hildesley, Jervas Bennet,</em> Esquires; Cap. <em>Adam Baines</em>, or any three or more of them; And <em>John Blackwel</em> the younger, and <em>Richard Dean</em> Esqs; to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> Treasurers at War.</p>

<p>Ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That <em>Thomas Rand, William Palmer, Robert Tarburrow, Nebemiah Rawson, William Harvey, William Welby</em> Esquires, and the Mayor of <em>Lincoln</em> for the time being, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> added to the Commissioners for the <reg orig="Monethly">Monthly</reg> Assessment within the County of <em>Lincoln</em>.</p>

<p><em>Philip Stansby</em> for the County of <em>Dorset</em>, The Mayor of <em>Banbury</em> for the time being, for the County of <em>Oxon</em>, and <em>Christopher Peircebay</em>, <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; and Sir <em>Robert Berwick</em> Knight, for the County of <em>York</em>.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <em>London</em> having invited his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector to Dinner, on such a Day as his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> would please to appoint, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath nominated Wednesday the eight instant to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> the day for that purpose, and great preparations there are already making for that Feast.</p>

<p>All Adventurers for Lands in <em>Ireland</em>, are desired to take notice, that the day for drawing of Lots for Baronies (being formerly appointed to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> on Thursday the ninth of this instant <em>February</em>) is now by the Committee for <reg orig="Claimes">Claims</reg> for Lands in <em>Ireland</em> (in regard of some <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> occasions intervening) ordered and appointed to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> at <em>Grocers hall London</em>, on Thursday the 23 of this instant <em>February</em>, and to begin at eight of the clock in the forenoon of the same day.</p>

<p><i>Will. Tibbs, Clerk.</i></p>

<p>From the Isle of Wight 3 February came thus: <i>Our fleet hath now set <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> and put to Sea from St. <reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg> Point, they are divided in three Squadrons, but are not at so great a distance but that <pb n="2" />upon any occasion they can soon <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> into one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> body, there being Scouts appointed, who are to give notice upon any appearance of the enemy.</i></p>

<p><i>From Deal 2 February thus.</i> Here is little News at present; a good number of ships bound to the Southward, as also for <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Ports of <em>France</em>, are gone from hence and from <em>Dover</em>. The French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> do still haunt about these parts, and are often <unclear>seen</unclear>, and as soon as any of our ships set sail to give them chase, they get their own coast before they can come up to them, there being two at present who are riding in <em><reg orig="Calice">Calais</reg></em> Road.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 1 Feb.</i> Col. <em>Morgan</em>, marching from <em>Aberdeen</em> with 14 companies of Foot, and 8 troops of horse and Dragoons towards the Enemy, <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em> and <em>Kenmore</em> the same day went out of <em>Maryland</em> toward the Hills, they burnt all the Lord <em><reg orig="Lothans">Lothan's</reg></em> land (the Lord <em><reg orig="Brodies">Brodie's</reg></em> <reg orig="Unckle">Uncle</reg>) because <reg orig="hee">he</reg> kept his house out against them in the late <reg orig="infall">in-fall</reg> into the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> quarters at <em>Dunkel</em>: There were <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> of the Scots, Cap. <em>Robertson</em> and Cap. <em>Hunter</em>, (a <reg orig="yong">young</reg> Lord who attended <em>Athol</em>) the 	Laird of <em>Baillacan</em>, Maj. <em>Mercer</em> run into the body with a Tuck, and through the <reg orig="arme">arm</reg>, it is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> will not live; there were about 20 more slain and desperately wounded. The 23 instant <em>Athol</em> had a <reg orig="Randevouze">Rendezvous</reg> of the country at a place <reg orig="cald">called</reg> <em>Cairan</em> two or three miles Northeast from <em>Dunkel</em>, but had a very slender appearance. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> and <em>Wogan</em> lie ill of their wounds at <em>Weems, Wogan</em> is not likely to recover: Col. <em>Hume</em> with about 16 more out of the <em>Merch</em> of <em>Berwickshire</em> are this week gone to join with those in the Hills.</p>

<p>From <i>Newcastle <unclear>1</unclear> Febru. For news <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have very little, only that which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> suppose you have heard of, the intercepting a great many Letters that came from the Scotch Cavaliers to the Malignant party here, which are sent up to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>. The truth is, there is such <reg orig="continuall">continual</reg> meetings of the Cavaliers, that any may judge without the intercepting of Letters, they have great <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> in hand. Here is much doing about the Quakers; they were at a place called <em>Hasington</em> on the Sabbath day, where there were such an hubbub that the Townsmen generally fell together by the ears, and did so exceedingly beat one another, that there were very few that went home without either face or head broke.</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<p><i>I have sent you here the Profession of the false Jew I formerly wrote of, that had been of the <reg orig="baptized">baptised</reg> Church, and proved a popish Jesuited Impostor, to carry on the popish <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> here, but upon discovery was cast out by them.</i></p>

<head level="3">The Declaration and Confession which was made at the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> meeting-house at <em>Hexam</em>, the fifth day of the fourth Month, 1653. By <em>Joseph Ben Israel</em>.</head>

<head level="3"><i>I say then, hath God cast away his People? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of <em>Abraham</em>, of the Tribe of <em>(Judah) Benjamin</em>.</i></head>

<p><i>Men, Brethren and Fathers,</i></p>

<p>My purpose is to declare unto this Congregation, first my Descent and Education; and secondly, the great work of my Conversion.</p>

<p>I verily am a man which am a Jew, of the Tribe of <em>Judah</em>, born in <em>Mantua</em>, a City in <em>Lombardy</em>, a Province of <em>Italy</em>, trained up in the Religion of my Fathers, and brought up in the choicest learning of my <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and having attained unto eight languages, I betook <reg orig="mee">me</reg> seriously to the study of Philosophy; where meeting with <em>Plato</em> (<reg orig="sirnamed">surnamed</reg> divine) <em>Trinum per unum, Socrates</em>, and <em>Hermes Trimegistus</em>, I found such light in the glorious Mystery of the <reg orig="Triunity">Trinity</reg>, that I was wonderfully <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> and amazed; and the more, that Heathens should come to the knowledge of this most excellent Doctrine.</p>

<p>O Lord, said I, how shall those Philosophers rise in judgement against us, who have more light, even <em>sepher battorah</em>, the Book of the Law? the former book <reg orig="rendred">rendered</reg> them inexcusable, but what will become of us, who have the revealed will of God?</p>

<p>I had not gone three <reg orig="foot-steps">footsteps</reg> in this way, but I found <em>Elohim</em> in the <reg orig="plurall">plural</reg> number, compounded with a singular word <em>Bara</em>, created, upon which my meditation was much raised to admire this mystery; when passing on a little further, I met with <i>Nangas haadam betrolmenu. Let us perfect man with our Image.</i> Why Us? but that <reg orig="wee">we</reg> should understand the plurality holden forth in the Creation: This drew my Meditations first towards the <reg orig="Christians">Christian's</reg> <em>Messiah</em>. But now Satan (the professed enemy of Christ, and of all that set their faces towards heaven) told <reg orig="mee">me</reg>, that these were but fancies, and delusions of my own brain; shall the Heathenish <pb n="4" />Philosophers be a rule for my Religion? No I will follow the Law under which I was born and educated. Behold the power of <reg orig="Satans">Satan's</reg> snares, an behold the <reg orig="vilenesse">vileness</reg> of mine <reg orig="owne">own</reg> heart, forsaking this blessed light, and rejecting all these holy motions, returning to my former old <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> again. But here, through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God, I found no rest, but very much trouble, and anguish of spirit: But O the loving <reg orig="kindnesse">kindness</reg> of God! whose <reg orig="designe">design</reg> graciously appeared to bring me to the knowledge of <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, even from our <reg orig="owne">own</reg> way of worship. Our Doctors <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> out a place to say every Morning and Evening; <i>Shemang Israel Adonay Elobenu Adona echad. Hear O Israel, the the<!--repeated in text--> Lord our God, the Lord is one.</i> Immediately upon this I find thrice, <i>Elohenu, Jehovah, Jehovah, the Lord &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>O Brethren, I cannot <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> the heart-searchings and movings that were upon me at that instant, which with my former Meditations, engaged my <reg orig="soule">soul</reg> in a firm <reg orig="beleef">belief</reg> of the blessed Three in One, which most sacred Trinity I do invocate as a <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> of the sincerity of my heart, holding concurrence with my words.</p>

<p>O Holy of Holies, Father, Son and Spirit, Searcher of the heart, and Tryer of the reins, be pleased to give strength and courage to avow thee; grant that my lips may enunciate truth, and <reg orig="deale">deal</reg> with thy servant according to the integrity of his heart.</p>

<p>After diligent enquiry of the Lord Jesus Christ, I did in heart confess him as the most high God, taking upon him our nature; but then Satan sets upon me with fresh and violent temptations, which caused me to break forth, O my soul, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> for thee I care; go I back to the Law, I lose thee, and thy case my body; go I forward to those that <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> this Messiah, and behold <reg orig="grosse">gross</reg> and abominable Idolatry; look upward, and behold a just and jealous God, the punisher of it; Look about thee, and behold all thy friends ashamed of thee, and thy nearest relations cursing thee and the Messiah whom thou <reg orig="beleivest">believest</reg>. But can this be the true Messiah, whose Disciples are so notoriously wicked, wallowing in all kind of sin, and <reg orig="woful">woeful</reg> Idolatry?</p>

<p>In the midst of these perplexities and distractions of spirit, I was almost swallowed up of despair.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>And while I thought of returning to the way of my Fathers, reading in the holy Scriptures, I discovered many <reg orig="grosse">gross</reg> untruths and corruptions of the Doctors; as concerning the incarnation of Christ, Behold a Virgin shall conceive and bear a Son, <em>Isa</em> 7.14, they render <em>Gnalmah</em>, a corrupted woman (which is no sign or wonder at all) namely, for a corrupted woman to conceive and bear a Son. So for the Sufferings of Christ, instead of <em>raru</em>, they digged, or pierced, they read <em>caari</em> as a Lion, that so they may cast a mist upon the true Messiah.</p>

<p>And now the good hand of Providence brought to my view the <reg orig="Syriack">Syriac</reg> and Greek Copies of <em>Guideo Fabricius Boderianus</em>, and by comparing these with the Law and the Prophets, I found all Prophecies fulfilled in Jesus Christ, without contradiction, which, through the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God, raised me to a full resolution, Avoid Satan, the enemy of my soul, I will delay no longer, but <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> to Christ; come Lord, the desire of my soul, lead me in the way of life. Now I resolved to leave my Country, and Friends, and to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> over the <em><reg orig="Alpes">Alps</reg></em> to find a people professing the true Messiah, not in legal <reg orig="waies">ways</reg>, but in spirit and truth; for the Papists go on the same way that my own people do, altogether legally, <i>ex opere operato</i>, rest on the work done, and by their horrible Idolatry to Pictures and Images, are a grievous stumbling block unto the Jews, and were a great obstruction to my conversion.</p>

<p>Coming into <em>Germany</em>, instead of finding comfort to my poor soul by communion with Christians in a <reg orig="spirituall">spiritual</reg> way of worship, without human Traditions, I find their great <em>Idol</em> Consubstantiation, and many other <em>Idols</em> of their own Inventions; this is not <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> way, I will not enter this way, no more of this. Lord what shall I do? I will not go without my <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>.</p>

<p>Away I <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to <em>Hessen</em>, where all are <em>Calvinists</em>; here Organs, <reg orig="Formes">Forms</reg>, and wicked Lives turned away my heart from them.</p>

<p>So <reg orig="tha">that</reg> from <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em> I came into <em>England</em>, and while I was thus seeking Christ without, in the way and order of his holy Gospel, I found him also within, to the exceeding joy of my <reg orig="soule">soul</reg>.</p>

<p>Blessed be thou King Jesus; who lives in thy Saints by Faith <pb n="6" />communicating thy <reg orig="selfe">self</reg> through thine Ordinances: thou <reg orig="shewest">showest</reg> me my lost estate in <em>Adam</em>, and the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> way of recovery in thy self.</p>

<p>When we come to a sight of our own undone condition, then we see the necessity of a <reg orig="Savior">Saviour</reg>, and the danger of our souls without Christ, and then Christ lovingly <reg orig="cloathes">clothes</reg> the poor sinner with the precious Robes of his own <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg>. Fleshy <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> <reg orig="intitles">entitles</reg> none to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of Christ, Though I might, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Lord Jesus present me at the day of Judgement before the Father in these long white Robes, I disclaim all other coverings; whatsoever I counted gain before, I now count <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> for Christ, yea, <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> and I count all things but <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for whom I have suffered the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of all things, and do count them but dung that I may win Christ, and be found in him, not, having mine own <reg orig="righteousnesse">righteousness</reg>, which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Christ. <em>Phil.3.7</em>.</p>

<p>And since my Lord Jesus hath appointed Ordinances for his people that have him within them, <reg orig="inthroned">enthroned</reg> in their hearts, and that I am called upon to arise and be baptised.</p> 

<p>I do here avow the Lord Jesus my true Saviour, and I <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> in thy Church and People, thy precious Saints, who <reg orig="doe">do</reg> here walk through thy grace according to thy Rule and holy Commands.</p>

<p>I do hereby solemnly vow thee my Lord and King, thy Saints and Ordinances; and now I heartily desire all the people of God to pray for me, that the residue of my <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> may be spent according to this beginning.</p>

<p>O Lord Jesus who hath appointed Ordinances, and sufferings for those who shall <unclear>reign</unclear> with thee in glory, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the desire of my <reg orig="soule">soul</reg> is to thee; <reg orig="doe">do</reg> thou therefore convey the grace of Ordinances into my heart, that I may live to the honour of thy Name, as <reg orig="becommeth">becometh</reg> thy professed servant, waiting for thy second coming. So come Lord Jesus and tarry not, <i><unclear>Baruch Adonay lengoham vanged</unclear> Amen ve Amen,</i></p>

<p><i>Scripsit propria manu. <em>B. Josephus B. Israel</em>, <unclear>Heb. Mant.</unclear></i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Friday 3. February.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Holland</em> came as followeth, (<em>viz.</em>)</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Holland touching the PEACE between <em>Holland</em> and <em>England</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>Not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the States of <em>Holland</em>, but the States General of <em>Holland</em> and <em>Westfreezland</em>, as I writ to you in my last, do concur for the Peace with <em>England</em>; but they have sent their opinions to the other Provinces, desiring their speedy concurrence therein with them.</p>

<p>We have Letters from private friends that the Lords <unclear>Laye</unclear> had a meeting in <em>Zealand</em> upon the Message sent to them touching the Peace, and did resolve to be at the <em>Hague</em>, on the day appointed to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Peace with the other Provinces, in case they do concur.</p>

<p>The Province of <em><reg orig="Utrich">Utrecht</reg></em> have also met, and there is a good correspondence by those Lords, in approbation of the Treaty of Peace with <em>England</em>, upon the terms signed and sent them from the <em>Hague</em>.</p>

<p>But the Province of <em>Freezland</em> (a Province not much considerable) when they met about it, did break up without concluding anything; for one of the House of <em>Orange</em> is their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and he used his interest to do what he could to hinder the Peace, but what shall be done upon their further meeting, or at the general Meeting of all the States General at the <em>Hague</em> at the time appointed, a short time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<p>The day on which the States General of all the Provinces are to meet, is appointed the 10 of <em>February</em> four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hence, that is the last of <em>January</em> upon the English account, and then will the result of all be soon determined.</p>

<p>But I assure you, I am verily <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> there will be a sudden Agreement to a Peace; which will be the more hastened because they cannot <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> that the Lord <em>Beverling</em> will prevail with the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, for a Cessation of Arms, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> there be a Conclusion; for there are so many ships both to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> out, and also to come in, and in such danger that they are necessitated to <unclear>hasten</unclear> a dispatch.</p>

<pb n="8" />

<p>The French Ambassador here, made many addresses, and large offers to have the War continue with <em>England</em>, and that the <em>French</em>, King would contribute in all things <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> the charges; But that being weighed, it was thought not to <reg orig="countervaile">countervail</reg> the losses they must necessarily suffer; and not to answer their expectation, which is getting of wealth, which must be by an open trade, and thereupon the French offers were refused.</p>

<p>Yet the French Ambassador makes often addresses to the States, but what is done is kept <reg orig="stil">still</reg> very secret, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they <reg orig="cal">call</reg> it a congratulation of their Peace with <em>England</em>; but if it be about that, I suppose it is either to see if it may be <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg>, or <unclear>to get</unclear> as good <reg orig="termes">terms</reg> for <em>France</em> as may be on it.</p>

<p>But they <reg orig="stil">still</reg> go on preparing their new ships of War every day, the Workmen never <reg orig="seasing">ceasing</reg>, but on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> <reg orig="daies">days</reg> and all, all day long are at work for dispatch thereof with all possible speed.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Newport</em> is at <em>Amsterdam</em>. It was under consideration upon the agreement to the Peace to have sent the Lord <em>Bredrode</em> General of the Land forces to be the Ambassador either alone, or the Lord <em>Updam</em> Vice-Admiral of their Navy with him, But the Lord General (because of his age) seems to decline it, but what <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be concluded by the States General at their meeting four <reg orig="daies">days</reg> hence, I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> unto you by the first opportunity.</p>

<p>But if there should not be a conclusion of Peace, truly I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not know what they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg>; the Merchants are undone. The fishers cannot work, the poor can have no <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> nor <reg orig="subsistance">subsistence</reg>; And there must needs <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a very great hubbub and distraction.</p>

<p>But I do not hear of any Province that refuseth it, but only that of <em>Freezland</em>, and it is thought when they meet here, seeing the rest agree, that they will also concur.</p>

<p><i>Hague 6 February (alias 27 Jan.) 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3">A List of the 36 Lords and other Members of the Council of the City of <em>Amsterdam</em>.</head>

<p><em>Anthoni Oetgens van Waveren.</em> Dr. <em>Niclaes Tulp</em>. Dr. <em>Gerrit Schaep. Jan Huydekooper. Hendrick Dirksz. Spiegal.</em> Dr. <em>Frans Banning Kock</em>. Dr. <em>Gerrit Schaep Pietersz. Albert Dircksz. Pater.</em> <pb n="9" /><em> Joris Backer. Cornelis Jacobsz. Weyer. Cornelis de Graef. Roel of Bicker Jacobsz</em>. Dr. <em>Cornelis Jan Wintz. Jan vander Pol</em>. Dr. <em>Gerrit Reynst. Bernart Schellinger. Simon van Hoorn. Pieter Kloeck</em>. Dr. <em>Cornelis van Dronkelaer. Lambert Reynst</em>. Dr. <em>Johan Blaeuw. Jacob van Neck. Cornelis Geelvinck</em>. Dr. <em>Gillis Valkenier. Cornelis van Ulooswiick. Niclaes van Loon</em>. Dr. <em>Gerrit van Helmont. Hans Bontemantel</em>. Dr. <em>Roetert Ernst</em>. Dr. <em>Hendrick Hudde. Gerrit Claesz. Hasselaer. Jacob Theunisz. Van Stralen.</em></p>

<head level="3">A List of the several Court in the City this present year 1654. for the <reg orig="wel">well</reg> Government of the several affairs thereof.</head>

<p>Judge Advocate, The Lord <em>Cornelius de Ulamingh, Ridder</em>, Lord of <em>Outshoorn</em>. <reg orig="Bugermasters">Burgomasters</reg>. Dr. <em>Frans Bannigh Kock</em> Lord of <em>Purmerlandien Yipendam</em>. <em>Cornelis Bicker</em>, Lord of <em>Swieten</em>, <em>Jan Huyderkooper, Ridder</em>, Lord of <em>Maarse-veen</em>. Dr. <em>Niclaes Tulp</em>.</p>

<p>Judges of the Upper Court, Mr. <em>Simon van Hoorn</em>. Dr. <em>Johan Blaeuw</em>. <em>Barnart Schellinger</em>. Dr. <em>Frans Reael Pietesz</em>. Dr. <em>Cornelis van Dronckelaer</em>. Dr. <em>Gerrit Reynst</em>. <em>Niclaes Paneras</em>, <em>Hans Bontemantel</em>.</p>

<p>Treasurers, <em>Cornelis de Graef</em>, Lord of <em>Zuyt-Polsbroeck</em> an <em>Ould-burgermeester</em>, <em>Niclaes Corver</em>, an Ould Burgemeester.</p>

<p>Judges for <reg orig="Wils">Wills</reg>, Orphans &amp;c. <em>Anthoni Oetgens</em> Lord of <em>Waveren</em>, old Burgermaster. <em>Ian van der Pol</em>, old Burgermeester. <em>Hendrick Dircksz. Spiegel. Albert Dircksz. Pater.</em></p>

<p>Commissioners for Marriages, <em>Cornelis van Ulooswick, Pieter Adriansz. Raep, Hendrick Hoost, Cornelis Abba, Jacob Jacobsz Rogh.</em></p>

<p>Treasurers Extraordinary <em>Niclaes van Loon, Jacob Valckenier.</em></p>

<p>Commissioners for Accounts. <em>Michiel Pancras</em>. Dr. <em>Johan Huydenkoper</em>.</p>

<p>Commissioners for the Assurance Chamber. <em>Jacob van Neck, Jan Hulst, <reg orig="Iacob">Jacob</reg> Servaes.</em></p>

<p>Commissioners for the Bank, <em>Munter, Jacob Bas, Pieter Trip.</em></p>

<p>Commissioners for debts of 60 <em>li.</em> and under. Mr. <em>Joris Backer</em>. <em>Jan van Waveren</em>. Mr. <em>Jochem Rendorp, cornelis Geelvinck</em>, Mr. <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> Bicker</em>, Dr. <em>Wybout Slicher, Dirck Tulp.</em></p>

<p>Commissioners for the Low Bank, <em>Roel</em> of <em>Bicker</em>. <em><reg orig="Iacobsz">Jacobsz</reg></em>, <em><reg orig="Iacob">Jacob</reg> Erans <unclear>Hinlopen</unclear>.</em></p>

<pb n="10" />

<p>Commissioners for Sea Affairs, Dr. <em>Gerrit Schaep Pletersz, Gerrit Hasselaer, <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> van Hwlmont, Niclaes van Waveren</em>, Dr. <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> Veneman</em>.</p>

<p>Commissioners for Bankrupts, Dr. <em>Gerrit van Halmont</em>. Dr. <em>Roetert Ernst Roetersz</em>, Dr. <em>Pelgrom ten Grootenbuys, Gran van Waveren, Zacharias Roode.</em></p>

<p><reg orig="Pentioners">Pensioners</reg>, Mr. <em>Coenraet van Beuningen</em>, Mr. <em>Pieter Voglesangh. Elesz, Pieter van Loon, Pieter Bas Pietersz.</em></p>

<p>Secrataries, <em>Bartholomeus Real, <reg orig="Iacob">Jacob</reg> Bruyning</em>, Mr. <em>Pieter <unclear>Hassler</unclear></em>, Dr. <em>William Backer</em>, Mr: <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> Roetersz</em>, Mr. <em>Gerard Hulst, Lieve van Loon</em>, Dr: <em>Cornelius Backer</em>, Dr: <em><reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> Corver, Nicolaes Nicolai.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 4 February.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Blake, and <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Penn</em> are at St: <em>Ellins</em>, with the Fleet, some parties are sent out several <reg orig="waies">ways</reg>:</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes this day certified of,</i></head>

<p>One Prize laden with Wine, and brought into <em>Falmouth</em> by the <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, but taken by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>One Prize laden with Raisins, Figs, &amp;c. taken by the <em>Old Warwick</em>, and brought into <em>Falmouth</em>, this ship supposed to be both a Man of War and a merchant man.</p>

<p>One man of war of 20 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance, and 70 men belonging to <em>Flushing</em> taken by the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Two ships of St. <em>Malloes</em> which came from <em><reg orig="Marcellice">Marseilles</reg></em> laden with Soap, <reg orig="Oyles">Oils</reg>, Almonds, Galls, &amp;c. taken by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>, the one of 14 guns, the other of 18 guns.</p>

<p>Two small private men of War of 6 or eight guns a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> taken to the Northward.</p>

<p>Letters from <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> say, that one of those who killed the Lord Ambassador <em>Askome</em> from <em>England</em> in <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, getting away from the Sanctuary privately, was flying towards <em>France</em>, and is taken and brought to <em>Madrid</em>, and like to suffer there if they play with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> came as followeth, (<em>viz.</em>)</p>

<pb n="11" />

<p><i>Dalkeith, 31 Jan.</i> Sir, upon the march of Col. <em>Morgan</em> from <em>Aberdeen</em>, the enemy hastened their march out of <em>Murriland</em> towards <em>Ross</em>, and the Hills, so that Col. <em>Morgan</em> returned back to <em>Aberdeen</em>, but Major <em><reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg></em> Cornet with a party of that Regiment took <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Captain Lieutenant, and 5 Horsemen, and sent them to <reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg>. <reg orig="Their">There</reg> being a small party Scotchmen who have formerly done good service in a smaller party, the Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> gave them encouragement to raise about 40 horse, with which they have more advantage to come upon the enemy by their Scotch tone, <reg orig="then">than</reg> our forces have. Saturday last this party fell upon the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> guards, upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Angus</em>, and killed the first Scout, and went on and charged a guard of theirs, and killed 3 or 4, and then fell into another quarter, took a Captain Lieutenant and a Cornet, and 15 others <unclear>prisoners,</unclear> with 20 horse, and killed 9 or 10, and 2 or 3 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before Cornet <em>Baily</em> (who is Cornet to that party) sent in a Captain, and another Horseman prisoners to <em>Dundee</em>, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> much resolution in the several charges given to the enemy.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, 6 February.</i></head>

<p>This day came an Ambassador from the great Duke of <em>Turkanny</em> to congratulate His Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>Two Agents made this day their Address to His Highness, from the Lord of the Isle of <em>Amiland</em> in <em>Holland</em>, about 9 English miles long, and some 3 or 4 broad, having upon it about 450 houses, to desire that they may be esteemed as Neutrals; and they have brought with them Credentials, and a List of the names of all their Ships and Fisher-boats, of which <reg orig="onely">only</reg> four are Merchant ships, the rest Fisher-boats belonging to that Island, and they have delivered in also the marks of the said ships, that so none may deceive us by seeking for protection in their names, and they desire to be accounted as a Free State, having not been hitherto subject (as is pretended) to any Country.</p>

<p>This day came a Letter from one or both the Ministers in <em>Windsor</em> Castle to His Highness, the Lord Protector.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 4 Febr.</i> Our <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg> towards the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end have done very good service of late in relieving sundry vessels and <pb n="12" />ships that were taken by the <em>Brest</em> men. A ship of above a hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, with some Iron guns in her, was stranded not far from <em>Dartmouth</em>, whose lading was Salt, and French built; she is <reg orig="ceized">seized</reg> on by the Vice-Admiral of this County for a <reg orig="wrack">wreck</reg>. A thousand stories are raised, (and daily discoursed off) upon the poor people, that go by the name of Witches in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, I think 20 are already committed as suspected, and more are daily detected; but the Lord deliver us from blood-<reg orig="guiltines">guiltiness</reg> in this <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg>, our Manufacture here hath a quick vent upon the hopes of peace with the Dutch. I am glad to hear the <em>Swedes</em> are so <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> to us, and hope, that if they be hearty, we may chastise the <em>Danes</em> and <em>Dutch</em> in case they juggle with us.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 7 February.</i></head>

<p>The Benches in <em>Westminster-Hall</em> are no filling with able learned Judges. Those already are,</p>

<p>Lord <reg orig="Cheif">Chief</reg> Justice <em>Roll</em>, and Justice <em>Ask</em> for the Upper Bench.</p>

<p>Lord <reg orig="Cheif">Chief</reg> Justice <em>St. John</em>, Justice <em>Atkins</em>, and Justice <em>Hale</em> for the Common Pleas.</p>

<p>Baron <em>Thorp</em>, and Baron <em>Nichols</em> for the Exchequer.</p>

<p>And five new <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> are made, who are to be made Judges to fill the Benches, (<em>viz.</em>) Mr. <em>Maynard</em>, Mr. <em>Steel</em>, Mr. <em>Windham</em>, Mr. <em>Newdegate</em>, and Mr. <em>Twisden</em>.</p>

<p>The Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are the same that were.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Warscow">Warsaw</reg></em> the 1 January. 1654.</i></head>

<p>When in all likelihood both Armies, that of His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> of <em>Poland</em>, and that of the Cossacks, should have come to a set battle, and so decided their differences, after that many of both sides have been killed and taken prisoners in a hot skirmish; there hath been an Address made to His Majesty by the said Cossacks, with the Advice and Counsel of the great <em>Cham</em> of the <em>Tartars</em>, to prevent further Bloodshed for a Peace.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Perpinian">Perpignan</reg></em> the 6 of January.</i></head>

<p>The Spaniards intending to besiege <em>Willa Franca, Don Joseph de Margarete</em> doth gather all the forces he can out of the <em>Roussillan</em>, to block it up.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Dantzick">Dantzig</reg></em> the 7 of January.</i></head>

<p>By an express from <em>Poland</em>, we receive advice, that the Peace <pb n="14" /> between His <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> and the Cossacks and Tartarians is concluded; that of both sides two great Lords were given as Hostages, till the Articles be ratified in the Assembly, which is to meet at <em><reg orig="Warchaw">Warsaw</reg></em> the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>. The conditions are, That the Tartarians shall receive five years of contribution, as arrears due to them by the King; and that <em>Chimilinsky</em> shall hold 6000 Cossacks at his service, thereupon His Majesty is come back to <em><reg orig="Warschaw">Warsaw</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Flushing</em> the 23 of January.</i></head>

<p>The Captain <em>Geleyn Brandt</em> hat brought here the 18 instant, an English <reg orig="Free-booter">Freebooter</reg> of 4 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance. The 19 and 20 are also arrived here three Danish ships with Ammunition of War, the one of 200 lasts, the other of 150, the third was a Galliot; there is also come in a ship laden with 250 barrels of Wine. Those of <em>Ostend</em> have taken from our Fleet, though we be friends, and free, five laden with Cheeses and Soap, and other Commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Colen</em> the 27 of January.</i></head>

<p>There hath appeared a Comet Star to those of the Town of <em>Prague</em>, and the same is yet at this present seen by those of <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Upsal</em> the 20 of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>.</i></head>

<p>My Lord <em>Whitlock</em>, the English Extraordinary Ambassador, is feasted at the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> charges, with his whole suite, which consisteth of 100 persons, amongst whom there is four high Officers, four Pages, eight Footmen, two Trumpeters, one Doctor, two Ministers, two Coaches, and forty saddle Horses. They are highly esteemed here by the <em>Swedes</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Marceille">Marseilles</reg></em> in <em>Provence</em> the 22 of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>.</i></head>

<p>The Hollanders have taken an English ship in these Seas, and have brought her hither.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the <em>Hague</em> the (6 of February) 27 of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>.</i></head>

<p>When the Lords States of <em>Holland</em> shall meet <reg orig="againe">again</reg>, which is to be the 10 of this instant, that is <em><reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg></em> 21 by the English Account. We hope that all the other Provinces shall bring in their Resolves concerning the Ratification of the Articles, with the present Government in <em>England</em>. It is thought that the same shall be conform to the Resolutions of the Province of <em>Holland</em> (although some will say that there is yet somewhat that sticks) and some <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> shall <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> over us <pb n="14" />the liberty of the Seas. We heard that the Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedland">Sweden</reg></em> hath written a Letter to <em>Charles Stuart</em> titular King of Scotland, at the instance of his Agent, wherein her <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> doth excuse <reg orig="herselfe">herself</reg> that the present condition of her <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> doth not suffer her to give him satisfaction upon his Demands, intimating that she <reg orig="pitties">pities</reg> his misfortune. We have a confirmation of the Peace concluded between the King of <em>Poland</em> and the <em>Tartarians</em> and <em>Cossacks</em>: And it is said that an Ambassador is come to <em>Upsall</em> in <em><reg orig="Sweadland">Sweden</reg></em> from the great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em>, to make known that his Master is ready to declare the War to the said King of <em>Poland</em>, to which end he hath mustered 160000 men, he shall in all appearance move the Crown of <em><reg orig="Sweadland">Sweden</reg></em> to declare also against him. Yesterday there arrived here 140 Seamen which are come from <em>England</em> having been prisoners there, they have received conduct money, and shall be sent toward <em>Amsterdam</em>, having the most part of their Habitations there and in the Northern parts.</p>

<p>Something was considered of in order to M. Gen. <em><reg orig="Browns">Brown's</reg></em> liberty.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 7 February.</i></head>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, being invited by the City of <em>London</em>, dined at Grocers-hall; So soon as His Highness entered the Gate at Temple-Bar, he was met by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen on <reg orig="horse-back">horseback</reg>; His Highness had the Sword delivered to him by the Lord Mayor, which was returned to the L. Mayor, and his Lordship being bare carried it before His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, who then came out of his Coach and rid through the City attended by the Aldermen, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Life Guard, the Colonels, and <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Officers of the Army, and divers Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen in their Coaches following after. Two Gentlemen rid bare before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>. And there were Trumpeters, and the Heralds of Arms also, and other equipage very gallant and comely with 12 of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Footmen in <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> coats and silver and black silk lace, and the streets were swept clean, and the Liveries of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Companies stood on both sides the way in double <reg orig="Rales">Rails</reg> with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> cloth, and some with Carpets all the way: And at Temple-Bar the <reg orig="Belconies">Balconies</reg> were hung with Carpets, and Hangings, and very great <reg orig="rejoycings">rejoicings</reg> in the City, and His Highness, and the Aldermen, and Colonels, &amp;c. alighted in the <reg orig="Poultrey">Poultry</reg>, and went to Grocers-hall, and there dined: The Speeches, Carriage, and Deportment of them there, was also with much sobriety and civility, as is much applauded by those present at the same. And after dinner His Highness returned to <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>. The Bells in several parts of the City ringing, and people much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg>, and some met together praying.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<p>The Holy Order; or, Fraternity of the Mourners in <reg orig="Sion">Zion</reg>, Whereunto is added Songs in the Night, or Cheerfulness under Affliction, By Joseph Hall, B.N. Sold by Nath. Brooks at the Angel in <reg orig="Cornhal">Cornhall</reg>.</p>

<p>The Arrow of the Almighty shot out of the <reg orig="Creatures">Creature's</reg> Bow, against the uncalled Ministers in England, By George Baitman. The Knowledge of Christ indispensably required of all men that would be saved; wherein the <reg orig="Tipes">Types</reg>, <reg orig="Prophesies">Prophecies</reg>, Genealogies, Miracles, Humiliation, Exaltation, and the Mediatorial Office of Christ, are opened and applied, By John Davenport, Pastor of the Church of Christ at Newhaven in New England. Generation Work, the second Part, wherein is <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg>, What the designs of God abroad in the world, may in all likelihood be at this present day, and in the days approaching; being an Exposition of the seven Vials. Revel.16. and other <reg orig="Apocaliptical">Apocalyptical</reg> Mysteries, By John Tillinghast, Minister of the Gospel. All sold by Livewell Chapman at the Crown in <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Head Alley.</p>

<p>Festorum Metropolis, the Metropolitan Feast, or the Birthday of our Saviour Jesus Christ, Annually to be kept <!--holy??-->hily by them that call upon him in all Nations. Proved by Scriptures. The practice of the Church, Primitive and Reformed, and the Testimony of the Fathers, and Modern Divines, By Allen Blayney, M. A. late of <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Oxford. The Blessed <reg orig="Birth-day">Birthday</reg> celebrated in some sanctified Meditations on the <reg orig="Angels">Angel's</reg> Anthems, Luke 2. 14. Also holy Raptures in contemplating some of the most observable Adjuncts about our <reg orig="Saviours">Saviour's</reg> Nativity, By <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Fitz Geffry. Both sold by Stephen Chatfield in St. <reg orig="Danstams">Danstam's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg> in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>.</p>

<p>The right constitution and true Subjects of the visible Church of Christ, with its Order, Ordinances, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, and Government, By Tho. Collier and unworthy servant of Christ. Sold by Henry Hills at the sign of Sir John Oldcastle in <reg orig="Pycorner">Pie corner</reg>.</p>

<p>A Discourse touching the peace and concord of the Church; wherein is elegantly and acutely argued, That not so much a bad opinion, as a bad life, excludes a Christian out of the kingdom of Heaven, &amp;c. A Twofold Catechism; the one simply called A Scripture-Catechism, the other, A brief Scripture-Catechism for Children, by John <unclear>Biddle</unclear>, M. A. of the University of Oxford. The Unknown Being of the Spirit, Soul, and Body, <reg orig="Anatomized">Anatomised</reg>. Wherein very many Scriptures <reg orig="falsly">falsely</reg> translated, and <unclear>corruptly</unclear> interpreted, are clearly Explained. By which, many Doctrines now taught that subvert the Faith of the Gospel, are discovered, by John Brayne. All sold by Richard Moon at the seven Stars in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg>, near the great North door.</p>

<p>Newly published, An Examination of Mr. <reg orig="Baxters">Baxter's</reg> Aphorisms of Justification; together with a Vindication of Justification by <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Grace, from all the Popish and <reg orig="Arminian">Armenian</reg> Sophisms, by which the Author <reg orig="labors">labours</reg> to ground it on <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> Works and Righteousness; wherein Mr. <reg orig="Baxters">Baxter's</reg> Aphorisms are repeated and confuted, By John Crandon, Minister of the Gospel. Sold by Tho. Brewster at the Three Bibles in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard, at the West end, and Livewell Chapman at the Crown in <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Head Alley.</p>

<p>A Perfect Guide for a studious <reg orig="yong">young</reg> Lawyer, both delightful and profitable for all Gentlemen, &amp;c. Being presidents for conveyances, and collected out of the <reg orig="Labors">Labours</reg> of the Lord Coke, Lord Hobbart, Lord Richardson, Justice Haughton, Reve, Bacon, and Godfrey, by Tho. <unclear>Fidel</unclear> of Furnivals inn, Gen. Who at spare houses made it his study for above 30 years. Sold by John Place at Furnivals Inn Gate in Holborn.</p>

<hr />

<p>A <reg orig="yong">young</reg> Black Nag near 14 handful high, with a small Star on his forehead, and a lock on his foot, lost out of a Pasture from Mrs. Henshaws of Kensington, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> London, on Tuesday the 17 of January. If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> shall bring intelligence of him thither, or to Mr. <reg orig="Wisemans">Wiseman's</reg> in the broad Sanctuary in Westminster, they shall be well rewarded.</p>

<p>At Mr. <reg orig="Hickfords">Hickford's</reg> at the sign of the Angel in Cheapside, you may hear of Silk Ribbons, and Silk and Silver Ribbons, <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of broken Plate, and Silver Spoons, which are supposed to be lost.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>