<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState230">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 230</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 16 of <em>February</em> To Thursday the 23 day of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 16. February. 1653.</i></head>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> with divers other Officers, are dispatched for <em>Ireland</em>, for filling up of the Regiments, and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> that Nation.</p>

<p>By Letters from the Generals at Sea, was this day certified, that they were returned back to St. <em><reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg></em> with three prizes.</p>

<p>Some persons apprehended, were this day examined by a Committee of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, about a plot lately discovered.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Articles of Agreement made and concluded upon between Maj. <em>Peter Wallis</em>, and <unclear>Cap. Tim. Coakely</unclear>, on the one party; and Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, in the behalf of himself and party on the other side.</i></head>

<p>First, That Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em>, with all such of his party as will <pb n="1" />adhere unto, and engage with him to be transported into <em>Flanders</em> for the service of the King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, in that Army whereof the Prince of <em>Conde</em> is General, do lay down their Arms, with such stores of Ammunition, and such other habiliments of War, without <reg orig="imbezlement">embezzlement</reg>, as is hereafter expressed in this Article, by Wednesday the 25 of this instant <em>January</em>; (<em>viz.</em>) Those of the County of <em><reg orig="Corke">Cork</reg></em> at <em>Moyallow</em>, and <em>Mackrompe</em>; those of the County of <em>Kerry, <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg></em>, &amp;c. in the respective Counties where now they are, except what is hereafter excepted; to Col. <em>Mortogh O Brien</em> one Case of Pistols, to every Colonel of his party one case of Pistols, and to all other commissioned Officers their Swords only.</p>

<p>2 That license be granted to the said Col. to transport <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, and as many of his party, as well of the Clergy, as others that <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere unto him, and will <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him for the service aforesaid; and also of all others protected persons, with such others as have been in arms, as are willing to engage with the said Col. to be transported as aforesaid, submitting themselves to the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, according to the Instructions of the Authority of this Nation; allowing the persons so submitting the benefit of the explanation of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, as is set <reg orig="downe">down</reg> and annexed to the Articles made with the Lord <em>Muskerry</em>.</p>

<p>3 That the said Col. be allowed Commissions for such numbers as he shall produce at the waterside, according to the Establishment of the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Army, and likewise to every private <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> six shillings each man at their going on shipboard, or twelve shillings each man when they are arrived in <em>Flanders</em>.</p>

<p>4 That the said Col. <reg orig="doe">do</reg> produce at the Waterside, at the <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> of <em>Kingsale</em>, to be shipped in order to their transportation, upon, or before the fourteenth day of <em>February</em> next <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg>, as many of his party as are now in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> in the County of <em>Cork, Kerry, <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg></em> and <em>Waterford</em>, as do adhere unto him, and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> engage with him in the aforesaid service; and also of all such other persons as do adhere unto him, and engage with him s aforesaid.</p>

<p>5 That Free-quarter be allowed the said Col. and all such of his party as do adhere unto him, and engage with him, and lay <pb n="2" />down their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> as aforesaid, from the time of their so laying down arms, until the time of their Transportation, according to direction from Col. <em>Phair</em> or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, or of any other <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> thereunto. And the benefit of quarter to be allowed to all such of the Clergy, and other protected people, and such as have formerly been in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> that do adhere unto the said Col. and <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him from the time of their so adhering and <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> as aforesaid, Provided, that they, and every of them, content themselves with such ordinary Diet as the Country usually allows themselves.</p>

<p>6 That eight <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time <reg orig="bee">be</reg> allowed to rally and draw together all such of his said party now in the County of <em>Cork, Kerry, <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg></em>, and <em>Waterford</em>, as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere unto him, and will engage with him for the service aforesaid without molestation or prejudice from any Forces or Garrisons, under the pay of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and likewise Free-quarter to all such of the said party in the respective Counties if they desire it where they now are, and their <reg orig="thorow fare">thoroughfare</reg> from County to County, in order to their laying <reg orig="downe">down</reg> of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> as is before appointed; Provided the said Colonel and every of the said party <reg orig="forbeare">forbear</reg> all Act and Acts of Hostility against the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> their Forces and <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>; And all persons whatsoever under the protection of the Commonwealth; provided also that the said Colonel or any of his party take not any prey of preys, nor offer any other violence to the protected people in the respective Counties after the date of these Articles, and the knowledge thereof communicated unto them: And in case any prey be taken by the said Colonel or party after the date of these Articles, before the knowledge thereof be communicated as aforesaid, in that case the prey or preys so taken to be restored to the Owners, all but what is disposed of to the necessary relief of the party of Parties so taking the said prey or preys; the like restitution to be made for any other violence or injury done or committed by any of the said party after the aforesaid date of the said Articles.</p>

<p>7 That the said Colonel and all such others of his party as do adhere unto him, and <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him as aforesaid, be freed and acquitted from all <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> arrears for debt, or <reg orig="claimes">claims</reg> of <pb n="3" />that nature, and from all manner of molestation, for any prey or preys taken, or any other Act or Acts done or committed by him, or every of them since the year 1640 but as is excepted and provided for in the second Article, provided also this extend not to the exempting of any of the Goods and Chattels of any of the aforesaid persons so adhering and engaging, as aforesaid from making satisfaction for any just debts for which any of the said persons may be convicted by due course of Law.</p>

<p>8 that the said Colonel and all others of his party as do adhere unto him, as well the Clergy, as those that have been in Arms, with such other protected persons as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> so adhere and <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with him, as aforesaid, as also all such of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> party as shall lay <reg orig="downe">down</reg> their <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, as aforesaid, be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and admitted to dispose of their Goods and Chattels to their best advantage within the aforesaid time of their Transported.</p>

<p>9 That all such of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> as <reg orig="doe">do</reg> adhere and engage to transport themselves and did not, be forgiven the forfeitures of their Bonds to themselves and their Sureties: And also that none of the said <reg orig="Colonells">Colonel's</reg> party now under his command be admitted to stay in this Nation, or to dispose of themselves without his license.</p>

<p>10 That the said <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> or any of his party so adhering and engaging, as aforesaid, be admitted to recover any of his or their Goods left in custody of any protected persons, which said persons have not discovered the said Goods to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next adjacent Garrison before the signing hereof:</p>

<p>11 That the said <reg orig="Colonell">Colonel</reg> be admitted to transport himself into <em>Flanders</em>, as aforesaid, with fifteen hundred Irish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and in case the said Colonel cannot produce at the Waterside the whole number by the time appointed, the said Colonel then to be allowed to depute an Officer to stay behind, who shall be qualified with power to rally and raise so many as may make up the said number, which number so raised, to be transported, as aforesaid, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> allowed the benefit of these conditions in all particulars, provided the said Officer or Deputy produce the <pb n="4" />said number of men at such Ports, and at such times as he shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> thereunto appointed by Col. <em>Phair</em>, or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them after the <unclear><!--large space approx. 8 characters long--></unclear> of <unclear><!--large space approx. 12 characters long--></unclear> next <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> provided also that the said Col. or Officer enter sufficient security to the said Col. <em>Phair</em> or Major <em>Wallis</em>, or either of them, that the said Officer, or any such as shall be raised or rallied in order to their transportation, as aforesaid Act not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> during before the time of their transportation, to the prejudice of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, their Forces or <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>.</p>

<p>12 That the Wives of all such of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> party be allowed to enjoy the benefit of the Act of Qualification, equally with the Wives of others in protection.</p>

<p>13 That all such of the said <reg orig="Colonels">Colonel's</reg> party to whom the charges of <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> may extend, be allowed 16 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time to state their cases in writing, and receive the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers thereupon; and also eight and forty hours after the knowledge of the opinion of the said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, is communicated unto the party so concerned, to dispose themselves for their own security (if they desire it.)</p>

<p>14 That the Articles be confirmed and allowed of by His Excellency the Lord General.</p>

<p>15 That for the performance of these Articles, sufficient Hostages shall be given upon signing hereof.</p>

<p>16 In Testimony whereof, we do hereunto interchangeably set our Hands and Seals, 12 <em>January</em> 1653.</p>

<p><em>Peter Wallis</em></p>
<p><em>Thomas Coakely</em></p>
<p><em>Mortogh O Brien</em></p>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em>, February 11. <em>Kenmore</em> with his Body of about 2000 of those wild people, is now at <em>Kildrunning</em>, an House of the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Mars</em> in <em><reg orig="Murryland">Murrayland</reg></em>. They have been very quiet of late, and if a Peace with the seven Provinces be concluded, they are not like to be very <reg orig="troublesom">troublesome</reg>: Most of <reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg> party (now he is gone the way of all flesh) are contriving to get as well out of <em>Scotland</em> as they came <reg orig="in to">into</reg> it.</p>

<p>We do daily snap divers of the Enemy in small parties; a Lieutenant Col. <em><reg orig="Faifaxes">Faifax's</reg></em> Regiment with twelve Dragoons, took four of <em><reg orig="Glengairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> own Troop, and 8 Horse and one Lieutenant <pb n="5" /><em>Rutherford</em>, who commanded them, narrowly escaped; <em>Glencairn</em> hath set out a Proclamation, threatening fire and sword to all those that do not comply with him in sending in their Levies.</p>

<p>Master <em>John <reg orig="Goodwins">Goodwin's</reg></em> Seventeen Queries are Reprinted at <em>Leith</em>.</p>

<p>On Sunday last four of Col. <em><reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg></em> Regiment, and two of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> going from <em>Drummond</em> Castle for St. <em>Johnstons</em>, were set upon by about 50 of the Remains of Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs's</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> horse, who took three of them, killed two, and the other escaped. There is a considerable party of the Enemy in those parts about <em>Conrie</em> who are very active, since the drawing of the horse Northwards, but upon the coming in of the two Regiments from <em>England</em>, our horse will be placed so as to meet with them at all turns. Col. <em>Drummond</em> is certainly got to the Enemy with further Instruction from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, from whom he is sent to see in what posture they are, and whether so considerable, as to protect him, in case he should come to them this Summer. He tells them, that His Majesty strained hard to send them over a ship with ten thousand arms, which is cast away upon the Coasts of <em>Ireland</em>; though I am apt to think it is the same Ship that was driven from the Coasts of <em>Loughaber</em> to <em>Killebeggs</em>. There is nothing come since my last from the North.</p>

<p>From <em>Newcastle</em>, 13 <em>February</em>. There are yet many ships here laden with Coals, and some other Commodities, but by reason of these Easterly winds cannot get out of the <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> over the Bar. We hear by a small Vessel, come two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since from Holy Island, that a private Man of War set out from <em>Leith</em>, hath brought in two Dutch prizes, the one of 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, and the other 150, laden with East-<reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> goods; also that of late there hath been some <reg orig="Shipwrack">Shipwreck</reg> about those Rocks which lie off that Island.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, 17 February.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance Declaring that the Offences therein mentioned, and no other, shall be adjudged High Treason within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em></i>, It is amongst other things, Ordained and <pb n="6" />Established, <i>That no Matter, Fact, Crime, or Offence whatsoever, other then such as are therein mentioned and expressed, should be deemed, taken, or adjudged to be High Treason.</i> And whereas some doubts and question may arise, whether that Clause in the said Ordinance, doth not extend to the Offences mentioned in the Instrument, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging,</i> and which are thereby declared to be High Treason. For clearing thereof, and removing of all scruples thereupon. His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice of His Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That neither the said Ordinance, nor any Clause of thing therein contained, shall extend or be construed, adjudged or taken to extend unto all or any the Offences declared by the said Instrument to be High Treason; but that all and every the Offences are hereby adjudged, and shall be adjudged, taken, and deemed to be High Treason; and that all and every the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg> and <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> shall suffer the pains and penalties of High Treason, the said Ordinance, or anything therein contained to the contrary, in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Also by another Ordinance, this day passed an Ordinance touching the Assessment, in which, His Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of His Council, doth Declare and Ordain, That in case the way, or manner of Assessing the said latter three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> Assessment by a Pound Rate, in such sort as is prescribed by the said Act, shall prove prejudicial, and obstructive to the bringing in the said latter Three <reg orig="Moneths">Months</reg> Assessment appointed by the said Act, by the time in the said Act for that purpose limited, That then, and in all such cases, the said Commissioners in any of the said Cities, Counties, Towns, and places in the said Act mentioned, where such obstructions shall be or happen, shall appoint a general meeting together, and the major part of them meeting may, and are hereby authorised (for the removal of such obstructions, and the more speedy and effectual execution of the said Act) to proceed according to the most just and equal way of Rates held in such places in the proportioning, levying and assessing the respective sums charged upon them, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Act <pb n="7" />to the contrary thereof contained in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Several Petitions were this day heard, and Orders made therein, by His Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, 18 February.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from beyond the Seas, came as followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Rome</em>, 13 January.</i></head>

<p>The Lord <em>Messino</em>, the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Nuncio, hath order to go into <em>Spain</em> to negotiate, and hasten the general Peace, according to the Instructions given him by his holiness; being charged to do the dame afterward with His Majesty of <em>France</em>: The Pope hath also by his Letters, given charge to the Cardinal of <em>Esle</em>, and to that of <em>Trivultio</em>, Protectors of <em>France</em>, and of <em>Spain</em>, to contribute their most earnest <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to make the <reg orig="designe">design</reg> to take effect, for the advance of the Romish Religion.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, 2 February.</i></head>

<p>Notwithstanding the <reg orig="Amnisty">Amnesty</reg> granted the agreement made between the Dukes of <em>Vendosme</em> and <em>Candale</em>, and this City, Mr. <em>d'Estrade</em> (who commands now here at this time) suffers none, but whom he pleaseth, to enjoy the benefit thereof, but according to the command he hath received from the Court, hath put a great number of our Citizens into the <reg orig="Justices">Justice's</reg> hands, and hath caused some to be put to death; having also lately caused Mr. <em>Dureteste</em>, who hath formerly <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> himself one of the best affected to the welfare of this City, to be arrested, to have his <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg> made to him by the <reg orig="Intendant">Intendent</reg> of Justice, that he may be deprived of all hopes and means of clearing himself. But the said Mr. <em>Dureteste</em> hath appealed to the Parliament, letting them know, that it more properly belongeth to them to judge him, insomuch, That the foresaid Mr. <em>d'Estrade</em> hath been forced to <reg orig="forbeare">forbear</reg> a while, and to send to the Court for further order.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Paris</em>, 7 February.</i></head>

<p>The Duke of <em>Longueville</em>, is at last, by the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> order, arrived here from <em>Normandy</em>, that he may be present to the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg>. Being no more doubted of the agreement between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the United Provinces, this Court would fain <reg orig="finde">find</reg> some way to be comprehended <pb n="8" />in the same, and it is reported that the Marshal <em>d'</em><unclear><em>Aumont</em></unclear> is like to be sent Ambassador for that purpose.</p>

<p>From Flushing 9 Febru. <i>One <em>Willebort Bosse</em> Inhabitant of this place coming lately from the Caribde Islands with a small vessel of six <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance laden with Tobacco and other like commodities, and having about the Canaries met with an English vessel of 3 or 4 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> only, laden with <reg orig="spanish">Spanish</reg> Soap and other Goods, esteemed to the value of 2000 li. Flemish, hath taken and brought her to Rochell. There was also 4 or five <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago by Cap. <em>Oliv. Danielle</em> brought in a prize worth 20 or 24000 <reg orig="Gilders">Guilders</reg>. And three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago one Cap. <em>Lembrant</em>, who hath taken five prizes with <reg orig="coales">coals</reg>, and amongst them a Flute called the <em><reg orig="Eliphant">Elephant</reg></em>, formerly taken by the English, Capt. <em>John van Brug</em> and another Freebooter had taken two prizes from the same Fleet, but they were parted by storm and misty weather, and so they lost them again.</i></p>

<p><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 11 Febru.</i> We begin to conceive great hopes of the Treaty between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, and are much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at the good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of that Negotiation. There are great preparations made by Sea in <em>Denmark</em>. We hear from <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em> that over against <em>Leatzer</em> the hath appeared in the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg> a star of an extraordinary bigness with many shining streams round about. And from <em>Erford</em> that in the Country thereabout there is so infinite a number of <reg orig="Mise">Mice</reg> of all colours, and of other like beasts bred out of corruption, that it is feared they will eat up the fruits of the earth, spreading all that Country over as far as <em>Brunswick</em>.</p>

<p><i>From the Hague 20 Febru.</i> This day Mr. <em>Stocker</em>, sent by the Protestant Cantons of <em>Switzerland</em> to mediate a Reconciliation between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and the United Provinces, who hath formerly resided long at <em>London</em>, is arrived here. The Freebooters <em>de Haen</em> hath brought in three ships taken upon the coasts of <em>Scotland</em>, two laden with coals, and a Flute laden with salted Salmon and other Goods. The last Sunday arrived here an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> from <em>London</em>, with Letters from the Lord <em>Beverling</em> to the Lords States General. The Provinces of <em>Zealand, Utrecht, Freezland</em>, and <em>Overyssel</em>; first brought into the Lords States General their Resolution upon the Ratification of the Articles of Peace, and according to the resolution of the Lords States of <em>Holland</em>, approved of, and ratified them. The next day the same was done by the States of <em>Gilderland</em> and <em>Gronning</em>. Insomuch that <pb n="9" />it is generally hoped that the Treaty <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> very shortly be brought to a full conclusion, and some Ambassadors go speedily for <em>England</em>, <reg orig="onely">on1ly</reg> altering some things in the Articles proposed and signed by the Deputies of both sides in <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>This day a 11 Prisoners were sent from <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> to the Tower accused to be actors in the late Plot.</p>

<p>The Design was so far as I have received Information, by what can be gathered from their Confessions, who have been examined about it; some of whom pretended to be ingenuous in laying open the whole Design.</p>

<p>1. That an Oath of <reg orig="Secresie">Secrecy</reg> should be given to all, to whom it should be revealed, which accordingly was done; and none was made privy to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of it, before he first took the Oath.</p>

<p>2. That the Design should be carried on in the management thereof, by such as should be judged Royalists, (as they call them) faithful Friends to <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, their Titular King.</p>

<p>3. That so many Persons should be engaged for Officers to an Army, as should undertake for the private listing of 30000 men to be ready to rise at a time appointed.</p>

<p>4. That at the same time wherein they should so rise, that they should fall on to act what was designed in all the several Counties, and parts of <em>England</em> at once.</p>

<p>5. That one party should at that time fall upon His Highness, the Lord Protector, to murder Him, and His Life-guard, and those Officers and others that should be about Him: and they had two days debate, Whether they should fall upon His Highness at that time when He dined in the City of <em>London</em>, and murder Him, and those with Him then; but it was resolved in the negative, because <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> was not in <em>England</em> <pb n="10" />, nor their Forces ready in other parts of <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>6. That the same time another party should have <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> on the Council at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and have murdered them, and their attendants. 7. That the Garrison at <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> should be also at the same time <reg orig="seised">seized</reg> on; and the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> surprised in their Quarters there, and at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>; and all those murdered that opposed. 8. That a strong party should at the same time <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> upon the Warders at the Tower of <em>London</em>; and others <reg orig="sculking">skulking</reg> up and down within, lying at the Taverns and Ale-houses, and other parts within ready to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, to <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> upon the Lieutenant and the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>; let out the prisoners, and take possession of the Tower. 9. That at this time <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> (whom they <reg orig="cal">call</reg> their King) should be ready private in a place of the City of <em>London</em>, and be brought forth and presently crowned and proclaimed King; and have the Government put into his hands by them: And all that should oppose it in the City, to be presently murdered. 10. That at the same time parties should <reg orig="seise">seize</reg> upon all the several Garrisons and Guards in <em>England</em>, where the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> are, to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> by force to be possessed of their Holds and Arms. 11. Proclamations to be sent out to all parts of <em>England</em>, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, Son of the late King, was crowned King, and received into the City (but not signifying by what means) offering Pardon to all, both <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and others, that would come in, and comply with the said Design. 12. That those of the late <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> party, and all Puritans, and strict Religious people that are zealous Protestants, <pb n="11" />should be strictly handled. 13. That all Papists, and Popish Priests, should have the free exercise of their Religion.</p>

<p>They had had many meetings in several places about this <reg orig="Businesse">Business</reg>, but removed from one place to another. And their last meeting was Tuesday 14 <em>Febr.</em> 1653. at Mr. <em>Tho. <reg orig="Amps">Amp's</reg></em> Vintner at the Ship Tavern in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>. So desperate they were even to themselves, that (as is confessed by one of those taken) one of the Plotters said to his fellow, that if ever they came to be discovered, and were taken, that if <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was with him, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> would have him presently pull out his knife and cut his throat, else he swore he would be the death of him, After <reg orig="severall">several</reg> meetings they came about two or three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> before it was discovered to consider of some choice persons to be at the helm, as it were, of a secret or cabinet <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to act above, touching the head motions of their Affairs as they should receive Instructions from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> their pretended King. And the number of these chief persons they resolved should be four, and accordingly they chose out 4. One of which, viz. Mr. <em>Cotes</em>, came to the Officers and revealed the Design, and much of the particulars, and assured them that if they went that night, which was Tuesday the 14 of <em>Febr.</em> 1653. They should find some of them met and sitting in such at the Ship Tavern in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>. And hereupon Lieut. Col. <em>Worsley</em> and divers others of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> at <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> went that evening to Mr. <em><reg orig="Amps">Amp's</reg></em> at the said Ship Tavern, and there found ten of them: They searched them, but could find not so much as any papers or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> about them that could make any discovery what they had done. And the Master of the Tavern protesteth that he knew not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of their Design, only they came in to drink, he was brought away prisoner with them, but because no charge was by any made against him, he was after let go again. They were that night brought to <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em>, and one or two of them, especially one very penitent, and <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> and took on lamentably; they were there kept until Saturday <em>February</em> 18 but in the interim, they were examined, and were <em>Februa.</em> 16 brought before a Committee of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and so at other times severally examined. Saturday 18 <em>Febru.</em> they were sent to the Tower where they are committed prisoners.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Names of those that are sent Prisoners from <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> to the Tower of <em>London</em>.</i></head>

<p><i>Mr. <em>Tomas Dutton</em>, Mr. <em>Joseph Sawyer</em>, Mr. <em>William Jenkins</em> Mr. <em>John Archer</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas Bunch</em>, Mr. <em>Joseph Parker</em>, Mr. <em>Roger Lee</em>, Dr. <em>Thomas Ross</em>, Mr. <em>Christopher Watkins</em> Captain <em>Smith</em>, Mr. <em>Roger Cotes</em>.</i></p>

<p>The Lord <em>Hastings</em> hearing he was named to be suspected hath been with the Council to clear himself. Some others are apprehended, and some Apprentices run away, and left <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> with their Masters for the moneys they have taken.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 20 Febru.</i></head>

<p>This day the 2 Deputies from the Governor of <em>Anceland</em> dined at his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg>, at the Cock-pit with great entertainment.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Letter of the routing of the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>I Marched out of <em>Aberdeen</em> on Wednesday last with 5 Companies of Col. <em><reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfield's</reg></em>, 3 of the late Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg></em>, 4 Troops of Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> horse, and two of Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em>, and the party that came from the <em>Merns</em> and <em>Angus</em>, with 3 Troops of my own Dragoons. And upon Thursday about two <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> we came to the <em>Lough</em> at the head of <em>Cromar</em>, where <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, where after a little dispute we totally routed their Army, but being so near the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> we could <reg orig="doe">do</reg> no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> take and <reg orig="kil">kill</reg> about 140 having pursued them seven miles into the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, their Gen. hardly escaping with about 40 horse. All the rest being quite dispersed, Maj. <em>Knight</em> came up even when we were going to engage; we are now upon our march towards their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Kildruny</em>, which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hope to give you a good account of, I shall give you the particulars in my next: no more but that I am <i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honours'</reg> humble Servant, <em>Tho. Morgan</em>. Lowrie 10 Febru. 1653, at 6 in the morning.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 14 Febr. 1653. <i>On Thursday last Col. <em>Morgan</em> with a <reg orig="partie">party</reg> of 1200 Horse, Foot and Dragoons engaged <em>Glencairn</em> and <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> Army (given out to be 2000) at a <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> which they had that day at the head of <em>Cromar</em> 16 miles from <em>Aberdeen</em>, and though the Enemy had the advantage, after a little dispute they were totally routed, <pb n="13" />and pursued seven miles in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. <em>Kenmore</em> had left a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in <em>Kildrumming</em> (the Earl of <em><reg orig="Mars">Mars's</reg></em> Castle) which our men were then marching against. Since this we have news of Cap. <reg orig="Motlowes">Motlow's</reg> marching out of the <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> of <em>Dunstasnage</em> and <em>Dunolly</em> with a party out of those two Garrisons, and that he fell upon the house <em>Archetton</em> in <em>Lorn</em> in <em><reg orig="Argileshire">Argyleshire</reg></em>, and took it with all the men Arms, and Ammunition in it. He killed three and afterwards (that it might not <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> any more of those wild <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>) fired it. Since which Lieut. Col. <em>Cotterel</em> marched out of <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> to reduce the Garrison of <em>Rosse-dew</em> <reg orig="neare">near</reg> <em>Loch Lomond</em>, and before he came <reg orig="neer">near</reg> it the Enemy ran away and left word they had no order to fight. We heard also yesterday that <em>Brokie</em> Cap. Lieut. to Col. <em>Wogan</em> is dead of his wounds, and the Earl of <em>Athol</em> (that fires and burns <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> corn and houses) <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> to shoot <em>Holland</em> the <reg orig="Chyurgion">Surgeon</reg> to death for not curing <em>Wogan</em> and <em>Brokie</em>. Some of these Blades begin to cry peccavi, and sent to desire liberty to live peaceably, and no doubt ere long they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> betray one another into our hand.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 21 February.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>Capt. <em><reg orig="Fosters">Foster's</reg></em> Letter of a hot fight with, and taking the convoy of the Dutch <reg orig="Fisher-men">Fishermen</reg>.</i></head>

<p><i>Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg>,</i></p>

<p>In pursuance of your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> Orders dated 28 <em>Jan.</em> 1653. I <reg orig="repared">repaired</reg> to the River <em>Humber</em>, the 11 instant, (having till then been prevented by Northerly winds and thick weather) and gave notice thereof to the rest of the Commanders appointed to proceed with me in this Expedition, whose answer to me intimated their unfitness to sail at that present. The 12. the wind being Southerly, the <em>Phenix</em> and <em>Amity</em> set sail toward the station, desiring the <reg orig="others">others'</reg> speedy repair to us; towards night the wind came to N.N.W. we standing alongst the Dogger, fell amongst the <reg orig="Hollanders">Hollanders'</reg> Dogger-boats. And the 13. so soon as day appeared in the morning we discovered two sails which we concluded to be their convoys, and bore the one of us to one of them, and the other to the other, they about two leagues distant from us. The <em>Phenix</em> sailing best, I chose the ship furthest off, fearing he might escape the other, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> up each with his chase, mine proved to be a <em><reg orig="Swead">Swede</reg></em> come from <em>Newcastle</em>, which having on board prohibited goods, exceeding his allowance for provisions, as also being <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> he was the man of <reg orig="Wars">War's</reg> prize, he being in the body <pb n= "14" />of their vessels, and having twice the number of men on board accustomed to <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> such a ship. I have thought it my duty to bring him into <em>Humber</em>, not assuming the power to permit <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> of whom I have the least just cause of suspicion. I gave referred him to the Commissioners for prize Goods at <em>Hull</em>.</p>

<p>The ship the <em>Amity</em> stood with, proved to be the <reg orig="Fishers">Fisher's</reg> convoy, a Man of War of <em>Zealand</em>, a ship of 20 guns and 70 men, and lying in his two courses, seemed (at a distance) to be no such ship; he discovering the <em>Amity</em> <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for him, they <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> very smartly for some time, The <em>Amity</em> having shot his Top-mast by the board, shattered the ship exceedingly, and slew and wounded most of his men. The <em>Phenix</em> by reason of her chase (and for that she <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> by all means to escape from us) and the wind shifting was to Leeward approaching <reg orig="neare">near</reg> them. The enemy <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> his ship to Capt. <em>Pack</em>. The <em>Amity</em> is shattered (but one man slain) the prize totally disabled. I have judged it best to secure her for her Guns and <reg orig="Cables">Cables'</reg> sake (she hath seven new Cables) which is most considerable in her; her Hull being old.</p>

<p><i>Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg>, Your <reg orig="Honors">Honours'</reg> humble Servant <em>Nicholas Foster</em>. Phenix <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> 14. <em>Febr.</em> 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of three other Prizes brought into the Fleet at St. <reg orig="Ellins">Ellin's</reg>.</i></head>

<p>1 <em>Jacob Yeankes</em> Mr. of the <reg orig="Pinke">Pink</reg> <em>St. David</em> of <em>Horn</em> 90 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> his lading 2000 Holland Cheeses, 8000 Pan Tiles, 21 Firkins of Butter, 2000 Pipe-staves, and some Hoops bound for <em><reg orig="Lisbone">Lisbon</reg></em>, taken by Captain <em>Francis Allen</em> Commander of the <em>Advice</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>
 
<p>2 <em>Jose Johnson</em> Mr. of the <unclear><em>Bean</em></unclear> of <em>Tragoose</em>, twenty last, laden with <reg orig="Wheate">Wheat</reg>, Rye, Beans, <reg orig="Pease">Peas</reg>, and six pots of Mather came from <em>Zealand</em>, and bound for <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> taken by Capt. <em>John</em> <unclear><em>Umpherias</em></unclear> Commander of the <unclear><em>Nightingale</em></unclear> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>3 <unclear><em>Cornelius Peterson</em></unclear> of <unclear><em>Reegn</em></unclear> in <unclear><em>Leizland</em></unclear> Master of the <em>Arms</em> of <unclear><em>Reegn</em></unclear> 120 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> nothing by Ballast bound for <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantws</reg></em>, taken by <reg orig="Captane">Captain</reg> <em>Robert Sansum</em> Commander of the <em>Adventure</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>This night from <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> until six were disputes at Dr. <pb n="15" /><em><reg orig="Chamberlins">Chamberlain's</reg></em> house in White-<reg orig="Friers">Friars</reg>, which is to continue every Tuesday night at the same time. The conclusion was, that disputes amongst Christians are warrantable by the Word, and of great use, if they be not with vain janglings, but for edification.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 22 Febru.</i></head>

<p><em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> in <em>Scotland</em> 13 <em>Feb.</em> On Thursday last Col. <em>Cooper</em> sent forth a party from hence of 400 foot, and about 100 horse and Dragoons to <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em>, and on Saturday by the advantage of this dry weather, they had a party of about 400 foot, and 100 horse in the Island, but upon our approach they are fled without any dispute at any <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, though they might have done it with great advantage, and out of great <reg orig="feare">fear</reg> quit their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> away the iron gates of it by boat.</p>

<p>Grimsby 16 Feb. <i>Capt. <em>Pack</em> hath taken a Dutch man of War, who fought 7 hours before he would <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, we slew 7 of his men, and wounded 15. His fore Topmast was shot by the board, and the ship so torn between wind and water that she was nigh sinking, and so towed hither, her name is the <em>Sandenburgh</em> of Syrick-sea, one Cap. J. <em>Arionson Blanker</em> commander she had 20 guns, we lost but one man, viz. our Cook and 4 wounded.</i></p>

<p>Letters from <em>Paris</em> say Mr. <em>Beverling</em> hath large Commission sent him to treat with <em>England</em>; and that honest Mr. <em>Du Rantiste</em> is put to death in <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, was put on the <reg orig="wheele">wheel</reg>, and his head set on a Pole.</p>

<p>Divers Petitions were this day answered by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>This day the Resident of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> from all the <unclear>Hans</unclear> Towns did congratulate his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in the present Government.</p>

<p>The wind hath been against the Lord Ambassadors coming from Holland; only this day it is changed, so that suddenly they are expected; however the Lord Ambassador Beverling, hath full power to sign the Peace.</p>

<p>I need not tell you of the people this day staring upon a <reg orig="Starre">Star</reg>; for such foolish actions are too much followed.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>The New Birth, in which is brought forth the New Creature. With a Description of the true marks and characters thereof; &amp;c. By R. B. a servant of Jesus Christ. Sold by L. Blaiklock at Temple Bar, and by J. Hancock in <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg>-head Alley.</p>

<p>The Anabaptists silenced in a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Dispute betwixt J. Tombs D. D. Respondent and J. Cragge, &amp; H. Vaughan M. A. Opponents touching Infant <reg orig="Baptisme">Baptism</reg>, Septemb. 5. 1653. in <reg orig="Maries">Mary's</reg> Church in Abergavenie in Monmouthshire, occasioned by a Sermon Mr. Tombs, with a Sermon of Mr. Cragge on the same Text. Sold by H. Twiford, Nath. Brook, and J. Place.</p>

<p>A Treatise of the <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> of Humility. Published by E. Duncan. To <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sold by Tho. Johnson at the golden Key in Paul's <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>