<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState234">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 234</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 16 of <em>March</em> To Thursday the 23 day of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 16 March. 1653.</i></head>

<p>The Ambassador from the Arch Duke <em>Leopold</em>, that had some weeks since had audience by the Lord Protector, to congratulate his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, being now to return back to his Master, hath taken his leave of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and is returning homeward.</p>

<p>Upon the debate of the Commissioners with the Dutch Ambassadors, the Articles drawn upon both sides upon the Agreement have been examined, and the differences compared and debated, and some things reconciled, the rest as to <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, considered of.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg> 6 March</i>. In my last I gave you an account of <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> landing in <em>Scotland</em>, there is since a <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> come for him into <reg orig="Carthnesse">Caithness</reg>, whether <pb n="1" /><reg orig="hee">he</reg> is gone to <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> if <reg orig="hee">he</reg> can to draw the Gentlemen of that Country into an <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg> with him, which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hear they are backward in, notwithstanding he gives out great words, and talks of divers Vessels with Arms to come to him: <em><reg orig="Seaford">Seafort</reg></em> is <reg orig="indevouring">endeavouring</reg> all he can to get some of his men together to meet him, the Country generally <reg orig="disrellishes">disrelishes</reg> their proceedings, by the next I may have an occasion of enlarging.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith 14 March.</i> Upon <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing in <em>Sutherland</em>, he sent summons to the Gentlemen of <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg> Sutherland and <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg>, to give him a meeting at his <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be the last of February (at the place where <em>Montrosse</em> was formerly overthrown) upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg>, and there to send in their Levies of men and horse.</p>

<p>When <em>Middleton</em> came <reg orig="ashoare">ashore</reg>, he writ to the <reg orig="Sheriffe">Sheriff</reg> of Sutherland, requiring him not to keep any more Courts in the name of the Commonwealth of England. <em>Seafort</em> hath gotten six hundred of his men together again, and is gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>.</p>

<p>There was brought in the Vessel with <em>Middleton</em> 300 barrels of Powder, 1000 Snaphance-firelocks, and as many Pikes, Muskets, and Pistols, as made in all 5000 Arms, which with two <reg orig="brasse">brass</reg> field pieces, were lodged in the Castle of Skelbo, which is secured by Major Gen. <em>Dyel</em>, and one Major <em>Watson</em>, with six or <reg orig="sevenscore">seven score</reg> men; <em>Glencairn, Kenmore, <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg>, Athol</em> and <em>Forbs</em>, with their Rabble, intend their <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> as on this day 24 miles from Aberdeen, from whence Col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched forth to <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> with them.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg></em> 12 March. A small <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> of Topsam that came from St. <reg orig="Sabastians">Sebastian's</reg>, and commanded by Cap. <em>Stafford</em>, who had a Commission for a private man of War, brought in hither a French prize of 30 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Iron, <reg orig="Licoris">Liquorice</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p><em>Beach, Charles <reg orig="Stewarts">Stuart's</reg></em> Pirate, and his crew are brought into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, and close Prisoners there till further Order for their <reg orig="triall">trial</reg>, which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> speedily.</p>

<p>The Ordinance for appointing Commissioners for approving of Ministers throughout the Nation, is in debate by the Council. Also an Ordinance for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Customs and Excise.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>By Letters from <em>Harwich</em> we understand of a Dutch ship of 400 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts and Iron, to a great value, brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>

<head level="3">From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 10 March.</head>

<p>A few <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since the Earl <em>Goldenlyon</em> is arrived here from <em><reg orig="Bruxell">Brussels</reg></em> to make some <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, but it is not <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> that he shall be able to obtain leave to do it. We hear from <em>Denmark</em> that the King is resolved to go into <em>Holstein</em> where all is in peace. We hear no more of the great preparations for setting His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Fleet to Sea, as it was formerly thought.</p>

<head level="3">From Texell the 13. Of March.</head>

<p><i>Two Freebooters are gone to Sea from this Road. And three <em>Swedish</em> ships are arrived here, amongst whom is a great Pinnace coming from <em>Sarrant</em> laden with Strong-waters and Tobacco, which was <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> away, and hath been kept in <em>England</em> about five months. The tenth instant two other <em>Swedish</em> ships sailed from hence to <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, and the same day came ten Merchants ships in here, one of them an East-India ship.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rome 19 February.</i></head>

<p>The Pope hath sent to Cardinal <em>Pamphilio</em> to warn him to depart from this City within 27 hours with all his near Kindred, the which Order hath been executed so, that the said <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> is within the time limited gone in a <reg orig="chut">shut</reg> Coach, with his Brother the Marquis <em>Astaly</em> to one of the said Marquis his houses called <em>Sambucy</em> not far from <em>Tivoli</em>, the which doth make <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> wonder at such an <reg orig="excesse">excess</reg> of <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg> from his <reg orig="Holinesse">Holiness</reg>; and it gives occasion to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> discourses, with expectation that His <reg orig="Holinesse">Holiness</reg> shall in the next Consistory disclose to his Cardinals the grounds of such a high displeasure. It is further muttered that he shall be arraigned and deprived of all his Revenues, a sum of 15000 Crowns belonging to him having already been forfeited to the Pope and his crimes seem to be so high that none of his friends durst as yet speak in his <reg orig="behalfe">behalf</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">From Montpellier 7 March.</head>

<p><i>The States of <em>Languedoc</em> have in their Assembly freely of themselves granted to the King a Subsidy of 150000 Crowns towards the War and Ordered the said sum to be forthwith <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> and paid.</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3">From <reg orig="Leige">Liege</reg> 20 March</head>

<p><i>The last Sunday very early came here an express from <em><reg orig="Bruxell">Brussels</reg></em> with Letters from his Highness <em>Leopoldus</em> intimating that as well the <em>Spanish</em> Forces, as those of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, as of the Dukes of <em>Wertembergh</em> and <em>Lorrain</em> are commanded to retire from this Country, so that we hope by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> mercy to recover shortly our peace again.</i></p>

<p>The Lords Ambassadors have received their Coach and other Treasure from <em>Holland</em>, the Coach is very rich, with the Prince of <em><reg orig="Oranges">Orange's</reg></em> <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> in gold, and <reg orig="faire">fair</reg> cullers at the end of the Coach.</p>

<p>Letters came from the Fleet that some of the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> and the rest that quartered at some distance from the Fleet, had Orders to march to the <reg orig="water side">waterside</reg>.</p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector was this day with the Council, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> were referred to Committees, and this day several Committees <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> and made <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> in divers businesses.</p>

<p>This night His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector lay in Whitehall, who being not well by reason of a cold, lay in one of the Chambers formerly the Queen's privy lodgings.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 17 March,</i></head>

<p>This day passed an Ordinance for continuance of the Excise for one year from March 1654. by which His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of His Council, doth Ordain, That from and after the five and twentieth day of this present <em>March</em>, the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Rates and charges hereafter set <reg orig="downe">down</reg>, and every of them and none other, in the right of the duty of Excise, shall be set, laid, and imposed, and are hereby laid, set, and imposed, to be had levied, demanded, collected, received, recovered and paid, in and through <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, and Town and Port of <em><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em>, upon all and every the Commodities, <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> and Manufactures, Native and Foreign, in manner following, that is to say,</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rates of Excise and Commodities of Inland making or growth.</i></head>

<p>For every <reg orig="Barrell">Barrel</reg> of Beer of Ale of above six shillings the Barrel brewed by the common Brewer, or any who sell Beer or Ale, to pay 2s.</p>

<p>For every Barrel of six shilling Beer or Ale, or above <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <pb n="4" />the Barrel, brewed by the common Brewer or any other who sell Beer or ale, to pay 6d.</p>

<p>And so proportionably for a greater or lesser quality of Beer or Ale above four shillings the Barrel.</p>

<p>And no allowance to be made from henceforth for any Beer or Ale to be used in Fishing Vessels at Sea, which is bought of the Common Brewer, or Retailer of Beer or Ale.</p>

<p>Allum English the hundred weight, containing one hundred and twelve pounds, to be paid by the Maker, 6d.</p>

<p><reg orig="Coper">Copper</reg> as English, the hundred weight, to be paid by the Maker 6d.</p>

<p>Hops English, the hundred weight, to be paid by the Planter, 2s.</p>

<p>Saffron English, for every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the Planter, 1s.</p>

<p>Tin for every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the buyer, 1s.</p>

<p>Iron English, for every hundred weight, to be paid by the Maker, 1s. 6d.</p>

<p>For all Aqua vitae or Strong-water, made or distilled within the Commonwealth, whether of <reg orig="Forregin">Foreign</reg> or <reg orig="Domestick">Domestic</reg> Spirits or Materials, to be sold, upon every Gallon, to be paid by the first Maker or Seller thereof respectively, 2d.</p>

<p>For every Barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within this Commonwealth of what sort soever, to be paid by the Maker, and so proportionably for hard <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> or soft <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within the Land, 4s.</p>

<p>For every Ounce Troy of Silver or Gold, prepared, melted down, or disgrossed for <reg orig="Wyer">Wire</reg>, to be paid at the Bar where the same shall be disgrossed, 2d.</p>

<p>For every pound weight, of any Copper, or other Metal, that shall be prepared, made fit, or disgrossed, to be paid at the Bar where the same shall be disgrossed, 1s.</p>

<p>For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Whale <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Blubber <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Rape <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Pilchard <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, and all other <reg orig="Oyls">Oils</reg> made within this Commonwealth, upon every <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, to be paid by the Maker, 6s. <em>per</em> Tun.</p>

<p>For every Fother of Lead, containing two thousand pound <pb n="5" />weight, at one hundred and twelve pounds to the hundred, to be paid by the Maker or Smelter, 6s. 8d.</p>

<p>For all Salt, made, or to be made whom <em>England, Wales</em>, or Town of <em>Berwick</em>, which is or shall be shipped or conveyed by water, to be paid by the first buyer of such Salt at the place of Landing or unloading thereof, upon every Gallon a half penny.</p>

<p>For all other Salt, made, or to be made within <em>England, Wales</em>, or Town of <em>Berwick</em>, and not shipped or conveyed by water, to be paid by the first buyer thereof upon the first delivering, upon every Gallon, a half penny.</p>

<p>Upon all Salt upon Salt, that is made of Salt within <em>England, Wales</em>, or Town of <em>Berwick</em> to be paid by the Maker thereof, upon every Gallon a farthing.</p>

<p>For all <reg orig="Syder">Cider</reg> and Perry, made, and sold by way of Retail, whether it be by the first Maker, or any Buyer or Receiver thereof, from the first Maker upon every Hogshead, and so for a greater and lesser measure proportionably, 2s. 6d.</p>

<p>For all Metheglin or Mead, and such like Drinks sold out by Retail, to be paid by the Retailer, upon every Gallon and so <em>pro rato</em>, 1d.</p>

<p>For all Starch, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, to be paid by the maker, 1s.</p>

<p>For all sorts of Glass or Glasses, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, to be paid by the maker, 1s.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rates of Excise of <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> Goods imported.</i></head>

<p>For every pound of Tobacco, which is not of the English Plantation, as well already imported and remaining in the hands of the Merchant or Importer, as to be imported, to be paid by the first buyer.</p>

<p>For every pound of Tobacco of the English Plantation, as well imported and remaining in the hands of the Importer, as to be imported, to be paid by the first buyer, 3d.</p>

<p>For every Tun of Wine already imported or to be imported, to be paid by the first Buyer, whether Retailer or private Consumptioner, 6 l.</p>

<p>For every Tun of Wine Vinegar, imported or to be imported, to be paid by the first buyer, 2 l.</p>

<p>For all Spirits imported, or to be imported, made, either of <pb n="6" />French, Rhenish, <unclear>or any other Wines upon every</unclear>, Gallon, to be paid by the first buyer, <unclear>4 l.</unclear></p>

<p>For all Spirits <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> or <reg orig="Domestick">Domestic</reg>, sold instead of Aqua-vitae or Strong-waters, upon every Gallon, to be paid by the utterer and seller thereof, <unclear>1 s.</unclear></p>

<p>For all Strong-waters perfectly made, imported, or to be imported, upon every Gallon, to be paid by the first buyer, 1 s.</p>

<p>For all Beer or Ale imported by Sea, or brought in by Land into <em>England, Wales</em>, or Town of <em>Berwick</em>, for every Barrel to be paid by the Importer, 5 s.</p>

<p>For all Pepper, Sugars, Sugars refined, white and brown Muscavadoes, Candy white and brown, and all other Grocery and Mercery-wares, wrought Silks, Silks in Gum, and ready thrown, <reg orig="Linnens">Linens</reg> fine and course, Upholstery, Haberdashery, Paper, Skins, and Leather, upon every twenty shillings value to be <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> by the first buyer, <unclear><!--2 characters--></unclear>.</p>

<p>For all manner of Drugs, according as they are distinguished by the Book of Rates for the Customs, upon every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the first buyer, 2 s.</p>

<p>For all <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> imported or to be imported, soft or hard, for every hundred weight thereof, to be paid by the first buyer, 5 s.</p>

<p>For all Saltery Wares not particularly rated in this Schedule imported or to be imported, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, as they or any of them shall be sold at a price, to be paid by the first buyer, 1 s.</p>

<p>For all Hops <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg>, the hundred weight, to be paid by the first buyer, over and above Customs, 5 s.</p>

<p>For all Hemp, Flax, <reg orig="Towe">Tow</reg>, Tar, <reg orig="Rozen">Resin</reg>, Pitch, Wax, Tallow, Cable, Cable-<unclear>yarn</unclear>, and all manner of Cordage, upon every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the first buyer, 6 d.</p>

<p>for all sort of Glass or Glasses; and all manner of Earthenware whatsoever, upon every twenty shillings value, to be paid by the first buyer, <unclear>2 s.</unclear></p>

<p>For all manner of <reg orig="Wooles">Wools</reg> Cloth, or Stuffs, or other <reg orig="woolen">woollen</reg> Manufactures imported, for every Yard measure over and above the Rates mentioned of Customs, to be paid by the Importer, 1 s.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>For all Raw Silk imported, or to be imported, for every twenty shillings value thereof, and so proportionably for a greater or lesser value, to be paid by the first buyer, 6 d.</p>

<p>For all <reg orig="Forreign">Foreign</reg> Salt imported, which hath not paid Excise, or to be imported, upon every Gallon, to be paid by the first buyer, three half pence.</p>

<p>For all Bone-Lace imported, for every twenty shillings in value, to be paid by the first buyer, 3 s.</p>

<p>For all <reg orig="died">dyed</reg> Silk imported, for every twenty shillings in value, to be paid by the first buyer, five shillings.</p>

<p>For all silk Lace imported, for every twenty shillings in value, to be paid by the first buyer, three shillings.</p>

<p>For all other Goods and <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> (except Bullion, Corn, Victual, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of Brass or Iron imported or to be imported) not specified or herein rated, to pay after the rate of five pound <em><reg orig="per Cent">percent</reg>.</em> according as the same are charged by the book of Rates for the Customs, to be paid by the first buyer, one shilling.</p>

<p>For all other Goods and <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> imported, or to be imported; upon which no values are set, either in the said book of Rates for Customs, nor in these present Rates for Excise, upon every twenty shillings value thereof, as they or any of them shall be sold at a price, to be paid by the first buyer, one shilling.</p>

<p>That for all Inland or <reg orig="Forein">Foreign</reg> Commodities in this Ordinance mentioned, whether rated by pound weight, hundred weight, fodder, pound value, gallon, Barrel, <reg orig="tun">ton</reg>, or other greater or lesser measure of weight whatsoever, the Excise shall be <reg orig="daly">daily</reg> paid for a greater or lesser quantity <em>pro rato</em>, according to the Rates therein appointed and prescribed respectively.</p>

<p>And it is likewise ordained, That from and after the said 25 day of <em>March</em> instant, <em>Thomas Allen</em> Alderman of the City of <em>London</em>, <em>Thomas Wood, Richard Bury, George Langham</em>, Esqs; and <em>George Foxcroft</em>, Merchant, are constituted and appointed, Commissioners and Governors of the Excise and New Impost, or any three or more of them. And that Sir <em>William Roberts</em>, Knight, <em>John Stone, Henry Elsing, Jervas Bennet, Adam Bains</em>, and <em>John Bocket Esqs;</em> or any three of them, be <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to receive all appeals, &amp;c.</p>

<pb n="8" />

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector received petitions by the hands of the Masters of the Requests. The Council sat in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Committees, about some Ordinances and other State Affairs.</p>

<p>This night His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> lay again at the Cock pit.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 18 March.</i></head>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector being yet not well, rid out in his Coach with some of the Lords of the Council through <reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg> Park.</p>

<p>Some Committees of the Council and other Commissioners and Committees <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> this day.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Warsaw in Poland.</i></head>

<p>The States of this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> have begun their sitting of the 10th. of this instant <em>February</em>. On the 14. the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Proposition was made by the great Lord Chancellor, and the same day the Prince <em>Charles</em> of this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of <em>Poland</em> made a very costly Banquet, where their Majesties were, and some other great Lords. We have received <reg orig="newes">news</reg> that the <em>Tartarians</em> have plundered the Country as far as five miles from <em>Lublyn</em>, carrying away with them many Men, Cattle and other Goods. Those of <em>Muscovy</em> have made an Invasion in the land of <em>Smolenskie</em>, whereupon the Prince <em>Radzelill</em> is gone to <em>Littoanen</em> as the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> General, to oppose them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Venice the 26 Feb.</i></head>

<p>We <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> from <em>Candia</em> that the that the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Canea</em> hath made a sally out upon the Turks, who were advanced under their <reg orig="wals">walls</reg>, and have after a hot fight been forced to retire to their old quarters. There are 4 ships, carrying 40000 Ducats, and some <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> newly raised, ready to set sail for <em>Candia</em>. Another <reg orig="Gally">Galley</reg> is gone into <unclear><em>Dalinatia</em></unclear> with 30000 Ducats to pay the Army. The Marquis <em>Berry</em> shall be <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Horse there and <em>Dam Camillo Gansagne</em> shall command those in <em>Candia</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From Paris 7 March.</head>

<p><i>It is certainly reported that Mr. <em>de Lionne</em> hath been sent to Rome to fetch Cardinal <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> Father, bringing him at the same time the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Patent to make him a Duke and Peer of <em>France</em>, as also Knight of His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Order which they call the Order of the Holy Ghost, the said Cardinal his Son purchasing for him against his coming the Dukedom of <em>Nevers</em>.</i></p>

<pb n="9" />

<head level="3"><i>From Paris 14 March.</i></head>

<p><em>Charles Stuart</em> the titular King of Scots is yet here, and it is reported that he shall go for <em>Scotland</em> as soon as he shall have dispatched some little businesses he hat to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> here. But that I think is but a <reg orig="vapor">vapour</reg>, he rather <reg orig="enclining">inclining</reg> (if it may be) towards the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Country; but <reg orig="goe">go</reg> somewhere he and his must. The last Monday his Majesty of <em>France's</em> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Brother, with the Marshals <em>du Plessis, Prastling</em> and <em>Villeroy</em>, and with the Lords <em>Vertamont</em> and <em>Briensack</em> Counsellors of State went to the Court of <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> to acquaint them with some of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Edicts or Ordinances. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> went also with the Marshal <em>de Lospital</em>, and the Lords <em>Villemontee</em> and <em>la Fosse</em> <reg orig="Counsellers">Counsellors</reg> of State, to the Court of Subsidies to acquaint them in the same manner of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> will.</p>

<head level="3">From Texel in Holland 18 March.</head>

<p><i>The Freebooter Captain <em>Oomke</em> with another went to sea the 12 instant, and two other Freebooters also went to sea the next day. The said Capt. <em>Oomke</em>, with Capt. <em>Hogtenbeen</em> came home the 15 with a good prize of a Flute laden with French Wines going for <em>London</em>, and from thence for <em>Leith</em>. It is here reported that 20 English ships have appeared before the wall, and that about 8 more are passed through towards the North. And that they have taken five fisher boats at the sight of this land, two belonging to this place, and three to <em>Huysdayne</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From the <em>Hague</em> 20 March.</i></head>

<p>There can be nothing else gathered out of the Letters come lately from <em>England</em>, but that our Ambassadors have been received there with great magnificence, and that we are like to hear by the next post of a full conclusion of the Peace: Some do say that the Ratification thereof shall be delivered of both sides within few weeks. The news concerning the Affairs in <em>Scotland</em> are very various here amongst us.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday 20 March.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance this day passed for continuance of the Act for Customs.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, that one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for continuation of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 16 of <em>March</em> in the year, 1652.</i> and all Powers and Clauses <pb n="10" />therein contained, be, and are hereby continued, and shall and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the six and twentieth day of <em>March</em>, in the year of our Lord, one thousand six hundred fifty eight. And be it further Ordained that the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg> shall not hereafter make repayment of the <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> <reg orig="Subsidie">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported, which have been, or hereafter shall be sold unto, or in the possession of any Shop-keeper or Retailer of the same Commodity, or for any such goods where the property, form or nature of the Commodity once Imported, is in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> altered, mingled, amended or confounded. And be it hereby further Ordained, That the Commissioners of the Customs for the time being shall have and receive upon every twenty shillings coming clear unto the Commonwealth upon their account such salary of poundage, as is or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for Regulating the Customs, or any other thereunto <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his Council.</p>

<p>A Petition from Col. <em>Gill</em> referred to a Committee was this day dispatched, who allow him a Fine, and is reported to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, divers other Petitioners also who have been oppressed find <reg orig="releise">release</reg>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> hasted this day to the dispatch of an Ordinance for the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>, for mending them where need is, and for prevention of breaking the <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> by such great <reg orig="Wanes">Wains</reg> and Carts as have been six, seven or eight Horses in a Team, not for the future to exceed such a number as shall be proportioned; and the Council were also about some other Ordinances which will shortly be dispatched.</p>

<p>A Petition Congratulatory hath been presented from the Town of <em>Newcastle</em> to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, professing much affection to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and the late change of Government.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Newcastle</em> is certified, <em>March</em> 13. That a great Fleet was <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from thence with <reg orig="Coales">Coals</reg> with a convoy for <em>London</em> and other parts: but that the ships mentioned in the last driven by the Pirates on <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg> were in number 12 which neither the Pirates then, nor we since could get any of them off <reg orig="againe">again</reg>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the men are all saved, and some small matter of the goods but the ships and the coals are all lost in the Sea, and none of them could by any means be gotten off. There was one more <pb n="11" />driven on <reg orig="shoare">shore</reg> which, after did get off <reg orig="againe">again</reg>,</p>

<p>By another of the same date from thence thus. <i>Since the Caper we took mentioned in my last Letter with five guns and 35 men. Another of the six Capers (for so many there were that did lurk hereabouts) one of them standing among the Rocks at <em>Readkaw</em> by <em>Hartlepool</em> was torn in <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, and the other four ply up and down about these coasts between this and <em>Leith</em>, and have taken a Yarmouth vessel before Leith, laden with wines come from <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>.</i></p>

<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Brown</em> is come home, being freely discharged, and is at his house in White-<reg orig="Friers">Friars</reg>, <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Paris</em> in <em>France</em> say, that there are Instructions passed for an Ambassador extraordinary with <reg orig="plenepotentiary">plenipotentiary</reg> power to treat and conclude with the Lord Protector for a peace with <em>England</em>, which if effected there must be permission in <em>France</em> for the preaching of the Protestant Religion: It is very like that the cup is now filling out for the Scarlet Whore of <em>Rome</em>, that she that hath so loved to drink the blood of the Saints, may now drink the dregs of the <reg orig="Almighties">Almighty's</reg> wrath, that she may fall and never rise <reg orig="againe">again</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>Since <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing the Enemy are very active in all parts, and will leave no stone unturned. There hath been a conjunction of Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em>, Mr. <em>Gregor</em>, and Mr. <em>Naughton</em> lately, and their <reg orig="generall">general</reg> <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg> was to be the 14 instant at <em>Rothemacchos</em>, or <em>Abernathy</em>. <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> hath obtained a man out of every Plough in <em>Strathrick</em>, and is to have horse and money according to former <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and requires the like from <em>Strathspey, Straddowne, Glenrennos, Bellevine, Murreland</em>, and of the <em><reg orig="Frazers">Frasers</reg></em> in <em>Straglas</em>, and if they <reg orig="faile">fail</reg> to send in their proportions according to the several Warrants, they must expect fire and sword.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Glengarne">Glencairn</reg></em> with his men are in <em>Baganoth</em>, from whom a Servant of one Lieut. Col. <em>Smith</em> with his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> horse ran into our Garrison at <em>Ruthven</em> Castle. They report that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor. There came with <em>Middleton</em> sixty and <reg orig="odde">odd</reg> Officers, the least a Captain and amongst the rest (besides those I formerly hinted to you) Col. <pb n="12" /><em>Henderson</em>, <em>Monroe</em>, and others of them had very cold entertainment in <reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg>. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> and Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> had a <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg> on Wednesday last of about 300 horse and 250 foot, they have place a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in a little house upon <em>Lough-Tay</em> where they intend to have a store of provisions of about 1500 <reg orig="Bolles">Bowls</reg> of <reg orig="victuall">victual</reg>, and to send such of the Commissioners and Heritors thither as refuse to send in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>. On Saturday last Mjor <em>Holmes</em> at <em>Linlithgow</em> having notice of a party of the Enemy in the Country, sent out a Quartermaster of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> Regiment with a party, who took a Cornet and four others of the Enemy, and 11 Horse.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith 14. March, 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 21 March.</i></head>

<p>This morning the Lords Ambassadors of the seven United Provinces of <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em> had audience by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector <reg orig="whether">whither</reg> they were attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, Major General <em>Lambert</em> waited on them betwixt His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> person and the Park gate.</p>

<p>The said Lords Ambassadors being now removed from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>, to Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> in <em><reg orig="Channil">Channel</reg> <reg orig="Roe">Row</reg></em>, near the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>-yard. The Commissioners of the Council appointed to confer with them, that met at the Conference on Wednesday last at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>, were this day appointed to meet them at a Conference at Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> this night. There hath been much pains on both sides since the former Conference, to make all things in as great forwardness as may be.</p>

<p>This night accordingly (about five <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>) the Commissioners with Master <em>Thurloe</em>, Secretary of State, and Master <em>Jesop</em>, Clerk to the Council, in the <em>Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg></em> Coaches, and Attendants, were carried to the Dutch Ambassadors; who when they came to the Gate, were met by the Ambassadors, who came out and saluted them; and with great <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg> and respect entertained them. and they went presently to Conference in a Chamber, by the Ambassadors fitted in Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> house for that purpose, where they Treated until it was late at night.</p>

<p>Some of those that robbed the last week about <em>Suiters hill</em> <pb n="13" />have been since taken; some of them are hurt, one of them in <em>Newgate</em> is sore wounded.</p>

<p>There is one in the <em><reg orig="Gate-house">Gatehouse</reg></em>, suspected to be one that hath an hand in the new counterfeit Half-crowns.</p>

<p>Letters out of <reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg> say, That some persons in that County, by reason of the cheapness of Corn, have in their Corn-fields planted Tobacco; but those that do, had best take heed, or they are like deeply to suffer upon the Act against Planting Tobacco in <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>By Letters from the Fleet is advertised, That since the taking of <em>Beach</em>, there is another private Man of War of <em>Brest</em> taken, of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg>, but much smaller <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="Beaches">Beach's</reg>. The English Fleet are about 100 Sail together about <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em>; besides the Squadrons that are abroad.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Ireland</em> say, That all is in a gallant equipage there; and that there is no discontent of difference, but all things go on wonderful sweetly.</p>

<p><i><em>Newcastle</em>, 16 March. Our Fleet is gone from hence, a great Fleet for <em>London</em>, and other parts that way; they had a good convoy. There were a few small ships more should have gone with them from <em>Sunderland</em>, but got not out soon enough, they lost a tide or two; and there was such a strong an seasonable wind, that the fleet thought it not discretion to stay, when they had so fair opportunity; yet there were 10 ships that got out on Monday last from <em>Sunderland</em>, and though they had no convoy with them, yet they thought they might venture between <em>Newcastle</em> and the Fleet there so lately put out before, and accordingly they put out to follow the Fleet; but were presently set upon by the Capers, and <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be taken, they were forced to run their 20 ships aground; but the Capers pursued then, and after the men were got out, the Capers hot off five of them, and the other five are lost; so that within about a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time, we have lost 22 Coal-ships.</i></p>

<p>Letters from the <em>Downs, March</em> 19. advertise, That that day the Fleet from <em>Newcastle</em>, and the Convoy are in the River of <em>Thames</em>; so that there are now good store of Coals in the River, and the price is like to be very reasonable.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Upsal</em> in <em>Sweden</em> say, The Treaty goes on still <pb n="14" />very hopefully, and that there is something in the <reg orig="Brest">Breast</reg> of the Queen, that makes her think of surrendering up the Government of that Crown into the hands of the States, for the Gentleman; she by their consent was agreed to be Successor. Some think she will marry: But these things are but <em>in <reg orig="embrio">embryo</reg></em>, therefore much (at present) cannot be said of it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 22 March 1653.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Protector this day published a Declaration, Declaring that his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> do purpose to set apart Friday next being the 24 of March instant, for a Day of Humiliation; And Ordered that timely notice <reg orig="bee">be</reg> given to the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, who no doubt will keep the same.</p>

<p>And notice to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> given through <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to have their meetings the same day Fortnight.</p>

<p>The Causes are, first, The common notorious sins impenitently practised amongst us. Secondly, the present long drought, threatening famine &amp; mortality.</p>

<p>The sins taken notice of by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> are, <i>Notwithstanding the just Liberty <reg orig="Spirituall">Spiritual</reg> and <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg>, God hath procured by his own people, yet want of humble walking in the <reg orig="Vertues">Virtues</reg> of Christ, or to communicate that liberty one to another. Or thankfully to acknowledge out liberty of <reg orig="worshiping">worshipping</reg> God in <reg orig="holinesse">holiness</reg>, Want of Brotherly Love. Not owning one another for the Grace of God more <reg orig="then">than</reg> form: Not seeking the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of Christ within us, before one without us. <reg orig="Listning">Listening</reg> to false Christs: <reg orig="Temporall">Temporal</reg> rule for Saints. A crying up of the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, and the other Fruits of the Spirit: And an <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> carriage towards them without: Crying down Ministers that have a large <reg orig="seale">seal</reg> of their Ministry, want of old Puritan <reg orig="selfe">self</reg>-<reg orig="deniall">denial</reg>; Mercy to the poor, uprightness, Justice, and contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, as it ought to be <pb n="15" /><reg orig="Apostatizings">Apostatisings</reg> of many running after notions and fancies against Magistracy, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, Scriptures and Ordinances, like those <em>2 Pet. 2.1 to 16.</em> and <em>Jude 4 to 20.</em> Contempt of the Gospel, and sincere professors of it, even for the Image of Christ in them. <reg orig="Oathes">Oaths</reg>, <reg orig="Drunkennesse">Drunkenness</reg>, Revellings, and all manner of licentiousness. And the impunity of these things, through neglect of the Magistracy in the several parts of this Nation.</i></p>

<p>The Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em> sent out precepts to all the Parishes in the City of <em>London</em>, to have the said Friday 24 <em>March</em> kept a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Fast.</p>

<p>An <em>Ordinance</em> passed for approbation of <em>Ministers</em>. And by the said <em>Ordinance</em> is appointed about 30 <em>Commissioners, Ministers</em> and other able and godly <em>Gentlemen</em>, who are to sit where His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> shall appoint for that purpose.</p>

<p>And another Ordinance for ejection of Ministers ignorant and scandalous is under debate by the Council, which will suddenly be finished.</p>

<p>The <em>Conference</em> between the <em>Dutch Ambassadors</em> and the <em>English Commissioners</em> hath almost finished the <em>Articles</em> to sign; the summing up the <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> of <reg orig="Denmarke">Denmark</reg> <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> hath taken up some time.</p>

<p>The King of <em>France</em> hath sent a Commission to the <em>Lord Ambassador <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> to treat and conclude Peace, who is shortly to be brought to <em>Westminster</em> in the equipage of an Ambassador, and have audience.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are by this all <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg>, Col. <em><reg orig="Ingolsbys">Ingolsby's</reg></em> which were the last, were to be <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> as Saturday last. The English Fleet is a gallant one, which seems to promise a <reg orig="releif">relief</reg> for Christians from Turkish slavery. The halt then may not be long at <em>Leghorn</em>.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>An Exposition on the whole Book of Canticles, wherein the <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> is explained and <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> Observations raised thereupon; Sold by G. &amp; H. Eversden at the <reg orig="Grey-hound">Greyhound</reg> in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p>From the Swan at <em><reg orig="Holburn">Holborn</reg>-Bridge</em> the Post-Coaches for the North do go to <em>York</em> in four <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, and to <em>Newcastle</em> in two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> more, which sets forth every Monday, Wednesday and Friday.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>