<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState233">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 233</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 9 of <em>March</em> To Thursday the 16 day of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 9. March. 1653.</i></head>

<p><i>To His most Excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> by the Divine Providence, <em>Lord Protector</em> of the three Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></p>

<p>The <reg orig="Cordiall">Cordial</reg> Declaration and humble <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> of the <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> and renowned City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, by the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, <reg orig="Sheriffes">Sheriffs</reg> and Common <reg orig="councill">council</reg> thereof, Signed and signified under the Common seal of the said City, at a Common <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> there holden.</p>

<p>Desert and Praise should always go together as Twins, where the one precedes it is an injury to <reg orig="with-hold">withhold</reg> the sequence of the other; So great hath been the desert of your most Excellent Highness (through <pb n="1" />the <reg orig="goodnesse">goodness</reg> of God) in the eyes of all these Nations for divers years past, that we humbly conceive we should make <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> a scorn in the ears of Foreigners for our ingratitude, if we should not make our Praises in some measure commensurable to Your <reg orig="vaste">vast</reg> Achievements.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> sincerely in what we Declare, and do hope that Adulation will not by any good men be interpreted to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> couchant in our Expressions, for we shall speak the words of Truth and <reg orig="Sobernesse">Soberness</reg>. To say nothing of the Pagan world, we presume, there is scarce an ear in Christendom, but hath heard of our distractions, and who it is, under God, that hath been the repairer of the Breach amongst us to purchase <reg orig="Freedome">Freedom</reg> and Liberty for us, that at last <reg orig="wee">we</reg> might sit every man under his own vine and under his own <reg orig="Figtree">Fig tree</reg>, and none to make us afraid.</p>

<p>You have done as <em>Zebulon</em> and <em>Napthali</em> did, jeoparded your precious life unto death for us in the highest places of the field. Your blood was not esteemed dear to You to save a Commonwealth from perishing; We may truly say of Your <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Lordship, as good <em>Jacob</em> said of <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, That in the day the drought consumed him and the frost by night, and his sleep departed from his eyes, and all to save his Uncle <reg orig="Labans">Laban's</reg> cattle, You have been the happy Instrument in the <reg orig="Almighties">Almighty's</reg> hand; You have been our Protector, and (blessed be God) we are not the least <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> of the protected (though inferior to <em>Jobs </em>Nobles) yet we can truly say as <em>Job</em> said of them, That when our ears hear of you, we can find in our hearts to <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> you, and when our eyes see you, to give <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> of you.</p>

<p>We do frequently ruminate the Dangers we have been in, and the Deliverances and the Victories which the wonder-working God hath wrought from time to time by You. We can say of our Nations (by Your jeopardies) what <em>Abraham</em> said of the land of <em>Muriah, Jehovah jireth</em>, in the Mount of the Lord, the Lord shall be seen; nay more, he hath been already seen <reg orig="againe">again</reg> and again: All that we can do is to sit at Your feet, with due submission and humble acknowledgement, and to lie down before the Throne of Heaven in our prayers for You, that God will follow You with future <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> as hitherto he hath done, and to make You as happy in the Protection of these Nations, as he hath made <pb n="2" />You successful in quelling the Enemies thereof, that Your Government may be established, and Your (and our) Adversaries may rise no more.</p>

<p>The desire of our Soul is, that all the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> people amongst us, would compose themselves to sit under your wings with <reg orig="gladnesse">gladness</reg> of heart, that out fluxable mutations may here stop: That all the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Friends may become Your Friends, that Peace and <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg> may flourish in these our <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and in our <reg orig="Childrens">Children's</reg> <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, and that our last Glories may <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> in <reg orig="brightnesse">brightness</reg> all former Splendances whatsoever. We dare not suffer <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to doubt, but as the Interest of Jesus Christ and his People hath been and is dear unto You, so all good men shall ever receive <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> from you. And as for <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg> considerations, we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that Cities and other places shall so far partake of Your Clemency, and Bounty in their ancient <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> to them, according to their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> demerits, as will give them cause, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> not to complain, but greatly <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> in You.</p>

<p>For our <reg orig="owne">own</reg> particular, as we are loath to be uncivilly importune in an eager or unseasonable pressing of Your most Excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, for the Confirmation of the Liberties and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> of this ancient Corporation of the Liberties and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> of this ancient Corporation, so we are willing to <reg orig="possesse">possess</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> in an humble hope that Your indulgence towards us (in that respect) will not be extenuated or fall short of what hath been <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> unto us through many Generations, but rather will be graciously augmented as opportunities may give way, it being a City <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> reputed famous for the profession of the true Religion, constantly affected (through all changes in these late years of troubles) to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Interest, and sincerely <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> in the Divine Providence, ordering and casting the Government of this Commonwealth into the hand of a person so pious, prudent, and prosperous as Your most Excellent Highness is, And this is all which (for the present) Your most <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> and humble Servants thought meet to Declare and prostrate with this further addition and Protestation; That as none hath been more ready in affection to <reg orig="owne">own</reg> (as well as to Proclaim) Your most Excellent <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in Your present Government, so none shall ever take up firmer Resolution to stand <pb n="3" />fast unto You, <reg orig="then">than</reg> we (Your most obliged Servants) shall, and (by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> assistance) ever will.</p>

<p>This Declaration was presented to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by these persons following, <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> thereunto under the Hand and Seal of the City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>.</p>

<!--table in 2 columns divided by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p><em>Will. Lenthal</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; Mr. of the <reg orig="Rols">Rolls</reg>, and Recorder of the City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>.</p>
<p><em>John Dorney</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; Town Clerk.</p>
<p><em>Tho. Pury</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; the younger.</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Captain <em>Godfry Ellis</em></p>
<p>Captain <em>Philips</em>.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>John Matthews</em></p>
<p>Mr. <em>Robert Wakeman</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>At the Committee of Adventurers for Lands in Ireland the 9 day of <em>March</em>. 1653.</i></head>

<p><i>Grocers Hall</i></p>

<p>By direction of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, the Lord Protector, we desire the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Ministers or <reg orig="Church-wardens">Churchwardens</reg> of each Parish Church and <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg> within <em>London</em>, the Liberties thereof, and the late Line of Communication, to appoint some meet persons to give notice in their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Congregations upon the nest <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day being the 12. day of this instant <em>March</em>: That all Adventurers of <reg orig="Rebels">Rebel's</reg> Lands in <em>Ireland</em>, are requested to meet at <em>Grocers-hall</em> upon Monday next, being the thirteenth of this instant <em>March</em>, at two of the clock in the afternoon, to receive an Account of the proceedings of their Committee since the late <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> meeting.</p>

<p><i>Signed by Command of the Committee of Adventurers. <em>Rich. Deacon</em> Clerk attending the Committee.</i></p>

<p>There hath been, and still is so great abuse in Farthing-Tokens, those that they are made for, making about 20 s. for about 11 s. and <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> names used, besides the gain of the Maker, much more; that the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have under consideration to have new Farthing-Tokens allowed to be made by one that <reg orig="wil">will</reg> make them of <reg orig="intrinsick">intrinsic</reg> value; So that all the Farthings that now are <reg orig="wil">will</reg> then be worth no more <reg orig="then">than</reg> old mettle, and new ones <reg orig="goe">go</reg> that there will never be <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> in.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 10 March.</i></head>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> received several Petitions, and passed divers Orders, for relief of divers poor people that made Addresses to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>This day General <em>Desborow</em> and the Commissioners of the Admiralty returned home from <em>Chattam</em>, and came to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, the English Fleet being ready, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> by the <reg orig="Sea side">Seaside</reg> ready to go on board if need be.</p>

<head level="3">Paris 27 Febru. 1654.</head>

<p><i>The Marshal of <em>Hocquincourt</em> having the last Campania commanded in <em>Catalonia</em> and being arrived here a fortnight <reg orig="agoe">ago</reg> is departed in haste without so much as taking his leave of His Majesty, nor of the Cardinal, the night between the 22 and the 23 instant to go to his Government of <em>Perone</em>, which sudden departure hath given occasion to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Rumors">Rumours</reg>. It is reported that the Prince of <em>Conti</em> did the last Sunday marry with the Lady <em>Martinezzi</em> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> of the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em>, and that the next morning he hath been presented with a gift of a million of <reg orig="Livers">Livres</reg>. That he shall go into <em>Catalonia</em> and reside there as Viceroy. There is a <reg orig="likelinesse">likeliness</reg> of a marriage between the King, and the Daughter of the Duke of <em>Madena</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Turin 21 Febru.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Servient</em>, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from France to this Court, fearing that the <em>French</em> Forces which have been countermanded from <em>Pignerol</em> should disband and be totally ruinated, seeing they could neither get money nor <reg orig="Freequarters">Free quarters</reg>, whereby they might subsist this Winter, is lately gone from hence towards them to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to keep them together with fair promises, and a little money which he hath <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> with him till they can receive fuller order from the Court of <em>France</em>, the which he hath effected, and at last hath received Order, by which the Marshall of <em>Grancy</em> is commanded to go back over the Mountains with all his Horse, and to keep his Foot in the Valleys above <em><reg orig="Pigneroll">Pignerol</reg></em> which the <em>French</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> pretend to be in their Dominions, except the <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> of <em>Savoy</em> doth give her consent for putting them into some <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, which is not likely to be.</p>

<p>It is confirmed from <em>Rome</em> that the Cardinal <em>Pamphilio</em> is deprived of all his Revenues, and that two places were made ready in the Castle of <em>Engelsburg</em> to keep him prisoner, and that his Secretary and Steward are fled into <em>Naples</em>, the same <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> having kept correspondence with <em>Spain</em>. As also that the Pope is at last resolved to give Audience to the <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p><i>We hear that the Forces of the Duke of <em>Loraine</em> are agreed with the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopoldus</em>, and shall quarter about <em>Dalen</em>, and that there are more of the said <reg orig="Dukes">Duke's</reg> Officers and Gentlemen arrested, himself being strictly kept.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam 7. March.</i></head>

<p>The Eastland Fleet which hath kept all this Winter in the Sound to the number of 140 to 150 <reg orig="sales">sails</reg>, is at last (God be thanked) safely arrived in the <em>Fly</em>, the last Sunday, having only lost a ship, sunk by the way by springing a <reg orig="leake">leak</reg>, the men whereof have been saved.</p>

<head level="3">From Rhyn 10 March.</head>

<p><i>The Treaty between the <em>Count</em> of <em>Harcourt</em> and the Marshall <em>de la Ferte</em> concerning the <em><reg orig="Brislack">Brisack</reg></em> is yet <reg orig="stopt">stopped</reg>, the said Count having arrested in that Town, the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Brimmon</em> upon the <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of the Duke of Loraine being kept prisoner, the said Marshall having quartered his Forces in <em>Elsatia</em>, it seems both parties will fall into hostility, one against another, thereupon the Count of <em>Harcourt</em> hath sent an Officer to the Court of France to <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> his proceedings.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris 6 March.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Bass</em> is gone from hence the third instant for <em>England</em> with a Commission for Monsieur <em>de <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> to be Ambassador, to whom he is adjunct as Commissioner. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the King of <em>Scots</em> hath received warning that it is not found convenient he should stay longer in <em>France</em>, seeing a French Ambassador is to <reg orig="acknowldge">acknowledge</reg> the Protector of <em>England</em> and <reg orig="treate">treat</reg> with him, and that the King will provide for his Pension in some other Country.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em> hath now obtained that his Letters of <reg orig="naturalization">naturalisation</reg> should be registered in Parliament. Our Chancellor was yesterday in the said Parliament requiring them in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> name, seeing his Majesty could not come there in person, that they should proceed in the <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg> of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, whereupon the <reg orig="Atturney">Attorney</reg> <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> desired them, that <reg orig="wheras">whereas</reg> <reg orig="no body">nobody</reg> had appeared for the said Prince at <em>Perone</em>, according to his summon, they should examine the Witnesses against him, which was granted, and they shall proceed in that cause, as if the King was present <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>. The <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>de la Melleray</em> is <pb n="6" />come hither to conclude the Marriage of his Son with Mis. <em>Manciny</em> the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> shall command in <em>Catalonia</em>, the Dukes of <em>Madena</em> and <em>Candale</em> in <em>Italy</em>. The <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> of <em>Turenne</em> in <em>Picardy</em> and <em>Flanders</em>, and the Marshal <em>de la Ferte Seneterre</em> in <em><reg orig="Champaine">Champagne</reg></em>: It is said that the King shall after Easter go to be Anointed and Sacred.</p>

<head level="3">From <reg orig="Brussel">Brussels</reg> 7. March.</head>

<p><i>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is arrived here from <em>Namur</em>, and being come through the Park to this <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>, was met and received by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> with all <reg orig="monted">mounted</reg> expressions of <reg orig="chearfulnesse">cheerfulness</reg> and love; and the said Prince being afterwards gone to the Lodgings prepared for him; where he hath been attended and feasted according to his quality and degree, his Highness went and visited him there on Sunday in the afternoon, both Princes using reciprocally all manner of demonstrations of affection and good intelligence.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Mastricht">Maastricht</reg> 10 March.</i></head>

<p>The <em><reg orig="Loraigners">Lorainers</reg></em> do quarter now between <em>Thienen</em> and S, <em>Trudens</em>, having left the Country of <em><reg orig="Leige">Liege</reg></em> and <em>Hesbay</em> after they have plundered and burned many places, amongst which is the house of the Earl of <em>Swaisemburg</em>. The French under the command of the Marq; of <em>Faber</em> have also <reg orig="repassed">re-passed</reg> over the <em>Maiz</em>, having published that if any of the <em><reg orig="Loraigners">Lorainers</reg></em> would take service under him, every Horse should have 10 pistols, and every foot six crowns.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday, <em>March</em> 11.</head>

<p>Some Addresses were this day made to congratulate His Highness, from some Parts in England.</p>

<p><i>Upsal. January 20, 1653.</i> The Treaty here by his Excellency the Lord Commissioner <em>Whitlock</em>, with the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> goes on very hopefully; The Government of <em>England</em> established under the Lord Protector, hath purchased high reputation with this Court and Country. The main thing that put an Halt to the business was (at first) the unsettlement of the Affairs of <em>England, Ireland</em>, and <em>Scotland</em>, which the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, and the Lord <reg orig="Chansellor">Chancellor</reg> did several times insist upon, and proposed to my Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, to declare what visible security there was of some fixed settlement, to be established in <em>England</em>, to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> this Crown; that by the conclusion of such an Union as is desired, the Crown of <em>Sweden</em> may enjoy a constant Friend <pb n="7" /><reg orig="equivolent">equivalent</reg> to those enemies, which by all probability this desired Confederacy would raise from other Nations against her Majesty. And they did much inquire, whether General <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> in particular did own this <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> sent from <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Whilst these things were in dispute, came Letters in opportune season, which cleared these things to their great satisfaction, of the Government <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> under His Highness, OLIVER <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg>, Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The first <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of it came to her Majesty in Letters that were sent to her from <em>England</em>; because they were first delivered, who was so glad of the <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> that (without delay) she sent the Lord <em>Viscount Toet</em> (who is the chief Gentleman of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Chamber, and Captain of her Life-guard) to advertise my Lord Ambassador of the <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, which was <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg> both to them and to us.</p>

<p>And not long after, Letters came to his Excellency and to several of us, of the particulars of the business, and new Credentials from the new made Lord protector, which so soon as his Excellency received, he forthwith made his address to her Majesty; receiving present Audience, presented the to her, by whom they were received with much readiness and grace: much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at the same.</p>

<p>The Queen said, she liked the business better <reg orig="then">than</reg> before; and that the Honour and Trust <reg orig="confer'd">conferred</reg> upon His Highness, was well merited by him, and that she would send Letters to congratulate him in his new Government.</p>

<p>There were some discourses about <reg orig="punctilioes">punctilios</reg> of honour, as to subscriptions of names, and such like things, which was quickly over.</p>

<p>Then her Majesty acquainted my Lord Ambassador, that she was to go a short Journey, to visit the Queen Mother at her Court, at <em>Nucupen</em>, (which is about 14 <em><reg orig="Swedes">Swede's</reg></em> miles off, that is above 60 English miles) only to show her respects to her <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> Mother.</p>

<p>And that my Lord Ambassador should have no cause to suspect that her Journey was a pretence to delay the business, <reg orig="shee">she</reg> <reg orig="refered">referred</reg> it to the <reg orig="Chancelor">Chancellor</reg> in her absence, to confer with him about the particulars; and some secret testimonies of real affection <pb n="8" />from her Majesty were <reg orig="aserted">asserted</reg>, which is fit for the present to be concealed.</p>

<p>On the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day (early in the morning) the Queen began her Journey in a <reg orig="Sledg">Sledge</reg> drawn with four Horses, and the Horses were changed every four miles, that is near as much as 20 English miles, which is a swift and convenient way of <reg orig="traveling">travelling</reg> here whilst the Snow continues, and that Night her Majesty arrived at her <reg orig="Journies">Journey's</reg> end, and returned hither early yesterday morning.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Upsal January 20 1653.</i></head>

<p>On Tuesday the 17 instant, The Lord Chancellor in prosecution of his instructions from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> attended my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>: There have been some advantages to the English, by treating with him, and some disadvantages: The advantages are his own natural <reg orig="wel">well</reg>-wishes to the English <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, his visible <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> affections to it, and his remembrance of the late King of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> <reg orig="scornfull">scornful</reg> usage of his Son, which makes him no <reg orig="Freind">Friend</reg> at all to the <em><reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> Family; And his disaffection to the French Nation. And the disadvantages are his weakness by Age, his scrupulous nature to raise unnecessary doubts, which causeth delay even to in matters he relisheth, and his experience in State matters, which makes him wary, (and so much time is taken up in consideration) that little may be left to <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg>; but her Majesty being now returned, doth <reg orig="chearfully">cheerfully</reg> quicken him in the work.</p>

<p><i>Upsal Jan. 20.</i> The Treaty goes on here hopefully, the Queen though able to speak <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, treateth in French or high Dutch more becoming the Court, but the Lord Chancellor, useth the common learned tongue of <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg>, accounting it to be the language of a Statesman.</p>

<p>The first day of the Treaty, after the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> last Letters and new Commission, These two things the Lord Chancellor desired satisfaction in.</p>

<p>First, touching the Letters of Credence, what satisfaction would be given that the Lord Protector would <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> what should be agreed unto.</p>

<p>Secondly, by what Authority His Highness was made Lord Protector.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<p>Touching which, my Lord Ambassador gave his Lordship such full answers, that at his departure he confessed ample satisfaction to both.</p>

<p>The next day they went over all the Articles: the first debate was then about the War defensive and Offensive, because <em>England</em> is now in actual <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, and <em><reg orig="Swede-land">Sweden</reg></em> in a <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Peace. To which my Lord Ambassador answered, that the present <reg orig="actuall">actual</reg> Wars of <em>England</em> might soon be ended by Victory or Treaty: then the interest of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> having some <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> on Foot could be laid down: That then Affairs in <em>Russia, Poland, Germany</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, &amp;c. were not so firmly composed, but that a short time might necessitate them to a War somewhere. It was offered to the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, to judge, whether the reputation of so potent an Ally as <em>England</em>, (at present so strong by Sea and Land) would not more advantage them either to keep off a <reg orig="warr">war</reg> or <reg orig="inable">enable</reg> to undertake when necessary, as the alliance of <em><reg orig="Swede-land">Sweden</reg></em> could advantage <em>England</em> at present, who alone had by the blessing of God, carried so many signal victories. And after some further Conference, the Lord Chancellor, after much scanning of all particulars, concluded with much contentment, desiring excuse for his strict inquiry into particulars, which was but his duty he owed to his Trust, from her Majesty. The way of this Crown is by private Conference, not obligatory to either party to prepare for overtures in writing, but plain down right treating and <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to the business. The Lord Chancellor at his departure professed his readiness to further the Proposals.</p>

<p><i>Upsal. Jan. 2.</i> the Queen hath been with the Queen Mother and is returned, and things go on well in the Treaty, which hath been <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on by the Chancellor in her absence: The Queen hath summoned her <em>Rix diat</em> (or <reg orig="counsell">counsel</reg>) to appear here against the later end of this month, and ordered all her Magazines to be fully furnished, which signifies her intent to <reg orig="warre">war</reg> this Summer, having in readiness for expedition 29000 Horse and Foot, of standing Militia, to be ready in 3 weeks warning, besides 10000 in <em>Pomerania</em>. The Swedish Commanders must have <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, being not content to live upon their small Pay in Peace, and their <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> also must not lose their discipline; and they must either be engaged with England somewhere, or else <pb n="10" />fall upon <em>Russia</em>, which the Emperor there fearing hath sent an Envoy hither with Letters to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to prevent, that he may the more freely fall upon <em>Poland</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 12. March.</i></head>

<p><i>Leith 4 March, 1653.</i> Major General Middleton is landed at the Ferry of <em>Uney</em> in <em>Southerland</em> in a Scotch Hoy from the <em>Hague</em> about twelve <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night, and another vessel at <em>Strathe Nemer</em>, in both 150 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of powder and 500 Arms as is given out, and with him are Sir <em>George Munroe</em>, the Lord <em><reg orig="Nappier">Napier</reg></em>, Alderman Tho. <em>Dyel</em>, <em>Lodowick Drumland</em>, and above 100 more, most Officers. They sent about forty of their men to <em>Achness</em> with eight horse-load of Arms, with the rest they are gone towards <em>Strathefleet</em>, towards <em>Assigne</em>; but part of this: they intend a <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg> with <em><reg orig="Glengarn">Glencairn</reg></em> in <em>Murray</em>, and to <reg orig="presse">press</reg> all the Countries to rise.</p>

<p>The Treaty goes on hopefully. The Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Major Gen. <em>Lambert</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Mr. <em>Lawrence</em>, Col. <em>Montague</em>, and Mr. <em>Strickland</em> are the Commissioners for the Lord Protector, that treat with the Lords Ambassadors from the States General of the United Provinces of <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em></p>

<p>This day the Lords Ambassadors of <em>Holland &amp;c.</em> were removing from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> to Sir John <em><reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> in <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> <reg orig="Roe">Row</reg> near the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>-Yard at <em>Westminster</em>, which they have taken to reside in; and this day before they went away, the Lord Ambassador of <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> gave them a visit, with both his rich Coaches and Attendants.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Hague 13 March.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Van Dalen</em> formerly Steward of the States Ambassadors at <em>Munster</em>, and now of those in <em>England</em> is going from hence thither, with their Excellencies Coaches, and silver Plates and other Necessaries. The same is since arrived here.</p>

<p>Two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago is come in by Catwick an English Ketch wherein <reg orig="no body">nobody</reg> was found, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some footsteps were <unclear>seen</unclear> <unclear>upon<!--this is totally blank but makes sense--></unclear> the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, and some men are come in the night to the <unclear><!--blank for approx. 10 characters--></unclear> who are not known what they are. <unclear>It is supposed</unclear> <unclear><!--blank for approx. 15 characters--></unclear> some that upon the discovery of the Plot <unclear>against the Lord Protector<!--guess from few characters visible and word continued on the next line--></unclear> are fled away from <unclear><em>England</em></unclear>.</p>

<pb n="11" />

<head level="3"><i>A Narrative of the sad accident that befell the Troops at the <em>Lanker</em>, in <em>Scotland</em>, published to prevent the mis-reports that perhaps some <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> spirits will be ready to make of it.</i></head>

<p>On the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day <em>Febru.</em> 19. 1653. Capt. <em>Mason</em> being at <em><reg orig="Dunfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, had intelligence that the enemy was at a place called the <em>Lanker</em>, about 16 miles from <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, upon which he forthwith marched with 80 of his Troop, whose approach the Enemy discovering left the Town, betaking them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>; Capt. <em>Mason</em> in pursuit took a Cornet and two more, the rest, (their horses being fresh, and his almost weary with the march escaped) Capt. <em>Mason</em> quartered in the Town that night, and about four in the morning Capt. <em>Palmer</em> came there with his party, having also had intelligence of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> being there, and knowing nothing what was done, took Cap. <reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg> Troop to be the Enemy, and a Scotchman one of the <reg orig="Dragoons">Dragoon's</reg> Scouts, being violently charged by <reg orig="Capt,">Capt.</reg> <em><reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg></em> men, who he thought to be the Enemy, declared the spirit of a Scotchman by saying that he was for the King, to save his life, by which means he lost it.</p>

<p>The whole party then <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to enter the Town, but the Guard repulsed them, upon which Capt. <em>Palmer</em> drew out a party of 20 to fire the <reg orig="Guard-house">Guardhouse</reg>, by which time Capt. <em>Mason</em> had got 30 or 40 of his horse together, and with them <reg orig="beate">beat</reg> out Capt. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> party, which they took to be the Enemy, they pursued in the evening, but at the <reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg>-end Cap. <em>Palmer</em> met them with the whole party, and fell upon them, both sides still judging each other to be the Enemy, in which unhappy Engagement six were slain of both parties and eight wounded, of which number Captain <em>Palmer</em> is one hurt.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 13 March.</i></head>

<p>This day Major <em>Bourn</em>, and divers others were robbed at <em>Shooters-hill</em>, and bound in a wood, some in a Coach fought, but the <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> slew one of the Gentlemen. Another Gentleman of them came to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg> at Mr. <em><reg orig="Mollins">Mollin's</reg></em> in <reg orig="Shoo">Shoe</reg>-lane, where one of the <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> came to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, but hearing he was dressing one hurt at <em>Shooters-hill</em>, run away without his <reg orig="Cloake">Cloak</reg>, which he had put off in expectation to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<head level="3">A Letter from the King of <em>France</em> to the Elector of <em><reg orig="Cullen">Cologne</reg></em>.</head>

<p><i>My Cousin,</i></p>

<p>As soon as I had intelligence of the hostile usage of your Countries by some Neighbours of mine, I did present my present <reg orig="helpe">help</reg> to free your Subjects from that Pressure which they felt: Had not the particular respect that I bear to your Neighbourship forced me to this, yet my sincerity of assisting you in order to the Treaties of peace at <em>Munster</em> makes me not to neglect it, by reason that the Princes and States of the whole Empire ought to have the security of that Peace granted by the former Treaty.</p>

<p>Therefore I have sent you a <reg orig="releise">release</reg> out of my Army commanded by the <reg orig="Marquesse">Marquis</reg> of <em>Faber</em> to assist you against the hostile proceedings of the Troops of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Loraigne">Loraine</reg></em> and the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, in the Land of <em><reg orig="Leige">Liege</reg></em>. And I have Ordered him to <reg orig="keepe">keep</reg> his Army in good Discipline, having no other end, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the perfecting of the Treaty of Peace, and by my force to free the Princes of the Empire from all violence, So <reg orig="Cousen">Cousin</reg>, I commend you to the Protection of the Almighty.</p>

<p><i>Paris 18. Janu. 1653. <em><reg orig="LOUYS">LOUIS</reg></em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the Marquis of <em>Faber</em> to the <reg orig="Ellector">Elector</reg> of <em><reg orig="Cullen">Cologne</reg></em>.</i></head>

<p><i>My Lord,</i></p>

<p>By the Copy of the Letter which my Master sent to the Emperor, your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> will see what command I have received from his Majesty to march into the land of <em><reg orig="Leidge">Liege</reg></em>, which is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to free them from the violence that is offered to them by the Troops of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and the Duke of <em><reg orig="Loraign">Lorain</reg></em> to the prejudice of the Treaty at <em>Munster</em>. So that there is no doubt to be made but that the intent of his Majesty is to secure the conditions of that Treaty, and to free the Subjects of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> from those unjust oppressions which they have suffered. So that his Majesty sends these forces as <reg orig="releise">release</reg> for their conservation, to <reg orig="keepe">keep</reg> them from utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>

<p>And in case there be such opposition. I am to use means to <pb n="13" />open the way by force, to make the Enemy leave the Country. My Master hath no other intention but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to <reg orig="expell">expel</reg> them, and then for the Forces to return.</p>

<p>This is all that I can assure your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> from my Master and that I am <i>Your Highness most obedient, most humble Servant. FABERT. <reg orig="Sidan">Sedan</reg> 11 Febru. 1653.</i></p>

<p>The King of <em>France's</em> Letter is to advertise him of his <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg> to assist the Princes of the Empire in the <reg orig="injoyment">enjoyment</reg> of the conditions of the peace at <em>Munster</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><em>Leopoldus Guillelmus</em> by the Grace of God, <reg orig="Arch-bishop">Archbishop</reg> of <em>Austrick</em> Duke of <em>Burgundy</em>, and Stateholder, Governor, and Captain-General of our Low-Countries, and of <em>Burgundy</em>, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>To all High Officers, Commanders, Masters of the Camps, Colonels and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, bearing Arms under the Colours of the Lord Duke, <em>Charles</em> of <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorain</reg></em>, Salute. Be it known, that having this day taken into safe Custody, for some time, the Person of the foresaid Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorain</reg></em>, according to the Order and Command received for that effect, from our Lord the King, for the own welfare of the House of <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorain</reg></em>, and other high considerations, relating to the welfare of the State, and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace. His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> intent and ours is, that the body of his Army should remain under the command of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Lignevile">Ligneville</reg></em>, in the same Service as it now is, till the Lord Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em>, shall <reg orig="repaire">repair</reg> here as it is like he will within few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, to be invested of the command of the said Army, for the preservation of the Rights of the said Lord Duke, and of the House of <em><reg orig="Lorrain">Lorain</reg></em> under the protection of his Majesty, declaring that none of that Army, nor any Officers of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the same shall be liable to any questioning under what Pretence soever, for the excesses that they may have committed under the Government of the aforesaid Lord Duke, as also we do by this Present, forbid them to take service, under any Potentate, or neighbour State, whether <reg orig="Freinds">Friends</reg> or Foes, under penalty of Corporal Punishment and loss of Estates, of the Vassals, and natural Subjects of his Majesty, and of those that have formerly <reg orig="enroled">enrolled</reg> and lifted themselves, and for all other Strangers upon pain of being punished as <reg orig="Runnawaies">Runaways</reg>; with provision nevertheless that those that have <pb n="14" />formerly been lifted, and taken in the Service of his Majesty, and are gone away from their Colours without leave; shall have liberty to <reg orig="returne">return</reg> to the same, without fear of being questioned for it; referring <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> moreover to what the Earl of <em><reg orig="Fuensaldaigne">Fuensaldagne</reg></em> Governor General of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg>, shall further express or <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> to them, concerning the advantages they shall receive in so doing. Given at <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em>, the 25 of <em>February</em>. 1654,</p>

<p>From the Sea came Letters of good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> of our ships in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts, Capt. <em>Heaton</em> of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> hath sent in nine ships to <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>, belonging as is supposed to <reg orig="Britanny">Brittany</reg> in France, but pretend to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> Hamburgers, they came from <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>.</p>

<p>Nine small ships taken upon the Coasts of Scotland, by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> English men of war, some with Wines, some with Salt, and the rest with ordinary <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, they came from <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>.</p>

<p>Two Merchants ships that were coming from Ipswich toward London, were taken by a Dutchman of War, they <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the English of both under the Deck of one of them, on Saturday the fourth of March; and then left them, sending them homewards; but the next day the English at a seasonable time lifted up the decks, relieved themselves, took the Dutch and <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> them under the deck where they were, and brought away both their ships to the Downs, which are now safe in the River, our men all well and theirs prisoners.</p>

<p>Three ships taken by the None-such, and other <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> in the Narrow, between Dover and <reg orig="Callice">Calais</reg>, two of 16 Guns <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>, and ballast, and the other laden with Beans.</p>

<p>Divers Dutch men of war, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> our Coast, have put ten or 12 great and small ships ashore between Flamborough and Scarborough, Capt. <em>Wilkins</em> hath taken one Caper with five Guns and 53 men, and brought her to Newcastle, and was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> taking another. Three ships retaken from Cap. <em>Beech</em> the great Pirate, by the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 15 March.</i></head>

<p><i>Dalkeith 9 March.</i> Since <reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg> landing, the Enemy go on to their <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which will be about <em><reg orig="Straithspey">Strathspey</reg></em> the 10 or 11 instant; they give out (to encourage the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>) that <em>Middleton</em> hath 3500 foot, and 500 horse, but the people know <unclear>the</unclear> contrary. There was besides Cap. <em>Johnson</em> (who was killed before <em>Blair</em> Castle) one Cap. <em>Scot</em> shot in the back, not likely to recover, and Lieut. <unclear><em><reg orig="Erwines">Erwine's</reg></em></unclear> horse killed under him. The enemy do rather diminish, <reg orig="then">than</reg> increase; very many through dislike, either of their Quarters or Service, do run from them. An order is issued forth, if any go down to the Lowlands, without a party, they are to be brought back, and suffer for it. The Lowlands men would fain be at home, the Highlanders are so barbarous towards them, <unclear>that if</unclear> they catch Lowland men apart from the <unclear>post</unclear>, they presently <unclear><!--approx. 25 characters--></unclear> <em>Athol</em> and <em>Forbs</em> are yet in <unclear><em>Glealyon</em></unclear>, but they are forced to remove every night. A party of horse from St. <em>Johnstons</em>, on Tuesday last, took a Sergeant, and another of his men. The main body of their forces, is yet in <unclear><em>Badgenoth</em></unclear>; <em>Middleton</em> is gone towards the Lord <em><reg orig="Reays">Reay's</reg></em> Bounds. The unhappy disaster of the two Troops, you have the particulars of before.</p>

<p>This day the Commissioners from the Lord Protector, went from His Highness in two Coaches with the Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council, and their attendants to the Dutch Ambassadors, at Sir Abraham <em><reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em>; from whence they are not removed to Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em>: They were met at the Gate by the Lord Ambassadors, where the Lord <em>Beverling</em> made a Speech to them, and they received them with great respect and love on both sides. Being come into the House and into a Chamber appointed for their Conference; they spent much time in order to the finishing of the Peace. The business this day, was, To confer their Papers of the Agreement; for though they have agreed, yet it is <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> by each side, and this day they compared their Papers; which when both compared together, do in all particulars agree; then they are to sign on both side. And what they sign, the Dutch Ambassadors do in the name of the States General. But to confirm it the more, it is to be sent to the States General, who are also to give their assent after the Ratification, and then they deliver the Articles on both sides; which it is hoped will be done in about three weeks time.</p>

<p>The two Ordinances touching Ministers, and touching the Law, is before a Committee, whereof Justice <em>Hayle</em> is in the <reg orig="Chiar">Chair</reg>. What the particulars will be, is not certain until they be finished.</p>

<p>It is uncertain also what will be done about Farthing Tokens.</p>

<p>Letters are come from Capt. <em>Potter</em>, Commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, that he hath with the loss of three men, after seven hours fight, taken Cap. <em>Beach</em>, <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <em><reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> chief Pirate at <em>Brest</em>, with 200 prisoners more, whereof 8 Captains, 38 Guns, and 4 more dismounted, and killed 20 of his men more off <em>Ushant</em>. Some others are to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> for their lives; they are sent to <em>Plymouth</em>. The Merchants are exceeding joyful of this news.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>The perfect Pharisee, under Monkish <reg orig="Holinesse">Holiness</reg>, opposing the Fundamental Principles of the Gospel, and Scripture Practices, in a Generation of men called Quakers, or a Preservative against their <reg orig="grosse">gross</reg> Blasphemies and horrid Delusions published by the Ministers of Newcastle.</p>

<p>The false Jew, Being a true <unclear>Relation</unclear> of one Thomas Ramsey who came from Rome and was <reg orig="baptized">baptised</reg> at London and afterward <reg orig="Rebaptized">Re-baptised</reg> at Hexham by Mr. Tillam, but found out at Newcastle to be a cheat. Both sold by Rich. <reg orig="Tomlins">Tomlin's</reg> at the Sun and Bible at <reg orig="Pye">Pie</reg> Corner.</p>

<p>A Plea for Anti-p&aelig;dobaptists, against the vanity and falsehood of <reg orig="Scribled">Scribbled</reg> Papers, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, The Anabaptists <reg orig="Anotomized">Anatomised</reg> and silenced in a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Dispute at Abergaveny in Monmouthshire Sept. 5. 1653, betwixt John Tombes, John Cragg, and Hen. Vaughan, touching Infant-<reg orig="Baptisme">Baptism</reg>. by Jo. Tombes, B.D. Sold by Hen. <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, at Sir John Old-<reg orig="Castles">Castle's</reg> in <reg orig="Pye">Pie</reg>-corner.</p>

<p>An Exposition on the whole Book of Canticles, wherein the Text is explained, and <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> Observations raised thereupon; Sold by G. &amp; H. Eversden at the <reg orig="Grey-hound">Greyhound</reg> in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p>A week since a grey Mastiff-Dog was lost about <reg orig="Chairing-Crosse">Charing Cross</reg>, his <reg orig="Eares">Ears</reg> whole, his <reg orig="Taile">Tail</reg> cut, a little white on all four feet, lately bit upon the Nose, He that shall bring him to Mr. <reg orig="Clergis">Clergis'</reg> <reg orig="Apothecaries">Apothecary's</reg> house near <reg orig="Chairing-Crosse">Charing Cross</reg>, shall have 20 s. and for certain notice where he is 5 s.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>