<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState224">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 224</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 5 of <em>January</em> To Thursday the 12 day of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 5, January. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Ministers and six of the Elders of the <em>French</em> Church, and a Marquis of <em>France</em> were with His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, to congratulate, declaring their <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of engagement, to <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God for Him, and their hope of protection to themselves, and the rest of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people from Him. And they received a very satisfying Answer; So that there is like to be that <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Protestant Churches of foreign parts, which yet hath not been: which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a great blow to Antichrist, and a great <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> to exalt the Throne of the Lord Jesus, when the multitudes of those that believe shall be of one heart, and of one mind; <pb n="1" />for the Spirit of the Lord worketh by love.</p>

<head level="3">By Letters from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts came as followeth, viz.</head>
<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <em>Myng</em>.</i></head>

<p><i>Honourable,</i></p>

<p>In pursuance of your Orders for the attendance of my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> the 15. <em>November</em>, we arrived at <em><reg orig="Gottenburg">Gothenburg</reg></em>. Some <reg orig="foule">foul</reg> weather parted company the day before, but through mercy, all well arrived, my Lord and his Retinue all well. The 23. My Lord set forward from <em><reg orig="Gottenburg">Gothenburg</reg></em> to the Court, Contrary winds detained us <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 22. of <em>Decemb</em>. We attempted once or twice to <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, but were forced in again: Our <reg orig="ships">ship's</reg> company hath been sickly, above 90 men sick at a time, five died, at present generally in a recovering condition, my Lord sent his Packet by the Phenix, who got out of Port a day before us, the wind taking us short as <reg orig="wee">we</reg> were going out the <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> under the lear; We met with three <reg orig="Hollands">Holland's</reg> men of war, and some 8 or 9 Merchant men with them, we fired ten guns upon them, but our sickly condition, our enemies odds, and a Lee <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, were the reasons upon which we left them. A day or two after come up the Phenix, who had been in a fight with a Holland man of war, he had four men killed, 11 wounded and lost his <reg orig="Boltsprit">Bowsprit</reg>, the further particulars your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> may expect from them, whom some two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since we left at an Anchor thwart of these Sands, we keeping under <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> fetched in with <em>Winterton</em>, where anchored until the <reg orig="stresse">stress</reg> of a <reg orig="Southernly">Southerly</reg> <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> was over, which I conceive force him from his anchor to Sea again. I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> use all advantages in out way to <em>Portsmouth</em>.</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> humble Servant, Ch: Myng. Yarmouth Road 2. Jan. 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Captain <em>Wilks</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>Right Honourable,</i></head>

<p>According to Order I have gotten the ship Discovery out of <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> to the Spitehead, where the <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> and Fleet ride, only the Squadron which are at Sea.</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> most humble Servant, Tho: Wilks. Discovery Spitehead 30 Decemb. 1653.</i></p>

<p><i>Weymouth 2 Jan. 1653.</i> A <em>Jersey</em> Vessel went <em>Saturday</em> last out <pb n="2" />this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> homewards, but the same night a very great storm rose at Sea, and brought the ship back <reg orig="againe">again</reg> upon our Coast, where she was cast away in the <em>West-bay</em> between <em>Portland</em> and <em>Rosberry</em> all the men being cast away but the shipman, and two Passengers that were <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> going over to <em>Jersey</em> or <em>Guernsey</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven <em>January</em> 2. There are <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Vessels here bound for <em>Ireland</em>, but <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> hereby reason of the contrary winds; we have not of late heard any <reg orig="newes">news</reg> from thence: The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> are still plying about the Isle of <em><reg orig="Lundly">Lundy</reg></em>, and often come into the Severn mouth, where sometimes they catch some of our <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels.</p>

<p>There is nothing more from our Fleet, but that part of them are about <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> and other places to the westward, some lie out towards the coast of <em><reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg></em>, to try if they can meet the <em>Brest</em> men of war, who have now got good ships, and have a considerable strength at Sea.</p>

<p>This week is arrived the Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em> consisting of about 40 sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich Goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg>, &amp;c. There is come likewise five ships from the East-land, as also one from <em>Zant</em>, with Currant but as yet not come up the River.</p>

<p>The Dutch Deputies being gone to <em>Gravesend</em> in order to take shipping for <em>Holland</em>, made some further application to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and His Council by a Letter, which whether or no it will occasion an absolute agreement, a short time will discover.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 6 January.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>A true Narrative of the cause and manner of the dissolution of the late Parliament</i>, Decemb. 12. 1653.</head>

<p>The Speaker taking the Chair, a Member made his <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> to him to this effect; That he must <reg orig="disburthen">disburden</reg> himself of some things that had a long time lain upon his heart; That he was now to speak to the (<em>Esse</em> or) being, rather than the (<em>bene esse</em> or) <reg orig="wel-being">wellbeing</reg> of the Commonwealth; which was ready to sink under us, through the ill management of the Power betrusted with them, and that for his own part he must resign his Power from whence he had it, foreseeing clearly that their waitings and expectations of ever coming on to things of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> <pb n="3" />good, were more and more disappointed; And so came to these particular <unclear>instances:</unclear></p>

<p>1 That some of the said Parliament had dealt disingenuously with the Army, in moving that the Officers should be treated with to lay down their pay; and when they could not effect that, the Bill of <reg orig="Assessements">Assessments</reg> was endeavoured to be cast out.</p>

<p>2 That they had not a spirit to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> Justice, which appeared in the Act for confirming the sale of Sir <em>John <reg orig="Stowels">Stowel's</reg></em> estate, though he were <reg orig="releived">relieved</reg> by the Court of Articles. And that he knew no but that man was left to be as a <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> upon them, whether they could do Justice or not.</p>

<p>3 That they had a principle of destroying and pulling down amongst them, though nothing were set up in the stead, and this was especially manifested in the Votes for removing the Chancery, and total alteration of the Laws.</p>

<p>4 That though they called themselves a Parliament, yet they acted most unlike unto it: and that appeared in their <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to destroy Propriety, in attempting to take off the power of Patrons to present to Church-Livings.</p>

<p>5 That they would destroy the Ministry <reg orig="it selfe">itself</reg>, which appeared by the Vote upon Saturday before. For these and other considerations they could not <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> Themselves to sit any longer, and so be guilty of bringing confusion and desolation upon the Nation. But if any would yet be so hardy as to continue there, he would say unto them in the words of the Prophet, <i>Ephraim hath <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> to Idols, let him alone.</i></p>

<p>This was seconded by two more, and then some objected; but others pressing the former Motion, the Speaker left the Chair, and went out of the House with them all, save only some thirty that <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> within, and would have continued, But the Speaker with the major part of the Parliament, delivered a surrender of their Power to the General. Whereupon His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> after several <reg orig="daies">days</reg> seeking God, was by those Members of Parliament, the Judges of the Land, the Officers of the Army, and the <reg orig="cheifest">chiefest</reg> persons of Authority in the Nation, desired to take the Government upon him, as the best means to preserve these Nations from ruin.</p>

<p>There have been several Congratulations to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <pb n="4" />the Lord Protector, made by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Churches and others. The copy of one from a gathered Church in <em>London</em> follows.</p>

<p>That considering what the Lord set upon our hearts long since and was by us at the dissolving of the former Parliament presented to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>; And in that the day before the breaking up of the last Parliament, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> spent some time in waiting upon the Lord to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> our troubled spirits about the proceedings of the House the day before; Our God hath given us the desires of our hearts.</p>

<p><reg orig="Wee">We</reg> do with comfort and <reg orig="chearfulnesse">cheerfulness</reg> acknowledge it to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> our duty to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> faithfully subject unto your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and your Honourable Council, as powers ordained by God; being likewise of this <reg orig="perswasion">persuasion</reg> (according to the word) that whosoever resisteth the powers, resisteth the Ordinance of God; and they that resist, shall receive to themselves damnation: And that those who desire to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> guided by a right regulated conscience, must needs <reg orig="bee">be</reg> subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake, <em>Rom.</em> 13.</p>

<p>And <reg orig="wee">we</reg> cannot but according to the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of our duty and your <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, importune the Throne of grace, that the most High would guide and <reg orig="councell">counsel</reg> you in your great affairs, <reg orig="Councills">Councils</reg>, Debates, and prosecution of the same: That you may do nothing from the motion of the spirit of man, contrary to his will, or <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> to his glory, <reg orig="councell">counsel</reg> and word: But in all things by the guidance of his holy spirit of truth, <reg orig="sutable">suitable</reg> and agreeable to the same.</p>

<p>For the work of God and Christ in the world is of great concernment, in setting forward and <reg orig="incouraging">encouraging</reg> his own <reg orig="spirituall">spiritual</reg> <reg orig="kingdome">kingdom</reg>, and subjects thereof; as by the word and Gospel and Spirit accompanying of it; so by raising Magistrates to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> as nursing Fathers, to encourage, countenance, and protect his Church and people, and all Converts, in the Doctrine and ways of Truth, and <reg orig="holinesse">holiness</reg>, worship, practice of <reg orig="godlinesse">godliness</reg>, and liberties of the same: Even of all such as keep the <reg orig="Commandements">Commandments</reg> of God, and have and hold to the Testimonies of Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>In deep <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of so great a mercy, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> do unanimously <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God for you, and walking comfortably together in Gospel order with our <reg orig="Pastour">Pastor</reg>, desiring the union of all those that fear God (though under various <reg orig="formes">forms</reg>) do not doubt by that <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <pb n="5" />shall enjoy protection from your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and your Honourable <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Signed in the name, and by order of the Church.</i></p>

<p>By Letters from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts beyond the Seas came as followeth, viz.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Rome</em> 1 Decemb. 1653.</head>

<p><i>By the means of Cardinal <em>Pamphilio</em>, the Office of Vice <reg orig="legat">legate</reg> hath been confirmed upon the <reg orig="Arch-bishop">Archbishop</reg> of <em>Avignon</em>, who hath appeased the differences there, between the Nobility and Gentry, by the People, the said <reg orig="Arch-bishops">Archbishop's</reg> cunning wit, having been most eminent by his Negotiation, having approved himself very trusty is those difficulties, wherein all his chief care hath been to appease these troubles, and to keep a hand over the Nobility and Gentry. By the death of the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em><reg orig="Machiavelly">Machiavelli</reg></em>, Cousin <reg orig="german">German</reg> to Cardinal <em>Barbarin</em>, dead the 20 of the last month, at <em>Ferrara</em> of a burning <reg orig="feavor">fever</reg>. There are now again eight <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> places vacant, as also the <reg orig="Bishoprick">Bishopric</reg> of <em>Ferrara</em>, of 18000 crowns <reg orig="yeerly">yearly</reg> revenue, besides some other ordinary livings. The Cardinal <em>Pimentelly</em> is since two days by the stop of his water, <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> into a great danger of his life. From <em>Civita-Vechia</em> we hear, that six ships of <em>Nova Francia</em> are arrived thither, laden with several quantities of salt fish.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> 16 Ditto.</i></head>

<p>In <em>Provence</em> are the 28 instant, the States of that Province to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> called to sit at <em>Aix</em>; for which; great preparations are making at <em>Reale</em> (where the Parliament of the said Province is now sitting) who hath received the last week, Letters <reg orig="provisionall">provisional</reg>, signed by the King, intimating that Marshal <em>Turenne</em> hath been promoted to the Government of the Province of <em>Limosin</em>, for his great services done to the Crown, in these late troubles.</p>

<head level="3">From St. <em>Minebolt</em> 20 <em>Decemb.</em></head>

<p>Our Governor during the repairing of our <reg orig="Wals">Walls</reg> and outward-works hath made a strict inquiry of those that had brought corn of our Enemies. The Spaniards have possessed themselves of the Castle of Vienne, a mile and <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> from the River <em>Aisne</em>, which they had forsaken during the siege of this place. Four <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago 5 Carts of Ammunition of War have been sent to meet the Earl of <em>Uxels</em> who is said to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> with 2000 Irish that have not been yet <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> in any Army, to the <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg> of <em>Breffort</em>. The Marshall <pb n="6" /><em>la Ferte</em> drawn by <em>Lorain</em> into <em>Eltacia</em> to give work to the Earl of <em>Harcourt</em>, who is at <em>Brissac</em>. The besieging of <em>Clermont</em> and <em>Stenay</em> is no more heard of, being like to seek for nothing but for <reg orig="quietnesse">quietness</reg> this winter.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> 25 <em>Decemb.</em></head>

<p>Last week hath been brought to the Emperor, and to the assembled Electors a Paper of weighty matters from the Elector of Brandenburg, desiring they should <reg orig="deale">deal</reg> graciously with the Protestants, and not <reg orig="goe">go</reg> beyond the <em>Instrumentum Pacis</em>, or Agreement made at <em>Munster</em>: But many doubt much of the effect of that good intent, because the said Electors have already answered, that they resolve to persist in their former resolutions, and to alter nothing of their mind.</p>

<head level="3">From <reg orig="Hamborrough">Hamburg</reg> 31. Decemb.</head>

<p>Yesterday there was a fire kindled in the new Town by <reg orig="carelesnesse">carelessness</reg>, but was quickly quenched by the care and present help of our men, insomuch that houses were <reg orig="onely">only</reg> burned. We have advice from <em>Pomerania</em>, That by the Town of Pirit over against Holdin there hath been a sight in the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg>, of a Coffin with a black <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg>, and there hath appeared also a Dutch Lord <reg orig="overcomed">overcome</reg> by another Nation: after which was seen a <reg orig="faire">fair</reg> <reg orig="Rainebow">Rainbow</reg>, and afterward the last Doom day, at which sight many have been astonished and affrighted. The <reg orig="Hollanders">Hollanders'</reg> Merchant ships are still in the Sound, because of the hard frost in these parts, which makes us think they shall not yet soon set <reg orig="sailes">sails</reg> for their Country. His Majesty of <em>Denmark</em> is come back to <reg orig="Coppenhague">Copenhagen</reg>,</p>

<head level="3">From <unclear><em>Luyck</em></unclear> or <em><reg orig="Leidge">Leige</reg></em> 2. Jan. new <reg orig="stile">style</reg>.</head>

<p>When we did imagine <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to have won all, and to be at this time wholly ridden of the Lorainers, they are under pretence of going into <em>Elsacia</em>, come back unaware, and fallen into this Dominion, having first <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and the Duke of <em>Witternburg's</em> forces in these parts, and between the Rivers of Maes and Sambre, and afterward have fallen upon us all along the land of <em>Mastick</em>, committing greater tyranny and excesses upon the Boats, or <reg orig="Country-men">Countrymen</reg> and Inhabitants then can be written by a pen, behaving themselves as if they had resolved to destroy all, to make an end of all. They are no before <pb n="7" />St. <em>Truden</em>, where they have found the greater <reg orig="resistancy">resistance</reg>, though that place must <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, ere it <reg orig="bee">be</reg> long. They boast they will make themselves Masters of all the <reg orig="strong holds">strongholds</reg>, that they may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> the better able to resist all those that shall undertake to rise against them.</p>

<head level="3">From Antwerp 24 December S.V.</head>

<p><i><reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have news from St. <em>Sebastian</em> of the 29 of <em>November</em> last, that as soon as his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> fleet was arrived there from the River of <em>Garome</em>, the Marquis of St. <em>Crux</em> was with his Vice-admiral made prisoners, by the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Command, because they had not followed his Orders for the <reg orig="releif">relief</reg> of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, and that when they should have <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> upon the <em>French</em>, they declined the fight and went out of the said River. Our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> <em>Don Baltazer Marcader</em> is lately gone to <em>Dunkirk</em>, to sail from thence into <em>Spain</em>, to acquaint his Majesty with the condition of our affairs in these parts.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Amsterdam 27 Ditto.</i></head>

<p>There hath been brought into <em>Zealand</em> by the Freebooter <em>Jochem Jochems</em>, two English prizes, being pinnaces, which are thought to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> rich prizes. They have been taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Jarmouths">Yarmouth's</reg></em>Road. Some passengers come from <em>London</em> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> report that our Deputies in <em>England</em> have broken off the Treaty without <reg orig="successe">success</reg> and that having hired a Ketch to come over, they have been accommodated by the English, who have fitted them with a better ship. The East Indy ships are come from the <em>Balgh</em>, to the Road of <em>Muscovia</em>, to an anchor, and shall <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to Sea with the first good wind. There is also a Freebooter gone from thence to Sea and there are in that same Road a great number of Merchant ships ready to <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> with the foresaid East India ships.</p>

<p>Some other Letters this day mentioned a great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> by a storm in <em>Holland</em>, but of that more by and by,</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 7 January.</i></head>

<p>This day was a Court Marshall held by the Officers of the Army, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Offences punished in the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<p>The Dutch Deputies this day set <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> from the Hope to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>Holland</em>, what the Answer will be returned by our <reg orig="Friggot">Frigate</reg>, time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<p>By Letters from Capt. <unclear><em>Foster</em></unclear> Commander of the Phenix <reg orig="Friggot">Frigate</reg> <pb n="8" />dated in <em>Ously</em> Bay the 3. of January 1653, was this day advertised, that he had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> with the safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the other ships and vessels appointed to attend his Lordship, <em>December</em> 15. last at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, where he was <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg> received by the Governor, and Magistrates of that City. And his Lordship went his voyage towards <em>Stockholm</em> with rainy blustering weather.</p>

<p>The 20. <em>Decemb</em>. He came out with his ship when the wind blew hard, with much snow, endeavouring the <reg orig="Yutish">Jutish</reg> coast, anchored in ten fathom water, and discovered a fleet of ships, and 21 <em>December</em> in the morning got the weather <reg orig="gage">gauge</reg> of them, endeavoured to discover what men of war were amongst them and saw only one ship of countenance, and a private man of war of 8 guns. The fleet being Hollanders ran from the Sound; and 72 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, some with 6. some 4. others 2. guns, upon our guns firing amongst them, cut their cables and run towards the Sound; but before they got clear we boarded and manned three of them, which prizes were kept to the windward of us, about 8 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> engaged them.</p>

<p>After the passing of two <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, the private man of war ran after their fleet, we continued the dispute until four <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night, (at which time we <reg orig="past">passed</reg> <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg> close board and board as fast as we could tack our ships.) The enemy then ran towards his fleet, we pursued him, and after several broadsides intended to board him; and though our <reg orig="Boultsprit">Bowsprit</reg> shot by the board, our Main and Fore-mast shot through, scarce a Shroud whole, our Hull much shot, 4 of our men slain, and 11 wounded; he firing as he retreated, yet we made him in such a sinking condition, that whilst he fired his guns, he called to his fleet to save his men, about four leagues off at anchor under an Island.</p>

<p>About 400 horse and foot were looking on us from the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, we received shot from the enemy of 36 l. weight. But night hindered our pursuit.</p>

<p>About three in the afternoon next day three Holland men of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, (two of them very great Ships) being come from Holland to convoy their <reg orig="Fleete">Fleet</reg>, came right before the wind upon us, we then <unclear>bore</unclear> to our prizes, took all our men out of them, and would have fired them had we had time. The enemy <pb n="9" />came up close and fired at us, and we at them (unanimously resolving to sink or burn, rather than to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> or call for quarter) the two first shot they made (that raked us) the one shot the chain of our Fore-yard in <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, and the other, two thirds of our main Top mast head above the bearing; they then would have boarded us, but we got without shot of them, who seeing we <reg orig="outstript">outstripped</reg> them, after an hours time bore to the prizes, who were by this time <reg orig="neare">near</reg> the <reg orig="shoare">shore</reg>, our men having cut away all their Anchors, leaving them in the <reg orig="bottome">bottom</reg> of this Bay.</p>

<p>The 22 a Holland man of war stood <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> our forefoot close to the windward of us, standing over to the coast of <em>Norway</em>, and the wind being fair for <em>England</em> we bore away to Sea.</p>

<p>The 25 we came up with our own ships from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, having seen them two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> before, but knew them not to be our ships, stood not with them till our ship was refitted the best we could, and then they sent to us. But on the 27. about eight in the night by reason of a violent <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> <reg orig="wee">we</reg> lost sight of them.</p>

<p>The <em><reg orig="Sweeds">Swedes</reg></em> of <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburgh</reg></em> report that the King of <em>Denmark</em> is much troubled that they affronted our Nation by their ships being <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg>, and blames <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> counsel for it. <em>De Witte</em> (when last in the Sound) <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> to comfort him with a cordial of their great victories obtained against us at Sea, giving him a List of 22 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of our ships <reg orig="sunck">sunk</reg> and 8 taken, boasting much of their putting us still to flight. But that <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> own Subjects are now able to <reg orig="informe">inform</reg> him that the <em>Hollanders</em>, and not we, are still the flying party, and that one day, one small <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, fought with and routed their fleet, and men of war, and the next day made her way (the Lord helping us) through three of their ships coming to avenge their quarrel, the least of which (as to countenance) exceeded the Phenix.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is said to arrive at <em>Upsall</em>, four <reg orig="Sweads">Swede's</reg> miles from <em>Stockholm</em> the 24 <em>Decemb.</em> Where he is to have his audience.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 8 January.</i></head>

<p>This day the Council considered of the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> touching His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg>, and made some <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> therein.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Captain <em>Cobham.</em></i></head>

<head level="3"><i>Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg>,</i></head>

<p>My humble service presented unto your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg>, according to my Order received from <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> for <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, the <em>Assurance</em> and <em><reg orig="Mearmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> and <reg orig="cruse">cruise</reg> between the Dogger bank, and the <unclear>Rosse</unclear>, to intercept such Merchant men as was expected from the Sound belonging to the Dutch, we proceeded, and ranging along our <reg orig="owne">own</reg> coast off <em>Flambrough</em> head, we <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> a private man of war of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> of six guns. The <em><reg orig="Mearmaid">Mermaid</reg></em> coming up with her, she <reg orig="lowred">lowered</reg>, so we left her in <em>Scarborough</em>, and proceeded on our voyage, and we fell upon the Dogger bank amongst their fishermen, and took three of them, and forced many away without making their voyage, leaving their Lines behind them.</p>

<p>And <reg orig="crusing">cruising</reg> in our station the 21 <em>Decemb.</em> we took a Fly-boat laden with Hops, Brandy, <reg orig="Whitewine">White wine</reg>, and several other goods <reg orig="fraighted">freighted</reg> at <em>Amsterdam</em> bound for <em>Copenhagen</em>, and understood by reason we had some <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, there would none of their Merchant men come out without a stronger convoy, yet we continued upon their coast until <reg orig="foule">foul</reg> weather forced us off, and coming over we <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> two Doggers more, and our prize being considerable, I ordered Capt. <em>Holland</em> in the Assurance to convoy the prizes into <em>Bridlington</em> Bay for fear of their <reg orig="privaters">privateers</reg>, and <reg orig="my selfe">myself</reg> with the <reg orig="Mearemaid">Mermaid</reg> to cruse upon the Dogger one day or two, if weather permitted, to force them off the bank; but it proving <reg orig="foule">foul</reg> weather the <reg orig="Mearemaid">Mermaid</reg> hath lost her Foremast, and sprung her <reg orig="Main-mast">Mainmast</reg>.</p>

<p>The Assurance as far as I can judge is put to the Northward, and the <reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg> and <reg orig="my selfe">myself</reg> came this sixth of January into <em>Bridlington</em> Bay. I am informed by the <em>Hollanders</em> that we have taken, there are 80 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of laden Merchant men in the Sound ready to come forth, and five <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of men of war with them.</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honours'</reg> humble Servant to command, Nath. Cobham.</i> <em>Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg></em> now riding at <em>Bridlington Bay</em> 6 <em>Jan.</em> 1653.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 10 January.</i></head>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his Council sat close about great <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>.</p>

<pb n="11" />

<p>There are Letters come from the State of France congratulatory, &amp;c.</p>


<head level="3">By Letters from <em>Holland</em> came as followeth, <em>viz.</em></head>

<head level="3"><i>Harlem in Holland 30 Decemb. (alias 9. Janu.) 1653.</i></head>

<p>On Tuesday last there rise a very great storm, which continued all night, and there being between 50 and 60 Merchants riding at anchor at the <em>Texel</em>, a great many of them are sunk and cast away, we hear but of 17 of them saved; so that between 30 and 40 are at best spoiled, sunk, and run <reg orig="a ground">aground</reg>, and of them 20 quite lost, that is the least; amongst the rest there was one East India ship cast away called the <em>Lilly</em> that was going out, and another East India ship called the Marygold is much hurt and shattered. The <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is great, both ships, goods, and <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> lives, the <reg orig="ships">ships'</reg> road very thick together, and many had their anchors came home, and <reg orig="drave">drove</reg> aboard other ships, and one tore and sunk another.</p>

<p>It was sad to hear the <reg orig="schriching">screeching</reg>, crying, tearing, calling, roaring, and lamenting that there was, when none could save hundreds that they saw drowning in this extremity, so that many are made Widows, and <reg orig="Fatherlesse">Fatherless</reg> whose extremities are very great, and the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> hand is sore upon us.</p>

<p>Divers of these ships have been driven <reg orig="a shoar">ashore</reg>, and some upon Shelves and Rocks, and many are lost in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts, yet some it is hoped will be gotten again.</p>

<p>What the particular losses have been in all parts of this Country and at Sea cannot yet be collected: But we much fear our East India fleet, of about 150 ships, which we hear are at Sea.</p>

<p>At <em>Amsterdam</em> also some hurt was done by this <reg orig="storme">storm</reg>, for without the gate of the City, by the <reg orig="Utrechts">Utrecht's</reg> <reg orig="Bole">Bowl</reg>, a Malt-mill of <em>Schepen <reg orig="Paters">Pater's</reg></em> fell on fire with the violence of the motion, which could not be <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> in that mighty storm: The chasing of the violent motion thereof set it on fire, whereby not only the Mill but four houses that stood by it were burnt, to the great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of <em>Schepen Pater</em>, who had much malt lay there. But he is able enough to bear it, having gained a vast estate by brewing for the men of War.</p>

<p>Also within the City of <em>Amsterdam</em>, the iron <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> (that <pb n="12" />is about 20 foot long, and weighed some 14 or 1600 l.) that stood upon the western Church newly built within few years, at the charge of the City, was by this violent <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> blown down, with the Weathercock above it, and the great copper <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> <reg orig="Bowle">Bowl</reg> under it, which was said to hold near an <reg orig="Hogshad">Hogshead</reg> of Beer, was all blown down, nothing being left standing above the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Crown on the top of that Steeple: All the said weight fell <reg orig="downe">down</reg> through the body of the Church, breaking the strongest corner of that new Church, and fell upon the grave <reg orig="stons">stones</reg>, <reg orig="brake">broke</reg> them, and tore the dead bodies in their graves.</p>

<p>But the greatest <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> I hear of was at <em>Rype</em> in North-<em>Holland</em>, where an <reg orig="Oyle">Oil</reg>-mill by the storm, in a violent motion by its own heat took fire in the <reg orig="spuriousnesse">spuriousness</reg> of the <reg orig="storme">storm</reg>, and that burning set divers houses on fire, and one house another <reg orig="untill">until</reg> some 5 or six hundred houses were destroyed, and in them many persons burnt alive; and abundance of goods, valued by many to a greater sum <reg orig="then">than</reg> I dare speak of; for this heavy Judgement by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Command made such quick dispatch, that many were taken in their beds, and others burnt alive before they could get out of <reg orig="doores">doors</reg>.</p>

<p>We hear there was pitiful lamentations, the Children crying to Parents, and Husbands to Wives of their <reg orig="bosome">bosom</reg>, and could not be helped, Many a <reg orig="Mothers">Mother's</reg> bowels pressing her into the <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> and flame to save her child, lost her life and her <reg orig="childes">child's</reg> also.</p>

<p>So the destruction of this Town was in a moment, where were so many rich Families, that now have lost all their goods, and have not an house to hide their heads in.</p>

<p>I cannot describe unto you the thousand part of the miseries of that poor Town, where not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the private houses, but the two Churches and Town house, and the way house also, as is said, are all laid in ashes.</p>

<p>The Lord stay his heavy hand of Judgement, for I tremble to <reg orig="thinke">think</reg> how terrible he is in his wrath; for the fire <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> not in this Town. but flew over the River sixty foot broad, that goes about the Bemster, and there upon the <reg orig="in side">inside</reg> of the Bank of the Bemstser burnt divers houses also; and burnt the very <pb n="13" />ships (though small ones) and boats that lay in the Haven; besides what harm it hath done in other parts not herein mentioned.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>
<p>The 28 of <em>December</em> the Enemy had a <reg orig="randevouse">rendezvous</reg> upon the Hough (a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of plain ground <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Weyme</em>.<!--Weems?-->) The parts about <em>Weyme</em><!--Weems--> are miserably wasted, and the Gentlemen of <em>Atholl</em> ill resenting their oppression. <em>Kenmore</em> and <em><reg orig="Glencarry">Glengarry</reg></em> marched North, with about 800 horse and foot, intending to meet <em>Seafort</em> at <em>Lagon Morghamdrum</em>, where their whole body intends to <reg orig="randevouse">rendezvous</reg>. Before their going, there was a falling out between <em>Kenmore</em> and <em><reg orig="Glencary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and a Duel appointed, but prevented by the <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> and wits of their <reg orig="Associats">Associates</reg>. <em>Wogan</em> with his <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg> are at present with <em>Atholl</em>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Logiret</em>, well mounted and armed, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> of them in rich <reg orig="apparell">apparel</reg>, which <reg orig="addes">adds</reg> <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> to the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> fury, the Enemy have generally spoiled most of such horses as they have taken out of <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> stables; their bellies almost <reg orig="dryed">dried</reg> up with heats, too much corn, and ill dressing.</p>

<p>On Friday last the Earl of <em>Kinoule</em> about 8 in the morning appeared <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Glans">Glams</reg></em> with a party of horse, consisting of 70 or thereabouts, his <reg orig="designe">design</reg> was to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the horse belonging to <em><reg orig="Glans">Glams</reg></em>, as they came from watering, lying in a covert place for that purpose, thinking thereby to increase his number, and to procure exchange for his men taken at <em>Eghill</em>, and <pb n="14" />coming at first with a small party riding into <em><reg orig="Glans">Glams</reg></em>, took 3 of our men, which Major <em>Ducket</em>, who commanded Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> Troop there, having notice of it sent out his <reg orig="Quarter master">Quartermaster</reg> with 10 horse to discover his party, who advancing with two files of Foot that were to make good a bridge, gave them a charge, an routed and dispersed their whole party, took the Lord <em>Kinoule</em> and 14 men, all much wounded, and about 35 horse, and at the coming away of the Letter had sent a party to gather up the rest, all quitting their horses and betaking to the <reg orig="Boggs">Bogs</reg>: Major <em>Ramsey</em> was there, but escaped, we had one man <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> and 7 wounded, all slightly, 3 of the Enemy were <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> on the plain.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 3 Janua. 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 11 January 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Ambassador newly come over from the King of France, had Audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, whom he congratulated in his new Government.</p>

<p>Letters from France say <em>Charles Stuart</em> at the Palace Royal in Paris, feasted the French King, with some French Lords and Ladies, and there were his brothers the Dukes of York and <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>. P. <em>Rupert</em> is come thither, but it holds true that P. <em>Maurice</em> is drowned.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith 5. Jan.</i> <em><reg orig="Glencairne">Glencairn</reg>, Lorn</em>, and <em>Athol</em> were about ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since in <em>Athol</em> with about 2000 foot, and 600 horse, <em>Kenmore</em>, and <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg>, went North, having 400 horse, and betwixt 200 and 300 foot. the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Athol</em> being acquainted with the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Proclamation, told his people, that all the horses they have will be taken away by the English, and hath thereupon given orders that his men should take all the horses they can lay their hands upon. I have sent you <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> the names of the <reg orig="Prisones">Prisoners</reg> taken at <em><reg orig="Glans">Glams</reg>.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration by the Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent, That (notwithstanding my Proclamation of Septemb. 27. last) many serviceable Horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great disservice of the peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much <reg orig="conivance">connivance</reg> of the Owners of Possessors: These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons who now are or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable Horses or Mares, exceeding the value <pb n="15" />of 5 l. sterling, to bring in the same within 48 hours, next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such horses and Mares as shall not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> brought in; the one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the use of the State, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to the party informing, but also <reg orig="bee">be</reg> deemed as an open enemy, and dealt with accordingly: Which horses and Mares so brought in, shall nevertheless be at the <reg orig="Owners">Owner's</reg> <reg orig="choyce">choice</reg> either to have meet satisfaction for them, as they shall be reasonably worth, or keep them within the said <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> or Quarters of our Army; And the respective Sheriffs and their Deputies within their Sheriffdoms, are hereby required, to cause these presents solemnly to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> proclaimed and published according to accustomed manners of publishing Proclamations. And afterwards, (that none may pretend ignorance) to cause to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> distributed to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Presbyteries within their said Sheriffdoms a competent cumber hereof.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and Seal at Dalkeith 14 Decemb. 1653. R. <reg orig="LILBVRNE">LILBURNE</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Prisoners taken at <reg orig="Glans">Glams</reg>.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Kinoule. Alexander Nipper Capt. John English, late foot <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> in Dundee but reduced. James Bowter. Patrick Rosse. Henry Fetchry. Will. Meward. Patrick Knock. John Hamilton. Rob. Jackson. James Blayer. Laird of Balgello his Brother, and late Capt. at Worcester. Patrick Macklane. William Menis. John Steward. Robert Lindsey. Theodore Bathon. David Grime, servant to the Lord Kinoule.</p>

<p>The Dutch are now gone over to Holland, yet there is some hopes there may be a conclusion of Peace, which will be within ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, or else not likely.</p>

<p>The English Fleet is still in the Channel, and General Pen with them, Gen Blake, Gen. Monke, and Gen. Desbrough are returned to Whitehall.</p>

<p>There was about a week since a Ring found in Westminster-hall, whosoever shall tell the marks <unclear>of to the keeper</unclear> of the Library at Westminster who found it, will deliver it to those who shall make it appear to be theirs.</p>

<p>Spiritual <unclear>Preachings</unclear> part the second, or a Treatise of sin, with its Causes, differences, mitigations, and aggravations; particularly, of the desperate <reg orig="deceitfulnesse">deceitfulness</reg> of <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> heart, of presumptuous, and of <reg orig="hypocrisie">hypocrisy</reg>, and formality in Religion; also handling the <reg orig="uprightnesse">uprightness</reg>, and <reg orig="tendernesse">tenderness</reg> of a gracious heart, and therein discovering the nature of a misguided Conscience; As also of secret and unknown sins that the best me are guilty of, with <unclear>directions</unclear> to the godly under their fears about them. In 23 Sermons. By <unclear><!--one initial--></unclear> Burgess sometimes Fellow of Emanuel <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Cambridge, and now Pastor of Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire. Printed for T.U. And sold by Tho. Newberry at the three Lyons in Cornhill by the Exchange.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>