<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState227">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 227</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 26 of <em>January</em> To Thursday the 2 day of <em>February</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 26. January. 1653.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Holland</em> came the Copy of a Printed Declaration as followeth, translated out of Dutch</p>

<head level="3">A DECLARATION</head>

<head level="3">By the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> at <em>Amsterdam</em></head>

<p><i>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of the Admiralty residing at <em>Amsterdam</em>, To all those before whom these presents shall come, Greeting.</i></p>

<p><i>Let it <reg orig="bee">be</reg> known, that it being conceived, thought, and apparent, that upon the coming og th Lords Deputies of this State from <em>England</em>, to make report how <reg orig="farre">far</reg> the Treaty there is by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> grace and favour effected some Merchants and Masters of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships, upon presumption of a cessation of hostility, have been so forward as to have brought out their ships and goods, and have beyond <pb n="1" />their hope suffered <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>; <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have found good, and resolved to give warning to all and <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> whom it concerneth, as also <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> is warned by these presents; That the former hostility doth yet continue, and that it is not fit nor convenient that <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> should in regard of the Treaty, think himself secure, before upon the continuation of the negotiation, there shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a cessation of the foresaid hostility proclaimed.</i></p>

<p>Acted in the Assembly of the said <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> the 16 <i>alias</i> 26 of <em>January</em> 1653-4.</p>

<p><i>F. Herberts. And by Order of the same. <em>David Wildt</em>.</i></p>

<p><reg orig="Mounsieur">Monsieur</reg> <em>Bevering</em>, one of the Dutch Deputies that were before in <em>England</em>, returning again back from <em>Holland</em>, was the night before this day, about nine <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night, with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, to desire a cessation by reason of the forward <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> they have made in <em>Holland</em>, for the ratification of the Peace.</p>

<p>This day Mr. <em>Feake</em>, and Mr. <em>John Simpson</em>, two who had been taken into custody the day before upon the Act for Treason, were examined before the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, and remanded into the <reg orig="Officers">Officer's</reg> hands.</p>

<p>An Order is appointed to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> drawn up by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, for propagating of the Gospel in the Northern Counties of <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Whereas the Committee for claims, sitting at <em>Grocers hall</em>, directed one penny (upon every pound adventured for Lands in <em>Ireland</em>) to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> paid Mr. <em>Turner</em> or some other by their Order; The Lord Protector with the advice of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> hath otherwise ordered the payment of the same, as appeareth by his Order, the copy whereof followeth.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday 26 January 1653.</head>

<head level="3">An Order by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</head>

<p><i>Whereas by an Order of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of State at <em>Whitehall</em> of the 2 of <em>July</em> last, It was ordered, that one penny in the pound (which amongst other things, by order of the said <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of the first of <em>June</em> last <reg orig="authorizing">authorising</reg> the Committee for clearing claims at <em>Grocers-hall</em>, to receive the said penny upon the pound, of <pb n="2" />and from every Adventurer) should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> paid unto such person or persons as the Committee of Adventurers (who are <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> by the Body of Adventurers) should nominate and appoint for that purpose, as by the said order of the second of <em>July</em> (among other things therein contained) may at large appear.</i></p>

<p><i>It is now thought fit, and so Ordered by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice of the Council, That the said Order of the second of <em>July</em> last, and every clause therein contained, to all intents and purposes, shall stand, and is hereby <reg orig="ratifyed">ratified</reg> and confirmed; any Act, Order, or Vote made to the contrary thereof in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> notwithstanding.</i></p>

<p><i>And it is further Ordered, that the said Committee for clearing the claims at <em><reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> hall</em>, shall not deliver out any Certificate to any of the said Adventurers for their respective allotments of land, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> they are satisfied by a <reg orig="noat">note</reg> under the hand of the Treasurer already appointed, or to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> appointed by the said Committee of Adventurers, that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath received the said penny upon the pound, according to the said Order of the Council of State of the second of <em>July</em> last, which every Adventurer is hereby <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> and required to pay accordingly.</i></p>

<p>W. Jessop, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>George Almary</em> living at the lower end of <em>Old Jury</em> is the Treasurer appointed by the Committee of Adventurers to the purpose aforesaid.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 27 January 1653.</i></head>

<p>There were two men this day set in the Pillory in <em>Smithfield</em>, the one a <reg orig="Carpenters">Carpenter's</reg> servant, for bearing and abusing his <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg>, the other for Perjury, and had his <reg orig="eares">ears</reg> nailed to the Pillory.</p>

<p>Between three and four of the clock this afternoon part of the Body of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church (but not the Steeple) at the great South door fell down, there being divers children about the time playing in the Church near the place, but <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hear as yet not of any <reg orig="kild">killed</reg>, but one or two sorely hurt.</p>

<p>From <em>Dalkeith</em> 22 <em>Janua.</em> In the last engagement of our party, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Drummond</em>, there were slain on the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> side, one Capt. <em>Ker</em>, and another eminent man, who they said was the second brave man of their Forces, very many of them wounded. The main body of them still continue in <em>Murray-land</em>, between <pb n="3" /><em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em> and <em>Aberdeen</em>. A party of which of 300 foot, under Lieut. Col. <em>Heniet</em> of <em>Newark</em>, and 100 horse, commanded by one <em>Inchinrole</em>, came into <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em> Town, stayed about an hour, and went their way: at their last going away before this, the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> was pasted up upon the Market <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg>, those expressions in it, <i>Our ancient old enemy, the Kingdom of England</i>; and our grand enemy, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the bottom of their <reg orig="designe">design</reg> to destroy the English, and is a very good invitation for them to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them: If their plots <reg orig="bee">be</reg> laid no deeper, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hope they will not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> able to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> us much more hurt. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> hear that Col. <em><reg orig="Humphreys">Humphrey's</reg></em> gallant Troop of Dragoons are on the Borders, and some other coming for our supply, which is welcome News; and now <reg orig="wee">we</reg> shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> able to meet with the enemy at all turns.</p>

<head level="3">A PROCLAMATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>By <em>William</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>, Lord <em>Kilmares</em>, commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service, and advancement of our ancient old Enemy the kingdom of <em>England</em> who by their <reg orig="perfideous">perfidious</reg> practice, and all <reg orig="unlawfull">unlawful</reg> means, still pretending the good and advancement of the Protestant Religion, has <reg orig="endevoured">endeavoured</reg> the reducement and enslaving of us, our predecessors and Country to their subjection. Many pretended countrymen of several qualities, within the shires of <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg>, <reg orig="Aire">Ayre</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg>,</em> and other adjacent places upon the South side of <em>Perth</em>, are not ashamed to bring in, sell and deliver to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Officers of <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, belonging to the said grand enemy, the whose serviceable Arms and other offensive weapons, they either have or can possibly acquire, whereby his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Levies in most parts of the said shires, are greatly impeded, far contrary to our <reg orig="naturall">natural</reg> Countrymen inhabiting the Northern shires, who by their good example, laying to heart the bleeding condition of this their native Country, do all unanimously take up arms, and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with us for relief and recovery thereof; <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> do therefore by these presents, <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> and declare, that whatsoever person or persons of whatsoever quality, within any of the said shire of <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg>, <reg orig="Aire">Ayre</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg></em>, or places adjacent, shall upon whatsoever pretence after publication hereof, presume to sell, give, or deliver up to any belonging to the said common enemy, any serviceable horses <pb n="4" />or <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, to the prejudice of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service or levies of <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> or foot, <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> upon any of them; that the whole good and <reg orig="geir">gear</reg> of the person or persons, disobeyers of this our command (without respect of any) shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sequestrate, and confiscate for the use of any whosoever can first apprehend them, for <reg orig="medling">meddling</reg> with, and effectuating whereof, these presents shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> an <reg orig="irreduceable">irreducible</reg> Warrant; and ordains publication hereof at the Market <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em>, whereby they, nor none inhabiting the shires of <em><reg orig="Aire">Ayre</reg>, <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg></em>, or places adjacent, pretend ignorance hereof. <i>Given at <em><reg orig="Weims">Weems</reg></em> this 22 of <em>December</em> 1653. sic subscribitur. GLENCAIRN.</i></p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Falmouth</em> thus, Here are <reg orig="severall">several</reg> ships come into this harbour, being wind-bound, and intending for <em>London</em> and those parts with the first opportunity, those that were here whom <reg orig="wee">we</reg> formerly mentioned, are now all gone out with these Easterly winds: There are many Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, who be still between the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end and the Isles of <em>Scilly</em>, and make it very dangerous to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> without a convoy. Some of the <em>Brest</em> French <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> (<reg orig="wee">we</reg> hear) have lately taken two small <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> of this Country, and sent them home. They have <reg orig="wee">we</reg> hear lately among them above 20 <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of men of war out, whereof one hath 36 Guns and 200 men, other about 24 and 20 Guns but most of 12 and under.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from an eminent person attending upon the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> in <em><reg orig="Sweaden">Sweden</reg></em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>According to my promise, these are to acquaint you of our safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> at <em>Upsal</em> her <reg orig="Mafesties">Majesty's</reg> University of <em><reg orig="Sweaden">Sweden</reg></em>, where <reg orig="shee">she</reg> hath given my Lord his audience in the Castle there. <reg orig="Shee">She</reg> hath been after an extraordinary manner pleased both with my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Speech, and with his judgement, which <reg orig="shee">she</reg> commends, and with the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> about which he is sent, which I doubt not but by the Grace of God, will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> speedily effected; <reg orig="shee">she</reg> having often expressed he <reg orig="willingnesse">willingness</reg> thereunto; my Lord hath had three times audience in this small time, twice private, and once <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, at which times his Lordship had time enough to give a right understanding of all things, as you may see by his Speech herewith sent.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>He being one time in a private Conference with her and <reg orig="no bodie">nobody</reg> <reg orig="besices">besides</reg> themselves near two hours, and at another, three, she is a <reg orig="Princesse">Princess</reg> of much worth, and a Lady of great Parts, and one that expresseth a great deal of affection to the English, and commends them much for their honesty. I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> if nothing intervene the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> here will be sooner concluded <reg orig="then">than</reg> you can imagine. Pray let me hear from you sometimes, how affairs go in <em>England</em> and concerning the Treaty with the Dutch, and what is become of the <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>. Her Majesty hath made a stop of all the Dutch ships at <reg orig="Stockholme">Stockholm</reg> by reason of some injury offered her Subjects by the Dutch, what that will produce I know not. Here are several Agents from the <em>Dutch, Spain, France, Denmark</em> and other parts.</p>

<p><i>Upsal 29 Decemb. 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>His Excellency the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> His Speech to the Queen of <em><reg orig="Sweadland">Sweden</reg></em> the 23 of Decemb. 1653.</i></head>

<p>MADAM,</p>

<p>By Command of my Superiors, <i>The Parliament of the Commonwealth of England</i>, I do with all respect salute Your Majesty, which had been sooner done if by <reg orig="extaordinary">extraordinary</reg> Accidents and Engagements in the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of three Nations, with no few foreign diversions. It had not been retarded.</p>

<p>And although the <em>Commonwealth of England</em> are not <reg orig="incouraged">encouraged</reg> to send abroad when they reflect upon the barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places, Yet Your Majesty perceives, that from Your Government, neither Our Masters nor their Servants have the least suspicion of any such Entertainment; But We who are here <reg orig="doe">do</reg> gratefully acknowledge Our experience of the contrary, and of much civility to Our Nation.</p>

<p>My <reg orig="Businesse">Business</reg> is to communicate with Your Majesty, matters relating to the common good, which is of such weight that it admits of no hopes of good <reg orig="successe">success</reg> without his special blessing, who by <reg orig="smal">small</reg> means can bring great things to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, the confidence whereof, with my submission to the Judgement and Commands of my Superiors, hath given me this <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg> of being in Your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence.</p>

<p>Whom I shall not weary with many words or expressions <pb n="6" />beyond meaning, I am no sent hither for that <unclear>cause</unclear> and it is as different from my own spirit, as contrary to <unclear>the</unclear> practice and commands of my Superiors, from whom, and <unclear>from</unclear> their Servant, according to the English reality, Your <unclear>Majesty</unclear> will <reg orig="finde">find</reg> all manner of plainness and truth in our Transactions, our Deliverances and Preservations, whereof we have been <unclear>eye</unclear> witnesses; have been so near to Miracles of infinite rich <unclear>Mercy</unclear> and Love from Heaven, that we should sin against them if <unclear>the</unclear><!--this is entirely blank but "the" makes sense--> least guilt or unfaithfulness, should infect our Conversation.</p>

<p>It is not my work to paint out my own <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, or to <unclear>draw</unclear> black lines upon any, though our Adversaries: Neither <unclear>shall I</unclear> take upon me to mention the Excellency of Your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Person and Government, or of Your People, and Countries, <unclear>lest</unclear> I should incur any merit. And because I speak to those who God hath <reg orig="favored">favoured</reg> with enjoyment of great Mercies, the increase and countenance whereof is heartily desired by my Superiors, and by me their Servant.</p>

<p>I shall not enlarge my discourse with observations concerning both Nations of likeness, in Language, Manners, and warlike Dispositions, Arguments more natural <reg orig="then">than</reg> artificial, for nearer union: But this I may not omit, the fruits whereof I have tasted.</p>

<p>The present happy Government under Your <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, which remembers unto us those blessed days of our Virgin-Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, under whom, above forty years the people enjoyed all Protection and Justice from their Princess, and she hold all Obedience and Affection from her people.</p>

<p>May this and more be the portion of Your Majesty and Your Successors; nor had it been lost in those who followed Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, though <reg orig="Forreigners">Foreigners</reg>, but through the extremity of their own ill government.</p>

<p>When attempts were made to ravish from us our highest Interests, the Orthodox Religion, and Just Liberty, the defence whereof undertaken by King <em>Gustavus Adolphus</em>, Your <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Royal Father of Blessed Memory, in His German expedition for the <reg orig="Protestants">Protestant's</reg> relief, was to him most <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> and successful, and surely for us most just and necessary, and alike crowned with gracious success by the Almighty.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>For the extirpation of both which by force, which had long been <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> otherwise, Auxiliaries were provided, and afterwards a War raised, which first appeared in <em>Scotland</em>, but there diligently resisted; and the English refusing to be Instrumental against <em>Scotland</em> for these ends, the storm was then blown over. In <em>Ireland</em> it rose so hideously, that 200000 poor Creatures, Men, Women, and Children, besides what the War devoured, were in cold blood barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, for no other reason, but because they were Protestants, and Commission <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> for it.</p>

<p>In <em>England</em> the fire brake out in all parts of it, from the one corner of the Land, unto the other; not a place, not a family, free from the rage of our <reg orig="Decenial">Decennial</reg>, more <reg orig="then">than</reg> Civil War.</p>

<p>An yet after so much blood poured forth, we bless God we live; and after so many devastations, a stranger passing through our <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, can hardly <reg orig="espie">espy</reg> the steps of it. Our good God hath given us in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and all the adjacent Isles and Territories of the Commonwealth, a full and happy Peace.</p>

<p>In all Appeals to Him, whereof we have seen many, he was pleased still to determine for the Parliament. And after these and eight Tenders and Treaties of Peace, wherein we received the denial from our Adversaries; it pleased the gracious, and <reg orig="al">all</reg>-disposing Hand of God, for the Good of <em>England</em>, to change the Government thereof; nevertheless, the same Common Interest which first begat former Alliances and Confederacies between the two Nations, do still continue and oblige both to desire the good of each other.</p>

<p>Whereunto they seem the more engaged, because we cannot <reg orig="finde">find</reg> that in any age there hath been a declared War between them, but a constant intercourse of Friendship and Amity, with mutual Offices of Kindness, out of which, great profit and happiness, hath redounded unto both.</p>

<p>These things being considered with the Affairs of Christendom, and especially of the <reg orig="Neighboring">Neighbouring</reg> Princes and States, through Divine Providence, in such posture and condition, as to give greater opportunity, an lay stronger Obligations upon <pb n="8" />both these Nations, to entertain a <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> union and correspondence <reg orig="then">than</reg> heretofore, whereby the commerce and tranquillity of both may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> preserved and provided for, with respect also to the common interest, and conservement of the true Protestant Religion: And your Majesty having by your late <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Ministers to <em>England</em> <reg orig="signifyed">signified</reg> your <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> inclinations and <reg orig="willingnesse">willingness</reg> by all good means to conserve and increase the ancient good understanding between these States; Upon these and other weighty considerations, and to show how acceptable the former overtures of your Majesty have <reg orig="bin">been</reg>, the Parliament have thought fit by <reg orig="mee">me</reg>, to make tender unto your Majesty of the friendship of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and to let you know, that they are not only ready to <reg orig="renue">renew</reg> and preserve inviolable, that amity and good correspondence which hath hitherto been between the two Nations, but are further willing to entertain a more strict alliance and union <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath as yet been, for the good of both.</p>

<p>And in such a way as shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> held requisite, I shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> ready more particularly to communicate what I have in charge for this purpose.</p>

<p><i>When his Excellency had ended his Speech, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> desired of the Queen to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> excused for being so long.</i></p>

<p>Her Majesty answered, that she liked it so well that <reg orig="shee">she</reg> could have been content to have heard him longer; and gave him very great applause.</p>

<p>Some Aldermen were this day from the City of <em>London</em>, to attend his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 28 Janua. 1653.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector hath consulted about the regulating of the Laws, and particularly of the Chancery, for the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> good of the Nation.</p>

<p>By a Letter from Cap. <em>Mill</em>, commander of the <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, was satisfied as followeth.</p>

<p>The 16 instant, the <em>Paul, Middleburgh</em>, and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> were all together, the 17 day <reg orig="wee">we</reg> having <reg orig="severall">several</reg> chases lost each other, and have not met to this day. The 18 instant I fell foul with 4 <em>Brest</em> men of war, of which <em>Beech</em> was one, with his <reg orig="flagge">flag</reg> in his <pb n="9" />main top, which gave chase to 4 <reg orig="smal">small</reg> vessels bound for <em>Rochel</em> from <em>Barstable</em>, laden with Herrings and <reg orig="Coales">Coals</reg>, with which men of war I did engage some six <reg orig="houres">hours</reg>, some 25 leagues Southwest of <em><reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg></em>, and put them to flight, and saved those small vessels from their hands. Yesterday I fell foul of one <em>Smith</em> of <em>Brest</em>, which had with him a <reg orig="vessell">vessel</reg> of <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>, <unclear>(one</unclear> <em>Parret</em> Master) bound for <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em>, which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> had in possession four days, which said <reg orig="vessell">vessel</reg> I did redeem, and took in him 17 <reg orig="French men">Frenchmen</reg> belonging to the said <em>Smith</em>, which said <reg orig="vessell">vessel</reg> of <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>, I have this day sent thither. Also this day I came up with 9 stout Merchant ships of <em>France</em>, which came from <em><reg orig="Marsilles">Marseilles</reg></em> bound for St. <em>Mallo</em>, but could do no good on them. I humbly take leave and remain, <i>your <reg orig="honours">honours'</reg> humble servant <em>Rob. Mill.</em></i></p>

<p><i>Falmouth <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> some 8 leagues from <em>Ushant</em></i> 23 Jan. 1653.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday 30 Janua. 1653.</i></head>

<p>Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Simpson</em> were this day committed prisoners to <em>Windsor</em> Castle.</p>

<p>One was this day set upon a wooden horse at <em>Tower hill</em>, and had his ears cut, for forging of an Order in the name of the Commissioners of the Navy, to <reg orig="cousen">cozen</reg> the State of nine pounds.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Genua">Genoa</reg></em> 28 Decemb. S.N.</head>

<p><i>The <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Ognato</em> is still here, preparing for his return into <em>Spain</em>, where Letters are come to the Court at <em>Madrid</em> from one Father <em>Jacob</em> of the Order of the Preachers of Jesus in the high <em>Armenia</em>, mentioning that lately one day about ten <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> in the morning, a great number of Turks, <reg orig="Moores">Moors</reg>, and other Infidels, being met their Church in the City of <em><reg orig="Meka">Mecca</reg></em>, they saw the chest in which the bones of their false prophet <em><reg orig="Mahomet">Mohamed</reg></em> were kept, fall to the ground and sink, and the pit remaining open for a quarter of an <reg orig="houre">hour</reg>, cast fire and <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> with a great stink, and afterward shut up as before, which caused such a fear and trembling amongst those Infidels, that acknowledge their madness and <reg orig="blindnesse">blindness</reg>, they gave themselves up to the same father, who converted them to the Christian Faith: But some think it was only a trick of that Priest, by this to <reg orig="indevour">endeavour</reg> the <reg orig="Infidels">Infidel's</reg> conversion that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> preached to. In <em>Corogna</em> there are 3000 Irish arrived, who have been sent into <em>Gallicia</em> for their Winter Quarters.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg> 6 January.</i></head>

<p>This day are come hither 3 ships from <em>Ireland</em>, reporting for <pb n="10" />News that the General <em>O Bryan</em> hath got a body of 4000 foot and 1000 horse, and doth <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> the Castle of <em>Dingle</em> by the <reg orig="Sea side">Seaside</reg>. This is reported by P. <em><reg orig="Ruperts">Rupert's</reg></em> friends here.</p>

<head level="3">From <em><reg orig="Antwerpe">Antwerp</reg></em> 21 Decemb.</head>

<p><i>The Irish Garrison in the Town of <em>Armentiers</em> have had a plot against the said Town, but the same being discovered, 18 of them that were guilty of that Treason, have been seized upon, and are in safe custody.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg> 15 Janua.</i></head>

<p>By the last <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have received advice that the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, and the <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> Cities have (notwithstanding the Protection of the <em>Swedes</em> to the contrary) admitted the City of <em>Bremen</em> into the number of the <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> Towns, as it hath been before; whereupon the said <em>Swedes</em>, have declared that they will not loose their <reg orig="claime">claim</reg> upon the said City, but will make it good whensoever they shall have the opportunity. The <reg orig="Electour">Elector</reg> of <em><reg orig="Colen">Cologne</reg></em>, and the French <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg>, <reg orig="Mounsieur">Monsieur</reg> <em>Vautorse</em>, having made the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> acquainted with the <reg orig="hostill">hostile</reg> invasion of the <em>Lorainers</em>, into the Dominions of <em>Liege</em>, it hath been concluded between the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> and the said <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> Towns, that they shall assist the said Elector, and <reg orig="endevour">endeavour</reg> to force the <em>Lorainers</em> out of that land and therefore his <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> Majesty is resolved to send his summons to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Towns for men and money.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Paris</em> 16 January</head>

<p><i>The English shops have taken two ships within the Haven of <em>Brest</em>, one laden with Wines, and another. His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> journey into <em>Normandy</em> is deferred for a while, In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> all the Sea ports have been well provided with <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and all <reg orig="munition">munitions</reg>. The Office of Grand Master of <em>France</em> being forfeited by the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, hath been bestowed upon the Prince <em>Thomas</em>, Uncle to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>, who hath the 12 instant taken his Oath, in his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> hands that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> faithful in his charge. <em>Charles <reg orig="Stewart">Stuart</reg></em> the pretended K. of <em>Scotland</em> hath with P. <em>Rupert</em> and others of his Council been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times deliberating about weighty affairs, the Treaty between <em>England</em> and the <em>United Provinces</em>, being much suspected by that party.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Liege</em> 20 Janua.</i></head>

<p>The Forces of the Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, are still hereabout, and do commit all kind of hostility, insomuch that <reg orig="no body">nobody</reg> can <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> <pb n="11" />in these parts, our party fell upon them about the Town of <unclear><em>Thuyn</em></unclear> and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> 500 of their men; Our Elector hath summoned all his Subjects by the 22 day, to appear all in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> at that time.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Rhynstroom 27 January.</i></head>

<p>Hereabout is a great fear occasioned by <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Regiments of <em>Swedes, Hesses</em> and <em>Brunswick</em> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, who are to march <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the Land of <em>Bergh</em>, for the assistance of the Elector of <em><reg orig="Colen">Cologne</reg></em>, who is assaulted in the Country of <em>Liege</em>, by the Duke of <em>Lorain</em>, who hath already issued out a Declaration, wherein he complains that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath himself been assaulted by the said Elector; doing at the same time all kind of hostility, and having taken the Castle of <em>Orsey</em>, where many <reg orig="Bores">Boers</reg> and Country people had fled for refuge, with their <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> and Cattle. <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath found there 2 or 300 horses, and hath taken 750 pistols of the said <reg orig="Bores">Boers</reg>, for the redeeming of their cattle, having left them to shift every one for themselves besides for their ransom. There are 600 foot and 200 horse sent from <em>Trevers</em> to the succour of the foresaid Elector, being more forward <reg orig="then">than</reg> the other Cities of the Empire, who are all to send him help and relief.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 31 January.</i></head>

<p>Some Aldermen were this day from the City to make an Address to His Highness, the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>A Declaration hath been presented from the Fleet to His Highness as followeth, <em>(viz.)</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>For His Highness, the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The DECLARATION, with the Humble Address of the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the Fleet, by them severally subscribed.</i></head>

<p>That these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, having been for some years like the Bush which burned, but is not consumed: And though the Nations round about us, stand gazing on to see us made a desolation, as well as a hissing unto them; yet we are hitherto by the mighty power of the Lord and his wonderful out-goings amongst us, made rather an astonishment in our Preservation, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a reproach, by our <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and devastation.</p>

<p>In which great Work of the Lord, we acknowledge with <pb n="12" /><reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath been a glorious Instrument, and hath undergone many hardships and <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of all that was near and dear unto you, even to life <reg orig="it selfe">itself</reg>, and understanding by providence Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> is <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with, and hath accepted of the Protection of this Commonwealth in the Government thereof.</p>

<p>We are in hopes that the Lord intends a settlement of Peace to these poor distracted Nations; and that <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with all the people of the Lord shall <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> and partake of the same under Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Protection, according to the Rule of the Lord Jesus. And therefore we have thought it necessary as a duty incumbent on us to DECLARE, that we shall willingly be obedient and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, in performance or Your great Trust, and also in the utmost hazard of our Lives (with what else is near and dear unto us) be serviceable unto You, in the station the Lord hath placed You, against Yours and the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Enemies in our <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places and capacities, during our employments.</p>

<p>And having had good testimony of Your great Affection and earning Bowels, after the <reg orig="weale">weal</reg> of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> People, we are <reg orig="imboldened">emboldened</reg> and encouraged in all humility to make this following <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg>.</p>

<p>That Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> will be pleased to have a more special eye of <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> unto them above all others, in regard they are near and dear unto him, who is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, even our Lord Jesus. For which cause he is not ashamed to call them Brethren, And <reg orig="doe">do</reg> humbly apprehend that their <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> will be Your <reg orig="Priviledge">Privilege</reg>. And to account of them as of Your greatest Jewels, which will <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> turn to Your great advantage.</p>

<p>And hereby You will for time to come not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> engage their hearts unto You, who in times past have not stood at a distance from You, But Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> will also engage the great Jehovah, Your and their Father to be a refuge, Shield and defence unto You as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as an everlasting rest for You, when all the storms of this Commonwealth shall cease, which is and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be the <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> prayers of,</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> most humble and faithful Servants,</i></p>

<pb n="13" />

<p>Signed by the Generals and the several Commanders present In the Fleet,</p>

<p>From the <em>Hague</em> 28 <i>(alias 18) Janu. 1653.</i> Report was made to the Lords States General, where the Commissioners of the Assembly of <em>Holland</em> were present, by the Lords Deputies come from <em>England</em> of their Negotiation in the matter of Peace whereupon Letters were sent to all the Towns of <em>Holland</em> to send their Deputies hither presently upon the reading of them (to resolve upon the ratification of the Articles concluded) the Lords States of <em>Holland</em> and <em>Westfreezland</em> have begun their meeting the 17. <i>(alias 27.)</i> in the morning in which also the Lords <em>Beverling</em> and <em>Newport</em> made their report to their said Great and Potent Lordships, whereupon the Lords States of <em>Holland</em> sat again in the afternoon <reg orig="til">till</reg> 11 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night. The next day the same Lords States of <em>Holland</em> went from their Assembly to that of the Lords States General, where they <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> <reg orig="til">till</reg> two of the clock in the afternoon. It is reported that they offered their Resolves upon the Articles of Peace, which were approved of, and the Lords Deputies has thanks returned to them for their Services done in <em>England</em> for the good of this Country. The Assembly of the States of <em>Holland</em> and <em>Westfreezland</em> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be shortly dissolved till the 20 of <em>Febr.</em> Next, and the Lord <em>Beverling</em> is returned for <em>England</em> to <reg orig="endevour">endeavour</reg> to procure a Cessation of Arms, till the other Provinces <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have time to bring in their Ratification to the Lords States General, and them a solemn Ambassage <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be sent into <em>England</em>, by the Gen. of the Land forces, and the Lord <em>Updam</em> Adm. of the Navy, as is thought, to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Peace. The <em>French</em> Ambassador hath 16 <i>(alias 26)</i> Instant had audience of the Lords States General; <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> thought that the said Lords States have given him notice of the Articles which their Deputies have agreed upon in <em>England</em>; and that the said Ambassador hath thereupon had another Audience of the said Lords General. What he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have propounded is <reg orig="stil">still</reg> under the secret.</p>

<p>Dalkeith 24 Janu. The 19. instant Col. Daniel Governor of St. Johnstons having Intelligence that the Enemy were in or about Dunkel, sent out 100 Horse, and 100 Dragoons under the Command of Capt. Lieut. Ashby of Col. <reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg> Regim. who came very near the Town undiscovered, and the Forlorn fell in with two of their Scouts, they made some resistance at the Baracadoe, but our few Dragoons beat them thence, <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> the town and killed six or seven at the <reg orig="enterance">entrance</reg>.</p>

<p>Our <reg orig="Forlorne">Forlorn</reg> went in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> to the other end of the Town, and pursued them, that upon the Alarm, got away to <pb n="14" />the Hills and Passages betwixt the Town and <em>Blair</em>, and there were 7 of them killed, many had the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> mark, and most of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Troopers made footmen: They brought 50 horses with them, and 7 prisoners of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Regiment, also many Carbines, Cloaks, Boots, and other things belonging to them; and had they not escaped to the very Woods and <reg orig="Craigs">Crags</reg>, which are at the very <reg orig="Towns">Town's</reg> end, there had been more in our custody. <em>Athol</em> was there himself, and I believe this will be a great obstruction to his Levies: He had about 100 or 150 foot with him, most of which got to the Hills. The horse pursued them above two miles beyond the Town, and wounded many; but being very eager in the pursuit, and the Woods within two or three yards of the passage, they had no more to do, but being <reg orig="knockt">knocked</reg> off their horses, to run into the thickets, and then they were safe. It was a very seasonable Mercy, both to <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg> their height upon the business of <em>Drummond</em>, and also to lay a discouragement upon the temper of that <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> people. There was one of Col. <em><reg orig="Twisletons">Twisleton's</reg></em> own Troop killed; some of the prisoners confess, that <em>Wogan</em> was run through the shoulder at <em>Drummond</em>, and lies at <em><reg orig="Weyms">Weems</reg></em>. Cap. <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> Lieutenant and Cap. <em>Ker</em>, did kill each other, both of them firing at one instant at more <reg orig="then">than</reg> 4 yards distance, with their <reg orig="Blunderbushes">Blunderbusses</reg>, and fell both from their horses immediately.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> are now in <em>Elgin</em>: Their General <em>Glencairn</em> with about 1200 foot and 300 horse, besides Dragoons; they have <reg orig="beleagured">beleaguered</reg> <em>Burgie</em>, which is a Garrison of ours. <em>Kenmore</em> is at <em>Forres</em>, and keeps his Guards upon the River <em>Findern</em>, to scour the passage from <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>; the 20 instant Col. <em>Morgan</em> was marching towards them with 14 companies of foot, and 8 Troops of Horse and Dragoons.</p>

<p>If these <unclear>sheets</unclear> shall come to the hands of Mr. Thomas Copwood, born at Dilvern in the County of Stafford, or to the hands of any that can give him Intelligence, either in this Commonwealth, or in any of the Plantations belonging to it, or other parts <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> he is, It is desired that he may understand, and have notice, That by his Elder <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> death there is an estate <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> to him.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 1 Febru. 1653.</i></head>

<p>There is news that the States are gone from <em>Zealand</em> to the <em>Hague</em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in Confirmation of the Peace with <em>England</em>, aforesaid. The Popish Princes are troubled at the <pb n="15" />settlement of <em>England</em> under the Lord Protector, who had a design in Confederacy from the Pope, against all Protestants, that is hereby prevented; and this Government doth much <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> all Protestants generally in several Nations. <em>Conde</em> refuseth to come in to the King of <em>France</em>; his Brother <em>Conti</em> was solicited to marry the Cardinal <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarin's</reg></em> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, which he first refused, but since inclines to. One <em>Orton Brooker</em> hat Licence to dig in some suspected places for Treasure long hid. The Generals are in <em>Stokes-Bay</em>, from whom is come a Confirmation of the prizes mentioned in the last, and some Squadrons are gone out.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 30 January.</i> This morning news is come from <em>Dartmouth</em>, that a great Flemming is put on shore, having on board her, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one dead man, being killed by a shot, the rest of the company forsaking her. Some Canary ships arrived at <em>Falmouth</em>, and 4 ships from <em><reg orig="Mallago">Malaga</reg></em> at this Port.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 26 Jan.</i> One Troop of Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Dragoons being relieved, are gone after him in the North; from whom we have not heard since he marched from <em>Aberdeen</em>. The Regiments in <em>Scotland</em> so well approve of the New Government in <em>England</em>, and the Officers generally send in their Addresses, to be sent to His Highness to that purpose; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some few of Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment, <reg orig="cheifly">chiefly</reg> of the <reg orig="Welch">Welsh</reg> Troop, the <reg orig="Quarter-Master">Quartermaster</reg>, and some <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> are gone off towards <em>England</em>, and the Chaplain to the Regiment. There was a Shallop built up, and 4 Guns put into her, to secure Trade in the River <em>Clyde</em>, and prevent the Highlanders falling into <em>Renfrewshire</em>, which they often did before; but there being present no other considerable Vessel to assist, (as was expected) 3 or 4 days <unclear>ago, one</unclear> Lieut. Col. <em>Harriot</em> with some Boats from the Loughs in the Hills, <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> the Vessel. A Lieutenant of Gen. <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> Regiment, and 7 or 9 other (most Officers) were lately taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Falkirk</em>, by a party, and carried to the Hills. Col. <em><reg orig="Humphreys">Humphrey's</reg></em> Troop is come to <em>Musleborough</em>, we long much for the other two Regiments.</p>

<p><i>Newcastle, 28 Jan.</i> The <em>Wetwang</em>, and the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Friggot">Frigate</reg>, have each of them brought in hither a prize, 2 Dutch Capers of 6 Guns <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>, and 100 hundred prisoners, 50 in each. We are here full of Dutch prisoners.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>