<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState231">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 231</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 23 of <em>February</em> To Thursday the 2 day of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 23. February. 1653.</i></head>

<p>An Order was sent to the Lieutenant of the Tower of <em>London</em>, for the Brother of the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em>Portugal</em>, to continue in the Tower, so that his <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> is again put off for this Sessions.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Paine</em> a Gentleman belonging to <em><reg orig="Mine">Mien</reg> <reg orig="Hier">Herr</reg> Beverling</em>, one of the Lord Ambassadors from the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the United Provinces, came this day to his Excellency; and he brings News that the other three <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> were set out from the <em>Hague</em> the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day before in the morning towards <em>Rotterdam</em>, and so to come for to <em>England</em>, by the way of <em><reg orig="Flushen">Flushing</reg></em>; and that that afternoon <reg orig="hee">he</reg> set <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> from thence in a small vessel.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 14 Febr. 1653.</i> This morning was brought into our Port a <pb n="1" />Fleming, which pretended to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a <reg orig="Swead">Swede</reg>, but is found otherwise.</p>

<p>From <em>Scilly</em> <em>Feb.</em> 18. came thus. The 13 instant, the Samaritan of <em>Bristol</em>, a ship of about 200 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, with 12 guns, laden with Wheat, together with a small Pink of <em>Plymouth</em>, came into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, which were both taken by <em>Beach</em> one of the <em>Brest</em> men of War, and were redeemed on Thursday the ninth instant by the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> and the <em>Constant Warwick</em>; yesterday the 15 of this month, the <em>Constant Warwick</em> arrived here for some <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg>, and fresh water: The <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he gave chase unto <em>Beach</em>, but the night came too fast on them, and were <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> from an engagement. <em>Hebditch</em> one of the old <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> was taken in the <em>Samaritan</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, and is now on board the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>: there is also a Vessel in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> called the <em>Peter</em> of <em>Dover</em>, that came from <em><reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg></em>, and the Master <reg orig="affirmes">affirms</reg>, that there are 20 Dutch ships bound for St <em><reg orig="Martins">Martin's</reg></em>, where are 40 more, and that then they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> have but three Convoys.</p>

<p><i>From Dalkeith Febr. 18.</i> About for <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since Col. <em>Daniel</em> with a party of Horse, Foot, and Dragoons, together with the conjunction of another party from <em>Dundee</em>, in all about 1000 <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> towards <em>Dunkel</em>, where the enemies most considerable quarters was, and where they had newly established a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Lord <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> house near the Church. And upon Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em> approach (the Lord <em>Athol</em>, and Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em>, having intelligence retreated to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and left only the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> and some few to defend the Church) those in the Church durst not stand, <reg orig="busled">bustled</reg> to the House, whereof men attempted them together, and got under the <reg orig="wals">walls</reg> with Pickaxes, and other instruments that were in <reg orig="readinesse">readiness</reg>, and in short time gotten to a part of the House without the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of one man; and having slain only three of the enemy, the rest <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> quarter and had it granted, yet notwithstanding unworthily began to resist a little, which quickened our men the more; and then the enemy <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out again, they would accept of the terms granted. In the House we took 1 Captain of Foot, Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs'</reg></em> own Quartermaster, and Sergeants, and 114 private Rogues, together with 80 Muskets and <reg orig="Bandeleevers">Bandoleers</reg>, some Firelocks, and Swords, about two Barrels of Powder, as also 25 Troop Horses, and 14 or 15 Case <pb n="2" />of Pistols, with much Meal, Malt and <reg orig="Oates">Oats</reg>, which not having convenience to carry away, we set fire to a barrel of Powder, and those Provisions, and blew up them and the house together.</p>

<p>About five <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago one of late Col. <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> men with three of his best horses, got his Landlord to help him to water them and run away with them to <em>Blaire</em> Castle, one of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, which makes our English fugitives <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> trusted by <em>Athol</em> and the Tories. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath also removed the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at <em><reg orig="Kildrumny">Kildrunny</reg></em>; and many of those <reg orig="Horse-men">Horsemen</reg>, he routed at his engagement with <em><reg orig="Glengarne">Glencairn</reg></em> running to <em>Athol</em> near <em>Dunkel</em>, he translated them to Foot.</p>

<p><i>St. Johnstones 15 February, 1653.</i> The Major and the Cornet had scarce time to read your Letter, being commanded at that time by Col. <em>Daniel</em> with 60 of our Horse, and 100 more out of other Troops in the Town, and four Companies of Foot, and as many Horse and Foot from <em>Dundee</em> commanded all by Col. <em>Daniel</em>, who were sent out to beat up the Quarters of the Highlanders at <em>Dunkel</em>; And now even as I was sealing up my Letter came in the Lieut. and the Cornet with the rest of the Horse saving 12 of our Troop, who were behind guarding of the Prisoners to Town. So soon as they came near the Den of Rogues, the <reg orig="forlorne">forlorn</reg> of our Horse was drawn out, which Col. <em>Daniel</em> gave the command of to our Lieutenant, <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> commanding the main Body. The foot fell on to storm so soon as they got up to the wall side, but were entertained very furiously, with good store of shot, but no hurt done to any of our men, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one foot <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> of <em>Dundee</em>. Our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> charged on very desperately upon them, an killed two or three and the they <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> themselves presently. They found little or nothing in the House and Castle, but two Barrels of powder and some Arms, and not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> else of great value. They have brought with them 114 Prisoners, whereof there is one Capt. of Foot, a Quartermaster, and a Sergeant, all the rest private-<reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>. It seems they had 200 horse there, but some Rogue of other gave them intelligence of our <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> coming, so they marched away before our men got thither, and went on the other side of the water, and there stood calling of our men <pb n="3" />Rogues, but they could not get to them: In the conclusion, Col. <em>Daniel</em> caused the house to be blown up with the Gunpowder they found there; so that now there will be no nests for them to stay there in any longer. Our Lieutenant had a shot made at him, which <reg orig="mist">missed</reg> him narrowly. Out men <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> themselves very forward, and behaved themselves gallantly.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, 25 February.</i></head>

<p>Several Petitions are by His Highness referred to the Council, and some by the Council to Committees.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A DECLARATION by the Burgomasters of <em>Breda</em>.</i></head>

<p>We do hereby give notice unto all people, before whom these presents shall come, That there is a Fair to be held at <em>Breda</em>, for the selling of Horses, which is to begin on the 13 of <em>March</em>, next ensuing, and to continue for three days. And we do declare, That whosoever shall be judged to have brought the best couple of Horses to be sold, at the said Fair, shall have given as a present from this Town, a Silver <reg orig="Curry-comb">Currycomb</reg>: And whosoever shall be judged to gave brought the second best couple of Horses, shall have given him a pair of <reg orig="wel">well</reg>-wrought Silver Spurs.</p>

<p><i>Breda, 20 Feb. 1654.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the Hague.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>The Peace is now fully concluded by the States General, and four Ambassadors are commissionated to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> it with the Commonwealth of <em>England, viz.</em> The Lord <em>Beverling</em>, a Member of the States General, who is already in <em>England</em>, and the Lord <em>Newport</em>, (who is Lord Receiver of <em>Holland</em>) both of them of the Province of <em>Holland</em>. The Lord <em>Youngstal</em> of <em>Freezland</em>, and the Lord <em>de Yong</em>, one of the <reg orig="Burgo-masters">Burgomasters</reg> of <em>Middleborough</em> in <em>Zealand</em>; which last three went from hence this morning towards <em>Rotterdam</em>, with their attendants; and the Lord <em><reg orig="Yongstals">Yongstal's</reg></em> Lady, and his Daughter, they are to take shipping in <em>Zealand</em>, and so for England <em>speedily</em>.</p>

<p>Here is great joy for Peace, almost <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> seeming to concur in the joy of it, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the English Cavaliers, and the Royal roaring party of this Nation.</p>

<p>The Ministers whose mouths were open very wide against <em>England</em>, reviling them in almost every Sermon, are now almost <pb n="4" />all silent; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Mr. <em>Beaumont</em>, who preacheth to the English Congregation at the <em>Hague</em>, (who spends not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a great part of his Preaching in railing against <em>England</em>, but almost half his Prayer is for the prosperity of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and his party against them;) and sometimes some of the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Chaplains that Preach there, do a little (though not altogether so much) <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> out that way: even Mr. <unclear><em>Lotius</em></unclear>, and Mr. <em>Strezo</em>, at the <em>Hague</em>, also, who was so bitter against the English, now meddles not with them, but are silent.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> who it was feared, would have made some obstruction in this business, are all quiet, no stirs, nor expressions of discontent, but all quiet; so that we are like men even risen up from the dead.</p>

<p>All, both States and Common people, Merchants, Seamen, <reg orig="Laborers">Labourers</reg>, all too full of <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at the Peace, that it is hoped it will be a means of very great Union and Love between both Nations.</p>

<p><i>Hague, 19 alias 29 Feb. 1654.</i></p>

<p><i><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg>, 23 Jan.</i> The King of Poland is returned again to <reg orig="Warsow">Warsaw</reg>, and the Armies were (both <em>Polanders</em> and <em>Cossacks</em>) marching home. The Peace is agreed, but not yet signed, which makes some doubt, whether it may hold or not.</p>

<p><i>Venice, 6 Feb.</i> The General <em>Mocenigo</em> hath received Orders here to levy 6000 <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, by reason many Officers in <em>Candia,</em> desire to be dismissed. The Letters from <em>Rome</em> tell us, that some <em><reg orig="Portuguizes">Portuguese</reg></em> were setting up their <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Arms above the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg>, but the Pope, by Cardinal <em>Este</em>, did forbid them. The King of <em>France</em> hath sent hither for Passes for 6000 horse, to see what he can do upon the Kingdom of <em>Naples</em>. The <reg orig="Viceroy">Vice Roy</reg> there, levies men apace. The Turkish General should have been executed, but his Son hath redeemed his by paying 200000 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Eight.</p>

<p><i>Bressau, 9 Feb.</i> All is referred in <em>Poland</em> until the next meeting, in which there shall be a day for a general meeting of the several Circles; but few of the Provinces seem to be willing to concur with the conditions the King hath made. Some of the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Commissioners have been at <em>Yaner</em> in <em>Silesia</em>, and whereas many of the poor Protestants opposed, the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> have slain divers, and apprehended many.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p><i><reg orig="Basil">Basel</reg>, 10 Feb.</i> The Deputies of the King of <em>France</em>, and those of Count <em>Harcourt</em>, inclines to an Accommodation, so that in all things they well agree. The Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em> continues still the <reg orig="siedge">siege</reg> of <em>Beaufort</em>, and hath sprung another Mine, and hath taken an Half-Moon, but could not keep it, being beaten out again by the <reg orig="besiedged">besieged</reg>. Some Officers that have been taken of the Town say, That the Count <em>de la Zufa</em> wants Ammunition within.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>, 12 Feb.</i> The point of Justice is now ended, the next thing will be to examine the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Capitulation; so that the Diet will end about the last of <em>March</em>, and the rest will be referred to the next meeting at <em><reg orig="Franckfort">Frankfurt</reg></em>. the Earl of <em>Thun</em> is chosen Archbishop of <em><reg orig="Saltzburgh">Salzburg</reg></em>. Their Masques here go on till Lent.</p>

<p><i>Rhine, 17 Feb.</i> Things carry an ill face here; the Duke <em>Neiuburgh</em> levies men in the Land of <em>Gulick</em> and <em>Berg</em>, it is thought against the Elector of <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em>, who puts himself in a posture of defence. The <em>Lorain</em> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> still trouble these parts; there is no hopes of a peace, until we are quit of them.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Cullin">Cologne</reg>, 20 Feb.</i> The Count of <em>Lodren</em> is yet here, and hopes to get part of the 400000 Crowns which the Count of <em>Fuensaldagnia</em> hath received at <em>Antwerp</em>.</p>

<p><i>Hague, 18 alias 28 Feb.</i> Monsieur <em>Stocker</em>, the Deputy from the Protestant Switzers, in order to the further Mediation between the two <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg> who is here, is thought comes to prepare the Mediation about the <em><reg orig="Amboynaes">Amboynes</reg></em> business.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, 26 February.</i></head>

<p>This day came news; that the Dutch Ambassadors were under <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> for <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> his House in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> at <em>Westminster</em> was this day in sitting to e prepared for their Reception.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Certain Positions touching the Worship and Order of the Gospel of Christ in his Churches, as they were <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in a Letter sent from a Justice of Peace in <em>Hertfordshire</em>; necessary for all such as are wishing in this hour of temptation, to stand with the Lamb on Mount Zion.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>Having (through rich Mercy) nigh lost amongst such as sigh for the abominations of Professors in this, and other Countries: Some whereof have dreadfully <reg orig="apostateized">apostatised</reg> from the <pb n="6" />Truth, others from the Worship, Order, and Government of the Gospel; some maintaining all Institutions to be swallowed up into Spirit, others, that they are lost in Antichristian defection; some holding a nullity, others a parity, as if all Members had the same office; the sin foretold by St. <em>Jude</em>, in the eleventh verse of his Epistle.</p>

<p>These things premised, It was upon my heart, to let you know how in this juncture the Lord hath (I hope in faithfulness, to such as fear before him) stirred up the spirit of Mr. <em>Lee</em>, Preacher of the Gospel at <em>Hatfield</em>, in this County, as hitherto against the common enemies of the Civil Interest of this Nation, and their <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg>; so now against the enemies of <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> Interest in Saints, that worship him, and in Ordinances, by which they are built up in that worship: And this not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in his <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Ministry, (under which, <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, with many others, have profitably <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> for this last seven years) but also in private Conferences, and especially in one lately in a solemn meeting; where in the hearing of very many, he laid down these following Theses, for the <reg orig="inlightening">enlightening</reg> of such as profess themselves to be in the dark, as to Churches, Ministry, Seals, and Censures, and for the establishing of others, who through weakness began to stagger.</p>

<head level="3">The Positions were these.</head>

<p>1. <i>Almighty God, hath, and will have his Churches on Earth, to the end of the World,</i> Matth. 16.18. &amp; 28.20.</p>

<p>2. <i>The Father hath committed unto his Son Jesus Christ, the (a) Second Person in the Blessed Trinity, both (b) God and (c) Man, all (d) Power and Judgement over these Churches, and hath appointed him to be a (e) King, a (f) Priest, and a (g) Prophet thereunto, so (h) long as these Churches shall continue here on Earth.</i> (a) Mat. 28.18 1 John 5.7. (b) John 1.1 1 John 5.20. (c) 1 Tim. 2.3,5. Luk. 1.35. (d) Matth. 28 18. John 5.22,27. (e) Psal. 45.6. (f) Psal. 110.4 (g) Acts 1.3,22. (h) 1 Corinth. 15.24.</p>

<p>3. <i>The Lord Jesus doth no <reg orig="onely">only</reg> teach these Churches inwardly, but hath also appointed External Ordinances, viz. (i) Preaching the Word, and Administration of the Seals, and Execution of the Censures, for the edifying his Churches to the (k) end of the World.</i> (i) Matth. 28.19. (k) Matth. 28.<unclear>20</unclear>. 1 Cor. 11.26.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>4. <i>For this Preaching of the Word, and Administration and Seals, and Execution of Censures, Christ hath appointed some (l) select persons, unto whom he hath (m) committed the Ministry of Reconciliation.</i> (l) Cor. 12.38,29. Eph. 4.11. (m) 2 Cor. 5.18.</p>

<p>5. <i>Of these some had a more long (n) Commission, reaching to all Nations, as the Apostles; others were appointed as (o) Patrons and Teachers, to some more (p) particular, and special people, and places.</i> (n) Mark 16.15. (o) 1 Cor. 12.28. (p) Acts 20. 27,28. Col. 1.7. Revel.2.1,8.</p>

<p>6. <i>Those Pastors and Teachers, are Officers of <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> (q) appointment, (r) distinct from the flocks, they teach, and take care of, as the several names given them in Scripture do import. <em>viz.</em> (s) Elders, Stewards, <reg orig="Over-seers">Overseers</reg>, Ministers, Rulers, Ambassadors, Men that must give an account, who are therefore as persons <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> to give themselves wholly to this Work.</i> (q) Ephef. 4.11. 2 Tim. 3.1. (r) Acts 20.28. 1 Pet. 5.2. 1 Tim 3.5. Heb. 13.7, 17. (s) 1 Tim. 5.17. 1 Pet. 5.1,2. Tit.1.7. Ezek. 33.7. 1 Cor. 4.1. Heb. 13.7. 2 Cor.5.20. Revel. 2.1. Heb. 13.17. 1 Tim. 4.12, 15,16.</p>

<p>7. <i>These Officers thus instituted are to continue in the Churches, so long as Christ hath a Gospel to be Preached, Sacraments to be Administered, Saints to be perfected, a Body to be edified, <reg orig="Gain-sayers">Gainsayers</reg> to be convinced, a Flock to be fed, that is to say, To the end of the World.</i></p>

<p>Lastly, <i>Notwithstanding these <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Offices, and Ordinances of Christ; for the edification of the Church, there lieth a duty upon private Christians, within the bounds of private Christians, to teach, and build up one another, as Parents their Children, Masters their Servants, and one Christian another, in the relation to, and communion one with another.</i> Gen. 18.19. Josh. 24.15. 1 Thes. 5.11. Tit. 2.2,3,4.</p>

<p>Such as have felt the weight, and experienced the comfort of these Truths, will not be <reg orig="tost">tossed</reg> with every wind. Consider of them, and whereunto you attain walk: If any be otherwise minded, God will reveal this to them, (if they belong to him) but evil Men, and Seducers, shall wax worse and worse, of whom be you aware. This is the Prayer of (Sir) <i>Your Faithful Friend.</i></p>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 27 February.</i></head>

<p>This day came <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of <reg orig="Mineheir">Mien heir</reg> <em>Newport</em>, and <reg orig="Mineheir">Mien heir</reg> <em>Yongstal</em> Lords Ambassadors appointed and sent to <reg orig="joyne">join</reg> in Commission with <reg orig="Mineheir">Mien heir</reg> <em>Beverling</em> from the States General of the United Provinces, that they were this day come to <em>Dover</em>, from whence they intended to haste to <em>London</em> by the way of <em>Gravesend</em>. They are suddenly to make their Addresses to His Highness about the Ratification of the Peace between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and the United Provinces.</p>

<p>The substance of some of the Articles have been formerly Printed, but because some were not then mentioned, here followeth an Abstract of the whole.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Extract of all the Articles of Peace between the two Commonwealths of <em>England</em> and the <em>Netherlands</em></i></head>

<p>1. That from hence forward there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be a more sure and inviolable Peace, sincere Friendship, and a closer Alliance, and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been ever heretofore, and of their respective Land, Cities and Countries, and of all under their obedience wheresoever, and of what condition soever.</p>

<p>2 That from hence forth all hostility shall cease.</p>

<p>3 That all wrongs and offences suffered either by the one or the other party shall be forgotten; and neither party <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> thereupon. All actions past shall be nulled, except those that shall be done in the British Seas after the time of 12 <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, and from that Sea to the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em> in the time of six weeks, and from thence in the <reg orig="Mediterrenan">Mediterranean</reg> Sea, as far as the line after the time of ten weeks, and at the other side of the line in the time of eight months to be reckoned from the time of the publication of the Peace, and all prizes taken after that time shall be restored.</p>

<p>4 That all the Prisoners of both sides be released without Ransom.</p>

<p>5 That both Commonwealths, shall be confederate Friends to defend one the other against whomsoever.</p>

<p>6 That neither of both shall act against the other, either by Land or by Sea.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<p>7 That the States shall cause restitution to be made of all the ships and goods seized upon the English by the King of <em>Denmark</em>, that are yet in being, as also a full compensation of the worth of those goods that may be sold already, and likewise that all the damages or <reg orig="spoile">spoil</reg> of goods shall be made good to the Owners, by estimation, and when such satisfaction shall be done by the said King, then all hostility shall cease between <em>England</em> and <em>Denmark</em>.</p>

<p>8 That no Inhabitants of either Commonwealth shall assist any <reg orig="Rebell">Rebel</reg> of either with moneys, ships, or victuals.</p>

<p>9 That both Commonwealths shall assist one the other at their proper charges against their Rebels.</p>

<p>10 that neither shall receive those that are, or shall be declared enemies of either Commonwealth.</p>

<p>11 That either Commonwealth having notice by the other that some of their Enemies are in its Dominions, they shall give them warning to depart in 28 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> upon pain of death.</p>

<p>12 That the States shall not suffer any of the Inhabitants of their Dominions to assist the Enemies of <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>13 That the English shall not pay greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> other Nations.</p>

<p>14 That the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships shall strike their Flag before the English in the <em>British</em> Seas.</p>

<p>15 that neither of the Commonwealths shall give retreat to any <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> in any of their Ports.</p>

<p>16 That in case the English or the Dutch make any Treaty with any Prince; they shall therein comprehend each other reciprocally, if they desire it.</p>

<p>17 That in case some hostility should happen between the Inhabitants of both Commonwealths, by one against the other; that the <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> shall <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> hold and remain in full force; and the parties that shall be found guilty shall be punished.</p>

<p>18 That the Subjects of the Commonwealth of England shall freely <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> through all quarters of the United Provinces by water or by land, or into any Cities or <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> thereof, armed or unarmed provided they go not above 40 in a company, either with or without their <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>, and the Subjects of the Netherlands are to have the like <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> in <em>England</em>, and every, <pb n="10" />and all places under their subjection, carrying themselves submissively to the Laws of each Commonwealth.</p>

<p>19 That if it so fall out, that any ships of either State shall by storm or <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> be driven into any of the Havens of the one or the other State, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have liberty to go to Sea again at their pleasure with their ships and goods without paying any Custom, or Impost; provided, that they break not the bulk, behaving themselves according to the laws and customs of the place where they shall take <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg>.</p>

<p>20 That no Merchants or <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> of one or the other Commonwealth, shall have their goods ships, or <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> arrested in any of the havens, or rivers of either Commonwealth to serve at war, or otherwise, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any general or particular command, except it be upon some inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction, not including herein, the Arrests by ordinary Courts of Justice.</p>

<p>21 That the Merchants and their Factors, and Servants, and the <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> may travel and turn back again to their ships from the Seas, Waters, and Havens of the one and the other Commonwealth, and at their landing may use for defence of themselves, and their goods all sorts of Arms offensive and defensive, save only, that being come to their <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg>, they shall lay their Arms aside until they return into their ships again.</p>

<p>22 That men of war of both Commonwealths, or Merchants ships meeting together at Sea, they shall defend each other against all whomsoever that shall offer to make any attempt upon either of them, so long as they sail on course.</p>

<p>23 That if any ship or ships of either <reg orig="Republick">Republic</reg>, or of a <reg orig="newtrality">neutrality</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> by a third party be taken out of the Havens or Dominions of either Commonwealth, both parties shall be engaged to follow the business for the restitution of the ships and goods to the owners.</p>

<p>24 That the Searchers, and other such Officers in the execution of their Office <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> regulate themselves according to the laws or each Country, and take no more of any, then is permitted them by their Instructions.</p>

<p>25 that if one party shall cause some damages to the other there shall be no Letters of <reg orig="Reprisall">Reprisal</reg> given; But if in three <pb n="11" />Months time, no satisfaction is done, then the said Letters may be granted.</p>

<p>26 That all persons of either Commonwealth going to Sea with particular Commissions (before their Commissions be granted) they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be obliged by sufficient sureties, before the Judges of the Court where they receive their Commissions (that have no part nor portion in the said ships) That they shall do no damage to any Subjects of either Commonwealth.</p>

<p>27 that no more but eight ships of War shall be suffered to come or remain in the Ports of each others Commonwealth at one time: and when there shall be occasion for a greater number, then the consent must first be asked.</p>

<p>28 That the States shall do Justice upon those that shall be found alive, that have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in <em>Amboyna</em>.</p>

<p>29 Lastly, That there shall be Commissioners established to examine the wrongs or injuries done, or pretended to be done or suffered by the Inhabitants of either Commonwealth in the <em>East-Indies, Greenland, Muscovey, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>, or other places. And if the Commissioners cannot agree thereupon within the time of three months. Then the aforesaid differences to be referred to the Judgement of the Protestant <em>Switzers</em>.</p>

<p>This day were three men and a woman hanged upon a Gallows in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg> against the <reg orig="Grey-hound">Greyhound</reg> Tavern door, where they hanged from about 11 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> until about 3 in the afternoon, for robbing of the said Vintner, whom they dangerously wounded. And four men and a woman were hanged at Tiburn the same day for several other facts.</p>

<p>Letters from <em><reg orig="Winsor">Windsor</reg></em> say that Mr. <em>Feak</em>, and Mr. <em>John Simson</em> are still there, well in health, and have been visited not only by <reg orig="complementall">complemental</reg> Visitors, but some godly friends of theirs have been advised to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to be sensible of their late mistakes. There is one at <em><reg orig="Winsor">Windsor</reg></em> belonging to the Ammunition that had <reg orig="imbezeled">embezzled</reg> some of the Powder, and being taken carrying it away, was apprehended, and is sentenced to ride upon a <!--??-->Saker, when it is shot off with an <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> charge.</p>

<p><i><em>Leith</em> in <em>Scotland</em> Febr. 21. The Lord <em>Athol</em>, the Lord <em>Bruce</em> and others have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> what forces they can get together, and are marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Glencairn, Kenmore, <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> and the rest, <pb n="12" />upon whose conjunction they, threaten to be revenged of Col. <em>Morgan</em> for the last rout, and perhaps he may make them amends with such another. Yet <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Foot are much discontented and leave him daily, complaining much of the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their Horse, so that now they have few Foot but only Runagadoes from the Lowlands. They have taken off the Roof from the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Weems</em>, and intend now to keep no <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> but run the same courses that <em>Montross</em> did, and keep their Ammunition in Woods, or little Villages in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 28 February.</i></head>

<p>Letters came from <em>France</em>, which say there is great longings there for a Peace with <em>England</em>, and that Letters were sent from the King to his Agent here, who it is thought hath a new Commission to enlarge his power here.</p>

<p>There hath lately been some meetings of godly Ministers about <em>London</em>, to consider of a way of union and reconciliation of the differences that unhappily have crept in among the godly, and other things in order to the <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> of the Gospel.</p>

<p>And this day Mr. <em>Owen</em>, Mr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, Mr. <em>Sydrack Simon</em>, Mr. <em>Nie</em>, and divers other Reverend pious Ministers were with His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>This day came Letters that the L. Ambassadors from the United Provinces were upon their way from <em>Dover</em> towards <em>Gravesend</em>.</p>

<p>Newcastle 23 Febr. <i>The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> had troubled us and taken some Vessels that went from hence; but since Cap. <em>Wetwang</em> came in to these parts he hath scoured these coasts of them, and they <reg orig="sculk">skulk</reg> further North, but he met with one of them, a <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> of <em>Horne</em>, that had taken some of our small vessels, and put out her own guns into them for their guard Holland-ward, and so was without in this vessel. And another <reg orig="Pickeroon">Picaroon</reg> Capt. <em>Wetwang</em> fought with and sunk, and there is a ship of six guns, and 48 prisoners sent in and other prize. But the news of a Peace with <em>Holland</em> will be welcome news here.</i></p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Ireland</em> is certified; that the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em> and the Commissioners there are well, that there is now little appearance of an enemy save what are packing away beyond Sea. Some things were at first by a few scrupled about the late change; But the return gave full satisfaction, and they are very unanimous.</p>

<p>This day an Ambassador from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> came <pb n="13" /> to <em>London</em>, and made his application to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Council, and it was ordered that he should have audience of the morrow, and Orders were issued out to Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies to attend the said Ambassador to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter out of the County of <em>Oxford</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>You know we want honest men to rule here, and such as are here to be defended, for to our <reg orig="griefe">grief</reg> we find that some good men have lately bee so wronged and openly affronted, and secretly undermined for appearing in honest causes and for good people (by those whose tongues are no slander, and love to <reg orig="brawle">brawl</reg> it out and carry the bell, and steep in a whole skin) that they are wearied out, and have no <unclear>heart</unclear> to act against such opposition, but rather to suffer wrongfully. But we shall find the want of such here, who was, and would have been a good check to the domineering of some, and a shelter to others. But God will still maintain the cause of his righteous ones, as hitherto he hath done, and deliver them out of the hands of all their Enemies, which shall be our prayers to God,</i></p>

<p>Your assured Friends to serve you and yours,</p>

<p>Tuesday 21 Feb. 1653. At seven of the clock at night Richard Luckin of Dives-Hall in the County of Essex Esq; was robbed of 700 li. in money 4 or 5 silver slip Spoons, one silver Preserving-Ladle with a round <reg orig="Bowle">Bowl</reg> punched with four rows of holes, and a fork at the other end of the handle; and a short Black Rapier with a black <reg orig="Horse-hair">Horsehair</reg> handle. The <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> one was a slender man with a thin Face full of <reg orig="Pockholes">Pock holes</reg>, his <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> was a white close <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> Coat and Breeches. Another was a <reg orig="Wel">Well</reg>-set man with a black bushy Hair, and a cast with his <reg orig="eie">eye</reg>, he was in a Liver-<reg orig="coulored">coloured</reg> Coat and Breeches. Another Young man with flaxen Hair and a round Face. Another was in a white loose <reg orig="Horse-mans">Horseman's</reg> Coat girt to him. Any that can, are desired to give notice of some of these or their Companions to Mr. Beachamp Goldsmith at the Rose in Cheap side, or Mr. Flatman Scrivener in Chancery-Lane, and they shall have 50 s. for their reward. The Spoons were marked with L R E</p>

<p>Upon addresses made to his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, by the Magistrates of the City of Westminster, touching a well-ordering of the Government thereof, there hath been <reg orig="severall">several</reg> meetings and debates thereon, and because it is of concernment to them, and also that the City of London is concerned therein; the said City hath also been heard therein. And to <pb n="14" />the end that there may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> with the union and content of both Cities. It was Ordered that the City of London, and the City of Westminster should both <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent for, and heard together on the morrow, by such as should come from the said Cities.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> is about a Corporation desired by those of the City of Westminster, who have long sued for it; desiring that they may have power to keep that City in Order, as other considerable places in this Commonwealth have.</p>

<p>Addresses have been made to his Highness the Lord Protector, by <em>Will: Lenthall</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; formerly Speaker of the Parliament, Tho: <em>Pury</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; and divers other Gentlemen from the City of <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>; who in the name, and under the seal of the said Town, and signed by the Magistrates thereof, presented to his Highness a Declaration congratulatory, blessing the Lord for this established Government, and protesting much affection thereto.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 1 March 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lord Mayor of the City of London, and the Recorder of the said City, on the party of the City of London, and divers Magistrates of the City of Westminster, according to an Order sent to them, came to attend his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, at the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> chamber in Whitehall; and this day were heard touching the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> for a Corporation to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> granted to the City of Westminster, and something therein, it is probable will shortly <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done.</p>

<p>Instructions were given for suppressing of a wicked sort of people called Hectors, and <reg orig="Playes">Plays</reg>, and other wicked disorders; and larger power will bee given if need require. </p>

<p>Divers godly Christians out of Hertfordshire, made their application this day to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by a Petition for the placing of a godly Minister.</p>

<p>The two Ambassadors from Holland, the Lords <em>Newport</em> and <em>Yongstal</em>, that are come to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Lord <em>Beverling</em>, are now at Gravesend, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> the Master of the Ceremonies hath orders to receive them on Friday morning next; at which time they are to come from Gravesend to the Tower hill, and from thence, Coaches will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> appointed to bring them and their attendants through the Cities of London and Westminster <pb n="15" />to Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> house in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>-yard at <em>Westminster</em>. The Gates of which house are new Painted, and the house newly fitted for their Reception, until they have Audience, and upon their dispatch therein, they are to provide themselves a place; which it is probable will York-house in the <em>Strand</em>, which their Agent is about, and likely to go through for.</p>

<p>An Ambassador Extraordinary from the Archduke <em><reg orig="Leopald">Leopold</reg></em>, according to the order the day before, had this day Audience by His Highness the Lord Protector, being conducted by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies. He did congratulate His Highness, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> his Credentials.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is much troubled at the Peace with <em>Holland</em>. An Agent is sent from him to the Pope. The French Agent hath bespoke 40 Beds, and is taking an house for an Ambassador from that King. There are many things charged upon the Duke of <em>Lorain</em>; the younger Brother, with <em>Spain</em>, and <em>Gonti</em> with <em>France</em>, are like to posses the Heritages.</p>

<p>the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> proceedings with the Swedish Queen are private: All demands of the Swedish Merchants are taken in in<!--repetition occurs in text--> love; and it is believed there will be a fair agreement after a while.</p>

<p>Since the routing of <em>Glencairn</em> by Col. <em>Morgan</em>, the Lowlanders are now quiet, and the present <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> forces do <reg orig="straiten">straighten</reg> their quarters more Northward.</p>

<p>There is upon the matter no field enemy in <em>Ireland</em>, all being quiet, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some few that rob and plunder in small parties as <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg>, which always they used to do: There wants <reg orig="onely">only</reg> people to plant the Country.</p>

<p>there was among other Books lately one called a Catechism with Texts of Scriptures, by <em><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Biddle</em>, M.A. Which (<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> a Letter from a Reverend Minister to me) is <reg orig="stuft">stuffed</reg> full of, and indeed the heads of the Socinian and <reg orig="Arminian">Armenian</reg> Doctrine, closely couched under Scripture phrases; and thereupon perusing of it, I <reg orig="finde">find</reg> the <reg orig="sallacious">salacious</reg> cunning lies in the Questions: But I desire all my Friends to take notice of this, that I do not insert the Books weekly mentioned, because I approve of them; but being permitted to be Printed, I do <reg orig="onely">only</reg> give notice, that there are such Books come out at the Stationers desire.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>The Mystery of the two Witnesses <reg orig="unvailed">unveiled</reg>. Wherein we have a description of their persons, time, acts, death, office, manner of <reg orig="prophecie">prophecy</reg>, sufferings and resurrection, with the Consequences that follow. By Joh Robotham, Preacher of the Gospel in Dover. Sold by G. and H. Eversden, at the Greyhound in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<p>Britannia Triumphalis, Or a <reg orig="briefe">brief</reg> History of the Wars and other State Affairs of great <reg orig="Britaine">Britain</reg> from the death of the late King to the dissolution of the last Parliament. Sold by Sam. Howes, at his shop in <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg>-head-Alley.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Greatnesse">Greatness</reg> of the Mystery of <reg orig="Godlinesse">Godliness</reg>, opened in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Sermons by Cuthbert Sydenham late Teacher to a Church of Christ in Newcastle. Sold by Ri. Tomlins at the Sun and Bible near Pie Corner.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>