<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState225">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 225</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 12 of <em>January.</em> To Thursday the 19 day of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 12. January. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> things of great concernment under consideration, as about one that is in custody for forging the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> name in <em>Buckinghamshire</em>, and suggestions about pretence of a private way of a Parliament, and other abuses; and other considerable <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg> January 2.</i> The <em>Elias</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come safe into this harbour, and brought us six months pay which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> were in arrears, other news, all being quiet, this place affords not any.</p>

<p>Major Gen. <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em> and Commissary General <em><reg orig="Whaleys">Whaley's</reg></em> Regiments of Horse, are to go for <em>Scotland</em>, and Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment of foot are to march into the County of <em>York</em>.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>The <em>Declaration</em> of <em>John Manley</em>, <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with the manage of the Posts, for the better establishing of the same.</i></head>

<p>Whereas I am <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, with the manage of the Posts of this Nation: These are to Declare to all Gentlemen, Merchants and others, whom it may concern, That I have established the places <reg orig="undernamed">under named</reg> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> for the receipts of Letters, as well those that <reg orig="goe">go</reg> to <em>Oxford, Cambridge, Southampton, Winchester, Lyn, Yarmouth, Norwich</em>, and the places upon those Roads, as to any of the other Roads of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; and to that end have contracted with such as are to receive them, as also with all Letter carriers in and about the City of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by <reg orig="mee">me</reg> for the purposes aforesaid; so that no man within the City or Suburbs, will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> necessitated to give them more <reg orig="then">than</reg> what his Letters shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> justly taxed at, according to the Rates established by the State, hereunder written.</p>

<p>And because I have determined upon no pretence whatsoever to countenance any of my Agents in their miscarriages; I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby promise upon reasonable notice of any abuse or exaction in that particular, to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> all persons that <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> right which the nature of their complaints may justly challenge from me, who shall make it my <reg orig="endevour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in all things serviceable to the Interests of those persons whose concernments <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through my hands.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Rates of Letters</i></head>

<p>To any place within 80 miles distance, 2d. a single Letter, 4 d. a double Letter. To a farther distance 3d. a single Letter, 6d. a double Letter. To <em>Scotland</em> 4d. a single Letter, 8d. a double Letter. To <em>Ireland</em> 6. A single Letter, 12d. a double Letter. And so proportionably for treble or greater packets of Letters, to any of the former places.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Places where Letters may be left.</i></head>

<p>Mr. <em>Genn</em> at Westminster Gate, Mr. <em>Adams</em> at the Savoy Gate, Mr. <em>Tyser</em> at the three Daggers in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>. <pb n="2" />Mr. <em>Humphreys</em> at the two Sugar loaves in <em><reg orig="Fanchurchstreet">Fenchurch Street</reg></em>, Mr. <em>Hall</em> at the <reg orig="Booksellers">Bookseller's</reg> shop at <em>Russel street end in Covent Garden</em>: Mr. <em>Netherwood</em> Pewterer at the 3 Foxes in <em>Long-Lane</em>: Mr. <em>Gregson</em> next door to the White Lion in <em>Wapping</em>: Mr. <em>Hutchins</em> at the White Hart at <em><reg orig="Charing">Charring</reg> <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg></em>: Mr. <em>Best</em> at <reg orig="Grayes">Gray's</reg> <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg> Gate, Mr. <em>Taylor</em> in Temple Lane, Mr is. <em>Smith</em> next door to the Cock in <em>Ratcliffe</em>.</p>

<p>It is declared that for the better conveyance, all persons will be pleased to give their Letters full directions to the places and Counties as shall be <reg orig="needfull">needful</reg>, to prevent mistakes.</p>

<p><i>London 12 Janua. 1653. John Manley.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 13 January 1653.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Holland</em> came as followeth, <em>viz.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Hague 30 Decemb. (alias 9 January 1653.)</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>Here hath again been a great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to this Country, both by fire and water, and all occasioned by a great storm of wind last Tuesday, all day and all night. But the first cause is <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> the wrath of God against this Country, which is so evident that <reg orig="truely">truly</reg> <reg orig="every body">everybody</reg> <reg orig="feeles">feels</reg> it, and few that have any grace, but will <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> it also: But are still as ignorant, how to pacify this anger of the Lord, as if they never had had <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Word amongst them.</p>

<p>It is true, the common sins of Pride, <reg orig="Whoredome">Whoredom</reg>, <reg orig="Drunkennesse">Drunkenness</reg>, and <reg orig="Excesse">Excess</reg>, are generally <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out against, as the cause of all out Miseries, and <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> these sins do much provoke the Lord, being come to so great a height in this Country: But these sins are too common to all Nations, especially in prosperity; and <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> the wiser sort do find fault with one another, <em>Adam</em> and <em>Eve</em> like, but very few that lay these things to heart, so as to say, this <reg orig="sinne">sin</reg> of mine is a cause, and so forsake the same.</p>

<p>The Ministers (though too carnal God knows) as the most <pb n="3" />seeing part of the Country, and by their Office, and interest thereunto instigated, cry out not only against these common sins, but also against the too much sufferance of Popery, and their Idolatry, and indeed the Popish <reg orig="Masse">Mass</reg>, and that Idolatry is so <reg orig="publick">public</reg> and frequent, that certainly it much provokes God to wrath, yea, some think about half the Country are Papists, and that there are more Priests and Jesuits, <reg orig="then">than</reg> Preachers of the Gospel; that turn many daily from the true Religion, and yet no course taken by the Protestant Magistrates, to increase and <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> the Preachers and Defenders of true Religion: and divers other miscarriages of the Magistrates; but no complaints against themselves, as if they had no share in these sins that hath so provoked <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath against this Country.</p>

<p>The Magistrates also, they see no sins of their own, but what is ordinary to all states, and they talk of the sins of the people in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>, and exhort the people to a better life, to remove <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath, as you may see in their Proclamation for a Fast day, soon after the last fight with the English fleet before the Texell and the Mase; but not a word will the <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> of their miscarriages and Government; though in private, every Magistrate complains of other, as they are divided into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> factions; but where find <reg orig="wee">we</reg> one complainer under the guilt of their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> sins?</p>

<p>The People also they complain, both of Magistrates and Ministers, every <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Religion complaining of other, and that for their miscarriage and Errors, <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath is thus hot against them: And the people of each <reg orig="severall">several</reg> faction against their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> Preachers, as cold, <reg orig="carnall">carnal</reg>, and seeking the things of this life in good earnest, both for themselves and their choice (whilst they <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> others to deny themselves and <unclear>forsake</unclear> them) being divers of them both gluttons and drunkards, and <unclear>daily at feasts</unclear> and weddings; bestowing their time with great <unclear>men</unclear>, and at Recreations; when it is hard for <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> men with <reg orig="intreaty">entreaty</reg> to get a little of their company, even when they <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> a dying.</p>

<p>Of the Magistrates also the people complain, as Gluttons and Drunkards, being daily at one feast or other, and oft going drunk home, many of them neglecting the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service, and <reg orig="mispending">misspending</reg> and wasting the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> stock, and still exacting more and <pb n="4" />more upon the people, <reg orig="inriching">enriching</reg> in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> their own families, so vastly, that many are accused for Thefts of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Treasury, and the one conniving at the other therein, so as no justice can <reg orig="bee">be</reg> had against them, that the whole Country is so full of complaints every one of his Neighbour, (and scarce <reg orig="any body">anybody</reg> of themselves) as is incredible.</p>

<p>But not a word from any shall you hear of their great sins against their brethren of <em>England</em> spoken of.</p>

<p>Yea they are so far from repenting thereof; That on the contrary the English are so daily railed upon, as the veriest Rogues, <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg>, and Devils that ever were in the world, by almost all sorts of people; That go you into <em>France, Spain</em>, or <em>Rome</em> <reg orig="it selfe">itself</reg>, you shall not hear so wild language against the English in any Nation and yet I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> in the end they will find that their malignity against their Brethren of <em>England</em> hath been a <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> sin that hath brought this great wrath of God upon this Country, which I pray God they may see and repent of, before it be too late.</p>

<p>For when they saw the Government of <em>England</em> divided, the King, his Popish Queen, all the Papists, Bishops and wickedest Rout of <em>England</em> on the one party; and the Parliament, with almost all of the Professors of true Religion, both in <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em> on the other party: it was not hard for any that feared God to know which side they should <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg>; For though the King, as a King ought to have been <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> and obeyed, and for my part I should never have opposed him as such, but have taken his side, and opposed the Parliament, if they had done as he did: Yet to see the Popish ceremonies so daily increasing, Popery and Papists <reg orig="favored">favoured</reg> and advanced, the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Nuncio residing in <em>England</em>, and all professors of true Religion so persecuted, and discountenanced. I say it was no hard thing for any that feared God to know which side to cleave unto; and as you see the eyes of all, both in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, were so clearly opened, that they refused to be governed any longer by the King, but <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together against him as a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> enemy to true Religion, and the true good of these Nations; Against whom <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the K. all the Papists in all Countries, either in word or deed, no otherwise <reg orig="then">than</reg> if it had been a war for Popery.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>When behold our good <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> of the united Provinces, from whom we expected more assistance <reg orig="then">than</reg> from any Nation (and had good reason so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, they having been much beholding to <em>England</em> and the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Rulers, being of the Protestant Religion.)</p>

<p>Behold I say how they sided with the King and Popish party, against all the Professors of <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, and did them more hurt <reg orig="then">than</reg> all the Nations of <em>Europe</em>, as I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg>. I know this will be thought very strange to some, for say they, the Prince and the States were Neutral, and held themselves indifferent, and would offend neither &amp;c.</p>

<p>But if they had not so much fear of God, as to have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the Parliament, to advance true Religion, but would needs have been Neutral; they should have kept themselves Neutrals as <em>Holland</em> at first had resolved, and neither have let King nor Parliament had any <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, &amp;c. for that had been greatly to the advantage of the Parliament, the King having no <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> almost, and the Parliament having all the <reg orig="Magazeins">Magazines</reg> in their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> hands; but no, this Order might not hold, but a new Order made, that both should be suffered to have what Swords, and Spears, (Guns, Shot and Powder) they pleased, to kill and slay one another, and to foment a <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, and it was done accordingly. Whereas otherwise the war had soon been at an end.</p>

<p>So besides, ships of <reg orig="Amunition">Ammunition</reg> privately sent away to foment the War: The <reg orig="Queene">Queen</reg> was <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> sent over in the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships, and three sips of Ammunition with her, which were landed at <em>Burlington</em>, and there by <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> <em>Tromp</em> defended in landing, against the ships of the Parliament, so as all came safe to Land; where with a whole Army was raised in the North, and divers Towns and Forts taken from the Parliament, to the great <reg orig="strengthning">strengthening</reg> of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Party, and <reg orig="indangering">endangering</reg> of the Parliaments.</p>

<p>Also the States sending over Ambassadors under <pb n="6" />pretence of mediating a peace between the King and Parliament; What did they, but upon all occasions advance the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Party, and understanding from both, all the secrets, and how things stood? <reg orig="Joyned">Joined</reg> still with the weaker side to foment the War, and at last <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> before they went away, Printed at <em>London</em> a Declaration in <em>English</em>, in <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> of the King against the Parliament, declaring to all the world, and especially to the City of <em>London</em>. That the fault of the War lay on the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> side, and that the King, as it were, was a good man, and would fain make peace; which was done at such a time, when the City of <em>London</em> would fain have had peace, that it put all in such danger, and <em><reg orig="Londons">London's</reg></em> discontent being hereby increased, had like to have risen against the Parliament, and endangered all; and the Parliament at present forced to put up this, and many other injuries for want of power, &amp;c.</p>

<p>And now though the Dutch could perhaps be content again to <reg orig="over-reach">overreach</reg> <em>England</em> by policy or power, or to have their end, if they could attain it, to carry on their own interest in the <reg orig="ruines">ruins</reg> of <em>England</em>; yet the Lord from Heaven hath so shaken them, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> by three times being beaten at Sea by the English in one year, and their whole Fleets routed; but the Lord from Heaven by storms and tempest, hath this last Winter twice miserably shattered them, besides the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> hand in the first storm by Water, and in this latter fire, hath so troubled them, that there is a probability they will seek peace, which will be welcome to many poor distressed souls: And believe it, the loss in the last storm was great, both by loss of above 30 ships in the <em>Texel</em>, and as many more in several other places, and many a brave ship pitifully shattered and broken; and some Merchant ships cast away coming home from <em>Denmark</em>. We look for the return of our Deputies from <em>England</em>, and then I shall have occasion to give you further advertisements of some things now under debate, by the States General, in order to an Agreement with <em>England</em>, accordingly as they shall like the Message they bring home with them.</p>

<p>This day the Officers of the Army held a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, for the punishing of Drunkenness, and other <reg orig="misdemeanors">misdemeanours</reg> in the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p><i>Saturday, 14 January.</i></p>

<p>This day the Lord Protector had private Consultations with his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at the <em><reg orig="Cock-pit">Cockpit</reg></em>; and a Committee of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Dover, 13 Jan. 1653. <i>W have several ships out in several parts, for securing the English Merchants in and out, which makes us now to hear little of the <em>Brest</em> men: And our Fleet with General <em>Pen</em> in the Channel, is ready for action, if the Dutch do not agree. The French are not a little troubled to hear there is such probability: But there was a sad accident <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> the Protestants in <em>France</em>, the last Sunday; for so soon as the Exercises were done at <em>Charington</em>, the place where the Protestants meet about two Leagues from <em>Paris</em>, many of them were cast away in a Boat coming home towards <em>Paris</em>. It seems there useth to go a Passage-Boat between <em>Paris</em> and that Church, to carry those that cannot well go on foot so far, and return with them when the Ordinances are over: and this Boat returning home with them on the last Sunday, there being in it about a hundred persons, and of them divers were whole Families; so soon as they were in the Boat almost, it being but newly put off, near a Mill, which was then going, they were by the stream forced under the Mill; which coming too near it, did suck them in, and about sixty of them are drowned; and amongst them two Lords, sons of that pious Protestant <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg>, the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> of <em>Mirambo</em>, and others of quality; which doth very much trouble the Protestants, and is no small sorrow to them, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the loss of those Godly and Religious Protestants with their Children, that were then drowned, but also because of the ill use the Papists make of it; both which is a great affliction to them. Yet this is observable, That some of them hath lately had too much tampering with <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> him some kindness and countenance the last <em>Christmas</em>.</i></p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Wales</em>, and also from several parts of <em>England</em>, is certified, the Magistrates freeness, and <reg orig="chearfulness">cheerfulness</reg> in proclaiming the Lord Protector; as also from <em>Yorkshire</em>, and the Northern Counties, <em>York, Hull, Durham, <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em>, and the rest.</p>

<p>We hear by Letters from several parts of the free Subscriptions of the Officers of the several Regiments and Garrisons, generally in all parts, declaring to stand by His Highness, and that <pb n="8" />they are preparing Addresses to His Highness to that purpose, and are signing the same.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday 16 January.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commissioners for the Admiralty and Navy.</i></head>

<p>Upon consideration had of the Results of a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> or War, held aboard the <em>Swift sure</em>, in the Fleet, the first of <em>December</em> 1653. concerning the Prize-money due to Seamen and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that have served at Sea in this last years Expedition, It is hereby Declared and Ordered as followeth.</p>

<p>1 That all Seamen and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that have served in the Fleet in the three last Engagements against the <em>Dutch</em>, and shall list themselves aboard any of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Ships, at or before the last of <em>March</em> next, shall have for their respective shares of Prizes, twenty shillings,</p>

<p>2 That such as have been in two of the said Engagements <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have thirteen shillings four pence.</p>

<p>3 That those who served <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in one of the said Engagements, shall have six shillings eight pence.</p>

<p>4 That all such Seamen and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> as have been disabled by sickness, or wounds received in the Service: As also the widows of any such Seamen or <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, slain in any of the said Engagements, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have paid unto them their full shares of Prize money, <em>viz.</em> twenty shillings.</p>

<p>5 That such of the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> as are now again entertained in the Army (having Tickets for their Prize-money) do produce unto the said Commissioners, a Certificate under the hand of the Captain, under which they now serve: As also a copy of the last Muster-<reg orig="Rol">Roll</reg> of the Companies to which they respectively belong, or default thereof, a Certificate under the hand of the Muster-master, testifying their being in the Service; whereupon Order shall be given for payment of the shares of Prizes due unto them.</p>

<p><i>John Disbrow, George <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg>, Rob. Blake. Vin: Gookin, John Stone, John Clerk. Robert Blackborne <em>Secret:</em></i></p>

<p>By Letters from General <em>Pen</em> dated aboard the <em>Swift-sure</em> in the Road of St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> the 9. Instant was certified the good condition of the English Fleet.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<p>By Letters from on board the Swift-sure dated the 11 of <em>January</em> 1653. was certified the examinations of some <reg orig="foreigne">foreign</reg> ships that came in to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> Market for <reg orig="Deales">Deals</reg>, Pitch, Tar, Iron, <reg orig="Steele">Steel</reg> and other Commodities, an extract of which <reg orig="followes">follows</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Extract out of the Examination of <reg orig="foreigne">foreign</reg> ships, the same taken on board the <em>Swift-sure</em>, 11 Jan. 1653.</i></head>

<p>1 The <em>Golden Mawken</em> of <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, a ship <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with large <reg orig="Deales">Deals</reg>, Masts, Iron, Pitch, and Tar, of which <em>Hans Benson</em> is Master, which said ship is gone into <em>Portsmouth</em> to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> market, she came in voluntarily into the Road.</p>

<p>2 The <em>Katherine</em> of <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg> having 18 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of Tar, 1200 great Deals, 11 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of Iron, 100 great <reg orig="Sparrs">Spars</reg>, going into <em>Portsmouth</em> to find Market, she came into the Road voluntarily, commanded by <em>John Jorgorson</em> the Master.</p>

<p>3 The ship called the <em>St. John of Lubeck</em>, having 6500 <reg orig="Deales">Deals</reg>, and some Pipe staves, of which <em>Joachim Niemeger</em> is Master, she is sent into <em>Portsmouth</em> to find Market, she came into the Road voluntarily.</p>

<p>4 The <em>St. John of <reg orig="Dantzig">Danzig</reg></em>, a ship having in her 800 Pipe staves, about 1000 li. weight of Hemp, 12 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of Pitch, and 12 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of Tar, 6000 li. weight of Lead, 6000 l. weight of Iron, 5000 l: weight of <reg orig="Steele">Steel</reg>, which ship was bound for <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg> in <em>France</em> (as was pretended, <em>George Vosse</em> is Master of her) which ship is at present in the Road of <em>Portsmouth</em>, desirous of demission rather than <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, she was met with at Sea, and there taken and sent in by the Adventure <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Breviate of <em>Hannah</em> whom some call a <reg orig="Prophetesse">Prophetess</reg> in <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</i></head>

<p>There is one <em>Hannah</em> a Maid that lives at <em>Hackney</em> near the City of <em>London</em>, the same that was formerly at <em>Dunbar</em>, a Member of Mr. <em>John <reg orig="Simpsons">Simpson's</reg></em> Church (as is said) who lives at one Mr. <em><reg orig="Roberts">Robert's</reg></em> an Ordinary in <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>; to whom many hundreds do daily come to see and hear, who hath now been there about a fortnight: Those that look to her, and use to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> with her, <reg orig="sayes">says</reg> she neither eateth nor drinketh, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> sometimes a <reg orig="Tost">Toast</reg> and drink, and that she is in a Trance, and some say that <pb n="10" /> what she doth is by a mighty inspiration, others say they suppose her to be of a troubled, and people flocking to her so as they <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, causeth her to continue this way, and some say worse, so <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> gives their opinions as they please. But this is visible to those that see and hear her.</p>

<p>1 That she is well in flesh in her hands and face, and seemingly lusty and strong; she hath Rings upon her fingers, and <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> in a bed continually in a Room where she is looked to.</p>

<p>2 She speaks to <reg orig="no body">nobody</reg>, but they that are about her, call it lying in Trance; she lies as if she was continually asleep, save only when she <reg orig="prayes">prays</reg>, sings, or drinks and <reg orig="eates">eats</reg> the <reg orig="Tost">Toast</reg>, only she breaths, and sometimes she turns <reg orig="her selfe">herself</reg> in her bed, and sometimes cover <reg orig="her selfe">herself</reg>, but most often others, some say, doth it.</p>

<p>3 In the afternoon (most commonly) every day she <reg orig="prayes">prays</reg> and sings, <reg orig="begining">beginning</reg> about that <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> time that folk have dined, and continues sometimes two or three hours, sometimes <reg orig="foure">four</reg> or five hours never ceasing, but praying or singing until she hath finished for that time, and then <reg orig="seaceth">ceaseth</reg>, not speaking to <reg orig="any body">anybody</reg>, nor praying, nor singing until the next day again.</p>

<p>4 Her custom is to pray sometimes an <reg orig="houre">hour</reg>, and sometimes two hours, and then sings two <reg orig="Hymnes">Hymns</reg> in two several Tunes, and then <reg orig="prayes">prays</reg> again, and sometimes sings again; sometimes oftener and sometimes fewer times; she is heard and understood very plainly by all when she <reg orig="prayes">prays</reg>, but when <reg orig="shee">she</reg> sings, very little is to be understood what she <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>.</p>

<p>5 Her prayers are in exceeding good method and order, good language, and such as indeed all that come <reg orig="doe">do</reg> much admire what they hear from her, excellent words, and well placed; such as are not ordinary.</p>

<p>6 Her matter is various, full of variety; for the Lord Protector, that God would keep him close to <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, as he hath hitherto, so <reg orig="stil">still</reg> to have his heart set upon the things of the Lord, not to be vain, nor regard earthly pomp and pleasure, and things below; but the things of God and his People, that he may be delivered from <reg orig="carnall">carnal</reg> <reg orig="Councels">Counsels</reg>, and being seduced to please the men of the world, and those that seek <reg orig="unrighteousnesse">unrighteousness</reg>, that he may not leave the <reg orig="councel">counsel</reg> of the Godly, to hearken to those who are worldly wise, and earthly Politicians, but wise in the <pb n="11" />Wisdom of God. That the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, whom God hath made Instrumental to overcome the enemy without, and in the world, may not be overcome of their inward spiritual enemies, to provoke God to lay them aside, and make use of others in the perfecting of that work, in which God hath so far employed them. That the Merchants of this Nation would not so far seek and <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> their great profit by Trade at Sea, to fill their own Warehouses and Bags and be great in the world, as thereby to provoke an ungodly and wicked peace with the Dutch, to the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of God, and <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> of the carrying on of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> work. That the people of God may not (as some of them have done) revile and <reg orig="scandalize">scandalise</reg> the Lord Protector behind his back, and speak reproachful words against him to others; (for, that she pleaded before the Lord, was not the way of God;) but to deal faithfully and plainly with him, and go to him privately, to speak of those things to himself <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, according to the Rule of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Word, wherein they are offended in <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> with him, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that he doth; and that there may be love among the Saints and people of God. That the Lord would cause the people of this Nation to leave their sins and profaneness, As <reg orig="Gentlewomens">Gentlewomen's</reg> black Spots and Patches, Powderings of Hair, Gold and Silver-Lace, and other wickedness; and that she did believe God hath some of his Elect even among such, and prayed to God for their conversion. That the Lord will cause witches, and such as by false delusions seek to delude the people, to be discovered and suppressed; that troubled spirits may be comforted, and believe; and consider, that the Lord doth call such to come and reason with him; and that he will make their Scarlet and Crimson sins as Snow, and as Wool; and that the Saints and people of God would <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> in the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> goodness to them. Consider, over what a Red-Sea and <em>Jordan</em>, he hath led them, and brought them into his Heavenly <em>Canaan</em>, where is no defilement, but all glorious, and peace.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 17 January.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dublin</em> in <em>Ireland</em>, was this day certified, That Lieut. Gen. <em>Fleetwood</em> and the Commissioners, are at <em>Dublin</em>. All is quiet there, and content at the New Government in <em>England</em>, and satisfied in it. That the Lord <em>Musgrave</em> is to be tried <pb n="12" />the beginning or the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>; that all is very quiet in <em>Ireland</em>, save some small parties of Tories, which are chiefly about the County of <em>Carlow</em>, where they lately fell upon and wounded some of the <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>; and do sometimes rob and steal where they dare venture, and <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> away again with their prey presently.</p>

<p>An Ambassador from <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em> was this day to congratulate His Excellency, the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>His Highness, and also the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, were this day upon matters of great concernment. A Committee of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> also <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> about the business of the Merchants.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Lislebone Long</em> is made Master of Requests for Petitions that are to His Highness.</p>

<p><i>Harwich, 12 Jan. 1653.</i> Capt. <em>Serland</em> came hither Convoy with 12 Merchant ships, and having <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> a few days to Tallow, is now going towards the North.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>. Our Lord General</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The humble <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army.</i></head>

<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services wherein through the blessing of God upon the <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg> and <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> of your Highness, we have in some measure been Instrumental in our places to free the Commonwealth from its enemies. So we now cannot but above all worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations after all the shakings which have been in the midst of us, set up upon its true and proper Basis and Foundation, and thereby brought into a <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of rest and safety. The <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and the whole Nation at this time when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment by inclining you to accept of the Government and Protection of this Commonwealth; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the people, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We judge it highly incumbent <pb n="13" />upon us to make our humble <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> unto you, and to declare that we shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be obedient unto you in the performance of your great Trust; but in our places most faithfully and diligently to the hazard of our lives, and whatsoever is near and <reg orig="deare">dear</reg> unto us be serviceable unto you in the Station God hath placed you against all opposition: Not doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; So you will to the utmost of your power and <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> lay forth your Self for the Glory of God, and the Good of this People amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of Faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take this <reg orig="boldnesse">boldness</reg> most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> more especially to spread the wing of your Protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, which you continuing to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> are confident their Father which is in Heaven, will be unto you a Buckler and a Shield and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> most humble and faithful Servants.</i></p>

<p>The Officers from the several <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> and Regiments, are very unanimous in signing the said <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg>, which is from most parts of <em>England</em> already sent up to His Highness, and the rest near finished, as is <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> by Letters from their several quarters.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 18 January.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> came this day thus.</p>

<p><i>Sir, <em>Kenmore</em> and <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, with their force, marched by the way of <em>Strathspey</em>, and <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg> Lane, Mac Aldny</em>, and some of <em>Mac Griggers</em> men, with the rest of the gang (<em>Athol</em> being left <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg>) marched by the head of <em>Badgnoth</em>, and <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> their forces within three miles of <em>Ruthuen</em> Garrison. Upon their approach <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em> sent a Letter to the Governor of the Castle, inviting him to come into His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces, and telling him, That all <em>Scotland</em> was up in Arms, and many had marched through <em>England</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them: To which, he received a very resolute and ingenuous Answer from the Governor, Cap. <em>Hill</em>; and it was not probable his Lordship had so great an Army, when he could provide no better Quarters for them. After they had been a while in <em>Lorne</em>, there fell a discontent between <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em> and <em>Lorne</em>, about the men of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, <em>Lorne</em> saying, That they being his men, he ought to have the ordering and <pb n="14" />disposal of them, as the Earl of <em>Athol</em> had of his; but <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em> told him, That he took up the Rents of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, the men were the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> of <reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg>. After many high words, <em><reg orig="Glancarne">Glencairn</reg></em> offered to draw his Sword, and <em>Lorne</em> went away in a great rage swearing, That rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> he would see his own people abused by <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em>, he would loose his life; and thereupon drew to the other side of the water with some of <em>Mac <reg orig="Griggers">Grigger's</reg></em> men, and about sixty horse with him: This difference hath put that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to a stand, who otherwise would have <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Lorne</em>; so that some of them are fled to <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>, and other parts, to secure themselves. Parties of Horse, and Posts are directed, every way, for the apprehending of <em>Lorne</em>. The enemy take up all the horses they can <reg orig="finde">find</reg> in the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>There is a report that the Earl of <em>Mane</em> is gone in unto them.</i></p>

<head level="3">Dalkeith, 12 <i>Jan.</i> 1653.</head>

<p>The Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother is by an Order of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, removed back from the Tower to Newgate. The Sessions being now there, but he hath not as yet been brought before the Bench.</p>

<p>There are many for Robberies and Stealing, now upon <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> at the Sessions.</p>

<p>There is also one for Ravishing of two Girls of about ten or eleven years of age, though the mother of one of them <reg orig="whipt">whipped</reg> her <reg orig="childe">child</reg> to have made her deny it.</p>

<p>A Polterer woman that married a Knight, for having another Husband.</p>

<p>A man that hath two Wives.</p>

<p>A Witch that upon malice <reg orig="bewitcht">bewitched</reg> a Woman and her Children, the Children <reg orig="blinde">blind</reg> and lame by it; and the Mother pained in her side, and back, and bound in her body: She went to several Doctors, but could have no help, until at last one Doctor told her she was bewitched, but he would give her <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, which if it did work, he would <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to help her: She took his <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, it wrought, and she returned to him, who appointed her to make a Cake, and knead it with her own water, and eat it, using a form of words, which he gave her in writing, which she did; and when she had eaten it, was distracted, scarce knowing what she did, but went to the <reg orig="Witches">Witch's</reg> house, and said she had her <unclear>Picture</unclear>; which making search in her house, she <pb n="15" />found, also of some of her <reg orig="Childrens">Children</reg>, with divers Pictures more, which she carried home and burnt, and they did stink for two or three days like <reg orig="Sulpher">Sulphur</reg>, very strongly; she thrust an hot Iron into the breech of her own Picture, and presently went orderly to stool: And in those places of her body where she was pained, the Picture had holes pierced in it; which she brought and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> to the Bench.</p>

<p>But that which is most remarkable, is, That she would have received the Sacrament with a Gathered Church; where she was told, That she was not to be admitted, because she was reputed to be a Witch, which bewitched such a Woman and her Children: She denied it, appealing to her god. She was asked, who was her God? she said, the god of the world; and wished that she might never speak, if it was true; and that her god would <reg orig="shew">show</reg> her some eminent judgement upon her, if it was true. Whereupon she was presently struck lame and dumb, and ever since <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> nothing, but I and No.</p>

<p>These are to give notice, That if any persons, concerned in Probate of Wills or Administrations, send for Commissions, they must return the same with speed from time to time, to the Office at <em>Star-Chamber</em> in <em>Westminster</em>; for that the power of the Court expires the first of <em>April</em> next.</p>

<p>There are come in divers Merchant ships to several ports.</p>

<p>There are yet come no Letters from Holland since the Dutch Deputies were come back there; but private Letters from thence dated Friday was sevennight last, the day the Deputies set out from hence say, that the States were very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> preparing a <reg orig="suddain">sudden</reg> Dispatch for their Answer, which report tends probably to peace (in their judgement) their Deputy Monsieur Borrel in France gives out report there, that the States have agreed to the English offers for Peace.</p>

<p><em>Hannah</em> the Maid that prayed at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, of whom you have the particulars before, this day rise and went from <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> home, speedily and lustily.</p>

<p>Dartmouth 12 Janu. The Hector hath sent in a ship hither, which hat in her 3000 Cheeses. The ship is of Amsterdam, and took in her lading at the Elve. There is a private man of war hath brought in a ship of Rotterdam laden with Herrings, and Holland Cheeses, and about 10 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of Pepper, and some Cloves.</p>

<hr />

<p>Brampton 14 January 1653. We have this Saturday a Robbery committed at Brampton. Sir John Norwich sold a grey Gelding for about 30 li. and was to deliver him at Kettering, and there his servant was to have the <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, who received it, but as <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was going home was robbed in Brampton Woods, and the horse he rode, on worth 30 li. also <unclear>taken</unclear> from him, an Iron grey stone horse, between 14 &amp; 15 hands high, 7 years old. On his <unclear>near</unclear> buttock is a white Lion in an <reg orig="Escocheon">Escutcheon</reg>, a strong made horse, and hath all his paces. Whosoever can discover either horse or man, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have <unclear>forty</unclear> shillings of Mr. King at the Rose in Smithfield, or of Sir John Norwich at Brampton by Dingly in Northamptonshire.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>