<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState242">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 242</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 11 of <em>May</em>. To Thursday the 18 day of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 11 May. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day was published an Ordinance for further doubling upon and finishing the sale of <reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg> and <reg orig="Chapters">Chapter's</reg> Lands, &amp;c. By which it is Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That over and above the <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of three hundred thousand pounds, appointed to be borrowed upon the security held forth by the first Act, and over and above the <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of one hundred and twenty thousand pounds more, borrowed upon the security held forth in the two other Acts, the sum of twenty thousand pounds shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> further borrowed upon the security of the premises, by way of doubling the like sum, as shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> due to any person or persons, Body politick or Corporate, for<pb n="1" />any Money, Plate, Horse, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> or other thing advanced upon the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith, or which hath been at any time allowed by any Act or Ordinance of Parliament, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> doubled as <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith; together with Interest upon such <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith Debts, after the rate of eight pounds in the hundred, by the year, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the stating of such Debts and Interest, by the Persons named and appointed in and by an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An <reg orig="Additionall">Additional</reg> Act for sale of several Lands and Estates forfeited to the Commonwealth for Treason</i>, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> Register Accomptant, or any of them. And to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> allowed only six pounds in the hundred by the year, for the whole of such doubled <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith Debts <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the payment thereof, or defalcation upon purchase, to whom any Debts capable of doubling within this present Ordinance, shall be due, and his and their respective <reg orig="assignes">assigns</reg>, and all persons doubling such debts and their respective Assigns, shall have all and the like liberties, <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, benefits, and advantages respectively in reference to the premises, as any might have had by the former Acts, save only what is hereby altered with restriction to Debts and Interests.</p>

<p>And they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> pay in to the Treasurers the money wherewith <reg orig="hee">he</reg> or they ought to double within ten days next after Certificate thereof to the Treasurers, or otherwise shall lose his or their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith Debts, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> or they shall <reg orig="shew">show</reg> good cause to the Treasurers for their <reg orig="failer">failure</reg>. And the Certificates or Receipts to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> given by the Treasurers, for money to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> doubled upon this Ordinance, as also all Certificates, Receipts, or <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> for moneys or Debts doubled or transferred upon the securities held forth by any the Acts aforesaid, which were defalkable in payment for any purchase made within the same former Acts <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be made defalkable in payment in manner &amp; form following.</p>

<p><i>1. That the Certificates or Receipts for moneys to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> doubled upon this Ordinance, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> defalkable in payment for both <reg orig="moyeties">moieties</reg> of the purchase moneys, payable for any part of the premises which yet remains uncontracted for, And in payment for all second <reg orig="moyeties">moieties</reg> payable upon contract made of any the said premises, at any time before the passing of this Ordinance.</i></p>

<p><i>2. And the Certificates, Receipts or Bills for moneys doubled or transferred upon the securities held forth by any of the said Acts, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg><pb n="2" />equally and alike defalkable for any or both moieties of the purchase money, payable for any the premises exposed to sale by any the former Acts either contracted or uncontracted for.</i></p>

<p>And it is further Ordained and Declared, That where any present Estate of, or in any the Lands &amp;c. of the late <reg orig="Arch Bishops">Archbishops</reg>, Bishops, &amp;c. shall be doubtfully returned upon any Survey, the <reg orig="Tennant">Tenant</reg> or Tenants claiming such Estate, shall (as to the Lands surveyed) before the first day of July, 1654. and as to the Lands unsurveyed, within three months next after the respective Returns of the Surveys thereof to the respective Registers for sale of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, make proof of their Estate before the Commissioners for removing of Obstructions, and procure their Order for allowance thereof, or otherwise shall for ever be barred and excluded from any benefit or advantage <reg orig="therby">thereby</reg>. And such who hold any of the Lands, &amp;c. exposed to sale, and yet undiscovered, and which are or ought to be in the present possession of the respective Trustees for the use of the Commonwealth, shall make the first discovery thereof to the Surveyor General, before named; every such person desiring the same shall be admitted the <reg orig="preemption">pre-emption</reg> of all such Lands, &amp;c. at the lowest rates the respective Contractors are enabled to sell the same for: And where any person possessed of all such Lands, &amp;c. yet undiscovered, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any Lease or Copy of Court-roll, dated before the first day of <em>December</em>, One thousand six hundred forty one, granted by any who have power to make or grant the same, shall before the said first day of July <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> bring or send in a true copy of his or their Lease or Leases, Copy or Copies of Court-roll, to the said Surveyor general, that a survey may be had of the premises, every such person coming in within thirty <reg orig="daies">days</reg> next after the Return of any such Survey, shall be admitted to the <reg orig="preemption">pre-emption</reg> of the reversion of his Lease or Copy, with the present rent incident thereunto at the lowest rates. And in case of his or their neglect to bring or send in such true copy or copies before the said first day of <em>July</em> all and every such person and persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> forfeit and lose his or their present estate by Lease or Copy, and any person or persons who afterwards <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> discover the same, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have and be admitted to the <reg orig="preemption">pre-emption</reg> of the present possession of such lands.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>And Sir <em>William Roberts</em> Knight, <em>John Blackwel</em> the elder, <em>James Russel, Thomas Middleton, Robert Fenwick, Thomas Aires</em>, and <em>Edward Cresset</em>, Esquires, or any three or more of them, are authorised to execute Acts, Authorities, powers and things relating as well to the sale of the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories, and Glebe Lands, &amp;c.</p>

<p>And the Trustees for sale of <reg orig="Bishops">Bishops'</reg> Lands have power to make Warrants to the Treasurers for the sale of the <reg orig="mannors">manors</reg> of Rectories, <reg orig="Glebs">Glebes</reg>, &amp;c. or one of them, for the payment of such incident charges as have or shall arise upon the sale of the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of Rectories, <reg orig="Glebs">Glebes</reg>, &amp;c. belonging to the late <reg orig="Arch bishops">Archbishops</reg>, and Bishops <reg orig="onely">only</reg>; and the Treasurers that receive such moneys as shall be doubled hereon, shall not issue forth any port of the twenty thousand pounds hereby appointed to be doubled, but by and in such manner, as His Highness with the advice and consent of the Council shall direct. And <em>James Noel</em> is Treasurer in the room of Alderman <em>Thomas Noel</em> late deceased.</p>

<p>This day came out a Declaration for a Thanksgiving, as followeth.</p>

<head level="3">A DECLARATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>By His Highness the Lord Protector for setting apart Tuesday 23. of this present May for a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> day of Thanksgiving, for the Peace concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Provinces, and for the late seasonable Rain.</i></head>

<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the <reg orig="out-stretched">outstretched</reg> arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment, and wonder, Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter and they will <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, and <reg orig="indeeed">indeed</reg> the dispensations of the Lord have been as if he had said, <em>England</em> thou art my <reg orig="first-born">firstborn</reg>, my delight amongst the Nations, under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us.</p>

<p>The Lord having added another Link to this golden Chain of his loving kindness by giving us a Peace with our <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> the United Provinces, (whereby he hath not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> stopped a great issue of blood, but we trust also given us hearts to unite our blood and strength for the <reg orig="mutuall">mutual</reg> defence of each other)<pb n="4" /><reg orig="cals">calls</reg> for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>

<p>It is therefore thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, and for the Thankful Acknowledgement of this blessing of Peace, which we hope hath in the womb of it many other Blessings.</p>

<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up, that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> <reg orig="famin">famine</reg>, and did cause the Beasts of the field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord imparted this Mercy to us, did any amongst us, <reg orig="fore know">foreknow</reg> it was coming, was it not by stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that immediately before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy? And doth not this bespeak?</p>

<p><i>1. That the manner of conveying this Mercy is the best part of the Mercy.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That the Lord has not cast us off, that his Spirit yet strives with us, that he hath a people of his love amongst us, and loves the Nation so far as to provoke it to be in love with calling upon the Name of the Lord for better things than Corn and Wine.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That he knows best how and when to answer the expectation of the Husbandman, and when to hear, even the mourning of the brute Beast, who will yet much more hear the desires of them that fear him, and that in the fittest season.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That the Heavens having thus declared the Glory of God, and the Earth answering thereunto in its fruitfulness, Why should we be melted and <reg orig="softned">softened</reg>, humbling <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> under these marvellous kindnesses, and abounding unto all fruitfulness in every good word and work of love; And if every place hath been made partaker of his <reg orig="showres">showers</reg>, why should not we (laying aside our differences) be <reg orig="inlarged">enlarged</reg> also each to other?</i></p>

<p><i>5. That seeing the Lord hath been thus universal in this Mercy, why should <reg orig="wee">we</reg> not universally <reg orig="turne">turn</reg> from the <reg orig="Nationall">National</reg> Evils and vain Practices which are yet too superstitiously and customarily exercised amongst us, which we need not repeat here, because they are too well known, and We trust will be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg> by those godly Ministers<pb n="5" />who shall be called to Preach unto the People upon this occasion</i>.</p>

<p>Conclude we with the words of David, Psal. 107.30,31,32,33,34,35,36,37,38.</p>

<p><i>Then they are glad, because they be quiet, so he bringeth them unto their desired Haven. O that Men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of Men. Let them exalt him also in the Congregation of the People, and praise him in the Assembly of the Elders. He turneth Rivers into a Wilderness, and the water-springs into dry ground. A fruitful Land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell in it. He turneth the Wilderness into a standing water, and the dry ground into Water-springs. And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a City for Habitation. And sow the Fields, and plant Vineyards, which may <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> fruits of increase. He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly, and suffereth not their <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg> to decrease.</i></p>

<p><i>O that Men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the Children of Men.</i></p>

<p>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 9th of <em>May</em>, 1654.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 12 May 1654.</i></head>

<p>There is every day in the week twice, <em>viz</em>. at ten a clock in the morning, and at six at night, a meeting of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Family at the <reg orig="Chappell">Chapel</reg> at <em>Whitehall</em>, where his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> Chaplin, Mr. <em>Lokier</em> <em>&amp;c.</em> expounds to them.</p>

<p><em>Warsaw 13 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>, The King of <em>Poland</em> is often in conference with the <reg orig="Senatours">Senators</reg> that are here, about the ways of providing moneys both for the Levies, and for the pay of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg> already raised, and in the service of this Crown. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have intelligence from the <em><reg orig="Ukrain">Ukraine</reg></em>, confirming the march of our <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Poloskey</em> with 12000 men as far as the River of <em>Bog</em>, under <em>Ploskeirow</em>, where <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> some forces of the Palatine of <em>Breslaw</em>, and of the new <em>Hospador</em> of <em>Walachia</em>, hoping with their assistance to carry the Town of <em>Vinniese</em> upon the said River, and thereby <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Cossacks, to foment their divisions and discontents, and gain the chiefest of them, being already very much weary of the great authority the Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> usurps upon them, whose armies do stand still, without attempting <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>. Few days since we had the News of the death of the Duke <em>Radzivill</em><pb n="6" />, whom the King of <em>Poland</em> had made a while since Palatine of <em>Poloskey</em>.</p>

<p><em>Reginsburgh 27 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. The 20. instant the Pallgrave arrived <reg orig="herewith">here with</reg> a small retinue and had audience of the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, the next day. His Majesty hath put off again his journey, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the fifth of the next month, that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> might <reg orig="bee">be</reg> present to the conclusion of the Diet, and have the answer of the States upon his demand of a <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> of money for his extraordinary charges during his abode here. The Deputies of the Elector of <em>Colen</em>, and of the Duke of <em>Newburgh</em>, have two days since received the investiture in the name of their Masters, from the Emperor, with the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> ceremonies.</p>

<p><em>Hamburgh 27 April</em>, The Count <em>Benedict Oxenstern</em> coming from <em>Wismar</em>, hath been here, and is going to <em>Sedan</em>, to meet <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Koningsmark</em>, as it is supposed with the Orders of the Qu. of <em>Sweden</em>, for blocking up the City of <em>Bremen</em>, after the taking of all places round about it. The said <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> hath armed all the Country people of the <reg orig="Arch-bishoprick">Archbishopric</reg> of <em>Bremen</em>, intending to besiege <em>Bezerkesse</em>. Those of <em>Bremen</em> continue their levies, being resolved to resist to the last extremity, hoping to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> protected and relieved by the <em>Hollanders</em> and other States, though <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> whether they will draw the Swedish Forces upon their back.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 13 May.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> Commander in chief in <em>Scotland</em>, hath published this following Declaration.</p>

<head level="3">A DECLARATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in chief of all the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>The Commonwealth of <em>England</em> having used all means of <reg orig="tendernesse">tenderness</reg> and affection towards the People of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the Liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much Blood and Treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more than their <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> proportion with <em>England</em>) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the Fruits and Benefits of Peace; Yet divers lewd persons, broken in their fortunes, and dissolute in their Lives, are run into<pb n="7" />Rebellion, who being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Brethren, <reg orig="Tuitors">Tutors</reg>, Masters, and people among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to Rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in Peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might <reg orig="bee">be</reg> left unattempted, for the prevention thereof.</p> 

<p>I by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the authority to me given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, do declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are expected in the Acts of Grace) who shall within twenty days after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next <em>English</em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> , and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall <reg orig="be">bee</reg>, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned, for any offence, spoil, or plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion (the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.)</p> 

<p>And I do Declare, that if any Parents, Brethren, or <reg orig="Tuitors">Tutors</reg>, who have assisted and connived at any their Sons, Brothers, or Pupils now in Rebellion, as aforesaid, shall within twenty days after publication hereof, cause their said Sons, Brothers, or Pupils, to render themselves, and give security, as aforesaid, that then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, are hereby freely pardoned; But if otherwise, then the said Parents, Brethren, and Tutors, who have so offended, shall be imprisoned during the time the said persons do remain in Rebellion.</p> 

<p>And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into Rebellion, without the knowledge or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth, I do therefore hereby Declare, that the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth, to render him or themselves within twenty <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after Publication hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the said Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned;<pb n="8" />But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said Parish and Presbytery, two shillings six pence a day for each Horseman, and ten pence a day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their Ordinary Sesse, out of the said Parish or Presbytery, which the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> is hereby authorized to levy and receive monthly, during the time the said persons shall so continue in Rebellion.</p> 

<p>And I do likewise hereby empower all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person, and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into Rebellion, or attempt so to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, and safely to deliver him or them to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the next English Garrison; and in case of resistance to take such weapons as they can get, and to fight the said person or persons; and if they shall kill any of the said persons so resisting, they shall not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive a reward of their good service, all such Moneys, Goods, Horses, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, as the said Rebellious Persons are then possessed of, besides full satisfaction of their pains and <reg orig="travell">travel</reg> therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Donald <em><reg orig="Mac-Donald">McDonald</reg></em> Laird of <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and Major <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Dayel;</p> 

<p>I do hereby therefore Declare, That what such person or persons soever of this Nation, (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said <reg orig="principall">principal</reg> Contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner, to any <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of any English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only <reg orig="bee">be</reg> pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> or they have acted in this late Rebellion, but shall also receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of two hundred pounds sterling, for every person so <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</p> 

<p>And lastly, for the encouragement of all peaceable and well affected people, both English and Scots, I do also hereby Declare, That what <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done to their persons, goods or <reg orig="Geer">Gear</reg>, for their good affection to the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>, the same shall bee again repaired out of the Estates of such as have done the <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg>, or out of the Estates of the Friends and harbourers<pb n="9" />of such <reg orig="wrong doers">wrongdoers</reg>, or out of the Parish, Presbytery, or Shire where the wrong is done, in case they do not apprehend the said Offenders, or give the English Forces such timely notice thereof, that the said Offenders may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> apprehended by them.</p> 

<p>And I do hereby require all Provosts, <reg orig="Bailiffes">Bailiffs</reg>, and Chief Officers of Head Burghs, in their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Burghs, to cause these presents to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> duly published and posted up, according to the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> form, and to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their doings therein to me, in writing, under his or their hands.</p>

<p><i>Given under my Hand at <em>Dalkieth</em>, this 4. day of <em>May</em>, 1654.</i></p> 

<p>GEORGE MONCK.</p>

<p>One <em>Downes</em>, and one <em>Smith</em>, were by the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg> this week found guilty of <reg orig="Coyning">Coining</reg> false half crowns, shillings, and six pences of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> stamps, of the Kings, <em>James</em> and <em>Charles</em>, and the States; the Rings fine silver, but the middle, base mettle.</p>

<p>One is Fined 1200 pounds, and <reg orig="perpetuall">perpetual</reg> Imprisonment, for taking off the Lead from <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>, and the Scaffolds, and carrying them away.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 15 May.</i></head>

<p><em>Constantinople 13 April</em>. Our fleet of war is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> 30 great <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> more than the last years was. <reg orig="Signieur">Signor</reg> <em>Capello</em>, the <em>Venice</em> <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> is still prisoner, without hope of any new Overtures.</p>

<p><em>Rome 20 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. The Pope is not yet well, but goes abroad. <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath given his last made Cardinals the Livings and <reg orig="Pentions">Pensions</reg> which <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Assi</em> had, who is still at <em><unclear>Saminey</unclear></em> with the <reg orig="Marquisse">Marquis</reg> his Brother. The King of <em>Spain</em> hath given <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Medici</em> all that the deceased <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Piemontelli</em> had, for his <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> service, to keep or dispose of. Some of those who some years since <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the Bishop of <em>Castino</em>, are brought hither prisoners.</p>

<p>The Pope declared the 13 instant, with his Consissory, that henceforth no Congregation shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> held in any of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> houses, under any pretence whatsoever, but all in <unclear>effect <em>Vatican</em></unclear>, because of <em><reg orig="Medicies">Medici's</reg></em> transactors for the Spanish Faction, and the Spanish Ambassador hath been refused audience, and his Letters have been opened in the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="pallace">palace</reg>. Madam <em>Lucretia Barberina</em><pb n="10" />, was married at <em>Loretta</em> the sixteenth instant, to the Duke of <em>Modena</em> by the Cardinal <em>Fachinatti</em>.</p>

<p><em>Milan</em> eighth <em>April</em>, Several Forces are come hither of the new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> from <em>Germany</em>, but the Vice King of <em>Naples</em> hath sent none as he promised, diverting his for <em>Catalonia</em>; the Country people rose and fell on the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Tarragona</em>, killed some Captains and others, and both parties are gone to <em>Barcelona</em>, to have that act judge; the people are weary of the Spaniards, and incline to the <em>French</em>, which makes the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> very diligent.</p>

<p><em>Turenn 20 April</em>, <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <em>Taracena</em> being to take the Field next month with twelve thousand of his own, and from <em>Lomberdy, Germany</em>, and the <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, besides those expected from <em>Naples</em>, order is given to all our <reg orig="Governours">Governors</reg> to be watchful.</p>

<p><em>Bremen 29, April</em>, an <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> of <em>Muscovie</em> with a hundred Horse passed by here, here are four new Companies raising.</p>

<p><em>Venice 20. April</em>, our General <em>Moclenigo</em> is ready to sail for <em>Candia</em> with twelve of the Nobility, four thousand Foot, and a hundred Horse, and many <reg orig="Engins">Engines</reg> to defend our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> there. The Turks <reg orig="re-inforce">reinforce</reg> the Fort of <em>Lazarotto</em> to hinder us; Forces are sent to <reg orig="releeve">relieve</reg> <unclear><em>Clissa</em></unclear>, if the <em>Turks</em> gathered at <em>Spalatro</em> move towards it. A new fashion vessel with thirty <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of Ordnance invented by <em>Angelo Barberigo</em> is making, he is to have a great reward if it perform what it promised.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg> 9. May</em>, The fourth instant the Duke went with forty Coaches (most with six Horses) to meet Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em><reg orig="Loreign">Lorain</reg></em> a league off from hence, and came in at eight at night, they have been sumptuously entertained. The 22 Troops in <em>Naples</em> have been mustered, 770 returned with orders to have new <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> two months hence, and then to remove their old quarters, during which time the Vice-Roy will visit the Frontiers, and finish the <reg orig="Leavy">Levy</reg> for <em>Catalonia</em> of 1200. foot upon eight <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Engonlesm 10. May</em>, Monsieur <em>Baleac</em> being dead hath left 2000. Livers to the <em>French</em> <reg orig="Accademy">Academy</reg>, for the most eloquent Orators for twenty years, and the like sum to buy Books for this Chapter, and made the poor of the Hospital where he was buried his Heirs.</p>

<p>Bassee 10. May, Our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> hath <reg orig="stopt">stopped</reg> the <em><reg orig="Loreigners">Lorainers'</reg></em> march by <reg orig="straitning">straightening</reg> them of Provisions, a Party from St. <em>Menebould</em><pb n="11" />fetched great plunder from beyond the Mease.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Venables</em> and Col. <em>Ingolsby</em> are come from Ireland, and have presented their addresses from the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> there, to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, May 16.</i></head>

<p>General Blake being come to Town from the Fleet, he with the Lord <reg orig="Mayer">Mayor</reg>, and some Lords of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> dined this day with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, General <em>Pen</em> is with the Fleet in the Downs, the Northern Squadron that convey the Coals will shortly be there God willing, the Brest Men are out, and do mischief upon the Western <reg orig="costs">coasts</reg>.</p>

<p>By Letters from several places of <em>England</em> is advertised, that the Peace hath been proclaimed with great joy, and the <reg orig="Peoples">People's</reg> affections more and more enlarged to his Highness the Lord Protector; as for instance, one Letter from <em><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em>, the like whereof hath been from many other places.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg>, May 7. 1654.</i></p>

<p>The joyful tidings of Peace was in great solemnity yesterday proclaimed in this Town, where was present the Mayor, Aldermen, and other Officers, all in their Gowns, with the Governor, and the Officers of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the <reg orig="Musicioners">Musicians</reg> in loud Instruments standing upon the Cross, and the Drums beating a Call, all the Towns inferior Officers standing in their Gowns bare-headed under the <reg orig="Muscioners">Musicians</reg> on the <reg orig="fore-side">foreside</reg> of the Cross, with their Maces elevated, and the Proclamation being ended there was great Acclamations, the people crying, <i>God save the Lord Protector of <em>England</em></i>, &amp;c. whereupon the Drums beat, <reg orig="Musitioners">Musicians</reg> played on their loud Instruments, and <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> rung apace, insomuch that quite round the Market the people could scarce hear one another speak for the <reg orig="noyse">noise</reg>; Mr. Mayor, the Aldermen and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and Officers went up to the Town Chamber, and there saluted each other, and the Mayor &amp;c. entertained the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> and <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> Officers with Banqueting <reg orig="stuffe">stuff</reg>, and several sorts of Wine very gallantly, for nigh the space of three hours; in the mean time the <reg orig="Musitioners">Musicians</reg> playing on the stair-head at the entrance into the great Hall, and truly yester night at nine a clock the solemnity of the day was not over, for the<pb n="12" /><reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> ceased not till that time, and Bonfires then burning apace; how we of this place relished the news you may imagine.</p>

<head level="3">The substance of the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Propositions to the States of <em>Bohemia</em> assembled 13 April 1654.</head>

<p><i>1. That they use their utmost <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> for the propagating of the Romish <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That they <reg orig="selebrate">celebrate</reg> the Feast of St. Joseph as the rest of the Patrons of the Kingdom <reg orig="use">used</reg> to do.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That they pay a considerable <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> to the Emperor for the maintenance of his <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> Officers, Ambassadors, Residents and Attendants.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That they pay their proportion for maintenance of the Frontier places of Hungaria.</i></p>

<p><i>5. That they continue the maintenance of the <reg orig="Imperiall">Imperial</reg> Forces quartered in that Kingdom, and pay those which his Majesty shall disband.</i></p>

<p><i>6. That they suffer not the importation of foreign Salt without paying the usual Customs and Duties.</i></p>

<p><i>7. That they neither suffer the importation, nor in any thing the use of the bad Turkish <reg orig="wooll">wool</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>8. That they shall incessantly cause the River of <em>Elve</em> to be made navigable as far as this Town.</i></p>

<p><i>9. That they perform whatsoever hath been agreed on in former Assemblies touching the other Affairs of the Kingdom.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Lubone 7 April.</i></head>

<p>It is confirmed from <em><reg orig="Brazill">Brazil</reg></em>, that our men have utterly driven out the <em>Hollanders</em> from those parts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris the 16 of April.</i></head>

<p>Last week the Deputies of the City of <em>Rheims</em> arrived here to assure His Majesty that the Inhabitants are about with a great care, befitting their zeal and fidelity to make all things ready for his Reception, against the Ceremony of his Coronation. The 11. instant the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> having <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> the French <reg orig="Accademy">Academy</reg>, with her picture, it was presented to them at the <reg orig="Chancellors">Chancellor's</reg> house in <em>Paris</em>, where they met and received as a precious testimony of that learned and worthy <reg orig="Princesses">Princess's</reg> affection. Mr. <em>Donjar</em> then President of the <reg orig="Accademy">Academy</reg> in Mr. <em>de la Brosse <reg orig="Montmors">Montmors's</reg></em> absence, who is their Director, having made<pb n="13" />a rare speech in commendation of the excellent qualities of the said Queen.</p>

<p>The 12. The King with all the Court returned hither from <em><reg orig="Fontanibleau">Fontainebleau</reg></em>. All is making ready here for the Campania, the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Forces in <em>Picaroy, Campaign</em> and <em>Burgundy</em>, having been commanded to make ready to be at the <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> about the end of this month. We are making great <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> here and <reg orig="every where">everywhere</reg>. <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>de Thurenne</em> is to command a potent Army in <em>Flanders</em>.</p>

<p>Yesterday we had news that the Count de Harcourt is wholly submitting to the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> will and ready to surrender <em>Bresac</em>.</p>

<p><em>Paris 9 May</em>. A week since one calling <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> Mons. <em>Quatarze</em> a person of note addressed <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> to the Abbot of <em>Palnan</em>, one of Cardinal <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> Chamber, who brought him to the Cardinal, and after a long Conference, he was the next day <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to <em>Montargie</em>, where great <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> are used for the general Peace. And <em>Mazarine</em> met the Lord <em>Pimontelly</em> there (kept <em>incognito</em>) <reg orig="onely">only</reg> he sent to acquaint the Queen with it. There are new Propositions offered for agreement with the Prince of <em>Conde</em>. The Duke of <em>Guise</em> is to be <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the French Fleet, and Marquis <em>du Plessis Bellieure</em> Lieut. <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, which is to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> either for <em>Naples</em> or <em>Catalonia</em>. The Duke of <em>Joyeuse</em> is to be Lieutenant General of the Horse in the Army of Flanders.</p>

<p><i><em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg> 6 May</em>, The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> hath now liberty of the walks in the Castle. The Lord <em>St. Martin</em> one of his Council, and Master of his Horse, and be that was Cap. Of his Life Guard are at liberty, and went out, and met, and returned with Prince <em>Francis</em>, with the Nobles and the Officers of the <em>Lorain</em> Forces, and the rest, who brought him hither in great pomp. Orders for the <reg orig="proces">process</reg> of the Earl of <em>Bassigny</em> and the Baron of <em>Mervy</em> is sent from Spain, who are kept more strictly than before.</i></p>

<p><em>Hague 10 May</em>, Strict guards were set upon our <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg> that no ships should go before this day. A <reg orig="smal">small</reg> prize came in last week to the <em>Texell</em> taken on the coasts of <em>Scotland</em>. Here is an Ambassador from <em>Muscovy</em>, who is going for <em>France</em>, &amp; doth by the way demand of us some Officers &amp; Ammunition of war. The Peace was published (the 8 May) by the English account the 28<pb n="14" /><em>April</em>. And there is no <unclear>fort</unclear> of any breach; If our fine provoke not.</p>

<p><i>Scilley 5 May. The Indians had a design to have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in <em>Virginia</em>, but it was discovered. A Brest man of war had taken an English Vessel, going to <em>Wales</em> with Coals, who only plundered it, and it came hither yesterday. Some poor <reg orig="English men">Englishmen</reg> taken in <em><reg orig="Meldrums">Meldrum's</reg></em> Brests ship, got liberty, and are since got to Brest in service again. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have taken one Brest man of <reg orig="warre">war</reg> lately, in which is <em>Thomas Sloe</em>, a notable Gunner.</i></p>

<p><em>Dalkeith 9 May</em>. On <em>May</em> the fourth his Highness the Lord Protector was Proclaimed at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> with great acclamation. Twelve sale of our men of <reg orig="warre">war</reg> are going from <em>Leith</em>. Gen. <em><reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg></em> is going towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>. Middleton hath sent out <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Commanders for Levies, <em>Drummond</em> to <em>Loughtay</em>, and <em>Glencairn</em> to secure him with 100 horse Col <em>Murray</em> to <em>Athol</em>: <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em> to <em>Branar</em>, and others to other places, But we shall shortly be among them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath had hard Duties, but the Enemy will not come near him, but gives him the slip among the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>. The Scotch Ministers even in our quarters pray for <em>Charles Stuart</em>, whom it seems they have a hope to see again among them, so besotted they are and mad; two ships from <em>Dunkirk</em> have brought Men, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and Ammunition to <em>Middleton</em>, but of all that <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them we hear of few that have estates to subsist on, but the <reg orig="Ring-leaders">Ringleaders</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Milford Haven 8 May: Our ships are gone hence for <em>Ireland</em>. The Brest men have taken three <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from <em>Dublin</em> to <em>Liverpool</em> and <em>Chester</em>.</i></p>

<p><em>Rye 12 May</em>. A <reg orig="Bark">Barque</reg> coming hither from <em>Diep</em>, in which was many passengers was set upon by an <em>Ostend</em> Freebooter and sunk, only most of the passengers were saved, but 7 of the <em>Ostend</em> men<pb n="15" />were slain. There are two French <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships have been lately taken prize with Wine, &amp;c.</p>

<p>An Ordinance passed this day for continuing the Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for relief of creditors and poor prisoners</i>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the 31 day of this instant <em>May</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 17 May.</i></head>

<p>The discontent in <em>Holland</em>, and what hath been done about it, is only thus. The Princess Dowager, and the Princess <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg>, and the rest of the Family of <em>Nassaw</em>, have made an application by a paper presented to the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, bemoaning their condition as sad by the late Articles of Peace with <em>England</em>, And some forty women came weeping and crying out, bemoaning the Prince of <em>Orange</em>, saying, <i>Ah! poor Prince, what hast thou done that thou shouldest <reg orig="bee">be</reg> thus used? ah, poor <reg orig="childe">childe</reg> ! what a sad condition art thou in?</i> and the like expressions; which was not much regarded; and that is all the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>. All being quiet, and in very good order, and if that Family will live peaceably, they may; The last week was the Fair kept at the <em>Hague</em>, at which time the Trained band (as they use to do every year) went out in, to the field in their gallantry.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is passed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, with advice of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, for the relief of poor Creditors in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for the Courts that use to be kept in <em>Chester</em> City, to be kept at <em><reg orig="North-wich">Northwich</reg></em> during the time of the Sickness being in <em>Chester</em> City.</p>

<p>An additional Ordinance passed for mending the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>.</p>

<p>There is nothing yet concluded in our Treaty with the <em>French</em> Ambassador, but what may be time will <reg orig="shew">show</reg>.</p>

<p>The Committee meet about the Law, but find it a hard work, to alter the old <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg>; But it is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> something will be dispatched about a fortnight hence for the Committee at <reg orig="Salters">Salter's</reg> Hall to act by.</p>

<p>The Government of <em>Jersey</em> is near finished. Mr <em>John Lilburn</em> received his <em>Habeas Corpus</em> from the Upper Bench, and the desire to be brought thither.</p>

<p>The Writs are preparing against the time they are to issue forth, for the calling of a Parliament according to the Instrument of the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>