<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState238">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 238</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 6 of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. To Thursday the 13 day of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 13 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Bedchambers and the rest if the lodgings and rooms appointed for the Lord Protector in <em>Whitehall</em>, were prepared for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to remove from the Cockpit on the morrow.</p>

<p>An Ordinance passed, and was this day published, <reg orig="Impowering">Empowering</reg> Commissioners to put in execution an Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> (<i>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco in <em>England</em></i>.) That upon consideration had of the great prejudice arising to the English Plantations in Foreign parts and the great damage and <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to Trade at home, by the planting of Tobacco in this Nation;</p>

<p>It is Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice<pb n="1" /> and consent of his Council, That Sir <em>Will. Roberts, John Stone, Jervas Bennet, Hem. Elsing, Adam Bains</em> and <em>Jo. Bocket</em>, Esqs; or any three or more of them, be and are appointed Commissioners, and are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, authorized and required, by all fit and lawful <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> and means to put in Execution an Act of Parliam. dated the first of <em>April</em>, 1652. <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg> (<i>An Act prohibiting the planting of Tobacco</i> in England) and every clause, article, matter and thing therein contained, any Act or Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding; and all Officers Civil and Military, and all other persons, are required to be aiding and assisting unto the said Commissioners, or any person or persons <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by them in this Service, for the effectual execution of all the Powers and Authorities, by the said Act or this Ordinance, granted and <reg orig="Intrusted">Entrusted</reg> to the said Commissioners.</p>

<p>From <em>Minehead April 10</em>. Here is little <reg orig="newes">news</reg> in these parts, only that the <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> of <em>Brest</em> do much harm in this <reg orig="Chanel">Channel</reg>, having of late taken several vessels, whereof some of a considerable value which belonged to <em>Bristol</em>, some of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that were appointed to keep these Seas, being gone towards <em>Dublin</em>, and so to the Westward of <em>Scotland</em>, giveth more liberty to these Rogues to commit their <reg orig="villanies">villainies</reg> without any opposition, coming into the very mouth of the <em>Severn</em>, there is lately come some <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> from <em>Ireland</em>, who bringeth <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, that the plague is well appeased in most parts of that Country, and all things quiet, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a great want of people to manure the ground in many parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> April 10. I Have nothing to add to the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>, but that we are now very quiet in these parts; The party that went hence towards <em>Kelsay</em>, have secured the parts thereabouts, and the Borders of <em>England</em>, and are returned with some prisoners: the ship with Ammunition, &amp;c. came yesterday into <em>Leith</em> road, That about ten other Merchants were conveyed by the <em>Raven</em>, and <em>Providence</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg> April 2</i>. Yesterday the Enemy had a general <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> in <em>Sutherland</em> near <em>Skilbo</em>, they were about 1200 Foot, and 800 Horse (500 little better <reg orig="then">than</reg> baggage horses, and many wanting Pistols) and after the receipt of Orders from Lieut. Generalissimo <em>Middleton</em>, most were to march for the South<pb n="2" /> Highlands, and the rest continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. <em>Middleton</em> added to their number at the <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about 200 Horse and Foot, and hath ordered to be levied out of <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg> 250, Sutherland 300, <reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg> 500</em>, and <em>Stranarvar 300</em>. He expects hourly <em>Seaford</em> with 500, and <em>Mackoldwy</em> to be ready with his Levies; He gives out that he hath brought a great store of Spanish gold lent his Master by the Emperor, from whom is expected a great Loan, and many men which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother-in law, which he had <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends, for his often failing in his promised <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> to them.</p>

<p>This day Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Mitchil">Mitchell</reg></em> marched hither with nine Companies of Foot, six Troops of Horse, and a commanded party of 180, with five Troops of Dragoons, which are to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> to <em>Braban</em>, to which are added four Troops of Horse, and three Companies of Foot. The use of the March is to keep a Pass at <em>Dinghil</em>, which by a numerous concurrence of knowing men of the Country, will force them to fight us, stay where they are, or <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> the loss of their Horse, by length, badness of way, and want of Provisions, if they march to the South by the <reg orig="North west">Northwest</reg> <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, they having no other way to march otherwise.</p>

<p>From the Isle of <em>Wight</em> the same day. There is no news to impart you since my last, only that our Fleet hath weighed anchor from <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> -point</em>, and is now come further in, and are now riding in <em>Stoaks-Bay</em>, which is not far from the place they were at before those ships that were gone into <em>Portsmouth</em> to take in their provisions, and to be new fitted for the Sea are near ready, there being no care nor diligence wanting to have the same done with all expedition.</p>

<p>All Adventurers for Lands in <em>Ireland</em>, which have not drawn Lots for Baronies, are desired to take notice, The Committee for Claims, have appointed Thursday the 27 of this instant <em>April</em> 1654. to be a day for drawing of Lots for Baronies at Grocers-hall London, to begin at eight of the clock in the forenoon of the same day.</p>

<p><i>Will. <reg orig="Tibs">Tibbs</reg>, Clerk.</i></p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">From <em>Toulon</em>, the 20 of <em>March</em>.</head>

<p>Three ships or Men of War were here lately <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> into the Sea, and three more will suddenly follow; they are also making great preparations at <em>Marceil</em>. We hear that the Plague is at last ceased in <em><reg orig="Barcelone">Barcelona</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, 14 April.</i></head>

<p>This day came news as followeth.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Hamburg</em> the 2 of <em>April</em>. 1654.</head>

<p>The Queen of <em>Swedland</em> having declared her resolution about the <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> of her Crown and Power, to settle them in the hands of the Prince <em>Palatine</em>. Her Counsels have done their utmost to <reg orig="disswade">dissuade</reg> her Majesty from it, but that great Princess cannot be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> otherways. She hath stayed some time at <em>Nekoping</em>, to confer about that business, and is since come again to <em>Upsal</em>, to call together the States of the Kingdom of to the 10 of <em>May</em> next. That great and generous resolution is to be seen in the Letter written from the said Queen to Monsieur <em>Chanut</em>, the King of <em>France</em> his Ambassador, to the States General of the United Provinces; who having resided long by Her Majesty, and being great in her <reg orig="favor">favour</reg>, hath <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> to <reg orig="disswade">dissuade</reg> her from that intent.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Denmark</em> is at <em>Geluckstadt</em>, where the Dukes of <em><reg orig="Brunswyck">Brunswick</reg></em> and <em>Luneburg</em> are come to meet him, They write from <em>Bremen</em>, that the General <em>Coningsmark</em> is marching there-wards with some forces, not being known to what design. We have advice from <em>Dantzick</em>, that there is a very great likeness of a greater war in <em>Poland</em>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever was, by the <em>Moscovites</em>, who are in all readiness to fall heavily upon that Kingdom; which hath given occasion of passing twelve Articles in the Assembly of States at <em>Warsaw</em>, for the defence thereof, and to get moneys and provisions for the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, as also for the repairing of the Bulwarks, and Works of <em>Smolensko</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter of the Queen of <em>Swedland</em>, written in French to Monsieur <em>Chanut</em>, Ambassador of the King of <em>France</em>; a copy whereof was sent to the Lords States Generals of the United Provinces, concerning Her Majesties Resolution of <reg orig="surrendrng">surrendering</reg> Her Crown and Kingdom.</i></head>

<p><i>C.R.</i> I have formerly given you an account of the Reasons<pb n="4" /> which have prevailed with me to go on in my design of <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> up my Crown: You know that fancy of mine hath lasted long, and that I have not rashly resolved to put it in execution; but that after I have no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> eight years exercised my thoughts thereupon. I have about five years ago imparted that resolution to you, and I then perceived that nothing so much as your pure affection, and the interest you took in my Fortune, made you dissent from me, notwithstanding my reasons with you could not condemn. Whatsoever <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> you made to <reg orig="disswade">dissuade</reg> me from it, I was glad to see you could not <reg orig="finde">find</reg> nothing in that thought unworthy of <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>. You know what I told you thereupon, the last time I had the satisfaction of speaking with you: In the interim of such a long time past, none of the things <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> since, could ever alter my <reg orig="minde">mind</reg>. I have directed all my actions to that scope, and brought them to that end, without declining doubtfully from it. I am, at this time, ready to end that play, to retire <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg> the Stage, and do not trouble my <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> about the <em>Plaudite</em>. I know well, that the scene I have represented, hath not been composed after the Common Laws of the Stage; and it is a hard matter, that what is in it strong, masculine, and vigorous, should please, I give leave to any one to judge of it according to his genuine, not being able to deprive him of that liberty, nor willing to do it, although I could. I know that very few will give a <reg orig="favorable">favourable</reg> judgment, and I do <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> of you, that you are of that number. Other men are unacquainted with my Reasons, and my <reg orig="Humor">Humour</reg>, having never opened my thoughts thereupon, but to you, and to another friend, of a <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> great and noble enough to be of the same judgment with you therein. <i>Sufficit unus, sufficit nullus</i>, I do scorn the rest, and should <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> him of the company, whom I should conceive ridiculous enough to <reg orig="disswade">dissuade</reg> me from it. I will never trouble <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> of making them any Apology, and shall never be idle enough in that rest I do prepare for me, to remember them. I will <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> that <reg orig="leasure">leisure</reg>, to examine my life past, to correct my errors, without repenting, nor wondering at them. What a delight shall it be to me, to remember that I shall have taken pleasure in doing good to men, and to have without mercy inflicted punishment upon those that had deserved<pb n="5" /> it; I shall have some comfort to have never <reg orig="rendred">rendered</reg> any one guilty, that was not, but to have spared even those that were such.</p>

<p>I have preferred the preservation of the State to all other considerations; I have ever, with joy, sacrificed to its Interests and have nothing to reprove <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> of in the administration thereof. I have possessed without pride, I do forsake with facility: Therefore fear not for me. I am secure, and my welfare is not obnoxious to the hazard of the Fortune, whatsoever <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> I am happy. <i>Sum f&aelig;lix tamen Osuperi, nullique potestas hoc auferre Deo.</i> Nay, I am happier <reg orig="then">than</reg> any, and shall ever be so. I am not afraid of that Providence you speak to me of, <i>Omnia sunt propitia</i>. If it be pleased to <reg orig="condiscend">condescend</reg> to the regulating of my affairs, I do submit <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> with the respect, and resigning I <reg orig="ow">owe</reg> to its will: if it leaves me free the conduct of <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, I shall make use of all the faculties wherewith it hath endowed my soul, and my <reg orig="minde">mind</reg>, to make <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> happy, and I shall be so, so long as I shall be <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that there is nothing I should be afraid of, neither from God, neither from men. I shall <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> the remainder of my life to render those thoughts familiar to me, to strengthen my soul, and to spy from the Port, the <reg orig="labors">labours</reg> and toilings of those that are agitated in this life by the storms that arise, for want of giving our <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> to those meditations. Am I not worthy of envy, in the condition I am in? I should no doubt, <reg orig="finde">find</reg> too many that would envy my happiness, if they knew it: Nevertheless you love me enough to not envy it, and I do deserve it, seeing I am so ingenuous as to confess, that I have part of those thoughts from you. I have learned them in your discourses, and hopes to improve them yet some time with you in my rest. I do <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, that you cannot fail to your word, and that you will not leave, for this change, to be my friend, seeing I do <reg orig="devest">divest</reg> <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> of none of those things which are worthy of your esteem. I will conserve you my affection in whatsoever condition shall be, and I will make it appear to you, That no change whatsoever may alter those senses of my <reg orig="minde">mind</reg>, wherein I <reg orig="glorifie">glorify</reg> <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>. You know all that, and believe, no doubt, that the greatest assurance I can give you of me, is to tell you, that I shall ever be <em>CHRISTINA</em>.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>It is also advertised, that so far as discovery can be made of the Design of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> herein, touching her Resolutions to lay down her Crown, that the business, according to my best intelligence therein, and I have been something curious in it, that it is thus, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>That the Queen of <em><reg orig="Sweadens">Sweden's</reg></em> Design to surrender her Crown, is to further the Match of the Princes Royal (that is to say, of the Widow of the last Prince of <em>Orange</em>, who is Sister to <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, Titular King of <em>Scots</em>) with <em>Charls</em> the Successor of the Crown of Sweden, who is of the House of the <em>Palitinate</em>, that upon their Marriage may be brought in the Princes of <em>Germany</em> into an alliance, to support the House of <em>Nassa</em>, which is now <reg orig="tortering">tottering</reg> by the league of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em> with the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, in which she seems very cunningly to flatter the <em>French</em> Ambassador and the States, <em>&amp;c.</em> as be her lofty language, and Court-like Letter aforementioned doth appear.</p>

<p>And this Design without doubt hath been carried in by the Spaniards, by <em>Piemontille</em> the Agent of the King of Spain lately with the Queen in Sweden, who having made a fair progress in it is returned home; The Spaniard now looking upon that as his chiefest strength to defend himself in the confederacy with them in case it be effected.</p>

<p>And it is thought that the Queen of <reg orig="Sweaden">Sweden</reg> upon laying down of her Crown had thoughts of going into the <em>Hague</em>.</p>

<p>But Letters from the <em>Hague</em> say, That the Spanish Agent there hath made some Addresses to the States to desire that he may be included in the League of the States, and <em>Denmark</em> with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>From thence Letters confirm that the States have ratified the Peace, and that a Messenger is certainly coming over with it fully ratified by all the Provinces, to his <em>Highness the Lord Protector</em>.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector with his Lady and Family this day Dined at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, whither his Highness and Family are removed, and did this night lie there, and do there continue.</p>

<p>Several Petitions were this day received, and answers returned to some.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Additional Ordinance touching Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg> for this present year, 1654.</i></head><pb n="7" />

<p>Whereas in an Ordinance for better amending and keeping in repair the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg> within this Nation, It is ordained, amongst other things, that two or more able and sufficient <reg orig="Hous-holders">Householders</reg>, as in that Ordinance is expressed, should be elected and chosen upon the first Tuesday next <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> the five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> yearly, to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-waies">Highways</reg>, within their respective Parishes for the year <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg>: And whereas by the reason of the late publishing of the said Ordinance, the time aforesaid for such Election for this year was elapsed, so as such Election could not be made on that day in pursuance of the said Ordinance, whereby the benefit intended to the people thereby is obstructed; Be it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the persons which already are chosen, or shall be chosen before the first day of <em>May</em> 1654. to be Surveyors of the <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> (which election is hereby <reg orig="injoyned">enjoined</reg> to be made in every Place and Parish by the time aforesaid, under the penalties in that Ordinance expressed) in case no election hath been already made, shall undertake the said Office, and be sworn on, or before, the sixth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid, under the penalties in the said ordinance set down in that behalf, and shall be Surveyors for this present year, as if such election had been made on the first said <em>Tuesday</em> after the said Five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> last, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the said Ordinance to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>And the said Surveyors so sworn, and all other persons authorised by the said Ordinance, shall be, and are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, to proceed in, and put in execution, all the Directions, Powers and Authorities in the said Ordinance contained, as fully to all intents and purposes, as if the election had been made on the day therein appointed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, 15 April.</i></head>

<p>His Highness went this day to <em>Hampton Court</em>, and returned again at night.</p>

<p>Pope <em>Innocentius</em> the tenth (now Pope of <em>Rome</em>) hath lately published a Declaration, touching the <em><reg orig="Arminian">Armenian</reg></em> points, in which he hath declared for the <reg orig="Jesuite">Jesuit</reg> faction; and by which we may perceive something of the same design hath been <reg orig="endeavored">endeavoured</reg> <pb n="8" /> in <em>England</em>, had not the Lord by the late change of Government prevented it; and therefore we may bless God for the present Commissioners for Approbation of <reg orig="Preechers">Preachers</reg>, that <reg orig="onely">only</reg> such as are found, may be employed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance and Declaration of the Pope of the 13. of <em>June</em>, 1653.</i></head>

<p>Whereas great differences are risen in several parts, and chiefly in <em>France</em> upon these 5 Points following, touching which, some Bishops there have importuned that upon the delivery of the said Points to Me, a clear Judgement may be given therein, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p><i>1. That some Commands of God are impossible to be kept by righteous men, who desire and <reg orig="indeavor">endeavour</reg> it, according to the present power they have received, and that they want grace by which obedience to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Laws should be possible. 2. That inward grace in the state of the lapsed Nature is resistible. 3. That to deserve and procure Grace in the state of lapsed nature, there is not required in man a liberty of necessity, but that a liberty from compulsion is enough. 4. That the Semi-Pelagians, who held that inward preventing Grace was necessary to every work, and to the beginning of Faith were held <reg orig="Hereticks">Heretics</reg>, because they would have the Grace of God to be such as the wills of men could resist or obey. 5. That it is Semi-Pelagianism, to hold that Christ died and shed his blood for all men.</i></p>

<p>We after weighty considerations thereof have commanded some Cardinals and many Masters of <reg orig="Theologie">Theology</reg> to be assembled, to whom we have delivered the said Points, and have desired their opinions both by word of mouth, and in writing, which after serious deliberation were brought in and our Judgement thereupon we are arrived at in this following Declaration, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p><i>We declare the first to be wicked, blasphemous, accursed and heretical. We declare the second to be heretical. We declare the third to be heretical. We declare the fourth to be false and heretical. We declare the fifth to be false and impious: And to hold that Christ died only for those that are predestinate, we hold it to be impious, blasphemous, contemptible, destructive to all good conversation, and heretical.</i></p>

<p>We do therefore command all Christian men and women, that neither they <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg>, learn, nor preach otherwise <reg orig="then">than</reg> as we have declared in this our Ordinance, upon pain of such punishments as are to be inflicted upon <reg orig="hereticks">heretics</reg>. And we do command all Patriarchs<pb n="9" />, <reg orig="Arch-bishops">Archbishops</reg>, Bishops, and other ordinary Inquisitors, to proceed against all opposers whomsoever, and to use all means to restrain them from any other Faith touching these Points, <reg orig="then">than</reg> is hereby declared, and (if need be) to use the assistance of the temporal Magistrate.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em>Rome</em>, in the year of the Incarnation of our Lord, 13. June 1653. in the 9th year of our Popedom. <em>Innocencius</em> the 10th.</i></p>

<p><i>Hi. Datarius. G. Gualterius. P. Ciampinus.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 17 April</i></head>

<p>This day came news of the good success of a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Squadron of 3 of the English <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> near the Isle of <em>Bass</em> against a fleet of <em>French</em>, as is certified by a Letter from Cap. <em>Cubit</em> commander of the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> one of the 3 that was in the Engagement.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the <em>Capt. Cubit</em> of the late fight with the French.</i></head>

<p>We departed from <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> the 1 of this month, that night we met the <em>Falmouth</em> and visited some ships of <em>Ostend</em> which came from St. <em>Lucas</em>. The third West-south-west from the Lizard met several ships of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, Stockholm, Emden</em>, and <em>Limbeck</em> with two ships of <em>Dover</em> in their company, all which came from St. <em>Martins</em> with Salt and Wine from that time until the 7. we were without the channel 20 or 30 leagues off. The 7 day the <em>Middleborough</em> came to us. The 9. we met with one who told me that I might expect with the first wind from S. <em>Mallows</em> 4 ships laden with cloth bound for S. <em>Lucas</em>, and 6 ships that were to go for the Bank. The 10 we chased a <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into <em>Broadsoand</em>. The 11, the wind coming to the South, and South-south-east, we with the <em>Middleborough</em> and <em>Falmouth</em>, very early in the morning passed to the northward of <em>Ushant</em>, and about 3 leagues to the eastward of the <em>Loor Rock</em>, descried a fleet of ships standing to the westward 48 sail. I knew not what to make of them at first, their number being so far exceeded what I expected, but found them to be <em>French</em> ships, we got the wind of them, and took a full view of their fleet, we took their <reg orig="flag ships">flagships</reg> to be cloth ships, fell in among them, where an Admiral and a Rear-Admiral laid near one the other, with divers ships by them. The Rear Adm. being windermost, and the best ship in the fleet, I came up with him first very close, and passed a broad side on him, and was very well seconded<pb n="10" /> by the <em>Middleborough</em>, the first and the second time. And as we received shot from several of their ships which lay by him, so especially from the Admiral which laid to Leeward, upon which also we spent some shot, one of which this time of Service carried his <reg orig="Main-mast">Mainmast</reg> by the board, and that <reg orig="halled">hauled</reg> his fore <reg orig="Top-mast">Topmast</reg> after it, so as he could do us little more hurt. Going to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> our third broad side, I shot the Rear <reg orig="Admirals">Admiral's</reg> main <reg orig="Top mast">Topmast</reg> by the board, and another <reg orig="ships">ship's</reg> fore <reg orig="Top-mast">Topmast</reg>. After the fifth broad side from us, and two from the <em>Middleburgh</em>, as above, he took in his flag, and called for quarter, came aboard with their Boat, and I sent men to possess her, but found it impossible to save her, being all torn to <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>. As soon as their men were aboard of us, she sunk without saving the value of six pence besides the Flag. She was a ship of 260 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, 18 guns, 4 brass Stock sowlers, and 85 men bound to <em>Burneus</em> for Salt, and thence to <em>Canade</em> to fish, her name the <em>Fourdore, Sebastian Penoire</em> commander, who informed me that all the rest were on the same design only two bound for S. <em><reg orig="Christophers">Christopher's</reg></em> with passengers. Having freed <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> from her, we bore with another, and coming to take her, we found her left by the company who were got into <em>Shallops</em>, one of which we took, and learned by them she was sinking, she was then on the <em>Curene</em>, her name the St. <em>Clement, John Gerrat</em> Master, The had 70 men and 14 guns, she received her shot from us about the time the <em>Fourdore</em> <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg>. The wind very much increasing, we stood after some which stood into the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, and near the Isle of <em>Bass</em> took the <em>John Baptist, John Paus</em> Master, with 14 guns and 70 men. The night approaching and the ships out of sight we came away with these. This was all done i9n sight of that coast or <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>. I <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God we lost not a man, had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> two hurt. The <em>Middleburgh</em> took the <em>Veirge de bon Voyage</em>, that Admiral whose Masts were shot off, as aforesaid with 18 guns and 70 men, and the <em>Lou Blanch</em> with 17 guns and 60 men. The <em>Falmouth</em> took the <em>Inques</em> with 8 guns, and 40 men.</p>

<p><i>Joseph Cubit.</i></p>

<p><em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> in <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> Sound 14 <em>April</em>, 1654.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of those ships of St. <em>Mallos</em> of the Fleet with which the three English ships fought.</i></head>

<p>The <em>Foundore</em> with 18 guns, and 85 men. The St. <em>Clement</em> 14 guns, and 70 men. The <em>Leveirg</em> 18 guns, 70 men, The <em>Lou</em><pb n="11" /> <em>Blanch</em> with 11 Guns, and 60 men. The St. <em>Jacques</em> with 8 Guns, and 40 men. The <em>John Baptist</em> with 14 Guns, and 70 men. The <em>Pelican</em> with 16 Guns, and 75 men. The <em>Concord</em> with 17 Guns, and 70 men. The St. <em>Peter</em> with 18 Guns, and 70 men. The <em>Protect</em> with 12 Guns, and 70 men. The <em>Mariagra</em> with 10 Guns, and 50 men. The <em>George</em> with 12 Guns, and 50 men. The St. <em>Joseph</em> with 12 Guns. The <em>Chevalier</em> with 8 Guns, and 20 men. The <em>Le Fume</em> with 8 Guns, and 55 men. The <em><reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg></em> with 4 Guns, and 20 men. The Palma with 6 Guns, and 20 men. The <em>Julia Lunia</em> with 4 Guns, and 20 men. Four more had 14 Guns, and <unclear>80</unclear> men <reg orig="a peice">apiece</reg>. The rest were Vessels of the Coast and <em>Normans</em>, which had some Guns, but the number we know not.</p>

<p>Of which number, Two of the chief were sunk, and four taken; and of those that escaped, divers were battered, and sustained much loss.</p>

<p><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, 10 April. <i>The enemy hasten to a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, and Colonel <em>Morgan</em> in preparing towards them; when General <em>Monk</em> is come hither with the additional forces are to follow, I believe you will hear either of some sudden action, and a vanishing of their Levies. We do almost every day fall into their Quarters to prevent their Levies; and some times do meet with some of them. They expected Supplies from <em><reg orig="Westmerland">Westmoreland</reg></em>, but as yet few are come.</i></p>

<p>There is appointed to go for <em>Scotland</em>, Colonel <em>Pride</em> with his Regiment, and the 5 Companies of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment that are in <em>Yorkshire</em>, who have received Orders to march.</p>

<p>General <em>Monk</em> passed well in health through <em>Yorkshire</em>, and it is believed that about this time he is in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>A Messenger came this day from the States General of the United Provinces, to the Ambassadors here in <em>England</em>, with a Ratification of the Peace; whereupon an Address was presently made to His Highness, the Lord Protector; of which, you shall have more in due place.</p>

<p>The Lord Lieutenant Admiral, Baron of <em>Opdam</em>, was then at the <em>Hague</em> when the Articles were signed and sealed by the States, as also Vice Admiral <em>Witte Wittense, Ruiter, John Everson</em>, with many other Captains of the Fleet, who received Commission from the Lords States, to provide all things speedily that may be necessary for their ships: And it is thought that the<pb n="12" /> general Rendezvous, both of the Merchant ships, and Men of War, will be at Goree.</p>

<p>One <em>Easterling</em> had a great Flute laden with Salt, that lay long at <em>Flushing</em>, and might have made a good Market for his Salt, but stayed to raise the price yet higher, at last his ship was cast away upon the Flats in the last storm, and so he lost all.</p>

<p>The French in <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em> are afraid that the King of <em>Spain</em> will deliver into the hands of His Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, the Town of <em>Dunkirk</em> for security of Forces which they fear shall be sent over to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, for the service of the King of <em>Spain</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 18 April.</i></head>

<p>This day the Council had under consideration, An Ordinance for the continuance of the Repealing of the Act for the Commissioners for Debts; also about an Ordinance touching Postages was under debate.</p>

<p>This day Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>, Colonel <em>Sidenham</em>, and Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, three of the Lords of the Council, were sent Commissioners, with Mr. <em><reg orig="Jesop">Jessop</reg></em> Clerk of the Council, to the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, Ambassador from the King of <em>France</em>, to Treat with him touching the Treaty with that Kingdom, for renewing of Amity; considering which, he lately delivered his <reg orig="Ambassie">Embassy</reg> to His Highness, the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador gave a late visit to the Dutch Ambassadors.</p>

<p><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 15 April. <i>Here are four French prizes brought in by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Friggot">Frigate</reg>, and the <em>Falmouth</em>, and <em>Middleborough</em>, which they took in a late engagement with a Fleet of them near the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> of <em>Basse</em>, besides two sunk; a List of both which, is here <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg>. They will suddenly be fitted out again; and the <em>Paul</em>, and old <em>Warwick</em> are ready to <reg orig="sale">sail</reg>, and the <em><reg orig="Saphir">Sapphire</reg></em> and <em>Constant Warwick</em> will be ready this night, or <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Prizes taken and ships sunk in the fight between the 3 English ships, <em>viz</em>. The <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Middleborough</em>, and the <em>Falmouth</em>; and the French Fleet near the Isle of <em>Basse</em>, on the 11 April. 1654.</i></head>

<p>1. The Admiral sunk, called the <em>Roundore</em>, commanded by Captain <em>Sebastian Penotre</em>, a ship of 18 Iron Guns, and 4 Brass,<pb n="13" /> with 85 men, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the men saved, and one Flag. 2 The St. <em>Clement</em> sunk, of which <em>John Gerrat</em> was Master, a ship of 14 Guns, with 70 men, some of which men are taken; but divers of them got into other ships. 3 The Rear Admiral taken, called the <em>Leveirge</em>, a ship of 18 Guns, with 70 men. 4 The <em>Leu Blanch</em> taken, with 11 Guns, and 60 men in her. 5 The St. <em>Jacques</em> taken with 8 Guns, and 40 men in her. 6 The <em>John Baptist</em> taken with 14 Guns, and 70 men in her.</p>

<p>Paris, 10 April. <i><em>Conde</em> hath routed a Regiment of 400 horse of the <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> <em>De Vieuvilles</em>. Duke <em>D' Augville</em> is gone to the Duke of <em><reg orig="Orleance">Orleans</reg></em>, perhaps to enjoy Conde's estate, in behalf of the marriage of his second daughter to Duke <em>D' Anguiens</em>, the said <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> son. Duke <em>Espersnoon</em> is gone from the Court discontented with <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> marriage of a <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> with the Duke of <em>Candale</em>. The Princess of <em><reg orig="Savoys">Savoy's</reg></em> Ambassador here, desires a <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> of <em><reg orig="Mazarines">Mazarine's</reg></em> for her Son, the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> Mother is to go to reside there now shortly.</i></p>

<p>Rhine, 14 April. <i>The French Forces from <em>Leige</em> have done great outrages about <em>Frier</em>, chiefly in the Abbey of St. <em>Maxamin</em>, and where the people had put themselves under the protection of <em>Spain</em>. The Emperor <reg orig="labors">labours</reg> for Rixday. Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> is still at the <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Court, not knowing yet whether he shall go to <em>Flanders</em>. The Elector of <em>Colen</em> <reg orig="labored">laboured</reg> to seize upon all the Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorains">Lorain's</reg></em> Goods, Jewels, and Moneys at <em><reg orig="Franckford">Frankford</reg></em>, since his imprisonment, but hath found nothing of value.</i></p>

<p><i>Warsaw, 12 March, 1654.</i> The <em>Muscovites</em> before they would grant to the <em>Cossacks</em> their protection, have obliged them to subscribe to a shameful agreement, and among other things, that they shall renounce the Amity of the <em>Tartarians</em>; that they shall never admit of, nor acknowledge their old Polish Lords; that they shall suffer no <em>Jews</em> to live in the County of <em><reg orig="Uckrain">Ukraine</reg></em>, that those that shall buy <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of them, shall be debarred from coming into the Church for three weeks time; that it shall be unlawful to any of them, to wear any <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> made after the Polish mode, or to wear any Red or Yellow Boots, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> Black ones; that they shall drink no strong Waters, nor take Tobacco, nor play at Cards, <em>&amp;c.</em> That Treaty is attributed to the desperate condition of their General <em>Kimilinsky</em>. The<pb n="14" /> Grand Duke of <em>Moscow</em> hath sent five of his chief Officers into that Province of <em><reg orig="Uckrain">Ukraine</reg></em> to govern there, having divided the same into so many Palatinates, and sent thither some of his Priests to reform all the <em>Russian</em> Churches, and rebaptise the people; who being most addicted to their own Religion, do look upon that change with a very great regret, and do much dislike also, that all their men able to bear Arms, are listed in every place, the rest being designed to Till the Ground, or to serve in the Armies as <reg orig="Pioniers">Pioneers</reg>. Their Army is about <em>Nieper</em>, all the strong Passages of it being delivered up to the said Duke, by the said <em>Kimilinsky</em>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 30 March</i>: The Swedish forces drawn out of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places in the <reg orig="Arch-bishoprick">Archbishopric</reg> of Bremen, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> daily increase, and are marching towards Bremerbourgh under General <em>Coningsmarck</em>, who intends to raise a Fort there to secure the <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a great annoyance to the commerce of that place, the Magistrates whereof have therefore sent Lieut. Col. <em>Keller</em> with 400 men and some <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordinance thither, to hinder the same.</p>

<p><i>Firbourg in Brisgaw 28 March</i>: The <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> of Inspruck having <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> under his horse, hath been dangerously wounded in the head; The States in his Territories having lately been assembled about a League defensive they will march into the Countries beyond the Rhine, whither they <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to draw the Duke of <em>Wittembirgh</em>, and the <reg orig="Marquisses">Marquises</reg> of <em>Baden</em> and <em>Dourlach</em>.</p>

<p><i>Colen 4 April</i>. The Forces of the Electors of Collen and Triers have besieged the <reg orig="Fortresse">Fortress</reg> of Humanstein, the Commander whereof inclines to a parley, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> <reg orig="bee">be</reg> speedily relieved by the Spaniards, who are gathering together for that end; Mr <em>Faber</em> being in the mean time in <reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg> with his Forces to hinder the said relief.</p>

<p><i>Naples 15 March</i>: Some Merchants here have engaged to furnish 4000 suits of <reg orig="Cloathes">Clothes</reg>, 8000 shirts, 2000 hats, and the like number of Swords, <reg orig="shooes">shoes</reg> and <reg orig="stockins">stockings</reg>, for the Spanish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> in Catalonia, whither our Viceroy intends to <unclear><!-- could be lend -->tend</unclear> shortly 30 battering <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, newly cast here, with great quantity of ammunition. <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath sent into Spain for 6000 natural Spaniards to supply the place of so many here, who being well <unclear>trained</unclear>, shall<pb n="15" /> <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent to the field Army. <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath sent into Dalmatia for raising a Regiment of Croats.</p>

<p><i>Venice 28 March</i>: Generalissimo <em>Movenigo</em> prepares for <em>Candia</em> to appease the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> that begin to mutiny for want of pay. <reg orig="Signieur">Signor</reg> <em>Battista Nani</em> doth prepare for his <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg> towards the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg>, <reg orig="Signieur">Signor</reg> <em>Gasparo Luca</em>, a famous Merchant, offers the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> 100000 <reg orig="Duckets">Ducats</reg> towards the charge of the <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, if they will receive him among their Nobles.</p>

<p>Madrid 24 March: <i>The fleet from New Spain, are not expected before June next, with that of Peru, his Majesty hath sent to the Duke <em>Vel Infantado</em>, Governor of <reg orig="Ciciley">Sicily</reg>, to set out as many Vessels as <reg orig="hee">he</reg> can, and to raise 2000 foot to help him.</i></p>

<p>A Gentleman from <em>Gilderland</em>, with many Gentlemen attending him in divers Coaches, did from thence this day congratulate His Highness, the Lord Protector, in His Government; and several Gentlemen from other parts beyond the Seas have done the like.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 19 April.</i></head>

<p>Divers Aldermen of the City of <em>London</em> were this day with His Highness, the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The <em>Constant Warwick</em> hath brought in Prize a <em>Brest</em> Man of War with 8 Guns, and 50 men into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The Articles of Peace are delivered to his Highness, the Lord Protector, in a Silver Box, signed and sealed by the States of the United Provinces, all concurring; and His Highness hath appointed the like to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> here, and to pass the Great Seal of <em>England</em>; and then he will sign it by His Sign <em>Manual</em>, which then is to be put into a Silver Box, and to be sent to the <em>Hague</em>; and after signification of the States General receiving thereof, it will be published in both Commonwealths.</p>

<p><i>Leith, 13 April.</i> This day a party from <em>Dalkeith</em> took one <em>Malcolm Rogers</em> (Agent for <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, who brought several Commissions from him) and also one <em>Stephens</em>, who had been a <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> in <em>Leith</em>, little above a <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> since: But the worst <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of News is, That on Tuesday last Cap. <em>Southwood</em> Commander of the <em>White Raven</em> going from <em>Leith</em> Road, towards <em>Newcastle</em>, was set upon by eleven Dutch Men of War, boarded and taken. This day a Private Man of War of ours, was <reg orig="accidently">accidentally</reg> blown up in <em>Leith</em> <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>, and 6 Men killed.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> with 850 horse, and 1600 foot hath beset the enemy, who is 800 horse and 3000 foot, resolving to fight them &amp; they can hardly escape him.</p>

<p><reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <em>Staner</em>, and <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <em>Smith</em> Commanders of the <unclear>Tonnington</unclear> and the <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken an Holland East India ship outward bound of 800 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with 750 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of Goods, and tour chest of silver.</p>

<p>A Christian sober, plain Exercitation on the Two Grand Practical Controversies of these times, Instant Baptism, and Singing of Psalms, proved by Scripture, by C. Sidenham, later Teacher to a Church at Newcastle. Sold by F. Tyton at the Three Daggers near the Inner Temple.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>