<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState222">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 222</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 25 of <em>Decemb.</em> To Thursday the 22 day of <em>December</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
  
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 22. December. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day was published this Proclamation following.</p>

<head level="3">By the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>

<head level="3"><i>A PROCLAMATION of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, with the consent of His Council, for continuing all Persons being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="publicke">public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> further Direction.</i></head>

<p><em>Oliver, Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, considering that whereas the exercise of the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, is invested and established in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, assisted <pb n="1" />with a Council, and left thereupon the settled ordinary course of Justice in the Commonwealth (if remedy were not provided) might receive interruption, His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in His Care of the State, and <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Justice thereof (reserving to future consideration the reformation and <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> of any abuses of <reg orig="mis-Government">Misgovernment</reg>, upon better knowledge taken thereof) is pleased, and doth hereby <reg orig="expressely">expressly</reg> <reg orig="Signifie">Signify</reg>, Declare, and <reg orig="Ordaine">Ordain</reg>, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, who have power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the meeting of the next Parliament to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, That all persons who in the tenth day of this instant <em>December</em> were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction or Government within this Commonwealth; shall be and shall so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and Places respectively as formerly they held and enjoyed the same, and not otherwise, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which respect or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Justice, and all Proceedings of what nature soever, in Courts of common Law, or Equity, or in the Court of Admiralty, or by Commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said tenth day of this instant <em>December</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further Order given by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> therein. And that in the mean time (for preservation of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, for Safety of the State) all the said persons, of whatsoever Place, Degree, or Condition, may not <reg orig="faile">fail</reg> every one severally according to his respective Place, Office or Charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all Duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them, whilst the former Government was in being.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 21. of December, in the year of our Lord, 1653.</i></p>

<p><i>Dalkeith December 17.</i> thus. The Enemy is departed from the hithermost parts of <em>Atholl</em>, and gone to <em>Kirkmichel</em> in order to their march Northwards; as I am informed <em>Kenmore</em> and <pb n="2" /><em>Glencarn</em> are both there, and their force reported to be 500 Foot and 500 Horse; but those that gave me Information that saw them, affirm they are not <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> that number, they lye under very many discouragements, and every place so eaten up where they come, that they are forced upon often removals; and now provision of Mutton, and <reg orig="Beefe">Beef</reg> begins to decay: I hear they intend for the North, that their quarters upon the Lowlands may be more assured and broader, where they expect the landing of foreign forces, Ammunition and <reg orig="Mony">Money</reg> from their Majesty and the States of <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p><em>Atholl</em> doth nothing considerable; the people refuse to raise his men according to command, one that saw him and his <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he hath not got above 40 foot, and Major <em>Mercer</em> is there with about 60 horse.</p>

<p>Cap. <em>Elsemore</em> of Col. <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> Regiment, sent out a party the other day from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, who took one Cap. <em>Stuart</em> who had a Commission from <em>Lorne</em> to raise Forces, and four others and killed three on the place. The Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> last week at his house of <em>Bogy-geith</em>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg> December 19.</i> A private man of War, we have intelligence hath brought into Holy Land two Dutch Vessels <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the East Country both being about an hundred and fifty <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, and the like commodities.</p>

<p>From <em>Falmouth</em> 19 instant. There were many ships in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> which are now all gone to their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> intended Ports. The Dutch are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts, so that it is very hard to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> by the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end without a good convoy: they have we hear, taken a ship of <em>London</em> coming from New <em>England</em>, laden with Masts, Beaver Skins, and the like commodities. Here have been some of the States ships to wash and tallow, and to take in fresh water, but they are all at Sea again, there remaining none at present in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Deale</em> 23. We have news this day that some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken some Beclanders belonging to <em>Calice</em>, who were bound for <em>Roan</em> and <em>Cane</em> in <em>Normandy</em>, laden with divers sorts of commodities, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> them into <em>Stoaks</em> Bay, where we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monke</em> with his <reg orig="Sqadron">Squadron</reg> was <pb n="3" />about four days since: Those ships lately gone from hence bound for <em>Roan</em> are safely arrived there, and their convoy is returned back.</p>

<p>Further from <em>Scotland, Decem</em>. 19. that the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> disperse themselves into several parts is confirmed; they are now <reg orig="endevouring">endeavouring</reg> to reduce their levies into form, by laying them upon all the nearest Parishes to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, but their demands are so high, that it is impossible the country (though willing) should be able to bear them. We have information that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all his endeavours to raise and force men, horses, and monies in the South, and intends to make some Inroads into the Borders of <em>England</em>, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> prevented, which is the more probable by that Information from <em>Durham</em>, That twenty horsemen well mounted, and armed with Pistols and Swords went through that <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> on Tuesday <!--??check typo-->last, by break of day amongst them a person of quality. The same number and party lay at <em>Peblis</em> on Saturday night last, and with them Col. <em>Wogan</em>, formerly a Capt. of Dragoons in the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> Army. Thursday nigh last Lieut. <em>Whitmore</em> going with a party toward the Hills took one Major <em>Morehead</em> (a prisoner of war, and yet upon parole and security) well mounted and armed going to the Enemy as himself <reg orig="confest">confessed</reg>. They <reg orig="doe">do</reg> much hearten their party, that their King is come into <em>Holland</em>; that Col. <em>Drummond</em> is <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg> with 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg>, <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> and ammunition; and that the Dutch have left off treating with the English: with all which, they feign a Post came lately from their King.</p>

<p>On Friday morning last, a party of these <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> Pilferers met the Post boy going from <em>Leith</em> with Letters for <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Haddington took his horse and Letters, and some Money, so that now it will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Powel</em> were this day brought before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, and examined touching some words that fell from them in preaching an praying, concerning the present Government; and were ordered to remain in the hands of the <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further consideration.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Montague</em> is one of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of State, besides those <pb n="4" />thirteen mentioned in the last <reg orig="Weeke">Week</reg>.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Thurlow</em> is Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Scobel</em> and Mr. <em>Jesop</em> are clerks to the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>.</p>

<p>The three Dutch Deputies treated this night personally with a Committee of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, <em>viz.</em> The Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Mr. <em>Strickland</em>, and Mr. <em>Thurlow</em>, in the Horse chamber at <em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and were together from 5 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> till after 7 at night. There is still hopes of agreement, a few meetings will determine something now, one way or another.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 23 December</i></head>

<p>Since the Declaration delivered to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by the major part of the House present when the Parliament brake up, divers of those Members that were absent, have freely been to subscribe to the same, abundantly blessing God for the present change of Government.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em> is preparing for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to reside in, and the old <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> chamber is sitting for the Honourable his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> to meet in,</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg> 22 Decemb</em>. Capt. <em>Richard Newberry</em> Commander of the Lawrell, is come in hither, who had been <reg orig="outby">out by</reg> order from the Generals, with his ship and the Ruby, the Kent, and the Industry, to ply between the Isle of <em>Wight</em> and the French coasts, where <reg orig="hee">he</reg> took some prizes: when they were toward the French coasts, they made a discovery of 4 <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of ships, to whom they gave chase, and followed them so close that they took two of them. Men were taken out of the Kent to man one of the prizes, which is come hither to the Downs.</p>

<p>The other prize was manned by men out of the Lawrell, which is also coming hither. Their lading is French wines, which they had taken in at <reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>.</p>

<p>The Lawrell and the Kent <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, are again preparing to go out to ply to the Westward.</p>

<p>Capt. <em>Martin</em>, commander of the Bristol <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, who hath the command of the Western squadron, meeting with Captain <em>Crispin</em>, commander of the Assistance, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> appointed him to convoy some Hamburgers, and <reg orig="Sweadish">Swedish</reg> ships, which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> safe to <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, and his Order being then to go out upon a <pb n="5" /><reg orig="designe">design</reg> with the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> from <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> to seek out if they could meet with any of the ships from <em>Brest</em>.</p>

<p>The Assistance and the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> sailed over to <em>Ushant</em> and <em>Cruse</em> and parts thereabout seven or eight <reg orig="daies">days</reg>, and they were together at the <em>Fourne</em> Rock. And the 14. <em>December</em> they sailed both together within <em>Ushant</em>, and being got thither they sailed into <em>Couquet</em> Road, and there anchored a while, after which they went out <reg orig="againe">again</reg> and <reg orig="plyed">plied</reg> even into the very mouth of <em>Brest</em> River, but the <em>Brest</em> men durst not stir out, whereupon our ships in the evening anchored in <em>Cammerit</em> Bay, to see if there they could find, or thereabouts meet with any of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> ships, or others of those of <em>Brest</em> men of War: But they had <reg orig="scukt">sucked</reg> in and durst none of them venture out.</p>

<p>There was a Fly boat a <reg orig="vessell">vessel</reg> of eight guns, and some six <reg orig="smal">small</reg> French ships more, who upon our approach ran themselves <reg orig="ashoare">ashore</reg>, and we have since taken three prizes about <em>Couquet</em> Road.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 24 Decemb.</i></head>

<p>By His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, these two Ordinances following were this day passed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>1. An Ordinance for continuing the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg></i></head>

<p>Whereas the time for receiving the duty of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> and New Impost is near expiration, and it being necessary for the peace and safety of this Commonwealth that the same be continued, both for the satisfaction of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Debts charged upon the said Grand Receipt, as also for carrying on the weighty <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> of this Commonwealth, His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, doth Ordain, and be it Ordained, that all and every the Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament touching the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, and every Clause, Sentence and Article in them or any of them contained, and now in force, as well for the collecting gathering and receiving, as concerning the Government and Ordering of the Excise and New Impost, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> continued, and the Duty of Excise or New Impost, according to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Rates in them, or any of them expressed, be received, collected and paid in and through <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, <pb n="6" />and Town and Port of <em><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg></em> upon <em>Tweed</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the five and twenty day of <em>March</em> next coming; And that <em>Luke Hodges</em>, <em>Thomas Bulstrode</em>, and <em>William Parker</em>, or any two or more of them, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> and are hereby constituted and appointed Commissioners of the Grand Excise and New Impost, and are hereby <reg orig="Impowred">Empowered</reg> and <reg orig="Authorized">Authorised</reg> to exercise and put in execution all and every the Powers and Authorities given or granted by, or contained in all or any the said Acts, Ordinances or Orders of Parliament, touching the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> and New Impost, as well for the collecting &amp; receiving the several rates aforesaid, as concerning the government and ordering of the said Excise or new Impost, as fully and amply as any Commissioners for Excise; at the time of the making of this present Ordinance, may or ought to have <reg orig="don">done</reg>, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> observe such further Orders and Directions as they shall from time to time receive from His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his Council touching the same.</p>

<p>And for their care, pains, and service therein, they shall have one penny in every Twenty shilling raised and <reg orig="levyed">levied</reg> for Excise and New Impost.</p>

<p>Provided nevertheless, and it is hereby Declared, That from and after the nine and twentieth day of <em>December</em>, One thousand six hundred fifty three, The Commissioners afore named shall not let to <reg orig="farme">farm</reg>, or admit any person of persons to <reg orig="farme">farm</reg> the Excise of any Goods, <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> and Manufacturers that are excisable by any Act, Ordinance or Order of Parliament, without the Order and Direction of such persons as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be appointed thereunto by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his Council; But the said Commissioners, or any two or more of them, shall <reg orig="mannage">manage</reg> and carry on the same, according to the best of their Judgements, by such good <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> and means as may be most for the ease of the People, and advantage of the Commonwealth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>2. An Ordinance for continuation of one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, An Act for Redemption of Captives.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That one Act of Parliament <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the Redemption of Captives</i>, Printed by Order of Parliament of the Six and twentieth day of <pb n="7" /><em>March</em>, One thousand six hundred and fifty, for and concerning the payment of one fourth part of one <em>per Centum</em>, being on shilling for every twenty shillings paid for <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> and Subsidy according to the new Book of Rates, and all and every the Clauses, Forfeitures, Penalties, <reg orig="Provisoes">Provisos</reg> and Powers therein contained, in reference to the collecting, receiving, and due payment, of the said Duty of one <em>per cent</em>. in such sort as by the said Act is appointed, be continued from and after the twenty <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> day of <em>Decem</em>. one thousand six hundred fifty and three, until the third day of <em>October</em>, which shall be in the year One thousand six hundred fifty and four, and no longer; And that the Commissioners for the customs for the time being, their Deputy and Deputies <reg orig="doe">do</reg> receive and collect the same, and shall pay out and <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> all such sum and sums of money, as have been or shall be by them received and collected by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the said before-mentioned Act, or any subsequent Act for continuation thereof, or by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of this present Ordinance, in such sort as His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> with the advice of his Council, or such person or persons as shall be appointed thereunto, shall order and direct, whose Order from time to time shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a sufficient discharge unto the said Commissioners for the Customs, for the same.</p>

<p><i>Henry Scobel Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> his Council, this day ordered Mr. <em>Feake</em> and Mr. <em>Powel</em> to be set at liberty.</p>

<p>This day was sent up a List of the <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> now ready for present service.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Scilley">Scilly</reg> 20 December,</i> Two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since failed Capt. <em>Martin</em> and the Portland <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> this way, who met with Cap. <em>Crispin</em> and Cap. <em>Penrosse</em>, with some prizes they had taken upon the coasts of <em>France</em>. The last night was a very sad <reg orig="storme">storm</reg> which continued <reg orig="untill">until</reg> this morning, with great violence, so that the Sails of the Yards blew away, which being over, some sailed towards the coasts of <em>France</em>, and others towards <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday, 26 December.</i></head>

<p>Papers were this day presented to the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council touching a Petition from the Town of <em>Lin</em> about <pb n="8" />the Fen <reg orig="drayners">drainers</reg>. The particulars are to <reg orig="adverise">advertise</reg>;</p>

<p>1 That the Port of <em>Lin</em> is an ancient and <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> Port, and hath belonging to it about 80 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of Ships and Barks <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> for the trade of Salt, Coal, Fish, and other necessaries, with which ten several Counties were supplied more or <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> from that Port by the benefit of several navigable Rivers, that had their out-fall at <em>Lin</em>.</p>

<p>2. That the Haven of <em>Lin</em> hath been ever known to be a safe and commodious <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg>.</p>

<p>3 That the undertakers for <reg orig="drayning">draining</reg> the Fens, have of late erected a Sasse or <reg orig="Sluce">Sluice</reg> near Salter load upon the River <em>Ouse</em>, beneath the mouth of most of the navigable Rivers that fell into it, whereby the passage of the Tides into all the said Rivers which were wont to be filled twice in every 24 hours, is wholly kept out for at least 26 miles of their usual flow. By means whereof, great prejudice hath been already occasioned to their Navigation. 2. That much prejudice hath happened since the Petitioners <reg orig="addresse">address</reg> to the Commissioners, sitting at <em>Ely</em> in <em>March</em> last. 3. That probably in a short time, this Sasse or <reg orig="Sluce">Sluice</reg> will be the <reg orig="totall">total</reg> destruction of their Navigation.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 20 Decemb.</i> Capt. <em>Crispin</em> with the Assistance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come in hither, he was in a storm near <em>Scilly</em> two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since; but afterwards sailed Eastward of <em>Tor</em> Bay, and is come safe hither, he hath been with Cap. <em>Hasfel</em>, and is to go to <em>Portsmouth</em> to be new fitted and supplied, and out again.</p>

<p><reg orig="Hee">He</reg> went from hence ten <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since, and hath been a great check to the <em>Brest</em> men of War: After which he with the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> that went out with him, on the 16 instant anchored in <em>Couquet</em> Road, where the boats were sent to fetch off two Vessels, one laden with Wine from <em><reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg></em>, the other light, and there were in the same place <reg orig="neare">near</reg> 30 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> more, two of which were supposed to be men of War, who with the rest hauled close under the houses, which were lined with what <reg orig="Musquetiers">Musketeers</reg> that Country could afford, with which (is being <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> <reg orig="ebbe">ebb</reg>) they beat off our boats, but by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> providence without <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> to us; the Non-such boat going in with a small Gun ours also returned with them, and attempted to set the said vessels on fire, but could not make way for our boats, so that <pb n="9" />Cap. <em>Crispin</em> was constrained to fire out of his <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Town, and upon the Vessels, against whom he made about two hundred and thirty great shot, which in sight of our men did the enemy very much <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg>; the enemy very much <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg>; the enemy made use of only one Gun, which they kept playing all the time at our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> <reg orig="untill">until</reg> we beat them from it. That <reg orig="afternoon">after noon</reg> we discovered a ship of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> plying in towards Brest, and the Non-such sailed after her, and that evening <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> her, she being a great Holland fly-boat of eight guns, laden with wine from <reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> this day passed an Ordinance, and Declaration for alteration of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Names and Forms heretofore used in Courts, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p><em>Oliver</em>, Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging; having the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, invested and established in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, who have power until the meeting of the next Parliament (which is to be on the third day of <em>September</em> now next ensuing) to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be necessary, which <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be binding, and in force until order <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be taken in Parliament concerning the same.</p>

<p>And the said Lord Protector finding it to be most necessary, that some speedy and effectual course be taken for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the names, and forms to be used in Patents, Commissions, and proceedings in Courts of Justice, the said Lord Protector, by, and with the advice and consent of his said <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and in pursuance of, and according to the power and trust reposed in him and them doth declare, and <reg orig="ordaine">ordain</reg>, and be it by the Authority aforesaid declared and ordained, that in al Courts of Law, Justice and Equity, and in all Writs, Grants, Patents, Commissions, Indictments, Informations, Suits, returns of Writs, and in all Fines, Recoveries, Exemplifications, <reg orig="Recognizances">Recognisances</reg>, Process and proceedings of Law, Justice or Equity, within the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging, instead of the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title, and <reg orig="Teste">Test</reg> (of the Keepers of the Liberty of England by authority <pb n="10" /> of Parliament) heretofore used, that from and after the six and twentieth day of <em>December</em>, 1653. the Name, <reg orig="Stile">Style</reg>, Title and <reg orig="Teste">Test</reg> of the Lord Protector for the time being, of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging shall be used, and no other; and the date shall be in the year of our Lord and no other.</p>

<p>And that all Duties, Profits, Penalties, Issues, Fines, Amercements, and Forfeitures whatsoever, which heretofore were sued for in the name of the Keepers of the Liberty of <em>England</em> by Authority of Parliament, shall from and after the said Six and twentieth day of <em>December</em> be prosecuted, sued forth, and recovered in the said name of the <em>Lord Protector</em>, for the time being, of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and no other. And in all or any of the proceedings aforesaid, where the words were, <i>The Jurors for the Commonwealth</i>; or, <i>The Jurors for the Keepers of the Liberty of <em>England</em> by Authority of Parliament, do say or present</i>, from and after the said Six and twentieth day of <em>December</em>, it shall be, The Jurors for the <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. do sat, or present, and no other, &amp;c.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That in all Oaths to be given to any Grand Jury or Petty Jury, or to, or for any Witness to give in Evidence to any such Jury or Juries, and in all other Oaths wherein the name of <i>Keepers of the Liberty, &amp;c.</i> was wont to be used, the same shall be given in the name of the <em>Lord Protector</em> instead of the name of the <i>said Keepers &amp;c.</i> any Law, Usage, or Custom to the contrary in anywise notwithstanding.</p>

<p>And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That such Forms and Course of proceedings, as were heretofore used in the name and time of the Keepers of the Liberty, &amp;c. in Causes Criminal or Civil, and of which no alteration is made in this Ordinance, shall stand and continue to be used and observed as formerly; and that all Indictments, Presentments, Inquisitions, Commissions, and Captions made with such Alterations, Additions, or Alterations as shall be proper and necessary for making good of Indictments, Presentments, Commissions, <pb n="11" />Captions, and Inquisitions, and supplying the <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> and meaning thereof, according to the present Government of this Commonwealth under the <em>Lord Protector</em> as aforesaid, shall stand and be good and effectual in Law to all intents and purposes, as if the same had been particularly herein named, Any Law, Custom, or Usage to the contrary in anywise notwithstanding.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em><reg orig="Swedland">Sweden</reg></em> is advertised, That the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> from <em>England</em>, is safely come thither with his retinue, joyfully received, and in good health.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 23 December.</i> Mr. <em>Brittan</em> a <reg orig="Marchant">Merchant</reg> of <em>Jersey</em> hath made a confiscation, by bringing in some French Wines into this Port, but it was done in much ignorance, and in conscience ought to be relieved. This Evening, blessed be God, is come an express from <em>Falmouth</em>, which brings news of the arrival of the <em>Bristol</em> and <em>Portland</em> <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg>, with the rest of the ships which were out with them in the late storm.</p>

<p><i>Yarmouth 22 December.</i> Yesterday the Bailiffs received the Proclamation to proclaim the Lord Protector, with an Order for the publishing of it in this Town; and this day accordingly it was proclaimed in a solemn manner in four places of this Town. The Bailiffs and Aldermen in Scarlet, and forty eight in their Gowns. The Governor and some of the Officers also accompanied them; and as soon as the Proclamation was published, the great Guns in the Town and Forts were fired. The generality of people here are well satisfied.</p>

<p>The like Letters came from <em>Bristol, <reg orig="Excester">Exeter</reg>, Salop</em>, and many other places, much to the same purpose.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday, 27 December, 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day divers Officers meet with his Highness at the Cockpit, and signified their full union in the present Government.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 19 Decemb.</i> The march Northwards of most of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Forces goes forward, and they are drawing together about <em>Dunkel</em>. The 16 instant, in the Evening Col. <em>Blakiter</em> and Major <em>Crawford</em> with <unclear>12</unclear> Troops of Horse and Dragoons being about 2000 came thither. <em>Lorn</em> is come to <em>Lough-Tay</em> with 500 Horse and Foot. About 100 horse and foot from <em>Weem</em>, and the <em>Tutor</em> of <em><!--typo??-->Macgregger</em> with 300 from <em>Loughaber</em>, are marching thither, and <em>Glencairn</em> hath promised to return speedily, or spare them what strength he can. What the design of this Conjunction is, is not known, but they talk of having 3000 horse and <pb n="12" />foot at next Rendezvous. They have not left in <em>Stermont</em>, a part of <em>Perthshire</em>, so much as a <reg orig="plad">plaid</reg>, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that is wearable, nor any <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>: The Country say, when they have taken all, they will go to them, and many of them are well contented, If their <reg orig="Neighbors">Neighbours</reg> suffer as much as they, which is all they care for.</p>

<p>The people in <em>Badgenoth</em> (a part of the North Highlands) are very quiet, and have very much resolved rather to suffer (if they be not able to oppose these Ramblers) <reg orig="then">than</reg> in any way to assist them: The last week some Rogues took away about 160 sheep of the late Governor of <em>Ruthen</em> Castle which were near the Garrison, and some Oxen belonging to it; but at the desire of the present Governor, Cap. <em>Mills</em>, they pursued them, and brought them back again from the <em>Braes</em> of <em>Athol</em> 24 miles.</p>

<p>The Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> hath sent forth Orders for the bringing in all the best horses in all our quarters within the shelter of our <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, or else that the owners part with them at reasonable rates for the mounting of Dragoons.</p>

<p>A Sub-Collector of <em>Sesse</em> in <em>Dunnipace</em>, in <reg orig="Sterlingshire">Stirlingshire</reg>, the last week kept out of his house a party of the enemy six hours, and after the breaking of six doors, they left him much wounded, and run his wife through the arm with a Tuck, and plundered the house; they discharged forty Pistols at the doors and windows, the Collector wounded two of them with a Spit, which was his weapon: By which it may be observed, That if the Country would resist them, they would be soon weary of these courses.</p>

<head level="3">A Letter from Cap. <em>Hills</em> to the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>, in <em>Scotland</em>, and may be of use for all the Scots in that Nation.</head>

<p><i>Gentlemen, The next day after I had a meeting with some of you, the Gentlemen of <em>Nede</em> (I suppose directed from the rest) came to <reg orig="mee">me</reg>, with that which seemed a very strange overture, howbeit, I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> it to be the result of that convent, <em>viz.</em> to inquire of me whether or not (in case the enemy should approach these parts) you might have liberty to give them some men and provisions to put them by the Country, to which I have taken this occasion (by the hands of the same Agent) to give you the ensuing answer (the effect whereof I gave <em>Nede</em> at such time as <reg orig="hee">he</reg> made that <reg orig="needlesse">needless</reg> offer). That you may take it for granted, that whosoever <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> either directly of indirectly, <reg orig="a&szlig;ist">assist</reg> those <reg orig="Theevish">Thievish</reg> Rebels, either with men, money or provisions, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be deemed by us as one of them, and shall forfeit whatever he hath both real and personal; and whereas it hath been said that some of our chief Officers have granted such liberty, or (as you call it) favour, to other parts of the Country, I must assure you (as I first told <em>Nede</em>) that report was, and is, as false in <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, as it hath <pb n="13" />been weakly seconded by your belief; neither will those who first spake it, be able to hold up their faces when called to account for it.</i></p>

<p><i><em>Gentlemen</em>, You may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> confident that if you suffer <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> by submission to the present power, the state is better able to make you some kind of satisfaction, (as on the contrary they are to give you the reward of your doings, in case you submit or give assistance to their (and indeed your own) enemies,) <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other now in <em>Scotland</em>, who may seek such things from you. And (that I may reason with you a little) what may you expect from an inconsiderable party (yea, though they were more numerous) of desperate men, of broken fortunes, or none at all; who dare not keep their homes for fear the just Laws of the Country should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> executed upon them; but that they should bring you into the same headlong, and vagabond condition with themselves.</i></p>

<p>Whereas on the contrary (<reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg> may in great part <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg>) the care of this state to settle your peace, and endeavour your prosperity (and, if you will but cast your eye upon things most probable) is not this State more likely to protect and make you prosperous, <reg orig="then">than</reg> those who not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> seek to destroy your peace, and devour that little <reg orig="morsell">morsel</reg> which they (and others like them) have left you (and which this state <reg orig="indeavours">endeavours</reg> to preserve to you) but even like Vipers, gnaw out the bowels of their Mother Country. Again, is not the state of <em>England</em> immediately about to incorporate and make you one Free Commonwealth with them? and what greater favour could they cast upon you? and are you not tenderly dealt with (your condition considered) what burden do you undergo which <em>England</em> is free from? and (if friendly and <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> dealing may gain <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> upon you) I am sure there was never any people (under the lash of the sword) more friendly <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg> and civilly used, by those in whose power it is, to exact and sweep their all from them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> you are? so indeed I could almost afford to ask you what was become of your Reason, while you assaulted me with this unreasonable overture? Again consider that God hath delivered into our hands the most Potent and best appointed Armies that <em>Scotland</em> hath been able to raise; and is it likely that this <reg orig="handfull">handful</reg> of <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> and Robbers should stand before us?</p>

<p><i><em>Gentlemen</em>, What I have spoken is out of a desire to your welfare, and I hope you will consider it accordingly, as also that you will give me some testimony of the reality of your intentions towards this state (to <pb n="14" />whom you stand <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg>) and so take off that doubt which (by your late offer) you have given me occasion to harbour, at least by hasting in such firing and other things as are by you deficient for the use of this <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: and the speedy payment of your <reg orig="Assesse">Assess</reg>. To conclude, this is <unclear>to</unclear> require you, neither to <reg orig="ayd">aid</reg>, abet, or any ways assist the Enemy with men, money, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, Provisions, or ought else, either directly or indirectly, as you will answer the contrary with the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of your estates, and hazard of your persons, and such as your carriage is herein, you may expect the like from</i> Gentlemen, Your humble servant, Jo: Hills.</p>

<p>Ruthen castle 24 Novemb. 1653.</p>

<p><i>For the Gentlemen of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</i></p>

<p>From aboard the Swift-sure in Stoakes Bay the 24. of December, 1653. We had yesterday a Court Martial for trial of several Offenders, one for endeavouring to ravish a maid in the open fields near Gosport, which being clearly proved, and the man very impudent, he was thus punished; His body was <reg orig="fastned">fastened</reg> to one of the <reg orig="Boats">Boat's</reg> thongs, and his hands to another, his body bending with a paper in his Hat, wherein was writ of his offence in Capital letters, a Drum in the <reg orig="Boats">Boat's</reg> head beating for <reg orig="publick">public</reg> notice, he was carried in the Boat to each flag ship, which were 4. in number, where he received 10 blows upon the bare back, with a Whip made of 9 <reg orig="smal">small</reg> ropes, by the side of each of the said ships, from whence he was carried ashore to the <reg orig="Plat-form">Platform</reg>, where <reg orig="hee">he</reg> received 10 stripes more, and from thence he was towed in the water at the <reg orig="Boats">Boat's</reg> stern over to Gosport, where he received 10 smart blows more, and was then <reg orig="casheered">cashiered</reg> like <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>; and another was <reg orig="duckt">ducked</reg> for Drunkenness. This day six mutineers of the Portland <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> received their sentence, which was for three of them to have their hands nailed to the <reg orig="maine">main</reg> mast, where accordingly they so stood an hour; and the other 3 had each of them 30. blows on their bare back with a whip of 9 cords, and I will assure you they were smart ones so <reg orig="farre">far</reg> as I could discern, their hideous <reg orig="cryes">cries</reg> demonstrated something of it, which I hope will be a <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> to others for the time to come. Truly I doubt not but the blessing of the Lord will <reg orig="stil">still</reg> attend us to the glory of his name, and the benefit of the whole fleet. Captain Cadman had his <reg orig="triall">trial</reg> also this day, but was not found guilty of <reg orig="murther">murder</reg>, only for his indiscretion is <reg orig="casheered">cashiered</reg> of any <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> in the Service for one <reg orig="yeare">year</reg> after the date hereof.</p>

<p>This day the Lord Ambassador of <em>Spain</em> had audience by his Highness, the Lord Protector, who did congratulate him in his now Authority.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 28 December. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day we may, I hope, without offence say, The peace with the Dutch is concluded in Matter, though not in Form, or Ceremony. <pb n="15" />What a mercy is here! Satisfaction, <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg>, Security, <em>Denmark</em> and all taken In: Blessed be God though some be for war, our <em>David</em> is for peace.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 22 December.</i> A party of Cap. <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> took Capt. <em>Stuart</em> and four more, and killed three, besides divers other taken by parties in other places, among which Lieut. Col. <em>Patwick Hay</em>, Lieut. Col. <em>Gambal</em>, the Laird <em>Lugton</em>, Cap. <em>Crichton</em>, and others of quality. Yesterday Cap. <em>Hart</em> pursued Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> from <em>Borthwick Bray</em>, where he was at Rendezvous, traced them by the Snow, routed them, took 65 horse, 16 prisoners, killed divers, few escaped without wounds. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, and Major <em>Erwin</em>, his Major, both wounded, and fled. We had one slain, and 16 wounded. <em>Glencarne</em> and most of their heads, are with 500 horse, and many foot, passed to the North, over the skirts of <em>Bays</em> <unclear><em>William</em></unclear>, three miles in the <em>Mews</em> and <em>Tividale</em>. <em>Middleton</em> sent a Letter to <em>Glencarne</em>, that Col. <em>Drummond</em> was 26. November, <reg orig="imbarked">embarked</reg> from the <em>Brill</em> with 1500 <reg orig="Voluntiers">Volunteers</reg> of divers Nations. The Titular <em>Scots</em> King also sent a Letter to <em>Glencarne</em>, dated 12. November, telling him, That the Kings of <em>France</em> and <em>Denmark</em>, the Duke of <em>Brandenburg</em>, the Emperor, and Princes of <em>Germany</em>, are not willing to assist him with men, but have assured him of a large proportion of Arms, Ammunition, and moneys, and that he would be with them Immediately after the receiving of <em>Drummond</em> and his forces, whose <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> is to be at <em>Loughbern</em>, the most fortified place in the Highlands.</p>

<p>Reader, whereas last week there was inserted the names of divers Inhabitants of <em>Sepulchres</em> Parish, which had been put into a Chancery Bill concerning Tithes, for the prevention of some misconstructions that might be made thereof, I am desired to give this true account of the said Bill, viz.</p>

<p>That whereas the Tithes of the whole Parish (if fully paid) amounts to 400 l. <em>per annum</em>, yet for divers years together in these latter times, there hath not been collected above 150 l. <em>per annum</em>, whereof two parts are paid to the Church-wardens for the use of the poor of the said Parish, and the other part to the Minister thereof; the Vestry of the said Parish taking notice, as of the increase of their poor, so of the decrease of one part of their maintenance, did after advice taken with Counsel give order, that the names of such of the inhabitants as were in Arrears should be put into a Chancery Bill, which accordingly was done, and six or eight <reg orig="Subp&aelig;nas">Subpoenas</reg> thereupon taken out for such who not only wholly refused to pat their dues, but gave some provoking words to such as demanded the same.</p>

<p>And whereas it was added, that they were prosecuted in the names of Master <em>Thomas Smith</em>, and others, you are desired to take notice, that they were only Feossees in trust, in whose names the Impropriation of <em>Sepulchres</em> for the <reg orig="poors">poor's</reg> two parts of the Tithe was taken; and therefore all proceedings in Law must <reg orig="goe">go</reg> in their names, whereas the benefit of the two parts of the Tithe redounds wholly to the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> of the said Parish, which are many hundreds.</p>

<p>One <em>Anne Birch</em> alias <em>Neal</em>, a maid of about 15 or 16 years of age, born at <em>Lyddington</em> in <em>Rutland</em>, she did wear (in case she hath not changed her apparel) a Daroy colour, or sad Red colour <reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg> <reg orig="Wastcoat">Waistcoat</reg> with three Laces about the skirt, and three up before of each side; she hath Brown curled hair, of a fresh countenance, she went away the <unclear>21</unclear> of <em>November</em>. 1653. If <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> can bring <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of her to Mr. <em>Edmund Cooper</em> at the Tennis Court in <em>Holborn</em>, or to her Father at <em>Lyddington</em> aforesaid, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have forty shillings for their pains. Or in case she be boarded in any ship, bound for <em>Virginia</em>, or any other Plantations, the Captain of such ship is desired to <reg orig="conveigh">convey</reg> her to any the places above specified, and he shall have his charges born, together with a gratuity to his full content.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>