<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState240">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 240</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 27 of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. To Thursday the 4 day of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 27 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. 1653.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Nathaniel Fines</em> is added a Member of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The Lords Ambassadors of the United Provinces this day dined with his Highness the Lord Protector at <em>Whitehall</em>, and the Lords of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, with some <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg> and other Gentlemen, at two Tables in the same room; And the Lords Ambassadors, the Lord President, and the Lord <em>Lisle</em> at the same Table with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>; and 20 Gentlemen were taken in to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Lifeguard of Foot (the whole number is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> threescore) who <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> up the meat, and many Gentlemen attended; And after Dinner there was a banquet. The <reg orig="Coates">Coats</reg> of the Guard are grey <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> with black Velvet<pb n="1" /><reg orig="collers">collars</reg>, and black Velvet and silver lace, and trimming.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples 1 April 1654</em>. Our Vice Roy is providing 4000 Suits of <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, 18000 Shirts 2000 Swords, so many Hats, Stockings and <reg orig="Shooes">Shoes</reg>, for the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and Shovels, Baskets, and 30 brass guns likewise to be sent into <em>Catalonia</em>, and hath given his order for the bringing in a Regiment <em>Crabates</em>, and 6000 new Spanish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to oppose the better the attempts of the Enemy against this Kingdom.</p>

<p>From Bremen 14. April. General <em>Keninksmarch</em> having again besieged the Burgh, after that some of our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> had come away from thence into the City, he with some Swedish <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and Boars shot in <reg orig="Granadoes">Granados</reg>, which did a world of <reg orig="mischeif">mischief</reg>, and afterward attempted the Fort, and while this City was preparing to <reg orig="releeve">relieve</reg> it, the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> having been shot in the head by a bullet they <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Dantzick 4 April</em>, We hear from <em>Warsaw</em> that the Princes <em>Janusius</em> and <em>Boguslaus Radzivil</em> were arrived, there with a train of more than 800 Horse, and 300 Foot. The <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> business that is now enacting is to deliberate whether the King <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> deliver or hold still the <reg orig="staffe">staff</reg> of Generalat of the Crown and of <em>Listland</em>.</p>

<p>From Rhynstream 21 April. <i>The Dean of the Cathedral of <em>Liege</em> is set free from Prison, and brought back again to <em>Colen</em> by the Imperialists. The Duke Francis of <em>Lorain</em>, with his two Sons are gone, and the Emperor and the King of the <em>Romans</em> departing from <em>Regensburgh</em>, and thereupon shall the Rixday make an end of their sitting being to meet again in a <reg orig="years">year's</reg> time.</i></p>

<p><em>Flushing 19 April</em>. The Factors here have declared upon the Peace with <em>England</em> to all Merchants, that from henceforth no Goods or Merchandizes <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be sent into <em>England</em> by the way of <em>Dunkirk</em>, but that there are here three small Vessels ready to lade them in for <em>London</em> by that time the limitation is expired, and that the next week some will also <reg orig="bee">be</reg> ready for <em>Calais</em>.</p>

<p><i><em><reg orig="Upsal">Upsala</reg> 27 March</em>. The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath of late begun to regulate her Court, having discharged several of her Officers, expecting still the next <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg>, where she pretends to execute her resolution of resigning her Government.</i></p><pb n="2" />

<p><em><reg orig="Wasow">Warsaw</reg> 2 April</em>. Our <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg> was dissolved upon the 28 of <em>March</em> last upon the difference happening therein between the <reg orig="Nuncioes">Nuncios</reg>, the King and his Senators were for dissolving it. The <em>Muscovites</em> are still in their old Quarters, the <em>Poles</em> not much regarding their warlike preparations since the relieving of <em>Smolensko</em> by an addition of some <reg orig="Germain">German</reg> Forces. The Palatines settled in the Land of <em>Ukraine</em> are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> still about reforming the Laws, and securing the Authority of their Master the Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> against <em>Kimelinsky's</em> attempts who begins now to fear the effect of the said <reg orig="Dukes">Duke's</reg> Power, in depriving him of his Estate there.</p>

<p><i><em>Regensburgh 13 April</em>, The <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg> here have resolved to take to heart the settlement of the common defence of the Empire, and the business of those who are to be <reg orig="redintigrated">reintegrated</reg>. The <reg orig="Dyet">Diet</reg> is to end the 20 instant. This morning the Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Loraine</em> is gone from hence with 30 of the <em><reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg></em> Guards towards <em>Ments</em> and <em>Flanders</em>.</i></p>

<p><em>Munster 15 April</em>, This week Mr. <em>Hofstatter</em> the Commissary for the Crown of <em>Sweden</em> arrived here, for the receiving of the 135968 Rixdoll: is remaining due to the Swedes by upper Circle of the Rhine, and after they are agreed for the sum pretended by the Garrison of <em>Vetcht</em>, it shall be <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> to this Bishop.</p>

<p><i><em>Rome 6 April</em>. The Signora <em>Lucresia Barbarina</em> hath taken her leave of the Pope going to marry the Duke of <em>Medene</em>. The King of <em>Spain</em> forbad Sir. <em>Massini</em> the Nuncio to come to <em>Madrid</em>, the Pope hath recalled him, being much incensed thereby against the <em>Spaniards</em>, and doth use Cardinal <em>Astalli</em> hardly, on whom they intend to bestow the <reg orig="Archbishoprick">Archbishopric</reg> of <em>Toledo</em>, because he is out of favour with the Pope:</i></p>

<p><em>Venice 6 April</em>. News is come hither of the <reg orig="defeate">defeat</reg> given to some of Gen. <em>Dolfinino's</em> Forces as they were marching to <em>Chin</em> in <em>Dalmatia</em> by 5000 Turkish Horse, who were in an Ambushcado, yet with such a stout defence of ours that about 1800 enemies have been killed upon the place. Orders hath been given here for gathering of Forces with speed to send that way, and be revenged of that affront, or at least hinder the like for the future. The Senate hath commanded Generalissimo <em>Moccenigo</em><pb n="3" />without any further delay to go for <em>Candia</em>, with Marquis <em>de Barri</em>, and the forces designed for that place, 400 <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of those raised by the Marquis <em>Facchinetti</em>, have been shipped at <em>Ancona</em> for <em>Dalmatia</em>, whither 300 horse and some money will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent also very speedily. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> are preparing here many new <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg>, whereof most are already very forward.</p>

<p><i><em>Genoa 15 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>: The sixth instant two Galleys of <em><reg orig="Maltha">Malta</reg></em> arrived here, to take in provisions for their further journey towards the Levant, for the service of the <em>Venetians</em>, another of their Galleys is at <em>Leghorn</em>, abundance of ships and other vessels have been lately cast away by the storm in the Straits, and among others 16 <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> have perished hard by <em><reg orig="Sicely">Sicily</reg></em>.</i></p>

<p>The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from the King of <em>Portugal</em> had this day Audience by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at <em>Whitehall</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 28 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>.</i></head>

<p>This day the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> passed <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Orders in divers Petitions formerly referred to them by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector; and dispatched above twenty <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Petitions this day.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> petitions were this day also presented to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by the Masters of Requests.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> addresses have also been lately presented to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> from divers parts of <em>England</em>, the people very much, more and more owning and <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> under the present Government, one of which addresses follows.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <em>Oliver</em> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></head>

<p><i>The humble Representation of the Justices of the Peace, chief Officers of Corporations, Ministers of the Gospel of the County of <em>Salop</em>, and of the Grand Jury at the Assizes held at <em>Salop</em> the 20 of <em>March</em>, in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> 1653.</i></p>

<p><i>Humbly <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg></i></p>

<p>That <reg orig="wee">we</reg> cannot but with all <reg orig="thankfulnesse">thankfulness</reg> of heart call to remembrance the late eminent actings of the Providence of God among us, in his Ordering our Wars, and Ordaining our Peace for us; And that after such variety of changes, which<pb n="4" />have passed over us, and with them so many fears, which have so deeply sate upon the hearts of many of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have such assured hopes of a settlement of these Nations in Truth and <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg>, by the exercise of the declared Government; wherein consisting the present support of our Religion, and Laws, <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> cannot but acknowledge it as a great Mercy of God, that so suitable a Remedy should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> so suddenly <reg orig="applyed">applied</reg> to our growing Maladies; and that our hopes after many years patient attendance upon other Instruments (when almost swallowed up in the multitude of our too just fears) are now revived, and recovered from so <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg> a condition, by the raising up of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in this juncture of time, and affairs, so seasonably to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> our Ruler, who have been so successfully our Leader, God having already put upon you as much of the Honour of our Peace, as men of the <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of our wars, and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> trust farther about to honour you (and you Him) with doing as much at the <reg orig="Helme">Helm</reg> of our Government, as in the Head of our Armies; In bringing to effect those great things, for which the <reg orig="Faithfull">Faithful</reg> in these Nations have from the beginning of our troubles continually contended with God by earnest prayer, and long with their <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> vast <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of blood, and treasure; <reg orig="Your Self">Yourself</reg> being made the Steward for laying out a far greater part thereof than any other, that best knowing the price, you might best value the purchase, and <reg orig="bee">be</reg> most tender of any new <reg orig="intrenchments">entrenchments</reg> upon those precious concernments, the Redemption whereof has cost so dear.</p>

<p>We have very strong <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg>, Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath already under consideration for our common good, more than probably <reg orig="wee">we</reg> know well how to request: <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> shall therefore in <reg orig="generall">general</reg> commend only to your best of care those two comprehensive Interests, Religion, and Justice; The two great Ordinances of God, for the due exercise of the one, and execution of the other, Magistracy and <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, together with the <reg orig="fruitfull">fruitful</reg> Nurseries of both these (as well as <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Ornaments to the Nations) our Universities, and <reg orig="Innes">Inns</reg> of Court. In your <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> pursuance of which so <reg orig="publicke">public</reg> concernments, the <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> in these Nations will follow you with their prayers, the Lord hear them for you, and follow<pb n="5" />you with good: And <reg orig="wee">we</reg> among the thousands of our <em>Israel</em> who make the like Addresses to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, faithfully serve you, and with you our Generation in our respective stations, who have subscribed our Names.</p>

<p>This <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> subscribed according to the stile, was to have been presented by two Justices of the Peace, <em>Philip Young</em> of <em>Cainton</em>, and <em>William Crown</em> of <em>Bridgenorth</em> <reg orig="Esquiers">Esquires</reg>, but Mr. <em>Young</em> being <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by <reg orig="sicknesse">sickness</reg>, It was presented only by Mr. <em>William Crown</em>, Justice of the peace: and Mr. <em>Thomas Porter</em>, and Mr. <em>Thomas Gilbert</em>, Ministers of the Gospel.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 29 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Addresses have been made about the business of planting Tobacco in <em>England</em>, and upon the result of all, and the Answer given to the Gentleman, whom a principle of charity had made Agent for the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> Planters in <em>England</em>, It is desired by the said Gentleman their Agent, that this may be published, who doth hereby <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>: That the planting of Tobacco in <em>England</em> is adjudged inconvenient, and that his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> are resolved to make good the late Act and Ordinance against planting of Tobacco in <em>England</em>: and to give no <reg orig="tolleration">toleration</reg> whatsoever to any: And <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> the said Agent desires that those persons concerned therein will take notice thereof, that so they may prevent such penalties as otherwise will inevitably befall them.</p>

<p><i>J.D.</i></p>

<p>There are many Letters from the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Counties which speak much of <reg orig="carefull">careful</reg> and just proceedings of the Judges in the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Circuits of <em>England</em>,<pb n="6" />and in some places some notorious wicked wretches have been put to death:</p>

<p>Among the rest there was one, a Papist, a Cavalier a very deboyst wretch, executed at <em>Hereford</em>, being found guilty upon <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Indictments for Robberies, and <reg orig="murther">murder</reg>, yet <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> as desperately as he had lived wickedly, touching whom one that was an eye and ear <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> at his execution, collected these particulars following, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>A Brief Copy of the Expressions that were of Captain <em>Walton</em> at the place of execution, Who was a notorious Cavalier, and condemned at the last Assizes at <em>Hereford</em>, for a notorious Robber, and for <reg orig="murther">murder</reg>, fully proved against him.</p>

<p>1. The said Capt. <em>Walton</em> being come to the place of Execution, he had three Papish men with him, fell on their knees as if they prayed, but none did hear their prayers, only observed their postures as they use in crossing themselves, and moving their lips and looking upwards, the other three were also known to be Papists.</p>

<p>2 When the Executioner came, which was long before he came with the Ladder, he with them that fell before, fell down again with him, as if they prayed, but none did hear them what they prayed, but their motions and carriage was again as before. And rising up spake to the Hangman, and then spake aloud in which he was impudent.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>3 Concerning the Fact he justified himself, and said he died wrongfully. And boasted that he was for the King, who if he had had an hundred lives he would willingly have laid them down all to go to those (brave many) Lords and Noblemen that were gone before him in this quarrel. Upon so vain a bottom is that Cause founded, and by such wretches much acted; By which we may easily perceive how much the Papists were <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> for that party.</p>

<p>4 That there were two men in the Court when he took his <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> sitting in black Caps that procured his death. Let wicked men vaunt never so much, there is an unquiet Conscience within that can find no rest, but is as a thousand witnesses.</p>

<p>5 Concerning the death of <em>Nicholas <reg orig="Teyler">Taylor</reg></em> he <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> it, though it had been clearly proved against him, and that was but one Branch of many Crimes for which he suffered death.</p>

<p>6 Concerning another young man (that it was more fully known he killed) he said he had no quarrel with him, and said he knew not whether he killed him or no. So by his own confession he might have killed more than he then <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg>: but why should a dying man so dissemble with God and his own <reg orig="Soule">Soul</reg>.</p>

<p>7 That <i>upon his Faith</i> he was a <em>Roman <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg></em> before but better confirmed in it now, and wished that all that heard him at that time might <reg orig="dye">die</reg> in that Faith that he did die in. So as he lived a Swearer and Blasphemer, so he died with an oath in his mouth. And for his Religion, you see how <reg orig="vaine">vain</reg> a basis it had.</p>

<p>8 He boasted that for ought he knew that his blood might be required at the hands of some ere it be long, and that this is but the beginning of a <reg orig="Morrice">Morris</reg> Dance, So <reg orig="vaine">vain</reg> and mad are Cavaliers still some of them, but blessed be God, the Lord hath put all those of them that have but common reason out of that hope now.</p>

<p>9 Concerning robberies upon the <reg orig="High-way">Highway</reg> he did utterly deny, and bid any one that could accuse him should come now to his face and <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> it. But the saddest was</p>

<p>10 His countenance did never change at all, he did shed never a tear, confess never a sin, not <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> the least remorse or<pb n="8" />sorrow at all; and as <reg orig="hee">he</reg> lived wickedly, so he dyed desperately.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Sunday 30 April.</i></head>

<p>This morning <unclear><!-- approx. 4 characters --></unclear> <unclear>paper stuck up</unclear> and <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> many places of the City of <em>London</em>, and chiefly about Church doors called, <i>A warning to all in the City called London</i>, subscribed <em>George Fox</em>, denouncing woe, and plagues against the City or the sins of Pride, Hard heartedness, Cruelty, Oppression, Lusts, Inventions, Images, <unclear><reg orig="Vailes">Vales</reg></unclear>, Filthiness, Dissembling, <reg orig="Hipocrisie">Hypocrisy</reg>, Coullers, <reg orig="fulness">fullness</reg> of bread, and plotting to do mischief, inviting the people to come out of these sins and repent.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 1 May, 1654.</i></head>

<p>This day was more observed by people going a <unclear>Maying</unclear>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> for divers years past, and indeed much sin committed by wicked meetings with <unclear><reg orig="Fidlers">Fiddlers</reg> </unclear>, drunkenness, ribaldry and the like: Great resort came to <em><reg orig="Hide">Hyde</reg> Park</em>, many hundreds of rich Coaches and gallants in Attire, but most shameful <reg orig="powdred">powdered</reg> hair men, and painted and spotted women, some men <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> with a silver <reg orig="Bal">Ball</reg>, and some took other Recreation.</p>

<p>But His Highness the Lord Protector went not thither, nor any of the Lords of the Council, but were <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the great Affairs of the Commonwealth, and amongst other things had under consultation how to advance Trade for the good of the people with all speed that might be, and other great Affairs for the good of the Commonwealth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris 18 April.</i></head>

<p>There are here every day secret meetings, and some great ones; and for all the King and his <reg orig="Councels">Council's</reg> sharp prohibitions, there are Libels dispersed through the street against the present Government.</p>

<head level="3">From Jamets 20 April.</head>

<p><i>Our Governor and the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Grandpre</em> fell on four Companies of the Forces of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, quartering at <em>Virton</em>, the 18. instant, and took the most part of the Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of that place.</i></p>

<head level="3">From Bremen 22 April.</head>

<p><i>The Villages upon the River of <em>Woser</em>, are full of <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> to hinder the invasion of the <em>Swedes</em>, who have unladen all the Turff ships<pb n="9" />upon some design, and they have forty ships of war in readiness with 30000 men, Horse and Foot to be shipped the next month.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Dantzick 11 April.</i></head>

<p>The Great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> hath not yet assaulted the City of <em>Smolensko</em>, which Prince <em>Radzwil</em> General of <em>Listland</em> hath strengthened with a Garrison of <em>High-Dutch</em> and <em>Hungarians</em>, and hath himself with 8000 men advanced toward <em>Orsaw</em>, a border place of <em>Muscovy</em>. We hear from <em>Warsaw</em>, that the Rixday or Assembly of States was dissolved the 28 of <em>March</em> without concluding <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>, which causes great sadness, the Nobility and Gentry much opposing one the other, and the King rules the <reg orig="Dukedome">Dukedom</reg> of <em>Listland</em> as well as the Crown of <em>Poland</em>. The <em>Muscovites</em> endeavour to divide us amongst <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">Rhinstroom 28 April.</head>

<p><i>The Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> with his two sons is to go this day from <em>Colen</em> to <em><reg orig="Dusseldorp">Dusseldorf</reg></em> where are some <em>Spanish</em> Forces come to meet him as a convoy.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris 24. April.</i></head>

<p>It is reported that the Pope shall send here an Ambassador, to proffer one of his <reg orig="Neeces">Nieces</reg> in Marriage to the King with a portion of five and twenty Millions of Livers, and an everlasting alliance with <em>France</em>. And the Duke of <em>Modena</em> hath intent to offer to his Majesty one of his Daughters with the Dukedom of <em>Modena</em>, by which means the King might have a foot in <em>Italy</em>. The last week there was an Ordinance of the great Council in the behalf of the Deputies General of the Protestant Churches of this Kingdom, that they shall <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> all the grants of the Declarations for Peace in all the Provinces.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Flushing 22 April.</i></head>

<p>Many ships are to go from hence for the East and West Indies, two went off, one for <em><reg orig="Brazill">Brazil</reg></em> and the other for the <em>Caribes</em> Islands, which are yet without this Haven, and yesterday 19 more followed them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Amsterdam 25 April.</i></head>

<head level="3">A PROCLAMATION.</head>

<p><i>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of the Admiralty sitting in <em>Amsterdam</em> make it known and give notice by these, according to the special command sent to them by the High and Mighty the Lords<pb n="10" />States General, of the 22 instant, That although the Treaty of Peace between the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em> on one part, and this State on the other, be at last concluded and subscribed no Master of Ships is to go to Sea with his Ships or Goods before the time expired, after which all acts of Hostility shall cease, whereof notice shall be given, upon the penalties to those that shall do <reg orig="otherways">otherwise</reg> as are expressed in the Ordinances made against the disobedient Skippers, whereby every one shall be bound to submit and prevent his loss and danger,</i></p>

<p>Given in the Assembly of the aforesaid <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> the 24, of <em>April</em> 1654.</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector. A PROCLAMATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>Of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> concerning a Cessation of all acts of Hostility between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and that of the United Provinces, and their respective people, and the restitution of all things taken and seized upon by either party after the fourth day of this instant <em>May</em>.</i></head>

<p><em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging. Whereas the Commissioners appointed by Us to Treat with the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the United Provinces; and the said <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, by way of Explanation of the third of those Articles of Peace, lately concluded between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Netherlands, and for removing all questions and differences which may arise thence-from, Have agreed and concluded the following Article, <em>viz</em>.</p> 

<p><i>That whereas in the third of those Articles of Peace, Union and confederation made, established, and promulged between the <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces, It is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges and <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, which either party hath sustained by the other since the 18 &amp; 28 of <em>May</em>, in the year one thousand six hundred fifty and two, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> taken away and forgotten, in such manner as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other, for, or upon occasion of any the aforesaid injuries, charges, and damages, but that there shall be a present abolition of all and every of them <reg orig="untill">until</reg> this present day. And all actions for the same shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> held and reputed <reg orig="voyd">void</reg> and null, excepting such depredations as shall <reg orig="be">bee</reg> committed<pb n="11" />by either side in these Seas after the space of twelve days, and in all other places on this side the Cape St. <em>Vincent</em>, after 6 weeks, and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> Sea, and to the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line after ten weeks, and beyond the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line, after the space of eight Months, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places.</i></p> 

<p>And whereas certain questions may possibly arise about the fore-rehearsed words, which may minister occasion of debates and disputes, the said Lord Protector and the said States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, to the end all manner of <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> and difference may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> removed, which might arise by reason of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in the aforesaid Article contained, Have unanimously accorded and agreed, and do by these presents publish and declare to all and singular their people and Subjects respectively, that immediately after publication of the Treaty of Peace, which is already done, all acts of hostility shall immediately cease in all places expressed in the said Article, and in all others wheresoever.</p> 

<p>And that all Depredations, <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, and Injuries which shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done or committed by one party against the other, after the fourth day of this instant <em>May</em>, in all places whatever, mentioned in the foresaid Article, or elsewhere, as well on this side the Line as beyond, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> accounted for. And all things taken or seized after the abovesaid fourth of <em>May</em>, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> restored without any form of <reg orig="Processe">Process</reg>, as also <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg> growing by occasion thereof.</p> 

<p>And to the end this Agreement and Article may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> the better known, both parties shall publish the same within their respective Territories and Dominions, and straitly charge and command as well their ships of War, as others whether in Port, or at Sea, to observe the same.</p>

<p>Wherefore <reg orig="we">wee</reg> having considered what is agreed as aforesaid, have confirmed and ratified, and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> do confirm and ratify the same by these presents, which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have caused to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> published, that all persons concerned therein may take notice thereof.</p> 

<p>And <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> <reg orig="doe">do</reg> hereby straitly charge and require all the ships of War, and others, either belonging to the State, or to any particular persons set forth upon private Commissions, or otherwise,<pb n="12" />to observe the said Agreement. And to the end none may pretend ignorance herein, The Commissioners of the admiralty are hereby required to give <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> notice hereof to all the ships of this State, either at Sea, or in Port, within these Dominions or elsewhere.</p> 

<p>And the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty are also by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of these presents, forthwith to call in upon their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> securities given in that Court, all such ships as have been set forth upon private Commissions against the <reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces, or the People thereof.</p> 

<p><i>Given at <em>Whitehall</em> this first of <em>May</em> in the year 1654:</i></p>

<p>OLIVER P.</p>

<p>In <reg orig="witnesse">witness</reg> whereof as well the Lords Commissioners of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> Extraordinary of the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, have signed these presents with their own hands.</p>

<p><i>Done at <em>Westminster</em> the 28 day of <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>, Old style, in the year 1654.</i></p>

<!-- The list of names which follows are set out in two adjacent columns -->

<!-- First column -->
<p><i>H. Laurence Pres.</i></p>
<p><i>Gil. Pickering.</i></p>
<p><i>E. Monutagu.</i></p>
<p><i>Wal. Strickland.</i></p>

<!-- Second Column -->
<p><i>H. Beverningck.</i></p>
<p><i>Wil. Nieupoort.</i></p>
<p><i>Alar. P. Longestall.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 2 May.</i></head>

<p>This day the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have sate upon great and weighty affairs.</p>

<p>Some things were this day referred to Committees.</p>

<p>The Committee hath made some <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of the Law.</p>

<p><i>Dublin 26 April</i>. The <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have met, and are shortly to sit again; The Lord Deputy and the Commissioners have lately had great consultations for the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of this Nation, now (blessed <reg orig="bee">be</reg> God) in a condition ready to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> if it were but peopled: and there are two Officers gone over from hence towards his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, who will give an account of all things here, and by whom you will understand that (blessed <reg orig="bee">be</reg> God) <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are in a good condition.</p>

<head level="3">Texel 26 April.</head>

<p><i>Five men of War are ready to sail towards <reg orig="Brazill">Brazil</reg>, and three others to cross towards our Freebooters to call them in. Here is a gallant Fleet of Merchant ships of about 100 sail ready to sail for <em>France</em><pb n="13" />, <em>Spain</em>, and other places. The 22. instant those Galliots that went to sea from hence the day before were driven in again by three English Freebooters, who took one of them. The 23 in the morning a fleet of our Merchant ships and men of War went to Sea.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague 21 April.</i></head>

<p>A day of Thanksgiving to God Almighty shall be appointed here for the Peace with <em>England</em>, the Lord having been pleased to take away the <reg orig="evill">evil</reg> of the War and all former differences between both Nations, and to desire him that the peace may for his glory be continued for ever, that we may <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> upon that blessing between both people, who stand in so great need thereof, as well in regard of the Common Protestant Religion, as of the Commerce of all the world, hoping that the time shall make us reap the fruits of that blessed Peace.</p>

<p>Here continues rumours of great Victories obtained in <em>Scotland</em> by the <em>Scots</em>, upon the <em>English</em>, although there is no certainty of it.</p>

<p>There are also <reg orig="severall">several</reg> discourses made of the <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> of the great <em>English Fleet</em>.</p>

<p>We cannot yet hear how things are between the English, and the Kings of <em>France, Spain</em> and <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, as well as <em>Sweadland</em>.</p>

<p>And it seems all these Negotiations have been deferred till that between <em>England</em> and the <em><reg orig="Vnited">United</reg> Provinces</em> should be fully concluded, the which being now done, it is conceived that there shall be a speedy and short resolution taken in the Treaties with the foresaid Princes, the which are like to bring great alterations in the world.</p>

<p><em>Dover 25 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>, Yesterday in the Evening came into this Road a private man of war, being a <em>Morget</em> Hoy of six Guns, and about fifty men, who having<pb n="14" />found in the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> a Dutch ship <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from the <em>West-Indies</em>, that had been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent by the <reg orig="tediousnesse">tediousness</reg> of the voyage, did on a sudden clap them aboard, and after a little dispute became Masters of her, and brought her along with them, the ship is said to be of great value, for besides Plate, whereof <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Letters say there is a good quantity, the Ship will be found full of other rich Commodities, which will prove very <reg orig="beneficiall">beneficial</reg> to the takers, when it comes to be judged prize.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 3 May. 1654.</i></head>

<p>This day some further <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> was made about the Law.</p>

<p>Something considered of about the <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg> of Money.</p>

<p>Divers Petitions were presented to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>The next <reg orig="Terme">Term</reg> is like to be kept without any interruption.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, was this day with the Lords <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> of the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the <em>Netherlands</em>, as their Lodgings at Sir <em>John Trevors</em>.</p>

<p>Some Forces are passing from the North of <em>Ireland</em> to the Islands in the North of <em>Scotland</em>, that upon their Landing there, they may alarm <em>Middleton</em>, who as some Letters say, was wheeling Northward, it is supposed he had taken an alarm.</p>

<p>Whereas there was lately published a Pamphlet, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> <i>The Articles of the perpetual Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, translated out of the <em>Dutch</em> Copy</i>; and surreptitiously printed, without Authority or Order from the State: These are to give notice, that that Pamphlet is a false Copy, and that the people be not deceived thereby, they are hereby given to understand, That by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> special command there is a true Copy now in the Press, and will speedily published.</p><pb n="15" />

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>Here is yet no <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> from Col. <em>Morgan</em>. These parts are now more quiet <reg orig="then">than</reg> formerly, and certainly exemplary Justice upon some, and sending others of the Rebels to <em><reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg></em> will something tame these <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> people.</p>

<p>Yesterday <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> <em><reg orig="Malcombe">Malcolm</reg> Rogers</em>, who was Agent between <em>Charles Stuart</em> and <em>Glencarne</em>, was executed at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, being <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, found guilty and condemned by a Court Marshal for a Spy.</p>

<p><reg orig="Hee">He</reg> confessed that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> killed one of our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> (pretending <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> a Merchant) between <em>Christorphin</em> and <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith 27 April, 1654.</i></p>

<p>The King of <em>France</em> is preparing large Offers to be made to the English for peace. And among other things, that the Protestants shall enjoy large Liberties and Freedom in Religion in <em>France</em>.</p>

<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Pen is going from <em>London</em> to the Fleet to <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Blake</em>.</p>

<p>The Instructions are private.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Berwick.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monke">Monk</reg></em> is safely arrived in <em>Scotland</em>. <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath sent for all his Officers at <em>London</em> to make speed to their Charges, being resolved to <reg orig="scowre">scour</reg> the Country of the Rebels. Some of the Scots are to be transported.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg> 28 April, 1654.</i></p>

<p><i>Chester 1 May, 1654.</i></p>

<p>There are two Colonels from <em>Ireland</em> coming to His Highness the Lord Protector. The Peace is welcome news here.</p>

<p>A very great Fleet of <reg orig="Coales">Coals</reg> is coming from <em>Newcastle</em> towards <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>A few small ships are taken, but not considerable.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant,</head>

<p>A second Part of Declarations &amp; Pleadings, by R. Brownsow Esq; Sold by M Walbank at <reg orig="Grays">Gray's</reg>-Inn-Gate, and J. Place at <reg orig="Furnivals">Furnival's</reg> Inn Gate.</p> 

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>