<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState243">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 243</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 18 of <em>May</em>. To Thursday the 25 day of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 18 May. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day about eleven a clock the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from the King of France had audience by the Lord Protector in the Chamber where the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of State sate, whither <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was brought to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> presence by Sir <em>Oliver <reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg></em>, Mr. of the Ceremonies, where after salutations, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> both put on their hats, (the Lords of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> and all the rest being bare) and after the chief of his Gentlemen (desiring it) had kissed his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> hand, the Lord Ambassador treated with the Lord Protector; what the event will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> as in order to Peace, time will show; But there was an English Master of a ship lately gave <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazerine</em> a witty answer about it: The<pb n="1" /><reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was thus: This Master had his ship with Merchandize taken by the French, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> made addresses to the French Court (among others in the like condition) to see if <reg orig="hee">he</reg> could recover it, or any consideration, but <reg orig="hee">he</reg> (as well as the rest) sought in vain, for <reg orig="hee">he</reg> and others are come into <em>England</em> without any satisfaction: But the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> had himself some private discourse with him, and asked him why <em>England</em> was so unwilling to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> amity with <em>France</em>, being <em>France</em> was so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> a neighbour, and could <reg orig="bee">be</reg> more <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> than <em>Spain</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>England</em>; And for that also Protestants have such liberty for the exercise of their Religion as they have in France, but are so punished by the Inquisition in <em>Spain</em>; And that <em>France</em> did so desire Peace, and that there may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> no breach between us.</p>

<p>The English man answered the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg>, that if that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> said were true, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> would tell him a way how <reg orig="hee">he</reg> might <reg orig="cousen">cousin</reg> <em>England</em>, the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> asked him how? why quoth the English Master of the ship, by letting <reg orig="mee">me</reg> and my <reg orig="Country men">Countrymen</reg>, whose ships you have taken, to have them restored to us again; For <reg orig="wee">we</reg> do <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> in <em>England</em> that you <reg orig="doe">do</reg> taken them from us in a way of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> and will not restore them, which if you do, you <reg orig="wil">will</reg> indeed <reg orig="cousen">cousin</reg> us, and indeed the man and others are come without any satisfaction.</p>

<p>There are many Stories of strange things about two ships of the <em>English</em> that plundered about St. <em>Mallows</em>, and a fight between them and some <em>French</em>, but it is all false, there was no such thing at all, but a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> rumour raised by some base people, I know not upon what design.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Ireland</em> say, that that Country is now very quiet, no enemy appearing but as Robbers, no Armies, or considerable strength to oppose any Party, and that upon peopling the Country there is like to be much peace, and good living.</p>

<p>It is considerable to take notice of the wonderful increase of all things, both Cattle, Fruits, Corn, and all other Provisions in the several parts of <em>England</em> of late, ever since our new change of Government. There was never known (as is said) so many Ewes bringing forth two Lambs, <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg> as now, and to particularise <reg orig="every thing">everything</reg> would be large.</p>

<p>The business of the new <reg orig="Coyn">Coin</reg> of Monies is still under debate by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>This afternoon about six a Clock the Lords <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> from the States general of the united Provinces of the Netherlands had audience by the Lord Protector, being brought to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> presence by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, in the Presence Chamber (which is that where the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State was wont to sit) and (after a salute) his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> were covered, and they did congratulate his Highness with much amity, and there were great expressions of joy for the Peace so happily (by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> blessing) concluded between both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>

<p>This day the Proposals offered to the Lord Protector by the Lord <em>Broghil</em>, Col. <em>Hewson</em>, Col. <em>Venables</em>, Col. <em>Ingolsby</em>, Sir <em>Robert King</em>, and Master <em>Hutchinson</em>, Commissioners from <em>Ireland</em>, in order to the government of <em>Ireland</em>, being committed by his Highness to the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, were referred to a Committee of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and the Committee met this afternoon about the same, and intend what possible speed may be therein.</p>

<p>This afternoon the Deputy from the King of <em>Denmark</em> had audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, in the old <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> of State Chamber at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, the satisfaction from that State will be given according to the Articles of Peace with the <em>Dutch</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, May 19.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>A Paper of the Proposals that were <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the consideration of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</i></head>

<p>The two main causes of obstruction of Justice, and why there is so little reformation of the abuses by all the good Laws are made, I have observed to be want of information, and want of prosecution, men <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not tell one against another, and trouble their Neighbours; and besides, it is somewhat troublesome and chargeable to go to Justices of Peace with complaints; and hence it is that not one of a thousand offences are complained of, then for many offences of the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg> cannot be convicted of it, and so punished for it but upon Indictment, which is tedious, troublesome, and somewhat chargeable to the Prosecutor. The informations that come in at the Sessions of Peace (for the most part) come in by the Presentment of the petty Constables who are never there, or by the presentment of the Grand Jury,<pb n="3" />or Petty Jury, the Party accused then appeareth, and is bound to Traverse, and in the Traverse no prosecution appeareth, and then he escapeth; and it is very common for the Prosecutor to be taken off, in case where the Prosecution is by Indictment, and not one of twenty Indicted, or Presented, is punished. And for this last cause I doubt little fruit will come of the new Law for <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> because the penalties (as I hear) are not recoverable but by way of Indictment.</p>

<p>If some Laws were made to this effect as followeth, we are confident they would do much to the furtherance of Justice in the punishment of <reg orig="evil doers">evildoers</reg>.</p>

<p>I. That some part of the Forfeiture, in case of Swearing, Sabbath-breaking, Incontinency, <reg orig="Drunkennesse">Drunkenness</reg>, and the like, be given to the Informer, and Prosecutor, or that it be in the power of the Justice of Peace before whom the Conviction is, to give part of it to the said Informer, if he see cause.</p>

<p><i>II. That he that shall hear another Swear, or see another Drunk, or the like, and shall not disclose it in such a time to a Justice of Peace, shall suffer the same punishment as the first <reg orig="offendor">offender</reg> should have done for his own offence.</i></p>

<p><i>III. That the High Constables of every Hundred in case of Swearing, Sabbath-breaking, and such like common offences, shall have power within his Hundred to take Oath, and to convict the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg>, and <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> it to a Justice of Peace, who shall then according to the Law proceed further against the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg>, as if he had been Convicted before himself.</i></p>

<p><i>IV. That the Conviction of all Offences upon any of the Laws now in force touching the Poor, Rogues, Vagrants, <reg orig="Ale-houses">Alehouses</reg>, <reg orig="Drunkennesse">Drunkenness</reg>, <reg orig="Tipling">Tippling</reg>, Swearing, Sabbath-breaking, false Weights and Measures, <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg>, may be before two or more Justices of Peace, by the Oath of two sufficient Witnesses, as well as by Indictment and Presentment, and a traverse of <reg orig="Triall">Trial</reg> thereupon. And that upon this Conviction the same Justices may proceed to inflict the punishment appointed to the offence.</i></p>

<head level="3">For the <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg>, if they please to consider if this Addition be not needful or convenient.</head>

<p><i>I. That if notwithstanding all this, the <reg orig="High ways">Highways</reg> shall be unamended, and dangerous to the Passengers, that any one Justice may<pb n="4" />view it, and if he <reg orig="finde">find</reg> <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> <reg orig="amisse">amiss</reg> there, that he may order the same to be amended, and execute all the power of the Act committed to the Surveyors.</i></p>

<p><i>II. That where a Justice of Peace shall Indict upon his own view there shall be no Traverse to it, but the <reg orig="Offendor">Offender</reg> shall stand Convict hereby, and be liable to a Fine, which shall be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to repair the same <reg orig="High-way">Highway</reg> by him Indicted.</i></p>

<p><i>III. Of the Act be so penned that it will not be in force till the next year, if this be intended by the <reg orig="Law-maker">Lawmaker</reg>, if not, that they would please to help it by an <reg orig="additionall">additional</reg> branch.</i></p>

<head level="3">For <reg orig="Ale-houses">Alehouses</reg>.</head>

<p><i>I. That no <reg orig="Ale-house">Alehouse</reg> keeper discharged shall sell again without License duly had, which if done that any two Justices upon proof of it upon Oath of two Witnesses, may send him to Prison or Bridewell for six Months without <reg orig="Bayl">Bail</reg>, or till he gives Sureties never to sell again.</i></p>

<p><i>That no <reg orig="Ale-house-keeper">Alehouse Keeper</reg> discharged by two Justices, shall be licensed again but in open Sessions.</i></p>

<p>Some Laws to these purposes will go <reg orig="farre">far</reg> in the work of Reformation in these things.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 20 April.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from the Navy came as followeth from several parts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from the Squadron in the North upon the coasts of <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>Vice Admiral <em>John Lawson</em>, commander of the <em>Fairfax</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and of this Squadron, hath received Orders from General <em>Monk</em> (since his coming into <em>Scotland</em>, after advice and counsel with the Officers at <em><reg orig="Endenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and from whence he is going toward, <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>) to ply towards <em>Hoosley</em> Bay.</p>

<p>On the eleventh day of this present <em>May</em> we discovered a Fleet of Dutch ships, which were about 70 sail (or more) of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> vessels intended for <em>Greenland</em>, and their convoy were Rear Admiral <em>de Witte</em> of <em>Amsterdam</em>, and two other men of War.</p>

<p>When we came up with them, they <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> themselves very lovingly, and did very <reg orig="chearfull">cheerful</reg> by submission acknowledge the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of <em>England</em> in these Seas, <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> as<pb n="5" />much to us as could be expected from any <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships; and after a friendly salute passed by, much civility and affection being expressed on both sides.</p>

<p><i>Dated, from the fleet off of <em>Aberdeen</em> 13 May, 1654.</i></p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 12 May</em>, The <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is come into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> to take in some fresh water, which it seems she wanted, and intends after a day or two, in which she hopes to be <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> to return presently.</p>

<head level="3">A Letter from the Squadron in the West.</head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>About four <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago two ships belonging to the Dutch sailing from <em>Holland</em> towards <em>France</em> passed by us: at the first when they got sight of our ships, they put up the <em>Holland</em> Colours and sailed on towards us: And so soon as they came near one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> which was nearest towards them, they freely took in their <em>Holland</em> <reg orig="cullours">colours</reg> and put up a white Flag of Peace, which signal of theirs was answered from our ship.</i></p>

<p><i>After which they took down their white Flag, and again spread their <em>Holland</em> <reg orig="cullors">colours</reg>, and <reg orig="lowred">lowered</reg> their <reg orig="Top-sails">Topsails</reg> on the Cape, and so sailed under our Stern.</i></p>

<p><i>And as the Dutch passed by they did make expressions of great joy for the Peace between their Commonwealth and ours. The Lord in mercy give us all hearts to improve these great providences which his <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> is pleased to <reg orig="dispence">dispense</reg> towards us poor worthless ones, and <reg orig="helpe">help</reg> us to <reg orig="seeke">seek</reg> after that Peace which hath eternity written in it.</i></p>

<p>May 13. 1654.</p>

<p><em>Plymouth Sound 16 May, 1654</em>. Sir Captain <em>John Seaman</em> Commander of the <em>Dragon</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> with the Adventure <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> plying off of <em>Alderney</em>, they met with a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Frenchman, which had been taken by an <em>Ostender</em> near <em>Bell</em> Island; Our Captains being informed that she was laden with English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> goods, they sent her into <em>Weymouth</em> to have that business further examined.</p>

<p>On the 10 instant, plying off to <em>Dartmouth</em> they met with three <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> which belong to <em>Lyn</em>, and upon the desire of the Masters thereof, they convoyed them safe over <em>Murleux</em>, whither they<pb n="6" />saw them safe, and standing off again, met with 25 sail of French men which were bound for <em>Rochel</em> to take in Salt, and so on for the bank of Newfoundland, but before they got to <em>Rochel</em> they chased them half a day, but could take but three of them, because they steered so many several courses, while we were upon the chase of them our men descried another Fleet to the windward, which were found to be thirteen sale of <em>Holland</em> merchant ships with one Convoy in their company, he saluted ours with three guns, and some expressions of love, and so they passed on their voyage, and ours parted from them, and are now at this present come in here to <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> Sound.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Paris 23 May 1654.</i></head>

<p>The 8 instant the Princess of <em>Conde</em> petitioned the Parliament to have the Sequestration off from her estate, but they would not hearken to it, but was referred to the King himself.</p>

<p>The 15. the Cardinal <em>Mazerin</em> feasted very sumptuously at the <em>Bois de Vicennes</em> the King, the Queen, the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> brother and several other Grandees, The same day the Queen sent her Congratulation to the <em>Marshal de l'Hospital</em> our Governor, about the birth of his Son.</p>

<p>The 20. the Italian Comedy was again represented before the Queen, where were present the little Queen, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> and his two Brothers, the Cardinal, and all the Court. The same day all the Hangings and other necessary <reg orig="Housholdstuff">Household stuff</reg> for the King and the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Lodgings at Rheims were sent from hence; Mr. <em>de Salntot</em> the Mr. of the Ceremonies being gone thither with the Orders for the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Coronation. Marshal <em>de Turenne</em> is preparing to go from hence to <em>Montcornet</em>, where is the general <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> of all the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> forces designed for that Army. All Officers are commanded to report thither speedily. The Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em> is re-establishing his great Library wherein are already above 30000 Volumes, among which are many excellent Manuscripts Greek, Hebrew and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Languages.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Bapume 18 May.</i></head>

<p>The 16 instant the Count <em>de Navailles</em> our Governor upon advice that some Horse &amp; Foot of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Castelet was plundering the Villages about him, sent Mr. <em>de la Grange</em> with part of<pb n="7" />our <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> to prevent their retreat which they did, and took forty Prisoners, and their Commander, with all their Plunder, which was presently restored to the <reg orig="Country-men">Countrymen</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>La Bassee the 17. of May, 1654.</i></head>

<p>There are daily some skirmishes between our Parties and the Enemies, which hath forced the <em>Lorainers</em> to remove from the Land of <em>Lalea</em>, and quarter themselves in an open Country upon the borders of the River of <em>Lys</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Mouson the 17 of May, 1654.</i></head>

<p>The Count of <em>Grandpre</em> our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, having <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> the great Convoy going for <em>Stenay</em>, and <em>Elermont</em>, and forced <em>Marchin</em> to retire himself into <em>Luxemburg</em>, and send his provisions into <em>Montmedy</em>, hath set a Corps de Guard at the very Gate of the said <em>Stenay</em>, and carried away all the Cattle there, on purpose to draw out the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, but they would not <reg orig="stirre">stir</reg>, and keeps therein the Count of <em>Meille</em>, <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Clemount</em> so close, that nothing can come in nor go out.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Venice the 27 of April, 1654.</i></head>

<p>Three of their <reg orig="Turkes">Turk's</reg> <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> have <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> <em>Canea</em>, the <em>Turkish</em> General hath challenged the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Candia</em> to a Skirmish, but nothing was done thereupon.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rome the 27 of Aril, 1654.</i></head>

<p>The eighteenth instant the Duke of <em>Terranova</em>, Ambassador of <em>Spain</em> had a long audience of the Pope, to whom he complained from his Master of the discontent he received in the person of his Ministers; and among others, that Cardinal <em>Colonna</em> was not suffered to propound in the Consistory the vacant <reg orig="Bishoprick">Bishopric</reg>, of <em>Catalonia</em>; that he was resolved not to permit any longer the Benefices within his Dominions, to be charged with any other Pension but such as he should be pleased to allow of.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Madora the 14. of March, 1654.</i></head>

<p>The Ships belonging to the <em>French</em>, of company of the Continent of <em>America</em> are gone from hence, having taken in some Wines, being well pleased to hear by a ship coming from thence that the <em>French</em> Plantation at <em>Cayenne</em> is very well <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, since people come from the adjacent Islands to inhabit there, there being abundance of lading for ships.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 2. of May, 1654.</i></head>

<p>Our Magistrates and those of <em>Lubeck</em>, have sent some Deputies<pb n="8" />towards <em>Bremen</em>, to mediate some accommodation between the <em>Swedes</em> and the said place, General <em>Koningsmarck</em> hath taken considerable quarter about the said City, which was <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> to him at <em>Mevas</em>, by forty men that kept it.</p>

<head level="3">A DECLARATION</head>
<head level="3"><i>By the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the united Provinces of the Netherlands.</i></head>

<p>The States general of the united Provinces of the Netherlands, to all Persons whom these presents shall come greeting.</p>

<p><i>Whereas is in the thirtieth Article of the Peace, Union, Confederation, and perpetual League, agreed between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and us the States <reg orig="generall">General</reg> of the united Provinces of the Netherlands, it was concluded amongst other things, that four Commissioners should be nominated on both sides to meet at <em>London</em> upon the eighteenth day of <em>May</em> next old stile, authorised and <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to examine and determine all the losses and injuries <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> by either side, to have sustained from the other side, since the year 1611. unto the 18 day of <em>May</em> 1652. old stile, as well in the <em>East-Indies</em>, as in <em>Greenland, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brazill">Brazil</reg></em>, or in any other place where either party can pretend they have suffered. We do therefore hereby warn all persons whom it may concern to bring in their particulars to be delivered into the Commissioners nominated as above before the said 18 day of May, under this restriction that after the said day prefixed no new complaint is to be admitted. And to the end that those Provinces who do exercise commerce, and <reg orig="traffick">traffic</reg> at Sea, the East and West India Companies, the <em>Muscovy</em> and <em>Brazil</em> Merchants and all such is the Provinces that drive any trade may have full notice thereof, we do therefore free <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> by this our Declaration, to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> the same, to the end all persons whom it may concern may bring in their Accounts from the year 1611. to the 18 May 1652. against the 18 of this month to <em>London</em>, and to deliver in their compliments to them on that day, it being the time prefixed for that <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Given at the meeting of the States General at the <em>Hague</em> 6. (<em>alias</em> 16.) May 1654.</p>

<p><em>John van <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear></em> President <em>pro tempare</em>.</p>

<p><em>N. Ruysch</em>, Clerk to the States General.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Proclamation by the States General of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>, for prevention of disturbances or breach of the Peace, Union, and Confederation, concluded and agreed between<pb n="9" />His Highness Oliver Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg>.</i></head>

<p>The States General of the united Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em>, to all persons to whom these presents <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> come <em>greeting</em>,</p>

<p><i>Whereas (to the praise of Almighty God, the advancement of the general good of the United Provinces, and of every particular person therein) Articles of Peace, Union, and Confederation, are concluded and agreed between His Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, and the Lords the States General of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em> in a Treaty at <em>Westminster</em> hearing date 5 <em>April</em> old stile 1654. and hath been published both in <em>London</em> and in these Provinces, and all acts of hostility are to cease. We therefore the Lords the States General do hereby warn all people of the United Provinces of the <em><reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg></em> that they do acknowledge and submit to the said Peace so ratified, and to obey the Ratification in all places without any breach thereof, upon pain of being punished as disturbers of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace, without expectation of any <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> or grace, but to be proceeded against according to Justice.</i></p>

<p>Given at the meeting of the States General at the <em>Hague</em> 7. (alias 17.) May, 1654.</p>

<p><em>Jacob Vetch</em> President <em>pro tempore</em>.</p>

<p><em>N. Ruysch</em>, Clerk to the States General.</p>

<p><em>Deal 18 May</em>, there are come into the River of Thames this week, many Dutch Merchants ships from <em>Holland</em> and <em>Zealand</em> with several Dutch Wares. There are also many Coal ships come into the Thames, besides many more that are gone for <em>Holland</em>, where they were in great want of them.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 11 May</em>, Yesterday Gen. <em>Monk</em> with divers Officers went from <em>Dalkieth</em> to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, where he hath given Orders for securing some passes to prevent the Scots from the Highlands from falling into the Lowlands thereabouts, as formerly they have done; he is very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in consultation with the Officers about marching into the field, we have lately fallen upon the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> new <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> in several parts, and dispersed them, and beaten some plunderers, we have also taken the brother of Major. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> and five Officers more, and routed that party, who were privately <reg orig="harbored">harboured</reg> at an Inn in <em>Muscleborough</em>, two of them<pb n="10" />have been <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> by a Council of War since Gen. <em>Monk</em> came into <em>Scotland</em>, who have been hanged for Spies, and the Inn where they <reg orig="harbored">harboured</reg> is burnt down.</p>

<p>This day Proclamation was made in St. <em>Giles</em> and <em>Holburn</em> and parts adjacent, to give notice of a <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> cutting and usage of a <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> body, without <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> or Legs, or any of the Head but the <reg orig="Eies">Eyes</reg>, Nose, Chin, and other parts of the Face left, nor any bones but two Ribs and part of the Back, covered over by a sack, and cast into a ditch half buried near <em>Totnam</em> Court, not far from <em><reg orig="Pancrass">Pancras</reg></em> Church, some are apprehended about it upon <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 20 May.</i></head>

<head level="3">A Narrative of the surrender of the <em>Recif</em> in <em><reg orig="Brasill">Brazil</reg></em>, by the <em>Hollanders</em> to the <em><reg orig="Portugalls">Portuguese</reg></em>.</head>

<p>The Governor of <em>Fernambove</em> in <em><reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em> for the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, whose name is <em>Francisco Barreto</em>, having obtained <reg orig="severall">several</reg> advantages upon the Hollanders there, blocked up their strong Fort of <em>Recif</em>, in the said <em><reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>, with the small forces <reg orig="hee">he</reg> had, notwithstanding the 28 Forts the <em>Hollanders</em> had round about, at length by the assistance of the <em>Portugal</em> fleet of 65 sail, who blocked up the place by Sea, and Landed some Forces there; on the fifth of <em>January</em> last <reg orig="hee">he</reg> stormed and took the Fort of <em>Salines</em>. The <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> <reg orig="hee">he</reg> came before the Fort of <em>Buraco</em>, which was presently abandoned and blown up by those within, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> came after to the New fort, the next to the <em>Recif</em>, and very strong and well manned, which after a stout resistance was taken by the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, as were since some other of their Forts, which so amazed the <em>Hollanders</em>, that though they had above 1500 men, and provisions for above six months in the <em>Recif</em>, they agreed to surrender the same on the 26 of <em>January</em> 1654. Being 24 years after they had taken it from the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>: The Articles were thus.</p>

<p><i>1. That <em><reg orig="Signieur">Signor</reg> Francisco Bareto</em> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> forget all Hostages made by the <em>Hollanders</em> against the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em> by Sea or Land. 2 All persons whatsoever, even the Jews in <em>Recif</em> and <em>Maurice</em> Town, though rebels against the King of <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="bee">be</reg> pardoned. 3. All <em>Hollanders</em> shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> free to carry away their goods they actually possess. 4. They <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have sufficient number of ships able to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the <reg orig="Equinoctiall">Equinoctial</reg> Line, with Iron guns for their transportation. 5 The <em>Hollanders</em> <reg orig="marryed">married</reg> with <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> women, or native there, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> dealt<pb n="11" />so withal as if they had <reg orig="marryed">married</reg> <em>Dutch</em> women, and shall, if the women consent, have power to carry them away with them. 6 Those that will stay and remain there, under the obedience of the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, shall be used as well as if they were native <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, and as to their Religion, they shall live as other strangers do in <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>. 7 All Forts about <em>Recif</em> and <em>Maurice</em> Town, viz. The Fort of 5 Bastions, <em>Boa, Vista</em>, St. <em><reg orig="Austines">Austine's</reg> Covent</em>, the Castle of <em>Maurice</em> Town, that of the 3 <reg orig="bastiens">bastions</reg>, the <em>Brum</em> with its Redout, the Castle of St. <em>George</em>, and all others shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> to the said <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Fernambove</em>, with all the Ordnance and ammunitions, presently after the subscribing of the said Articles. 8. The <em>Hollanders</em> shall be free to remain in <em>Recif</em> and <em>Maurice</em> Town for three months, they <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> their <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, which shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> restored to them, when they shall take shipping, and in the mean while they shall have power to buy them necessary provisions of the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, for their voyage. 9 All negotiations and alienations shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> made during the said three months, according to the present Articles. 10 The said Governor shall quarter his Forces where he please, shall protect the <em>Hollanders</em> from all molestation, and during these three months, shall suffer them to end their private differences before their own Judges. 11 They shall carry away all their papers whatsoever. 12 If they cannot sell their goods in the said three months time, they shall leave them with whom they please, under the obedience of the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> disposed of according to their own Order. 13 They shall have all victuals in the <reg orig="store-houses">storehouses</reg> in <em>Recif</em> and other Forts for their Voyage.</i></p>

<p><i>14. As to their <reg orig="pretencions">pretensions</reg> against the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, they may sue them at the King of <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portugal's</reg></em> Court. 15 All their vessels shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> restored to them, which they may fit for their voyage. 16 They may <reg orig="advice">advise</reg> all their ships upon the coasts to come to <em>Recif</em> where they might load them with their goods. And 17 Upon the demand of the <em>Hollanders</em> that this Treaty might not prejudice any former Treaty between the King of <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> and the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, the said <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> would not agree thereunto.</i></p>

<p>As to the Military Forces they had the following Articles granted them.</p>

<p><i>1 All offences and hostages shall be forgotten. 2 All <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> shall go out of <em>Recif</em> and other Forts, with their Arms, Match lighted, Bullet in mouth, spread colours, but <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in at the <em>Portugal</em> Army they shall put out their march, and put their<pb n="12" /><reg orig="armes">arms</reg> in the <reg orig="Magazeens">Magazines</reg> appointed by the Governor, to be restored them at their departure, they going to <em>Nantes, Rochel</em>, or any other place of the United Provinces, and not to any belonging to the King of <em>Portugal</em>; for security whereof they shall give three Hostages, and all Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be <reg orig="shiped">shipped</reg> together with Gen. <em>Sigismond Schop</em> after the delivery of the Forces of <em>Riogrande, Paraiba</em>, and <em>Tantaries</em>.</i></p> 

<p><i>3 The said General shall have 20 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of brass Ordnance from four pounds bullet to 18, with all their <reg orig="furnitures">furniture</reg>, besides all necessary iron guns for the defence of the ships that shall be afforded them for their transportation. 4. The said ships shall be afforded him ready with Ammunition and Artillery. 5. The <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> shall have victuals according to the Tenor of the thirteenth Article aforesaid, and if there be not enough the Governor to afford the overplus. 6 The General <em>Sigismond</em> shall either carry away or sell all his goods whatsoever in <em>Recif</em>, and his slaves also, which <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> shall extend to all his Officers of War. 7. All sick and wounded persons shall remain in the Hospital till they be recovered. 8. Whilst the said <reg orig="Generals">General's</reg> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> shall remain there, they shall receive no offence from the <em><reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg></em>, and in case of any wrong they shall be righted by the Governor. 9. The said Governor cannot agree that the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> might go with those now in <em>Recif</em>, who have <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> or be made prisoners, 10. A general Pardon is granted to all Rebels, chiefly to <em>Amboina, Mendez</em> and all other <em>Indians</em> and <em>Negroes</em>, but they shall not have the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> to go out with their Arms. 11. Presently after the subscribing of the Articles, all the aforesaid places shall be <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> with the Artillery and Ammunitions, and sufficient guard given for the safety of General <em>Sigismond</em> and his Officers. 12. The Governor cannot agree to the demand that this Treaty might not prejudice the former Treaties. 13. The <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Council at <em>Recif</em> oblige themselves to the <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> of the Island of <em>Farnam, Noroga, Viaca, Riogrande, Paraiba</em>, and <em>Tamarica</em> upon the same conditions for the Inhabitants as are granted to those of <em>Recif</em>.</i></p>

<p>These Articles were signed and delivered on both sides at the <reg orig="Campe">Camp</reg> of <em>Taborda</em> the 18 of <em>January</em>, 1654.</p>

<p>These two or three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> have been <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about a Plot by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Providence discovered. Some of the Actors were this day sent to the Tower of which more in due place.</p>

<p>The business of St. <em>Mallows</em> was taken upon trust <unclear>by</unclear> the Diurnal; but it is utterly false, not <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> of it.</p><pb n="13" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 23 May. 1654</i></head>

<p>This day was kept a day of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Thanksgiving to Almighty God, according to the Declaration of His Highness the Lord Protector, lately mentioned, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, and Mr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>, prayed and preached at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, where His <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> and Council were present. And after Sermon a woman made a disturbance by reproaching the present Authority. It was kept in many Parishes in <em>London</em>, and by divers Churches, yet some would not observe it, and some kept a day of Humiliation.</p>

<p><em>Hague 6 (alias 16.) May</em>. Here is arrived an Envoy from the City of <em>Bremen</em> to acquaint the States General of the condition they are in, and to desire counsel and help against the Invasion of the <reg orig="Sweades">Swedes</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Hague</em> 10 (alias 20) <em>May</em>.</head>

<p>Besides the first private Publication and Thanksgiving, the next Monday the Publication of the Peace concluded between <em>England</em> and this State, is to be made through all the United Provinces, and in the evening <reg orig="Bone-fires">Bonfires</reg>, with shooting off the Ordnance, and there shall be eight <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after a day of Thanksgiving shall be kept. The States of <em>Holland</em> are yet sitting. The Princess Royal went yesterday to <em>Onstaerdiick</em> with the young Prince her Son. There is a triumphal Arch built at <em>Amsterdam</em> upon the place called the <em>Dam</em>, where also all the <reg orig="Cannons">Canons</reg> have been brought from the <em>Arsenals</em> to made use of for the expressing our joy upon the news of peace.</p>
	
<head level="3"><i>From the River Elve 6 May.</i></head>

<p>The Magistrates of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em> and <em>Lubeck</em> have sent some Deputies to mediate an agreement between the <em>Swedes</em> and the City of <em>Bremen</em>, whereupon the quarters of the Low <em>Saxony</em>, have also Deputed to <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in that mediation. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> hear from <em>Sweadland</em> that the Queen hath already discharged a great many of her Court Officers and Servants, and that the Lord <em>Erick Oxenstern</em> is named to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent Extraordinary Ambassador into <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Bremen 17 May.</i></head>

<p>The <em>Swedes</em> have commanded upon great penalties the Inhabitants of this County to work about the fencing of the Suburbs of this City, lately taken by them. The <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> hath<pb n="14" />in the mean time issued out a command, by which the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Koningsmark</em> is forbidden to molest any more this City, and commanded to deliver us up again our Suburbs, <em>Veghemsack</em>, and all the other places <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath taken from us, forbidding also the Bores, or any other of these parts to assist the <em>Swedes</em>.</p>

<p><i>From Hamburg 12 May</i>. The Deputies of the Low <em>Saxony</em> have not only met here with our Commissioners about the relief of the City of <em>Bremen</em> but also to make a defensive league with us.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 24 May.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>By the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Enemies of the peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal Providences of God in frustrating of their former counsels and malicious Designs) do appear still restless in their Attempts, to involve this Commonwealth in blood and confusion. In order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of the Commonwealth. His Highness with the advice of his Council, hath therefore thought fit, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> charge and command, that for the better discovery of persons <reg orig="il">ill</reg> affected to the peace of this Commonwealth, the Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westm</em>. <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em> and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the publication hereof, repair to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> houses within their respective Parishes, and require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as now do or did lodge in their respective houses on Friday night last being the 19. of this instant <em>May</em>, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names upon peril of being reputed and dealt withal as <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg> and Partakers in the said Designs. Which List so delivered, the respective Constables of the parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em> &amp; <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em> and Lines of Communication, are within 48 hours to deliver the Lord Mayor of London, &amp; <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of Westminster &amp; Southwark, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril.</p>

<p>And the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffes">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>,<pb n="15" />immediately after the receipt thereof. And his Highness doth likewise strictly command and require, that no person or persons whatsoever lodging, within the Lines of Communication, do change his or their several &amp; respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the date hereof, without a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> <reg orig="Licence">License</reg> and <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor of the said City of <em>London</em>; or <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Westminster</em> or <em>Southwark</em> respectively, under their respective hands and seals; which <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> the said Lord Mayor and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em> and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are hereby authorized to give all such persons concerning whom they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be satisfied, that they have no ill intentions or designs against the Commonwealth, and to none else. And if any such person shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without <reg orig="Licence">License</reg> obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a contempt of this his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> command and be punished according to its demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, of <em>Westminster</em> and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after publication thereof, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Constables as aforesaid, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<p><i>Given at Whitehall 23 May.</i></p>

<p>The Plot upon the best Intelligence I have, was to have Murdered the Lord Protector, the time to be Saturday or Sunday last, then to have seized on all our Ports, and to rise in several parts to a bloody massacre, and <em>Charles Stuart</em> to be brought over, and proclaimed King.</p>

<p>A Vessel was taken with letters from <em>France</em>; And he whom they say should have murdered his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, leaped <reg orig="Over-board">Overboard</reg> and drowned himself, whose name was <reg orig="Fitz-James">Fitzjames</reg>, several of those taken, <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> the Plot, and that it was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Execution, which had it taken would have probably been the bloodiest day that ever was in <em>England</em>; but blessed be God that hath prevented it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of those that are apprehended, some of which are committed to the Tower some at <em><reg orig="Jamses">James's</reg></em>, and two of them under Bail.</i></head>

<!-- The following is arranged in a double column list. The two columns are separated by a single vertical line -->

<p><em>Gilbert Gerhard</em> Esq; Knighted by the late King.</p>
<p><em>John Gerhard</em> a Kinsman of <em>Gilbert <reg orig="Gerhards">Gerhard's</reg></em>.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Tuedor</em> Apothecary by Profession, that lodged in <em>Westminster</em>.</p>
<p>M. <em>James</em> Apothecary in the Strand.</p>
<p><em>Sidney <unclear><!-- name; approximately 9 characters --></unclear></em> a West countryman.</p>
<p>M. <em>Baggaly</em> Secretary to the Ear. of <em>Kingstone</em> titular <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of <!-- 2nd column starts here --> <em>Dorchester</em>, who did formerly belong to the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of Derby.</p>
<p>Dr. <em>Naudin</em> a <reg orig="Physitian">Physician</reg>, a member of the <reg orig="Rebaptized">Rebaptised</reg> Church in White-Friars a <reg orig="French-man">Frenchman</reg>.</p>
<p>Major <em>Mason</em> a <reg orig="Fenser">Fencer</reg> in the New-market <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Covent-Garden.</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Peter Brown</em>.</p>
<p>M. <em>Hill</em> besides others taken about <em>Dover</em>, and other places.</p>

<p>Gen. Monk is gone to <reg orig="Glasco">Glasgow</reg>, where he intends to take the field. Several of the Scots have been brought in prisoners by parties <reg orig="sine">since</reg> he went from Dalkeith.</p>

<p>Another French Prize with Wine is brought into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>


