<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState226">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 226</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 19 of <em>January</em> To Thursday the 26 day of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 19. January. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> removed from the place where hitherto they had met, and <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> in the old <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> chamber where the Council used to sit in former times.</p>

<p>The Spanish Ambassador had this day audience in the horse Chamber, about some affairs touching <reg orig="Merchandizings">Merchandisings</reg>.</p>

<p>Gen Blake went to the Navy.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Sadler</em> is <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with Mr. <em>Long</em>, they being both made Masters of Requests, touching Petitions; and Mr. <em>Hatter</em> is their Secretary. Mr. <em>Emery</em> is Surveyor of the House.</p>

<p>This day passed these two Ordinances following.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>1 An Ordinance by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of the Council, that one Act of Parliament, published in print the second day of <em>January</em> 1649. <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for subscribing the Engagement</i>: And certain Orders, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>Resolves touching the subscribing to an Engagement, &amp;c.</i> And all and every Clause, Branch, Article, and Sentence in them, and every or any of them contained, shall from and after the nineteenth day of <em>January</em> in the year of our Lord 1653. stand and <reg orig="bee">be</reg> absolutely repealed, and <reg orig="adnulled">annulled</reg>; And that all and every Clause, Branch, Article, Proviso or sentence contained in any other Act, Ordinance, Resolves or Order of Parliament, whereby the said Oath of Engagement is directed, and appointed to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> taken, and administered, and all and every the penalties, losses, incapacities, disabilities, and forfeitures for not taking or subscribing the same, shall from and after the said nineteenth day of <em>January</em> in the year of our Lord 1653. (as to so much only, (and no more) as concerneth the said Engagement, and the penalties, losses, incapacities, disabilities, and forfeitures for not taking or subscribing the same, <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, and are hereby utterly repealed, and made void, &amp;c.</p>

<p>2 An Ordinance whereby His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> doth Declare, Establish and Ordain, and be it Established and Ordained by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of His Council, That if any person or persons shall <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg> or imagine the death of the Lord Protector for the time being; Or if any person or persons shall maliciously or advisedly either by writing, printing, openly declaring, preaching, teaching, or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector and the people in Parliament assembled are not the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Authority of this Commonwealth; Or that the exercise of the chief Magistracy and administration of the Government over the said Countries and Dominions, and the people thereof, is not in the Lord Protector assisted with a <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>; Or that the said Authority or Government is tyrannical, usurped or unlawful; Or that there is any Parliament now in being, or that hath any continuance, or any Law in force for continuing the Parliament which is hereby declared to have been absolutely dissolved and determined upon the twentieth of <em>April</em>, 1653. and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be adjudged <pb n="2" />and taken so to be; or shall plot contrive or <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to stir up or raise force against the Protector or the present Government, or for the subversion or alteration of the same, and shall declare such endeavour or endeavours by any open Deed, Then every such Offence shall be taken and adjudged to be High Treason. &amp;c.</p>

<p>Or if any person (not being an Officer, <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> or Member of the Armies or Forces) shall plot, contrive, or endeavour to stir up any mutiny in the said Armies, or among the said Forces, or any of them; Or to withdraw any <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> or Officers from their obedience to their Superior Officers, or from the present Government as aforesaid; Or if any person or persons whatsoever shall procure, invite, aide, or assist any Foreigners or Strangers to invade <em>England, Scotland</em> or <em>Ireland</em> or any the Dominions thereunto belonging; Or shall adhere unto any Forces raised by the Enemies of this Commonwealth; or if any person and persons shall plot, contrive, or endeavour the betraying, surrendering or <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up any City, Town, Fort, Magazine, Ship, Vessel or Forces by Sea or Land belonging to this Commonwealth; Or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the great Seal of <em>England</em>, or of <em>Scotland</em>, or <em>Ireland</em> for the time being, used and appointed by Authority of Parliament, or by the Lord Protector with the consent of the Council; or the sign Manual, Privy Signet, or Privy <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> of the Lord Protector for the time being; Or if any person or persons whatsoever shall Proclaim, Declare, Publish or any way promote <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> Eldest son to the late King, or <em>James Stuart</em> one other of his Sons, or any other the Issue or Posterity of the said late King, or any other person or persons claiming by, from or under him or them, or either or any of them, to be King or <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Magistrate of <em>England, Scotland</em>, or <em>Ireland</em>, or of either or any of them, or of any the Dominions to them, or either or any of them belonging; Or if any person or persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give, keep, or hold any Intelligence whatsoever, by Letters, Messages, or otherwise, to or with the said <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, James Stuart</em>, the late Queen their Mother or any of them; Or if any person or persons shall counterfeit the money of this Commonwealth; or shall bring any false money into this Land, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg>, and it is hereby declared to be the <pb n="3" /><reg orig="ful">full</reg> purpose and true intent and meaning of this Ordinance, that the Laws and Statutes made in the times of the late Queen <em>Elizabeth</em> and of King <em>James</em> against the pretended Authority of the Bishop of <em>Rome</em> and his See, <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits</reg>, Seminary Priests, and Professors of the Romish Religion, should not be repealed, but stand, be, and continue in full force and effect in every Clause and part thereof, &amp;c. as is more at large <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in the Acts themselves, Printed by <em>William Du Gard</em> and <em>Henry Hils</em>, Printers to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 20 January, 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Council met at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector received divers petitions, by the Masters of Requests, at the Cock pit, and present dispatches issued out.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> was this day advertised as followeth,</p>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>The last Letters from the North inform, that the Lord <em>Kenmore, <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg>, mac Aldow</em> with 6 or 700 men, are about the Lord of <em><reg orig="Grants">Grant's</reg></em> bounds, and <em>Strathspey</em>, where <em><reg orig="Seaforths">Seaforth's</reg></em> party is expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath drawn out a party of Horse and Foot to engage them (if possible) in case they come <reg orig="downe">down</reg> from the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. Capt. <em>Hart</em> lately sent a party of Horse from <em>Kelso</em> into <em>Northumberland</em>, where they took one <em>John Richardson</em> a Mosse Trooper, who lay to be a <reg orig="guid">guide</reg> to some party out of <em>England</em>, and one <em>John King</em> who was a Corporal with Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, we have not certainty whether Sir <em>Arthur</em> be dead or living. Young <em>Montrosse</em> with about 20 horse is lately <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with the Enemy, and also the Lord <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Gordon</em> (<reg orig="onely">only</reg> Brother to the late Marquis <em>Huntley</em>, and the head of that <em>Clan</em>) is gone in to them. They proceed very vigorously in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> was lately with 2 or 300 Horse, and about 500 Foot at <em>Cowper</em> in <em>Angus</em>, and from thence went to <em>Meagil</em> and so back to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>.</p>

<p>I have sent you the copy of one of Gen. <em><reg orig="Glengarns">Glencairn's</reg></em> Letters; the like of which he sent to the several other <reg orig="Sherifdoms">Sheriffdoms</reg>, where he hath any hopes to raise <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg>. And I have also sent you the copy of a Letter sent to the Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> from the Governor of <em>Ruthen</em> Castle.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p><i>Noble Friends,</i></p>

<p>The <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>, Lord <em>Lorn</em>, <em>Kenmore, Mac Gelday <reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> and some of <em><reg orig="Macgriggers">Macgrigger's</reg></em> men, and <em>Mungo Murray</em> and divers other have been in this Country near a week, and yesterday had a <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg> not far from this Garrison, their whole number of Horse and Foot being about 1500. But most of their Horse are poor country, bare-foot, work beasts, their Infantry, poor, starven, naked yet wicked wretches, very many of them without Arms, and all without Ammunition, except one charge or two.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em> and <em>Lorn</em> fell out to sword drawing, about the command of the men of this Country: And <em>Lorn</em> (I conceive) thinking <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> not able to <reg orig="deale">deal</reg> with <em><reg orig="Glengarne">Glencairn</reg></em>, whose Force was too great for him; The last night with Col. <em>Meines</em> and six Horse, withdrew himself from the Army, and <em><reg orig="Glengarne">Glencairn</reg></em> immediately after notice thereof sent a party of Horse to apprehend him, and hath also sent post to <em>Athol</em> to the same purpose.</p>

<p>The Enemy if they hold their Resolution, after they have devoured this Country (which at the rate they use it now <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not last long) will divide <em><reg orig="Glengarn">Glencairn</reg></em> towards <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg>, <reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Cathnesse">Caithness</reg></em>, and <em>Kenmore</em> towards <em>Aberdeenshire</em>. <em><reg orig="Glengarn">Glencairn</reg></em> sent me a Letter stuffed with Scotch Complements, to which I gave him a plain Dunstable English Answer. What is become of <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> men since his departure I have not yet certain knowledge, but the flying Report is, they have dispersed themselves.</p>

<p>Since I came to write, my Intelligence assures me, that the occasion of <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> so sudden flight, was that after he had fallen out with <em><reg orig="Glengarne">Glencairn</reg></em>, the same night he sent a Letter to me, to advise me where to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> <em><reg orig="Glengarn's">Glencairn's</reg></em> men with best advantage; but his Bearer proving false carried his Letter to <em>Kenmore</em>, whereupon they drew up some part of their Army that way thinking to take him that night, but he fled as aforesaid, they have imprisoned seven or eight of the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Gentlemen that were with him; <reg orig="Its">It's</reg> also said that <em>Lorn</em> posted a Letter away to his Father, acquainting him with his condition, and that he was coming to him, the bray men of this Country do close with the Enemy. This is all at present from <!--large space--> Gentlemen,</p>

<p><i>Your Humble Servant, <em>Jo. Hills</em>. Ruthen Castle 2 Janu. 1653.</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i><em>William</em> Earl of <em><reg orig="Glencarne">Glencairn</reg></em>, Lord <em>Kilmore</em>, Commander in chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of <em>SCOTLAND</em>.</i></head>

<p>By <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to Us by his Majesty for levying of Force, Horse and Foot, for suppressing the Common Enemy within this Kingdom; <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> do hereby require you, and every of you, within the shires of <em>Ayre</em> and <em>Renfrew</em>, upon sight hereof, to send forth for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service (forth of every thousand pounds Rent within your said shires respectively, one sufficient well-mounted, with pistols, and other furniture and weapons belonging thereto, and to deliver the same at <em><reg orig="Roscow">Roscoe</reg></em>, to Lieut. Col. <em>George Maxwell</em>, Lieutenant Col. <em>George Herriot</em>, and Captain <em>James Cunningham</em>, or any having their Orders for that effect; certifying all persons of whatsoever quality, within the said shires respectively, that doth either refuse or delay to give obedience to this Our Order, and Commands, they shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> taken notice of, and proceeded against as disloyal Subjects, and <reg orig="profest">professed</reg> Enemies to the present Expedition.</p>

<p>Whereas by the contrary, Wee do oblige <reg orig="Our selves">Ourselves</reg> to protect and defend against all Enemies whatsoever, all such as shall willingly put forth their several proportions of the foresaid Horse levy.</p>

<p>And whatsoever Horses, or any other Goods, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> taken from any one of them, so protected, in any disorderly manner, shall not only <reg orig="bee">be</reg> restored again, but the person or persons offenders, shall according to the quality of the offence, at the sight of the party offended, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> severely punished, to the terror of others; And ordains this to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> published at every Headborough or Parish Church, within the said shires respectively, That every Heritor, and others therein contained, pretend no ignorance of the premises. <i>Given at Garth the 23 of December 1653. Sic Subscribitur, GLENCAIRN.</i></p>

<p><i>For the whole Noblemen, Gentlemen, Heritors, and others, Inhabitants within the Sheriffdoms of <em>Ayre</em>, and <em><reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg></em>.</i> <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> expect your answer at <em><reg orig="Roscow">Roscoe</reg></em> the six of <em>January</em> 1653.</p>

<p><i>This from Colonel <em>Cooper</em>, upon the aforesaid Paper to the Noblemen <pb n="6" />, &amp;c. of <em>Ayre</em> and <em><reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg></em>, is as followeth.</i></p>

<p>Having seen a paper, subscribed <em>Glencairn</em>, <unclear>directed</unclear> to the <em>Noblemen Gentlemen, Heritors, and all others within the shires of Ayre and <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg></em>. Commanding them to set forth horses furnished for war, with sufficient Riders thereon, and to bring in the same to <em><reg orig="Roscow">Roscoe</reg></em>, and to deliver them to such persons as shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> there to receive them.</p>

<p>And least <reg orig="bigge">big</reg> words should fright some, and <reg orig="subtill">subtle</reg> <reg orig="perswasions">persuasions</reg> delude others into obedience of the same papers, to the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, not only of the persons so <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg>, but to the apparent hazard of the peace and welfare of the said Shires, and the inevitable mischiefs that will ensue; These are therefore to require all Noblemen, Gentlemen, Heriots and others, in the said shires of <em>Ayre</em> and <em>Renfrew</em>, to refuse obedience to all such commands, and not in the least <reg orig="bee">be</reg> aiding and assisting to the said Levies, directly or indirectly, nor to hold any correspondence with the said <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>, or his <reg orig="associats">associates</reg>, now in rebellion against the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, as they would not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> held and deemed <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Enemies, and proceeded against as such with the utmost of extremity.</p>

<p>And lest any should pretend ignorance in the same, the Sheriffs of the respective shires are required to take special notice, that copies hereof may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sent to every Church within the said shires to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> published. <i>Given under my hand at <em>Glasgow</em>, this fifth day of January 1653.</i></p>

<p>THO. COOPER</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Wee">We</reg> hear by a ship come from <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>, and also many ships this week come from <em>Dunkirk</em>, of ten of our Merchant men come safely to <em><reg orig="Gotternberge">Gothenburg</reg></em> laden with all Eastern commodities, and five of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> convey to them, who have also homewards bound made several prizes upon the coast of <em>Norway</em>, which will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in <em>England</em> very shortly.</i></p>

<p>All persons are desired to take notice that the Committee for claims for Land in <em>Ireland</em> have appointed Thursday the 9th of <em>February</em> 1653. for Adventurers to draw lots at <em>Grocers hall London</em> for <reg orig="Barronies">Baronies</reg>, and that all persons who intend then to draw lots, do before that day pay their pence.</p>

<p><i>William Tibbs</i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>From the <i>Isle of Wight came thus</i>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Pen</em> is still riding with the Fleet without St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em> Point; some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are passed by to the Eastward, as convoy to 12 sail of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships for the <em>Downs</em>, the winds <reg orig="favoring">favouring</reg> them: Those eight <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> sent to <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> are come in <reg orig="againe">again</reg>, and have brought in with them two Dutch Prizes; there is another party sent out in their stead.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 21 January.</i></head>

<p>Neither His Highness the Lord Protector nor His <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> did this day sit at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>; His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> having divers matters of concernment under His consideration at the <em>Cock-pit</em>, by whose providence, love, and care, many poor oppressed people do already find great <reg orig="releife">relief</reg>.</p>

<p>I am told that there are some, who pretend to <reg orig="godlinesse">godliness</reg>, that are offended with my so freely owning and declaring for this present Government and Change. My Answer is, that though they stand not with it, yet the Lord stands with it, and therefore I can comfortably <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God for it; not that I flatter <reg orig="Greatnesse">Greatness</reg>, for it is well known, most of the Prisons in <em>London</em> are witnesses of my sufferings for opposing Prelacy; and my deep sufferings for appearing for the Saints to the late King, both by Prison, Fine, and Pillory, and hardly escaping with my life is <reg orig="wel">well</reg> known both to the City and the Country; though I never fought for Place, Preferment, or any reparations for my sufferings; My Conscience is my guide, and that taught by the Word of the Lord, and in that give me leave to take my liberty as well as others. I have discoursed with many, and seriously debated it, yet could never find one that could give me a rational account why they were discontented at the present Change of Government, something they have offered, which when weighed hath proved nothing.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> came thus.</p>

<p>Dalkeith 14 Jan. <i>The Printed Government gives much satisfaction to our friends here, and it is Re-printing at <em>Leith</em>, We have received the Letters from the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Officers at <em>London</em> to the Regiments here, and they are signing Representations of approbation thereof, divers of which are sent in, and the rest will be speedily ready, declaring to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> herein.</i></p>

<pb n="8" />

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Regiments in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<!--table in 2 columns separated by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Redes">Rede's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Fenwickes">Fenwick's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Fairfaxes">Fairfax's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Twissletons">Twissleton's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Overtons">Overton's</reg></em></p>
<p>That which was M.G. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Alureds">Alured's</reg></em></p>
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em></p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Colonel <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Ashfields">Ashfields</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Cobbens">Cobben's</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Salmons">Salmon's</reg></em></p>
<p>Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em></p>
<p>Part of Colonel <em><reg orig="Sandersons">Sanderson's</reg></em>.</p>
<p>The Company at <em>Dunbarton</em></p>
<p>Besides going to <em>Scotland</em>.</p>
<p>Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em></p>
<p>Commis: Gen. <em><reg orig="Whalleyes">Whalley's</reg></em></p>
<p>Part of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday, Jan. 23.</i></head>

<p><i>Dalkeith 17 Jan.</i> The Enemy are part in <em>Bagenoth</em>, and part in the Laird of <em><reg orig="Grants">Grant's</reg></em> Bounds. The party that Col. <em>Morgan</em> drew from <em>Aberdeen</em> toward <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em> could not get over <em>Spey</em>, the waters were so high. The <em>Boggy-geith</em> is a very useful Garrison, the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg></em> being removed to <em>Strathbogie</em>. The Enemy are much startled at <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> revolt, and think there is a greater <reg orig="designe">design</reg> in the same <reg orig="then">than</reg> is yet apparent. There is to be a great meeting of all the Clan Campbell in <em>Argyle</em>, it is said to offer some Proposals to the Commander in <reg orig="Cheife">Chief</reg>. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> yet lies wounded in some part of <em>Monteith</em>.</p>

<p>On Thursday last <em>Athol</em> and <em>Lorn</em> were at the house of <em>Balloch</em> near <em>Lough Tay</em>, since which <em>Athol</em> is very sick and in <em>Weems</em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, &amp; <em>Lorn</em> pretends his Father is not <reg orig="reconcileable">reconcilable</reg> to him, whereupon he goes not home. The 14 instant Cap. <em>Crose</em>, Capt. Lieut. to Col. <em>Okey</em> with a party from St. <em>Johnstones</em> fell into the Quarters of about forty of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse about <em>Strabengham</em> near little <em>Dunkel</em> under Lieut. Col. <em>Ramsay</em>, took ten prisoners, and sixteen horses, and killed two on the place.</p>

<p>But a party of Cap. <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> Troop from <em>Drummond</em> had not so good <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, for the Lieut. being sent out with a party of thirty Horse to rescue some Sheep taken by the Enemy near the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> pursued so far as to rout them, but another party of sixty Horse and 100 or 200 foot lying in Ambuscado, our men made a very difficult retreat, in which the Lieutenant, the Cornet, one <pb n="9" />Corporal, and two Troopers was killed, and seven Troopers taken. Divers of the Enemy were killed, and amongst the rest <em>Wogan</em> (as is supposed) <reg orig="hee">he</reg> and the English with him giving the first charge.</p>

<head level="3">From <i><reg orig="Gottenburg">Gothenburg</reg> 22 December, 1653.</i></head>

<p><i>Here are 8 or 10 English Merchant ships esteemed worth 120000 li. <reg orig="sterlings">sterling</reg>, here are also two English men of War, with three Freebooters who <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> daily between <em>Schagen</em> and <em>Notwege</em>, and have brought in two prizes the one of <em>Munikedam</em> coming from <em><reg orig="Dantzick">Danzig</reg></em> and a Dutch Flute.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From Paris 3 January, 1653.</i></head>

<p>The 29. of the last Month, His Majesty and the Cardinal came hither from St. <em><reg orig="Germane">Germain</reg></em>, and the first instant the pretended King of <em>Scots</em> and the Dukes of <em>York</em> and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em> did hear privately a Sermon preached by the Arch Bishop of <em>Ainbrun</em>. There was last week a Proclamation made by order of the Grand Provost, forbidding upon pain of death, that none whosoever should meet within or about this City or in the Suburbs to fling stones one to another, or to fight with any manner of Weapons.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Flushing</em> 5. January.</head>

<p><i>Two <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago came in two Freebooters the one called Capt. <em>Peter Allard</em>, and the other Cap. <em>Cornelius Allard</em> bringing with them two prizes being two Flute of 180 to 200 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, the one with 18 the other with 11 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance, coming from <em>Virgin</em> a laden with Tobacco, Sugar, <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg>, and <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg>-<reg orig="wooll">wool</reg>, the same having been taken upon Christmas even 20 or 30 miles from the Channel. There are also making ready by the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> of the Admiralty 20 new ships of War, of 150, 136, to 130 foot long, and from 36 to 38 foot broad. The Lord <em>Le Brun, Spanish</em> Ambassador is dead in the <em>Hague</em>. There are also two English prizes brought into the <em>Ulie</em> by the Freebooters and some ships coming from the <em>Beld</em> are safely arrived thither,</i></p>

<head level="3">From <em>Amsterdam</em> 13 January.</head>

<p><i>There are some East India ships come into the <em>Ulie</em> four or five of which have been stranded; these had left the whole Fleet about <em>Schagen</em> which is now said to be at the sight of the Land.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From the <em>Hague</em> 16 January.</i></head>

<p>It was here strongly reported that the Highlanders have already obtained a great victory against the English, to wit, that they have taken 2000 horses from them, and taken the City of <em>Aberdeen</em>. The which <reg orig="newes">news</reg> <em>John Evertsen</em> lately come from <pb n="10" /><em>Zealand</em>, first brought hither. And the same <reg orig="newes">news</reg> was after written from <em>Amsterdam</em>. So mad are they here in lies. The ship <em>Aberdeen</em> hath <reg orig="miscarryed">miscarried</reg> upon our coasts. Lieutenant Gen. <em>Middleton</em> who is <reg orig="stil">still</reg> here hath boasted of a Letter from <em>Scotland</em>, pretending that the Highlanders have taken 1500 horses from the English; which they say happened in this manner, to wit, that the English having gathered from <em>Aberdeen</em> and other <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> towns to a great number of horses, and intending to fall upon the Highlanders who were met in a very considerable body, these latter having had warning thereof, and being better acquainted with the Country, have cut the way to the English, in so much that they were forced to march through a <reg orig="Morasse">Morass</reg> ground where their Horses have sticked fast, and by that means they have lost their Horses and <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and have fled a foot back to Aberdeen, the which Town being one of the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Sea towns, the Highlanders have afterwards taken.</p>

<p>And many more such lies are daily here vented. He <reg orig="sayth">sayeth</reg> the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> sent thither from <em>Amsterdam</em> are safely arrived there.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Flushing</em> 16 January.</head>

<p><i>We have daily prizes brought in hither, and the <reg orig="Freebooters">Freebooter's</reg> Capt. <em>Geleyn Brant</em>, Cap. <em>John Brugge</em>, and Cap. <em>Oliver Danielse</em> are lately gone to Sea from hence to meet with some.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>From <em>Mayn</em> 13 January.</i></head>

<p>We hear from <em>Stockholm</em> by the way of <em>Hamburg</em> that the English Extraordinary Ambassador was come to <em>Upsall</em>, and was there <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg> entertained, and that the Great Chancellor had some conference by word of mouth with the said Ambassador, the same Chancellor being thought to be a touchstone in matters of State.</p>

<head level="3">From the Texel 18 Janu.</head>

<p><i>We have news that there was a <reg orig="Streightes">Straits</reg> man come in laden with rich commodities and all manner of fruit, the same having sailed out of the <em>Straits</em> with a fleet of 24 ships, from which he hath been parted by ill weather, and hath passed the danger, and met with no English. Other <em>Straits</em> ships are come since within the <em>Fly</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3">From the Hague 22 <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>.</head>

<p>The Deputies of the States arrived yesterday from <em>England</em>, and thereupon the Lords States have been assembled this day, where <pb n="11" />the said Deputies have made their Report to their High and Mighty Lordships of their Negotiation there. The common report here is that the foresaid Lords Deputies being gone from <em>London</em> to <em>Gravesend</em> without any conclusion of the Treaty, with a Resolution to return home, there came some Commissioners from the Lord Protector to confer with them about the differences remaining, which are said to be; that the English would exclude the King of <em>Denmark</em> from the Treaty; And that this point at last was to remain undecided till the Lords the States General should have ratified the Articles of the said Treaty, the which many do <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be done. The Lords States of the Province of <em>Holland</em> have also met in the assembly of the said Lords States General to have communication of the said Report made to their High and Mighty Lordships to give advice of the same to the towns.</p>

<p>The Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> hath lately received a Letter from <em>Scotland</em> from <reg orig="Glengarn">Glencairn</reg> giving him notice that he by the <reg orig="helpe">help</reg> of the Highlanders hath made <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> Master of <em><reg orig="Sterlingshire">Stirlingshire</reg></em>, and of the whole Northern Quarters of <em>Scotland</em>, and that they have <reg orig="onely">only</reg> need of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> presence, with more <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg> to effect great things against the English.</p>

<p>The Lord Protector and the Council sat close this day in the Council-Chamber.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Terme">Term</reg> this day began, and the Judges sat in the several Benches in <em>Westminster</em>-<reg orig="hal">hall</reg> </p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 24. January.</i></head>

<p>A Translate of a Paper Printed at <em>Harlem</em> in <em>Holland</em> <reg orig="followes">follows</reg> that you may see what they Print there touching the Treaty.</p>

<head level="3">PEACE,</head>

<head level="3"><i>Or true <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of the Peace concluded between the United Provinces, and the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>: To God alone be the glory reported upon the return of the Lords Deputies.</i></head>

<p>That the Deputies of <em>Holland</em> by the dissolution of the last Parliament, and the transferring of the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the said Commonwealth of <em>England</em> to <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> Lord Protector had been interrupted three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> in their Negotiation.</p>

<pb n="12" />

<p>That the third of <em>January</em> 1653. they treated very close with the English Commissioners at <em><reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and the eight very <reg orig="neer">near</reg> perfected the Treaty, which was not brought to a full end, because of some difficulty.</p>

<p>Thereupon their Lordships (as they had done some time before) declaring to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> desirous to return home, and demanding a <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> to that effect; it was granted them the ninth day, and they being gone to <em>Gravesend</em>, the said Treaty hath there been resumed in hand by the English, and all the Articles renewed, whereupon the Allies and Confederates were comprehended in it. And that the fourteenth the Peace was there agreed on, concluded and signed, God Almighty <reg orig="bee">be</reg> praised; being a great blessing for the whole <reg orig="Christendome">Christendom</reg>.</p>

<p>Afterward the Lord Deputies of <em>Holland</em>, after many loving <reg orig="imbracements">embracements</reg>, are gone the 16th into a ship appointed for them, and ready to set <reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, and their Lordships are arrived in the <em>Mase</em> the 21. and about noon to <em>Schiedam</em>, from whence they came that evening to the <em>Hague</em>, where, upon their coming, and the report they have made of the peace concluded, and of all the circumstances, there hat been a great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg>.</p>

<p>The 22 the States have sent Letters to all the Towns and <reg orig="Burroughs">Boroughs</reg> concerning this great and good <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> might <reg orig="bee">be</reg> informed thereof.</p>

<p>The time will not give <reg orig="mee">me</reg> leave (good <reg orig="Country men">Countrymen</reg>) to afford you more particulars of the Treaty; I shall only <reg orig="adde">add</reg> that the Lords States shall at the first day call for a meeting, to agree, <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, and approve the said Articles of Peace. God grant it.</p>

<p>This paper aforesaid was printed in <em>Holland</em>, and it is their News, brought over hither and translated. It is well if they make it good.</p>

<p>There are divers Ambassadors from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Princes come to the <em>Hague</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Capt. <em>Heaton</em>.</i></head>

<p><i>Right Honourable,</i></p>

<p>The 16 instant about 27 leagues W.S.W. from <em><reg orig="Vshant">Ushant</reg></em>, I spake with one of <em>Ostend</em>, who <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that the Thursday before <reg orig="hee">he</reg> came out of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, in company with 40 Hollanders, and 20 others homeward bound; They kept the French shore, <pb n="13" />but had no Convoy; for a ship of 34 guns on whom they depended grounded upon the Pole head coming out, and there sunk of the 17th. at two in the Afternoon with the wind at East.</p>

<p>As I <reg orig="plyed">plied</reg> <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> about 16 leagues south from <em>Scilly</em>, I met with four <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> that bore the English Ensign, and the old <reg orig="Unicorne">Unicorn</reg> Jack.</p>

<p>The greatest was a new ship, not much unlike the <em><reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg></em>, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> somewhat shorter, with a <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Head, a Rampant <reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg>, with a <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Crown in her Stern, and a <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="streake">streak</reg>, as hath the <em><reg orig="Lawrel">Laurel</reg></em>; this I suppose was <em>Beach</em>.</p>

<p>The three smaller did weather us a Saker shot, and the other <reg orig="halfe">half</reg> a shot, as he <reg orig="past">passed</reg> he fired one gun; though four to one yet they would not bear up. They standing to the Northward I <reg orig="tackt">tacked</reg> in their <reg orig="wacke">wake</reg>, and kept them company till night drew his curtain. All this day it was so much wind and Sea, that we could not with safety open a top Sail.</p>

<p>On the 18. instant I hailed with the Lizard, thinking to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> him, and met with 16 of our Merchant ships outward bound, whom I say 20 leagues to the Westward. On the 19 at noon, I met with the Middleborough, and with her a supposed prize. And the last night <unclear><!--four characters--></unclear> with a pretended Dover-man. But the whole company are French, save one Rob. Hopkins of Dover, both which Vessels laden with wine, I have sent into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> by the <reg orig="Middleborow">Middleborough</reg>, and am ranging where I can best imagine, to clear the coast and <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg> of the <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>. The aforesaid Rob. Hopkins <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that on Saturday last, there came out of St. Martins in his company a ship of 26 Guns that came from the West Indies, and with him nine more which are gone on the back side of Ireland, for they steered West from <em>Aberonne de Baies</em>.</p>

<p>And further say that they look for a fleet of 200 sail from <em>Holland</em> which are to come round.</p>

<p><i>From on board the <reg orig="Saphir">Sapphire</reg> in sight of the Lizard, Jan, 20. 1653. Your <reg orig="Honours">Honours'</reg> and the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> humble Servant to be commanded, <em>N. HEATON</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 25 Janua.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> close this day, and <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> late at night. Some persons are apprehended upon the Ordinance for Treason.</p>

<p>Letters from France say <em><reg orig="Conte">Conti</reg></em> is making his peace with the King, and <em>Conde</em> hath a fortnights time to come in, which if he refuse, his estate to be <pb n="14" /><reg orig="sequestred">sequestered</reg>, and he proclaimed <reg orig="Traytor">Traitor</reg>, the Rentiers in <em>Paris</em> grow numerous, and their discontents high.</p>

<p>Some English ships are arrested in <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>A Declaration is signed unanimously by the officers of the English Navy protesting to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with the present Government.</p>

<p>The news from <em>Holland</em> is yet <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg>, notwithstanding all that the Dutch say, and have Printed, the particulars thereof are before expressed.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is highly <reg orig="favored">favoured</reg> by the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, and <reg orig="honored">honoured</reg> by the people.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 19 Jan.</i> The <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Body of the Enemy is now <reg orig="faln">fallen</reg> into <em>Murrayland</em>, where they are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in levying their Sess, and intend to debar correspondence between <em>Aberdeen</em> and <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>. Col. <em>Morgan</em> is drawing all the forces of the Northern parts together to attempt their driving out thence. <em>Athol</em> was <reg orig="latelie">lately</reg> is <em>Strathardle</em>, where he <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> all men to rise, and got together about 500 who had not <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> long with him, but 300 departed without leave. Whereupon he gave <reg orig="libertie">liberty</reg> to all but 60 to be ready upon occasion. The enemy I am confident were no gainers by the loss of Cap. <em><reg orig="Elsmores">Elsmore's</reg></em> party from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, he that commanded the first <reg orig="partie">party</reg> (supposed to be Col. <em>Wogan</em>) was slain, and many of his men. The party consisted of <em><reg orig="Wogans">Wogan's</reg></em> English being 30, and about 40 of Sir Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbs'</reg> his men that were beaten in the South; and the other were Major <em><reg orig="Mercers">Mercer's</reg></em> men that belong to <em>Athol</em>. <em>Wogan</em> and his men stood valiantly to it, otherwise we had totally the <em>Scots</em>. Lieut. <em>Caleb Leigh</em> is certainly killed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes taken since the last week.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from the Generals at Sea dated 20 <em>January</em> in the <reg orig="channell">channel</reg>, is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that the Diamond hat forced on shore, <unclear>(</unclear>on the French side) A Vessel from New Haven, where it is supposed <reg orig="shee">she</reg> is bulged.</p>

<p>A Prize of Wines taken by the <reg orig="Middleborow">Middleborough</reg>, is brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>A French man taken by Cap. <em>Heaton</em>, laden with Wines sent into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>A Fly Boat, called the spotted <reg orig="Oxe">Ox</reg>, an Holland Merchant ship coming from <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> laden with Wine, of 140 Lasts, taken by Cap. <em>Hide</em>, sent into <em>Dartmouth</em>.</p>

<p>A Small Vessel called the Hope of <em>Campheir</em>, with Deal boards and ballast, brought in by the Expedition.</p>

<p>An Holland Merchant ship richly laden, <reg orig="sunke">sunk</reg> upon the coasts of <em>France</em>, upon a chase.</p>

<pb n="15" />

<p>2 Dutch ships sunk <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the coasts of <em>Norway</em>.</p>

<p>A Dutch Merchant ship taken upon the coasts of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>&#x261e; <reg orig="Spirituall">Spiritual</reg> Experiences of sundry <reg orig="Beleevers">Believers</reg>. Held forth by them at <reg orig="severall">several</reg> solemn Meetings and Conferences to that end. With the Recommendation of the sound, <reg orig="spirituall">spiritual</reg> and savoury worth of them, to the sober and <reg orig="spirituall">spiritual</reg> Reader. By Vavasor Powell, <unclear>Minister</unclear> of the Gospel. The second Edition with Additions. To be sold by Thomas Newberry at the three Lions in Cornhill, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Exchange.</p>

<p>An excellent <unclear>piece</unclear> <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, Observations on the present manners of the English, <unclear>briefly</unclear> <reg orig="anatomizing">anatomising</reg> the living by the dead, with an <reg orig="usefull">useful</reg> detection of the Mountebanks in both Sexes. By Richard Whitlock Dr. in <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>, late of All-souls <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Oxon. To <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sold by Humphrey Moseley at the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard.</p>

<p>Parlamentum Imperatorium: Seu Carmina Progymnastica, in centum quinquaginta <unclear>quatuor</unclear>, omnium, Gr&aelig;corum, &amp; Germanicorum C&aelig;sarem, &agrave; C. Julio C&aelig;sare usq; ad <unclear>Ferdinandum</unclear> Secundum C&aelig;sarem Austriacum, Symbola, &amp; dicta Imperatoria. Opera <unclear>Lusiditerania</unclear> Thom&aelig; Crymes, D. Georgii Crymes (alias Graham) de Peckham in Com. Surr. Equitis <unclear>silii</unclear> natu maximi. &AElig;tatis su&aelig; decimoquarto. Sold by L. Chapman at the Grown in Popes head Alley.</p>

<p>Jus Divinum Regiminis Ecclesiastici: Or the Divine Right of Church-Government, asserted and evidenced by the holy Scriptures. The third Edition corrected and augmented in many places, and an <reg orig="Alphabeticall">Alphabetical</reg> Table to the whole annexed. By sundry Ministers of Christ within the City of London. Sold by George Calvery at the Half-Moon in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church yard">Churchyard</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the little North door.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Prayer unclasped, with a Vindication of it against all <reg orig="Schismaticks">Schismatics</reg>, and <reg orig="Hereticks">Heretics</reg>, called Enthusiasts, and Fratricilli, By James Harwood, B.D. Sold by G. and H. Eversden at the <reg orig="Grey-hound">Greyhound</reg> in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p> 

<p>The French Cook, prescribing the way of making ready all sorts of Meats, Fish and Flesh, with the proper sauces, together with the whole skill of <reg orig="Pastery">Pastry</reg> work, and a Treatise of Conserves both dry and liquid, A la mode de France. The second Edition corrected and <reg orig="Inlarged">Enlarged</reg>. Also</p>

<p>A Learned Discourse of Ceremonies, retained and used in Christian Churches, Written by the Right reverend Father in God Lancelot Andrews, late Bishop of Winchester, a little before his death, printed by the <reg orig="Originall">Original</reg> Copy, written with his own hand. Both sold by Charles Adams at the <unclear>Talbot</unclear> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Danstans">Danstan's</reg> Church in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>.</p>

<p>The Works of Dr. Tho. Taylor, late Minister of Aldermanbury London, containing 24 Treatises, besides divers Sermons on sundry Texts, published under the hands of Edm. <unclear>Calamy</unclear>, Jo. Caryll, Dr W. Gouge, W. Strong, Geo. Gryfith, Ra. Venning, W. Greenhil, Tho. Manton, W. Jemmat, Tho. Brooks.</p>

<p>A Treatise called the Establishment, handling the power of the <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg> Magistrate in matters of Religion, particularly in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of Tythes, and Toleration An Instituted and fixed <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>. The necessity and excellency of humane Learning.</p>

<p>The Works of Robert Harris, once of Hanwell, now President of Trinity <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> Oxon. Revised, Corrected, and now collected into one Volume, with an addition of sundry Sermons, some not printed in the former Edition, others never before extant, by R. Harris D D Oxon.</p>

<p>A <unclear>Discourse</unclear> of the state of man in the first and second Adam, printed by <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> in 12, published by Ro. Harris D D. being part of the folio Works.</p>

<p>Certain Sermons of Ro. Harris once of Hanwell, now President of Trinity <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg> in Oxon, being a supplement printed for their benefit who have the works of a former Edition. All to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> sold by John Bartlet at the Gilt Cup in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Churchyard, over against the Woollen Drapers.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>