<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState223">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 223</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 29 of <em>Decemb.</em> To Thursday the 5 day of <em>January</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Beginning on Thursday 29. December. 1653.</head>

<head level="3"><i>The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<p>1 That the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative Authority of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, shall be, and reside, in One Person, and the People assembled in Parliament; The <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of which person shall be <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>2 That the exercise of the chief Magistracy and Administration of the Government over the said Countries and Dominions, and the People thereof, shall be in the <em>Lord Protector</em>, assisted with a Council, the number <pb n="1" />whereof shall not exceed twenty one, nor be <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> thirteen.</p>

<p>3 That all Writs, Processes, Commissions, Patents, Grants and other things, which now run in the Name and <reg orig="stile">style</reg> of the Keepers of the Liberty of <em>England</em> by Authority of Parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> run in the Name and Style of the Lord <em>Protector</em>, from whom, for the future, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be derived all Magistracy and <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> in these three Nations; and shall have the power of Pardons, (except in case of Murder and Treason) and benefit of all forfeitures for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> use. And shall govern the said Countries and Dominions in all things by the advice of the Council; and according to these Presents, and the Laws.</p>

<p>4 That the Lord <em>Protector</em>, the Parliament sitting; <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> dispose and order the Militia and Forces both by Sea and Land, for the peace and good of the three Nations, by consent of Parliament; And that the Lord <em>Protector</em>, with the advice and consent of the major part of the Council, shall dispose and order the Militia for the ends aforesaid in the Intervals of Parliament.</p>

<p>5 That the Lord Protector by the advice aforesaid shall direct, in all things concerning the keeping and holding of a good <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> Kings, Princes and States; and also with the consent of the major part of the Council have the power of War and Peace.</p>

<p>6 hat the Laws shall not be altered, suspended, abrogated, or repealed, nor any new Law made, nor any Tax, Charge, or Imposition laid upon the people, but by common consent in Parliament, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as is expressed in the thirteenth Article.</p>

<p>7 That there shall be a Parliament summoned to meet at <em>Westminster</em> upon the third day of <em>Septemb.</em> 1654. and that successively a Parliament shall be summoned once in every third year, to be accounted from the dissolution of the preceding Parliament.</p>

<p>8 That neither the Parliament to be next summoned, not any successive Parliaments, shall, during the time of five Months, to be accounted from the day of their first meeting, be adjourned, prorogued or dissolved without their own consent.</p>

<p>9 That as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> the next as all other successive Parliaments, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be summoned, and elected in manner hereafter <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; That is to say, the persons to be chosen within <em>England, Wales</em>, the Isles <pb n="2" />of <em>Jersey</em> and <em>Guernsey</em>, and the Town of <em>Berwick</em> upon Tweed, to sit and serve in Parliament, shall be, and not exceed the number of four hundred. The persons to be chosen within <em>Scotland</em> to sit and serve in Parliament <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and not exceed, the number of thirty. And the persons to be chosen to sit in Parliament for <em>Ireland</em>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and not exceed the number of thirty.</p>

<p>10 That the persons to be elected to sit in Parliament from time to time for the several Counties of <em>England, Wales</em>, the Isles of <em>Jersey</em> and <em><reg orig="Guernesey">Guernsey</reg></em>, and the Town of <em>Berwick</em> upon Tweed and all places within the same respectively, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be according to the proportions and numbers hereafter expressed, That is to say,</p>

<p>For the Town of <em>Bedford</em> 1. For the County of <em>Bedford</em> 5. <em>Abingdon</em> 1. <em>Reading</em> 1. the County of <em>Berks</em> 5. Buckingham 1. <em><reg orig="Alisbury">Aylesbury</reg></em>1. <em>Wiccomb</em> 1. the County of <em>Bucks</em> 5. <em>Cambridge</em> 1. The University of <em>Cambridge</em> 1. <em>Ely</em> 2. the County of <em>Cambridge</em> 4. <em>Chester</em> 1. the County of <em>Chester</em> 4. <em>Launceston</em> 1. <em>Truro</em> 1. <em>Penrin</em> 1. <em>Eastlow</em> and <em>Westlow</em> 1. the County of <em>Cornwall</em> 8. Carlisle 1. the County of <em>Cumberland</em> 2. <em>Derby</em> 1. the County of <em>Derby</em> 4. <em><reg orig="Excester">Exeter</reg></em> 2. <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> 2. <em>Dartmouth, Clifton</em>, and <em>Hardness;</em> 1. Totness; 1. <em>Barnstable</em> 1. <reg orig="Tiverten">Tiverton</reg> 1. <em>Honyton</em> 1. The County of <em>Devon</em> 11. <em>Dorchester</em> 1. <em>Weymouth</em>, and <em>Melcomb-Regis</em> 1. <em>Lyme-Regis</em> 1. <em>Pool</em> 1. The County of <em>Dorset</em> 6. <em>Durham</em> 1. the County of <em>Durham</em> 2. <em>York</em> 2. <em>Kingston</em> upon <em>Hull</em> 1. <em>Beverly</em> 1. <em>Scarborough</em> 1. <em>Richmond</em> 1. <em>Leeds</em> 1. <em>Halifax</em> 1. the County of <em>York</em>, the West-riding 6. the East-riding 4. the North-riding 4. <em>Maldon</em> 1. Colchester 2. the county of <em>Essex</em> 13. Gloucester 2. <em><reg orig="Tewksbury">Tewkesbury</reg></em> 1. Cirencester 1. the County of <em>Gloucester</em>, except the said City 5. <em>Hereford</em> 1. <em>Leompster</em> 1. the County of <em>Hereford</em> 4. St. <em><reg orig="Alban">Albans</reg></em> 1. <em>Hartford</em> 1. the County of <em>Hartford</em> 5. <em>Huntington</em> 1. the County of <em>Huntington</em> 3. <em>Canterbury</em> 2. <em>Rochester</em> 1. <em><reg orig="Maidston">Maidstone</reg></em> 1. <em>Dover</em> 1. <em>Sandwich</em> 1. <em>Quinborough</em> 1. the county of <em>Kent</em> 11. <em>Preston</em> in <em>Anderness</em> 1. <em>Lancaster</em> 1. <em>Liverpool</em> 1. <em>Manchester</em> 1. the county of <em>Lancaster</em> 4. <em>Leicester</em> 2. the county of <em>Leicester</em> 4. <em>Lincoln</em> 2. <em>Boston</em> 1. <em>Grantham</em> 1. <em>Stamford</em> 1. <em>Grimsby</em> 1. the county of <em><reg orig="Lincolne">Lincoln</reg></em> 10. <em>Westminster</em> 2. the county of <em>Middlesex</em> 4. the City of <em>London</em> 6. the county of <em>Monmouth</em> 3. <em>Norwich</em> 2. <em>Lynn-Regis</em> 2. <em>Yarmouth</em> 2. the county of <em>Norfolk</em> 10. <em>Peterborough</em> 1. <em>Northampton</em> 1. the county of <em>Northampton</em> 6. <em>Nottingham</em> 2. the county of <em>Nottingham</em> 4. <em>Newcastle</em> upon <em><reg orig="Tine">Tyne</reg></em> 1. <em>Berwick</em> 1. the county of <em>Northumberland</em> 3. <em>Oxford</em> 1. University <pb n="3" />of <em>Oxford</em> 1. <em>Woodstock</em> 1. the county of <em>Oxford</em> 5. For the county of <em>Rutland</em> 2. <em>Shrewsbury</em> 2. <em>Bridgnorth</em> 1. <em>Ludlow</em> 1. the county of <em>Salop</em> 4. <em>Lichfield</em> 1. <em>Stafford</em> 1. <em>Newcastle</em> on the Line<!--under Lyme?--> 1. the county of <em>Stafford</em> 3. <em>Taunton</em> 2. <em>Bath</em> 1. <em>Wells</em> 1. <em>Bridgewater</em> 1. the county of <em>Somerset</em> 11. For the City of <em>Bristol</em> 2. <em>Winchester</em> 1. <em>Southampton</em> 1. <em>Portsmouth</em> 1. the Isle of <em>Wight</em> 2. <em>Andover</em> 1. the county of <em>Southampton</em> 8. Ipswich 2. the <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Bury St. Edmonds</em> 2. <em>Dunwich</em> 1. <em>Sudbury</em> 1. the county of <em>Suffolk</em> 10. <em>Southwark</em> 2. <em>Guilford</em> 1. <em>Rygate</em> 1. the county of <em>Surrey</em> 6. <em>Chichester</em> 1. <em>Lewis</em> 1. <em>East-<reg orig="greenstead">Grinstead</reg></em> 1. <em><reg orig="Arundal">Arundel</reg></em> 1. <em>Rie</em> 1. the county of Sussex 9. the county of <em><reg orig="Westmerland">Westmoreland</reg></em> 2. <em>Coventry</em> 2. <em>Warwick</em> 1. the county of <em>Warwick</em> 4. <em>Worcester</em> 2. the county of <em>Worcester</em> 5. <em>Sarum</em> 2. <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em> 1. <em>Devizes</em> 1. the county of <em>Brecon</em> 2. The county of <em>Cardigan</em> 2. the county of <em>Carmarthen</em> 2. the county of <reg orig="Carnarven">Caernarfon</reg> 2. The county of <em>Denbigh</em> 2. The county of <em>Flint</em> 2. The town of <em><reg orig="Cardiffe">Cardiff</reg></em> 1. For the county of <em>Glamorgan</em> 2. The county of <em>Merionoth</em> 1. The county of <em>Montgomery</em> 2. <em>Haverfordwest</em> 1. the county of <em><reg orig="Pembrock">Pembroke</reg></em> 2. For the county of <em>Radnor</em> 2.</p>

<p>The distribution of the persons to be chosen for <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, shall be according to such proportions and number, as shall be agreed upon, and declared by the Lord Protector and the major part of the Council, before the sending forth Writs of Summons for the next Parliament &amp;c.</p>

<p>11 That the Summons to Parliament <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be by Writ under the great Seal of <em>England</em>, directed to the Sheriffs of the several and respective Counties, with such alteration as may suit with the present Government, to be made by the Lord Protector and his Council, which the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal, shall seal, issue and send abroad by Warrant from the Lord Protector. If the Lord Protector shall not give warrant for issuing of Writs of Summons for the next Parliament, before the first day of <em>June</em> 1654. or for the Triennial Parliaments before the first day of <em>August</em> in every third year, to be accounted as aforesaid. That then the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal for the time being <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> without any warrant or direction within seven <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the said first day of <em>June</em>, 1654. seal, issue and send abroad Writs of summons, &amp;c.</p>

<p>12 That at the day and place of Elections, the Sheriff of each <pb n="4" />county, and the said Majors, Sheriffs, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other head Officers within their Cities, Towns, <reg orig="Burroughs">Boroughs</reg> and places respectively, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take view of the said Elections, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> make return into the <em>Chancery</em> within twenty <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the said Elections, &amp;c. wherein shall be contained, that the persons elected shall not have power to alter the Government as it is hereby <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in one single person and a Parliament.</p>

<p>13 That the Sheriff, who shall wittingly and willingly make any false return, or neglect his duty, shall incur the penalty of two thousand Marks.</p>

<p>14 That all and every person and persons, who have aided, advised, assisted or abetted in any war against the Parliament, since the first day of <em>January</em> 1641 (<reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they have been since in the service of the Parliament, and given <reg orig="signall">signal</reg> testimony of their good affections thereunto) <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be disabled, and be uncapable to be elected, or to give any Vote in the Election of any Members to serve in the next Parliament, or in the three succeeding <reg orig="Trienniall">Triennial</reg> Parliaments.</p>

<p>15 That all such, who have advised, assisted, or abetted the Rebellion of <em>Ireland</em>, shall be disabled and uncapable <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> to be elected, or to give any Vote in the Election of any Member to serve in Parliament; as also all such who do or shall <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> the Roman <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion.</p>

<p>16 That all Votes and Elections given or made contrary, or not according to these Qualifications, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be null and void: And if any person who is hereby made uncapable, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give his Vote for Election of Members to serve in Parliament, such person <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> lose and forfeit one full years value of his real Estate, and one <reg orig="ful">full</reg> third part of his personal Estate.</p>

<p>17 That the persons who shall be elected to serve in Parliament, shall be such (and no other <reg orig="then">than</reg> such) as are persons of known Integrity, fearing God, and of good conversation, and being of the age of one and twenty years:</p>

<p>18 That all and every person and persons seized or possessed to his own use, of any estate real or personal, to the value of 200 li. and not within the aforesaid exceptions, shall be capable to elect Members to serve in Parliament of Counties.</p>

<p>19 That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the <pb n="5" />Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg>, shall be sworn before they enter in their Offices, truly and faithfully to issue forth, and send abroad Writs of Summons to Parliaments at the times and in the manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>; And in case of neglect of <reg orig="failer">failure</reg> to issue and send abroad Writs accordingly, he or they shall for every such offence <reg orig="bee">be</reg> guilty of High Treason, and suffer the pains and penalties thereof.</p>

<p>20 That in case Writs be not issued out as is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, but that there be a neglect therein,, fifteen <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the time wherein the same ought to be issued out by the Chancellor, Keeper or Commissioners of the Great Seal, that then the Parliament shall, as often as such <reg orig="failer">failure</reg> shall happen, assemble and be held at <em>Westminster</em>, in the usual place, at the times <reg orig="prefixt">prefixed</reg>, &amp;c.</p>

<p>21 That the Clerk, called <i>The Clerk of the Commonwealth</i>, in Chancery for the time being, and all others, who shall afterwards execute that Office, to whom the Returns shall be made, shall for the next Parliament, and the two succeeding <reg orig="Trieniall">Triennial</reg> Parliaments, the next day after such Returns, <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> the Names of the several persons so returned, and of the places for which he and they were chosen respectively, unto the Council, who shall peruse the said Returns, and examine whether the persons so Elected and Returned be such as is agreeable to the Qualifications, and not disabled to be elected: And that every person and persons being so duly elected, and being approved of by the major part of the Council to be persons not disabled, but qualified as aforesaid, shall be esteemed a Member of Parliament, and be admitted to sit in Parliament, and not otherwise.</p>

<p>22 That the persons chosen and assembled in manner aforesaid, or any Sixty of them, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and be deemed the Parliament of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative Power to be and reside in the Lord Protector and such Parliament, &amp;c.</p>

<p>23 That the Lord Protector, with the advice of the major part of the Council, shall at any other time <reg orig="then">than</reg> is before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, when the necessities of the State shall require it, summon Parliaments in manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, which <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be adjourned, prorogued, or dissolved without their own consent; during the first three months of their sitting. And in case of future war with any Foreign State, a Parliament <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be forthwith summoned for their advice concerning the same.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>24 That all <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> agreed unto by the Parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be presented to the Lord Protector for his consent; and in case he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not give his consent thereto, within twenty days after they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be presented to him, or give satisfaction to the Parliament within the time limited; That then, upon Declaration of the Parliament, that the Lord Protector hath not consented nor given satisfaction, such <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> into, and become Laws, although he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not give his consent thereunto; provided such <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> contain nothing in them contrary to the matters contained in these Presents.</p>

<p>25 That <em>Phillip</em> Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em>, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Fleetwood</em> Esq; <em>John Lambert</em> Esq; Sir <em>Gibert Pickering</em> Baronet, Sir <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Wolsely</em> Bar. Sir <em>Anthony Ashley-Cooper</em> Bar. <em>Edward Montague</em> Esq; <em>John Desborow</em> Esq; <em>Walter Strckland</em> Esq; <em>Henry Lawrence</em> Esq; <em>William Sydenham</em> Esq; <em>Phillip Jones</em> Esq; <em>Richard Major</em> Esq; <em>Francis Rous</em>, <em>Phillip Skippon</em> Esq; or any seven of them shall be a Council for the purposes <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in this Writing; and upon the death or other removal of any of them, the Parliament <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> nominate six persons of Ability, Integrity, and fearing God, for every one that is dead or removed, out of which the major part of the Council <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> elect two, and present them to the Lord Protector, of which he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> elect one, &amp;c.</p>

<p>26 That the Lord Protector and the major part of the Council aforesaid, may at any time before the meeting of the next Parliament, add to the Council such persons as they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> think fit; provided the number of the Council be not made thereby to exceed one and twenty, and the <em>Quorum</em> to be proportioned accordingly by the Lord Protector and the major part of the Council.</p>

<p>27 That a constant yearly Revenue <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be raised, <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and established for maintaining of ten thousand Horse and Dragoons, and twenty thousand Foot, in <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, for the defence and security thereof, and also for a convenient number of Ships for guarding of the Seas; besides two hundred thousand pound <em>per annum</em> for defraying the other necessary charges for administration of Justice, and other <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government; which Revenue <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be raised by the Customs, and such other <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> and means as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be agreed upon by the Lord <pb n="7" />Protector and Council, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be taken away or <reg orig="diminisht">diminished</reg> nor the way agreed upon for raising the same altered, but by the consent of the Lord Protector and the Parliament.</p>

<p>28 That the said yearly Revenue shall be paid into the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Treasury; and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be issued out for the Uses aforesaid.</p>

<p>29 That in case there shall not be cause hereafter to keep up so great a Defence at Land or Sea, but that there be an abatement made thereof; the money which will be saved thereby, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> remain in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Service, and not be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to any other use but by consent of Parliament; or in the intervals of Parliament by the Lord Protector and major part of the Council.</p>

<p>30 That the raising of <reg orig="mony">money</reg> for defraying the charge of present extraordinary Forces both at land and Sea, in respect of the present wars, shall be by consent in Parliament and not otherwise: Save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Lord Protector, with the consent of the major part of the Council, for preventing the disorders and dangers which may otherwise fall out both at Sea and Land, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have power until the meeting of the first Parliament, to raise money for the purposes aforesaid, and also to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding and in force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same.</p>

<p>31 That the Lands, Tenements, Rents, Royalties, Jurisdictions and Hereditaments which remain yet unsold or undisposed of Act or Ordinance of Parliament, belonging to the Commonwealth, (Except the Forests and Chases, and the <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> and Manors belonging to the same; the Lands of the Rebels in <em>Ireland</em>, lying in the four Counties of <em>Dublin, Cork, Kildare</em> and <em>Katerlaugh</em>, the Lands forfeited by the people of <em>Scotland</em> in the late wars; and also the Lands of Papists and Delinquents in <em>England</em> who have not yet compounded) shall be vested in the Lord Protector; to hold, to him and his Successors, Lord Protectors of these Nations, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be <unclear><!--7 characters--></unclear> but by consent in Parliament: And all Debts, Fines, Issues, <unclear>Amerciaments</unclear>, penalties and profits, certain and casual, due to the Keepers of the Liberties of <em>England</em> by Authority of Parliament, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be due to the Lord Protector, and be payable into his <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Receipt, <pb n="8" />and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be recovered and prosecuted in his Name.</p>

<p>32 That the Office of the Lord Protector over these Nations, shall be Elective, and not Hereditary; and upon the death of the Lord Protector, another fit person shall be forthwith elected to succeed him in the Government, which Election shall be by the Council &amp;c. Provided that none of the Children of the late King, nor any of his Line of Family be elected to be Lord Protector or other <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Magistrate over these Nations, or any the Dominions thereto belonging. And <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the aforesaid election be past, the Council <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take care of the Government, and administer in all things as fully as the Lord Protector, or the Lord Protector and Council are <reg orig="inabled">enabled</reg> to do.</p>

<p>33 That <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> Captain General of the Forces of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, and is hereby declared to be Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging, for his life.</p>

<p>34 That the Chancellor, Keeper of Commissioners of the Great Seal, the Treasurer, Admiral, <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Governors of <em>Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, and the chief Justices of both the Benches, shall be chosen by the approbation of Parliament; and in the intervals of Parliament, by the approbation of the major part of the Council, to be afterwards approved by the Parliament.</p>

<p>35 That the Christian Religion contained in the Scriptures, be held forth and recommended as the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> profession of these Nations; and that as soon as may be, a provision, <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> subject to scruple and contention, and more certain <reg orig="then">than</reg> the present, be made for the encouragement and maintenance of able and <reg orig="painfull">painful</reg> Teachers, for instructing the people, and for discovery and confutation of Error, <reg orig="Heresie">Heresy</reg>, and whatever is contrary to found Doctrines: And that until such provision be made, the present maintenance <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be taken away nor impeached.</p>

<p>36 That to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> profession held forth, none <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be compelled by penalties or otherwise, but that <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> be used to win them by found Doctrine, and the example of a good Conversation.</p>

<p>37 That such as profess Faith in God by Jesus Christ (though differing in judgement from the Doctrine, worship, or Discipline <pb n="9" /><reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth) shall not be restrained from, but <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be protected in the <unclear>profession</unclear> of the Faith, and exercise of their Religion; so as they abuse not this liberty, to the <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> <reg orig="injurie">injury</reg> of others, and to the actual disturbance of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> peace on their parts. Provided this liberty be not extended to Popery nor <unclear><!--Prelacy??-->Prefacy</unclear>, nor to such as, under the profession of Christ, hold forth and practice <reg orig="licentiousnesse">licentiousness</reg>.</p>

<p>38 That all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances and Clauses in any Law, Statute and Ordinance to the contrary of the aforesaid Liberty, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be esteemed as <reg orig="nul">null</reg> and void.</p>

<p>That the Acts and Ordinances of Parliament made for the sale or other disposition of the Lands and Heriditaments of the late King. Queen and Prince, of Arch-Bishops and Bishops, &amp;c. Deans and Chapters, the Lands of Delinquents, and Forest Lands, or any of them; or of any other Lands, Tenements, Rents and Hereditaments belonging to the Commonwealth, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> no <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> be impeached or made invalid, but <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> remain good and firm: And that the Securities given by Act and Ordinance of Parliament for any sum or sums of <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, by any of the said Lands, the Excise, or by any other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Revenue; and also the Securities given by the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith of the Nation; and the engagement of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Faith for satisfaction of Debts and Damages, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> remain firm and good, and not be made void and invalid upon any pretence whatsoever.</p>

<p>That the Articles given to, or made with the Enemy, and afterwards confirmed by Parliament, shall be performed and made good to the persons therein. And that such appeals, as were depending in the last Parliament, for <reg orig="releise">release</reg> concerning <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> of sale of <reg orig="Delinquents">Delinquent's</reg> Estates, may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> heard and determined the next Parliament, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in this Writing, or otherwise to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>41 That every successive Lord Protector over these Nations, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take and subscribe a Solemn Oath, in the presence of the Council, and such others as they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> call to them, that he will seek the Peace, Quiet, and Welfare of these Nations, cause Law and Justice to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>, and that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> will not violate or infringe the matters and things contained in this writing; and in all other things will to his power, and to the best of his understanding, govern these Nations, according to the Laws, Statutes and Customs.</p>

<pb n="10" />

<p>42 That each person of the <unclear>Council shall</unclear>; before they <unclear>enter</unclear> upon their Trust; take and subscribe an Oath, That they will be true and faithful in their Trust, according to the best of their knowledge; and that in the Election of every Successive Lord Protector, they shall proceed therein impartially and do nothing therein for any promises, fear, <reg orig="favor">favour</reg>, or reward.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Oath taken by His Highness <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p><i>Wherein the <unclear>Major part of the last</unclear> Parliament (judging that their sitting any longer, as then constituted, would not be <unclear>for</unclear> the good of this Commonwealth) and did dissolve the same, and by a writing under their hands, dated the Twelfth day of this instant <em>December</em>, resigned unto Me their Powers and Authorities; And whereas it was necessary thereupon, That some speedy course should be taken for the settlement of these Nations upon such a Basis and Foundation, as, by the blessing of God, might be lasting, secure Prosperity, and answer those great Ends of Religion and Liberty, so long contented for; and upon full and mature consideration had of the Form of Government hereunto annexed, being satisfied that the same, through divine assistance, may answer the Ends <reg orig="afore-mentioned">aforementioned</reg>: And having also been desired, and advised, as well by several persons of Interest and Fidelity in this Commonwealth, as the Officers of the Army, to take upon Me the Protection and Government of these Nations in the manner expressed in the said Form of Government, I have accepted thereof, and do hereby declare my acceptance accordingly. And do promise in the presence of God, That I will no violate, or infringe the matters and things contained therein, but to My Power, observe the same, and cause them to be observed; and shall in all other things, to the best of My Understanding, Govern these Nations according to the Laws, Statutes, and Customs, seeking their Peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally administered.</i></p>

<p>O. <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Hague (2 Jan. alias) 23 Decem. 1653.</i> The Dutch <reg orig="Deputies">Deputies'</reg> Letters say, The English press for satisfaction, security, the dominion of the Seas, the contribution for Fishing, &amp;c. In which, they desire further Instructions, which are sent, and 30 new <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg> ordered to be built, Admiral <em>Van Galen</em> was buried in the New Church from the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Court. First went the Lord <pb n="11" />Major in <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, <unclear>on horse back, his Guards on foot, then divers Officers</unclear> trailed Pikes, then four <reg orig="Trumpetters">Trumpeters</reg> with his Arms in <unclear>Taffeti</unclear>, then his Flag with his Arms, then his Secretary with his <unclear>Sentcheup</unclear>, one with his <reg orig="Gantlet">Gauntlet</reg>, and one with his Helmet, with red and yellow Feathers, then his Spurs, and Sword, and <reg orig="Ponnyard">Poniard</reg>, Coat of Arms of <unclear>Taffeti</unclear>, and arms before and behind, then his Mourning Horse led by his Lieutenant, and then his Corps<!--possibly Corpse-->, and the <reg orig="Hears">Hearse</reg>-<reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg> carried by 16 Captains, Admiral <em><reg orig="Tromps">Tromp's</reg></em> son one; after followed others with the <reg orig="Cuirats">Curates</reg>, carrying the <reg orig="Commanders">Commander's</reg> Staff, then his <reg orig="Kinred">Kindred</reg>, and after the Lords of the Admiralty, the <reg orig="Burgo-masters">Burgomasters</reg>, and the 36 of the Council, last India's Company, Directors of the East and Mediterranean Seas, and after all the <reg orig="Colledge">College</reg>, and the Officers of the <reg orig="Burgers">Burghers</reg>. Mr. <unclear><em>Chanut</em></unclear> the French Ambassador here, is daily treated with. One Ambassador, Mr. <unclear><em>Berel</em></unclear>, in <em>France</em> hath offered something there. The Lords States General do not sit until after <em>Christmas</em> <reg orig="Hollidayes">Holidays</reg>. <unclear><em>Wiste Wistense</em> is</unclear> here</p>

<p>The 23 instant, two English prizes were brought in, laden with 160 lasts of Salt, the other with Coals. The dead body of the Deputy <unclear><em>Vandir</em></unclear><em> Par</em> from <em>England</em> is arrived at <em>Flushing</em>, to be buried there. The ship of the late Admiral <em>Tromp</em>, is gone down the River almost <unclear><!--4/5 characters--></unclear>, and is to carry 72 Guns, 4 more new <reg orig="Friggots">Frigates</reg> of 40 and 42 Guns are ready to set sail. We daily expect 150 ships from the <em>Sound</em>, several Men of War are gone for their convoy. The Ordinance brought from <em>Sweden</em>, have been <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> at <em>Amsterdam</em>, there are 500 pieces, most part half Cartows. Cap. <em>Nicholas Pater</em> hath taken an English Ketch before <em>Hull</em>, another at <em>Flambrough</em> Head; a Flute of 12 Guns, and 4 of Wood, of about 130 lasts, with Hemp, Flax, Coals, and some <reg orig="Saltpeter">Saltpetre</reg>. Also near <em><reg orig="Whitebay">Whitby</reg></em> a Pinnace of six Guns, with refined Salt, and one by the <em>Hover</em>, laden with Salmon, Sheep skins, and Herring; but the loss of Cap. <em>Hans <reg orig="Margaren">Margaren's</reg></em> ship, a Man of War, with 18 Guns, which we hear the English have taken near <em>Newcastle</em>, was worth almost all these; and we hear of 8 ships taken from the Caribes, with Sugar, Tobacco, and other <reg orig="Marchandize">Merchandise</reg>, with their convoy of 30 Guns. Eight of the <em><reg orig="Newfound-land">Newfoundland</reg></em> ships we took, are Men of War. We have taken a Turkish ship, and another in <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear>. One <unclear><em>Goldfolk</em></unclear> hath rowed an English prize of 22 Guns into <em>Brest</em>. An English <reg orig="Friggot">Frigate</reg> met with 5 French ships of St. <em>Mallo</em>, took one called the <em>Year of Grape</em>; the <em>Toree Kings</em> hardly escaped, not yet heard of, the other three are at <em>Calise, Cornelius Joast</em>, with <em>Thymen Theaneste</em>, with the ammunition, are safely arrived from hence in <em>Muscovy</em>. There is like to be hot war by <em>Prussia</em> and <em>Muscovia</em>, against <em>Poland</em>, and is already proclaimed in <em>Muscovia</em>, and Deputies are sending to all the Princes in Christendom, about it. One army (and the biggest) is marched from <em>Muscovia</em>, towards <unclear>Smolansko</unclear>, and so on in the County; The Emperor will be there in person. A second commanded by Field Marshal <unclear><!--most of line, all names in italics--></unclear>, go from <pb n="12" /><unclear><em>Plescow</em></unclear> <unclear><!--half a line--></unclear> <unclear>among which 2000 are well trained Russians.</unclear> The third of 35000 from <unclear><em>Potsen</em></unclear>, to the help of the <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear> Cossacks.</p>

<p>The Dutch Deputies has passes to return home.</p>

<p>An Ordinance passed for reviving the Act of Parliament for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations, and <em>Rich <unclear>Lacy</unclear>, John <unclear>Hildsley</unclear>, Nath. Barton, Jarvis Bennet, Anth. <unclear>Rous</unclear>, Jo. Matthews, Ed. Clad, Tho. Wood,</em> Esqs; and Alderman <em>Titchburn</em>, to be added Judges to the former.</p>

<p>An Ordinance passed for Sir <em>Wil Roberts, John Stone, Jarvis <unclear><!--approx. 6 characters--></unclear>, John Hildsley, Richard <unclear>Lacy</unclear>, Edward Clud, Thomas Wood, Anthony <unclear>Rous</unclear>, James Phillips</em>, and <em>Nathaniel Barton</em>, Esqs; to be Commissioners for the better ordering and bringing in the duty of Excise, and the Arrests thereof.</p>

<p>This present Thursday, the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador came to <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> to congratulate the Lord Protector, his Brother is committed prisoner to the Tower.</p>

<p>Letters came from General <em>Monk</em>, and General <em>Pen</em>, aboard the <em>Swift-sure</em> in <em>Stokes</em> Bay, advertising, That there are 5 prizes laden with Wine, brought in; four into that Road, and the other sent into <em>Dover</em>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>, 26 Decemb. There were 3 Dutch men of War, about 40 Leagues West of <em>Scilly</em>, have taken two ships coming from <em>New England</em>, laden with Masts, and are carried into <em>Brest</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday, 30 December.</i></head>

<p>This day His Highness, the Lord Protector, and His Council, with the Officers of the Army, met at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, and kept a day of Fast and Humiliation, until about three <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>, and <em>Mr. Sterry, Mr. Tho. Goodwin</em>, and <em>Mr. Lackler</em>, prayed and preached.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturdy, 31 December</i></head>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 25 Decemb.</i> The Lowland party like not, that <em>Glencarne</em> should be their Lord General, as being a person too low. <em>Athol</em> and <em>Glengary</em> are also at odds. They are quiet in <em>Lewis</em> Island, where our forces are supplied with provisions in a Market once a week. The chief of <em>Mac <reg orig="Clouds">Cloud's</reg></em> people in the <em>Harris</em>, have subscribed and Engagement, to act nothing prejudicial to the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, nor against the <em>Lewis</em>. But <em>Mac Cloud</em> himself gave Bond, besides Engagement, <reg orig="dishonorably">dishonourably</reg> and perfidiously is run in to the enemy. This day <reg orig="neer">near</reg> 100 foot were mounted from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> and <em>Leith</em>, and sent out to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> those parts. In the late defeat of Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, we since the last understand, that <em>Forbs</em> himself being beat off his horse, shot in the thigh, and dangerously cut in the head, lay upon the ground, as if he had been dead, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> our men were gone on the pursuit, and then crept away. There were 7 of the Tories found dead, amongst whom Cap. <em>David Moor</em>, and <em>John Moor</em> his Brother, Cap. <em>Robert Stuart</em>, so to the late Earl of <unclear><em>Rothwel</em></unclear>, that lately surprised the Post Letters, and Lieut. <em>Boyde</em>; and we took prisoners, one <unclear><!--3 letters--></unclear> of <em>Northumberland</em>, and 17 Scotchmen, of what quality we know <pb n="13" />not, but there were 18 Captains with the party. We had on out part <reg orig="Quarter-master">Quartermaster</reg> <em>Ward</em>, and 26 more wounded, and one slain. Mr. <em>Sculle</em> the High-Sheriff of <em>Roxburghshire</em> (whom they had surprised in his own house) is rescued, but one of our Troopers ran him through the Thigh, (not knowing him) but not dangerous. It was a seasonable mercy, many having designed to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> out of the <em>Mers</em> and <em>Tividale</em>, but also out of <em>Northumberland</em>; which by this means, may perhaps be discovered. <em>Glencarne</em> is marched over the skirts of <em>Bray Willin</em>, three miles off <em>Glenella</em> and <em>Ellit</em>, with 500 horse, and at least 2000 foot, towards the North; they marched near a mile in breadth; but they have left several parties in the <em>Mers</em> and <em>Tividale</em>, to raise levies, and steal horses. Since <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> <em><reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg></em> death who died at his house at <em>Boggigerth</em>. A party of his followers fled to the Hills, were met by 8 Troopers of Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment; one of the Scots, and two English were slain: and four of our men were taken prisoners, the other two got away. They have lately taken and imprisoned some Heritors near <em>Blackford</em> in <em>Perthshire</em>, for denying their levies, and threaten to do the like against others.</p>

<p><i>Deal, 29 Decemb.</i> several <reg orig="Marchants">Merchant's</reg> ships are come into this Road, most of them bound for <em>London</em>, among which, are the two <em>Morlex</em> ships, with others from several parts. Here are also divers ships bound for <em>Malaga</em>, the <em>Canaries</em>, and the <em>West Indies</em>, when a good Convoy is appointed.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from <em>Johnstons</em>, in <em>Scotland</em></i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>A Fortnight since came hither the five prisoners taken by Capt. <em>Elsmore</em> about <em>Comry</em>, guarded by 10. of his Troop, they were waited upon by 23 of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> Horse to <em>Perth</em> town without molestation, and the went Northward that evening. They did <reg orig="steale">steal</reg> several Horses in <em>Moretown</em> <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> to the North Inch of <em>Johnstons</em>.</p>

<p><em>Glencarne, <reg orig="Glengerry">Glengarry</reg></em>, and <em>Kenmore</em> are marched Northward. All their <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> are formed for the Highlands, and out of 1000 l. Scotch Rent they expect an horse and man, the charge whereof being 17 l. sterling. It is agreed for the prosecuting their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, that <em><reg orig="Glancarry">Glengarry</reg></em> is to be for the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> about <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>. <em>Kamsey</em> for the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> of <em>Angus</em>, where he is: Earl of <em>Athol</em> (who is at his house two miles from <em>Dunkel</em>) for the Blair of <em>Athol</em>: <em>Adavample</em> and <em>Mac Nab</em> for the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> of <em>Perthshire</em> (out of which Shire is a Regiment of Horse and Foot to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> under <em>Athol</em>) and <em>Mac Naughton</em>, and <em>Maggrigs</em> for the for the west Highlands. Their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Weems</em> hath very large quarters. They are laying in a store of provision against their forces <reg orig="returne">return</reg>. <em>Lorne</em> is very much discontented, and hardly <reg orig="reconciable">reconcilable</reg> to <em>Kenmore</em> or <em>Glencarne</em>, <pb n="14" />and in probability, <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be but a <reg orig="cypher">cipher</reg> and <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> nothing.</p>

<p><i>Johnston 24 Decemb. 1653,</i></p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 2 January.</i></head>

<p>Dalkeith 27. Decemb. 1653. <i>Major <em><reg orig="Bramstons">Bramston's</reg></em> party had light upon Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> upon Saturday last, had not an old K. near <em><reg orig="Pebbles">Peebles</reg></em> sent him notice of our parties coming thither, he being then at the Kirk of <em>Atterick</em> very sore wounded, yet upon hearing of their approach marched towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> his number being then made 70 Horse by the occasion of our Cap <em>Steward</em> with 20 horse, our men took two more of them that were in the former fight, and one Mosse Trooper,</i></p>

<p><i>The Enemy have now a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in <em>Rosdew</em> about ten miles from <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em>, from whence they came commanded by one <em>Colgrave</em>, with about 80 Foot last week to <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em>, and in the dead of the night <reg orig="tooke">took</reg> two of the Bailiffs and other principal men of the Town to the number of 36. whom they threaten to keep <reg orig="til">till</reg> they send them in 4 <reg orig="horse men">horsemen</reg> and 37 <reg orig="foot men">footmen</reg> for their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>We have heard nothing of their motions in the North lately, their greatest bodies continue about <em>Lough-<reg orig="tay">Tay</reg></em>, and <em>Athol</em>, and trouble the Country by small parties in the night. They have a design Northward with all the body they can make.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 3 January</i></head>

<p>The English Fleet is put out from <em>Stoaks Bay</em> to Sea, about 50 men of war. The <em><reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg></em> hath taken a ship of 300 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> laden with Wines. The men run her <reg orig="a shoare">ashore</reg> and would have blown her up, but failed and themselves fled.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuing the Powers of Commissioners for Compounding, &amp;c. the Committee for advance of Money, and Commissioners of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Be it Ordained by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector by and with the advice and consent of His Council, That an Act of Parliament <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act <reg orig="impouring">empowering</reg> <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Commissioners to put in execution all and every the Powers and Authorities heretofore given <reg orig="io">to</reg> the Commissioners for compounding with Delinquents, and for managing all Estates under Sequestration; And to the Commission for advance of <reg orig="mony">money</reg> formerly sitting at <reg orig="Habberdashers">Haberdashers</reg> <reg orig="hall">shall</reg></i>, be, and is hereby continued, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> stand, be and continue in force until the first day of <em>Feb</em>. 1653, And that <em>Samuel Moyer, Josias Berns, Richard Moor, John Upton, Edward Cary</em>, and <em>Rice Williams</em> Esqs; or <pb n="15" />any four of them be hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to put in execution the said Act, and all and every the Powers and Authorities in and by the said Act given and every Clause, Article and thing therein contained. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that an Act of Parliament <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for <reg orig="transfering">transferring</reg> the Powers of the Commissioners for <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg></i>, be, and is hereby continued, and shall stand, be, and continue in full force, until the said first day of February 1653. And that the Commissioners herein named, or any four or more of them be hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and authorised to put in execution the said last mentioned Act, and all and every the Powers and Authorities in and by the same Act given, and every Clause and Thing therein contained.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 4 January.</i></head>

<p>Gen. <em>Blake</em> is going to the Hope, a fleet of 50 ships are already out together in the Channel, and more will suddenly <reg orig="bee">be</reg> with them.</p>

<p>If the Dutch do break off, and refuse to confirm a peace with England, let them expect that God will have a greater <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> with them <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever before; It is good for them to hear in their day the things that belong to their peace, least another day they be hid from their eyes.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 29 Decemb.</i> The Enemy (for now <reg orig="wee">we</reg> must call them so) still go on with their levies in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> parts of the hills, and will <reg orig="bee">be</reg> numerous, do what <reg orig="wee">we</reg> can to prevent them; though I see not how they can keep together in a body when <reg orig="conjoyned">conjoined</reg>, the Country not being able to bear them: Kenmore lies up towards the Bray of Mane and in the Glens that way, within the hills <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Woods and Rivers, and all along in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Fast places from Lough Tay, towards the Brays of Stermont and Angus.</p>

<p>Lieut. Whitmore of Col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Regiment went up lately into the Hills, and took 40 sheep, and 5 cows, which Sir Mungoe <reg orig="Murrag">Murray</reg> their Quartermaster General sent forth of the highlands to bee kept <unclear>near</unclear> his own house, Sir <reg orig="Mungoes">Mungoe's</reg> man, and one horse of the Laird of Lenes (who took Cap. Townesend and Cap.Scroop) but the Rider <reg orig="escapt">escaped</reg>: Yesterday a party of the Tories met with 4 of Col. <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Troop of Dragoons <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Levingston house about 10 miles from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, whom they barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, one of them fled into the House for safety, but the people would not protect him, but left him to the cruelty of those Villains. A party of our Dragoons from the Bray of Mane, fell upon the Enemy, <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> one, wounded 3 and 4 horses. I cannot think there is a pack of more merciless Rogues in the world, <reg orig="then">than</reg> these now gathered together in this County, and many of them were at Dunbar, and Worcester, and had liberty given them though out too much lenity.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>