<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState236">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 236</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 30 of <em>March</em> To Thursday the 6 day of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 30 March. 1653.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration and Ordinance, Declaring that the proceedings in case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> in <em>Ireland</em>, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> as formerly.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by the Laws of <em>Ireland</em>, the proceedings in case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, and against <reg orig="murtherers">murderers</reg>, hath been used to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> as in case of Treason and against Traitors; whereupon a doubt hath arisen, whether by the Ordinance, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Ordinance, declaring that the offences therein mentioned, and none other, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> adjudged high Treason, within the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging</i>, the same <reg orig="bee">be</reg> not taken away and repealed; For clearing whereof, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> it declared, Ordained and established by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, <pb n="1" />by and with the advice and consent of His Council, that the offence, proceedings, and punishment in case of <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, and of <reg orig="Murtherers">Murderers</reg> in <em>Ireland</em>, and all commanders, aiders, or <reg orig="abetters">abettors</reg>, in or unto any such fact, or person, shall remain, continue and be the same to all intents and purposes, as the same was or were before the making of the said Ordinance, and as if the said Ordinance had not been made, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein contained, or any Law, or Statute to the contrary thereof in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> notwithstanding.</p>

<p>This following Ordinance passed this day.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for <reg orig="releif">relief</reg> of persons that have acted in the Service of the Parliament.</i></head>

<p>Whereas many good and necessary Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament have heretofore been made for the encouragement, <reg orig="indempnity">indemnity</reg> and saving <reg orig="harmlesse">harmless</reg> of such persons as have in any sort either by Sea or Land engaged or acted, or commanded to be done any matter or thing whatsoever by Authority, or for the Service or benefit of the Parliament; and Committees being appointed to take care therein, and that Justice should be done accordingly, the power of which Committees being determined, and so no course settled for parties grieved, His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> having a continued and lively sense of such <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> undertakings and hazards for the Service of the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> in times of eminent danger and extremity, and being willing that full remedy should be provided for their safety, doth, by and with the consent and advice of his Council, Declare, Establish, and Ordain, that all and every the said Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament, and every Article, Clause, and Sentence in them, or any of them contained, shall stand, remain, and be in full force effect and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, and be put in practice and execution, and be pleadable and made use of in all Courts of Justice, as fully and absolutely, to all intents and purposes, as if the same had been now particularly made for such purpose.</p>

<p>And it is further Declared, Established and Ordained, That the words, clauses and sentences, in all and every the said Acts, Ordinances and Orders of Parliament, shall be adjudged, expounded, and taken in all Courts and proceedings of Justice, and elsewhere, most beneficial and available, to all and singular <pb n="2" />the persons that have so acted or done by Authority, or for the service or benefit of the Parliament; And if, upon any <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg> or proceedings in any Court of Justice, it shall appear unto the Judge, or Judges, before whom such <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> or proceeding shall be had or made, that the party that hath so acted by Authority or for the Service or Benefit of the Parliament, hath not had, or cannot have such full and just <reg orig="Releif">Relief</reg> therein, as by the said Acts, Ordinances or Orders of Parliament was intended or provided, then such Judge or Judges shall, and are hereby required to make certificate thereof to the Barons of the Exchequer, upon which certificate, the said Barons, or any two of them, shall have Authority, and are hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg>, and required upon such certificate and complaint of the party grieved, to proceed, and do therein to all intents and purposes; And they have hereby given unto them the same and like Powers, Authorities, Jurisdiction, and course of proceeding, in all causes for <reg orig="releif">relief</reg> of such party of parties grieved in the premises, as any Committee or Commissioners of or for <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, appointed by authority of Parliament, had, or lawfully might have exercised.</p>

<p>And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that where any person, that ought to have been <reg orig="Indempnified">Indemnified</reg>, by the true meaning of the said Acts and Orders of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, hath any Judgement or Verdict already obtained against him at Law, for any matter or thing for which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> ought so to have been <reg orig="indempnified">indemnified</reg>, by reason whereof he is disabled to plead his matter of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg> before the said judges, before mentioned, that then every such case, upon complaint exhibited before the said Barons of the Exchequer, setting forth his case, and <reg orig="alleadging">alleging</reg> such matter for his <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>, as that Court shall judge sufficient; and also give in such Security as the said Barons shall approve of, to pay costs unto the party molested or drawn so in question before the said Barons, in case he <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not prove his suggestion of the said complaint, the said Barons, in such special case, also may proceed to do therein, for <reg orig="Indempnifying">Indemnifying</reg> the said party grieved, as hereby they are <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to <reg orig="doe">do</reg>, upon the Certificate of the Judges before mentioned.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg>, That nothing in this Ordinance be construed <pb n="3" />or understood to revive the power of the said Committees in any the former Ordinances or Acts of Parliament named, so as to enable the said Committees to intermedle in the execution of any the said Acts or Ordinances.</p>

<p>An expedient was offered for conclusion of the peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em></p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector sent to appoint the Commissioners for approbation of Ministers to meet in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, on the morrow at three <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> in the afternoon.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 31. March.</i></head>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 25. March.</i> The Commander in <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> having issued forth a Proclamation, requiring all <reg orig="Burroughes">Boroughs</reg> and other Parishes to secure all suspicious persons, or otherwise to give intelligence of them to the next adjacent <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> or Quartermasters under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present Government, and proceeded against accordingly: Several Towns have been lately found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a Court Marshall for the same. The last week the parish of <em>Liberton</em>, two miles from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, for harbouring 15 of the Enemy by the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving Intelligence of them, and the Tories at their going away stealing fifteen horses: Th Parish was for that offence fined 200 l. sterling, the person in whose house they were concealed, sentenced to imprisonment during pleasure, and the house where they were harboured to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="raced">razed</reg> to the ground, and a <reg orig="paire">pair</reg> <reg orig="Gallowes">Gallows</reg> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> built there.</p>

<p>There are divers other Parishes who are summoned in to Court Marshals upon the very same account, who will suffer for it. It is hoped this course will in time compel the <em>Scots</em> no to give any Entertainment unto the Tories, but give notice of them, <reg orig="where ever">wherever</reg> shall come, otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>

<p>The 21 instant Col. <em>Cooper</em> with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <em>Glasgow</em>, and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of <em>Beven</em>, where about 300 of the Enemy quartered (about <reg orig="foure">four</reg> in the morning) took <em>Mac-<reg orig="Naughtons">Naughton's</reg></em> Trumpet, and 35 other Prisoners, and narrowly missed <em>Mac-Naughton</em> <pb n="4" />and <em><reg orig="Newarke">Newark</reg></em>, who were both there; They killed 12 whereof one of them (as the Enemy <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg>) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 Horse, and some <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, totally scattered the whole party, and returned without any <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>

<p>This week Capt. <em>Ortan</em> Commander of the <em>Sun</em>, and Capt. <em>Lilburn</em> of the <em>Union</em> came into <em>Leith</em> road, from <em>Lewis</em> and <em>Orkney</em>, and brought three Companies of Col. <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> Regiment, and therewith a particular relation of the late infall of the Earl of <em>Seafort</em> into <em>Lewis</em> Island, much to the same purpose formerly related.</p>

<p><i><em>Dublin</em> March 18. Since the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> departure for England, we have nothing further of <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, but that about 1200 Tories are shipped away from <reg orig="Limbrick">Limerick</reg>, and 1700 more are ready for transportation, which renders the whole Nation more free, than in times of the greatest Peace this Land hath enjoyed.</i></p>

<p><i><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> Fort, March 24. The news this place affords is, the Commander of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in hither a Dutch prize, which hath loading <reg orig="onely">only</reg> some few barrels of pitch, &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>This day the conclusion of peace came very near between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland &amp;c.</em></p>

<p>There are three considerable things which I cannot omit, as being fit to be published, and worthy consideration.</p>

<p>And I received the confirmation of the truth of them from persons of Honour; who with very great affection acquainted me therewith, and assured me of the real truth thereof.</p>

<p>The first is, That a Minister of State should Declare, That it is good to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in Amity with this present Power, because the Lord blesseth them in all their undertakings.</p>

<p>The second is, That a great <reg orig="Cavaleer">Cavalier</reg> that hath all along been for the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> party against the Parliament and Army, did lately Declare that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was now for this present Power, and could not but <reg orig="owne">own</reg> it, and being asked his reason why <reg orig="hee">he</reg> that had all along been against it, did now comply with it:</p>

<p>And his Answer was, That <reg orig="hee">he</reg> saw the Lord did own it, and heard their Prayers, and blessed them, and all along <pb n="5" />went on with them: And therefore he had reason to own them, and that they were <reg orig="mad-men">madmen</reg> that would any longer appear against them.</p>

<p>And the third was a notorious obstinate Cavalier, that had a journey to go from <em>London</em>, who so soon as he heard of the late Fast for Rain, appointed by His Highness, the Lord Protector, he sent presently to have his Horse ready, and called for his Boots, for he would away presently into the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whither he was to go: And being asked why he made such haste, his answer was, <i>That he knew there would be great Rain, and the <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> would be dirty, because, whatsoever this present power prayed for, they had; and therefore he would be gone before the Rain came.</i></p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of <em>Portugal</em> made this day Application to His Highness, the Lord Protector, to desire Audience. And His Highness ordered, That he should have Audience on the Monday following, and Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em> was appointed to wait upon His Excellency to His Highness that day, to the Cockpit accordingly.</p>

<p>This day passed these two Ordinances following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance prohibiting Cock-Matches.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>-meetings and Assemblies of People, together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence or Matches for Cock-fighting, are by experience found to tend may times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practices, to the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of god, and do often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of persons and their families.</p>

<p>For prevention thereof, Be it ordained by His Highness the Lord Protector, by, and with the advice and consent of his Council, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> or set Meetings or Assemblies or any persons within <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, upon Matches made for Cock-fighting: And that every such Meeting, and Assembly of people, for the end and purposes aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an unlawful Assembly, and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be, and punished: And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, <reg orig="Majors">Mayors</reg>, Bailiffs, Constables, and Head-boroughs, within their several Counties, <pb n="6" />Cities, Limits, and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such Meetings and Assemblies.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance of suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, An Act for the Relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners.</i></head>

<p>Whereas upon perusal and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners:</i> Many doubts and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorised for Sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such Explanation and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges, authorised in an by the said Act, several inconveniences and mischiefs would grow, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the said Creditors and Prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles, and Suits in Law, and Equity: For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: And whereas many of the said Prisoners have offered really to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the satisfaction of the said Creditors, if some further time may be given for that purpose.</p>

<p>Be it therefore Ordained by His Highness, the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the Sale or Disposition of any the Estates Real or Personal, of any of the said Prisoners, or of any other person or persons whatsoever mentioned or intended, in, or by the said Act; nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any the powers or authorities given by the same, until the Twentieth day of <em>April</em> next.</p>

<p>And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Acts or Things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, colour, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said <pb n="7" />Twentieth day of <em>April</em>, shall be utterly <reg orig="voide">void</reg>, null, and of none effect; saving <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, that it shall and may be lawful for the said several and respective Judges that gave bailed or let out any Prisoners upon <reg orig="Suerties">Sureties</reg> or otherwise, out of Prison (which Prisoners are to appear again at a certain day before the said Judges, and are not absolutely discharged by any Order of the said Judges) to sit <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the remanding and recommitting of the said Prisoners into their former Prisons and <reg orig="Goals">Gaols</reg>, where they formerly were detained in Prison, there to remain in safe custody, and to continue and be in the same condition as formerly they were, at the time of their Bailing or Letting out as aforesaid.</p>

<p>This day the Commissioners for Approbation of Ministers, met in <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and ordered to meet on the morrow to seek to the Lord for Council, Direction, and help from him in that great business.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, April 1.</i></head>

<p>This day the Commissioners for Approbation of Ministers, met in <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, and spent some time in seeking the <em>Lord</em>, for help and assistance from him in that work, which indeed is very hopeful to be for much good to this Nation, in <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> a godly, and able Ministry, in all parts of the Nation.</p>

<p>The said Commissioners appointed to meet on the Monday following, to choose their Register, and other Officers, to settle presently to the work.</p>

<p>This day the business of Ratifying the Peace between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, &amp;c. was <em>effective</em> concluded. The sum for the loss by <em>Denmark</em> agreed: And <em>Denmark</em> taken in fully with the States of the United Provinces: And on the Monday following the Dutch were to bring their Security.</p>

<p>His Highness, the Lord Protector, had under consideration the filling up of the Benches in the Courts of <em>Westminster-<reg orig="hal">hall</reg></em> for this next Term: And some things were resolved particularly in order to the Chancery, in order to the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the most able Lawyers in this Nation to be Commissioners there.</p>

<p>Upsal. 24 Febr. 1653. <i>I presume when the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hears that the English and Dutch are agreed, there will soon be a conclusion here. Her Majesty still continues her desires of resigning up <pb n="8" />the Government. And thereupon she is gone to <em>Westraas</em>, seven Leagues from this place to meet with the Prince <em>Palatine</em>, her <reg orig="Cousen">Cousin</reg> German, and her declared Successor, and to treat with him concerning the same. Some are of opinion that the <em>Prince <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg></em> (for so he is termed) will totally <reg orig="wave">waive</reg> this Overture, and will by no means be courted thereunto. But his private will must give way to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Determination of the Grand Assembly of the States, which will be <reg orig="conveened">convened</reg> very shortly and which way the will cast it, is very <reg orig="doubtfull">doubtful</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>Some are very forward beforehand to presage great Alterations that must happen in this <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg>: And indeed this Offer of the Queen which amuseth all, doth portend something which is hidden, as well in the effects of it, as in its causes. The Discourses hereabout are very various; There wants not those which say, that <em>Piemontelli</em>, the <em>Spanish</em> Resident has been here all this while to Negotiate a Match between this Queen and the King of the <em>Romans</em>, and that Count <em>Mont Cucully</em> General of the Horse to the Emperor had no other business here but to agitate the same, though he made his <reg orig="pretentions">pretensions</reg> that he came to this Court <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as a <reg orig="Travellor">Traveller</reg>, But others who would be thought understanding in such <reg orig="affaires">affairs</reg>, <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> no such thing, and are very confident that the Queen is fixed in her resolution never to marry, but she is a woman. But this is certain, that the Queen doth earnestly <reg orig="presse">press</reg> to lay down the Crown, and desires to have <em>Pomerania</em> the Town of <reg orig="Gottemburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, and 200000 <reg orig="Duccats">Ducats</reg> to maintain her whiles she lives. But whatever the issue of this be, she has promised my Lord Ambassador to dispatch his <reg orig="Businesse">Business</reg>, and that to his contentment.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 3 April.</i></head>

<p>This day was presented to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector this following Declaration, and Recognition which was presented by Mr. <em>Dickeson</em> Alderman, and Sir <em>Tho. Withrington</em> Recorder of the City of York.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To His Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The Recognition of the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the ancient City of <em>York</em>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord, whose eyes run to and fro through the earth, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg> strong on the <pb n="9" />behalf of them whose hearts are perfect towards him, to make bare his Arm and bring Salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, and to break many yokes from off our necks, in accomplishment whereof, though humane Might and Power have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and overruled by the Spirit in the <reg orig="middest">midst</reg> of the <reg orig="wheeles">wheels</reg>, that we may justly say; we are not saved by Bow, or by Sword, but by the Lord our God, and therefore,</p>

<p>In the first place, we look upon it as our duty to acknowledge Salvation, and blessing to him that sits upon the Throne of Heaven judging the right, who hath done whatsoever it pleased him, both in Heaven and in Earth and in all deep places.</p>

<p>Yet when we also consider how it hath seemed good in the eyes of God to single out Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> as the man of his right hand, whom <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath made strong for <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, and through Your <reg orig="Vigilancy">Vigilance</reg>, Courage, and Constancy to <reg orig="doe">do</reg> great and <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg> things in the midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left.</p>

<p>While, we <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the Lord, out heart is also to the Governors of <em>Israel</em>, who have jeorparded their lives in the High Places of the Field, and are daily going on to second their valiant Acts by prudent Councils, that we may enjoy the end of every just war, which is, a safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> peace.</p>

<p>Unto Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> therefore (as all the people of <em>Israel</em> to their Ruler) we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and peace be to thine helpers.</i></p>

<p>If we should promise to <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> too much concerning your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, or any of the Sons of Men, especially in this day, wherein the Lord hath so often rejected our confidences, and proclaimed to us by the <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> of manifold providences, <i>Cease from man, whose breath is in his nostrils</i>; We should not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="Intrench">Entrench</reg> upon the <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> of God, and our own peace, but be injurious to Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, who are better able to bear the <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of much trouble, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a little of that trust which we owe to him alone, in whom there is everlasting strength, who turns every staff into a reed when it is rested on.</p>

<p>Yet we cannot but <em>Declare</em> our great hopes, that the Lord <pb n="10" />will still delight to use Your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> as a blessed Instrument of much honour to his great Name, and <reg orig="happinesse">happiness</reg> to this Commonwealth, that as he hath helped you to build the wall of <em>Jerusalem</em>, the defence and safety of his people even in <reg orig="troubleous">troublous</reg> times, so he will also <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> your Heart and enable your Hands, according to your eminent Station to further the spiritual work and welfare of his Church and Temple, which waits for a season of more <reg orig="tranquility">tranquillity</reg>.</p>

<p>We <reg orig="adde">add</reg> <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Declaration of our satisfaction in the present Government, <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> by your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and our <reg orig="chearfull">cheerful</reg> submission thereunto, which we shall be ready to second with our prayers and endeavours for your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> prosperity, and the people of God which sit under your shadow.</p>

<p>Humbly begging your <reg orig="favorable">favourable</reg> Aspect and Influence upon the Honours and <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> of this ancient City, whose strength is much decayed, though their <reg orig="Burthens">Burdens</reg> be increased, which yet they are more willing <reg orig="then">than</reg> able to undergo, till a just and seasonable remedy may be procured,</p>

<p>Our lot is fallen something remote from the great Scene of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Affairs, which hath been prejudicial to us; But we trust though we <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> not so much warmth of the Sun as the Southern parts, yet the beams of your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Goodnesse">Goodness</reg> and Justice (whom God hath set up in the midst of us) shall comfortably reach this place, which though in many outward advantages it may come behind others, <i>Yet will shine to an <reg orig="equallity">equality</reg> with the best in their affections and faithfulness to your Highness and this Commonwealth.</i></p>

<p>Thanks was returned by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> to the City of <em>York</em>, and to the Gentlemen that presented it.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em> had this day audience by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at the Cock-pit, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, and many Gentlemen, there being divers of the Lords of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, and Mr. Secretary of State with His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>The Committee for approbation of Ministers sat this day chose their Register, and other Officers, and began to proceed in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> according to the Ordinance of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector with the advice of his Council. The place they <pb n="11" />sit in is <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, at the end of the stone Gallery, at the corner of the Court, and their proceedings are such as promiseth much good to this Nation, by the settling of an able; godly, and powerful Gospel <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>.</p>

<p>Letters from Mr. <em>Feake</em>, and Mr. <em>John Simpson</em> say to their Friends, that they are still the same men, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on under the same confidences.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Declarations from the Churches in <em><reg orig="Norfolke">Norfolk</reg>, Monmouthshire</em>, and other parts of <em>Wales, &amp;c.</em> do own, and <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> God for the late change, and present Government.</p>

<p>This day the Regiments of Horse and Foot that are about <em>London</em> and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Life-guard of Gentlemen of Horse were all mustered in <em>Tuttle</em>-fields.</p>

<p>This day was the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of Peace with <em>Holland</em> carried on as far as might be, all is fully agreed, and one thing after another, <reg orig="every thing">everything</reg> is done in order, The Merchants came this day and were present by the Dutch to sign for security for payment of the moneys to the Merchants for the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> by them sustained in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of <em><reg orig="Denmarke">Denmark</reg></em>, for <em>Denmark</em> is wholly taken in also into the Peace, and in few <reg orig="daies">days</reg> all will be concluded, and totally finished, that the Peace may be ready to be Proclaimed.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> for appointing Commissioners for the Great Seal, was ordered to be on the morrow, in order to which several things were this day done by way of preparation.</p>

<p>The <em><reg orig="Sweadish">Swedish</reg></em> Agent made <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and it was ordered that he should have Audience on the morrow, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Mr. of the Ceremonies, was appointed to attend accordingly.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 4 April.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of State attended His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector at the Cock-pit, after which they say in Council in <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, and several businesses of great consequence were transacted.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador is removed from Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> to his own lodgings in Covent Garden.</p>

<p>This day the Agent from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had audience by His Highness, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, and divers Gentlemen <pb n="12" />, there being with His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> divers Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Sir <em>Thomas Wethrington</em> and the Lord Commissioners <em>Lisle</em>, were this day sword Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em> for the Court of Chancery by the Clerk of the Commonwealth, before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and the Council, in the Council-Chamber at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> who is now in Sweden, is also to be one with them.</p>

<p>This day was published an Ordinance for continuing one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations</i>, as followeth.</p>

<p>Be it Ordained by His Highness, the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for Probate of Wills, and granting Administrations</i>, and all the Powers, Authorities, Matters and Things therein contained, shall be, and are hereby revived and continued, in full power and force, to all intents and purposes, until further Order.</p>

<p>And it is hereby further Ordained, That <em>Richard Lucy, John Hildesley, Nathaniel Barton, Jervas Bennet, Anthony Rous, Joachym Matthews, Edward Cludd, Thomas Wood</em>, Esqs; and <em>Robert Titchburn</em>, Alderman of <em>London</em>, be added to the Judges mentioned in the said Act, and that the said Judges named in the said Act, and in this present Ordinance, or any three of them, be, and are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to put in execution all and every the Powers given by the said Act, as fully as any of the Judges therein named might have done by force of the said Act.</p>

<p>An Ordinance was also published this day for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> and confirming of the <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of <em>Framlingham</em> and <em>Saxtead</em>, in the County of <em>Suffolk</em>, and the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments thereunto belonging, devised, to certain Charitable uses by Sir <em>Robert Hitchman</em> Knight, late <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at Law, who did heretofore purchase of <em>Theophilus</em>, late Earl of <em>Suffolk</em>, and his <unclear>Feoffees</unclear>, the Castle and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of <em>Framlingham</em> and <em>Saxtead</em>, and divers Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, with the appurtenances, lying and being in <em>Framlingham</em> and <em>Saxtead</em> in <pb n="13" />the County of <em>Suffolk</em>, which were by his direction conveyed and assured unto <em>Richard Keebie</em>, one of the Lords Commissioners for the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, and to <em>Francis Bacon</em>, Esq; and <em>James Rivet, William Buts</em>, and <em>Robert Buts</em>, Gentlemen, and their Heirs, who were persons <reg orig="onely">only</reg> trusted by Sir <em>Robert Hitcham</em><!--same person as Robert Hitchman?-->.</p>

<p>And whereas afterwards, <em>viz.</em> The Eighth of <em>August</em>, 1636. the said Sir <em>Robert Hitcham</em> made his last Will and Testament in writing, and thereby did, amongst other things, will, limit, and appoint, That as touching the said Castle and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> of <em>Framlingham</em> and <em>Saxtead</em>, and all the Lands and Hereditaments which he and his Feofees purchased of the said <em>Theophilus</em> Earl of <em>Suffolk</em>, and his Feoffees, the said Sir <em>Robert <reg orig="Hitchams">Hitcham's</reg></em> Feoffees and their Heirs, after his debts paid, should stand seized in trust to the uses of the Masters and Fellows of <em>Pembroke-hall</em> in <em>Cambridge</em>, and their Successors, and that upon request his Feoffees should make a good assurance unto them accordingly; of which, the College should have to their own use, the Castle and Royalties, and Rents of Tenure, with the <reg orig="Mear">Mere</reg> and Fish-ponds, the Advowson of the Church, the Hundred of <em>Loes</em>, the Fairs and Markets there; but the <reg orig="Demeasn">Demesne</reg> Lands of the said <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg>, and all the Hereditaments and Lands purchased of the Earl of <em>Suffolk</em>, as aforesaid, the said College should have <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in trust, to be by them converted to the uses following, <em>viz.</em> That they should pull down all the Castle save the stone buildings, and therewith erect at <em>Framlingham</em> one house to set the poor on work, the poor and most needy and impotent of <em>Framlingham, Debenham</em>, and <em>Coxal</em>, first, and after them of other Towns if they see cause; and to provide a substantial stock to set them on work, and to allow such needy persons of them so much, as the College should further think fit; and that they should build one or two Alms-houses consisting of twelve persons (namely six <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>) for twelve of the poorest and <reg orig="decrepid">decrepit</reg> people there, which are to have each of them two shillings <em>per</em> week, during their lives, and forty shillings <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg> for a Gown and Firing, every year: And that they should build a <reg orig="School-house">Schoolhouse</reg> there at <em>Framlingham</em>, and appoint a Master, who is to have forty pounds <em>per annum</em> during his life, to teach thirty of forty, or more, of <pb n="14" />the poorest children of <em>Framlingham, Debenham</em>, and <em>Coxal</em>, to write, read, and cast <reg orig="accompt">account</reg>, as the College shall think fit, and then they to have Ten pounds a piece to bind them Apprentices, at the Discretion of the four Senior Fellows of the said College; and that they should build an Alms-house at <em>Levington</em> for six of the poorest persons of <em>Levington</em> and <em>Nacton</em>, which is to be built upon his Tenement near the street there, and they to have the like allowance in all things, as the poor of <em>Framlingham</em> are appointed to have; and that there should be <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> one to read prayers in the Church of <em>Framlingham</em> daily, at the hours of eight in the forenoon, and four in the afternoon, who is to have twenty pounds <em>per annum</em>, and the Sexton five pounds yearly; And such of the poor aforesaid, or the <reg orig="School-master">Schoolmaster</reg>, or Scholars there, as should make default in coming to prayers, their allowance to be proportionably abated for the same neglect (except their excuse be allowed by the Minister of <em>Framlingham</em> for the time being) and whatsoever should further come of what which the Testator had formerly given in Trust to the said College, they to convert the same to the like use or uses, to continue as before <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, April 5.</i></head>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 28 March.</i> Our forces from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em>, have taken 60 Horse, and 36 Prisoners beyond <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em> Castle. Since which, one of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Captains was taken near <em>Haddington</em>, with six more. About 50 Gentlemen are gone from the West to the Hills, with good Horses, Arms, &amp;c. of which, some Knights, and two of the Lord <em>De la <reg orig="Banks">Bank's</reg></em> Brothers. <em><reg orig="Gencarn">Gencairn</reg></em>, <em>Kenmore, Athol, Forbs</em>, and <em><reg orig="Glangary">Glengarry</reg></em>, &amp;c. are gone Northward to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton, Seafort</em>, and the Lord <em>Ray</em>, and so to force <em><reg orig="Southerland">Sutherland</reg></em> and <em>Caithness</em>, to rise with them; their return it is thought will be about a fortnight hence, <em>Seafort, Middleton</em>, and <em>Raget</em> men, <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> a Vessel of ours going to the <em>Lewis</em> by some Boats they sent out; we had in her 14 men, Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg> for that Garrison. <em>Middleton</em> hath besieged <em>Cinkeler</em> Castle in <em>Caithness</em>, but they bad him defiance. Colonel <em>Morgan</em> returned from <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> the 21 instant over the Hill, for <em>Aberdeen</em>. The enemy have been cruel in burning and destroying the Country that do no freely <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; yet <pb n="15" />Sir <em>James Mac <reg orig="Donnald">Donald</reg></em>, and the Captain of the <em>Clan Renolds</em> are in Arms against <em>Middleton</em> in the Hills, for preservation of their <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 28 March</i>, An <em>Ostend</em> man of War is brought in by the <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>. And three Dutch prizes are also brought into this Port, one with Figs, and Raisins from St, <em>Lucas</em>, the other two with French Wines.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Ellins">Ellin's</reg> 1 April</i>, Yesterday the Reserve <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one of our Scouts brought into the Fleet a prize called the <em>John Baptist</em>, <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with some Pepper, and <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg>, her <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> is about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> from St. <em><reg orig="Malloes">Mallo's</reg></em>, bound for <em>Amsterdam</em>, the <reg orig="Captaine">Captain</reg> of her a <reg orig="French-man">Frenchman</reg> made some short dispute and then surrendered.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Rous</em> is added to the Committee of the Admiralty and Navy. The Committee for approbation of Ministers sit on <reg orig="Mundays">Mondays</reg>, Wednesdays and <reg orig="Fridaies">Fridays</reg>.</p>

<p>All is quiet in <em>Ireland</em>, <em>April</em> 6. is to be a General Council.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is under debate about adjourning Easter-Term, or part of it.</p>

<p>This night between six and seven <reg orig="a Clock">O'Clock</reg>, the English Commissioners went to the Dutch Ambassadors at Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevors">Trevor's</reg></em>, in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coaches, with Mr. Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council; and about nine <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night, totally finished the Ratification of the Peace: The Articles being wholly agreed for <em>Holland</em> and <em>Denmark</em>, with us, and they were then signed by the Lords Ambassadors, on the one side, with full power from the States, and the Lords Commissioners, with full power from the Lord Protector on the other side, and sealed and delivered on both sides; so that now all is done and the PEACE is fully made.</p>

<p><i>To God be all the Glory.</i></p>

<hr />

<p><reg orig="Lost">Last</reg> Wednesday 22 March at Dingly in Northamptonshire, a black roan Mare five years old, with a fair Star in the forehead, a bob Tail, between 13 and 14 hands high branded with a G on the near Thigh, trots and paces. If any bring tidings to Mr. Knight at the Red Bull in Drury Lane, or to Sir Edw. <reg orig="Griffins">Griffin's</reg> at Dingly, they shall have 40 s. </p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>The Mystery of the two Witnesses <reg orig="unvailed">unveiled</reg>. Wherein we have a <unclear>description</unclear> of their persons, time, acts, death, office, manner of <reg orig="prophecie">prophecy</reg>, sufferings and resurrection, with the Consequences that follow. By Joh. Robotham, Preacher of the Gospel in Dover, Sold by G. and H. Eversden, at the Greyhound in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>