<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState221">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 221</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>
<head level="3">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>
<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 25 of <em>Decemb.</em> To Thursday the 22 day of <em>December</em>. 1653.</head>
<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Begining on Thursday 15. December. 1653.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Wee">We</reg> are informed from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em> 9 <em>Decemb</em>. That last week a party of fourscore of these broken people, took away 7 or 8 good horses from the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em><reg orig="Weems">Weems's</reg></em> house in <reg orig="Fyfe">Fife</reg>, and a party of four Rogues came into the Laird of <em><reg orig="Womats">Womat's</reg></em> house, three or <reg orig="foure">four</reg> miles from Leith, and <reg orig="stabed">stabbed</reg> an Englishman, who was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by the Commissioners to gather in the Rents of his Coal-pits, by which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> may perceive what usage <reg orig="wee">we</reg> might expect, if <reg orig="wee">we</reg> were at their mercy.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A new <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> of the Inhabitants of the Lowlands in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>I do hereby oblige me, my Heirs and Executors, That I shall and will live peaceably under the command of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, <pb n="1" />And that I, or any other under my Command, shall not act directly or indirectly to the prejudice of the Commonwealth aforesaid, in aiding and assisting the Highlanders, and others now in arms, and who hereafter shall be in Arms against the said Commonwealth in person, <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg>, Advice, Means, or any other manner of way whatsoever, under the penalty of forfeiture of Life and Estate, and to be proceeded against as the Parliament of the Commonwealth, and those <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> by them shall appoint: In witness whereof I gave subscribed the same at the 28 day of <em>Novemb</em>. 1653.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By a Letter intercepted from one of their own party thus.</i></head>

<p>All our <reg orig="Commission'd">Commissioned</reg> Officers are going now to their several <reg orig="Locallities">Localities</reg> for Levies (which was not till now determined upon) both of Horses and Foot, the Earl of <em>Athol</em> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horses in Perthshire, and the whole foot thereof: <em>Kinoul</em> hath the horses of the shire of Angus and Mernes: <em>Glengary</em> is to levy a Regiment of horses out of Caithness, Sutherland, Ross, and Murray, and to be Commander in chief of the Foot levied there. <em>Kenmore</em> is to levy the horses of the shire of Aberdeen. Col. <em>Blakader</em> of Iulliallen is to levy in a part of the shire of Fife, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> left us two nights, being discontented for not getting a <reg orig="Locallity">Locality</reg> on the North-side of Forth, he was, and is General Quarter master, and is again reconciled, and is to have <reg orig="Sterlingshire">Stirlingshire</reg> for a <reg orig="Locallity">Locality</reg>, for levying the horses there.</p>

<p>We are now about 1000 good, well armed, resolute foot, and 500 horse, the riders are singularly good, they and the horses are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> ill equipaged. Saddles and <reg orig="Briddles">Bridles</reg> that are good, are rare here, I have sent you a purse-penny, I <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> that there be not a word of the other. This is all, I remain.</p>

<p><i>Pool, Decemb. 9.</i> About fourteen days since, Captain <unclear><em>Green</em></unclear>, Commander of a private Man of War, brought into this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> a prize, pretending to be of Dunkirk, she hath about 114 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg><!--possibly is Tuns--> of French Wine on board, came from Nants, the Master is a <reg orig="Scotchman">Scotsman</reg>, put in as is supposed for colour <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, which with other circumstances, give great expectation, that she will prove a prize.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>This day the same Captain <em>Green</em> hath brought in another Vessel, called the <em>Grout-pot</em>; she names <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> of <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg>, the <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> name is <em>Steven van Collen</em>, she hath about 70 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of French Wine, and some Ginger, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> believed she will also prove prize.</p>

<p><i>Downs 13 December</i>, General <em>Monk</em> is here safely arrived in the Downs, where so many of the ships as are ready are within, and more are daily coming to them, he will shortly be a considerable number, orders are sent to hasten all away.</p>

<p><em>Harwidge</em> 11. Decemb. The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> went to Sea a week since, and are before this with the General in the Downs, or gone by Orders elsewhere; the <em>Expedition</em> hath been ready this fortnight: We shall have a gallant Navy before <em>February</em>, there are two or three <reg orig="smal">small</reg> men of War that have much infested this coast, and sometimes endangered to have done great <reg orig="mischeife">mischief</reg> to some <reg orig="Cole">Coal</reg>-ships, and other <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Boats, which they have at <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times chased in here, and to other ports; but the <em>Rowling ground</em> being sent hither hath <reg orig="frighted">frightened</reg> them away, which plies too and again between this and <em>Yarmouth</em>. There are also others ships here ready, and going out, viz. the <em>Convertin</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Middleborough</em> the <em>Centurion</em>, and <em>Maligo Merchants</em>; and here are also the <em>Advice</em> the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, the <em>Recovery</em>, and the <em>Advantage</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> all tallowed, and their words were finished, and so ready, that they are preparing to take in their Victuals; the <em>Unity</em> came hither last week from the Northern coasts of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p><i>Dover 14 Decemb.</i> There went by several ships here this week bound for <em>London</em>, some came from the <em>Canaries</em> laden with Wines, and one from <em>Maligo</em>, whose loading is all fruit: there is a Dutch Prize also laden with Wines, which was taken by a private man of war, belonging to <em>London</em>, whose lading is all white Wines.</p>

<p><i>Chattam 10 Decemb.</i> The <em>George</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is now ready to set sail this day, the <em>James</em> on Monday, the <em>Lyon</em> about three <reg orig="daies">days</reg> hence, the <em>Triumph</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> is rigged, and we doubt not but will be got ready to be <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> before the Spring Tides are over: They intended suddenly to fall to work in getting out Ballast, and sitting of the <em>Resolution</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> for docking: Yesterday morning fell <pb n="3" />out an unhappy accident, but blessed <reg orig="bee">be</reg> God that it was no worse, for the great danger was wonderfully prevented. The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> was thus. The Gunner of the <em>Victory</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and his Boy went down with a <reg orig="Lanthorn">Lantern</reg> into the Powder room; but when he came there the <reg orig="Lanthorn">Lantern</reg> being faulty, the candle <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> out of it, and presently took hold of some loose powder, for there was some loose grains of Powder scattered in the <reg orig="Store-house">Storehouse</reg> room, by which means it was set on fire, and it would have endangered the ship to have been wholly spoiled, had not by great providence good help, and provisions extraordinary been at hand for the prevention of it, which by the blessing of God proved so effectual, that there is no great hurt done, which is to be looked on as a great mercy.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 12 Decem.</i> Here are lately brought in about 10 prizes at <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times, Dutch and French: the 12 fats of Beaver mentioned in my last is not commodities for these parts, but they have Chapmen enough for Sugar, Salt, <reg orig="Oyles">Oils</reg> and Wines which are the <reg orig="cheifest">chiefest</reg> lading of the rest. A sad disaster <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> the Sussex <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, which by accident took fire in her Powder room, and is blown up, with about 50 men in her, the men most of them lost and the ship spoiled.</p>

<p>The <em>Portugal</em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother that escaped out of Newgate, was so narrowly pursued by the Officers of the Prison, who made such lamentable cry and furious search up and down for him that at last they had discovery of him, and took him again, and brought him back to Newgate, where he is with the rest of his Fellows in order to his trial.</p>

<p>Addresses were made to his Excellency the Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> this day, as also some <reg orig="daies">days</reg> before, pressing his Excellency for the good of the Three Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, to take upon him the Government thereof, as the only means to rescue the people from the danger of ruin, which was made so clear and plain to him, and from <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> holy Word, such satisfactory Scriptures were brought to his mind that he might comfortably expect a blessing in, from some promises, which hat of old been his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> recourse to, who in this had much fought to the Lord for direction therein day after day.</p>

<p>This day his Excellency the Lord General <em>Cromwell</em> by the <pb n="4" />advice of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, and other persons of Interest, and <!-- typo or reg??-->Authourity, concurred to accept of their desires, that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> made Lord Protector of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>: And godly, able and <reg orig="discreet">discrete</reg> persons to be appointed the number of 21. to be his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and a Parliament to be afterwards called, &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 16 Decemb.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Committee for claims for Lands in <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<p>All persons who are Adventurers for Land in <em>Ireland</em>, are desired to take notice, that the Committee for claims for Lands in <em>Ireland</em>, have appointed Thursday the 12 of <em>January</em> next coming, to be a day of lottery at Grocers-hall <em>London</em>, both for Provinces and Counties: And Thursday the 29 of the same <em>January</em> to be a Lottery for Counties for all such Adventurers who have made their choice in Provinces, and after the said 19 of <em>January</em> the said Committee to sit three mornings in a week, viz. <em><reg orig="Tuesdaies">Tuesdays</reg></em>, <em><reg orig="Thursdaies">Thursdays</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Saturdaies">Saturdays</reg></em>, for preparing Certificates for such Adventurers as have or shall by that time draw their Lots.</p>

<p>W: TIBBS.</p>

<p><i>Amsterdam 10. (alias 20.) Decemb. 1653.</i> Here are Letters come from our Deputies with you in <em>England</em>, which <reg orig="seeme">seem</reg> to promise some hope of agreement, what the particulars are, is kept very close; but in general it is said, that there is great probability of a composure, which makes our Merchants <reg orig="chearful">cheerful</reg>, and some of them have abated their fury as the hearing of the news: But <em>Middleton</em>, and the English of his party endeavour to report the contrary; who tell us such strange news of <em>Scotland</em>, that the Scots <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> forces have beaten the English back into <em>England</em>, and intend to pursue them; And that <em>England</em> is so divided that it cannot send out any more fleets to Sea, but they have been so often found such notorious <reg orig="lyars">liars</reg>, that their reports are not much regarded: and we are in great fear the English fleet will be ready before this <reg orig="States">State's</reg>, and our Merchants are in great fear. The States are in great want o present moneys for Naval affairs, which they find very difficult to raise, so much having lately been <unclear>exacted</unclear>, so that they are troubled what exploit to use to raise some considerable sum.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>Divers do force the paying of Tithes by Law, in the High Court of <em>Chancery</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The names of several Inhabitants of the Parish of <em>Sepulchres, London</em>; who are now prosecuted for the not paying of Tithes, in the High Court of <em>Chancery</em>.</i></head>

<!--table in 3 columns divided by vertical lines-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Dorothy Hammerton</p>
<p>Hugh Stokely</p>
<p>Peter Arris</p>
<p>Anthony Harman</p>
<p>Thomas Thomason</p>
<p>James Kansam</p>
<p>Richard Heusly</p>
<p>Amb. Gatebrand</p>
<p>Richard Beaumont</p>
<p>John Singleton</p>
<p>Evan Simons</p>
<p>Ellis Jinks</p>
<p>Anne Witton</p>
<p>Thomas Hunt</p>
<p>Thomas Goodale</p>
<p>John Wyber</p>
<p>William Kemp</p>
<p>Samuel Beck</p>
<p>John Jiggens</p>
<p>Thomas Lion</p>
<p>William Jewel</p>
<p>Samuel Meremay</p>
<p>Nicholas Perry</p>
<p>Thomas Goddin</p>
<p>Thomas Rands</p>
<p>Elizableth Collins</p>
<p>Thomas Simson</p>
<p>Elizabeth Winter</p>
<p>Anne Traughton</p>
<p>Henry Cuyon</p>
<p>William Goodwin</p>
<p>John Barns</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Henry Davis</p>
<p>Edward Tomlins</p>
<p>John Mason</p>
<p>Henry Felps</p>
<p>Thomas Butler</p>
<p>Edward Bacon</p>
<p>Ralph Walker</p>
<p>Jeremy Jones</p>
<p>Thomas Cornfoot</p>
<p>William Percy</p>
<p>John Dent</p>
<p>Thomas King</p>
<p>Henry Surrey</p>
<p>Edward Shatton</p>
<p>Thomas Johnson</p>
<p>Nicholas Gilpin</p>
<p>George Blinckco</p>
<p>Thomas Neal</p>
<p>Richard Airs</p>
<p>Thomas Searl</p>
<p>John Rickman</p>
<p>Eleanor Gaudren</p>
<p>Robert Gregory</p>
<p>Henry Johnson</p>
<p>Joseph Hope</p>
<p>Christopher Basset</p>
<p>Jane Sharp</p>
<p>Susanna Barton</p>
<p>James Arnet</p>
<p>Richard Hunt</p>
<p>Robert Wedy</p>
<p>Rowland Woodbridge</p>

<!--column 3-->
<p>John Brockson</p>
<p>Edward Perkins</p>
<p>John Stone</p>
<p>Christopher Tillier</p>
<p>John Collis</p>
<p>Roger Brian</p>
<p>John Quelch</p>
<p>John Walker <i>the Elder</i></p>
<p>John Walker <i>the Younger</i></p>
<p>Arthur Willis</p>
<p>Henry Cuttris</p>
<p>Richard Rose</p>
<p>William Cooper</p>
<p>Thomas Tunman</p>
<p>James Wright</p>
<p>Samuel Windsor</p>
<p>William White</p>
<p>Peter Frothingham</p>
<p>Simon Hide</p>
<p>William Tailor</p>
<p>Thomas Beely</p>
<p>Rich. Hammerton</p>
<p>John Wiseman</p>
<p>John Gravesam</p>
<p>Percival Shergold</p>
<p>Francis Dag</p>
<p>Robert Slim</p>
<p>Daniel Humphreys</p>
<p> Reynold Condler</p>
<p>Rich. Dennington</p>
<p>Thomas Butler</p>

<pb n="6" />

<!--3 column table contines-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>James Elkinton</p>
<p>Fardinando Pennithorn</p>
<p>George Stretton</p>
<p>Thomas Howard</p>
<p>James Badnedge</p>
<p>Stephen Painter</p>
<p>John Allen</p>
<p>John Bromfield</p>
<p>Andrew Leak</p>
<p>John Rogers</p>
<p>Edward James</p>
<p>William Pelchard</p>
<p>William Dod</p>
<p>John Clark</p>
<p>William Jeffreys</p>
<p>John Hoar</p>
<p>John Holloway</p>
<p>John Dunmore</p>
<p>George Douswel</p>
<p>William Lethal</p>
<p>John Norman</p>
<p>Rose Elms</p>
<p>John Dearman</p>
<p>Matthew Wildebore</p>
<p>Richard Cashwel</p>
<p>Thomas White</p>
<p>Robert King</p>
<p>John Davis</p>
<p>Henry Woodly</p>
<p>William Page</p>
<p>Richard Hatton</p>
<p>Christoph. Cloudy</p>
<p>Palchal Knell</p>
<p>Thomas Gates</p>
<p>William Chenal</p>
<p>Thomas Francis</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Margaret Trever</p>
<p>George Johnson</p>
<p>Robert Cobber</p>
<p>John West</p>
<p>James Heb</p>
<p>Richard Smith</p>
<p>Robert Hitchcock</p>
<p>John James</p>
<p>Robert Booth</p>
<p>Mrs. Cantrel</p>
<p>William Rabbon</p>
<p>John Brush</p>
<p>John Cosins</p>
<p>Josias Ward</p>
<p>Humphry Pitford</p>
<p>Richard Chandler</p>
<p>Edward Newcomb</p>
<p>Henry Walker</p>
<p>John Bitterton</p>
<p>Alice How</p>
<p>Jane James</p>
<p>Andrew Dickson</p>
<p>John Airs</p>
<p>John Rotchford</p>
<p>Samuel Waters</p>
<p>Thomas Wallis</p>
<p>John Thomson</p>
<p>Cordwel Lawters</p>
<p>Oliver Atkinson</p>
<p>George Youl</p>
<p>John Fisher</p>
<p>Thomas Langford</p>
<p>Elizabeth Thomson</p>
<p>John Warwick</p>
<p>Samuel Hill</p>
<p>Jinkin Lloid</p>
<p>James Briginsley</p>
<p>Robert Bently</p>

<!--column 3-->
<p>Thomas Web</p>
<p><i>The Lady</i> Jane Garret</p>
<p>John Gaskin</p>
<p>Rob. Westbrook</p>
<p>Robert Sauner</p>
<p>William Brileton</p>
<p>Roger James</p>
<p>James Dannolson</p>
<p>Nathaniel Wells</p>
<p>John Harris</p>
<p>John Ratcliff</p>
<p><i>Widow</i> Draper</p>
<p>Edward Brooks</p>
<p>Ralph Peckman</p>
<p>Stephen Evans</p>
<p>Francis Westerman</p>
<p>John Appletree</p>
<p>Daniel Major</p>
<p>Joseph Tennant</p>
<p>William Haslel</p>
<p>William Burton</p>
<p>Edward Beringer</p>
<p>Edward Conniers</p>
<p>Fardinando Eden</p>
<p>Robert Williams</p>
<p>William Fells</p>
<p>Solomon Bowlstreet</p>
<p>Abigal Rogers</p>
<p>William Goodman</p>
<p>John Ward</p>
<p>Stepehen Larret</p>
<p>Christopher Parret</p>
<p>Stephen Bayard</p>
<p>Edward Searl</p>

<pb n="7" />

<!--table continues in 2 columns divided by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Henry Yoe</p>
<p>Francis Chantree</p>
<p>Nathaniel Channeld</p>
<p>Peter Partington</p>
<p>John Hubbald</p>
<p>Phillip Smith</p>
<p>John Last</p>
<p>Nicholas Latimer</p>
<p>Theophilus Child</p>
<p>John Hadly</p>
<p>Elizabeth Burnham</p>
<p>Samuel Barker</p>
<p>John Baker</p>
<p>Henry Cobden</p>
<p>Thomas Peak</p>
<p>John Pendleton</p>
<p>Edward Huskins</p>
<p>Anne Beane</p>
<p>William Abraham</p>
<p>William Seale</p>
<p>Matthew Madden</p>
<p>George Palmer</p>
<p>Samuel Osburn</p>
<p>Thomas Needham</p>
<p>Anthony Ellingham</p>
<p>Richard Costerd</p>
<p>Francis Sturly</p>
<p>Richard Horn</p>
<p>John Roe</p>
<p>George Perkins</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Thomas Osborne</p>
<p>Miles Tilliard</p>
<p>Henty Waterfall</p>
<p>Margery Cole</p>
<p>Samuel Watson</p>
<p>Tristam Harding</p>
<p>Henry Stone</p>
<p>Aquila Garfield</p>
<p>William <reg orig="Iackson">Jackson</reg></p>
<p>Thomas Wit</p>
<p>Thomas Davenant</p>
<p>William Strange</p>
<p>Sivester Harding</p>
<p>Roger Gale</p>
<p>Thomas Dawson</p>
<p>Thomas Clarke</p>
<p>Rody Dinsdale</p>
<p>Christopher Bercot</p>
<p><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stamino</p>
<p>William Whetly</p>
<p>John Ferris</p>
<p><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Grove</p>
<p>Thomas Wildman</p>
<p><reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Allen</p>
<p><reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Kerby</p>
<p><i>Of which <reg orig="onely">only</reg> six have appeared, that is to say,</i></p>
<p>Samuel Barker</p>

<pb n="8" />

<!--table continues-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>William Burton</p>
<p>William Seale</p>
<p>George Palmer</p>
<p>Samuel Osborne</p>
<p>Richard Costerd</p>
<p>which six are of the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg> Quarter.</p>
<p>Prosecuted in the names of.</p>
<p>Mr. Thomas Smith.</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Mr. Nathaniel Camfield</p>
<p>Mr. John Smith</p>
<p>Mr. William Goodwin</p>
<p>Mr. John Wilcocks</p>
<p>Mr. John Walker</p>
<p>Mr. Thomas Tunman</p>
<p>Mr. William Joyce</p>
<p>Mr. Edward Brooks</p>
<p>Mr. James Stephens</p>
<p>Mr. John Cox</p>
<p>Mr. John Blinkcoe</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Letter from Scotland</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>An account as to those particulars I wrote about, you will perceive by the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> which is a Letter from one in the Hills, in what postures they represent themselves though the Intelligence we have from better hands is, that they <reg orig="finde">find</reg> an impossibility of keeping any together, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> they could have a certainty of Quarters in the Lowland parts, Provisions are so scarce with them. They are at much division when they are <reg orig="emboydied">embodied</reg> bout superiority, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not yet increase by any way of <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>; and their fiery <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg>, violent carriage, and other <reg orig="Bug-bears">Bugbears</reg> begin to be little prevalent to the Country. Some <reg orig="Country-men">Countrymen</reg> near <em>Cowper</em> of <em>Angus</em> did twice rise against a party of them that attempted to steal their horses, with Clubs, Pitchforks, and such weapons, and drove them away; and <reg orig="questionlesse">questionless</reg>, if others in the Lowlands would but take the same course they would be soon discouraged in their attempts of ruining the Country, who must taste a little more of their violent dealing before they will make any discovery of them.</p>

<p>Something might have been done by those in Authority to have prevented, and may be done to weaken this <reg orig="wilde">wild</reg> party; and I wish the neglect of them may not <reg orig="bee">be</reg> too prejudicial.</p>

<p>The first had been an <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> to many. <em>Huntley</em> (who still lives <unclear>probably</unclear>) and others in the <unclear>transporting</unclear> of some of them to <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> Service <unclear>or Stage</unclear> in amity with us. Another <pb n="9" />had been, by adjourning this last Sessions of Justice at <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, their rigorous proceedings against Debtors by caption, makes them rather to run to the Hills, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> laid in prison. A third is; the continuance of Sequestrations without distinction, which <reg orig="dis-inables">disenables</reg> them to dispose of Lands to pay debts, and making many desperate. A fourth thing necessary would be a Proclamation promising a reward to those that could bring in the heads of the <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> of them, and <reg orig="indempnity">indemnity</reg> to those that come in by such a day; for I have <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> informations, that both the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Athol</em>, and <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Seaforth</em>, who are the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> of estate amongst them, would willingly come, if they had any handsome opportunity.</p>

<p>The money is come safe to <em>Haddington</em> this night, though the Robbers had some design upon it.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith 8 Decemb. 1653.</i></p>

<p>This day his Excellency the Lord General <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> about one of the clock in the afternoon passed from <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> to the streets all along, and in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> at <em>Westminster</em> were many <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> both Horse and Foot; His Excellency was attended by the Lords Commissioners of the great Seal of <em>England</em>, the Judges and Barons of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Benches in their Robes, and after them the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of the Commonwealth: And the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of <em>London</em>, in their scarlet <reg orig="Gownes">Gowns</reg>, with the <reg orig="Recordar">Recorder</reg> and Town Clerk, all in their Coaches, who passed before his Excellency; and last of all came his Excellency in a black Suit and <reg orig="Cloake">Cloak</reg> in his Coach, with his Life Guard, and divers bare before him; and many of the <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> Officers of the Army with their Cloaks, and Swords, and Hats on, passed on foot before and about his Coach.</p>

<p>In this Equipage His Excellency, and Attendants came to <em>Westminster</em>-hall, where was a Chair placed in the High Court of Chancery; where being come, the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em> stood next to the Chair, the one on the one side, and the other on the other side, and next to the Lord Commissioner <em>Lisle</em> who stood on the left hand of the Chair stood His Excellency (all being bare; and His Excellency <pb n="10" /> also) on every side of the Chair; in the next place, stood the Judges and Barons on both sides; and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen on the right-side of the Court, next unto the Judges and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and the <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Officers of the Army on the left side of the Court.</p>

<p>The Rules for this New Government were then read, which consist of many particulars, expressed in an Instrument.</p>

<p>The Instrument is large, which took up above half an hours reading, and was read by Mr. <em>Jesop</em>, one of the Secretaries of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; after which, the Lord Commissioner <em>Lisle</em> read a Parchment in the nature of an Oath, to engage His Excellency to perform on his part, according to the Government before mentioned: During which time, His Excellency held up his hand; and having heard it read, accepted thereof, and subscribed thereto, in the face of the Court.</p>

<p>The Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal, and the Judges, &amp;c. invited him to take possession of the Chair, as Lord Protector of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; which he did, and <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> down with his head covered, the Court continuing all bare.</p>

<p>The Lord Commissioners delivered up to His Highness, the Purse and Seals, and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> of <em>London</em> his Sword; which were presently delivered to them back again by His Highness; and then after a salute, the Court rise.</p>

<p>First came the Aldermen and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> before His Highness from the Court to <em>Westminster-<reg orig="hal">hall</reg></em> Gate, where the Coaches were; after them the Judges, then came the Commissioners of the Great Seal, one of them bearing the Purse and Seals; and before His Highness came the Life-guard, then four <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> of Arms with their Maces, one being the Mace of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and the other of the Parliament, borne by the Sword-Bearer of <em>London</em>, <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Middleton</em>, <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Dendy</em>, and <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> <em>Berkehead</em>; and the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> of the City of <em>London</em> went next before His Highness with the Sword, and the Officers of the Army about His Person; and in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> they took Coach at the Hall Gate, and returned to <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> in the same Equipage they went; the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> rid bare with the Sword <pb n="11" />in the Boot of the Coach with His Highness; and there were great acclamations and shoutings all along the streets as they passed.</p>

<p>His Highness, the Lord Protector, being returned to <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, he went with his attendants to the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House, where they heard an Exhortation made by Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, Chaplain to His Highness; which being ended, they were dismissed with three <reg orig="Vollies">Volleys</reg> of shot by the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, between four and five <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> at night.</p>

<p>There is more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary joy, in, and about <em>London</em>, (both by the Inhabitants, and the <reg orig="Soudiery">Soldiery</reg>) for this happy day.</p>

<p>The Title of the Instrument aforesaid, is thus.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<p>The substance of the said Instrument, is</p>

<p>I. <i>That the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative Power of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, shall be, and reside in one single Person, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of thirteen at least, and twenty one at most, and the Commons assembled in Parliament.</i></p>

<p>II. <i>That this single person shall be called</i> The Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>III. <i>That there be constant Triennial Parliaments, and the first to begin the third of <em>September</em>. 1654.</i></p>

<p>IV. <i>That the Parliament shall have power of making all Laws, saving some Cased relating to the Guards of the Commonwealth, and Matters of Religion, (for which there is particular provision made in the Instrument,) containing the Government.</i></p>

<p>V. <i>That all Bills that pass in Parliament, shall be offered to the Lord Protector for his consent; which if he do not assent unto within twenty days, shall notwithstanding pass into, and become a Law; provided they contain nothing contrary to the Matters expressed in the said Instrument.</i></p>

<p>VI. <i>That the Lord Protector is to be Elective, and not <reg orig="Hereditory">Hereditary</reg>, and to be chosen by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> immediately upon the death of the Lord Protector.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, 19 December, 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day His Highness, the Lord Protector, met with those named of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, in the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> Chamber at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, <pb n="12" />it being the place where the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State used to sit, and several things were transacted in order to a settlement; and this following Proclamation was ordered to be Printed and Published on the Monday following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday, 19 December. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day His Highness, the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> being thirteen in number, met in the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> Chamber at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em>, where his Highness in s sweet Speech to them, pressed the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to act for God, and the peace, and good of the Nations; and particularly recommended to them, to consider and relieve the distresses of the poor and oppressed.</p>

<p>This day this Proclamation following was published at <em>Westminster</em>, and in the City of <em>London</em>, by divers <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> at Arms with their Maces. The Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen, being present at the <em>Exchange</em>, &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, a Proclamation.</i></head>

<p><i>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, by a <em>Lord Protector</em>, and Successive Triennial Parliaments, is now established; and whereas <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Captain General of all the Forces of this Commonwealth, is declared <em>Lord Protector</em> of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof; We have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make Publication of the Premises, and strictly to charge and command all and every person and persons, of what quality and conditions soever, in any of the said Three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, <reg orig="Majors">Mayors</reg>, Bailiffs, and other <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Ministers, and Officers, whom this may concern, are required to cause this <em>Proclamation</em> to be forthwith published in their respective Counties, Cities, Corporations, and Market Towns, to the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</i></p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> this Sixteenth day of December, 1653.</i></p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, 14 Decemb. 1653.</i> the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> Leaders are using their interests, what they can, in the several parts of the North, to get force together. The Writs issued out against persons in debt, makes many in the Lowlands <reg orig="flie">fly</reg> to them. there are almost 4000 Writs issued out against several persons, who have not money nor estates to pay their debts.</p>

<pb n="13" />

<head level="3"><i>Proposals <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg>, for relief of poor Debtors.</i></head>

<p><i>1. That the Debts of the Inhabitants of <em>Scotland</em>, may be judged according to Law; and that those who are not able to pay their debts presently, may give security to pay it in a reasonable time, at a day appointed, without allowing any use.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That such as will have benefit of the Infefment<!--possibly insesment, but the characters are crossed--> upon Land, may have the Land made over to them at such a rate, as it would have yielded at such time as the moneys was lent upon it.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That the Act of Pardon and Confiscation may be passed with much mercy for time past.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That a Proclamation be issued out, That after the said Act of <reg orig="Favor">Favour</reg>, those that are to receive benefit thereof, may be co curbed, That if any person <reg orig="contemn">condemn</reg>, or shall hereafter rise in Arms against the Power of the Commonwealth; that they be banished the three Nations, and all their estates to be confiscated.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 20. Decemb.</i></head>

<p>Whereas we are informed that many scandalous reports are spread abroad in the City of <em>London</em> and other parts of the Nation, that the <reg orig="mony">money</reg> collected in the Nation for and towards the <reg orig="releise">release</reg> of the distressed inhabitants of <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em>, who sustained great losses by the late dreadful fire that consumed the most considerable parts of the said Town is detained in the hands of the principal men of the said <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg>, and that the poorer sort have received little benefit by the free charity of <reg orig="wel">well</reg>-disposed persons. To vindicate <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, and to undeceive the Nation we hold <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> bound to make this <reg orig="insuing">ensuing</reg> Declaration. That whereas the <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Committee appointed by the <reg orig="Counsil">Council</reg> of State for the managing of the Collections for our Town sitting <reg orig="ta">at</reg> Saddlers <reg orig="hal">hall</reg> <em>London</em>, and have <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> us whose names are here <reg orig="under-written">underwritten</reg> to dispose of 2000 l. by them sent from several good Cities, Towns, Parishes, and Persons, and paid in to the hand of <em>Wil. Blisses</em> Esq; late Mayor of our <em><reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg></em> up to above two hundred for the poorer sort of persons of the said Town, and have not given one penny of the money collected and so brought in, and sent down unto us, unto any of the Common Council of the said <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg>, except four persons <reg orig="onely">only</reg>; <pb n="14" />that were in eminent present necessities, without which their Families could not subsist, and that there are above forty persons more that have not received one penny towards their said <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> fifteen of which number have lost above 15000 l. by the said fire; and we have hitherto forborne to distribute any unto <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>; or many others of out own rank and quality, although we are (many of us) reduced to very great <reg orig="streights">straits</reg> and necessities to borrow great Sums of <reg orig="mony">money</reg> to preserve our Families from <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, that we might discharge our trust, and first <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the present necessities of the poorer sort that suffered: And this we <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>.</p>

<p><em>John Lawrence</em> Mayor, <em>Will Blisses</em>, <em>Nicholas Profet</em>, Minister of <em><reg orig="Peters">Peter's</reg></em>. <em>Will. Hughes</em> Minister of <em><reg orig="Maries">Mary's</reg></em>, Tho. <em>Hunt</em>, <em>Will. Gough</em>, <em>John Baily</em>, <em>Tho. Baily</em>, <em>Jo. Keymes</em>, <em>Rich. Web</em>, <em>Nath. Baily</em>, <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em>28 <em>Novemb.</em> 1653.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Committee appointed to <reg orig="mannage">manage</reg> the Collections for the distressed Inhabitants of the Town of <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em>, in the County of <em>Wilts</em>, sitting at Sadlers-hall <em>London</em>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas this Committee is credibly informed, that <reg orig="severall">several</reg> sums of money collected (by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of Letters Patents) granted for the relief of the distressed Town of <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em>, in the County of <em>Wilts</em>, are detained in the hands of several persons, notwithstanding the directions of this Committee in that <reg orig="behalfe">behalf</reg> given, and the most <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> and pressing necessities of very many sad and miserable Families, crying and calling upon us for <reg orig="releife">relief</reg>.</p>

<p>It is therefore Ordered, that upon Certificates to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> made unto this Committee by the Receiver-General for the Army in every respective County, of the names of such persons who do detain the collected Moneys in their hands as aforesaid, that this committee shall <reg orig="returne">return</reg> the names of all such persons unto the <reg orig="Counsil">Council</reg>, that such speedy course may be taken with them therein, as the <reg orig="Counsil">Council</reg> shall seem meet. And that the Receivers General are hereby desired to give notice to this Committee of all such persons before the 20. day of <em>January</em> next accordingly. And all Ministers and others, where the said Letters Patents have not yet been read: nor Collections made, are also earnestly desired forthwith to proceed therein, that the poor people of that Town may be speedily <reg orig="releived">relieved</reg>.</p>

<p><i>F. Burroughs Clerk to the said Committee.</i></p>

<pb n="15" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 21 Decemb.</i></head>

<p>This day His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> with the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> which are 13 in number, in the <reg orig="Counsil">Council</reg> Chamber at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and several things were transacted in order to a quiet and peaceable settlement of the three Nations.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The names of the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the <reg orig="Counsil">Council</reg></i></head>

<!--table in 3 columns divided by vertical lines-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Mr. <em>Laurence</em>: the President</p>
<p>Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em></p>
<p>Maj. General <em>Lambert</em>,</p>
<p>Maj. General <unclear><em>Duborow</em></unclear>,</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Skippon</em></p>
<p>Col. <em>Jones</em>.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Seydnham</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em></p>
<p>Sir <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Woosley</em></p>

<!--column 3-->
<p>Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em></p>
<p><em>Mr. Rouse</em></p>
<p><em>Mr. Strickland</em></p>
<p><em>Mr. Major.</em></p>

<p>There have been some hundreds of Barrels of Gun powder discovered about London, some part of it no body, in some <reg orig="Store-houses">Storehouses</reg>, will be known to own. We have cause abundantly to bless God for this new change of Government.</p>

<p>The probabilities of peace with the Dutch are yet more and more, and there will be transactions with other Nations also.</p>

<p><unclear>The Fleet</unclear> is at St. <reg orig="Ellins">Ellen's</reg> Road about <unclear>30</unclear> <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> with Gen. Monk. Scouts are sent out, and some small Prizes brought in; some small Boats the Dutch have taken with small <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg>. His Highness <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, being Thursday, goes into the City of London.</p>

<p>Dalkeith, 15 Decemb. 1653. Yesterday there came Intelligence, That the tenth <unclear>instant;</unclear> Cap. Lisle of Col. <reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg> Regiment, hearing of a party of the enemy about <unclear>ten miles</unclear> from his quarters, marched in the night from Montros with 100 Horse and Dragoons, and fell upon them by break of day, near Glams; took 40 horse, 19 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, two Captains of Horse, one Cornet, and one <reg orig="Quarter-Master">Quartermaster</reg>, and killed nine or ten of them, all of the Earl of <reg orig="Kinouls">Kinoul's</reg> Regiment, which he was raising in Angus and the Mearns. The next day Col. Morgan having notice of a party of them in Eghil, a strong house in Angus, near the Hills, marched towards it, but the enemy having notice, fled away upon his approach; he pursued and took 15 horse, but the Lord Kinoul and his Lieutenant Colonel Ramsay, who were with them, escaped. They still go on with their Levies, and stealing horses, though they <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg> many good horses through hard riding, and ill looking too, and lately 15 died out of one <reg orig="Lairds">Laird's</reg> ground. Another party of ours took some of these Bobtails near Aberdeen, yet they increase; most of them are now gone Northwards to receive some Arms landed from Holland.</p>

<p>A party of Major General <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> Regiment were at the heels of Col. Wogan, and those that came with him at Kelsith, but they recovered the Hills before they could have full <reg orig="sent">scent</reg> of them; <reg orig="its">it's</reg> supposed he and some others landed in Lancashire, have Commissions and Instructions from <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart.</p>

<head level="3">A List of the Prisoners taken out of the Lord <reg orig="Kinouls">Kinoul's</reg> Regiment, 10. Dec. 1653</head>

<p>Cap. Mich. Balfoor, Cap. Wil. Blare, Cornet James Ramsey, <reg orig="Quarter-Master">Quartermaster</reg> Wil. Frier. Troopers, Geo. Flack, Jo. Merlin, Pra. Sharp, Div. Ramsey, James Bruce, Jo. Macklain, Wil. Fife, Dan. Lawson, Jo. Gardner, Ro. Swan, Jo. Brand, Arch. Meal, Ja. Batteson, Hen. Man, Hen. Goodlee,Wil. Eriston, Geo. Mac Donel, Dan. Calmanich.</p>

<p>These few lines are desired to be inserted, as tending to <reg orig="publick">public</reg> benefit. If any person be desirous to have any of the new plate, it is to be sold by Laurence Dyer, at the <unclear>corner</unclear> Pewterers shop at the Pump, at the upper end of Aldermanbury, where they may have <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> that is usually made in Silver, (viz. Dishes, Trencher-plates, <reg orig="Sawcers">Saucers</reg>, <reg orig="Flaggons">Flagons</reg>, Tankards, Candle-cups, Beat-<reg orig="bowles">bowls</reg>, Beakers, <unclear><!--6 characters-10 characters--></unclear> , Spoons, Tobacco-boxes, Sugar-boxes, <reg orig="Inke">Ink</reg>-horns, &amp;c.) all which is so well <unclear>performed</unclear>, and sold <unclear><!--2 char. 2 char. 4 char. approx. 8 char.--></unclear> as will be to the satisfaction and content of those who please to make use thereof, <unclear>we giveth</unclear> directions likewise to keep it <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> to its primitive <unclear>lustre</unclear> and beauty.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>