<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState235">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 235</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 23 of <em>March</em> To Thursday the 30 day of <em>March</em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 23 March. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day passed this following Ordinance.</p>

<p><reg orig="Bee">Be</reg> it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act of Impressing of Seamen</i>, and all Powers and Clauses therein contained, <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, and are hereby revived, and shall continue and stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first day of <em>November</em>, in the year one thousand six hundred and fifty four.</p>

<p>These three following Ordinances, were also this day published.</p>

<p><reg orig="Bee">Be</reg> it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An <pb n="1" />Act for laying an Imposition upon <reg orig="Coales">Coals</reg>, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas;</i> And all Powers and clauses therein contained, <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, and are hereby continued, and shall and do stand in full force, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the six and twentieth day of <em>March</em> 1655.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance of passing Custodies if Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Act of the late Parliament on the <reg orig="behalfe">behalf</reg> of Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, it was among other things enacted, That the <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> for passing of the custodies of the said Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, should be signed by the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of State before the Commissioners of the great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> of <em>England</em> should <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the same under the said Seal; And whereas that <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> is since dissolved, Be it ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the Chancellor, Keeper or Commissioners of the Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> for the time being, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> not <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> the said Custodies under the Great <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> before the same be signed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and that the same so signed by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> shall be a sufficient warrant for passing the same under the said Great Seal, any Law, Statute, Act, Ordinance or <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> to the contrary thereof in <reg orig="any wise">anywise</reg> notwithstanding.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers.</i></head>

<p>Whereas for some time past hitherto there hath not been any certain course established for the supplying vacant places with able and fit persons to preach the <reg orig="Gospell">Gospel</reg>, by reason whereof not only the Rights and Titles of Patrons are prejudiced, but many weak, scandalous, popish, and illiterate persons have intruded themselves, or been brought in, to the great <reg orig="griefe">grief</reg> and trouble of the good people of this Nation; For remedy and prevention, Be it Ordained by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, that every person who shall from and after the five and twentieth day of <em>March</em> instant be presented, nominated, chosen or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with care of souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> settled Lecture in <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em>, shall, before he be admitted into any such Benefice, or Lecture, be judged and approved by the persons hereafter named, to <pb n="2" />be a person for the Grace of God in him, his holy and unblameable Conversation, as also for his Knowledge and Utterance, able and fit to preach the <reg orig="Gospell">Gospel</reg>; And that after the said five and twentieth day of <em>March</em>, no person, but such as shall upon such approbation be admitted by the said persons, shall take any <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Lecture, having a constant stipend legally annexed and belonging thereunto, or take or receive any such Benefice as aforesaid, or the profits thereof.</p>

<p>And be it further Ordained, That <em>Francis Rous</em> Esq; Dr. <em>Thomas Goodwin</em>. Dr. <em>Tuckney</em>, Dr. <em>Horton</em>, Mr. <em>Joseph Caryl</em>, M. <em>Phillip Nie</em>, M. <em>William Carter</em>, M. <em>Sydrach Simpson</em>, M. <em>William Greenhill</em>, M. <em>William Strong</em>, M. <em>Thomas Manton</em>, M. <em>Samuel Slater</em>, M. <em>William Cooper</em>, M. <em>Stephen Marshal</em>, M. <em>John Tombes</em>, Mr. <em>Walter Cradock</em>, M. <em>Samuel Fairclogh</em>, M. <em>Hugh Peters</em>, M. <em>Peter Sterry</em>, M. <em>Samuel Bamford</em>, M. <em>Thomas Valentine</em> of <em>Chaford</em>, M. <em>Henry Jessee</em>, M. <em>Obadiah Sedgewick</em>, M. <em>Nicholas Lockier</em>, M. <em>Daniel Dyke</em>, M. <em>James Russel</em>, M. <em>Nathanael Campfield</em>, <em>Robert Titchburn</em> Alderman of <em>London, Mark Heldesly, Thomas Wood, John Sadler, William Goff, Thomas</em> St. <em>Nicholas, William Packer</em>, and <em>Edward Cresset</em> Esquires, shall be and hereby are nominated, constituted and appointed Commissioners for such approbation and admission as is abovesaid, and upon death or <reg orig="removall">removal</reg> of any of them, others shall from time to time be nominated in their places by the Lord Protector and hid Successors, by advice of his Council, in the <reg orig="intervall">interval</reg> of Parliaments, and sitting the Parliament, by the Protector and <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>; And the said Commissioners or any five or more of them, met together in some <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> place in the City of <em>London</em> or <em>Westminster</em>, as his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> shall appoint, are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to judge and take knowledge of the ability and <reg orig="fitnesse">fitness</reg> of any person so presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed according to the qualification above mentioned, and upon their approbation of such his ability and <reg orig="fitnesse">fitness</reg>, to grant unto such person admission to such Benefice or Lecture by and Instrument in writing under a Common Seal to be appointed by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and under the hand of the Register or Registers for the time being to be also nominated by the Lord Protector and his Successors, which Instrument the said Register of Registers <pb n="3" />shall cause to be <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> in a book for that purpose, and kept upon Record.</p>

<p>And it is <reg orig="herby">hereby</reg> declared, That the said person so admitted into any such Benefice, shall be Possessor and Incumbent of the same, and <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg> thereby to the Profits, <reg orig="Perquisits">Perquisites</reg>, and all Rights, and Dues incident and belonging thereunto, as fully and effectually as if he had been instituted and inducted according to the Laws of this Realm; as also the person that shall be so admitted to any Lecture as aforesaid, shall be thereby enabled, according to the establishment and constitution of such Lecture, to preach therein, and to have, and receive the Stipend or Profits to such Lecture belonging.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg>, That no person who shall tender <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, or be <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> for approbation as aforesaid, shall be concluded by any vote of the said Commissioners which shall <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> in the Negative as to his approbation, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> nine or more of the said Commissioners be present at such Vote.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That all Patrons of any Benefices that are now void, shall within six Months next after the five and twentieth of this instant <em>March</em>, and of any Benefice that shall hereafter be void within six months next after the avoidance of the same, present unto the said Commissioners, or any five of them, some fit person to be admitted, and for default of such Presentation within that time, the Presentation for that turn, shall devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector, and his Successors.</p>

<p>Provided <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg>, That in the case Patron be disturbed to Present unto such Benefice, and <reg orig="therupon">thereupon</reg> within six months after the avoidance of such Benefice a <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> be commenced for the recovery of such Presentation, and notice thereof in writing left with the said Commissioners, or any five of them, or the Register, that ten such notice shall be as <reg orig="effectuall">effectual</reg> to prevent the lapse, as where the <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg> was heretofore commenced against the Bishop or Ordinary.</p>

<p>And it is further Ordained, That during the vacancy of such place, by reason of such <reg orig="Sute">Suit</reg>, the said Commissioners, or any five more of them, have hereby authority to sequester the fruits and profits thereof for supplying of the place with an able Preacher, <pb n="4" />the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, to be nominated and approved of as aforesaid.</p>

<p>And for as much as many persons since the first day of <em>April</em> last <reg orig="past">passed</reg> have been placed in such Benefices, and <reg orig="publicke">public</reg> Lectures, It is hereby Ordained, That in case such person shall not before the four and twentieth day of <em>June</em> next, <reg orig="obtaine">obtain</reg> approbation and admittance in the manner before <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg>, Then such person or persons as have right thereunto, shall or may present, or nominate some other fit and able person to such place.</p>

<p>And in default of such Presentation within two months after the said four and twentieth day of <em>June</em>, or within six months after the place became void, the Presentation for that turn shall likewise devolve by lapse unto the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>And for the better satisfaction of the said Commissioners touching the godly and unblameable conversation of such persons as are to be admitted into any place as aforesaid.</p>

<p>It is further Declared and Ordained, That before any admittance of any person as aforesaid, there shall be brought to the said Commissioners, or any five of them, a Testimonial, or Certificate in writing, subscribed with the hands of three persons of known <reg orig="godlinesse">godliness</reg> and integrity, whereof one at least to be a Preacher of the Gospel in some constant <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> place, Testifying upon their personal knowledge, the holy and good conversation of the person so to be admitted, which said Certificate shall be duly <reg orig="Registred">Registered</reg> and filed. And it is also Declared, that the penalty for, or in the Act of the thirteenth <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, <reg orig="Intituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>Reformation of disorders in the Ministers of the Church</i>: or for not producing such Testimonial as in the said Act is required, shall from henceforth cease and be void.</p>

<p>An whereas for the better maintenance for Preaching Ministers, <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Augmentations by Authority of Parliament have been heretofore granted; Be it further Ordained that all person or persons, who claim, or shall hereafter claim the benefit of such Augmentation, shall before he of they receive the same, <pb n="5" />obtain the approbation of the said Commissioners of five of them, as a person qualified as is before mentioned. And is case of approbation, such approbation shall be <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> by the Register, who under his hand shall also <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> the same to such person or persons as are, or shall be <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to pay such Augmentation, who are hereby required and <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> from time to time to pay the person or persons so approved, such Augmentation as hath been, or shall be granted unto him, or the place where her preacheth, taking his or their Acquittances for the same. Provided, and it is hereby Declared, that this Ordinance, or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> therein contained, shall not be construed to extend unto, or to revive any Dignities, Offices, or Benefices Ecclesiastical, suppressed by Authority of Parliament. Nor to any Benefices <reg orig="Ecclesiasticall">Ecclesiastical</reg> that were not presentative before the Ordinance for suppression of Bishops: Nor to any Lectures preached or read in any of the Universities.</p>

<p>And it is hereby lastly Declared and Ordained, That the approbation, or admittance aforesaid, in such manner as is before prescribed, is not intended, nor shall be construed to be any Solemn, or Sacred setting a part or <reg orig="aperson">a person</reg> to any particular Office in the Ministry; but only by such <reg orig="triall">trial</reg> and approbation, to take care that places destitute may be supplied with able and faithful Preachers throughout this Nation. And that such fit and approved persons faithfully labouring in the work of the Gospel, may be in a capacity to receive such <reg orig="publick">public</reg> stipend and maintenance, as is or shall be allotted to such places.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 24 March 1653.</i></head>

<p>This was the Fast day in <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, and parts adjacent, which was observed very strictly; the Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, and the Justices in the other parts, having sent out Command before for the strict observance thereof. The Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> were at the <reg orig="Chappell">Chappel</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, whither resorted a great number of people; and there Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, Mr. <em>Strong</em>, and Mr. <em>Cradock</em>, prayed and preached that day.</p>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and Family remain as yet at the Cock-pit, only that one night mentioned in my last, which his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> lay at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, but not since.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> having made his application to the Lord Protector, his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> ordered that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> should be received as an Ambassador, and Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> house in on the Monday following; and Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em> Mr. of the Ceremonies, had orders to attend the said Lord Ambassador, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> also ordered that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> should have audience the next day after, being Tuesday.</p>

<p>Letters have been sent the Lords Ambassadors from the States of the United Provinces of <em>Holland, &amp;c.</em> upon a return of which something will probably <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done one way or other about the Peace.</p>

<p>A Vessel is appointed for the passage of the Ambassador from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg>, who having done his <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> with the Lord Protector, is returned.</p>

<p><em>Muchill <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg></em> in <em>Scotland</em> 14 <em>March</em>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have here blessed <reg orig="bee">be</reg> God, one time with another, <reg orig="temperoll">temporal</reg> food <reg orig="plentifull">plentiful</reg> enough, but for <reg orig="spirituall">spiritual</reg> food for our <reg orig="soules">souls</reg>, it is very hard to attain, insomuch that our <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> <reg orig="soules">souls</reg> are almost famished in some places, where sometimes I am, where I do hardly know how the Lords day passeth away, by reason of marching after the Enemy, in which <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are exposed to a great deal of hardship, and yet not to that effect <reg orig="wee">we</reg> desire, because the Enemy hath so much Intelligence, so that when <reg orig="wee">we</reg> make our approach towards them they cowardly fly from us up into the Hills, where <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are not like to do them much hurt, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Winter be <reg orig="past">passed</reg>, but in the Summer approaching, I hope by the blessing of God, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> shall destroy them who trust more in their feet than in God.</p>

<p>I beseech you that I may have the <reg orig="injoyment">enjoyment</reg> of your prayers, for the Lord doth know that I am in very great need of them, being in a barren Country, where the Word of God by the Inhabitants is but little observed, which makes <reg orig="mee">me</reg> sensible of the want I now have of the sweet opportunities which I did enjoy when I was in <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>This night the time expired for the bringing in or Claims of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Debts, and no more are to be received.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 25. March, 1654.</i></head>

<p>A Woman was sentenced to be sent to prison, and there to <pb n="7" />be severely <reg orig="whipt">whipped</reg> for attempting to <reg orig="couzen">cozen</reg> the State and the Navy.</p>

<p><i>Newcastle 20 March</i>, Two of our <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em> ships being impatient to stay here <reg orig="untill">until</reg> Convoy came adventured out, and one of them is returned hither again from thence safe, the other hath made her voyage, and went towards the Downs. Our ships have taken some Dogger Boats near the Dogger Sands. The news of peace will be welcome to these parts.</p>

<p><i>Milfordhaven 18 March, 1653.</i> Three Vessels arrived here this <reg orig="weeke">week</reg> from <em>Ireland</em>, laden with Hides, Tallow, and other Irish Wares, and some few passengers that they brought over.</p>

<p><em>Ireland</em> in many parts wants people to <reg orig="til">till</reg> and manure the ground; the Tories and others of that bloody crew are very near all <reg orig="supprest">suppressed</reg>, there being <reg orig="onely">only</reg> very small parties remaining on foot but dare not to stand to any engagement with such parties of ours as are sent for to destroy them, and so <reg orig="cleare">clear</reg> the Country from them, upon the least report that they hear of our <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> approaching they presently run into the Woods and Bogs where there is little or no <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> to them.</p>

<p>We have not been much troubled with <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, one only was seen the beginning of this week to the Westward of the Isle of <em>Lundy</em>, but upon the report made him by a <reg orig="Fisherboat">Fisher-boat</reg>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> appointed to keep these Seas was in pursuit, he immediately went away, and left this Channel, sailing towards the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, he hath about 6 guns and 16 men being a Dutch Vessel, but a singular good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Scarborough</em> March 20. Since that the fleet of Colliers bound for the Southward hath passed by, there hath not sailed this way many ships, save only a few bound for <em>Newcastle</em>, <em>Berwick</em>, and the <em>Frith</em> in <em>Scotland</em>. Two days since two Dutch Freebooters were seen about <em>Fylie</em> Bay, and seeing nothing to prey upon, they went about <em>Flamborough</em> into the Bay as <reg orig="neare">near</reg> <em>Bridlington</em> as they durst: But seeing nothing ready to be <reg orig="snapt">snapped</reg> up, they sailed into the Sea, and were seen this evening hovering about the mouth of <em>Humber</em>.</p>

<p><i>Leith March 18.</i> There is no account yet come of the Highlanders great <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, which was to be about Wednesday <pb n="8" />last in <em>Badgenoth</em>, in order to which all their forces are drawn Northwards, where they will arm those that want, and <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to raise <em>Sutherland, <reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em>, and so drain the Country of all the sensible men they can get together, though I suppose when that is done they will not be able to keep them, without coming into the Lowlands, which if once they become more numerous they will attempt.</p>

<p>By another Letter further thus, <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to 700 and the last <reg orig="generall">general</reg> <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> of them all they <reg orig="spake">spoke</reg> themselves to be 7000 armed, but have no moneys, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> are fed with hopes of great sums to come out of <em>Germany</em>, and that the Titular Duke of <em>York</em> is to bring from thence an <reg orig="additionall">additional</reg> supply of men under his Conduct, and upon this depends the great expectation of <em>Charles <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> arrival amongst them. In the interim they march towards out Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p>

<p>This morning about three of the clock the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg> with the Dutch Letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, was seized and broke open by <reg orig="Theeves">Thieves</reg> within a mile of <em><reg orig="Southwarke">Southwark</reg></em>, which they did (as is supposed) upon hopes to <reg orig="finde">find</reg> money, but finding none, broke open all the Letters that were in packets, and threw them upon the ground, and turned the man back again.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday 27 March, 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had his reception at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> house in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard at <em>Westminster</em>, being brought from Tower <reg orig="Wharfe">Wharf</reg>, where he landed, thither through the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em> in great state, with between 50 and 60 Coaches.</p>

<p>In the first Coach, which was the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> rich Coach was the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, and five or six of his <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> Gentlemen attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Coachman and Postillion, and ten of his Pages in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Liveries, and the Lords <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassadors'</reg> Pages with his Liveries.</p>

<p>Next went the French <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> own rich Coach with others of his Gentlemen in it, that are come from France to attend the Lord Ambassador.</p>

<pb n="9" />

<p>Then went the <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> Coach of the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em> with the <reg orig="cheife">chief</reg> of the <em>Portugal</em> Gentlemen in it, and the Coachman and Postillion riding in Crimson Velvet coats, laid thick with rich silver lace.</p>

<p>After them followed about 20 more with six horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg> of the Coaches of the English Nobility and Gentry, The foremost of which was the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> second, Coach: And then about 12 with four horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>, and lost of all some 20 Coaches with two horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>.</p>

<p>There was a mistake at their taking Coach between some Gentlemen of the Lord Ambassador of the King of France, and Gentlemen of the Lord Ambassador of the King of <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> of their Coaches, some of the French Gentlemen thinking that their Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> second Coach should have gone before the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> first Coach, which did occasion drawing of Swords, and some small <reg orig="harme">harm</reg>; but the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> stepping in, disarmed those that drew on both sides, and the mistake being understood, they were all reconciled, and in friendly <reg orig="kindnesse">kindness</reg> passed along in the order aforesaid.</p>

<p>The old Commissioners of the Excise this day surrendered up their powers to the new Commissioners, who this day took possession of their Office.</p>

<p><em>Dalkeith</em> 21 March, 1653. The Lord <em>Ray</em> hat sent to Skelbe for <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> for his men, <em><reg orig="Seaford">Seafort</reg></em> was expected the 10 instant, within five miles of Crabsdale with his men, Sir <em>George Monroe</em> and <em>Middleton</em> were then in <unclear>Strawcaver</unclear>, and to meet <em>Seafort</em> and <em>Ray</em> at <em>Jura</em>, with their whole force, where also <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em> with his Rabble are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, and so force <em>Sutherland</em> and <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> to rise with them. The <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Lewis</em> have made slaughter of the Country people that <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Seafort</em>, and they have also slaughtered some of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the old Natives <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with our men against the rest of the <reg orig="Countrie">Country</reg>; so that these Divisions cause great Devastations in these parts.</p>

<p><i>Rhinstroom 24 March.</i> The Prince of <em><reg orig="Leige">Liege</reg></em>, Elector of <reg orig="Collen">Cologne</reg> is agreed with the Spaniards about the differences happened in that Country, upon these terms. 1. That the Forces under the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and the Duke of <em><reg orig="Lorraign">Lorain</reg></em> shall retire from thence and come there no more. 2. That the said Elector shall <pb n="10" />for satisfaction for his losses have paid to him the sum of 200000 Rix <reg orig="Dollers">Dollars</reg>, for the security whereof he shall have the two Lordships of <unclear><em>Korpen</em></unclear> and <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters--></unclear>. That the Inhabitants of the Country of <em><reg orig="Leige">Liege</reg></em> shall pay no Contribution. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the French under the Marquis <em>Faber</em> do ransack all in <em><reg orig="Luxemburg">Luxembourg</reg></em>, which hath given occasion to the Spaniards to get there in haste and without noise a body of 2000 men, who are fallen upon the French about <unclear><em>Clermont</em></unclear>, but with what <reg orig="successe">success</reg> at is not yet known.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague the 27. March.</i></head>

<p>The last Thursday were brought here in a Pink sent for that purpose Letters of the 20 instant from the Lord Ambassadors now in <em>England</em>, whereby we hear they gave advice to the Lords States, that the Treaty of Peace was not yet concluded, but that preparations for Sea were made there in all <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, the occasion whereof was unknown to them, which caused some suspicions and jealousies amongst the said Lords States; Insomuch that the Vice <reg orig="Admirall">Admiral</reg> <em>Ruyser</em>, and the Scout by night <em>Tromp</em> with other Captains received orders to resort presently to <em>Amsterdam</em>, which they did accordingly Wednesday morning, as also <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Messengers were dispatched to the Counsels of the Admiralties. The Lieut. Admiral, the Lord Van-<em>Opdam</em> was likewise commanded to come from <em>Brabant</em> where he was hither.</p>

<p>And yet we cannot understand by the Letters come from <em>London</em> the night between the 20 and 21 that any difficulties should have arisen wherefore the Treaty should not go on, so that it is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> that the same may have a good <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, and that those preparations made there may be for some other design. We have very little certainty of the Scottish Affairs. It is presumed that <em>Middleton</em> is arrived in <em>Scotland</em> to gather what forces he can to restore the titular King His <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> fortune. Last night a Pink hath been by the Lords States dispatched from Scheveling into <em>England</em>, though he be but stirring up <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> to a <reg orig="boyle">boil</reg>, which without question will break this Spring.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 28 March. 1654.</i></head>

<p>Those that were taken about suspicion of <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> of false moneys it is said have impeached others. One also is discovered who used to carry a <unclear>Box</unclear> before him up and down <em>London</em>, in which he sold many small Wares, Laces, Combs, <pb n="11" />and such like things, and (as it is said) in the <reg orig="bottome">bottom</reg> of his Box <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> Pick-locks, and Stamps for <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> of moneys, and some sorts of <reg orig="Engins">Engines</reg> which he traded in, to sell to Customers, for whom he provided them.</p>

<p>From several Counties are come Letters of the gallant receptions of the Judges in their Circuits in several places. The Justices filling up the Benches, the Country coming in, and much joy in the several parts, for the hopes the Country have of a good settlement under this new Government.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Congratulations are signed in several Counties to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and some are already delivered to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as from <em>Monmouth</em> Shire, and other parts.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of 14 Prizes taken by the <em>Phenix, Newcastle, Assurance</em>, and <em><reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</i></head>

<head level="3">March 2. 1653.</head>

<p>1 Taken then by the Phenix <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Claus</em> of <em>Housdown</em>, 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>Jacob Timison</em> Skipper, with Masts, Yards and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, with main-<reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, fore-<reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, <reg orig="Gibb">Jib</reg>, Crosiack, top-<reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, <reg orig="Mizen">Mizzen</reg>, and Sprit-<reg orig="saile">sail</reg>, 3 Anchors, 3 and half <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, one <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <reg orig="hauser">hawser</reg>, one new boat, 4 Oars and Rudder, which had only ballast on board.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 2. 1653.</i></head>

<p>2 Taken by the Phenix her boat, the <em>Plumpart</em> of <em>Mazeland sluce</em>, 30 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, <em>William </em><unclear><em>Parmiston</em></unclear> Skipper, with Masts, Yards and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, with main-sail, fore-sail, <reg orig="gibb">jib</reg>, top-sail, sprit-sail, <reg orig="mizon">mizzen</reg>, and two fluting sails, 3 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, 4 anchors, one small <reg orig="warpe">warp</reg>, which had on board 40 barrels of fish, six <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of Salt, and 40 empty casks.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 17.</i></head>

<p>3 Taken by the Phenix, the <em><reg orig="Blew">Blue</reg> Pigeon</em> of <em>Pamerland</em>, 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>Peter Johnson</em> Skipper, with Masts, Yards, Sails, one <reg orig="sute">suit</reg> with one main topsail, one <reg orig="mizon">mizzen</reg> <unclear>span</unclear>, with rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, 3 anchors, 3 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, 2 <reg orig="hausers">hawsers</reg>, one boat, <unclear><!--single number--></unclear> Oars, one mast-sail and rudder, laden with Brandy wines, white wine, claret wine, and Prunes.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 17.</i></head>

<p>4 Brought by the Lee, by the Phenix and her boat set on board and afterwards run on board by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, who broke her head and <reg orig="boltsprit">bowsprit</reg>, and forced the Phenix her boat off, and <pb n="12" />was after taken. The <em>Fortune</em> of <em>Delphi</em>, 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>James Jacobson</em> Skipper, with masts, Yards, sails, one <reg orig="sute">suit</reg>, and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, 5 anchors, 3 new <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, and two <reg orig="hausers">hawsers</reg>, laden with Brandy wine, claret wine, white wine, Prunes, one boat, six oars, mast, sail and Rudder.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 2.</i></head>

<p>5 Taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot hoy, and having shot her mast by the board, burned her. This is all the account given of her, <reg orig="shee">she</reg> being taken out of sight of the squadron.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 2.</i></head>

<p>6 Taken by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Hope</em> of <em>Housedown</em>, 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>Adrian Jacobson</em> Skipper, with Masts, Yards and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, with main-sail, fore-sail, <reg orig="gibb">jib</reg>, crosiack, topsail, <reg orig="mizen">mizzen</reg>; and sprit-sail, one boat, 4 Oars, and rudder, 3 anchors, 3 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, one small <reg orig="hauser">hawser</reg>, having only ballast on board.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 14.</i></head>

<p>7 Taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigate's</reg> boat, the <em><reg orig="Shelfish">Shellfish</reg></em> of <em>Mazeland sluce</em>, of 25 Tuns burden. <em>Jacob Johnson</em> Skipper Skipper, with masts yards and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, main-sail, fore-sail, <reg orig="gibb">jib</reg>, topsail, <reg orig="mizen">mizzen</reg> sprit-sail, and two fluting sails, 3 anchors, 3 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, one small <reg orig="warpe">warp</reg>, which had on board her 20 <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of fish, 4 <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of Salt, and 26 empty casks.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 12.</i></head>

<p>8 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Providence</em> of <em>Mazeland sluce</em>, 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>Aryan Yoresson</em> Skipper, with masts, Yards, and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, with main-sail, fore-sail, <reg orig="gibb">jib</reg>, top-sail, sprit-sail, <reg orig="mizon">mizzen</reg> and two fluting sails, 4 anchors, 5 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, one small warp, which had on board her 10 barrels of fish, six <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of Salt, and 56 empty casks.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 14.</i></head>

<p>9 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmayds">Mermaid's</reg></em> boat, the <em>Fortune</em> of <em>Mazeland sluce</em>, 32 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> burden, <em>Aryis Yaris</em> Skipper, with masts, Yards and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, with main-sail, fore-sail, <reg orig="gibb">jib</reg>, topsail, <reg orig="spritsail">sprit-sail</reg> and <reg orig="mizon">mizzen</reg>, and two fluting sails, 4 anchors, 3 and a half <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, one small <reg orig="warpe">warp</reg>, which had on board 77 <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of fish, six <reg orig="barels">barrels</reg> of Salt and 40 empty casks.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 18.</i></head>

<p>10 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot hoy of <unclear>21</unclear> <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burden, with masts, Yards, sails, and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>.</p>

<pb n="13" />

<head level="3"><i>March 19.</i></head>

<p>11 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, a Scotch vessel, laden with Beef, <reg orig="Flower">Flour</reg>, <reg orig="Trayn">Train</reg> <reg orig="oyle">oil</reg>, Deer skins and Sugar.</p>

<p>12 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg></em> at the same time another Scotch <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg>, which had in her only ballast.</p>

<p>These two Scotch Vessels were going for <em>Holland</em>, and had been taken by a private man of war belonging to <em>Anchusen</em>. There were none of the people that did formerly belong to them in them; and therefore at present no further particular account could bee got of them.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March 20.</i></head>

<p>13 Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg></em>, the <em>Waking Boy</em> of <em>Anchusen</em>, a private man of war, commanded by Cap. <em>Tho. Johnson</em>, with masts, Yards, sails one suit, with 4 fluting <reg orig="sailes">sails</reg>, two top-gallant sails, and Rigging <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg>, all new; 4 anchors, 4 <reg orig="cabels">cables</reg>, 8 guns, 150 li. of gunpowder, and shot proportionable, 12 Pikes, 10 Muskets, 8 Pistols, and one Boat with four Oars.</p>

<p>14 Taken by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a private man of War.</p>

<p>The day of the <em>French</em> Ambassadors <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Audience was not this day as was thought, but was appointed on the morrow, against which time all things were ordered to be ready.</p>

<p>the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, with his Gentlemen, was this day in person to visit the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>France</em> at his lodging at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williamses">Williams's</reg></em>, where he <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> a great while in conference with him.</p>

<p>This day the Members of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> were with the Lord Protector at the <em>Cock-pit</em>.</p>

<p><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Committees of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> about the Scotch <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>, and about <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Petitions, and other businesses referred to their Lordships by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p>It is <reg orig="wondred">wondered</reg> by many, that so many Gentry, and especially <em>English</em> Ladies, have this Easter made such <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> to the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg>, to see their Popish Trumperies, their <reg orig="Passeover">Passover</reg> on the Thursday, and one acting the part of <em>Judas</em>, their Picture of Christ on the Cross, with piercing of his side, and burying that which they made in Picture of Christ, the Watchmen and Angels, and all their superstitious actings as <pb n="14" />Players in a Stage play during those <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and all this chiefly on Friday last, when those that fear the Lord, were upon that solemn day of Humiliation seeking to the Lord by prayer and fasting. But blessed be God, the sweet showers we have since had to refresh the earth is a great comfort in <reg orig="regarn">regard</reg> of their prayers, and may cause those Ladies, and others <unclear><!--2 letters--></unclear> blush with shame that they should be spending their time so vainly, when God was sought unto by those that fear him for the blessings we enjoy, and hope for, lest God smite them that they enjoy no part thereof.</p>

<p>The English Fleet is in a gallant Equipage in the Narrow about St. <reg orig="Ellins">Ellin's</reg>, whence they have sent our several Squadrons.</p>

<p>It will be appointed where the Commissioners for Approvers of those that are to preach in places of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> allowance shall meet so soon as conveniences can be dispatched.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday March 29.</i></head>

<p>This day the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Audience in the Banqueting house in <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, which was richly hung with stately Hangings, and thousands of people present. The Lord Ambassador was carried in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> Coach, and with him some of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, attended by divers of the Nobility and Gentry in the Coaches of the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador, and the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, and the Nobility and Gentry of England, above forty Coaches, most with six horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>.</p>

<p>Being come to <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the Lord Ambassador was received by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, where his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> was with his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> at the upper end of the Banqueting house, where after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Congies">Cognises</reg>, he returned <reg orig="backe">back</reg> again.</p>

<p>The Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech was to declare that he came from the King of <em>France</em> his Master to treat in order to a <reg orig="firme">firm</reg> peace to be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> with <em>England</em>. Touching which he had a kind answer.</p>

<p>There are four prizes taken at Sea besides those 14 mentioned in the foregoing List.</p>

<p>1 A small Merchant ship brought in prize into <em>Rye</em>.</p>

<p>2 A Denmark ship taken and brought in prize into <em>Scarborough</em>.</p>

<p>3 A rich prize being a man of War taken with Sugar, <pb n="15" />and other <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg> taken by a private man of War worth 150000 l.</p>

<p>4 A private man of War belonging to <em>Camseare</em> in <em>Zealand</em>, commanded by Captain <em>John Poll</em> a Flushinger, taken 13 <em>March</em> by the <em>Paul</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, about 10 leagues to the Northward of <em>Ushing</em>, taken with 15 <reg orig="peece">piece</reg> of Ordinance and 60 men after six <reg orig="houres">hours</reg> dispute, she is brought into <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> is returned from <em>Ireland</em>, and is (blessed be God) safely arrived at the Cock-pit. All is quiet and in a good condition.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of the Treaty with the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg>, lies thus (according to my best intelligence) That the Lords Ambassadors had power to have signed when they were here before, and when all was then agreed, it was their fault they signed not, which if they had done, Peace had been then concluded: And now they themselves say that they were <reg orig="chid">chided</reg> by the States General because they did not the <reg orig="signe">sign</reg>; And now <reg orig="wee">we</reg> are in all things agreed between us and <em>Holland</em>, and they may <reg orig="signe">sign</reg> that agreement when they please, which they have power to do; But seeing that they will treat for <em>Denmark</em>, to have that Crown brought in also; It is but reason that the <em>English</em> Merchants who sustained <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> by their confederacy with <em>Denmark</em> against them, should <reg orig="bee">be</reg> paid for their ships and goods, which were there taken from them, which is the main thing the Treaty sticks at; The Dutch may have peace for themselves if they will, and leave <em>Denmark</em> to themselves; or if the Merchants (which is the life of Trade in a Nation, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="payd">paid</reg> what was wrested from them) all is agreed. But that which they offer will scarce half pay the Merchants: But the Lords <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> have sent over to the States, I suppose that their message is to know their pleasure herein.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>&#x261e; Heaven on Earth, or a Serious Discourse touching a well grounded Assurance of <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> everlasting <reg orig="Happinesse">Happiness</reg> and <reg orig="Blessednesse">Blessedness</reg>. Discovering the Nature of Assurance, the possibility of attaining it, the Causes Springs, and Degrees of it, with the resolution of several weighty questions. By Tho: Brooks, Preacher of the Gospel at <reg orig="Margarets">Margaret's</reg> <reg orig="Fishstreet">Fish Street</reg>-Hill. Sold by John Hancock in <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg>-head Alley in Cornhill.</p>

<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>