<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState241">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 241</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 4 of <em>May</em>. To Thursday the 11 day of <em>May</em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 4 May. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> were upon weighty affairs about <reg orig="Forain">Foreign</reg> transactions, and other considerable <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> sate while almost nine a clock at night.</p>

<p>Two Merchant ships were burnt on <em>May</em> day morning in the Thames <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Ratcliffe</em>, laden with Merchandizes fitted to go out; by an accident of Pitch <reg orig="boyling">boiling</reg> in a Kettle in one of them, that ran over and set fire of that ship, and so of the other that rid by it.</p>

<p>This day came out the Articles of Peace concluded between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, which being of so great concernment to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> known to all persons, are here Printed <em>verbatim</em>, and are as followeth.</p><pb n="1" />

<p><i>Articles of Peace, Union and Confederation, concluded and agreed between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging. And the Lords the States General of the United Provinces of the <em>Netherlands</em>. In a Treaty at Westminster bearing date the <reg orig="fift">fifth</reg> of <em>April</em> Old Stile, in the year of our Lord God, 1654.</i></p>

<p>1. It is agreed, concluded and accorded, that from this day forward there shall be a true, firm, and inviolable Peace, more sincere Friendship, and nearer Alliance, Union and Confederation than heretofore, betwixt the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the States General of the United Provinces of the <em>Netherlands</em>, and the respective Lands, Countries and Cities without distinctions of places, under their obedience, and the people and Inhabitants of them respectively, of what quality and condition soever they be.</p>

<p>2 <em>Item</em>, Agreed, That from henceforth all enmity, hostility, discord and War betwixt the said two Commonwealths, their People and Subjects, shall cease, and each party shall hereafter abstain from all offences, spoils, depredations, and injuries by Sea, Land and fresh-waters in all their respective Lands, Countries, Dominions, Places or Governments whatsoever.</p>

<p>3. <em>Item</em>, That all offences, injuries, charges and damages, which either party hath sustained by the other since the 18 (<em>alias</em> 28) of May, in the year 1652, shall be taken away and forgotten in such manner as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other for or upon occasion of any the aforesaid offences, injuries, charges and damages; But that there shall be a perfect abolition of all and every of them <reg orig="untill">until</reg> this present day. And all actions for the same shall be held and reputed void and null.</p>

<p>4. That all Prisoners of both sides of what condition, or in whatsoever place they be shall be set at liberty, without ransom or consideration given for them.</p>

<p>5. That the two Commonwealths shall remain confederate Friends, <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg>, and allied together for the defence and preservation of the Liberties and Freedom of the people of each against all whomsoever, who shall attempt the Disturbance of either State by Sea or Land, or be declared Enemies to the Freedom and Liberty of the people living under either of the said Governments.</p>

<p>6. That neither of the Commonwealths shall make do, act, treat of, or attempt <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other, or the people of either, in any place either at Land or Sea, or in any the Havens, Creeks, Precincts, or fresh-waters of either, upon any occasion whatsoever, Nor that either of them, or the people of either, give, <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, or afford any aid, counsel, favour, or assent that <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> shall be done, treated of, or attempted by any other whomsoever, to the injury and wrong of the other, or the people of either, but shall <reg orig="expressely">expressly</reg> and with effect contradict, <reg orig="gain-say">gainsay</reg>, oppose, and really hinder all whomsoever abiding or dwelling within either of the Commonwealths respectively, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be under their power that act, do, treat of, or attempting any thing against either of the Commonwealths.</p>

<p>7. That neither of the Commonwealths, or the people abiding, inhabiting, or dwelling within either of them respectively, or within their power, shall <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, give, or afford any aid, counsel or favour to the Enemies or <reg orig="Rebells">Rebels</reg> of either, but shall <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg>, really, and with effect hinder any inhabiting, dwelling or abiding within either of them, or within their power, from giving any aid or assistance unto such Enemies or Rebels, by Men, Shipping, Arms, Ammunition, Money, Victuals, or otherwise by Sea or Land, and all such ships, Arms, Ammunition, Money, Goods, or Victuals, of or belonging to any<pb n="2" /> person or persons whatsoever, that there shall be provided, employed, or made use of, contrary to the intent of the Article, shall be confiscate and forfeited to the respective Commonwealths. And the person or persons who shall wittingly and willingly do attempt, counsel, or be employed therein, shall be declared Enemies to both Commonwealths, and shall suffer the pains and penalties of Treason within the Commonwealth where the offence shall be committed. And to the end, there may be a specification made of what Goods shall be deemed prohibit, or contraband, Commissioners may in convenient time be appointed to determine herein. Provided in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> that this extend not to the impeachment of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> contained in the present Article.</p>

<p>8. That the two Commonwealths shall truly and sincerely assist each other, as need shall require, against the Rebels and Enemies if either, at Sea and Land, with Men and Ships, at the Costs and <reg orig="Expences">Expenses</reg> of the party requiring the same, in such proportion and manner, and upon such Terms and Conditions, as the two States shall agree, and the present occasion require.</p>

<p>9. That neither of the Commonwealths, or the People of either shall receive into any of their Jurisdictions, Countries, Lands, Ports, Creeks, or Precincts, any person or persons, that are or shall be declared by either of the Commonwealths to be Enemies, Rebels or fugitives of the other; nor shall give, <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> or afford to any such declared Enemy, Rebel or Fugitive within the places aforesaid, or other where, though out of their Territories, Countries, Lands, Ports, Creeks, or Precincts, any aid, counsel, Lodging, Entertainment, <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, Ships, Money, Arms, Ammunition or Victuals. Nor shall either of the States permit such Enemies, Rebels or Fugitives to be received by any person or persons whatsoever in their Jurisdictions, Countries, Lands, Ports, Creeks, or Precincts, nor shall suffer any Aid Counsel, Lodging, Entertainment, <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, Ships, Money, Arms, Ammunition, or Victuals to be given, <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> or afforded unto such Enemies, Rebels, or Fugitives, but shall <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> and effectually oppose, withstand, and really hinder the same.</p>

<p>X. <em>Item</em>, It is agreed, That if either of the said Commonwealths shall by their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> and <reg orig="Authentick">Authentic</reg> Letters, give notice, <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, or declare to the other Commonwealth any person or persons, to be, and have been their Enemy or Enemies, Rebel or Rebels, Fugitive or Fugitives, and that they are, or reside within the <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Jurisdictions, Territories, Dominions, Lands, Ports, or Precincts, or therein be hid, or shelter themselves; then that Commonwealth which shall receive such Letters, or unto which such notice shall be given, and declaration made concerning such Rebels, Enemies or Fugitives, shall within the space of twenty eight days to be reckoned immediately from the day of the aforesaid notice given, charge and command such Enemy or Enemies, Rebel or Rebels, Fugitive or Fugitives, to withdraw and depart out of their Jurisdictions, Territories, Dominions, Lands, and Precincts, and every of them. And if any such enemy, Rebel or Fugitive shall not withdraw and depart, as aforesaid, within the space of fifteen days after such charge and command given, That he or they shall be punished with death, and loss of Land and Goods.</p>

<p>11. That no Rebel or declared Enemy of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, shall be received into any of the Castles, Towns, Ports, Creeks, or other places privileged, or not privileged, which any person of what degree and quality soever he be, or shall be, hath, or hereafter shall have and possess by any Title whatsoever, within the Dominions and Jurisdictions of the United Provinces; nor shall be suffered by any person of what degree and quality soever to be received thereunto, or abide therein. Neither shall the Lords, the States General of the United Provinces, permit or suffer in any of the places aforesaid, any assistance, counsel, or <reg orig="favor">favour</reg>, in Ships, Men, Money, Victuals, or in any other manner to be given by any person, of what degree and quality soever to any such Rebel, or declared Enemy, but shall openly, and <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> prohibit and hinder the same. And if any person or persons of what degree and quality soever living or remaining within the Jurisdictions of the United Provinces, or under their power, do<pb n="3" /> to the contrary hereof: Then all and every such person and persons so doing, as aforesaid, shall for their respective lives, forfeit and lose all such Castles, Towns, Villages, Lands, and other places, which they or any of them shall at such time have, or pretend to have, by any Title whatsoever. And likewise that no Rebel or declared Enemy of the States of the United Provinces shall be received into any of the Castles, Towns, Ports or other places privileged, or not privileged, which any person or persons of what degree or quality soever he or they be, have or shall have, hold or possess within the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, or Dominions thereof, by any Title whatsoever; nor be suffered by any person or persons to be received there into or abide therein. Neither shall the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, permit or suffer, in any of the places aforesaid, any counsel, assistance or <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> in Ships, Men, Money, Victuals, or in any other manner to be given by any such person or persons of what degree or quality soever he or they be, to any such Rebel or declared Enemy, but shall openly and <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> <reg orig="prohibite">prohibit</reg> and hinder the same. And if any of the people of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, or under their power, shall do or attempt <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to the contrary hereof: That every such person or persons, shall for their respective lives, forfeit and lose all such Castles, Towns, Villages, Lands, and other places, which they or any of them shall at such time have or pretend to have, by any Title whatsoever.</p>

<p>12. That the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the People and Inhabitants thereof, and the said United Provinces, and the Subjects, and Inhabitants thereof, of what quality or condition soever they be, shall be bound to treat each other on both sides with all love and friendship: That they come by Water or by Land, into each others Lands, Towns, or Villages, walled or unwalled, fortified or unfortified; their Havens, and all their respective Dominions in <em>Europe</em>, with freedom and security, and in them remain and continue as long as they please, and there without <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg>, buy Victuals for their necessary use. And may also Trade and <reg orig="Traffick">Traffic</reg>, and have commerce in any Goods or Commodities they please, and the same bring in and carry out at their pleasures, paying always the Customs that shall be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, and saving always all and singular the Laws and Ordinances of either Commonwealth respectively. Yet so, that the People and Inhabitants of either, using Commerce in the Countries and Dominions each of other, shall not be constrained to pay any greater Customs, Tolls, or Tributes, <reg orig="then">than</reg> according to such proportion as other Strangers exercising Commerce in the same places pay.</p>

<p>13. That the Ships and Vessels of the said United Provinces, as well Men of War as others, meeting with any of the Ships of War of this Commonwealth in the British Seas, shall strike their Flag, and lower their <reg orig="Top sail">Topsail</reg>, in such manner, as hath ever been at any time practised heretofore under any former Government.</p>

<p>14. <em>Item</em>, For the greater Freedom of Commerce and Navigation, it is agreed. That neither of the said Commonwealths shall receive into any of their Havens, Cities, or Towns, or permit, or suffer that any of the people or Inhabitants of either of them respectively, do receive, keep, <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg>, or give any assistance or <reg orig="releif">relief</reg> unto any <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> or Sea-Rovers, but shall cause both the said <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg> and Rovers, and also their Receivers, Concealers, and Assistants, to be prosecuted, apprehended, and condignly punished for terror to others. And all ships, Goods, and Merchandise, by them Piratically taken, and brought into the Ports of either State, that shall be found in being; yea, though they have been sold, shall be restored to the right owners, or made good to them, or such as have their Letters or Attorney or Procuration to claim the same, due proof of the Proprietors being first made in the Court of Admiralty, according to Law.</p>

<p>15. That if either the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, or the United Provinces of the Low Countries shall hereafter make any Treaty of Amity, Alliance, or Friendship with any other Commonwealth Princes, or States, the one shall comprehend the other, and the Dominions therein, if they shall desire to be comprehended: And of all such Treaties, each shall be bound to give notice to the other.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>16. That if it shall happen that during the Amity, Confederation and Alliance, <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> shall be acted or attempted by any of the People or Inhabitants of either of the said Parties against this Treaty, or any part thereof, either by Land or Sea, or other Waters, this Amity, Confederation, and Alliance between the said Commonwealths, shall not be hereby interrupted or broken off, but shall continue and remain in its full and whole power, and in such case, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> those particular persons, who have offended against the said Treaty, shall be punished, and no other; And that justice shall be done, and satisfaction made to all persons concerned, within Twelve <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, after demand thereof made, upon all such persons who shall have done <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against this Treaty, by Land or Sea, or other waters in any part of <em>Europe</em>, or any place within the <reg orig="Straights">Straits</reg> of <em><reg orig="Gibralter">Gibraltar</reg></em>, or in <em>America</em>, or upon the Coasts of <em><reg orig="Africk">Africa</reg></em>, or in any Lands, Islands, Seas, Creeks, <reg orig="Bayes">Bays</reg>, Rivers, or any other places on this side the <em>Cape</em> of <em>Good Hope</em>. And in all places whatsoever as aforesaid, beyond the said <em>Cape</em>, within Eighteen <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> next after demand of Justice, shall so as aforesaid be made: And in case the persons so as aforesaid offending, shall not appear and submit themselves to justice, and make satisfaction within the times respectively here before limited, the said persons shall be declared Enemies to both Commonwealths, and their Estates, Goods, and effects whatsoever, shall be confiscate and employed to a due and full satisfaction for the wrongs by them done, and their persons to be liable to such further punishment, when they shall come within the power of either State, as the quality of their offence shall deserve.</p>

<p>17. That the people of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the Dominions thereof, may freely unmolested and securely travel in and through the Countries, and singular the Dominions of the United Provinces in <em>Europe</em>, by Land or by Water, to any place in them, or beyond them, and pass by any of their Towns, <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg>, or Forts in any places within the Netherlands whatsoever, or <reg orig="elswhere">elsewhere</reg>, in any of their Dominions in <em>Europe</em>, to follow their <reg orig="Traffick">Traffic</reg> in all places there; as also their Factors and Servants armed or unarmed; but if armed, not above forty men in company, as well without as with their Goods and Merchandizes, whither they please. And likewise the people and Inhabitants of the United Provinces of the <em>Netherlands</em> may enjoy the same liberties in all the Dominions of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> in <em>Europe</em>. They and either of them observing and conforming in such their Trade and <reg orig="Traffick">Traffic</reg> to the Laws and Ordinances of each Commonwealth respectively.</p>

<p>18. <em>Item</em>, agreed, That if the Merchant Ships belonging to the People and Subjects of one or the other side, shall through tempest, <reg orig="Pirats">Pirates</reg>, or any other necessity, be driven into Port within the Dominions of either, it shall be free for them to depart thence securely with their Ships and Merchandize, without payment of any Customs, or other Duties; provided, they break not bulk; or expose <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to sale, nor shall they be subjected to any trouble or visitation, so be it they receive not aboard any persons or goods, nor shall do <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> contrary to the Laws, Statutes, and Customs of that place whither they come into Port as aforesaid.</p>

<p>19. That the Merchants, Masters, Pilots, or Mariners of either Commonwealth, their Sips, Goods, Wares, and Merchandizes, shall not be seized or arrested in the Lands, Ports, Havens, and Rivers of the other, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any general or particular commands, for any warlike or other service, except upon inevitable necessity, and upon just satisfaction for the same; provided, that hereby shall not be excluded the Arrests and Seizures in the ordinary way of Law and Justice of each Commonwealth respectively.</p>

<p>20. That the Merchants on both sides their Factors and Servants, as also the Shipmasters and other Seafaring men, may as well travelling and returning by Ships over the Seas, and other Waters as in the Havens of each other, and going on shore, carry and use for the defence of themselves, and their Goods, all sorts of Arms for defence and offence; but being come to their several Lodgings or Inns, they shall lay down their Arms there, and so leave them till they go again to the Ship, or on board.</p>

<p>21. That the Men of War of either Commonwealth meeting or overtaking any Merchant ship or ships at Sea, belonging to the other, or to the people or inhabitants thereof,<pb n="5" /> holding both one course, or going both one way, shall be bound, so long as they keep one course together, to take them under their protection, and to defend them against all and every that shall attempt upon them.</p>

<p>22. That if any ship or ships of the People or Inhabitants of either Commonwealth, or of a Neuter, shall be taken in the Havens of either by any third party, being none of the people or Inhabitants of either Commonwealth; They, in or from whose Havens and Liberties the said ships shall be taken, shall be bound together with the other party, to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> that the said taken ship or ships may be followed, brought back, and restored to the owners, but all at the charges of the proprietors or <reg orig="interessed">interested</reg>.</p>

<p>23. That Searchers and other Officers of that nature, on both parts, shall, in execution of their Offices, regulate themselves according to the Laws of each Commonwealth respectively, and shall not <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> or take more than they are allowed by their Commission or Instructions:</p>

<p>24. That in case any wrong or injury done by either Commonwealth, or by the people or Inhabitants thereof, against the people or Inhabitants of the other, either against any the Articles of this Treaty, or against the common right, there shall yet no Letters or <reg orig="Reprizals">Reprisals</reg>, Mark or <reg orig="Counter-mark">Countermark</reg>, be granted by one or the other Commonwealth, till first Justice be there sought in the ordinary course of Law, and in case that Justice be there refused or delayed, then, that demand be made thereof from the <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Power of the Commonwealth, whose People or Inhabitants have suffered wrong, or from such as the supreme power shall depute, to that Commonwealth where justice is as aforesaid <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, or <reg orig="delaid">delayed</reg>, or to such power as shall be by them appointed to receive such demands, that all such differences may be composed amicably, or in the ordinary course of Law. But if there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be yet delay, and that Justice be not done, nor satisfaction given within three months after such demand made, that then Letters of <reg orig="Reprizal">Reprisal</reg>, Mark or Countermark may be granted.</p>

<p>25. That all persons on either side that shall go out to Sea upon particular Commissions shall be bound before they take out their Commissions to put in good and sufficient Security by responsible Men not of the ships Company, before the Judges of the Court whence the said Commission is issued, that they shall do no wrong or injury to the people or Inhabitants of either side.</p>

<p>25. That the people of either side shall have free access to each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Ports and may there stay and thence depart not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> with their <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> Ships and such as are laden, but also with their ships of war, whether belonging to the State or to such as have obtained particular Commissions, whether they shall arrive either by stress of weather, or to avoid the danger of the Sea, or for repairing their ships, or for provision of victuals, so be it they exceed not the number of eight ships of War when they come in of their own accord, nor that they continue or make stay in the Havens or about the Ports, longer than for the reparation of their ships, buying in of victuals, or for provision of other necessaries, And whensoever any greater number of ships of War than is above specified shall have occasion of access into those Ports, then shall it not be lawful for them to make any entrance, without first obtaining leave for this purpose from those to whom the said Ports belong, unless they be constrained by weather or any other force or necessity for avoiding the danger of the Sea. And when it shall so happen, they shall presently make known the cause of their coming to the Governor or chief Magistrate of the place and shall make no longer stay there <reg orig="then">than</reg> the Governor or <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Magistrate shall permit, and during their stay in those Ports they shall commit no hostile Act, nor do <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to the prejudice of the said Ports.</p>

<p>27. That the Lords the States General of the United Provinces shall take care that Justice be done upon those who were Authors or Abettors of the <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg> committed upon the English in <em>Amboyna</em>, as the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> was pleased to <reg orig="qualifie">qualify</reg> it, in any of them be yet alive.</p>

<p>28. Whereas certain English Ships and Goods have been seized and detained within<pb n="6" /> the Dominions of the King of <em>Denmark</em>, since the 18 day of the <em>May</em> in the year 1652, it is on both sides concluded, accorded and agreed, and the Lords the States General have obliged themselves, as they also do by these presents, That restitution shall be made of all and singular the English ships and Goods, detained as aforesaid, and remaining yet in <em>Specie</em>; together with the true and just price of such as are sold, <reg orig="imbezled">embezzled</reg>, or otherwise disposed of, within fourteen <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the arrival of the Merchants and Masters <reg orig="interessed">interested</reg> therein, or their Assigns, for the receiving of them. And also that Damages be given for the losses sustained by the English, by reason of the said detention; according to what shall be arbitrated and awarded by the said detention; according to what shall be arbitrated and awarded by <em>Edw. <reg orig="Winslo">Winslow</reg>, James Ruslel, John Beex, Wil. Vander Cruyssen</em>, Arbitrators indifferently chosen, as well on the part of the Lord Protector, as the said States General (the form or instrument of which Arbitration is already agreed upon) to examine and determine the demands of the Merchants, Masters, and Owners to whom the said ships, goods, and damages appertain. Which Arbitrators are to meet at <reg orig="Gold-smiths">Goldsmith's</reg> <reg orig="Hal">Hall</reg> here in <em>London</em>, the 27 of June next, old stile, or sooner if it may be; and shall the same day make solemn Oath before the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty of England, that they will proceed without respect or relation had to either State, or any particular interest whatsoever. And moreover, the foresaid Arbitrators <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from the first day of August next, unless they agree upon sentence sooner, be shut up in a chamber by themselves, without fire, candle, meat, Drink, or any other refreshment, till such time as they come to an Agreement concerning the matters referred to them: And the Sentence which they shall award shall be obligatory to both parties. And the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the United Provinces do firmly oblige themselves by these presents, to execute and perform the same; as also to pay such sum of moneys here at <em>London</em>, as the said Arbitrators shall adjudge to be paid, for the use of the said Owners, to such person, or persons as the Protector shall nominate, within 25 <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the Instruments of Ratification of the said Articles of Peace are mutually delivered, pay here at London the sum of 5000l. ster, towards the Charges of the Merchants, Masters, or their Assigns, for their <reg orig="Journy">Journey</reg> to Denmark, &amp; the sum of 20000 Rix Dollars, to such persons as his said Highness shall appoint, within six <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the arrival of the said persons there, for the use of the Merchants, Masters and Owners, towards repairing their ships and fitting them for Sea. Which said sums shall be accounted in part of payment of such sum, as shall be awarded by the said Arbitrators: And that Caution and Security be given (the form of which Caution is already agreed upon) by sufficient and responsible men, living here in London, and binding themselves in an Obligation of one hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling (which Obligation is to be delivered at the same time with the Instrument of Ratification) that restitution shall be made according to the<pb n="7" /> premises; and that the submission and payment as well of 20000. Rix Dollars, as of such sum, or other things, as shall be adjudged and determined, as aforesaid, shall on their part be duly performed. And if all and singular the Conditions be not really and effectually performed in the part of the Lord the States General in manner and time aforesaid, then the said Obligation shall be forfeited, and the said sum of One hundred and forty thousand pounds sterling, shall be paid to such person and persons as His Highness shall nominate, to the end the losses of the Merchants, Masters, and <reg orig="interessed">interested</reg>, may be satisfied.</p>

<p>29. <em>Item</em>, That whereas certain Questions and Differences have arisen between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the King of <em>Denmark</em>, by reason of the detention of the Ships and Goods mentioned in the former Article, and the States General of the United Provinces have undertaken the restitution of the said Ships and Goods, and agreed to give security and caution for the damages in the manner <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> in the former Article: It is agreed and concluded, That the same being done and performed, all questions, strifes, wrongs, and acts of hostility between the said Commonwealth and King, by reason of the said detention, shall cease and be <reg orig="for ever">forever</reg> forgotten, in such manner, that the said King with his Kingdoms and Dominions, shall, as a friend, be comprehended and included in this Treaty and Confederation, so as to be restored to the same friendship and alliance with either Commonwealth, in which formerly he was, before the said detention, and as if it had never been. As also his Deputies and Ambassadors shall be admitted with like <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> as the Deputies and Ambassadors of other States are, being Friends and Allies.</p>

<p>30. <em>Item</em>, Agreed, That at the time of the delivery of the Instruments of Ratification, four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides to meet here at <em>London</em>, upon the eighteenth day of <em>May</em> next, old stile, who shall be authorised and <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, as also by these presents that are authorised and <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to examine and determine all the losses and injuries which either side alleges to have sustained from the other since the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> One thousand six hundred and eleven, unto the Eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, 1652, old stile, as well in the <em>East-Indies</em>, as in <em>Greenland, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>, or in any other place: The particulars of all which are to be delivered into the Commissioners nominated as above, before the said Eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, under this restriction, That after the said day prefixed no new <reg orig="Alligations">Allegations</reg> shall be admitted. And if the abovesaid Commissioners shall not within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> space, to be accounted from the said Eighteenth day of <em>May</em>, come to an agreement, concerning the differences aforesaid, delivered in writing, and expressed in particular: That in such case the aforesaid differences shall be submitted, as by these presents they are submitted, to the judgment and arbitration of the Protestant Cantons of <em>Switzerland</em>, who by an Instrument for this purpose (the form of which is already agreed upon) shall be desired to take upon them that<pb n="8" /> Arbitration, and appoint like Commissioners <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and instructed to give final judgement thereupon within six months next following after the expiration of the three months aforesaid. And whatsoever the said Commissioners or the major part of them, shall award and determine within the said six months, shall oblige both parties, and be performed accordingly.</p>

<p>31. It is also agreed, that both parties <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> firmly and truly perform and observe this present Treaty, and every Article and thing <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg> and concluded therein; and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> cause the same to be performed and observed by their respective People, Subjects and Inhabitants.</p>

<p>32. For better security that this peace and confederation <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be truly and sincerely performed on the part of the Lords the States General their people and Subjects, it is agreed and concluded, and the Lords the States General, do these presents agree and firmly oblige themselves, that all and singular, whom, either they the States General, or the States Provincial, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> at any time elect, constitute or appoint Capt. General, <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> Governor, or Stadtholder, Commander of their Army or Forces at Land, or Admiral of any of their Fleets, Ships or Forces at Sea, shall confirm by Oath this Treaty, and all the matters and things therein contained, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> promise by oath to observe, and as much as in him or them lies, inviolably to perform and keep the same. And as far as concerns them, command the same to be performed and put in execution, and take care that they be performed and executed by others accordingly.</p>

<p>33. Lastly, it is agreed, that the present Treaty, and all and singular the matters and things therein contained and agreed on, shall within fifteen <reg orig="daies">days</reg> next ensuing, or sooner if it may be, be confirmed and ratified in due and <reg orig="authentick">authentic</reg> form, by the said Lord Protector, and the said States General of the United Provinces by their Letters <reg orig="Pattents">Patents</reg> under their Great Seals, and that Instruments of Ratification shall be delivered interchangeably, within the time aforesaid. And furthermore that this Treaty and confederation shall immediately after delivery of the Instruments, be published according to the usual solemnity, and in the places accustomed; and that all Acts of hostility <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> cease on both sides from that time.</p><pb n="9" />

<p>A congratulatory Petition was this day presented to his Highness the Lord Protector from divers persons of the County of <em>Hertford</em>.</p>

<p>This day passed an additional Ordinance touching the Excise, That all other goods and Merchandizes mentioned in the book of Rates for the Customs (except Bullion, Corn, Victuals, Arms, Ammunition, Ordnance of brass or iron, and wools of Sheep imported or to be imported, which are not in the said Rates of Excise, before or otherwise charged, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> hereafter pay Excise, after the rate of <em>5 l. per <reg orig="cen">cent</reg></em>, to be paid by the first buyer from the Merchant or Importer, that from the 25 of <em>March</em> last the Revenue of the Excise <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be but one receipt, and brought into one General Revenue. And the <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> of all fines and forfeitures after 25 <em>March</em> paid towards the maintenance of widows and maimed <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>. And out of the general cash 26250 <em>l</em>. yearly, be paid weekly to persons appointed to pay it to the use aforesaid by his Highness and Council.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 5 May.</i></head>

<p>This day the Deputy from the King of <em>Denmark</em> had audience by the <em>Lord Protector</em> being brought to <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em> in his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Coach, attended by Sir <em>Oli. Fleming</em> Mr of the Ceremonies who did with great joy of the Peace congratulate his Highness.</p>

<p>The Commissioners from his Highness this day treated with the Lord Ambassador from the King of <em>France</em> at his lodgings in <em>Covent Garden</em> touching Peace. The Judges sat this day in <em>Westminster <reg orig="hal">hall</reg></em>, and so every day in this last Return of this Term.</p>

<p>Naples 7 April, <i>The <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> designed for <em>Piombino</em> and <em>Porto Longo</em> are come back with the Ammunition and Provisions. Yesterday 22 Troops of Horse were mustered by our General <em>Duke Sesto</em>; many Ordnances newly cast are speedily to be sent into <em>Catalonia</em> and other parts. The King of <em>Spain</em> hath ordered Cardinal <em>Filomarini</em> our Archbishop to depart this Kingdom. Count <em>d'Ognate</em> our late Vice Roy is in great favour with the King of <em>Spain</em>, and is made President of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> of <em>Italy</em>.</i></p>

<p><em>Venice 17 April</em>. The Turk prepares again to storm <em>Candia</em>, before their new General comes. But the Town lately made a sally and killed about 500 Turks, and in the loss we had in <em>Dalmatia</em> 1800 Turks were killed, the prisoners they took there they <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg><pb n="10" /> to <em>Constantinople</em>, and presented to the grand <reg orig="Segnior">Seignior</reg> by the Basha of <em>Boshina</em>, and presume their Fort of <em>Clim</em> is now secure; but we have here <reg orig="imbarked">embarked</reg> a considerable strength for <em>Dalmatia</em>, and are preparing great forces for <em>Candia</em>, under Gen. <em>Morenico</em> and Marq. <em>Barry</em>. The Turks being 9000 about <em>Spalatto</em> have taken From <em>Zara</em> many men and store of cattle.</p>

<p><i><em>Rome 13 April</em>. The Lady <em>Lucretia Barbarina</em> receiving a <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> of Diamonds of a Present from the Pope worth 5000 Crowns, went yesterday towards <em>Lorretra</em>, and is to marry with the Duke Of <em>Modena</em>. The Pope is high against <em>Spain</em>; he had sent Signior <em><reg orig="Massinis">Massini's</reg></em> Nuncio to the King, and <em>Trivaltio</em> sent a Gentleman of his from Rome along with him, who understanding his Instructions got before him and told the King his Errand, and thereupon the King sent to stop him in his journey. <em>Trivaltio</em> is used hardly by the Pope for it, and the Pope hath recalled his Nuncio, he was since sending. Here is an Ambassador from the King of <em>Portugal</em>, which notwithstanding all that the Spaniards can do to hinder, is like to have audience.</i></p>

<p><em>Warsaw 6 April</em>, The Diet broke up much divided, are to meet again in <em>July</em> next. The <em>Muscovites</em> come not out as feared, upon their knowledge of our great preparations they give out the raised forces in fear of an invasion by the <em>Tartars</em>, upon this Prince <em>Janus Radzivill</em> General of <em>Lishmania</em> <reg orig="staies">stays</reg> his advance.</p>

<p><em>Genoa 22 April</em>, Besides the ships mentioned in my last there have been cast away three <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> of <em>Genoa</em> near <em><reg orig="Scilley">Sicily</reg></em> with an English ship and a Dutch ship.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Viena">Vienna</reg> 22 April</em>, His Imperial Majesty is shortly expected here, several vessels from <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> with his goods are on the way, one of which was cast away upon the <em>Danube</em>. Here are great preparations for him. Four gates with Towers of the old Romish way are building with <unclear>Triumparches</unclear> and other antiquities; the Nobility, Gentry, and Burgomasters are to meet him in three Regiments on <reg orig="horse-back">horseback</reg> in arms, and 150 brass guns are planted on the <reg orig="wals">walls</reg> to be shot off at his <reg orig="enterance">entrance</reg>. The <reg orig="Emperors">Emperor's</reg> Ministers sent into <em>Bohemia</em> are returned with the money they were sent to demand.</p>

<p><i><em>Bremen 21 May</em>. Our troubles increase here, Drums beat, and Gen. <em>Coningsmark</em> who since he took these Suburbs hath seized on other passes and <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> by force or craft, and intends to block it up round, and he<pb n="11" /> is <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to <em>Staden</em>, and arms all he can. They have sent to their <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> States of the Empire for assistance. An Ambassador from <em>Muscovy</em> past here last week with about 30 followers towards the <em>Hague</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 6 May.</i></head> 

<p><i><em>Cowes 4 May</em>. The English ships met ten sail of French near the <em>Conquet</em>, took 5 and pursued the rest, The Brest pirates are rife abroad, who lately took an English ship bound for <em>Morlem</em> laden with <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> cloth for <em>London</em>. Yesterday Gen. <em>Blake</em> with the English Fleet was under sail in <em>Stoaks Bay</em>, and put forth to Sea, towards the Downs, some in <em>Portsmouth</em> will suddenly be ready to follow them.</i></p>

<p><em>Deale 4 May</em>. Here are arrived a great number of our English men of War, more are expected <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>; the general <reg orig="Rendezvouses">Rendezvous</reg> is to be suddenly here in the <em>Downs</em> of the whole fleet. Gen. <em>Pen</em> is expected to meet them here. There are many Merchants ships here, but loath as yet to go out without a convoy until the Dutch Letters of Mart are come in.</p>

<p>A ship called <em>Anancino</em> belonging to the Merchants of <em>Genoa</em>, and an <em>Hollander</em> called the <em>Pelican</em> coming from <em><reg orig="Lisbone">Lisbon</reg></em> and <em>Cadise</em> have been cast away by storm in the <em>Sicilian</em> Sea, with 15 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of gold. The French are preparing at <em>Toulon</em> 6 ships of war, &amp; 6 Galleys to <reg orig="releive">relieve</reg> <em>Rosa</em>. Ships are making ready at <em>Rochel</em> and in <em><reg orig="Britany">Brittany</reg></em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them, but they fear the English will keep them in.</p>

<p>The Peace between the <em>English</em> and the <em>Dutch</em>, and <em>Danes</em>, made alterations in the Assembly at <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em>, where the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Montecuculi</em> is arrived from <em>Sweadland</em>, with a message to far from pleasing, as hath caused them to rise, and he is returning back to <em>Sweadland</em> by <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Upsal">Upsala</reg> 8 April</em>, It is now like to be long before my Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> returns, for he hath concluded the Peace in behalf of <em>England</em> with the Queen of <em><reg orig="Sweaden">Sweden</reg></em>, to as much her and their joy, as ours. The Articles are all agreed and engrossing fair to be sealed and delivered on both sides, whereby you, and we, and all the world may see how the Lord doth wonderfully own <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> late Government and that her alterations and now settlement is of God; The Queen professeth she is glad to see it accomplished before she <reg orig="laies">lays</reg> down her Crown. It is thought that the Ceremonies of the Prince <reg orig="Palatines">Palatine's</reg> Coronation<pb n="12" /> will be about <em>June</em> or <em>July</em> next, after which the Queen will take possession of the Isle of <em>Ocland</em>, and other Lands that were given to him for his maintenance as Heir apparent of the Crown, which he is to return to her upon her demission of the Government, all other Estates wherewith she hath gratified divers Noblemen of the Court, are likewise to be restored to her. The Earl <em>Magnum de la Gardie</em> hath already <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg> the Isle of <em>Orsel</em> to her, worth 100000 Livers <em>per an</em>. Here are 40 men of war ready and 30000 <em><reg orig="Sweads">Swedes</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 8 May.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from the <em>Hague</em> in <em>Holland</em> is advertised, that on the (7 <em>May</em>, that is) 27 <em>April</em> on the English account, the States General received an express from their Ambassadors in <em>England</em>, with the Ratification of Peace subscribed <em>OLIVER</em>. P. sealed with the great Seal of <em>Engl</em>. in a silver and guilt box. The 28 <em>April</em> it was appointed to be proclaimed, and the Lords States concluded a Thanksgiving day to be kept with great expressions of joy.</p>

<p>The 27 <em>April</em>, An Envoy from the great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> (that is the Emperor of <em>Russia</em>) with about 20 followers came to the <em>Hague</em> desiring audience by the States General.</p>

<p><em>Dover 4 May</em>, There hath been a great uproar at St. <em>Mallo</em> in <em>France</em> upon the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of their ships lately taken by the English, they have <reg orig="barborously">barbarously</reg> assaulted the English Merchants and Factors in their houses, <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> their goods, and wounded some of them; the King hearing of it sent orders presently to command the English to be protected. We have a squadron of ships gone that way. There were lately two Spanish <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> in a storm put into the little Sea near <em>Guienna</em>, sent some men <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg> to steal some Cattle, which the people discovering fell on them, killed two and forced the rest to swim for their lives, and by the help of some Vessels they <reg orig="stil">still</reg> pursued, and the next morning assaulted the <em>Spaniards</em>, and though they were well armed, yet in a short time <reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> themselves of both their <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, We hear that an Ambassador from the King of <em>Spain</em> is arrived at <em>Paris</em>, whereupon it is suspected there are great <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> for a peace between those two Crowns. It is believed that the French King will shortly marry after his <reg orig="annointing">anointing</reg> and Coronation, as some are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to match with the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, &amp; others with others<pb n="13" /> from Italy, and other parts. Some have been so bold, as to offer him the late King of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> daughter; but neither she, nor her Mother, nor Brother <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em>, are like to stay long in <em>France</em>. Deputies have been several times with the King from the Protestants in <em>France</em>, about their <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>; to whom he hath lately <reg orig="shewn">shown</reg> much <reg orig="favor">favour</reg>, which hath brought much joy to them but the <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits</reg> are exceedingly troubled at it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday. 9 May.</i></head>

<p>This day His Highness the Lord Protector sate with his Council, and they were private upon weighty business.</p>

<p><em>Paris 1 May</em>. On Sunday last, the <reg orig="Water-men">Watermen</reg> of the Parish of St <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>, went to the Lord Chancellor to demand their Curate, who by the <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits'</reg> instigation was apprehended for Preaching Sedition, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg>, That if he was not set free and restored to his place, they would set on fire all the houses of those Wolves (the <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits</reg>) that seek to worry him. The Chancellor admonished them to take heed, how they attempt any such thing, and promised them, That he would acquaint the King with their demands.</p>

<p>Those of <em>Sorbonne</em>, and most of the Curates of this City, have met together, and resolved, That no <reg orig="Jesuite">Jesuit</reg>, nor any other Monk shall be permitted to Preach in their Parishes.</p>

<p>The King gave an Ordinance, signed by his own hand to Monsieur <em>De Beaumont</em>, Governor of St. <em>Germans</em>, to receive some moneys of the <reg orig="Superintendant">Superintendent</reg>, or chief Master of the Exchequer; he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> it to Monsieur <em>Serpiant</em> the said Master of Exchequer, who told him, That he neither knew that writing, nor the hand that had subscribed it. Report hereof was made to the King, who the same day demanded of him himself, whether he knew not the hand that subscribed that Ordinance, which to his Majesty he could not deny, whereupon the King asked him, Why he did then refuse to pay it; his answer was, That there was no monies in His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Coffers: His Majesty told him, That he knew there was money enough for that, and how it should be disposed of: And Cardinal <em>Mazarin</em>, who indeed was the cause of his not receiving it, seeing the, King so earnest upon his Interest, and fearing his <reg orig="favor">favour</reg> by the King, the said <em>Beaumont</em> was paid.</p><pb n="14" />

<p>Here is talk of Propositions for a Truce with <em>Spain</em> for ten years.</p>

<p>Three days since, the King, Queen, and Duke <em>D' Anjou</em> did sup together, and that evening His Majesty did dance the great Ballet, where the late Queen of <em>England</em>, and <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> her Son were present, but <em>Mazarin</em> was not there.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Thurin">Turin</reg>, 25 April, 1654</em>. The Marshal <em>De Grancey</em> is gathering of his forces together, who are to be 330 foot companies, and 120 Troops of horse, besides the 3000 Irish who are quartered in <em>Dauphine</em>, and as many French raised by way of recruits, and a thousand Savoyards, whom the Duke of <em>Savoy</em> levies now, to <reg orig="adde">add</reg> to his former forces. According to the order, the said Marshal hath received from the King of <em>France</em>, every Troop of Horse is to be of 46 men, with the Officers, and the Foot companies 40.</p>

<p><em>La Bassee, 3 May</em>. The <em>Lorrain</em> forces, still quartered a league off of this place, are preparing to march to their <reg orig="randezvous">rendezvous</reg>, as soon as they hear that Duke <em>Francis</em> is arrived at <em><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg></em>. The Archduke <em>Leopold</em> hath likewise commanded all the Spanish forces in <em>Flanders</em> to march to their <reg orig="randezvous">rendezvous</reg>.</p>

<p><em>Paris, 29 April alias 9 May</em>. The 4 instant, <em>Don Francisco Cotinho</em>, the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador here, had audience of their Majesties, to whom he imparted the news of a victory the <em>Portugal</em> fleet hath gotten upon the <em>Hollanders</em> in <em><reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>; and of the taking of <em>Reclif</em> from them with other adjacent places. The Marquis <em>Pallavicini</em>, the Commonwealth of <em>Genoa's Envole</em> here had likewise audience that day of their Majesties, and the <em>Italian Comedy</em> acted again, that night before them. The fifth, their Majesties, with the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Brother, the Cardinal, and all the Court, went from hence for <em>Fountainbleau</em>, whither, having dined at <em>Essone</em>, they arrived that night.</p>

<p>If <em>John Eveley</em> of <em>Stourton</em>, in the County of <em>Wilis</em>, be yet living in this Nation, let him know, That his Father is dead, and unless he appear to claim and possess the Living of his deceased Father, his distressed Wife and Children, will be owner thereof, and suffer extremity. And all friends and Acquaintances of his, to whose hands this may come, are desired to acquaint him herewith.</p><pb n="15" />

<p>This day the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Spain</em> had audience by His Highness at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, whither he was attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, in his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Coach.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 10 May.</i></head>

<p>There is a groundless report of Mr. <em>John Lilburne</em> being <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> and executed at Jersey; where indeed he is prisoner. But that he hath been executed or <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, is false. His Highness and Council are about <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Government of <em>Jersey</em>, because all the Jurates (except <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one) have been lately turned out, and the Judge there cannot sit without seven, at the least; so that at present there is no jurisdiction for a Court to sit there. And this is not any thing relating to Mr. <em>Lilburn</em>, when it is done, but for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Government of the Island.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, 3 May</em>. General <em>Monk</em>, hath had meetings with a Council of Officers, and we are in preparations against the forces from <em>England</em> come, to be ready to march into the Field after Col. <em>Morgan</em>, who hath so frighted the enemy in the Hills, that they durst not venture to come out, but have found a way through to the Hills to get Provisions, which we wonder how they came by. <em>Middleton</em> hath, we hear, sent a Messenger to the Islands, to double their Guards. Some Scotch Towns have made stay of a few passengers, but not considerable: We have taken a few <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> people that were going towards the Hills. There hath been great <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in the North of <em>Scotland</em>: There hath been lately no considerable actions, but two or three small skirmishes with parties.</p>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> is with the Fleet in the Downs; Letters from Spain and France, both say they are afraid of them. General Pen is near ready to return to the Fleet.</p>

<p>The business of the Law goes on a pace, which will be to the great ease of the Nation in regulating the course of the Law, that it may be with much Justice, Ease, and Speed.</p>

<p>The Dutch have had Peace proclaimed, and a day of Thanksgiving kept.</p>

<p>There is Extant,</p>

<p>A brief Explication of the last 50 Psalms, by David Dickson. Sold by Tho. Johnson at the Golden Key in <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> <reg orig="Curch-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Lost out of a Meadow from Mr. Satter <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> of <unclear>Ashton</unclear> in <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> Parish in Northamptonshire, on Thursday 20 April, 1654, One <unclear><!-- apprix. 5 characters --></unclear> brown Gelding, about seven years old, with a little Blaze down the Forehead, and a white <unclear>stripe</unclear> on the Nose, two white Rings about the bottom of his Ears, one black Eye and the other white, and three white Feet; he had all his Paces <unclear>excellent</unclear> well, <unclear><!-- approx. 13 characters --></unclear> Hand-Gallop: Whosoever shall bring tidings either to Mr. Satter <unclear><!-- approx. 14 characters --></unclear>, or to Mr. King at the Rose in Smithfield, near the Sheep-pens, London, shall have 40 s. for their pains.</p>

<p>There was yesterday a white Bag with divers Papers and Writings in it, lost as it is supposed, upon the way between Stratford Langton in Essex, and Moor-gate, London: If the same be found and brought by any person to Mr. <reg orig="Carters">Carter's</reg> house at the lower-end of Aldermanbury, London, there shall be good content given to the party for finding and bringing thereof.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>