<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState232">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 232</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1"><reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Proceedings</head>

<head level="3">OF</head>

<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="3">In <em>England, Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="3">From Thursday the 2 of <em>March</em> To Thursday the 9 day of <em>March</em>. 1653.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>
 
<hr />

<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbison</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1653.</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 23 February. 1653.</i></head>

<p>This day his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector consulted again with Mr. <em>Owen</em>, Mr. <em>Lockier</em>, Mr. <em>Sydrach Simpson</em>, Mr. <em>Nye</em>, and divers other Ministers of the word of God; and many things were under consideration, for suppressing of all <reg orig="prophane">profane</reg>, scandalous and ignorant Ministers, and provision to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> made for those that are godly; though in things indifferent, they differ in form.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors being shortly to have their audience, and other Ambassadors also coming from <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Princes; the great room at the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg> was Ordered to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> made ready, and is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> hung with rich hangings. And <i>What shall one answer <pb n="1" />the </i>(Ambassadors and) <i>Messengers of the Nations.</i> Surely the Lord Protector hath a sweet word from God; <i>That the Lord hath founded <em>Zion</em>, and the poor of his people shall trust in him,</i> Isa. 14.32.</p>

<p>This day was published an Ordinance by His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector with advice of his Council, for reviving the jurisdiction of the County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em>, and for holding an Assizes there to this effect.</p>

<p>That all <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> and Jurisdictions belonging to the County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em> and the Inhabitants thereof, be, and are hereby revived and continued, as fully and amply to all intents and purposes, as the same were at any time before the tenth day of <em>October</em> last. And that all actions as well <reg orig="reall">real</reg> as <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, and all other Actions <reg orig="mixt">mixed</reg> or otherwise, Pleas, Precepts, Writs, <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg>, Demurrers, <reg orig="Recognizances">Recognisances</reg>, Fines, Recoveries, and all other Proceedings, matters and things, of what nature or quality soever, now depending in any Court, within the said County <em>Palatine</em>, or there commenced or prosecuted since the said tenth day of <em>October</em> shall be and stand revived, continued, and of full force and effect in the Law, to all intents, construction and purposes. And that all <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg>, Pleas, Demurrers and Proceedings in every such Action, Actions, Suits, <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> or Plaints, which were there depending the said tenth day of <em>October</em> last, or commenced or prosecuted there at any time since, shall stand good and effectual and be proceeded in according to the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> of the Nation, and the proceedings used within the said Country <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster.</em></p>

<p>And it is further Ordained that <em>Matthew Hales</em>, one of the Justices of the Court of Common-Pleas at <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Hugh Windam</em> Sergeant at Law, shall be Justices of Assizes and <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> delivery within the said County <em>Palatine</em>, and that the said Justices, or either of them, shall and may act, do and perform all matters and things, as well concerning <reg orig="criminall">criminal</reg> as Common-Pleas, and all other Pleas and <reg orig="Proces">Process</reg> whatsoever, in such manner and form as any other Justice or Justices of Assizes at <em>Lancaster</em> have usually acted, done and performed at any time heretofore, And the Commissioner for keeping the <reg orig="Seale">Seal</reg> of the said County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em> hereafter named is hereby <reg orig="Authorized">Authorised</reg> <pb n="2" />and appointed to issue forth to the said Justices, for the execution of the premises, such Commission or Commissions as in such cases have been heretofore in the said County <em>Palatine</em>, used and accustomed. And that <em>Tomas Fell</em> <reg orig="Esq">Esq.</reg>; be, and is hereby made and appointed Commissioner for keeping of the Seal of the said County <em>Palatine</em> of <em>Lancaster</em>, and shall have all such powers as any Chancellor of Commissioner for keeping the Seal of the said County <em>Palatine</em> hath formerly lawfully used and exercised concerning the same, till further order.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Brazil 13 Febru.</i></head>

<p>The seventh instant; the <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> of <em>Beffort</em> hath agreed, that if in a fortnight they were not <reg orig="releeved">relieved</reg>, the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> should issue out with Bag and Baggage, and that the <em>Comte de Lasuse</em> should with his forces be <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> in the King of <em>France's</em> service and should be Lieut. Gen. in the Army of <em>Champagne</em>, and the <em>Comte de Charlo</em> the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Cousin is to be <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> in the said Town of <em>Beffort</em>. The Treaty of <em>Brissac</em> which the Marshal <em>de la Ferte</em>, the Baron <em>de la Melon</em>, the Lord Intendent <em>de Morun</em>, and Captain the <em>Besman</em> have concluded and subscribed of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> side, hath also been ratified by Prince <em>Harcourt</em>, the Maj. Gen. <em>Charlevois</em> and the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, upon condition to bring it to effect when the promised sums of monies shall be paid.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From Luxembourg 18. Feb.</i></head>

<p>The French are 5 or 6000 strong towards <em>Sedan</em> and did intend upon intelligence of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of the Castle of <em>Stenay</em>, which is since discovered, to have made themselves Masters of that place.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> 24. Febru.</i></head>

<p>The Inhabitants of <em>Elsatia</em> and <em>Switzerland</em> are very much displeased at the <em>French</em> in those parts who live at <reg orig="descretion">discretion</reg> and do plunder all the Towns and Villages they can come into, those of <em>Montbeliard</em> and of <em>Brisack</em> doing also the like. So that it seemeth that they do intend to ruin and desolate the whole <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. Some <reg orig="daies">days</reg> ago is passed through this City an Ambassador of the King of <em>Denmark</em> to <reg orig="goe">go</reg> for <em>England</em> and congratulate the Lord Protector.</p>

<p><i>From Antwerp 25. Feb.</i> We have here certain advice from <em>Spain</em> that the Fleet coming from the Indies is safely arrived at <em>Cadiz</em>.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>From the Texel 16 (alias 26.) Feb.</i></head>

<p>Captain <em>Oomke</em> is come in here bringing along with him a prize being a Flute laden with goods esteemed worth 30000 Guilders. A Freebooter of <em>Enchusen</em> hath also recovered before the <em>Ulie</em> a prize taken by the English coming from <em>Norvege</em>. This week are arrived here many ships from <em>France</em> with two ships coming from the <em>Caribe</em> Islands. There are also three ships in this road making ready to go for <em>Brazil</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 3. March.</i></head>

<p>This day the three Lords Ambassadors from the States General of the United Provinces, <em>viz.</em> the Lord <em>Beverling</em>, the Lord <em>Newport</em>, and the Lord <em>Yongstal</em>, passed through the Cities of <em>London &amp; Westminster</em> to Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> house in the Palace yard at <em>Westminster</em>, in His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Coach, with Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Mr. of the Ceremonies, and Mr. <em><reg orig="Claypoole">Claypole</reg></em> Gentlemen of the Horse, and divers other Gentlemen, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Footmen attending on both sides the Coach, and also the Coaches and Gentlemen of the Lord Ambassador of the King of <em>Portugal</em>, and the Resident of the King of <em>France</em>, and above 50 Coaches more, of divers of the English Nobility and Gentry, whereof above 20 of the said Coaches were with six horses, and <reg orig="neare">near</reg> 20 of them with four horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>, and the rest with two good Horses and Furniture; and as soon as they alighted in the Palace yard they were saluted with a noise of Trumpets.</p>

<p>The letters from <em>Holland</em> say, that their judgement there is, that the Treaty of Peace between the two Nations is so far advanced, that there is very few <reg orig="doe">do</reg> make any doubt of it, since all the Provinces sent their consent thereunto to the Lords the States General, amongst whom those of <em>Groning</em> were the last, and so the Ratification by the States was then sent to the Lord <em>Beverling</em> to <em>England</em>. And upon his answer to the States Ambassadors were chosen to go to <em>England</em> to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Peace. And accordingly the Lords <em>Newport</em> and <em>Yongstal</em> were commissionated, there were two others chosen, but they excused, and after them one <em>Yong</em>, who because of much business and other reasons, had leave to stay (at least for a time) and power was given to the Lords <em>Beverling, Newport</em>, and <em>Yongstal</em> to conclude and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Peace with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p><i>Hague 26 Febr.</i> <em>Mr. Stocker</em> the 22 Instant had audience of <pb n="4" />the Lords States, in the name of the Protestant Cantons of <em>Switzerland</em>, offering (as is reported) his best <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to reconcile the differences between them and <em>England</em>, if there <reg orig="remaine">remain</reg> yet any they shall differ upon.</p>

<p>This day divers Orders passed in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Petitions presented to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> referred Mr. <em><reg orig="Smiths">Smith's</reg></em> Petition and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> others to be examined by Committees.</p>

<p>His Highness appointed that the Lords Ambassadors from the States General of the United Provinces should have <reg orig="publick">public</reg> audience on the morrow, and Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Mr. of the Ceremonies had orders to attend their Lordships to the Banqueting house at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> accordingly.</p>

<p>And the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house was Ordered to be made ready against the morrow morning for that purpose.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Whitby</em> in the North of England is certified, that the Phenix <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath sent thither a prize which she took at Sea, a small man of War, which hath in her only three guns and 30 prisoners.</p>

<p>Another small prize also was taken further Northward.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em> February 20. The Enemy are divided into divers parties to raise their assigned Levies, keeping themselves on parts <reg orig="neare">near</reg> to the <em><reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg></em> for their security; and from thence summon in the Country for Horse and Foot, whom they threaten with ruin for not accomplishing their unjust Demands.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Glengairne">Glencairn</reg></em> is to command all the Forces levied in these Shires of <em>Murray</em>, and so Northward, he with 80 Horse and 200 Foot keeps near the Hills, that upon notice of the approach of any of our Forces they may secure themselves in the <reg orig="unaccessible">inaccessible</reg> bounds. Our Horse Scouts now and then glean up some of them, having lately taken among others a notorious Rogue who threatened to burn divers of the Inhabitants houses who are serviceable to the Garrison.</p>

<p><i>Leith Febru. 25.</i> <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> levies are most certainly spoiled and the people wearied in their respects to them, despairing of <reg orig="helpe">help</reg> from <em>Holland</em>, and a report amongst them, that a Gentleman (their friend) in <em>Fife</em> had lately a Vision, in which he <pb n="5" />was commanded by one in form of a Man to speed to <em>Glencairn</em> and tell him, that he must decline his course which will be destructive to him, and all under him, and then vanished. The Gentleman neglected it, and then had a second vision in which he was sentenced to be dumb for his neglect, which he now is, and certifies the same under his hand, as they report: This latter prevails much on the vulgar <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, and the two former hath influence on all their Army, that they are much dejected and sad. <em>Athol</em> is about <em>Glenlyar</em>, and hath with him about 300 Horse and Foot, he hath sent forth the fiery <reg orig="Cresses">Crosses</reg>, but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> little observed, some of his men are gone to <em>Badgenoth</em>, where <reg orig="its">it's</reg> informed <em>Glencairn</em> is.</p>

<p>The old Laird of <em>Glenusq</em>; at <em>Balloch</em> hath sent for, and accepted of a protection from the Governor of St. <em>Johnstons</em>, and hath engaged to keep all quiet in his Bounds for doing any prejudice to the Commonwealth: <em>Athol</em> was there to demand his House to be demolished (as <em><reg orig="Weyms">Weems</reg></em> is) but the old Gentleman (of eighty years of Age) absolutely refused.</p>

<p>On Tuesday last Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> with what Horse <em>Athol</em> could make, marched towards <em>Monteith</em> of <em>Lenox</em>, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived in a design for the South.</p>

<p>The 22 instant there was one of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniel's</reg></em> Regiment hanged at St. <em>Johnstons</em> for running to <em>Athol</em>, who was taken at <em>Dunkel</em> the last week, and another was tied up to the <reg orig="Gollows">Gallows</reg>, who was intercepted in his running to <em>Athol</em>. There are some others that ran from the same Regiment to <em>Athol</em>, who were taken at Dunkel, but preserved by Articles. Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em>, and Commissary General <em><reg orig="Whaleys">Whaley's</reg></em> Regiments of Horse are come up hither, and will be a very seasonable supply.</p>

<p>From <em>Milford</em> Haven the 28 <em>February</em>. Here are some lately come from <em>Ireland</em>, who tell us no more as for news, but that according to the late Treaty made with <em>Mac O Mortague</em>, there are great numbers of Irish ready to take shipping for <em>Flanders</em>, to serve the King of <em>Spain</em>, but there are still small parties of Tories, who lie lurking in the Woods and Bogs, and do much disquiet the peace of the Country, but so small, that there are scarce twenty together of them in three parts of <em>Ireland</em>, which is still in great want of people to inhabit those parts.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is safe arrived in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em>, 2 <em>March</em>. Two days since all the Merchants ships as were here, and in <em>Dover</em> Road, set sail, having a fair wind to go for the southward; also several convoys to bring them to their distinct places. There hath been likewise some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> here, but are all gone again Westward, where we hear our Fleet rideth still near St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em> point, by the Isle of <em>Wight</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday, March 4.</i></head>

<p>By Letters came from beyond the Seas as followeth.</p>

<head level="3">From<i>Turin, 6 February. 1653.</i></head>

<p>The disorders and excesses which the French forces do commit daily at <em>Orbazano</em>, as well as in other places thereabouts, are so great, that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> people have been forced in many places to take up Arms against them, whereby some have been killed of both sides, and great complaints have been made thereupon, being observed, That the French do very slightly their word and engagements; in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the Marshal of <em>Grancey</em> hath according to his last order received from the Court of <em>France</em>, a supply of 26 Troops of Horse, and 14 Companies of Foot, and maketh 40 other Companies march towards the <em>Dolphin</em>, and as many to <em>Pignerol</em>, the rest remaining in their Winter quarters, staying for the next news from <em>France</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From <em>Rome</em>.</head>

<p>The Pope hat sent his Letters through all <em>Italy</em>, to command Prayers to be made for the good success of the Peace between <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em>. His Holiness hath banished his Nephew the Cardinal <em>Pamphilio</em>, and will confiscate his Revenue, and Goods, because as it is reported he hath revealed his secrets concerning <em>Spain</em> and <em>Portugal</em>.</p>

<head level="3">From <i>Paris, 21 February.</i></head>

<p>The marriage of the Princess of <em>Loves</em> of <em>Carigan</em>, Daughter of Prince <em>Thomas</em> of <em>Savoy</em>, with the <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg> of <em>Boden</em>, hath been celebrated this week in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> if <em>Soissons</em>, the Prince <em>Eugene</em> her Brother having married her in the name of the said <reg orig="Marquess">Marquis</reg>. The Prince of <em>Conti</em> who is at last returned here the 16 instant, hath been received in the Louvre by their Majesties, with a great demonstration of joy: The next day he hath been <pb n="7" />most nobly feasted by the Cardinal, and at night had the sport of the Ballet, called, of <em>Proverbs</em>, which was danced before him. It is certainly believed, that he is fully agreed to marry with the <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg> of the said Cardinal, one of the <em>Martinezzi</em>, and that the eldest sister is to be married afterward to the Duke of <em>Candale</em>. The said Prince of <em>Conti</em> as is reported, shall command this year the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army in the <em>Roussillon</em>, upon condition, that he shall resign all his Church Livings to the said Cardinal.</p>

<p>The great Royal Ballet of Thesis, her Weddings, a very costly <reg orig="peece">piece</reg>, all sorts of persons having been sent for out of <em>Italy</em>, as Singers, Dancers, and the like, is deferred till <em>Easter</em>.</p>

<p>This day the Lords Ambassadors from the States of the seven United Provinces of Holland, Zealand, &amp;c. had audience by his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, in the Banqueting house at Whitehall, which was hung with extraordinary rich hangings, and divers Lords, Knights and Gentlemen, Officers of the Army, and thousands of people in the said room present, and all the Galleries round the room, full of people; besides many in the Courts and other places about that could not get in.</p>

<p>They were fetched from their lodging in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard at Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Willams">Willams's</reg></em>, by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Mr. of the Ceremonies; and with him two of the Lords of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, <em>Strickland</em> and <em>Jones</em>, who were all three with the three Ambassadors, brought in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Footmen, besides the <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassador's</reg> Footmen to run by the Coach; and after the said Coach followed a great many Coaches belonging to <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Lords and others, most with six horses, in which rid <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons of Honour, and the Gentlemen belonging to the Ambassadors.</p>

<p>There were set at the upper-end of the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> house at Whitehall, a chair of State, very rich, for his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and by it on the right hand, three rich high <reg orig="stooles">stools</reg> for the Ambassadors, and a place railed in covered with Carpets, and the ground spread with carpets, wherein the chair and <reg orig="stooles">stools</reg> were set.</p>

<p>First his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector came into the Banqueting <pb n="8" />House with the Lords of the Council, and Mr. <em>Thurlow</em> Secretary of State, and Mr. <em><reg orig="Claypoole">Claypole</reg></em> Gentleman of the Horse, at whose coming in, all the people put off their Hats and stood bare, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> put off his Hat to the people, and went up to the Chair, but did not sit down in it at all, all the while, neither before, at, nor after the Audience. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> stood on the left side of the <reg orig="Chaire">Chair</reg> with his Hat on, and the Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary, and Mr. <em><reg orig="Claypoole">Claypole</reg></em> were within the <reg orig="Railes">Rails</reg>, some on the one side and some on the other, all of them bare all the while, in this Equipage His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> waited a short time, for the reception of the Ambassadors, and a lane was made for the Ambassadors to come up to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> from the one end of the Room to the other.</p>

<p>So soon as the Ambassadors were come into the Room they put off their Hats to salute His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> did the like to them, and so again a second and a third time as they came nearer to His Highness, and when they came up to the place where the Chair, <reg orig="Stooles">Stools</reg>, and Carpets were, where His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector was, with the Lords of the Council and after a low salute of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Lords Ambassadors each to other; the Lord Protector put on his Hat, and the Ambassadors put on their Hats also, the Lords of the Council and all others being bare, His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Ambassadors all standing up.</p>

<p>Then the Lord <em>Yongstal</em> made a Speech to His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> made presently another Speech to the Ambassadors. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and the Ambassadors often in both the Speeches putting off their hats to salute each other, upon some words of Protestation of Affection of the one Commonwealth to the other, and desire of firm Union.</p>

<p>The substance of the <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> speech was, To declare the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> of their coming, to renew the old friendship which hath been for many years, and to make and <reg orig="setle">settle</reg> a more firm Peace and <reg orig="Aliance">Alliance</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever before heretofore. And that to this purpose their Superiors, the Lords the States of the United Provinces of the <reg orig="Neatherlands">Netherlands</reg> do all of them agree and consent to the agreement of peace between us and them, which they their Ambassadors Extraordinary are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg>, desiring a speedy <reg orig="sessation">cessation</reg> of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and that all acts of hostility may <pb n="9" />cease on both sides; So that the chiefest thing that is yet behind is <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to explain some things in some of the Articles.</p>

<p>Afterwards His Highness and the Ambassadors saluted each other, and the Ambassadors returned, three times turning back to salute His Highness, and His Highness then also staying for that purpose, saluted them; and they being gone down, His Highness with the Lords of the Council, returned also by the Privy door, through which he had come thither.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 24 Feb.</i> We have taken <em>Kildrummy</em> the Earl of <em><reg orig="Mars">Mar's</reg></em> house, who after he had made it a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> pretended to be surprised by the Enemy to deceive us. One Capt. <em>Thompson</em>, and Lieut. Col. <reg orig="Ramsies">Ramsey's</reg> Lieutenant came down with five of six more into the Lowlands to plunder Horses, and Lieut. <em>Hellin</em> Lieut. to Major <em>Bramston</em> having intelligence thereof marched forth with seven more Dragoons with him, out of the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Thornston</em>, pursued them ten miles through the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, killed one of them, and brought the rest Prisoners to <em>Dunotter</em> Castle.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Summons to the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Kildrummy</em>.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p>The command of the Forces in the North of <em>Scotland</em> being committed to my conduct, I thought good to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> that yesterday meeting the Forces commanded by the Lord <em><reg orig="Glencarn">Glencairn</reg></em>, it pleased God that we <reg orig="disperst">dispersed</reg> and totally routed them, and understanding that you had possessed the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>, to the great disturbance of the peace of this Nation, I marched hither, and do strictly summon you upon sight hereof to deliver unto me the said house of <em>Kildrummy</em>, with all the Arms and Ammunition therein for the use of His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and in case you <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> obedience thereunto, I shall give you liberty to go to your own homes, and live at peace, you <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> that you will act nothing prejudicial to the English Army, but on the contrary, if there happen the least effusion of blood unto any under my command, then expect no mercy. Your answer I expect within half and hour, and remain <i>Yours as I find you, <em>Tho. Morgan.</em> For M. J. <em>Wil. Drummond</em> Officer in chief within the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>. Feb. 22. 1653.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Major <em><reg orig="Drummonds">Drummond's</reg></em> Answer.</i></head>

<p>Sir, I received yours, and find your Propositions very hard without order from my Lord General, <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> Sir, if you will <pb n="10" />be pleased to suffer me to send one to my Lord General, and upon his return we shall render the house if they come not again on Monday at night for our relief, we shall march with our Horse and Arms to any part of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army in <em>Scotland</em>, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> the place be made useless for any <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and for the effusion of blood, we take God to witness, yours shall be the fault: No further but <i>Yours as time shall produce, <em>Wil. Drummond</em>. For Col. <em>Morgan</em>, Commander of the English forces.</i> <em>Kildrummy</em>, 22 Feb. 1653.</p>

<p>Sir, I have considered your Answer, and cannot grant your desires, yet so tender am I of shedding blood, in case you be not satisfied with the terms I offered, if you please to send one or two Officers fully authorised to Treat in order to your sudden surrender, I shall rather deal <reg orig="honorably">honourably</reg>, then use cruelty, I expect your Answer by this Bearer, and am <i>Yours as occasion shall serve, <em>Tho. Morgan</em>. For Major <em>Drummond</em>, Officer in chief in the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>.</i></p>

<p>Sir, I have received yours, and am as <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to shed blood at this time as any shall be. Sir, I thought you would have suffered me to have sent to my Lord General, because I being put here by him, and on such a sudden to surrender, I believe no man of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, but might esteem me the basest of men; but however for the matter of Treaty, if you please to send down to the gate one or two, I shall wait on them there to hear your will. No more but that I am <i>Yours to meeting <em>W. Drummond</em>. For Col. <em>Morgan</em>, Commander in chief of the English Forces in the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</i></p>

<p>Sir, according to your intimation I have sent Lieut. Colonel <em>Simmons</em>, and Major <em>Knight</em> to Treat, in order to your sudden surrender of the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>, and <reg orig="what ever">whatever</reg> they conclude, shall be made good by me. <i><em>Tho. Morgan</em>. For Major <em>Wil. Drummond</em>, Officer in chief within the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>.</i></p>

<p>The Commissioners could not agree, so that the Treaty broke, but the next morning <em>Drummond</em> sent his Drum with this following Letter.</p>

<p>Sir, I though good to show you that it is but a short time betwixt Monday and Thursday, and because we have bedding, and some other things which we brought from the Country people, <pb n="11" />and did <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> to give them back at out leaving the place, before which time we can hardly get done; if you Sir, think this fit, let us meet, and condescend on Articles, and to such time I rest <i>Yours as occasion offers, <em>Wil. Drummond</em>. Kildrummy, 23 Feb. 1653. For Col. <em>Morgan</em>, Commander in chief of the English forces in the North. These.</i></p>

<p>Sir, I perceive that you still persist in your <reg orig="delayes">delays</reg>, but this may suffice you, that I shall not afford you any longer tome to march <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> at ten <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>, and because your redelivery of the <reg orig="Countreys">Country's</reg> Goods, shall not cause you to Dispute. In case those whom I send to Treat, and conclude, and you agree, I shall give you liberty to leave one <reg orig="behinde">behind</reg>, to see the Goods disposed on according to your engagement, who shall have free liberty to act accordingly. I expect your immediate Answer, and remain <i>Yours, if you be your own, <em>Tho. Morgan</em>. For Major <em>Drummond</em>, Commander in chief within the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>.</i></p>

<p>Sir, I received yours, and if we agree on Articles, I shall march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> by ten <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>; so expecting those whom you send to Treat at the place where we met last night, where I shall attend them. I rest Sir, <i>Yours as before. Kildrummy, 22 Febr. 1653. For col. <em>Morgan</em>, Commander in chief of the English forces in the North. These.</i></p>

<p>Upon which, these ensuing Articles were agreed upon, and Cornet <em>Burbom</em> was sent into the house as Hostage on our part, and Cornet <em>Gordon</em>, <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> Cornet was delivered as Hostage for the house.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Articles agreed upon for the surrender of the house of <em>Kildrummy</em>, this 23 Feb. 1653. betwixt Lieut. Col. <em>Simmons</em>, and Major <em>Knight</em>, on the behalf of the English forces. And Major <em>Wil. Drummond</em>, Governor of the foresaid house, and Cap. <em>Matthew Hambleton</em>, on the behalf of the Scotch forces.</i></head>

<p>I. That the said Governor is to march with all the forces in the said House, Arms, Ammunition, Bag, and Baggage, tomorrow morning by ten <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg>, to the nearest place where any of the Scotch Forces are, without molestation, and to have a Pass to that purpose from Colonel <em>Morgan</em>, unto whom he <pb n="12" />is to surrender the said House without any demolition, for the use of His Highness, the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>II. That the said Governor shall have liberty to leave an Officer to dispose of the Country Goods which are in the said House, either belonging to the Earl of <em>Marr</em>, or any other.</p>

<p>III. That the said Governor shall march tem miles a day, with the party under his command, except the first day, till they come at the forces, and are not to molest or trouble any of the forces belonging to His Highness, the Lord Protector, upon their march, upon any account whatsoever: For the performance whereof, each subscribed.</p>

<p>In case the Castle had not been delivered that day, neither our Horse nor Foot had been able to have continued there one night longer, the season of the year not permitting it: Neither were we able to do any good upon the House without battering Guns, which could not have come to us in a weeks time.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday, 6 March.</i></head>

<p>This day General <em>Desborow</em>, General <em>Monk</em>, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty, went towards <em>Chattam</em>, for dispatch of the <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> of the Navy now near ready. <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> were <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg>, and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> drawn out of the Regiments, to be put on board, and a gallant Fleet will presently be at a <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>. The Dutch have also 60 new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> to <reg orig="adde">add</reg> to their Fleet, which will shortly be ready. Both sides strengthen themselves as well as they can, least there should not be a conclusion at last: But it is not much doubted.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith, 28 Febr.</i> the last week Lieutenant <em>Hollin</em>, Lieut. to Major <em><reg orig="Bampstons">Bampston's</reg></em> Troop of Dragoons, having notice, That one Cap. <em>Thomson</em>, and Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Ramseys">Ramsey's</reg></em> Lieutenant, with five more of the enemy, were come down into the <em>Mearns</em>, presently mounted with seven more of the Troop, pursued them about ten miles into the Hills, and at last took them, their Horses and Arms; one of them being an Englishman, refused to take quarter, and was killed. A party of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse and Foot being before <em>Down</em> Castle, five miles from <em>Sterling</em>, Major <em>Bridges</em> went from <em>Sterling</em> with a party of 60 Horse; upon which the enemy fled, our men pursued, and about 4 miles from <em>Down</em>, came in sight of them. We took <reg orig="onely">only</reg> six prisoners, <pb n="13" />and about 19 or 20 Horse, Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> was there, and escaped very narrowly, as did Cap. <em>Hamilton</em> whose Horse was taken but he escaped over a Bog. The 10 of <em>March</em> is appointed for the Enemies great <reg orig="Randesvouz">Rendezvous</reg> about <em>Badgenoth</em>. <em>Montross</em> and Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> came with orders to <em>Athol</em> when he flighted <em>Weems</em>, to prepare all the force he could against that time. There was a late falling out among them, and one <em>Graham</em> shot <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Groom through the head, and <reg orig="yong">young</reg> <em>Montross</em> had like to have killed <em>Lorn</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 7 March.</i></head>

<p><i><reg orig="Bruxels">Brussels</reg> 28 Feb.</i> The Earl of <em>Garzia</em> Field Marshal General of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army pretended to the Duke of <em>Loraine</em>, that the Arch D. <em><reg orig="Leopald">Leopold</reg></em> would speak with him to treat about the Country of <em>Liege</em>, and having <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> him the 25 instant, so soon as he came into the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> the doors were shut, and the Duke apprehended by order from the King of <em>Spain</em>, his house and places where his goods and treasures were kept, were seized, his chief <reg orig="Stuart">Steward</reg>, his Secretary, and one of his <reg orig="Councellors">Counsellors</reg> apprehended, and one <em>Boule</em> his <reg orig="Favorite">Favourite</reg> a Jeweller hiding <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, was by a Citizen discovered the next day and apprehended.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Loraine</em> was kept prisoner all night in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>, desiring to speak with the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg>, it was refused him; then he writ to him, desiring a speedy Answer, which he had by word of mouth, that he should be brought to Prince <em>Thomato's</em> quarters.</p>

<p>And the next day about 10 <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> he was sent towards <em>Antwerp</em>, with 100 armed Horsemen before, and the Count <em>Garzia</em> with his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> men immediately before the Coach wherein he was with six Cavaliers with him, and 200 Horse more followed, and between this and <em>Mechelen</em> 1200 horse to secure the way, and as many more between <em>Mechelen</em> and <em>Antwerp</em>, where he was put into the Castle that night.</p>

<p>The cause of his imprisonment is by the <reg orig="Arch Dukes">Archduke's</reg> Manifesto pretended to be for <reg orig="ungratefulnesse">ungratefulness</reg>, and <reg orig="unfaithfulnesse">unfaithfulness</reg> to his Majesty of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, and his great excesses of plundering and devastations, the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> hath sent a Commission to his younger Brother Prince <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> to command the Army, and an <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> is sent to the Emperor.</p>

<pb n="14" />

<p><i>Hague 11 March.</i> It is hoped that within a few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after our Ambassadors are arrived in <em>England</em> there will be a publication of peace made. We are told here, that the Negotiation between <em>France</em> and <em>England</em> is much advanced, and that both Treaties are like to be ended at the same time. We have news here that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> must be <reg orig="packt">packed</reg> out of <em>France</em> suddenly. If the Scots had been considerable he would have gone to head them. Four of our ships have suffered <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> and are sunk by storm before <em>Enchusen</em>, but most of the men saved, we have news that the Cantons of Switzerland have (contrary to all opinions) renewed their alliance with the Crown of <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Ireland</em> confirm again that all is quiet there, and there is little want of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> but people to <reg orig="inhabite">inhabit</reg>, to <reg orig="compleate">complete</reg> a settlement of that Nation. There is a great Robber that fled from <em>England</em> is taken there, that robbed the Carriers from Sturbridge <reg orig="Faire">Fair</reg> and others, taken and imprisoned in <em>Dublin</em> Castle, who is to be sent over into <em>England</em> to be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Upsal</em> of the Treaty of the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> with the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> is certified, that the Queen hath <reg orig="onely">only</reg> five <reg orig="daies">days</reg> in the Country to visit her Mother, during which time the grand Chancellor, who had full commission was treated with, and <reg orig="progresse">progress</reg> is made in the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>. The Chancellor made some <reg orig="queeries">queries</reg> at the first meeting, but at the second had much satisfaction by the Lord <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Commission, giving him power to conclude and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> whatsoever shall be determined by the Treaty.</p>

<p>They have treated of every Article, There is great probability of a short and good issue, <reg orig="onely">only</reg> there was some demurs about the Article of an offensive and defensive War; the English being at present in wars and the <em><reg orig="Sweades">Swedes</reg></em> not.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Upsal 20 Febru.</i></head>

<p>Things <reg orig="goe">go</reg> well on here: The Queen and her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> look on <em>England</em> as much more settled under the Lord Protector <reg orig="then">than</reg> before. His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> being one whom she much <reg orig="honors">honours</reg>, and also approves of the change of the Government, she hath been in the Country, but is newly <reg orig="returne">returned</reg>, and in half a day and a night (after five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> absence making speed to us) <pb n="15" />is come back through very hard Frosts in a <reg orig="Sledg">Sledge</reg> of this Country, in which she rid as long a way as contains above fifty English miles.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, 8 March.</i></head>

<p>Several Petitions were this day received by His Highness, and orders passed therein. The Committee have finished Sir <em>Wil. Dicks</em> business, and others to be reported to the Council.</p>

<p>Several Complaints from divers places in <em>England</em>, are made of some that disturb the meetings of godly people; when these things are examined, some will be called to account.</p>

<p>The Lords Ambassadors of the United Provinces of <em>Holland</em>, &amp;c. say, That if the Articles can be engrossed in a day, they are ready to sign the Ratification of the Peace; and Commissioners are appointed by His Highness, the Lord Protector, for speedy dispatch with them.</p>

<p>There is a near conclusion also with the French Resident, Monsieur <reg orig="Berdeox">Bordeaux</reg>; who it is thought will have suddenly a Plenipotentiary power.</p>

<p>The late Queen of <em>England</em> is to depart <em>France</em>; she goes to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>, the <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> being her sister.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and the Dukes of <em>York</em>, and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, are also to depart, they intend for <em>Germany</em> to the <em>Palsgrave</em>.</p>

<p>The Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> also is to depart <em>Holland</em>, she returns to Her Son the <em>Palsgrave</em>.</p>

<p><em>Sweden</em> and <em>Switzerland</em> will <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in it, and <em>Denmark</em> not a little glad when they shall be taken in.</p>

<p><reg orig="Some thing">Something</reg> is referred by His Highness, the Lord Protector, to a Committee of the Council, to consider of, touching Religion, in order to what hath been offered by the Ministers that have so often met before His Highness.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>&#x261e; A Discourse Apologetical, wherein Lilies <reg orig="leud">lewd</reg> and loud lies in his Merlin for the year, 1654. are clearly laid open; his shameful decision of his own cause is further discovered; his shameless slanders fully refuted; and his malicious and <reg orig="murtherous">murderous</reg> <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> inciting to a general Massacre of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Ministers from his own Pen, evidently evinced, By Tho. Gataker, B.D. and Minister of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Word at Rotherhith.</p>

<p>The Life and Death of (that eminent Christian) Mr. Ignatius Jurdain, one of the Aldermen of the City of Exeter, drawn up Mr. F. Nichols, and published by Mr. Tho. Manton, Minister of Newington. Both to be sold by Tho. Newberry at his Shop at the Three Lions in <reg orig="Cornhil">Cornhill</reg>, near the Royal Exchange.</p>


<head level="2">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>