<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState237">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 237</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg></head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 6 of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. To Thursday the 13 day of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 6 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. 1653.</i></head>

<p><i>Newcastle 1 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg> 1654.</i> came thus. Some Malignants in these parts are <unclear><reg orig="puft">puffed</reg></unclear> upon a sudden, and give out they have hopes of the Scots, who are with a party come to <em>Norwood Plane</em>, within 14 miles of <em>Carlisle</em>; and some more would go to them, but that they fear the peace with <em>Holland</em>. The six <em>Hamborough</em> ships went from hence the last week. Get us but Convoys, and <reg orig="wee">we</reg> shall supply you with <reg orig="Coales">Coals</reg> good store.</p>

<p>A Petition was presented this day to the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, from divers Merchants of the City of <em>London</em>, about some particulars touching the <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>.</p>

<p>An Order lately passed touching <em>Jersey</em>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p><em>Innerness</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, March 20 thus, These parts affords little more <reg orig="newes">news</reg> of the Enemy (this week) <reg orig="then">than</reg> what I formerly gave you an account of <em>Middleton</em> and his Crew continues still in <em>Caithness</em> and <em>Sutherland</em>, in prosecution of their <reg orig="businesse">business</reg>; <em>Glengarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> with about 500 Horse and Foot marched by the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Badgenoth</em>, and faced <em>Ruthen</em>, where he sent the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Letter, and received the <reg orig="under-written">underwritten</reg> Answer; they were expected to quarter at the head of <em>Loughnesse</em> the 17th. instant, and having <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Glengary</em>, were afterward to march to <em>Middleton</em>. They expected <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> should follow them within one <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> march, of which if he failed, they feared he had deserted them. <em>Glengary</em> still threatens fire and sword to them that <reg orig="sailes">sails</reg> of answering his Warrants for Levies.</p>

<head level="3">For Cap. <em>John Hill</em> Governor of <em>Ruthen</em> Castle of <em>Badgenoth</em>.</head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p><i>The last time I was in this Country, one of my Troopers named <em>Angus <reg orig="Mac Parsons">McParsons</reg></em> being commanded to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> near the Castle, was by some of your <reg orig="Horse-men">Horsemen</reg> made Prisoner, if you will <reg orig="doe">do</reg> me the favour to release him presently, and send him to <reg orig="mee">me</reg> by this Bearer my Trumpet, I <reg orig="doe">do</reg> oblige <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> upon my <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg>, to release to you any other Prisoner of the same quality of yours, that shall happen to fall into my hands upon your desire made known unto me, who am Sir,</i></p>

<p>Your affectioned Friend and Servant, <em>GLENCAIRNE</em>.</p>

<p>15 of March, from <em>Knigxsie</em>.</p>

<head level="3">For the Earle of <em>Glencairn</em>.</head>

<p>My Lord,</p>

<p>Your Trooper is where he wants not that <reg orig="Civill">Civil</reg> Usage which you may befit his quality and Condition, neither shall, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> you have one of ours of like quality to offer in exchange for him, until which time your Lordship must excuse my Detention of him; who am, My Lord,</p>

<p><i>Your humble Servant, <em>JO. HILL</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>Ruthen-Castle, March 15. 1653,</i></p>

<p>An Ordinance was published for mending and keeping in better repair the <reg orig="High-wayes">Highways</reg> in this Nation, the substance,<pb n="2" /> That every Parish is to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> once in the year two or more <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>, to serve one whole year. A Tax to be made for the payment of such charges as shall be requisite for that work, the Justices being <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> within the several limits of their Commission. That no <reg orig="Waggon">Wagon</reg> or Cart go or travel upon the <reg orig="High-way">Highway</reg>, having any more than five Horses, or Mares, or six Oxen, and one Horse, That to any party so offending, all and every Constable hath power to stop all those that are supernumerary, or beyond the number specified, the party so offending, paying within seven <reg orig="daies">days</reg> after the <reg orig="distresse">distress</reg> or <reg orig="seasure">seizure</reg> aforesaid, the Sum of twenty shillings for each Horse or <reg orig="Oxe">Ox</reg> so distressed or <reg orig="seased">seized</reg>, and in default thereof the Officer is <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> to sell them, levy the fine and other charges he hath been at for keeping of the said Horse or Oxen, and return the overplus to the party owner of them, That any Streets or Pavements in any City or Town Corporate, shall be counted as <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg>, and each respective Scavenger to be as a Surveyor to his Parish, or Precinct: And lastly that the Act made in the time of Queen <em>Mary</em>, concerning the mending of the Causie between <em><reg orig="Shatsbury">Shaftsbury</reg></em> &amp; <em>Sherborn</em> shall be received and be in full force <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first of <em>September</em> 1662, you may see further at large by the Act <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> printed.</p>

<p><i>An Ordinance for Adjourning part of <em>Easter</em> Term, 1654.</i></p>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained, out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to Adjourn part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>; Be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That part of the said term of <em>Easter</em> now next coming be Adjourned, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em> unto the first Return of Trinity Term called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>: And all and every person or persons, which have cause, or Commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day, or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, and during the term called <em>Easter Term</em> may tarry at<pb n="3" /> their dwellings, or to where their business shall lie, without resorting any of the said Courts for that Cause, and without danger or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf. And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that the Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, giving them Authority to Adjourn the said Term of <em>Easter</em> as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the first return, called <em>Quindena Pasc&aelig;</em>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the first return of <em>Trinity Term</em>, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em> as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made as aforesaid, And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that all the Matters, Causes, and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> depending in any of the said Courts shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, <reg orig="doe">do</reg> forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the <reg orig="chiefe">chief</reg> Market Towns within their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Counties.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 7 April.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> 1 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>, <i>We have many prizes brought in hither, and the 10 instant is to be a survey of the prize goods, the value of which according to computation by some of good judgement, cannot be <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> 140000 l. sterling.</i></p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 19 March.</i> The Enemy being gone Northward to body, we cannot (at present) hear from our Forces in the <em>Lewis</em> and <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em> for all our Letters are intercepted as they are <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> through the Highlands. The <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Cinkeler</em> Castle kept by one of Col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Company of Foot, <reg orig="besiedged">besieged</reg> by <em>Middleton</em>, is <reg orig="releived">relieved</reg> by two <reg orig="months">month's</reg> provisions sent in thither, and three months Provisions more, are going to them, which I will hope will be with them before this be with you, with Ammunition and other necessaries for their accommodation. The Castle in which they are is very strong, though the houses be mined. It is seated upon the top of a High Rock where the Sea comes almost round. It is a great difficulty for Forces to march into<pb n="4" /> <em>Southerland</em> and <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, there being so many places to ferry, and but one or two Ferry-boats at a place, and at two of the Ferries the Enemy hath Garrisoned two houses to hinder passage, they have been very <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> in burning and destroying the Estates of those people that will not comply with them. I do not hear of any more ships come to <em>Middleton</em>, since those two vessels formerly mentioned which brought him over with about 80 ragged Officers with the Arms and <reg orig="Ammunion">Ammunition</reg> formerly mentioned. In the most remote parts of <em>Scotland</em>, the <em>Glem Reynolds</em>, and Sir <em>James <reg orig="Mac Donald">McDonald</reg></em> have bodied with a considerable strength against Middleton, and skirmished with parties, being resolved to keep that Army out of their Country if possible.</p>

<p>Dalkeith, April 3. <i>The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> relates this Northern news, To which I have <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to <reg orig="adde">add</reg>, That <em>Capt. Sherwin</em> Commander of the <em>Primrose</em>, and <em>Cap. Smith</em> Commander of the <em><reg orig="Dutchesse">Duchess</reg></em>, in their return from <em><reg orig="Orknay">Orkney</reg></em> took a <em>Dutch</em> Vessel laden with <em>French</em>, and <em>Spanish</em> Wines, <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg> <reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg>, and other good Commodities, bound for the West Indies, which they sent into <em>Aberdeen</em>.</i></p>

<p><em>Aberdeen</em> March 28. 1654. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is come to <em>Glencarn</em> with about 700 Horse and Foot, <em>Seafort</em> and some new raised Forces by him are daily expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. <em>Glencarne</em> with his whole force, being 2000 horse and foot is at <em>Dingwel</em>, two miles from <em>Braban</em>, not undeserving the name of an Island, which gives hopes of engaging Enemy there. In order to which, Lieut. Col. <em><reg orig="Mitchil">Mitchell</reg></em> is to march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> towards <em>Inverness</em> with nine Companies of Foot, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> follows him the day after with five Troops of Col. <em>Rich</em> his Regiment, and four Troops of Dragoons. He intends to take with him Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment, which is in his way, and to draw five Companies of Foot out of <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Some young Lairds and others that had a purpose to glean a party of Horse in <em>Lothian</em>, and so repair to the Enemy, were lately taken, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> Prisoners to <em>Dalkeith</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Cowes</em> in the Isle of <em>Wight</em>, April 6. A private man of War hath brought in two days since two <reg orig="smal">small</reg> French vessels, the one laden with Salt, the other hath little in her but Ballast; there is nothing more of our Fleet, but that they are the most part near to <reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg> point, &amp; the rest at the Spits head, being in all near 100 sail,<pb n="5" /> gallant ships and bravely accommodated; here was likewise the Holland ship taken by one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, who had 8 Bales of Paper, and some small quantity of Indico, and she is carried to <em>Portsmouth</em>: Here are at present <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Merchant ships in this road being wind-bound, and expecting some Easterly winds to carry them on their voyage, and many that were here, went away yesterday morning towards the Downs.</p>

<p>From <em>Deale</em> the 7. instant: The Ships that were in this road are for the most part gone up into the Thames, there remaineth <reg orig="onely">only</reg> a few which are bound to the Southward, this day also passed by about forty or fifty <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> of ships great and small, which we suppose to be the <em>Dunkirk</em> Fleet bound for London: And this morning is gone out of our men of War for <em>Holland</em> to get the Ratification of the Peace made with them and an <reg orig="Expresse">Express</reg> from the Dutch Ambassadors of the Agreement.</p>

<p>The Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers <reg orig="doe">do</reg> humbly and earnestly beseech all the people of God throughout the Land, who shall send any Certificate to them, that they would not take things upon the Opinion and Report of others, but to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> their own personal knowledge and experience, so as neither any whom God accepteth may want the testimony of his Servants, nor any be recommended by them whom he disalloweth, lest guilt be contracted by you, to whose Testimonials so much is referred, as that through <reg orig="carelessnesse">carelessness</reg> or partiality therein very unworthy men may unawares be admitted, to the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of God, the prejudice of his Church, and the utter frustrating of the pious intentions of our Governors, besides the blot which will deservedly stick to them, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the present, but with posterity, and succeeding times, for as much as the Certificates now exhibited will appear upon Record.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 8 April.</i></head>

<p><i>Newburgh upon the Donaw 11 March.</i> On Thursday last, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times since, hath appeared a strange sight, between Echniel and Unterstall, <reg orig="testifyed">testified</reg> by many witnesses examined before the Judge of Naffenveld, of a Troop of black horsemen, and a Coach and some <reg orig="Waggons">Wagons</reg> with many Footmen in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Liveries coming out of a Wood, and another troop in white which engaged with the black, but were put to flight. Then appeared<pb n="6" /> a tall man in black, with some white strappings retiring towards Naffenveld, who with another strong party in white, fell upon the black, and the fight being ended, the black man grew <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> and <reg orig="lesse">less</reg>, and so vanished, the others retreating into the wood with a great <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> and noise as if a great army had been fighting; and the sound of Drums and Trumpets.</p>

<p><i>Rome 7 March</i>. The Duke of Terranneva, <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> from the King of <em>Spain</em>, received here in great pomp, hath kissed the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> feet, who seeks much to ingratiate himself with the Cardinals, and the Princes that are the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Nephews, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> resideth in the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Trivalcio's</em> <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg>, and is shortly to have <reg orig="publick">public</reg> audience. The Pope sent him variety of fruits, costly wines, and sweet meats.</p>

<p><i>Venice 9 March</i>, There have been 12 French, English and Holland ships arrived at Constantinople, to take service under the Turks. Orders have been sent from thence into <reg orig="Barbury">Barbary</reg> and <reg orig="monie">money</reg> also, and the Commissions to seize upon all ships that shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> found. Signieur <em>Delfino</em> <reg orig="Provedidor">Provider</reg> of our fleet, hath taken six of the <reg orig="Turks">Turks'</reg> ships going with <reg orig="Victuall">Victual</reg> from Canea, which are brought into the <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of Candia.</p>

<p><i>Dantzick 14 March</i>. In the assembly of the States at Warsaw, the Spirituality have declared highly against the peace with the Cossacks; in which the King hath consented to break the league between the Romish and Greek Churches, and both demand restitution of their Churches, yet it thought to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> only a pretence for the great Duke of Muscovy to make war with <em>Poland</em>, into which Kingdom he is already entered in person with 50000 men, to besiege Smolensko, and hath sent 40000 men more towards Pezzois, and 40000 more to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Cossacks, and is desired of <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Radzivel</em> of <em>Litton</em>, to relieve Smolensko, and the King demands assistance of the Prince of <em>Sevenburgh</em>, and of the <em>Hospadith Kreymisken Seron</em>, and the Tartarians; all which are engaged to him by the last treaty, and have long desired war with the Muscovites.</p>

<p><i>Liege 23 March</i>. The French have taken <em>Hart</em> in <em>Limburgh</em> by storm, and put all to the sword, and got a great booty, and have retreated thence to <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, and the Spanish forces of <em><reg orig="Loraigne">Loraine</reg>, Conde</em> and <em>Wittemburgh</em>, are advanced to Namur, where the<pb n="7" /> Prince is in person, such store of <reg orig="cattell">cattle</reg> are brought hither plundered from the French (from whom some have been redeemed) that a Cow hath been sold for a 2 s. and some for 18 d.</p>

<p><i>Genoa 13 March</i>. The King of <em>Spain</em> is making great preparations for war, and hath laid new Imposts on Tobacco, <reg orig="Wooll">Wool</reg> and Salt. The Queen is said to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> again with child.</p>

<p><i>Paris 27 March</i>, <em>Don Joseph de Margnerita</em> is <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of Catalonia, the Lords there <reg orig="solicite">solicit</reg> hard for <reg orig="reliefe">relief</reg>, 10 Companies of French, and 4 of Switzers are gone this day towards Calaus to <reg orig="re-inforce">reinforce</reg> the Garrisons <reg orig="there abouts">thereabouts</reg> for fear of the English, suspect some attempt over <em>Bulloign</em>. The Duke of <em>Guise</em> intends for Italy and Naples. Saturday last the Earl <em>Ambijoux</em> Governor of Montpellier and three more were hanged in <reg orig="Effigie">Effigy</reg>, for having fought a Duel two months since. The putting down of Officers called <em>Eleus</em> incenses many against the Court, several Families that engaged their whole Estates and Friends to buy Places there being undone by it. This and the new Impositions that are contrived to get monies from the people, besides the ordinary Taxes, cause great complaints and discontents in France, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> is looked on at a greater distance <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Monday 10 April.</i></head>

<p>This day was this following Declaration presented to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by Col. <em>Barkstead</em> who had great expressions of thanks from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>.</p>

<p><i><em>Moot-hall</em> in <em>Colchester</em>. At the Assembly of Mr. Mayor, with the Aldermen, Assistants, and Common-<reg orig="councell">council</reg> of the said Town, April 6. 1654. The Honourable Col. <em>Barkstead</em> Lieut. of the Tower of <em>London</em>, high Steward of the said Town of <em>Colchester</em>, being then and there present.</i></p>

<p>At this assembly it is earnestly desired by the said Mayor, Aldermen, Assistance and Common <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, that the said high Steward should present their humble duties and services unto the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of E<em>ngland, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>; and to let his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> know, how readily, cheerfully, and willingly they have submitted, and <reg orig="doe">do</reg> submit themselves to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness's</reg> Government, and to return humble thanks to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, for giving their high Steward leave to come amongst them.</p><pb n="8" />

<p>This is <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Town Register with the hands of the Mayor, Aldermen, Common-council and free Burgesses.</p>

<p><em>Wil. Cockerel</em> Town Clerk.</p>

<p><em>Colchester</em> 8. April, 1654. Upon knowledge of Col. <em><reg orig="Berksteads">Berkstead's</reg></em> coming hither, who after the death of the <reg orig="Earle">Earl</reg> of <em>Holland</em> was freely chosen by this Town to be our High Steward.</p>

<p>Tuesday 4. instant, The Mayor, Aldermen, Common-<reg orig="councel">council</reg> and Burgesses with some Coaches, and about 200 Horse met him three miles off, Mr. <em>Barnardiston</em> the Recorder then alighted out of his Coach, and made a short Speech to him, which was answered by the High Steward, and after loving salutes of the Company, they attended him to the Town where 10000 more met to welcome him: after he had been at the <reg orig="Mayors">Mayor's</reg>, he went with them to the Sessions then held for the Town where the High Steward was sworn free <reg orig="Burgesse">Burgess</reg>, and a Justice of Peace, the latter of which <reg orig="Oathes">Oaths</reg> were also given to the Mayor and all the Justices present, <i>To execute their duties as Justices of Peace according to the best of their <reg orig="skil">skill</reg>, and knowledge, under this present Government.</i></p>

<p>Wednesday 5 They met at a Sermon.</p>

<p>Thursday 6, There met a greater number of Aldermen, Common-<reg orig="councill">council</reg> and Burgesses <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg>, where the High Steward made a Speech, which gave an abundance of satisfaction to all present: After which there was a DECLARATION agreed on and signed by them all, to be sent to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by their High Steward, after which he was not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> accompanied by the Mayor, and the many Aldermen and Gentlemen three miles on his way towards <em>London</em>, but some of the chief of the Town rode before to the Inn where we was to lie that night, and there prepared against his coming, a Banquet of Sweet-meats which they carried from <em>Colchester</em> with them.</p>

<p>A Congratulation was delivered to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> by the Lord <em>Strickland</em>, Mr. <em>Rushworth</em>, and Mr. <em>Muddison</em> (the Agent for <em>Newcastle</em>) as followeth, which was the second that was presented, and had then a thankful Answer.</p>

<head level="3"><i>For his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging,</i></head>

<p><i>May it please your Highness,</i> Many of the precious servants<pb n="9" /> of God in these Nations (over which the Lord hath set your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>) have gotten upon their watch Tower to see if they can discover what hath been the eminent design of the Lord in these latter days. For the <reg orig="Al">All</reg> -wise God hath of late visibly been out of his common road of Providences, his paths have been in tempests and thick <reg orig="darknesse">darkness</reg>, plucking up by the roots the greatest of men, and the highest of Powers, like Cedars in <em>Lebanon</em>, that he might make way for the glorious bringings forth of Truth and <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg>. And we question not but the Lord is fulfilling that great Prophecy, <i>Isa. 60. 17. I will make thine Officers Peace, and thy Exactors <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg> </i>. For when we consider how the Lord hath eminently made your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> <reg orig="Instrumentall">Instrumental</reg> for the breaking off the Iron <reg orig="yoake">yoke</reg> from off the necks of the three Nations, and likewise hath invested you with the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Power of this Commonwealth, whereby you may be exceedingly Instrumental to the Lord Jesus in the advancing of his <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> in <reg orig="Righteousnesse">Righteousness</reg> and Peace, we having the sense of these things with weight upon our spirits, having judged it our duty to <reg orig="professe">profess</reg> our great Resentment of this <reg orig="signall">signal</reg> mercy from the hands of our God, and do solemnly <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the Lord for setting up your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> over this great people, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> through the strength of Christ, to live in all humble obedience to your <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, as <reg orig="becommeth">becometh</reg> those who are under your Government and Protection.</p>

<p>Febr. 25. 1653.</p>

<p><i>Signed in the name, and by Order of the Common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <em>Newcastle</em> upon <reg orig="Tine">Tyne</reg>, Wil Johnson <em>Mayor</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>Brishaw 19. March</i>, There are great complaints and bewailings in this Country of the oppression of the poor Protestants by the Papists, by whom they are more and more persecuted, and not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> deprived of the liberty of their Meetings in their Church, but also from Christening their children, and forced to have them brought up in Popery.</p>

<p><em>Naples</em> 7 March. Three English ships richly laden, coming from <em>Smyrna</em>, were by <em>Cape Spartivento</em> set upon by three French men of War after a hot fight one of them was taken by the French, another stranged, and the third fled away by <em>Missinas</em>. The 25. of the last month the <em>Mont Visure</em> began to cast fire and<pb n="10" /> ashes, the people ran into the Churches and rung the <reg orig="bels">bells</reg>, to give warning of it all the Country about.</p>

<p>Rome 14 March. <i>The Pope hath made nine new Cardinals to fill the Consistory. The Ambassador of <em>Spain</em> hath had his first <reg orig="publick">public</reg> audience with a magnificent equipage and company, being followed by 300 coaches of <reg orig="Prelats">Prelates</reg> and other great persons of quality of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Nations. The <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Pamphilio</em> is still in the Castle of <em>Sambuci</em>, and is to leave the <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> and other prerogatives and qualities which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> <reg orig="injoyed">enjoyed</reg> as the <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> Nephew.</i></p>

<p><i>Venice 25 March.</i> The Venetians having besieged <em>Elim</em> in <em>Dalmatia</em>, and not well secured their quarters, have been set upon by the Turks with 5000 horse and 2000 foot, and forced to retreat in disorder with the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of 1000 men, amongst whom were many of the chief Officers, the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the Morlacks deadly wounded.</p>

<p><i>Frankford 29 March</i>. Col. <em>Wyngard</em> in the Castle of Falkenstein, turned a Minister living by him, out of his house with his wife and children, after <reg orig="hee">he</reg> had plundered the same, pretending he had spoken ill of the Duke of <reg orig="Loraign">Lorain</reg>, the said Parson seeking revenge, took to sit a time for it, that when a strong party was sent out of the Castle, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> with some country people the 25 instant came very early in the morning, and assaulting the castle-gate with great force, got in, killed the <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> which they found in <reg orig="armes">arms</reg>, and their Commander in his bed, and so delivered that Castle from those plunderers.</p>

<p><i>Flushen 2 <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. The last Monday arrived here two West India ships richly laden with Indico, Hides, Sugars and other goods. There are ten fire ships preparing at <em>Calice</em>, which are to be made use of in the <em>Straits</em>, cap. <em>Bastian Sensen</em>, Cap. <em>Brandt</em>, Cap. <em>Brugge</em>, Cap. <em>Philips Ras</em>, are all in company gone from hence two days since, for the coasts of Portugal, where some other freebooters more are to follow.</i></p>

<p><i>Paris 3 April.</i> The King went the 27 of the last month to the Parliament, where an Arrest or sentence was exhibited against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and his abettors, containing that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> executed by whatsoever kind of death his Majesty shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> willing to command, being declared guilty of the crime of high Treason: all his Lands and <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> estate, and whatsoever goods, are to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> forfeited to the King, <reg orig="hee">he</reg> is declared <reg orig="uncapable">incapable</reg><pb n="11" /> for ever of pretending to the Crown, and forbidden to use any more of the name of <em>Bourbon</em>, and is deprived of all dignities, or prerogatives of a Prince of the Blood, that all his <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> in whatsoever things <reg orig="ingraved">engraved</reg>, printed or set up, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> broken and defaced. The same sentence was the next day pronounced by the Parliament in scarlet Robes, the King being there sitting in his bed of Justice. There was also other sentences given in a <reg orig="particuler">particular</reg> against some of the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> followers, the Earl of <em>Bouteville</em>, the Marq. Of <em>Persan</em>, the Gen. <em>Marsin</em>, the Presidents <em>Viole</em> and <em>Laisne</em>, the which are condemned to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> beheaded at the place of Greve in <em>Paris</em>, in case they can be taken, otherwise they shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> hanged in <reg orig="effigie">effigy</reg> in the same place. As concerning the Lords <em>Meilles, Chamilley, Cerisi, Montalt, du Lignon, du Harlay, de Aumont, la Bernaise de St. Estienne</em>, and <em>St. Martin</em>, as also the Earls of <em>Fiesque, Bouteville de Duras, de St. Hibal</em>, and one called <em>Servienti</em>, there shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> informations made, and proceedings against them accordingly. Four days ago the Cardinal of <em>Retz</em> was by the mediation of the first President <em>de Bellieur</em>, and of the Marshall <em>de la Melleray</em> freed out of the <em>Bois de Vicennes</em> to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to the Town of <em><reg orig="Nantz">Nantes</reg></em> in <em><reg orig="Britanny">Brittany</reg></em>, to <reg orig="resigne">resign</reg> there into the hands of the King, the <reg orig="Arch-bishoprick">Archbishopric</reg> of <em>Paris</em>, worth 120000 Livers <em>per annum</em>, to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> disposed as his Majesty shall think fit, and <reg orig="hee">he</reg> shall receive in compensation seven <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg>, to dispose of them, and the sum of 200000 Livers in money.</p>

<p><i>Amsterdam 11 April. stilo novo</i>. The Lord Lieutenant Admiral <em>Opdam</em>, the Vice Admiral <em>Ruiter</em> and young <em>Tromp</em>, Scout by night are here at this present. The Drums do beat lustily, and great number of Seamen are gathered, so that our fleet as well in the Sud as in the Nord of <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Freezland</em> and <em>Zealand</em> is making ready in all haste to go to Sea, but all gape for Peace. An <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> is sent by the States to the K. of <em>Denmark</em> to <em>Geluckstadt</em>.</p>

<p>This day three men were hanged at <reg orig="Tiburn">Tyburn</reg> from Newgate one who had killed a Strumpet he kept company with in Old-street, when he was condemned did curse and revile the Court, &amp; most desperately died this day; he carried a bottle of sack with him in the Cart, and as he was going near Sepulchres Church, swore God <reg orig="dam">damn</reg> him, he would fill his guts with Sack before he <reg orig="dyed">died</reg>.</p><pb n="12" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 11 April.</i></head>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 3 April</i>. Notwithstanding all the several beatings those which raise <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg> meet with, yet so inveterate is the malice of these people against us, that they will be barking: several parties of them that have been up in Galloway have been met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and within these 4 or 5 days Maj. <em>Bridges</em> with a party of Col. <em><reg orig="Okies">Okie's</reg></em> took 8 of the Rebels, and 12 Horse in one place, in another place killed 3. took 8 and 25 Horse. Cornet <em>Kennet</em> with a party of 20 horse of Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> late Regiment, coming from <em><reg orig="Dunfreeze">Dumfries</reg></em>, a party of 40 of the Enemy made an attempt upon them, they received the onset, and then charged through them, routed the Rebels, killed 4 on the place, took 6 (whereof 3 mortally wounded) and divers horse. The next day Lieut. <em>Hickman</em> of that same Regiment <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> with him <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> a party of 80 of the Rebels, took 11 prisoners, and above 20 horse, Cap. <em>Campbel</em> who commanded them was shot in the back, his horse taken, but himself escaped.</p>

<p><em>Glencairn, Glengary</em>, &amp;c. are gone over <em>Tayne</em> into Sutherland to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton</em>, they give themselves out to be 4000. but I doubt not but Col. <em>Morgan</em> will engage them with his party. <em>Montrosse</em> and the Lord <em>Dudhop</em> are raising their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Angus</em>, they two will be met <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> in time.</p>

<p><i>Glascow 3 April</i>, thus. Lieutenant <em>Hickman</em> whom Col. <em>Cooper</em> sent out with a party of Horse towards <em>Galloway</em>, met with the Enemy about 80 horse, who routed them and took 23 horse, wounded the Capt. that commanded the party, killed 5 men, and wounded divers, and took 11 prisoners.</p>

<p>This day was published this following Ordinance:</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for Adjourning part of <em>Easter Term</em>, 1654. And repealing the former Ordinance of the <reg orig="sixt">sixth</reg> of this present <em>April</em>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas many abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained; Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to adjourn part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>; Be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his Council, that part of the said<pb n="13" /> Term of <em>Easter</em> now next coming be Adjourned, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em> unto the last Return of the said <em>Easter Term</em>, called <em>Crastino Assesionis</em>; and all and every person or persons, which have cause, or <reg orig="commandement">commandment</reg> to appear in any of the Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, in or at any day, or time, from and after the said Return, called <em>Quindena Pasch&aelig;</em>, and during the term called <em>Easter Term</em> may tarry at their dwellings, or where their business shall lie, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that cause, until the said last Return called Crastino Assensionis, without danger of forfeiture, penalty, or contempt to be in that behalf.</p>

<p>And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that Writs of Adjournment shall be directed to the Justices of the said Courts, and Barons of the <em>Exchequer</em>, giving them authority to adjourn the said part of the said term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the said first Return, called <em>Quindena Pasc&aelig;</em>, until the said last Return of the said Term, called <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>, as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained, that all Matters, Causes, and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg> depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Assensionis</em>, as is aforesaid; And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And <reg orig="bee">be</reg> it further Ordained, That a former Ordinance of the sixth day of this instant <em>April</em>, for the Adjourning of part of the said Term, until the first Return of <em>Trinity Term</em> next, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, be from henceforth repealed and void. And it is lastly Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, do forthwith proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the chief Market Towns and usual places within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 12 April.</i></head>

<p>It is advertised, That the Peace is welcome news to the States of <em>Holland &amp;c</em>. and that they will suddenly send a Messenger with Thanks to their Ambassadors, and their Approbation; and then it is to be published by both, on the same day.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The substance of the Peace agreed upon between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em><pb n="14" />, &amp;c. according to the best Intelligence that I can gather, is to this effect, but much more large in the particulars, <em>viz</em>.</i></head>

<p>That there shall be a closer <reg orig="Aliance">Alliance</reg> and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> was ever heretofore. That the Peace be published by both Commonwealths, upon one and the same day; after which, all acts of Hostility to cease after 10 days in the British Seas; from thence to the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em> after six weeks, and to the Mediterranean Sea after ten weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> ; after which, all prizes to be restored. That all acts past be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither to act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other. That all Hostility cease between <em>England</em> and <em>Denmark</em>; none to assist the Rebels of either Nation with any supply, but assist each other against them; and the one not to receive those the other declares to be enemies, but cause them upon notice to depart within 28 days, upon pain of death. That no private persons be suffered to assist the enemies of either, not to pay to either greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> the others. The <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships to strike their Flags to the English in the British Seas; no retreat to be given to Pirates in any of the Posts of either; each to comprehend the other in any Treaty with any Nation, if desired. That if any particular persons break the Peace, it shall not break the National Confederacy, but those that do it to be punished. The Subjects of each to travel freely through all quarters of each, by Water or Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and submitting to the Laws where they are. That in storms each may have <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> under other, if they break not Bulk, without paying of Customs. The Merchants or Mariners of other Commonwealth not to be pressed to serve under the other, but on inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction. That in each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> , they pass between their Ships and Inns with lawful Weapons, Offensive and Defensive. That all ships of both Commonwealths defend each other against all whomsoever, sailing their course together. That if any other take any ships out of either of their Dominions, both parties to engage against them, until restitution be made. The Searchers of both, to take no more of<pb n="15" /> any of either, <reg orig="then">than</reg> their Instructions. Letters of Reprisal not to be given for damage caused, if in 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> , satisfaction may be had. That such as have private Commissions, put in good security not to damage the Subjects of either Commonwealth, That not above 8 ships of War remain in any Port of the <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Commonwealth, without consent. That Justice be done by the States on those that are alive, that murdered the English in <em>Amboyna</em>. That there be Commissioners on both sides to examine the Differences of the Inhabitants of both Nations in the <em>East Indies, Greenland, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>, or other places, and if they cannot agree within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> , to refer to it to be determined by the Protestant <em>Switzers</em>.</p>

<p>Security is already given for payment of the moneys to the <em>Eastland</em> Company, upon the business of <em>Denmark</em>, and the sum agreed upon.</p>

<p>Some Merchants have Letters that the Messenger is coming from the State; and that the Peace it is thought will be proclaimed <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> Sevennight, and that an Agent is coming from <em>Denmark</em>.</p>

<p>A Messenger is sent from the King of <em>France</em> also to the French <reg orig="Ambassadour">Ambassador</reg> here. <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg> are coming from several Princes.</p>

<p>The Scots rise in several parties in the Lowlands, and 4 or 500 have been lately dispersed in several parties, and divers of them killed and taken, Gen. <em>Monk</em> is gone to take the command of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, An Ordinance is past <reg orig="tendring">tendering</reg> pardon, only with some Exceptions, 1000 of the Scots have gotten leave to be transported to serve the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, or the Grand Duke of Muscovy, which they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg>,</p>

<p>The Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers sit in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> , near the great gate.</p>

<p>On Friday next his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> intends to come to <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, and is that day to Dine there.</p>

<hr />

<p>A very <reg orig="stowt">stout</reg> bay Gelding, with a black Mane and a black Tail, branded with a Cross in an <reg orig="Escocheon">Escutcheon</reg> upon one of his hind Legs, and a cleft in one of his hinder Hoofs to the Toe. Lost from Woodford-Bridge in the County of Essex about ten <reg orig="daies">days</reg> since, if any can bring the Horse (or tidings of him) to the Water-mill at Woodford, or to Mr. <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Barker</em>, (an Attorney) at his Office in <reg orig="Woodstreet">Wood Street</reg> London near the Counter, he shall have twenty shillings for his pains.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>