<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="ProcState239">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>Severall Proceedings of State Affaires, Issue 239</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="1">Several Proceedings</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="2">STATE <reg orig="AFFAIRES">AFFAIRS</reg> </head>

<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. With the Transactions of the <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> in other NATIONS.</head>

<head level="2">From Thursday the 20 of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. To Thursday the 27 day of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em>. 1654.</head>

<head level="3">Appointed to be Printed: And is <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the <reg orig="Registor">Register</reg> Book kept by the Company of Stationers, according to the late Act for PRINTING.</head>

<hr />
<head level="3">Printed at <em>London</em> for <em>Robert Ibbitson</em> dwelling in Smithfield <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hosier Lane. 1654</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning on Thursday 20 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. 1653.</i></head>

<p>Addresses have been made to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, by some persons sent from the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Common <reg orig="councill">council</reg> of the City of <em>London</em>, to desire, that the buildings may not go on at the West end of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>, which was always a common <reg orig="high way">highway</reg>, and lay open to the street, and yet one is now raising buildings there, where the dust is taken up, where many dead <reg orig="corps">corpses</reg> lye buried, and is sifted to mix with the <reg orig="morter">mortar</reg> to build with.</p>

<p><reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> is also made from the said Common <reg orig="councill">council</reg>, to desire to know the pleasure of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> touching <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>, and that it may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> disposed of to some use, as shall bee thought fit.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>It was also desired that there may <reg orig="bee">be</reg> some suppressing of the multitudes of Hackney Coaches now in and about the City of <em>London</em>, which are many ways <reg orig="prejudiciall">prejudicial</reg> to the Commonwealth.</p>

<p><i>Rome 30 March</i>. The Pope hath made Father <em>Gabriel Sateren</em>, and Seignior <em>Gozzadino</em> Bishops of <em>Vigevano</em> and <em>Zant</em>. The 23 the Pope held a <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> about some propositions touching some <reg orig="Bishopricks">Bishoprics</reg>, where <reg orig="hee">he</reg> opened the mouth to the new Cardinals, and being sick was then <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to his bed: <reg orig="Hee">He</reg> hath given them all the Church-livings of the Degraded Cardinal <em>Astalli</em>. The <em>Spaniards</em> upon consideration of the advantage they may receive by Cardinal <em>de Medici</em>, have bestowed upon him all the benefices that are vacant by the death of <em>Pimentelli</em>, to keep or dispose of them.</p>

<p>Venice 30 March. <i>General <em>Foscolo</em> before his departure from <em>Candia</em>, is setting all things in order to receive Gen. <em>Moccinigo</em>, who is to succeed him in that place. Our Resident <em>Capello</em> is still prisoner at <em>Andronopoli</em>. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> have small hopes that the Turk will <reg orig="renue">renew</reg> his Treaty, for they are making great preparations against us. The Turkish fleet are stronger by 30 <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg>, than they were the last year. <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> hear from <em>Dalmatia</em> that Gen. <em>Dolphino</em> having besieged the Fort of <em>Clim</em> with 6000 men, the besieged being <reg orig="re-inforced">reinforced</reg> from <em>Bossine</em>, made a folly upon him, and 1500 of our men are <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> and taken prisoners, and the rest routed, and all our Ordnance and baggage lost.</i></p>

<p><i>Genoa 8 April</i>. Our 4 <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> who <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> Count <em>de Ognate</em> (formerly Vice-Roy of <em>Naples</em>) into <em>Spain</em>, having landed him at <em>Valentia</em>, are returned hither, and <reg orig="hee">he</reg> is gone from thence towards <em>Madrid</em>. The Duke of <em>Montalto</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Valentia</em>, makes levies for the Spanish Army in <em>Catalonia</em>. Two great vessels have lately been cast away in the Port of <em>Laone</em>, one the Pelican of <em><reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg></em>, laden at <em>Cadis</em> with 300000 <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of eight, and much other goods, and divers passengers, but most of the men are saved; The other belonging to Cap. <em><unclear>Avenilno Genniads</unclear></em>, coming from <em><reg orig="Lisbone">Lisbon</reg></em> with 800 chests of Sugar and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> other Goods, and many passengers, whereof 150 were drowned, and amongst others the Count <em>Ottonelli</em>, and the Duke of <em>Modene's</em> Ambassador coming from <em>Madrid</em>, and his Retinue.</p>

<p>Bethune 15 April. <i>5000 Spaniards in <em>Mainaut</em> and <em>Brahant</em><pb n="2" /> are marching towards <em>Lisle</em>, Those that quartered this Winter between the River of <em>Lys</em> and the sea, have received orders to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> ready. The <em>Lorainers</em> have stayed behind expecting the Prince <em>Francis</em>.</i></p>

<p>Ponta Mousson 17 <reg orig="Aprill">April</reg>. <i>Marquis of <em>Fabert</em>, <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Sedan</em>, having passed <em>Moselle</em>, quartered the 12 instant at <em>Esteia</em> with all his forces, which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> is sending back again, himself returning to his Government.</i></p>

<p><i>Bruxels 18 April.</i> The <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> having met at <em>Louvain</em> with the Elector of <em>Colen</em>, after two days conference, the Elector returned home very much <reg orig="satisfyed">satisfied</reg> by their meeting, and received from the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> a present of two rich suits of hangings, and four of his best horses, and was conducted by the <reg orig="Arch Duke">Archduke</reg> as far as <em>Arschat</em>. Count <em>Ligneville</em> was 13 instant at <em>Onain</em>, with the Lorain Forces, and is gone towards <em>Lisle</em>.</p>

<p>Jamets 20 April, <i> Mounsieur <em>De Manimont</em> our <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg>, and Count <em>de Grandpre</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Mosson</em>, had a <reg orig="designe">design</reg> upon the Enemy at <em>Virton</em> in <em><reg orig="Luxemburgh">Luxembourg</reg></em>, which they have effected, and they have slain divers, and taken the rest prisoners, and possessed themselves of their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>.</i></p>

<p><i>Paris 25 April.</i> This week the King made <reg orig="choyce">choice</reg> of Father <em>Francis Annot</em>, <reg orig="Provintiall">Provincial</reg> of the <reg orig="Jesuites">Jesuits</reg>, of the Province of <em>France</em>, for his Ordinary <reg orig="Confessour">Confessor</reg>. Monsieur <em>Philippo</em> Eldest son to Monsieur <em>de la Uraillier</em> Secretary of state was sworn Secretary to his Majesty, to succeed his Father after his death, in regard of the great services his Predecessors have for fifty <reg orig="yeers">years</reg> faithfully executed in that place.</p>

<p>The 18 instant the Italian Comedy was played the third time before the King. The 19 the King with his Brother and many Lords, and the <reg orig="Cardinall">Cardinal</reg> <em>Mazarine</em> had a great Hunting in the <em>Bois de <reg orig="Vicennes">Vincennes</reg></em>, and returned the next day to the <em>Louver</em>. The Queen passed all that day in the <em>Val de Grace</em>. The 22 one <em>James Darcy</em>, an Irish Gentleman, Brother to the sometimes (popish) Bishop of <em>Drommon</em>, had conferred on him by the King of <em>France</em> the place of Lieutenant in the Regiment of the pretended Duke of <em>York</em>, in consideration of his late services in the said Register both in <em>France</em> and in <em>Alsatia</em>: And the next day <reg orig="hee">he</reg> was Knighted by <em>Charles Stuart</em>, <reg orig="Tituler">Titular</reg> King of <em>Scots</em>, with the <reg orig="usuall">usual</reg> Ceremonies.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for further suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in an Act <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <em>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners.</em></i></head>

<p>Whereas in regard of many doubts arising upon an Act of the late Parliament, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</i>, and <reg orig="severall">several</reg> inconveniences and mischiefs like to grow from thence, not only to the Creditors and Prisoners themselves, but to divers other persons, without some Explanation and further direction to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> given to the several and respective Judges authorized in and by that Act; It is by an Ordinance of the one and thirtieth day of March One thousand six hundred fifty and four, Ordained, That the said <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Judges should not proceed to sale or disposition, nor otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any of the powers and authorities given by the same, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the twentieth day of <em>April</em> instant:</p> 

<p>And whereas the way for prevention of those evils, and the better accomplishing the ends intended by the said Act, is now under consideration, which will necessarily require some longer time to perfect the same.</p> 

<p>Be it Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, That the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the said Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale or disposition of any of the estates <reg orig="reall">real</reg> or <reg orig="personall">personal</reg>, of any of the said prisoners, or of any other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in or by the said Act, nor shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act, or of any of the powers or authorities given by the same, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the fifteenth day of <em>May</em> next coming.</p> 

<p>And <reg orig="bee">be</reg> it further Ordained, that all Acts and things to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> done by the said <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective Judges, or any of them, by <reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg>, colour or pretence of the said Act from henceforth and before the said fifteenth day of <em>May</em> aforesaid (saving only in such cases, and according to such limitations, as by the said Ordinance they had power to do, before the said twentieth day of <em>April</em>) shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> and are hereby declared to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> utterly null and void.</p>

<p>This day the Articles of Peace between <em>England</em> and the <em>Netherlands</em><pb n="4" /> engrossed in Parchment were signed by His Highness the Lord <reg orig="Proctor">Protector</reg>, OLIVER <unclear>P.</unclear> and sealed by the Commissioners of the Chancery by the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, sitting in the Inner-Court of Wards, and the Seal thereof put into a round silver and guilt Box, with the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> graven upon the said Box, and compassed about with two olive branches, on either side of the <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> one.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Friday 21 April.</i></head>

<p>A Declaration and Petition from the Corporation of <em><reg orig="Guldeford">Guildford</reg></em>, was (on Tuesday last in the afternoon) brought by the Mayor, and four of the Aldermen, the Steward and the <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of that Town to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, where they <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> it to one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Gentlemen, and <reg orig="intreated">entreated</reg> his assistance to bring them where they might present it to His Highness; which Gentleman <reg orig="curteously">courteously</reg> brought them to the Gallery where the Chair is fixed, and desired them to have a little patience, till His Highness was risen from Council, and they should then have admittance to him.</p>

<p>They observed his direction, and after some time of necessary waiting, they were called into the next Chamber, which is between the two Galleries, and there received by another Gentleman of very great and exceeding becoming civility, who conducted them where his Highness stood, and some of his Heroes, and divers other Gentlemen of quality attending on him, in an handsome and somewhat an <reg orig="awfull">awful</reg> posture, fairly pointing towards that which of necessity, for the honour of the English Nation must be <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> to Him who is their Protector.</p>

<p>And Mr. Mayor of <em>Guildford</em> and his Company, by what they then observed, and by what some of them had observed heretofore, do declare and say, that they are confident that His Highness is pleased with those <reg orig="Philactaries">Phylacteries</reg> and Fringes of State (if pleased with them at all) because he must rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> he would wear them; And that His Highness knows that there is more in <reg orig="harmeless">harmless</reg> Ceremonies of State <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> common and weak eyes discern, or have any wise cause to be offended at.</p>

<p>Mr. Mayor and his Company (about ten steps distance from the Lord Protector) made a stand, and His Highness, minding<pb n="5" /> of them, lest speaking to some other Gentlemen, and came towards them, and the Stewart in humble manner by direction from Mr. Mayor presented the Declaration and Petition saying.</p>

<p>May it please your Highness,</p>

<p><i>I do humbly present this Declaration and Petition on the behalf of the Mayor, and approved men of the Town of <em><reg orig="Guldeford">Guildford</reg></em> to your Highness.</i></p>

<p>His Highness took it, went to the window and heedfully read it over, being as followeth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>To His Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord <reg orig="Proctor">Protector</reg> of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></head>

<head level="3"><i>The humble Declaration and Petition of the Mayor, and approved men of the Town of <em><reg orig="Guldeford">Guildford</reg></em> in the County of <em>Surrey</em>.</i></head>

<p>Notwithstanding the great and many Victories over our Enemies in <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, obtained by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> blessing on Your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Valor">Valour</reg> and Prudence, the same whereof doth ring throughout and beyond the Christian world; We were obliquely running into a worse condition (if worse might be) <reg orig="then">than</reg> when our Troubles first broke out.</p>

<p>Which Your Wisdom perceiving, and being willing to prevent, we do <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> out of constraint, rather <reg orig=" then "> than </reg> desire, You did take upon Your Shoulders that great and ponderous burthen of the Government of the three Nations and Dominions to them belonging, whereof You have, and long may You have, the Honour, and we (amongst the rest of the people) and our Children the benefit, by sitting as we do in peace and safety under Your Protection, and <reg orig="chearfully">cheerfully</reg> following the works, and comfortably <reg orig="injoying">enjoying</reg> the fruits of our Callings.</p>

<p>And we clearly see to our great contentment by Your countenancing of a godly and learned Ministry, and making of honest and learned Judges of the Land, You are resolved to uphold Religion and Justice, the principal Pillars and <unclear>Suppositors</unclear> of States and Commonwealths.</p>

<p>But the weight of Your high Calling lies heavily upon You, and therefore it is the Duty and <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be the Wisdom of the people to ease You what they can, which may be done by their ingenuous<pb n="6" /> and willing submission to Your Just and Wise Government, and that we of this Town do humbly acknowledge and subscribe unto; And Declare, that we will be ready to the <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of our lives for You (who have so many times valiantly and gallantly hazarded Your life for us) against all Enemies who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> dare to rise up against You:</p>

<p>We find no cause to doubt but that You will vouchsafe to this ancient Corporation, much spoken of, for good Government, love to Religion, godly Ministers, unanimous and constant conjunction with those of this Nation who have opposed Tyranny, the <reg orig="injoyment">enjoyment</reg> of those <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> which they have a long time had, whilst they are not found any <reg orig="waies">ways</reg> pernicious to the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg>.</p>

<p>And we do assure You that we have not made this application to flatter You nor <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg>, but in Conscience to discharge that Duty which may be justly expected at our hands, hoping You will look upon the Affections of our Hearts, and excuse the bluntness and plainness of our phrase.</p>

<p>Lastly, we do presume to make known, that our Minister of <em>Trinity</em> and <unclear><em>Marries</em></unclear> Parishes is very lately dead, and that Living is in Your Gift, And therefore we humbly pray Your Highness to <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg> Your pleasure to the Lords Commissioners for Your Great Seal, or to such persons as are <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> for that Affair, that they may for this turn grant it to such a one as we shall <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> to them to be a godly and learned Minister, and to no other man.</p>

<p>After the Lord Protector had read this Petition, His Highness was pleased to give this Answer, standing uncovered, which may be truly termed gracious.</p>

<p>Gentlemen,</p>

<p><i>I have read Your Paper, wherein, what you there express touching My taking of the Government upon Me, you say what is truth, I did not desire it, nor have I (I am sure) told you so; I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> God put it into your <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear>, I shall desire your prayers, that it may <reg orig="doe">do</reg> as you have expressed; for God is My <unclear>bottoin</unclear>, and in him <reg orig="onely">only</reg> do I trust: As for your desire of a Minister, I think I have not granted the Living away, and upon your making <reg orig="choyce">choice</reg> of such a one as you Paper mentions, I shall take Order that you shall have your <unclear>Suit</unclear></i></p><pb n="7" />

<p>His Highness afterwards asked the value of the Living, and the quality of the deceased Minister, and then dismissed them, who were conducted to the door, by the Gentleman that had conducted them up, with so much <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg> and respect as the Mayors and Aldermen of the greatest Cities, or the persons who may justly account themselves Some-bodies, might be well pleased with.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday 23 April.</i></head>

<p>An Ordinance is <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> for continuing the Impositions of Coals for building of ships.</p>

<p>The business of improving of <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg> is under consideration.</p>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 16 April</i>, Maj Gen, <em>Dyal</em> is to besiege <em>Sinclair</em> Castle, we have six <reg orig="months">months'</reg> Provisions there, 30 horse load are sent to supply <em>Ruthen</em> Castle. 40 Scots horse were pursued by Lieut. <em>Hunt</em> to <em>Alberfast</em>, seven Prisoners taken with eleven horse, 20 Cloaks and some plunder, two prisoners rescued which they had taken on the <reg orig="boarders">borders</reg> of <em>Cumberland</em>. Col. <em>Irwin</em> commanded their Rear. <em><reg orig="Mac Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg></em> losses have made him withdraw, and we think his party will offer terms to come in.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Council at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas a Peace is made, concluded and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the United Provinces of the Low Countries. And whereas it is agreed, that publication thereof shall be made on both parts on Wednesday next, being the six and twentieth day of this instant <em>April</em>; From which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after twelve <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> within these Seas; And in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks; And from thence, within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranian">Mediterranean</reg> Sea</em>, and to the <em>&AElig;cquinoctial</em> Line after ten weeks; And beyond the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> after the space of eight months: Which several places were so limited, to the intent convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Ports of this Commonwealth, and to all others, whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof;<pb n="8" /> To the end they may have warning, to provide for their own safety, and not expose their ships to danger, within the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> and respective times aforesaid.</p>

<p>Cap. <em>Potter</em> hath taken the <em>Bridget</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a <em>Brest</em> man of war with four Guns, brought in to <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em>.</p>

<p>There are three Dutch Prizes brought to <em>Deal</em>, one was bound for the East Indies, the other two are of good value.</p>

<p>There are brought into <em>Harwich</em> two Dutch prizes, which came from <em>Norway</em>, and some Busses are taken by a private man of war with some fish.</p>

<p>This Evening the Dutch Ambassadors attended his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> and his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> at <em>Whitehall</em>, and <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> before many Gentlemen, Merchants and others, the Ratification of the Peace was fully finished; his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> delivered it signed and sealed to them and they to him, in a solemn manner, before all the Gentlemen present, and both <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> the publication thereof in both Nations on the Wednesday following.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> 24 April.</i></head>

<p><i><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> <em>18 April</em>. The Commander in chief being willing to use all means possible to prevent the further spreading of this Insurrection, (in which the people are mad from all parts to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg>) hath published the <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> Proclamation. The forces in the North are much in the same posture, our Horse is yet at <em>Dingwell</em>, and the Enemy in <em>Sutherland</em>, where it is very probable they cannot get away without <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg>. Amongst the party which were defeated about 9 days since, at <em>Kilowoch</em>, the Earl of <em>Selkeithe</em>, who was just run to the Enemy was one, the Rebels at his coming to <em>Abersoyl</em> took him for an Enemy, shot him in the face and wounded two others of his party. A party from <em>Dalkeith</em> this day took 11 horse, and yet nothing but <reg orig="Barbadoes">Barbados</reg>, or the Gallows will tame, or <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg> these Rogues.</i></p>

<head level="3">A PROCLAMATION</head>

<head level="3"><i>By the Commander in chief of all the Forces in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>Whereas (amongst all other things) by Proclamation of the 27 of <em>Sept</em>, 1653, all <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> and Officers of Burghs an Parishes and all other persons whatsoever, are required to secure, or give intelligence of all suspected persons, travelling through or abiding within their bounds or jurisdictions, as in and by the said Proclamation more particularly is expressed: Notwithstanding<pb n="9" /> nothing to this time hath been effectually done, but on the contrary, divers Rebels, as well considerable numbers as <reg orig="Spyes">Spies</reg>, have been, and <reg orig="stil">still</reg> are frequently permitted and suffered to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, march through and abide in any Burgh or Parish within the quarters of our Army unquestioned, as if no rebellion were, who thereby take opportunity, not only to get Intelligence, but also to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> many loose persons to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them in Rebellion, and commit frequent Robberies and barbarous <reg orig="murthers">murders</reg>, and other outrages upon the persons, goods and <reg orig="geer">gear</reg>, as well of Scots as of English. These are therefore strictly to charge and command, that no person or persons, of what degree or quality soever (not being a member of the English Army) do presume after ten days next after publication hereof, to <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> above five miles from his and their respective abodes or habitations, <reg orig="unlesse">unless</reg> he or they have first obtained a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> from <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, or the Commander in Chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em> for the time being, or from the next chief Officer of the English Army, or the Judge Advocate of the Army, (of whose circumspection and care in parting with the said passes to persons well-affected, or upon good caution, I nothing doubt) which said <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> is to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> signed and sealed with my hand and seal, conform to the hand and seal hereunto subscribed and affixed, or the hand and seal of the Commander in chief for the time being, and subscribed by the said Officer from whom it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be obtained, with his name, together with the time and place of his subscription, (except <reg orig="hee">he</reg> or they, make it appear, he or they are upon their ready way to the next chief Officer for obtaining the said <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> ) under the pain of being adjudged, deemed and taken as Enemies in Rebellion against the peace of the Commonwealth, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly. And all Magistrates and Officers, and all other persons whatsoever within Burghs or Parishes, are hereby strictly required, that if any person or persons (except as before is excepted) and not being Members of the English Army, shall contrary hereunto presume to march, <reg orig="travell">travel</reg>, <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through, or abide in any Burgh or Parish without a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> as aforesaid, the said Magistrates, Officers and parishioners of such Burgh and Parish, are hereby required to secure them, if they shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> of strength sufficient, and them safely to keep, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> notice be given to <reg orig="my self">myself</reg>, the Commander in chief for the time being, or the next adjacent Officer<pb n="10" /> in chief of the English Forces (any of whose Orders theranent is duly to be observed) under the penalty of twenty pounds sterling, and such further punishment, according to the quality of the offence, as to a Court <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> to be held for the <reg orig="head-quarters">headquarters</reg>, or any other inferior Court Marshal, before whom the matter shall be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be thought just; And whensoever any party of the Rebels which now are, or hereafter <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> break forth into Rebellion, or any other person, or having a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, as aforesaid, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> break forth into Rebellion, or any other person, not having a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, as aforesaid, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> march or <reg orig="travell">travel</reg>, into or through any Burgh or Parish; and if the Burgh, Parish and Inhabitants shall not be of strength sufficient to secure them: That is such case the Magistrates, Officers, and Inhabitants of the said Burgh, and parishioners of the said parish, and every <reg orig="individuall">individual</reg> person thereof, are hereby strictly charged and required, to take care that such expedient <reg orig="bee">be</reg> found out amongst themselves, that upon the first entrance of such Rebels, or persons not having a <reg orig="passe">pass</reg>, as aforesaid, whether they make stay or not, immediately to take care that all possible speed, one or more persons, mounted on as good a horse as at present may be had, or otherwise a nimble Footman, to post away with all possible speed to the next and <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> Forces of the English Army, wheresoever they shall happen to be, and give true Intelligence to the Officer or Officers thereof, of their number, and who commands them, so near as may be, under the like penalty of twenty pounds sterling, and such farther punishment, according to the quality of the Offence, as to a Court <reg orig="Martiall">Marshal</reg> of the Army, before whom the matter shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> in like manner thought just.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and seal at <em>Dalkeith</em> the 7 of April 1654.</i></p>
<p>R. LILBURNE</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday 24 April.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Venice 3 April</em>, In the last overthrow we have received before <em>Clin</em> in <em>Dalmatia</em>, we have lost 3000 men killed and taken prisoners, and the matter of 1000 Turks have been killed upon the place. The <reg orig="Popes">Pope's</reg> <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> and the Germans have behaved themselves most valiantly, and of them, are the most part of our deads. There are arrived at <em>Genoa</em> four Galleys from Spain, bringing a million of Crowns for <em>Milan</em>, and also between<pb n="11" /> 4 and 5000 men newly levied in Switzerland and Germany, whereupon the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of the said Town of <em>Milan</em> doth intend to take the field before the French, to make his best advantage against them. The Generalissimo <em>Macenico</em> doth prepare to go for <em>Candia</em>, and shall take along with him those ships that have been kept at <em>Livorn</em> for the service of this Signiory, which to that end shall be brought hither as soon as may be. He shall have Order to take also with him out of the Island of <em>Zante</em>, <em><reg orig="Signior">Signor</reg> Andreo Carnacio</em>, who is destined to be General of the Kingdom of <em>Candia</em>. We hear by some Letters from <em>Corfu</em>, that they had advice from <em>Dalmatia</em> that the Turks had made an invasion into <em>Narrante</em>, whence they have carried away many persons to make them slaves. We understand also that the Dukes of <em>Florence, Madena</em> and <em>Parma</em>, do make great preparations of war.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of Prizes taken by several <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> of the English Fleet.</i></head>

<p><em>April 10</em>. A ship of <em>Amsterdam</em> 100 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, 5 guns, taken by the Assurance and Amity. A ship with Pitch, Linseed and Deal boards, belonging to <em>Rotterdam</em>, taken by the Pearl. A French ship taken by the Pearl. A Vessel belonging to <em>Flushing</em> with 26 cases of Glass taken by the Drake. A small Pink of Flushing laden with wines from <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, taken by the Non-such.</p>

<p><em>April 15</em>. A private man of war taken by the Mermaid about Flambrough-head. From Dublin is advertised, that a private man of war of Brest sunk near the coasts of Ireland by the Fox <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> and the Fox <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sunk with her in the engagement whilst they were grappling each other.</p>

<p><em>Newcastle, 20 April</em>. Here are a great fleet of Colliers 300 <reg orig="saile">sail</reg> near ready. Here is an <em>Ipswich</em> man run <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg> Southward of Sunderland. The <reg orig="Mosse">Moss</reg> Troopers are so <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> on our Borders that some of our Gentry fear their Rent-gatherers to be robbed. Gen. <em>Monk</em> went from hence, Wednesday morning last, when he came hither all the ships put out their colours, those that had guns shot them off, and 15 great guns more upon the Key as he passed the Bridge, and Mr. Mayor, the Recorder, the Sheriff and Aldermen gave him a visit, and sent him three sorts of wine, loaf-Sugar, Cakes and <reg orig="Lemmons">Lemons</reg>, &amp;c. and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg><pb n="12" /> great affections to him and to the present Government under His Highness the Lord Protector. Col. <em>Monk</em> sent Orders to the Shields and Sunderland to stay the Coal ships till the Peace be perfected, or more men of war come to convoy them, for 12 Dutch men of war hover near <em>Barwick</em>, and can be at our Bar with a <reg orig="westernly">westerly</reg> wind before the ships can be at Sea. The guns went off again at Gen. <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> departure, divers Sea Officers with great humility went to present their service to him. A ship of this Town coming laden from <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> is sunk at Sea.</p>

<p>This day was published four Ordinances touching <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>1. An Ordinance for uniting <em>Scotland</em> into one Commonwealth with <em>England</em>, 30 persons to be called thence in every Parliament. That <em>Charles Stuart</em> and all of the late <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Posterity be disabled to <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg> the Crown of <em>Scotland</em> or Name, Title, Stile, Dignity, <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg>, or any Possessions of any Hereditaments thereto belonging. As also the Convocation of the three Estates of <em>Scotland</em> to be abolished, That St. <em><reg orig="Andrews">Andrew's</reg></em> Cross the <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> be born in the Arms of this Commonwealth, That Customs and Excise of Goods, be no otherwise between <em>England</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> from one place of <em>England</em> to another. And <em>Scotland</em> to submit to the Customs of this Commonwealth. That Taxes be proportionable to <em>England</em>. And that all possessors of Lands in Scotland, after 12 <em>April</em> 1654. shall hold their Lands of the Lords by Deed, <reg orig="Pattent">Patent</reg> or Enfeoffment, to be renewed upon the death of every Heritor to his Heirs, under such Rents, and Services as are due by Deeds now in being, without <reg orig="rendring">rendering</reg> any other duty, service, vassalage or demand whatsoever, except Heritors where the same are due. Fines certain or uncertain, not above a <reg orig="years">year's</reg> value upon the death of the Lord, or death or alienation of the Tenant. Doing such suit and service as is ordained by the <i>Ordinance for Erecting <reg orig="Courts">Court's</reg> Baron in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></p>

<p>2 An Ordinance for Erecting Courts Baron in <em>Scotland</em>, Every place which is really a <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg>, there to be one Court, which is to be in the nature of a Court Baron, or Court of a <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg> here in <em>England</em>, to be holden every three weeks, to have power to judge all Contracts, Debts, Promises, and Trespasses not exceeding 40 s. sterling.</p>

<p>3 An Ordinance of Pardon and Grace to the people of <em>Scotland</em> after 1 <em>May</em> 1654. except the persons following, and their Estates.</p><pb n="13" />

<!-- the following list of names etc. is set out in two adjacent columns separated by a vertical line -->

<!-- First column -->
<p><em>Henrietta Maria</em> late Queen</p>
<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> her Son.</p>
<p><em>James Stuart</em> her Son,</p>
<p><em>James</em> late Duke <em>Hamilton</em></p>
<p><em>William</em> late Duke <em>Hamilton</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Craford Linsey</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Calender</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Marshal</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Kelly</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Lauderdale</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Loudon</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Seaforth</em></p>
<p>Earl <em>Athol</em></p>
<p>Viscount <em>Kenmore</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Lorn</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Machlin</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Montgomery</em></p>

<!-- Second Column -->
<p>Lord <em>Spynle</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Cranston</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Sincleer</em></p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Dalyel</em>.</p>
<p>Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em></p>
<p>Viscount <em>Newburgh</em></p>
<p>Lord <em>Bargany</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Thomas Thomson</em></p>
<p>Laird of <em>Womat</em></p>
<p>Laird <em>Napier</em></p>
<p>Earl of <em>Glencarne</em>.</p>
<p>Divers others are fined to pay <reg orig="certaine">certain</reg> sums of moneys, <em>David Leshly</em> 4000 li. Marquis <em>Douglas</em> 1000 l. and many other several sums.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A yearly Allowance given to their Wives and Children, out of their <reg orig="Husbands">Husband's</reg> and <reg orig="Fathers">Father's</reg> Estates.</i></head>

<p>400 l. sterling to <em>Anne</em> Duke <em><reg orig="Hambletons">Hambleton's</reg></em> Daughter, paying 20 l. a year to the Lord Protector and his Successors.</p>

<p>200 l. to her Sister <em>Susan</em>, paying 10 l. to his Highness.</p>

<p>400 l. to <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> <em>Hamilton</em>, paying 20 l.</p>

<p>400 l. to Countess of <em>Craford</em> paying 20 l.</p>

<p>400 l. to Countess of <em>Lowdone</em>, paying 20 l.</p>

<p>Countess of <em>Callender</em> her <reg orig="Joynture">Jointure</reg> conveyed from her former Husband, Earl of <em><reg orig="Dunfermlin">Dunfermline</reg></em>.</p>

<p>200 l. to <em>Mary</em> Earl <em><reg orig="Marshals">Marshall's</reg></em> Daughter, 150 l. on her three Sisters, paying 32 l. 10 s. 300 l. to the Countess of <em>Louderdale</em>, paying 15 l. 200 l. to Lady <em>Cranston</em>, paying 10 l. 250 l. to Lady <em>Bargany</em>, paying 12 l. 10 s. 120 l. to Lady <em>Thomson</em>, paying 6 l.</p>

<p>4 An Ordinance for settling the Estates of those several excepted persons in Scotland, in Sir <em>John Hope, Wil. Lockard</em>, Esq; <em>Rich. Sallonstal</em>, and <em>Edw Siler</em> Commissioners at <em>Leith</em>. L. Col. <em>Wilks</em>, Deputy Governor of <em>Leith</em>, <em>David Barkley</em> Esq; and <em>John Harper</em> Advocate Trustees for the use of His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Successors, for the benefit of the Commonwealth.</p><pb n="14" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday 26 April.</i></head>

<p><i>Dalkieth 20 April. Col. Morgan is marched from Dunghil to Tay. On Thursday 1000 Foot (supposed Loughabecians) marched over the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> above Brahan towards Southerland. Sir Geo. Monroe and Glencarn have had a Duel about the plundering of the Laird Fowls (Brother to Sir George) in which Glencarn was cut in the head and Monroe had his right hand almost cut off and a cut in his Forehead. There was also a quarrel between Athol and Glengarry about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg> of place, and the field appointed but the business was taken up by the Commanders. Our <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> near <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> have this week fallen into divers of the <reg orig="enemies">enemy's</reg> quarters, and taken divers prisoners and amongst the rest a party from Buhaanon marched into the Parish of Strablame, where Cap. Cunningham was taken, and Capt. Edmiston narrowly <reg orig="mist">missed</reg>, he and some others got away, leaving their Breeches behind them, and what papers and <reg orig="mony">money</reg> they had in them, for haste. Gen. Monk is this night at <reg orig="Barwick">Berwick</reg>.</i></p>

<p>This day the Proclamation for Peace was Proclaimed by 12 Trumpets, and 4 Heralds at Arms, first at Whitehall before his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his Council (both Courts being full of People, and loud acclamations, crying <i>God <reg orig="blesse">bless</reg> the Lord Protector</i>, And afterwards in the City of <em>London</em>, met by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen at Temple bar; and Proclaimed in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg> , the Exchange, and other places. The people much <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg>, and great <reg orig="Fire-works">Fireworks</reg> were made by water at night, before the Dutch Ambassadors Lodgings at Sir <em>John Trevers</em> at <em>Westminster</em>.</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector</head>

<head level="3"><i>A <em>PROCLAMATION</em> Of the <em>PEACE</em> made between this Commonwealth, and that of the United Provinces of the <em>Netherlands</em>.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, considering how necessary it is, not only to preserve Peace and Quiet at home, but as far as in him lies, to live in Amity and Friendship with his Neighbours, hath by the blessing of God, with the advice of his <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, made and concluded a Peace, Union and Confederation to continue for ever, between this Commonwealth of the one part, and that of the United Provinces of the Low Countries of the other part; their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories, Places and People, by Sea, Land Fresh waters and elsewhere; By the which Peace it is agreed, That all Enmity, Hostility, Discord and War between the said Commonwealths, their People and Subjects shall cease, and all injuries and Wrongs whatsoever done since the 11 of <em>May</em>, One<pb n="15" /> thousand six hundred fifty two, shall cease, and <reg orig="bee">be</reg> forgotten, except such Depredations as shall <reg orig="bee">be</reg> committed by either side in these seas after twelve days, from the date of these presents, and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks; and from thence, within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranian">Mediterranean</reg></em> Sea, and to the <em>&AElig;quinoctiall</em> Line, after ten weeks; and beyond the <em>&AElig;noctiall</em> Line, after the space of eight Months, or immediately after sufficient notice of the said Peace given in those places. And that the People and Inhabitants of each party respectively, of what quality of condition soever they <reg orig="bee">be</reg>, shall treat each other with love and Friendship, and may freely and securely come into, and <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> through each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Countries, Towns, Villages and Precincts, and there stay and abide, and from thence depart again at their pleasure, without any <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> and molestation and likewise trade and have commerce, and generally do, use, and exercise all other things (observing the Laws and Customs of each place respectively) as freely, fully and securely as they might have done in time of Peace. Whereof all persons whatsoever in these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, are to take notice, and conform themselves accordingly.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 26 day of <em><reg orig="Aprill">April</reg></em> 1654.</i></p>
<p>O.P.</p>

<p>This night are come out new Farthings, weighing a quarter of an ounce fine Pewter, which is but the price of new Pewter; that so the people may never hereafter fear to <reg orig="loose">lose</reg> much by them; with the Harp of one side, and a <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> on the other, with T.K. above it.</p>

<p>The Stationers instead of two <reg orig="Bookes">Books</reg>, are henceforwards to pay 12 d. a Line, and leave no Books.</p>

<head level="3">There is Extant</head>

<p>1 The Duty of Instant <reg orig="Baptisme">Baptism</reg> <reg orig="cleered">cleared</reg> 2. Something about the Sabbath, and the nature and increase of the <reg orig="Kingdome">Kingdom</reg> of Christ, By W. Carter, Minister, and one of the late Assembly of Divines. A Heavenly Conference between Christ and Mary, after his Resurrection, Discovering the familiarity of Christ and a <reg orig="Beleever">Believer</reg>. By Rich. Sibbs DD. And A Warning to Backsliders, in a Sermon at <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Church before the Lord Mayor. By Mr. Ralph Venning. All three sold by John Rothwell in Cheapside, in <reg orig="Goldsmiths">Goldsmith's</reg> Row.</p>

<p>Dr. <reg orig="Drakes">Drake's</reg> Bar to the Sacrament removed, or a Vindication of Mar <reg orig="Humphries">Humphries's</reg> Free Admission to the Sacrament: Wherein the most materials in Dr. Drake are answered; with a Speech to them of the <reg orig="Congregationall">Congregational</reg> way, and an examination of the Scripture <unclear>Real</unclear> made by some Ministers in <reg orig="Glocestershire">Gloucestershire</reg>, done by Jo. Timson, To be sold by Tho. Williams at the Bible in Little <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>