<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="TruePerfInf03">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The True Informer, Issue 03</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The true and Perfect</head>
<head level="1">INFORMER:</head>
<head level="2"><i><reg orig="COMPRIZING">COMPRISING</reg></i></head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Seueral">Several</reg> PROCEEDINGS of the ARMIES both by Sea and Land: As also the</head>
<head level="3">truest Intelligence from all parts of <em>England, Scotland, Ireland, Holland, France, Denmark, Swedeland</em> and divers other places, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the present state of Affairs.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>Appointed by Authority to be printed and published for the true information of the people of this Nation.</i></p>
<hr />
<p><i>From Friday January 13. to Friday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 20. 1653.</i></p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 13.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Holland</em> came as followeth,</p>

<p>Here hath again been a great loss to this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, both by fire and water, and all occasioned by a great storm of wind last Tuesday, all day and all night. But the first cause is doubtless the wrath of God against this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, which is so evident that truly <reg orig="every body">everybody</reg> feel it, and few that have any grace, but <reg orig="wil">will</reg> confess it also: But are <reg orig="stil">still</reg> as ignorant how to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg> this anger of the Lord, as if they never had had <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Word amongst them. It is true, the common sins of Pride, Whoredome, Drunkenness, and Excess, are generally <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out against, as the cause of all our miseries, and doubtless these sins do much provoke the Lord, being come to so great a height in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>: But these sins are too common to all Nations, especially in prosperity, and therefore the wiser sort do find fault with one another, <em>Adam</em> and <em>Eve</em> like, but very few that lay these things to heart, so as to say, this sin of mine is a cause, and so forsake the same.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>The Dutch Deputies are now gone over to <em>Holland</em>, yet there is some hopes there may be a conclusion of peace, which will be within ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, or else none likely.</p>

<p>The English Fleet is still in the Channel and General Pen with them, Gen. Blake, Gen. Monk, and General Desborough are returned to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Monk is ordered to go for Scotland.</p>

<p>This day the Ambassador newly come over from the King of France, had audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, whom he congratulated in his new Government.</p>

<p>Letters from France say, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> at the Palace <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> in Paris, feasted the French King, with some French Lords and Ladies and there were his brothers the Duke of York and <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, Prince Rupert is come thither, but it holds true, that Prince Maurice is drowned.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration by the Commander in Chief of the forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent, That [notwithstanding my Proclamation of Septem. 27. last] many serviceable horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great disservice of the Peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much connivance of the Owners or Possessors: These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons, who now are or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable horses or Mares, exceeding the value of 5 l. sterling, to bring in the same within 48. hours next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such horses, and mares, as shall not be brought in the one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the use of the State and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to the party informing, but also be deemed as an open enemy, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and seal at Dalkieth, Decem. 14. 1653.</i></p>
<p><i>R. Lilburn.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the prisoners taken at Glans.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Kinoule Alexander Nipper Capt. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> English late Foot <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> in Dundee, but reduced. <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Bowter, Patrick Henry Fetchry. William Moward. Patrick Knock. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Hamilton. Rob Jackson. James Blayer, Laird of Balgello his Brother, Laird Ross, late Captain at Worcester.</p><pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>Saturday Jan. 14.</i></head>

<p><i>This day the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> considered of the business touching his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="houshold">household</reg>, and made some progress therein.</i></p>

<p><i>By Letters from Captain <em>Foster</em>, Commander of the Ph&oelig;nix <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, dated in <em>Ously Bay</em> the 5. of <em><reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>, 1653</em>. Was this day <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that he had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, with the safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the other ships and <reg orig="Vessells">Vessels</reg> appointed to attend his Lordship, Decem: 17 last at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, where he was honourably received by the Governor, and the Magistrates of that City. And his Lordship went his voyage towards Stockholm with rainy blustering weather.</i></p>

<p>The 21. of December, he came out with his ship when the wind blew hard with much snow, endeavouring the Yutish coast, anchored in ten fathom water, and discovered a Fleet of ships; and December 22. in the morning got the <reg orig="weathergage">weather gage</reg> of them, endeavoured to discover what men of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> were amongst them, and saw only one ship of countenance, and a private Man of War of eight Guns. The Fleet being Hollanders, ran from the Sound; and 72 sail, some with 6. some four, others two Guns, upon our Guns firing amongst them, cut their cables and run towards the Sound; but before they got clear we boarded and manned three of them, which prizes were kept to the windward of us, and about 8 a clock we engaged them.</p>

<p>After the passing of two <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, the private Man of war ran after their Fleet, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> continued the Dispute <reg orig="untill">until</reg> 4 a clock at night, (at which time <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <reg orig="past">passed</reg> <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg> close board and board as fast as <reg orig="wee">we</reg> could tack our ships.) The Enemy then ran towards his Fleet, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> pursued him, and after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, intended to board him; and though our Boultsprit shot by the board, our Main and <reg orig="Fore-mast">Foremast</reg> shot through, scarce a shroud whole, our Hull much shot, four of our men slain, and eleven wounded; he <reg orig="fireing">firing</reg> as he retreated, yet we made him in such a sinking condition, that <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he fired his Guns, he called to his Fleet to save his men, about 4 leagues off at Anchor under an <reg orig="Iland">Island</reg>.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>About 400 horse and foot were looking on us from the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, we received shot from the Enemy of 36. l. weight. But night <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> our pursuit.</p>

<p>About three in the afternoon next day three Holland men of war (two of them very great ships) being come from Holland to convoy their Fleet, came right before the <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> upon us, we then bore to our prizes, took <reg orig="al">all</reg> our men out of them and would have fired them had we had time.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan. 16.</i></head>

<p>The last news from <em>Warsovia</em>, that the King with all his Army, consisting of above eighty thousand men Horse and Foot, was upon their March to encounter the Tartars and <reg orig="Cosacks">Cossacks</reg>, who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together, but remain asunder, being in two distinct bodies: By some prisoners lately brought to his Majesty, we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that the General of the Cossacks hath made a particular Treaty with the Kam of the <reg orig="Tartares">Tartars</reg> which if true will exclude him from making any peace or accommodation with the Crown of <em>Poland</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg></em> thus: The <em>Diet</em> is not yet concluded, there being new differences <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> between the Prince Elector, and his <reg orig="Vncle">Uncle</reg> the Duke of <em>Simmeren</em>, about the enjoying of some Land which each other pretended to be his. Some Commissioners are appointed to examine the matter, and so to report it: as also some differences <reg orig="betwen">between</reg> the Landgraves William, and the Earnest of Hassia,</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Dusseldorf">D&uuml;sseldorf</reg></em> we are advertised thus: The duke of Newburgh is still at Mulheim, being not well pleased with the Assembly met in this City, by reason that they have denied him the sums of money which <reg orig="hee">he</reg> demanded of them.</p>

<p>The difference between the City of <em>Cullen</em> and their Elector is <reg orig="neer">near</reg> agreed, he having set at liberty all the Barges and Boats, which by his order had been stopped at <em>Bonna</em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Italie">Italy</reg></em> and parts adjacent came information thus: The Infanta Maria of Saucy is here at Rome, but yet as <em>incognito</em>; she intends to remain here for some time.</p>

<p>The Pope hath also given several <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg>, and other good Benefices to <reg orig="som">some</reg> of his <reg orig="domestique">domestic</reg> Servants, and appointed new <reg orig="Nuntioes">Nuncios</reg> to go into several places of those parts.</p><pb n="4" />

<p><i><em>From Genoa thus</em>: We hear from Madrid, that an Express was come to the Court to inform his Majesty that there was landed at Coronna in Galazia, three thousand Irish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> who were appointed to Winter Quarters, which doth something startle the Portugals, who made a <reg orig="shew">show</reg> as if they would have besieged Cindad Rodrigo. The Duke of Tursie is also expected at Barulona with four Galleys, who are to bring good store of Ammunition and Moneys for the payment of the Garrison: One of the Spanish Galleys hath lately taken a very rich prize upon the French, being a ship bound for Marscillis.</i></p>

<p>Concerning our Fleet by Letters from Portsmouth thus, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Blake</em> and General <em>Monk</em> being now at London, General <em>Pen</em> rides as Admiral of the Fleet without St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point, three Leagues from Portsmouth, with forty sail of gallant ships ready upon any advice of the Dutch ships coming out to put to Sea: Some part of them are already sent out to ply between this place and the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, and over upon the coast of France, to suppress the Brest and Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, who of late begin to be strong, and have done much harm upon the Western Coast.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conti</em> is not yet <reg orig="arived">arrived</reg>, but is expected here <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> there is a strong report that this Prince intends to match with one of the <reg orig="Cardinals">Cardinal's</reg> Nieces, but many are of a contrary opinion, which is truest, will be known very shortly.</p>

<p>The Lord Chancellor hath been this week at the Parliament, to have a <reg orig="Supersedeas">Supersedes</reg> to the passing the Declaration which is drawn up against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, the same to continue for six weeks.</p>

<p>The Cardinal <em>de Retz</em> doth still lie a close prisoner, there being little hopes as yet of any <reg orig="inlargement">enlargement</reg>, his Antagonist the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> being very obstinate in the demand he hath made so many times, that he should resign his Coadjutership of Paris, and to <reg orig="intice">entice</reg> him the more there is offered him the two rich <reg orig="Abbies">Abbeys</reg> of S. <em>Denis</em> and <em>Cluni</em>, which offer he will by no means accept.</p>

<p>There are yet come no Letters from Holland, since the Dutch Deputies were come back there; but private Letters from thence dated Friday was sevennight last, the day the Deputies set out from hence say, that the States were very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in preparing a sudden Dispatch for their Answer, which report tends probably to yeace (in their judgment) their Deputy Monsieur <em>Borrel</em> in France gives out report there, that the States have agreed to the English offers for peace.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Jan. 17.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we received information, that by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a pretended Commission from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, Glencarn</em>, whom the Highlanders call their <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, issueth forth Warrants for the levying of horse, men and arms in a high nature, beginning thus.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg>, Earl of Glencarn and Kenmore, &amp;c.</em> These are straightly to charge and command you, to levy and have in readiness out of your Shiredom one hundred horse well manned and armed, by the <!-- blank space covering up a day of the month --> day of January; at which time you shall receive further Orders from me, to repair to such place of <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> as shall be appointed: Whereof you are not to fail, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<p>Our men are drawn forth of <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and other garrisons, and are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in chasing the enemy from place to place, and daily take many of these thieving Villains, and three Regiments are marched from hence towards Scotland, it is likely they would soon be <reg orig="quell'd">quelled</reg> if they would stand to fight.</p>

<p>From <em>Portsmouth</em> they write, that a Squadron of our Fleet have taken very lately six <reg orig="prises">prizes</reg> from the Hollanders.</p>

<p>The preparations for War in <em>Holland</em> are very great, and they talk of some great matters agreed upon betwixt them and the French, but nothing openly declared, till they hear what becomes of their <em>Treaty</em> with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Gottenburgh, Novemb. 30.</em> After that Captain <em>Welch</em> had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, he put to Sea again, and met with two Hollanders riding at the <em>Scah</em>, the one 400. the other the 350 <reg orig="Tuns">Tonnes</reg>, laden with Wheat, <reg orig="Rie">Rye</reg>, Wool, and Planks, both which he took, and brought away with him, and by storm was forced to come a little way within this port, but without the command of the Forts. The Lord Ambassador was earnestly pressed to send for the Captain, and to discharge the prizes, but answer was given, that it was conceived a matter not appertaining either to himself, or the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Officers to meddle with; and believed, that the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> ports would not be denied to any <reg orig="English-man">Englishman</reg>, who had Commission by Authority of Parliament, coming here to shelter himself against storms: That the Conflict had been upon the high Seas, betwixt the English and Dutch, who were enemies. For these Reasons, his Excellency the Lord Ambassador refused to do <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in it.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday Jan. 18.</i></head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Lime</em> we are advertised by a Barque that came from <em>Brittania</em>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch <reg orig="Pickeroon">Picaroon</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Vshant</em>, gave him chase, and followed so close, that he forces him to run on ground on the hither side of the Bay of Camaret, and by reason of his shooting hard at him, made the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to come down to the Water side, it happened that some shot did make execution on the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, there being four killed and wounded; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> being all <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg> thereby, could not fetch her off; but ours put to Sea again, to <reg orig="cleare">clear</reg> from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> other Letters from Scotland we received information to this effect.</p>

<p>The Highlanders continue their stealing, and plundering of their own <reg orig="Countreymen">Countrymen</reg> that will not rise with them, or pay the Contribution Money that they lay upon them, though I am confident many have not <reg orig="wherewithall">wherewithal</reg> to subsist, paying likewise their <reg orig="Assessements">Assessments</reg> for the maintenance of the English Army; but when Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em> Commissary General <em>Whalley's</em> Regiment of Horse, with Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment of Foot, which we hear are upon their march, are come in to us, we doubt not but to send this Heathenish and plundering Enemy so far back into the Highlands, as that they shall not dare to approach the Lowlands, whereby to do the Inhabitants any considerable hurt: And how the Highlanders are able to keep horse foot, is <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to be imagined, all their <reg orig="dependance">dependence</reg> being upon <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> with the Dutch for Money and Arms; but a peace with Holland, (which we hear is in a very probable way for a very speedy conclusion) disperses them to their several mountainous habitations without ever drawing the sword against them; and then the Lords and Chieftains amongst them, may expect a liberal reward of Justice for doing their Master such rebellious service, which hath been, and is destructive to the generality of Scotland, that a few <reg orig="months">month's</reg> continuance will bring them to the sad condition of the Irish, that have been forced to eat the <reg orig="corps">corpse</reg> of their deceased Friends after many days interment; yet are not the people of Scotland very much to be pitied, in regard they will <reg orig="seldome">seldom</reg> give notice to any of our Garrisons, when any party of the Enemy marches through the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might <reg orig="bee">be</reg> the better preserved from their violences and cruelty, choosing rather to<pb n="7" /> be willingly destroyed by them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> be treacherous, as they call it, to their own <reg orig="Countrey-men">Countrymen</reg>. Some Arms they pretend are lately landed for the Enemy in Scotland, but this is more to encourage their forces and naked party, <reg orig="then">than</reg> otherwise considerable.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday Jan. 19:</i></head>

<p>From Dartmouth, <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 12. thus: The Hector hath sent in a ship hither, which hath in her 3000 Cheeses. The ship is of Amsterdam, and took in her lading at the Elve. There is a private Man of War hath brought in a ship of Rotterdam, laden with Herrings and Holland cheeses, and about ten <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> of Pepper, and some Cloves.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Brother is by an Order of the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, removed back from the Tower to Newgate. By Letters from on board the Swift-Sure, dated the 11 of <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 1653. was certified the <reg orig="Exeminations">Examinations</reg> of some <reg orig="forrain">foreign</reg> Ships that came in to find Market for Deals, Pitch, Tar, Iron, Steel, and other commodities, &amp;c. The Officers from the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Garrisons and Regiments, are very unanimous in signing the said Address which is from most parts of England already sent up to his Highness, and the rest <reg orig="neere">near</reg> finished, as is expressed by Letters from their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Quarters.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Dublin</em> in <em>Ireland</em>, was this day certified, That <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> General Fleetwood and the Commissioners, are at <em>Dublin</em>, all is quiet there, and content at the New Government in <em>England</em>, and satisfied in it. That the Lord <em>Musgrove</em> is to be tried the beginning of the next <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>; That all is very quiet in <em>Ireland</em>, save some small parties of the Tories, which are chiefly about the County of <em>Carlow</em>, where they lately fell upon, and wounded <reg orig="som">some</reg> of the <reg orig="Surveyers">Surveyors</reg>, and do <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> rob and steal where they dare venture, and fly away <reg orig="againe">again</reg> presently.</p>

<p>An Ambassador from <reg orig="Hamburgh">Hamburg</reg> was this day to congratulate His Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. His Highness and also the Council, were this upon matters of great concernment.</p>

<p><i>This is Extracted out of the Original papers <unclear><!--approx. half a line --></unclear> to the late Act for Printing.</i></p>

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>T. Lock</em>, living in <unclear><!-- approx. a third of a line --></unclear> sign <!-- there seems to be writing missed off the bottom of the page here --></p>
</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>