<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="TruePerfInf01">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The True (and Perfect) Informer, Issue 01</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">True Informer</head>
<head level="2"><i><reg orig="COMPRIZING">COMPRISING</reg></i></head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Seueral">Several</reg> PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="1">STATE AFFAIRS</head>
<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">With the Transactions and Affairs in other Nations.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From Friday December 30. to Friday January 6. 1653.</i></p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday Decemb. 30.</i></head>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> is going to the <em>Hope</em>, a Fleet of 50 ships are already out together in the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg>, and more will suddenly be with them.</p>

<p>If the <em>Dutch</em> do break off, and refuse to confirm a peace with <em>England</em>, let them expect that God will have a greater <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> with them <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever before; It is good for there to hear in their day things that belong to their peace, lest another day they be hid from their eyes.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> 29 December</em>, The enemy still go on with their levies in several parts of the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, and will be numerous, do what we can to prevent them, though I see not how they can hold together in a body when <reg orig="conjoyned">conjoined</reg>, the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> not being able to bear them. <em>Kenmore</em> lies up towards the Bray of Mane, and in the Glens that way, within the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Woods and Rivers, and all along in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> fast places from Lough Tay, towards the Brays of Stermont and Angus.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>From <em>Dalkeith, December 27.</em> we are advertised thus. The enemy is departed from the hithermost parts of <em>Athol</em>, and <reg orig="gon">gone</reg> to <em>Kirkmichel</em> in order to their march Northwards; as I am informed <em>Kenmore</em> and <em>Glencarn</em> are both there, and their force reported to <reg orig="bee">be</reg> 500. Foot, and 500. Horse; but those that gave me information that saw them, affirm they are not half that number, they lie under very many discouragements, and every place so eaten up where they come, that they are forced upon often <reg orig="removalls">removals</reg>, and now provision of Mutton and Beef begins to decay: I hear they intend for the North, that their Quarters upon the Lowlands may be more assured and broader, where they expect the landing of <reg orig="Forrain">Foreign</reg> Forces, Ammunition and Money from their Majesty and the States of <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p><em>Athol</em> doth nothing considerable; the people refuse to <unclear><reg orig="uise">use</reg></unclear> his men according to command, one that saw him and his <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, he hath not got above forty Foot, and Major <em>Mercer</em> is there with about 60. Horse.</p>

<p>Captain <em>Elsemore</em>, of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Riches">Riche's</reg> Regiment</em>, sent out a party the other day from <em>Drummond</em> Castle, who took one Captain <em>Stuart</em>, who had a Commission from <em>Lorne</em> to raise Forces, and four others, and killed three on the place. The Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> last week at his house of <em>Bogygeith</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Darwicks, Decemb. 28.</em> thus: A private Man of War, we have intelligence, hath brought into Holy Land two Dutch Vessels, coming from the East Country, both being about an hundred and fifty <reg orig="tun">ton</reg> burthen, laden with Pitch Tar, and the like Commodities.</p>

<p>From Falmouth, the 2 instant, we received intelligence, That there were many ships in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> which are now all gone to their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> intended Ports: The Dutch are still very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in these parts, so that it is very hard to pass by the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end without a good Convoy. They have, we hear, taken a ship of London, <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> from New-England, laden with Masts, Beaver-skins, and the like commodities. Here have<pb n="2" /> been some of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships to wash and tallow, and to take in fresh water, but they are all at Sea again, there remaining none at present in this <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday Decem. 31.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Deal Decemb. 29.</em> We received this day intelligence, That some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken some Beelanders belonging to <em>Calice</em>, who were bound for <em>Roan</em> and <em>Cane</em> in <em>Normandy</em>, laden with divers sorts of commodities, and carried them into Stoaks Bay, where we <reg orig="heare">hear</reg> that <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monke">Monk</reg></em> with his Squadron was about <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since: Those ships lately gone from hence bound for Roan are safely arrived there and their Convoy is returned back.</p>

<p>On Wednesday morning a party of these Royal Pilferers met the Post-boy going from Leith with Letters for London, and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Haddington took his horse and Letters, and some money, so that now it will be uncertain sending Letters <reg orig="with out">without</reg> a Convoy.</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Powel</em> were brought before his Highness the Lord Protector and his Council, and examined touching some words that fell from them in preaching and praying concerning the present Government, and were ordered to remain in the hands of the <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> at Arms <reg orig="untill">until</reg> further consideration.</p>

<head level="3">From the <em>Downs, Decem. 29</em>. thus.</head>

<p>Capt. Richard Newberry, Commander of the Lawrell, is come in hither, who had been out by order from the Generals, with his ship and the Ruby, the Kent and the Industry, to ply between the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> of Wight and the French coasts, where he took some prizes, when they were towards the French coasts, they made a discovery of four <reg orig="sale">sail</reg> of ships, to whom they gave chase, and followed them so close that they took two of them. Men were taken out of the ship <reg orig="cald">called</reg> the Kent, to man one of the prizes, which is come hither into the <em>Downs</em>.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan 2.</i></head>

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, with his honourable <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg>, had the large and last conference at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg> with the Dutch Ambassadors, where his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> insisted upon the ensuing propositions. <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>1. That satisfaction be given for all the injuries and wrongs sustained by the English, since the first affront offered by <em>Van trump</em> upon the Downs.</p>

<p>2. That they shall pay the same contribution and <reg orig="custome">custom</reg> for fishing upon the Narrow Seas, as was formerly paid in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of Qu: <em>Elizabeth</em>.</p>

<p>3. That the dominion of the Seas be invested upon the English, and that all such Vessels whatsoever that carries the <em>Dutch</em> <reg orig="colors">colours</reg>, shall strike sail unto the ships of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland or Ireland.</p>

<p>4. That Security be given, for performance of all the particular Articles contained in the Treaty &amp;c.</p>

<p>To which the Lord Ambassadors returned Answer, That they could not assent unto the proposals, without further Instructions, and desired a Convoy for their <reg orig="owne">own</reg> <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, whereby they might return an account of the Transactions of the Treaty, and be <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> with further Instructions if convenient. Whereupon a convoy was appointed, and in the evening about 9 of the clock, they <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth in a stately Barge towards Gravesend.</p>

<p>The Spanish and <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> Ambassadors have likewise congratulated his Highness, and have so far agreed, that the Lord <em>Pontania Sasa</em>, brother to the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> removed from Newgate to the Tower of London.</p>

<p>This day we received intelligence from the titular King of Scots, that he sent a Letter to <em>Glencarn</em>, dated <em>Decemb. 21.</em> telling him, <i>That the King of France and Denmark, the Duke<pb n="4" /> of Brandenburg, the Emperor and Princes of Germany, are not willing to assist him with men, but have assured him of a large proportion of Arms, Ammunition and Moneys, and that he would be with them immediately after the receiving of Drummond and his forces, whose <reg orig="head quarters">headquarters</reg> is to be at Longhorn, the most fortified place in the Highlands.</i></p>

<p>France and we are yet at a distance; their Ambassador hath had no audience of late, he is waiting to see what will be the issue of the Treaty in England.</p>

<p>The Assistance and the <reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> sailed over to Vshant and Cruse, and parts <reg orig="there about">thereabout</reg> seven or eight days, and they were together at the Fourn Rock. And <em>decem</em>. The 29, they sailed both together within Vshant, and being got thither they sailed into Conquet Road, and there anchored awhile, after which they went out again and plied even into the very mouth of Brest River, but the Brest men durst not stir out; whereupon our ships in the evening anchored in Cammerit Bay, to see if there they could <reg orig="finde">find</reg>, or thereabouts meet with any of <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> <reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> ships, or others of those of Brest Men of War. But they had <unclear>selkt</unclear> in, and durst none of them venture out.</p>

<p>There was a <reg orig="Fly boat">Flyboat</reg>, a Vessel of eight Guns, and some six small ships more, who upon our approach ran themselves <reg orig="ashoare">ashore</reg>, and we have since taken three prizes about Conquet Road.</p>

<p>By Letters from Swedeland it is advertised, That the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> from England is safely come thither with his retinue, joyfully received, and in good health.</p>

<p>I hear there are some English prizes brought in lately into Zealand, taken by some of their Men of War: that province is generally more inclined to War <reg orig="then">than</reg> any of the rest, thought they have thriven no better by it <reg orig="then">than</reg> their Confederates.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Jan. 3.</i></head>

<head level="2"><i>The oath taken by his Highness <em><reg orig="Oliuer">Oliver</reg> <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Major part of the last Parliament (judging that their sitting any longer, as <reg orig="then">than</reg> constituted, would not be for the good of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>) did dissolve the same, and by a writing under their hands, dated the twelfth day of this instant December, resigned unto Me their Powers and Authorities: And whereas it was necessary thereupon, That <reg orig="som">some</reg> speedy course should be taken for the speedy settlement of these Nations upon such a Basis and Foundation, as (by the blessing of God) might be lasting, secure Property, and answer those great ends of Religion and Liberty, so long contended for; and upon full and mature consideration had of the Form of Government hereunto annexed, being satisfied that the same through Divine assistance, may answer the Ends <reg orig="afore mentioned">aforementioned</reg>: And having also been desired and advised, as well by several Persons of Interest and Fidelity in this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, as the Officers of the Army to take upon Me the protection and Government of these Nations in the manner expressed in the said Form of Government, I have accepted thereof, and do hereby declare my acceptance accordingly. And do promise in the Presence of God, That I will not violate or infringe the matters and things contained therein, but to my power, observe<pb n="6" /> the same, and cause them to be observed; And shall in all other things, to the best of my understanding Govern these Nations according to the Laws, Statutes and Customs, seeking their Peace, and causing Justice and Law to be equally <reg orig="administred">administered</reg>.</p>

<p>O. CROMWELL.</p>

<p><i><em>Oliver Cromwell</em>, Captain General of all the Forces of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and now declared <em>Lord Protector</em> thereof, did this sixteenth day of <em>December, 1653</em>. sign this Writing, and solemnly promise, as is therein contained, in presence of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, who <reg orig="administred">administered</reg> the same Oath, and of the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of the City of <em>London</em>, divers of the Judges of the Land, the Officers of State and Army and many other persons of Quality.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 4.</i></head>

<p>From Scotland, December 30 we received intelligence, <i>That the Enemies disperse themselves into several parts: They are now endeavouring to reduce their levies into form, by laying them upon all the nearest Parishes to the Hills, but their demands are so high, that it is impossible the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> though willing, should be able to bear them.</i></p>

<p><i>We received information that <em>Kenmore</em> will use all his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise and force men horses and moneys in the South, and intends to make <reg orig="som">some</reg> Inroads into the Borders of <em>England</em> unless prevented, which is the more probable by that information from <em>Durham</em>, That twenty <reg orig="horse-men">horsemen</reg> well mounted, and armed with <reg orig="pistolls">pistols</reg> and swords, went through that Town on Tuesday last by break of day, and amongst them a person of quality.</i></p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em> <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 5.</head>

<head level="3"><i>From Pembrook, Decemb. 25.</i></head>

<p>On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last we had here the fearfullest Thunder, Lightning and Rain as hath been heard of, and some <reg orig="cattel">cattle</reg> <reg orig="destroyd">destroyed</reg> thereby. The Lord speak peace to his people, many constructions poor people make thereof.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 4. 1653.</i></head>

<p><i>The Trustees for the sale of <reg orig="Forrest">Forest</reg> Lands, have appointed upon Tuesday next, the tenth of this instant January, in the forenoon, to sit for the allowance of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Faith Bills to be doubled upon security of the said Lands, and thenceforth weekly every Tuesday in the forenoon, till the sum to be doubled be full.</i></p>

<p>William <reg orig="Tayleure">Taylor</reg> Secr. to the said Trustees.</p>

<p><em>Whitehall Jan. 2.</em> The <em>Dutch Deputies</em> had their last conference and spent the whole day therein; but came to no conclusion. The next News we hear of them is, That <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 3. they departed from their house, sent their Goods a shipboard, and <reg orig="them selves">themselves</reg> went after about nine of the clock the same night.</p>

<p>We hear no news from Sea, save that our fleet rides on the <reg orig="Channell">Channel</reg>: And that we have last two ships of eighteen Guns, and four hundred <reg orig="Tuns">Tonnes</reg> a piece, laden with masts, and some other commodities; which were taken by certain <em>dutch</em> men of War this last week and carried into <em>Flushing</em>.</p>

<head level="3">Thus have you represented.</head>

<p><i>The great strength of the Highlanders: and their coming up within ten miles of <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>: and the cruel murder and bloody execution done upon the English. Also the proposals and demands of his Highness the Lord Protector to the Lord Ambassadors from the States of Holland as <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last at Whitehall upon their great conference and Treaty, touching the dominion of the Seas and the Customs of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em> and their <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> Answer thereunto; and their departure from London on Tuesday night last: With the strange Thunder and lamentable Lightning and Rain, which <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> in Pembroke.</i></p>

<hr />

<p><em>LONDON</em>, Printed by <em>T. LOCK.</em> 1653.</p> 


</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>