<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="TruePerfInf02">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The True (and Perfect) Informer, Issue 2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">True Informer</head>
<head level="2"><i><reg orig="COMPRIZING">COMPRISING</reg></i></head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Seueral">Several</reg> PROCEEDINGS</head>
<head level="2">OF</head>
<head level="1">STATE AFFAIRS</head>
<head level="2">In <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</head>
<head level="3">With the Transactions and Affairs in other Nations.</head>
<hr />
<p><i>From Friday January 6. to Friday <reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg> 13. 1653.</i></p>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Beginning Friday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 6.</i></head>

<p>The Dutch Deputies are now gone over to <em>Holland</em>, yet there is some few hopes there may be a conclusion of peace which will be within ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, or else none likely.</p>

<p>The English Fleet is still in the Channel and General Pen with them, Gen. Blake, Gen. Monk, and General Desborough are returned to <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the prisoners taken at Glans.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Kinoole Alexander Nippr Capt. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> English late Foot <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> in Dundee, but reduced. <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Bowter, Patrick Rols, Henry Fetchry. William Moward. Patrick Knock. <reg orig="Iohn">John</reg> Hamilton. Rob Jackson. James Slayer, Laird of Balgello his Brother late Captain at Worcester.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>The States assembled in <em>Province</em> are now sitting at <em>Bagnolle</em>, where the Duke of <em>Mercoeur</em> the Governor, and the other Procurators are also gone, they <reg orig="doe">do</reg> sit daily, and hope to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> many abuses, and redress grievances which do much burthen the people there. The Commissioners appointed to draw out the Charge of high treason against the Prince of Conde have met <reg orig="severall">several</reg> times, and it is said that it is finished, only it wants <reg orig="ingrossing">engrossing</reg>. We received Information that the Prince hath surprised a little town and Castle in Champagne, and <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> pitifully: A List hath been brought to his Majesty of the Regiment of the Guard, which is found to consist of about 6000. men fit for service.</p>

<p>From <em>Warwick <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg> 5.</em> we received information, That Mr. <em>Bulstrode</em>, one of the <reg orig="Iudges">Judges</reg> of North Wales, came hither by a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> Commission of <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> delivery, he heard a Sermon on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning, and went directly from thence to the Hall, where there was a very great appearance, and a very able grand <reg orig="Iury">Jury</reg>, there hath not been a greater <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg> known these many <reg orig="yeers">years</reg>: there is five men and one woman condemned to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg>; seven likewise burned in the hand, and two men would not plead to be pressed: the <reg orig="Iudge">Judge</reg> used his <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to plead, telling them what a sad condition they would bring themselves into; but the resolute villains were resolved to die in their wickedness, I will assure you the <reg orig="Iudge">Judge</reg> carried the business very well, and gave the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> a great deal of satisfaction; he spake something in his charge in relation to the late Government, he said that it was now <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> upon such a Basis as was like to conduce much to the happiness of all good people; he gave strict Orders to the Grand Jury, that if they heard of any that were Perturbers of this, that they should not fail to bring them to the Barr of justice, and a great deal more to the same effect.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 4</em> thus. We received this day intelligence, That some of our <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> have taken <reg orig="som">some</reg> Beelanders belonging to <em>Calice</em>, who were bound for <em>Roan</em> and <em>Cane</em> in <em>Normandy</em> laden with divers sorts of commodities, and carried them into Stoaks Bay, where we hear that <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Monke">Monk</reg></em> with<pb n="2" /> his Squadron was about <reg orig="foure">four</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since: Those ships lately gone from hence bound for Roan are safely arrived there, and their Convoy is returned back.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Saturday <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 7.</i></head>

<p>From Weymouth Ian. 4. we received intelligence, <i>That a <reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg> <reg orig="Vessell">Vessel</reg> sent out of this Harbour homewards, but a very great storm the same day rose at Sea, and brought the ship back again upon our coast, where she with <reg orig="som">some</reg> others, was cast away in the West-Bay, between Portland and Rotberry, all the men being cast away but the Shipman, and the Passengers that were <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> going over to Jersey or Guernsey.</i></p>

<p><i>From Milford Haven the 4 January. There are <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="Vessells">Vessels</reg> here bound for <em>Ireland</em>, but stayed here by reason of the contrary winds; we have not of late heard any news from thence; The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> are still plying about the Isle of Lundy, and often come into the Severn mouth, where sometimes they catch some of our small Vessels.</i></p>

<p><i>There is nothing more from our Fleet, but that part of them are about Plymouth, and other places to the Westward, some lie out towards the coast of <reg orig="Brittanie">Brittany</reg>, to try if they can meet the Brest Men of War, who have got now good ships, and have a considerable strength at Sea.</i></p>

<p><i>This week is arrived the Fleet from Dunkirk, consisting of about forty sail, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg>, &amp;c. There is come likewise five ships from the Eastland, as also one from Zant with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet not come up to River.</i></p>

<p><i>The Dutch Commissioners, whom we mentioned before to be gone to Gravesend in order to take shipping for Holland, have not yet set sail, but remains there and have made some further application to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, which whether or not it will make an absolute Agreement, or occasion their coming back again a short time <reg orig="wil">will</reg> discover.</i></p>

<p><i>By an Express from Holland, we received certain intelligence, That upon Tuesday last they had about Amsterdam a most mighty<pb n="3" /> Thunder, Lightning and Tempest, and that by this Thunder and lightning there were about 500 houses burnt and destroyed in and <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Amsterdam, besides above 40. <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships <reg orig="sunke">sunk</reg> in the Texel, and many other great damages; But the greatest loss I hear of, was at <em>Rype</em> in <em>North Holland</em>, where an <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>-Mill by the storm, in a violent motion by its own heat took fire in the furiousness of the storm and that burning set divers houses on fire, and one house another, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> some five or six hundred houses were destroyed, and in them many persons burnt alive, and abundance of goods, valued by many to a greater sum <reg orig="then">than</reg> I dare speak of: I could be a great deal larger in relating the full particulars, but for want of room I must omit it <reg orig="untill">until</reg> my next.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Jan 9:</i></head>

<p><i>This day the <reg orig="Councill">Council</reg> considered of the business touching his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="houshold">household</reg>, and made some progress therein.</i></p>

<p><i>By Letters from Captain <em>Foster</em>, Commander of the Ph&oelig;nix <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, dated in <em>Ously Bay</em> the 3. of <em><reg orig="Ianuary">January</reg>, 1653</em>. was this day <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that he had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>, with the safe <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the other ships and <reg orig="Vessells">Vessels</reg> appointed to attend his Lordship, Decem: 17 last at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, where he was honourably received by the Governor, and the Magistrates of that City. And his Lordship went his voyage towards Stockholm with rainy blustering.</i></p>

<p>The 21. of December, he came out with his ship when the wind blew hard with much snow, endeavouring the Yutish coast, anchored in ten fathom water, and discovered a Fleet of ships; and December 22. in the morning got the <reg orig="weathergage">weather gage</reg> of them, endeavoured to discover what men of <reg orig="Warr">War</reg> were amongst them, and saw only one ship of countenance, and a private Man of War of eight Guns. The Fleet being Hollanders, ran from the Sound; and 72 sail, some with 6. some four, others two Guns, upon our Guns firing amongst them, cut their cables<pb n="4" /> and run towards the Sound; but before they got clear we boarded and manned three of them, which prizes were kept to the windward of us, and about 8 a clock we engaged them.</p>

<p>After the passing of two <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, the private Man of war ran after their Fleet, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> continued the Dispute <reg orig="untill">until</reg> 4 a clock at night, (at which time <reg orig="wee">we</reg> <reg orig="past">passed</reg> <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg> close board and board as fast as <reg orig="wee">we</reg> could tack our ships.) The Enemy then ran towards his Fleet, <reg orig="wee">we</reg> pursued him, and after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="broad sides">broadsides</reg>, intended to board him; and though our Boultsprit shot by the board, our Main and <reg orig="Fore-mast">Foremast</reg> shot through, scarce a shroud whole, our Hull much shot, four of our men slain, and eleven wounded; he <reg orig="fireing">firing</reg> as he retreated, yet we made him in such a sinking condition, that <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> he fired his Guns, he called to his Fleet to save his men, about 4 leagues off at Anchor under an <reg orig="Iland">Island</reg>.</p>

<p>About 400 horse and foot were looking on us from the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, we received shot from the Enemy of 36. l. weight. But night <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> our pursuit.</p>

<p>About three in the afternoon next day three Holland men of war (two of them very great ships) being come from Holland to convoy their Fleet, came right before the <reg orig="winde">wind</reg> upon us, we then bore to our prizes, took all our men out of them and would have fired them had we had time.</p>

<p>The Spanish and <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg> Ambassadors have likewise congratulated his Highness, and have so far agreed, that the Lord <em>Pontania Sasa</em>, brother to the <reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg>, <reg orig="bee">be</reg> removed from Newgate to the Tower of London.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Jan. 10.</i></head>

<p><reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Whitemore of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Regiment, went up lately to the Hills, and took forty sheep and five Cows, which Sir <em>Mungoe Murtag</em> their Quartermaster General sent forth of the Highlands to be kept <reg orig="neer">near</reg> his own house, Sir <reg orig="Mungoes">Mungoe's</reg> man, and one horse of the Laird of <em>Lowes</em>, who took Capt. <em>Townsend</em> and Capt. <em>Scroop</em>, but the Rider <reg orig="escapt">escaped</reg>: Yesterday a party of the Tories met with four of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> Troop of Dragoons <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Levingston</em> house, about ten miles from <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, whom they barbarously <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg>, one of them fled into the house for safety, but the people would not protect him, but left him to the cruelty of those Villains. A party of our Dragoons from the Bray of <em>Mane</em>, fell upon the enemy, killed one, wounded three, and <reg orig="foure">four</reg> horses, I cannot think there is a pack of more merciless Miscreants in the whole world than these now gathered together in this <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and many of them were at <em>Dunbar</em>, and <em>Worcester</em>, and had liberty granted them through our too much lenity.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> Jan. 6. thus. The last News from our Army in <em>Alsatia</em> imply, That the <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> <em>de la Ferte</em> hath invested Beffort, and is now making his Lines of Communication, and other works belonging to a siege: there hath been several pieces of Ordnance drawn out of <em>Nancy</em>, which are on the way, and will come to the Leagure as soon as any Batteries will be raised for to plant them upon: The Marquis <em>de Uxeles</em> is to be <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and is expected there with three thousand men. This <reg orig="Designe">Design</reg> hath much <reg orig="allarmed">alarmed</reg> the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and so much the more the <reg orig="yeelding">yielding</reg> up of the strong Castle of <em><reg orig="Philipsburgh">Philipsburg</reg></em>, which was taken by a <reg orig="surprizall">surprisal</reg> without the loss of one man. The manner thus. The Deputy Governor being gone a hunting, with some of the high Officers of that Garrison, notice being given to one of the <reg orig="Cardinalls">Cardinal's</reg> creatures, he <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg> with alacrity that occasion, and being come into the place, he so prevailed upon the Garrison, that he became Master of the place, and this Deputy<pb n="6" /> Governor being come in the evening, knowing not what had passed, found the Bridge drawn up, and entrance <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> him, whereupon he was forced to retire speedily. The Duke <em>d' Amville</em> being sent by the King to <em>Blois</em> to try once more whether he could prevail with the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>, and so bring him again to the Court, returned back this week, and the report is at Court, that <reg orig="hee">he</reg> hath brought a very good Answer, and that he will be shortly in this City; but others are of a contrary opinion.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday Jan. 11.</i></head>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we received information, that by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a pretended Commission from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart, Glencarn</em>, whom the Highlanders call their <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, issueth forth Warrants for the levying of horse men and arms in a high nature, beginning thus.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg>, Earl of Glencarn and Kenmore, &amp;c.</em> These are <reg orig="straitly">straightly</reg> to charge and command you, to levy and have in readiness out of your Shiredom one hundred horse well manned and armed, by the <!-- blank space covering up a day of the month --> day of January; at which time you shall receive further Orders from me, to repair to such place of <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> as shall be appointed: Whereof you are not to fail, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<p>Our men are drawn forth of <em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and other garrisons, and are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in chasing the enemy from place to place, and daily take many of these thieving Villains, and three Regiments are marched from hence towards Scotland, it is likely they would soon be <reg orig="quell'd">quelled</reg> if they would stand to fight.</p>

<p>From <em>Portsmouth</em> they write, that a Squadron of our Fleet have taken very lately six <reg orig="prises">prizes</reg> from the Hollanders.</p>

<p>The preparations for War in <em>Holland</em> are very great, and they talk of some great matters agreed upon betwixt them and the French, but nothing openly declared, till they hear what becomes of their <em>Treaty</em> with <em>England</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><i>Thursday Jan. 12.</i></head>

<p>This day the Ambassador newly come over from the King of France, had audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, whom he congratulated in his new Government.</p>

<p>Letters from France say, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> at the Palace <reg orig="Royall">Royal</reg> in Paris, feasted the French King, with some French Lords and Ladies, and there were his brothers the Duke of York and <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, P. Rupert is come thither, but it holds true that P. Maurice is drowned.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A Declaration by the Commander in Chief of the forces in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></head>

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent, That [notwithstanding my Proclamation of Septem. 27. last] many serviceable horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great disservice of the peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much connivance of the Owners or Possessors: These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons, who are now, or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable horses or Mares, exceeding the value of 5 l. sterling, to bring in the same within 48 hours next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such horses, and mares, as shall not be brought in, the one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the use of the State, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to the party informing, but also be deemed as an open enemy, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and seal at Dalkeith, Decem. 14. 1653.</i></p>
<p><i>R. Lilburn.</i></p>

<head level="3">Thus have you represented,</head>

<p><i>A great fight obtained against the Highlanders, by the English and their whole party totally routed, and dispersed, took the Lord Kinoule, and about 35 horse, and wounded 14, and <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> three on the place. The Declaration of R. L. Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, for the bringing in of all horse and mares that are serviceable for the State. With a List of the prisoners taken at Glans: And divers other intelligence from the Navy, and other parts.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>Finis.</i></head>

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by T. Lock. 1653.</p> 

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>