<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell147">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 147</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 6. to <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 13. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 6.</head>

<p>Two thousand pound is a great Wager indeed to be laid on a light pair of heels. Although the race was run on <em>Thursday</em>, yet I will begin it upon Tuesday and be (the length of two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>,) before the swiftest of the foot-men. The <em>Irish</em> man did see forth from Saint <em>Albans</em> as if he had been all<reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, and would have overtaken, or gone before the Winds, but the sure, and fair speed of the <em>English</em> man did win the wager, who did run twenty miles from St <em>Albans</em> to <em>London</em>, in less than an hour and a half, and the four last miles so gently, that he seemed to meditate, and not to <reg orig="ensult">insult</reg> on the conquest, but did make it rather his recreation, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Race. It is not so <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> to relate, as it is hard to believe, what a confidence those of <em>Croydon</em> did repose in the swift pace of their townsman the Butcher, I am informed that those who had <reg orig="mony">money</reg> did gage a great part of it on his side. Those who had none did not only venture what they had in the fields, but what they had in their Houses, and their <pb n="1" />Chambers, nay what they had in their Barns, their own sustenance and the expectation of their Children for their daily bread. Now God speed thee (good fellow) who dost make such <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> up the Hill towards <em>Highgate</em>, and seest no more thy Compeer by they side, nor dost hear his feet pressing on thy heels. Well <reg orig="maist">mayst</reg> thou run a pace, on whole swiftness do depend the fortune of so many Families.</p>

<p>I shall in this place give you the humble Petition of <unclear>Capn</unclear> <em>William Baltiser</em> who coming in upon the Act for calling home the Seamen, to Prisoner in <unclear><em>Norgate</em></unclear> being prosecuted by one Mr: <em>Skelt</em> in the <reg orig="sheweth">showeth</reg> that proceeding in his resolution for this States service, being in his journey from <em>Plymouth</em> in company with Captain <em>George Blague</em> (<reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em><reg orig="Blagues">Blague's</reg></em> Brother) for <em>London</em>, to make his Address to the Parliament, and <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State for present employments and having occasion to visit a Friend by the way, the said <em>Skelton</em>, with many others, whom he had gathered together for that end, laid wait for him and without Warrant, suddenly set upon him, and carried him away Prisoner to <unclear><em>Ilchester</em></unclear> Goal, and then informed the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of State, that he had apprehended a <em><reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg></em>: Upon which false suggestion, Order was given in <em>March</em> last for his safe custody, till further Examination. And the said <em>Skelton</em> <reg orig="possest">possessed</reg> himself of most of his Goods, <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> of Exchange and caused his Wife to be imprisoned in <em>Ilchester</em> <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>, and afterwards in <em><reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg></em>, without any cause at all <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg>, on purpose (as he conceived) to prevent her from assisting him or seeking for his enlargement, and restitution of their goods, whereby he might starve in Prison, and the said <em>Skelton</em> enjoy his estate.</p>

<p>That the said <em>Skelton</em> hath ever since laboured by all indirect means he could to take away his life, and still giveth out that nothing will <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> him but his blood, although he never gave him any cause of offence; nor ever saw him the said <em>Skelton</em>, until he apprehended and imprisoned him. And the said <em>Skelton</em> told your <reg orig="Petitioners">Petitioner's</reg> Wife, that if your Petitioner had agreed with him and been ruled by him, that he would have had your <reg orig="Petitioners">Petitioner's</reg> name privately <unclear>entred</unclear>, and <pb n="2" />your Petitioner should never have been troubled, but should have <reg orig="injoyed">enjoyed</reg> the benefit of the said Act, which now he endeavoureth totally to deprive him of, and caused your Petitioner to be committed to prison as a <em><reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg></em>, and prosecuteth your Petitioner for piracy, whereas your Petitioner never acted anything but by Commission under the late King, and his son <em>Charles Stuart</em>, unadvisedly, and not as any Pirate, as by Commissions ready to be produced before your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> may appear, which your Petitioner then, and yet believeth, is pardoned by the very words of the said Act, although your Petitioner hath by the said <em><reg orig="Skeltons">Skelton's</reg></em> prosecution been carried from one Gaol to another, and still continued in prison without any legal <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg>, but only upon the false allegations and accusations of him the said <em>Skelton</em>, without any proof or conviction.</p> 

<p>And your Petitioner further <reg orig="sheweth">showeth</reg> unto your Honours that he being confident of his <reg orig="Innocency">Innocence</reg> and Integrity according to the direction and tenor of the said Act, hath to his great cost and trouble procured two several Commissions of Oyer and Terminer from the Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal, directed to all the <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Judges of the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Courts at <em>Westminster</em>, the Judges of the Admiralty, and to the Lord, Alderman, and the Recorder of <em>London</em>, for his legal <reg orig="Tryall">Trial</reg>, as by the Act is appointed, and sent a Messenger with a Warrant above 130 miles from <em>London</em> to the said <em>Skelton</em>, to come and prosecute against your Petitioner in any just way he could; yet hath the said <em>Skelton</em>, by all malicious and unjust means laboured to defer the <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg>, and to divert the course of Justice, and so overthrow the Commissioners of the Great Seal, and the Commissions so sued out as a foresaid by your Petitioner, &amp; refuseth to come to trial with your Petitioner thereupon, on purpose to keep your <reg orig="Petitioners">Petitioner's</reg> goods to himself, and your Petitioner still in prison, contrary to all Law, Equity and good Conscience, and <unclear>to your</unclear> Petitioner, his Wife, and <reg orig="Childrens">Children's</reg> utter undoing, and <unclear>then</unclear>, they being like to persist for want of sustenance by cruelty and unjust <pb n="3" />dealing of the said <em>Skelton</em>, which your Petitioner humbly prayeth by your <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> may be graciously considered, there being hardly any president of greater oppression, nor a more lamentable object of pity, then your <reg orig="Petitioners">Petitioner's</reg> present sad condition.</p>

<p>In tender consideration whereof, and for that it is evident by your <reg orig="Petitioners">Petitioner's</reg> endeavouring his peace before the said Act and since by his returning home voluntarily without constraint, deferring his Commission and <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg> abroad, bringing into <em>England</em>, his Wife, family, and Goods, and making his humble Addresses for Employment under the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; he most humbly beseecheth that he may enjoy the benefit of the said Act, and that the said <em>Skelton</em> may be prohibited from proceeding in the said <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> and malicious way against him.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Decemb: 7.</head>

<p>It was this Day certified that our Fleet was in a <reg orig="readines">readiness</reg> to put to Sea, the Generals at Sea are, General <em>Robert Blake</em> General <em>George Monk</em>, General <em>John Desborough</em>, and General <em>William Pen</em>. The other Commissioners for managing the affairs of the Admiralty are <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Joans</em>, <reg orig="Coll:">Col.</reg> <em>Clerk</em>, Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Thomas Kelfey</em>, Major <em>Burton</em>, <em>John Stone</em>, <em>Edward Horseman</em>, <em>Vincent Gookin</em> Esquires.</p> 

<p>There have been many Treaties between the Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of State, and the <em>Dutch</em> Deputies, at the last whereof the <em>Dutch</em> Deputies did break off upon matter of security, but it is hoped that speedily they will close again.</p>

<p><em>Monsieur Van de Par</em>, one of the Dutch Deputies <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> yesterday at his Lodgings in <em>Covent Garden</em>.</p>

<p>Several Orders have been given to the Commissioners of the Admiralty, to <reg orig="imploy">employ</reg> those in the service, who shall be found to be most able, and to be well affected, and to remove all such as are otherwise.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Holland</em>, that they make great preparations for Sea against the next Spring, they intend to have <pb n="4" />one hundred and twenty sail, whereof most of them are to be <unclear>new</unclear> ships.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>France</em>, that sixteen Men of War are ready to set sail out of <em>Brest</em>. This I hinted to you in my last, there is nothing new worthy observation, but only that the <em>French</em> have built a <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> of thirty six Guns, which is to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in the mouth of the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, and do us all the mischief that it can.</p> 

<p>Although the <em>Dutch</em>, and <em>French</em> Men of War do <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> about the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end yet we have received advertisement from <em><reg orig="Bristoll">Bristol</reg></em> that four prizes have brought into <em>Plymouth</em>, which do all belong to <em>Holland</em>, or to <em>Zealand</em>.</p>

<p>There is the <em>Hope</em> of <em>Delf Haven</em>, of one hundred and thirty <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, she is laden with Brandy Wine, bound for <em>Rotterdam</em>, she was taken by the <em>Assistance.</em></p>

<p>Another was a <em>Zealand</em> ship of two hundred and forty <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Wine and Salt, taken also by our <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> the <em>Assistance</em>.</p>

<p>The third was the <em>Orange</em> of <em>Amsterdam</em> of 120 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden also with Wine and Salt, she was taken by the <em>Hampshire</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>The last was the <em>Peter</em> of <em>Rotterdam</em> of one hundred <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Wine, and bound for <em>Amsterdam</em>; she was taken by the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Decemb: 8.</head>

<p>It is again advertised, that the <em>Lorrainers</em> being repulsed from the <reg orig="frontires">frontiers</reg> of the <em>Dutch</em>, are returned with greater force; whereupon the Lord <em>Brederode</em> and <em>Grave Horn</em> with about sixteen hundred Horse, and 3000 Foot are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to secure those parts, but dare not encounter the <em>Lorrainers</em> who are said to be 8000 Horse and Foot. The States have sent 300 which is the Prince of <em><reg orig="Oranges">Orange's</reg></em> own Troop, to assist the Lord <em>Brederode</em> and <em>Grave Horn</em>.</p>

<p>It is certified, that the <em>Highlanders</em> being 1000 Horse and Foot are in <em>Montroth</em>, the greatest part of them have not arms but <pb n="5" /><unclear>dully</unclear> expect that what <em>Middleton</em> hath brought from <unclear><em>Holland</em> shall</unclear> be sent to arm them. <em>Glencarn</em> intends to have a <unclear>Footman out of</unclear> every hundred pound rent, and a Horse and a man out of every thousand and pound <em>Scotch</em>; but we have sent some Forces to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at <em>Stirling</em> <em>St Johnstons</em>, and <em>Dundee</em>, which will be a <reg orig="speciall">special</reg> means to make them to keep the <unclear>Hills</unclear>. They fear no Winter it seems, but are all moving to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in one Body. They are all to march they say towards <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and they presume that some private will assist them in their advance to facilitate the Design.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Portsmouth</em>, that the Squadron of <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> for the West are still in <em>Portsmouth</em> Road, and going off. The ships which lay in <em>Deal</em> Road, and were bound for <unclear><em>Mouleux</em></unclear>, <em>St. Matthews</em> and <unclear><em>Rochel</em></unclear> are by this time there, and the trade for Pepper, Linen, and other Commodities in those places will be quickened again.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Decemb: 9.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the Earl of <unclear><em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em></unclear> is much discontented. The Country comes not in unto him, according to his expectation. Those Gentlemen in whom he reposed greatest trust, do forsake him, and his own Tenants refuse to pay him Rent. The <em>Highlanders</em> are not in want, or in a resolution to fight with us. Three hundred of ours did what they could to engage four hundred of them, but they durst not stand to it, but retreated to their Mountains to protect them.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Lilburn</em> was advanced towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>. The Highlanders have drawn a considerable Body to a <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> betwixt <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> and Saint <em>Johnstons</em>, where they begin to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg>, but no doubt will suddenly be removed. They have <reg orig="stollen">stolen</reg> so <pb n="6" />many sheep from the <em>Lowlands</em>, that knowing not where <unclear>to keep them</unclear>, two of them (according to their <unclear>proportion</unclear> which they do allow themselves, do eat up a <unclear>sheep a day.</unclear></p>

<p>Two <unclear>Troop<!-- approx. 4 characters illegible--> their</unclear> Horse (which they have distributed into <unclear><reg orig="severall">several</reg></unclear> Parties) taking the opportunity of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Lilburns">Lilburn's</reg></em> being at <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, are come down on <unclear>this side</unclear> <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and in the <em>Mey</em> and <em>Tivisdale</em> have taken away great number of Horse, they came so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em>Berwick</em>, that they seized upon two Soldiers of that Garrison, they have come into several <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> Houses in that Country, and have disarmed them: The <unclear><em>Lowlands</em></unclear> are said to be as Malignant as ever. The <unclear><reg orig="civill">civil</reg> usage</unclear> of our Officers, and Commanders hath not at all <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> them to the English Interest. They only do wait an opportunity, when the <em>Highlanders</em>, under <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Glencarn</em> and the rest shall become so considerable, that they may rise as one man to destroy us. Our Horse and Foot in most parts of <em>Scotland</em> are often out in parties against the <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> <em>Highlanders</em>, but through want of timely Intelligence, cannot <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb: 10.</head>

<p>It is advertised that <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> with a gallant Squadron of ships did set sail from <em>Tilbury Hope</em>, and is gone for the <em>Downs</em>. The rest of the Ships, as fast as they can be made ready, are there to meet him.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Decemb: 12.</head>

<p>It was this day advertised that the Men of War which belong to <em>Brest</em> in <em>France</em> are come abroad; some of them ply about the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, but the greatest part about <em><reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em> <reg orig="Sande">Sand</reg>; It is said that Prince <em>Rupert</em> is in person amongst them in the ship called <em>The Swallow</em>, which hath been lately new builded<pb n="7" />, and rigged at <reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg>. General <em>Monk</em>, and Gen: <em>Pen</em> with a brave Fleet are not far from him, if they meet him, no doubt they will strike sure with him, or make the <em>Swallow</em> fly.</p>

<p>The Letters this morning from <em>Scotland</em> do make mention, that a Party of our Horse hath <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> fourteen of the new <em><unclear>Mosse</unclear> Troopers</em>, and brought them Prisoners to <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>. It appears by them that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> hath lately sent a letter to the Lord <em>Lorn</em>, and the rest of the Nobility who are Commanders in the Army, in which he thanks them for their <reg orig="faithfulnes">faithfulness</reg>, and promiseth them all possible assistance both from himself, and from his friends, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<p>This Day there was a Debate concerning the Ministers, and their maintenance, for which the Lord General, and a Great part of the House this Day have much declared themselves, but the House this Day not agreeing, and the honour of the Church being of great concernment; It was thought fit the Parliament should be Dissolved, which accordingly was done.</p>

<p>It is again certified that the <em>Lorraigners</em> are retreating from the <reg orig="frontires">frontiers</reg> of <em>Holland</em>. The <em>French</em> King is come to <em>Paris</em>, he was met in the way by the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> on Horseback some four miles from the City, where many gratulations passed betwixt them.</p>

<p>Five tall Men of War, and gallantly appointed are come to our Fleet in the <em>Downs</em>, from <em>Portsmouth</em>. The <reg orig="Corographers">Chorographers</reg> affirm that <em>Paris</em> is more <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em>London</em> <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em>Dublin</em>, and it appears so, for every week we hear from <em>Paris</em>, but from <em>Dublin</em>, not these five weeks.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable, is:</head>

<p><i>The dissolution of this present Parliament. <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> set forth to the <em>Downs</em>, Prince <em>Rupert</em> not far from him in the <em>Swallow</em> with some <em>French</em> Men of War. The good service performed by the <em>English</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, and fourteen of the <em>Highland</em> Troopers brought Prisoners to <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>. The Letters of the titular King to them, promising more assistance. The propositions at which the <em>Dutch</em> do stick in their Treaty with the <em>English</em>. And several considerable <em>Dutch</em> Prizes taken by the <em>English</em>.</i></p>
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>