<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell224">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 224</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, March 21. to <em>Tuesday</em>, March 28. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 21.</head>

<p>The <em>Dutch Ambassadors</em> had this day Audience, they were attended by Sir <em>Oliver <reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg></em>, Master of the Ceremonies, Major Gen: <em>Lambert</em> waited on them betwixt his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> person, and the Park-gate; In the evening about five of the clock the Commissioners with the Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council, were carried in the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coach to the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, who met them at the gate, and with great <reg orig="courtesie">courtesy</reg> saluted them. The Conference presently began in a chamber for that purpose prepared in Sir <em>John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg></em> house, where the Ambassadors now <reg orig="lodg">lodge</reg>; they treated until very late at night. There have been great pains on both sides, to put things in all forwardness; the summing up the accounts due from <em>Denmark</em>, hath taken some time.</p>

<p>Letter from <em>France</em> make mention, that there is an Ambassador coming over to treat for a Peace with <em>England</em>, which is effected, there must be permission in <em>France</em> for the Protestant Religion.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>You are to understand that <em>Thomas Allen</em> Alderman, <em>Thomas West, Richard Bury, George Langham</em> Esquires, and <em>George Foxcraft</em> Merchant, are constituted Commissioners, and Governors of the <reg orig="Excizes">Excises</reg>; and <em>Sir William Roberts, John Stone, Henry Elsing, Jervas Bennet, Adam Bains</em>, and <em>John Poch</em>, or any three of them are authorized to receive all appeals.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Newcastle</em> 16 March.</head>

<p>Our Fleet is gone from hence, a great Fleet for <em>London</em>, and other parts that way; they had a good Convoy; there were a few <reg orig="smal">small</reg> ships, more should have gone with them from Sunderland, but got not out soon enough, they lost a tide or two; and there was such a strong and seasonable wind, that the Fleet thought it not discretion to stay, when they had so fair opportunity; yet there were 10 ships that got out on Monday last from <em>Sunderland</em>, and though they had no convoy with them, yet they thought they might venture between <em>Newcastle</em>, and the Fleet there so lately put out before, and accordingly they put out to follow the Fleet; but were presently set upon by the <em>Capers</em>, and <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to be taken, they were forced to run their ten ships all aground; but the <em>Capers</em> pursued them, and after the men were got out, the <em>Capers</em> got off five of them, and the other five are lost; so that within about a <reg orig="fortnights">fortnight's</reg> time we have lost 22 Coal ships.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> March 22.</head>

<p>His Highness being not very well, takes the morning <reg orig="ayr">air</reg> often, he lies again at the Cockpit.</p>

<p><i>A Declaration of his Highness the Ld: Protector, Inviting the People of England and Wales, to a Day of Solemn Fasting, and Humiliation.</i></p>

<p>The common and notorious sins so boldly and impenitently practised amongst us, notwithstanding all our Deliverances and Mercies, together with the present Rod of an Exceeding and Unusual Drought, which hath <reg orig="layen">lain</reg> upon us some years,<pb n="2" /> and still continues, and increasing upon us, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Famine and Mortality, are no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> the voice of God, calling aloud in our ears to Fasting, and Mourning, and great Abasement of soul before him.</p>

<p>And although the General End and Intendment of inviting to a Day of Fast, be, that all of every Condition and Quality whatever, do try and examine their heart and way more especially, according to their own Light, and in the use of such Helps and Means as the Lord in his Providence shall afford to each one, before and upon the said day of Meeting; yet finding some thoughts set seriously upon our Heart, We judged it not amiss to recommend the same to Christian consideration, not to impose them upon any, or to confine any within the compass thereof; but leaving every man free to the Grace of God, and to the work of his Spirit, who worketh all things in the hearts of the Sons of Men, according to the <reg orig="Councel">Counsel</reg>, and Good pleasure of His own Will.</p>

<p>It cannot be denied but that God hath vouchsafed to appear very much in working the Deliverance of the Nation from their bondage and <reg orig="thraldome">thraldom</reg>, both spiritual and Civil, and procuring for them a just Liberty by his own People.</p>

<p>Do we now walk worthy of our high Calling in humbleness and lowliness of mind, holding forth the Virtues of Christ in time of Peace, which was our strength, by the efficacy of which all our great things were accomplished in time of War.</p>

<p>Have we a heart prepared as willingly to communicate the said Just Freedom and Liberty to one another, as we were industrious to get it?</p><pb n="3" />

<p>Do we thankfully <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> our mercy in the Liberty of Worshipping God in Holiness and Righteousness without fear, being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies?</p>

<p>Is Brotherly Love, and a Healing Spirit of that force and value amongst us that it ought?</p>

<p>Do we own one another more for the grace of God, and for the spiritual Regeneration, and for the Image of Christ in each other, or for our agreement with each other in this or that form, or opinion?</p>

<p>Do we first search for the Kingdom of Christ with in us, before we seek one without us? Or do we listen to them that say concerning the coming of Christ Lo here, and lo there?</p>

<p>Do we not more contend for Saints having Rule in the world, than over their own hearts?</p>

<p>Are there not too many amongst us that cry up the Spirit, with a neglect of Love, Joy, Peace, Meekness, Patience, Goodness, Temperance, Long-suffering, Forbearance, Brotherly kindness, Charity, which are the fruit of the Spirit?</p>

<p>How do we carry <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> not only to the Churches of God, and the Saints, but towards them that are without?</p>

<p>Do not some of us affirm <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to be the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> true Ministry, and true Churches of Christ, and only to have the Ordinances in purity, excluding our Brethren, though of equal gifts, &amp; having as large a seal of their Ministry, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<head level="3"><i>Thursday, March 23.</i></head> 

<p>There is come into the River a great Fleet of Coals from <em>Newcastle</em>, the News is confirmed that we have lost twelve ships laden with Coals, six were taken by the Capers, and six<pb n="4" /> devoured by the Sea, having run themselves on the Sands, to run from the <em>Dutch</em>.</p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> they write that <em>Middleton</em> hath sent for the Ld: <em>Ree</em> to come and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, and hath given him express command to raise all the people within his territories to come and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; they have had two or three <reg orig="Rendezvouze">Rendezvous</reg> lately in the <em>Highlands</em>, and talk of great numbers of Horse and Foot to come out of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>; and they are carried aloft with great expectations of store of aid coming from <em>Holland</em>: thus are the <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> people ensnared, and drawn to destroy themselves, a little to trouble us. They talk of a certainty that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> will be there this <reg orig="Sommer">Summer</reg>, and say that the Emperor hath raised one hundred and sixty thousand Dollars, to raise 30 Regiments for the <em>Scotch</em> Kings; nay they report further, that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> is to marry the daughter of the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, with whom he is to have 4 Millions; but the Letters from <em>Flanders</em> say that this Lady hath lately lost two Millions in Jewels, and that her Father is now <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> upon as a lost Prince, and in the mean time the K: of <em>Scots</em> is <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> by the <reg orig="legg">leg</reg> at <em>Paris</em> for want of money to carry him thence for want of payment of the stipend promised. The last week the K: of <em>France</em> was in person in Parliament at the pronouncing sentence of death against the Pr: of <em>Conde</em>. That State seems to covet very much a Peace with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p><i>An Ordinance for Continuation of an Act of Parliament, intituled, An Act for the Continuation of the Customs <reg orig="untill">until</reg> 26 <em>March</em> in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> 1653.</i></p> 

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg>, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Continuation of the Customs until the 26 of <em>March</em> in the <em><reg orig="yeer">year</reg></em> 1653. and all the Powers and Clauses therein contained, be, and are hereby continued, and shall, and do stand in <reg orig="ful">full</reg> force, until the 26 day of <em>March</em>, in the <reg orig="yeer">year</reg> of our Lord, 1658. And be it further, that the Commissioners of the Customs shall not hereafter make <unclear><!-- approx. 2 characters --></unclear> payment of half <reg orig="Subsidie">Subsidy</reg> for any goods at any time exported<pb n="5" />, which have been, or hereafter <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be sold unto, or in the possession of any <reg orig="Shop.keeper">Shopkeeper</reg>, or retailer of the said commodity, or any such goods where the property, form, or nature of the commodity once imported, is in any wise altered, mingled, amended or confounded. And be it hereby further Ordained, That the Commissioners of the Customs for the time being, shall have, and receive upon every 20 shillings coming clear unto the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> upon their account such <reg orig="sallary">salary</reg> of Poundage, as is, or shall be agreed upon by the Committee for Regulating the Customs, or any thereunto authorized by his His Highness and his Council.</p>

<p>Our Fleet is in a gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg>, the Soldiers are all shipped; they seem to promise a relief for Christians, from <em>Turkish</em> slavery, if they make not too long a stay at <em>Legorn</em>.</p>

<p>The Council have made a Dispatch of an Ordinance for mending the <reg orig="High wayes">Highways</reg> where need is.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the <em>Highlanders</em> are very active, they report that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor, at what time they say their titular King is expected in <em>Scotland</em> again, to be head their Army, or if things there are not secure enough for him, he will send the Duke of <em>York</em> some say that they will both be there, but this we leave to time to confirm. Major <em>Holms</em> hearing where a <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> party of the enemy were, sent out a party, and took a Cornet, and four others, and 11 Horse.</p>

<p>Prince <em>Rupert</em> coming from St: <em>Germans</em>, and being affronted with some Gentlemen belonging to the Marquis of <em>Da Plessis</em>, one of his Retinue shot a Gentleman belonging to the said Marquis, and Prince <em>Rupert</em> to secure himself, did shoot another of them into the belly.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, March 24.</head>

<p>According to Order, the Fast this Day was solemnly kept in the Cities of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>, and it is observed, that it was the first Fast that for these many <reg orig="yeers">years</reg> hath been commanded on a Fast day set <reg orig="a part">apart</reg> to that holy use, by the reverend Authority of the Church, no doubt <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> but the Congregations were more full <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary,<pb n="6" /> and that the unanimity of our devotion will be answered with some sudden blessing. There preached before the Protector, and his Council at <em><reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg></em> Mr: <em>Strong</em>, Mr: <em>Cradock</em>, and one Mr: <em>Lockier</em>, that is his Chaplain.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is published for continuing the Act for laying Impositions upon Coals, towards the building and maintaining of ships for the guarding of the Seas, which is to continue in force one year.</p>

<p>An Ordinance for continuing the Act for Impressing of Seamen, and Mariners, which in to be in force seven months and seven days.</p>

<p>An Ordnance is also passed for Guardians for <reg orig="Ideots">Idiots</reg> and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>.</p>

<p>The Act is published for appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, that shall be presented to them, and for the <reg orig="removall">removal</reg> of all such who since the 1. of <em>April</em> last being placed in Benefices shall be found to be defective in knowledge and conversation.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, March 25.</head>

<p>All things are quiet in <em>Ireland</em>, Men are only wanting for the plantation of the <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> made desolate by War. There are a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> party of the Tories <reg orig="stil">still</reg> remaining, but they dare not stand to any <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg>, but on the first approaches of our men do run into the wood for their protection.</p>

<p>Our Fleet who distribute themselves into <reg orig="severall">several</reg> squadrons, the better to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> and secure our Seas, have taken another <em>Brest-man</em> of War, and a <em>Dutch</em> Merchant bound for <em>Rotterdam</em> laden with considerable goods.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 27.</head>

<p>We fasted on <em>Friday</em> last, and besought the Almighty for the former and the latter rain. It hath pleased God this morning to send us some showers, and the thick clouds do promise more.</p>

<p><em>Monsieur de Neufueille</em> the <em>French</em> Ambassador attended with several Coaches was this day brought in his <reg orig="Excellencies">Excellency's</reg> own Coach through the City to Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em><pb n="7" /> house at <em>Westminster</em>. On <reg orig="too morrow">tomorrow</reg> he is to have Audience of his Highness.</p>

<p>I had almost forgot to inform you, that the <em>Dutch</em> Packet of Letters going to <em>Dover</em>, was broken up not far from Saint <em>George</em> his Church in <em>Southerwark</em>; it is said that it was done by <reg orig="theeves">thieves</reg>, who breaking open all the Letters, did throw them on the ground, and turned the man back again.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>France</em> represent, that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> <unclear>is</unclear> very sorry to understand the taking of Capt: <em>Beach</em> by the <em>Warwick</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, which being noised over all the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> in the morning, was contradicted at noon, but confirmed again in the evening; the taking of this Admiral hath possessed the rest with so great a fear, that the Letters say, they are afraid to venture any more in the Narrow, but are all going to <em>Toulon</em>, in the service of the King of <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>The killing of one of the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Plessis">Plessis's</reg></em> men, and the wounding of another by Pr: <em>Rupert</em>, one of his Gentlemen is so ill resented, that an Order was coming forth for the banishment of the said Prince from the Court, and Kingdom of <em>France</em>, which is since demurred upon; this makes little for the affairs of the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, whose condition was there low enough before. We have taken this week (say the Letters from <em>Scotland</em>) divers who were going to assist the <em>Highlanders</em>, whose Army is marched more Northwards <reg orig="then">than</reg> it was; there is a Report that the titular <em>Scots</em> King was to Marry the Daughter of <em>Lorraign</em>, and that the Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> is to marry the Son of the Emperor of <em>Germany</em>; this is <reg orig="al">all</reg> I can learn for this week.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>&#x261e; The magnificent Entertainment of the <em>French</em> Ambassador; and the proceedings of the Treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>, and the reason of the long Debate with them Some <em>French</em>, and <em>Dutch</em> Prizes taken by the <em>English</em>. The great boasts of the <em>Highlanders</em> of a formidable Army coming from <em>Germany</em>, and their titular King to head them. The Report of his Marriage with the Daughter of <em>Lorrain</em>; and the Qu. Of <em>Sweden</em> with the Emperor. The Order for the banishment of Prince <em>Rupert</em> from the Court, and Kingdom of <em>France</em>, and the reason of it.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>