<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell223">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 223</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, March 14. to <em>Tuesday</em>, March 21. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 14.</head>

<p><reg orig="Somthing">Something</reg> was taken into observation concerning the abuse of Farthing Tokens, and a Debate was, whether they should pass with some alloy or not; the further consideration was referred unto another time.</p>

<p>General <em>Desborough</em> is returned from the Fleet, and made account thereof unto the <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council; The Fleet is gallantly manned, and will be ready to set forth on the first opportunity; the <em><reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em> is under sail with them.</p>

<p>Several ships have been taken from the <em>French</em>, and <em>Dutch</em> who continue <reg orig="stil">still</reg> roving on the Seas, but the Peace being concluded, which was never in fairer way <reg orig="then">than</reg> at this present.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last, that the City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em> had declared <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> how happy she was under the protection of his Highness, those who subscribed to this Declaration, were,</p><pb n="1" />

<p><em>William Lenthal</em> Esquire, Master of the <reg orig="Rols">Rolls</reg>. <em>John Dorny</em> Esquire.</p>
<p><em>Thomas Pury</em> the Elder Esq; Captain <em>Godfrey</em>.</p>
<p><em>Thomas Pury</em> the <reg orig="yonger">younger</reg>, Esq; Captain <em>Philips</em></p>
<p><em>Robert Wakeman</em></p>

<p>Since which time several other places have made the like Declarations, which come in daily to his Highness.</p>

<p><i><em>Leopoldus Guillelmus</em> by the Grace of God, <reg orig="Arch Bishop">Archbishop</reg> of <em>Austrick</em>, Duke of <em>Burgundy</em>, and Stateholder, Governor, and Captain General of our Low Countries and of <em>Burgundy</em> &amp;c.</i></p>

<p>To all High Officers, Commanders, Masters of the Camps, <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg> and Soldiers bearing Arms under the Colours of the Lord Duke, <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg></em> of <em>Lorraign</em>, Salute. Be it known that having this day taken into safe custody, for some time, the Person of the foresaid Duke of <em>Lorraign</em>, according to the Order and Command received for that effect from our Lord the King, for the own welfare of the House of <em>Lorraign</em>, and other high considerations, relating to the welfare of the State, and the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Peace. His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> intent, and ours is, that the body of his Army should remain under the Command of the Earl of <em>Lignevile</em>, in the same service as it now is, <reg orig="til">till</reg> the Lord Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorraign</em> shall repair here, as it is like he will in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, to be invested of the command of the said Army, for the preservation of the Rights of the said Lord Duke, and of the House of <em>Lorraign</em> under protection of his Majesty, declaring that none of that Army, nor any Officers, or soldiers of the same shall be liable to any questioning under what pretence soever, for the excesses that they may have committed under the Government of the aforesaid Lord Duke, as also we do by this present, forbid them to take service under and Potentate, or <reg orig="neighbor">neighbour</reg> state, whether friends or foes, upon penalty of Corporal punishment, and <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of Estates, of the vassals and natural Subjects of his Majesty, and of those that have formerly <reg orig="enroled">enrolled</reg>, and listed themselves, and for all other strangers upon pain of being punished as <reg orig="Runnawaies">Runaways</reg>, with provision nevertheless that those that have formerly Listed in the service of his Majesty, and are gone away from their colours without leave,<pb n="2" /> shall have return to the same, without fear of being questioned for it. &amp;c.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Council sat in Debate of some things propounded by divers Godly Ministers, (though of several Judgments) and the said Council being sensible of the great necessity there is, that matters of Religion should be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in the Church, as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as temporal Government in the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, are advising of a way whereby the Godly, and able Ministry shall be encouraged, and that false and idle <reg orig="shepheards">shepherds</reg> may be removed, and kept out for the future.</p>

<p>There be some Copies of Letters intercepted from <em>Scotland</em>, sent to <em>London</em>, which in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will be made <reg orig="publick">public</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Amsterdam</em> they write of a stately Fleet almost in a readiness, and say, that it far exceeds the number they have yet had forth to fight, and their <em>Prospective</em> out of <em>England</em> a Reciprocal, and say some of the Letters all Christendom stand amazed at the transaction of these two so mighty, and considerable <reg orig="Common.wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, yet they seem not to doubt but their Ambassadors have before this time ratified the Peace with <em>England</em>, saying that they had but six weeks allotted them for their stay in <em>England</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 8.</head>

<p>The <em>Orange</em> party are indifferent quiet for the present, though they talk very high, but being they are put to play an after-game, the manner is so much the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> considerable.</p>

<p>We told you before of some Letters, and papers taken in <em>Scotland</em>, one was a Letter from <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> to the Lord General (as they call him) <em>Glencarn</em>, beginning thus.</p><pb n="3" />

<head level="3">CHARLES <reg orig="STUARTS">STUART'S</reg> Letter to the Lord General <em>Glencarn</em>.</head>

<p><i>After our heavy commendations, <em>&amp;c.</em> We cannot but give you thanks for your <reg orig="activenes">activeness</reg> in doing of us, and our Kingdom service and we do hereby give you further to understand, that we do highly value, and approve of your endeavours in a service which doth so much import us, and to the end you may receive some other <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> from our self, we have given special order to <em>Middleton</em> to hasten unto you: He hath provided in <em>Holland</em> a considerable number of able Commanders, every way fit for our service. The arms which we sent from <em><reg orig="Nants">Nantes</reg></em> may happily be with you before this Letter. We wish that the late differences between <em>Seafort</em> and you, may not be prejudicial to our affairs; we bid you right heartily <reg orig="farwel">farewell</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Signed, C. Rex.</p>

<p>Upon the Intelligence that <em>Middleton</em> was landed in <em>Scotland</em>, <em>Glencarn</em> set forth this Proclamation.</p>

<p>To all whom it may concern</p>

<p>I do hereby strictly will, require, and command all Officers, and soldiers, Horse, and Foot: now under my command, that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the publishing hereof, they and every of them do repair to their several Quarters, and be ready to perform their duties in their several places, and that they nor any of them do presume upon any pretence whatsoever, to depart from their Colours, without special Licence. And I do further Require, and Command all the chief Officers of the several Regiments of Horse and Foot to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> me from time to time the particular Names of such several Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> under them, who have been negligent in the prosecution of nay my former Warrants, for the speedy effecting, and bringing<pb n="4" /> in of <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, or who shall neglect, or wilfully contemn this command. Commanding all Officers and soldiers to be obedient hereunto, that they may be ready to appear upon summons, at what place shall be appointed for their Rendezvous, as they will answer the contrary at their utmost perils.</p>

<p><i>Subscribiter Glencarn.</i></p>

<p>The Privy Lodgings for his Highness the Lord Protector in <em>Whitehall</em> are now in a readiness, as also the Lodgings for his Lady Protectoress; and likewise the privy <reg orig="Kitchin">Kitchen</reg>, and other <reg orig="Kitchins">Kitchens</reg>, Butteries, and Offices, and it is conceived the whole family will be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> there before <em>Easter</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Tables for Diet prepared are these.</i></head>

<p>A Table for his Highness. A Table for the Gentlewomen.</p>
<p>A Table for the Protectoress. A Table for Coachmen, Grooms, and other <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Servants.</p>
<p>A Table for Chaplains and Strangers. A Table for Inferiors or Subservants.</p>
<p>A Table for the Steward and Gentlemen.</p>

<p>At a Conference in the afternoon yesterday betwixt the Commissioners for the Ld: Protector and the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, there was very large expressions of Love and Amity; and the Ld: <em>Beverling</em> expressed in a Speech, that they were clear and <reg orig="unwreathed">enwreathed</reg> in their intentions for making a firm League. After this both parts of the Articles were compared, and they are now Engrossing.</p>

<p>Some of the chief of the <em>Highlanders</em> have made overtures or Propositions to allay the present distempers without shedding more blood (but they have not prosecuted them.</p>

<p><i>1. That Sequestration of <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> Estates hath made many desperate, and put themselves in Arms.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That <reg orig="personall">personal</reg> Arrests may cease, and Creditors contented to take all the Lands and Goods they find, for satisfaction.</i></p><pb n="5" />

<p><i>3. That <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> of Fortune who have spent their best days and got nothing; might be considered, and transported.</i></p>

<p>Some <em>Dutch</em> Men of War were discovered <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Goodwyn Sands</em> lately, they forced 12 <em>English</em> ships to run <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg> between <em>Falmouth</em>, and <em>Scarborough</em>.</p>

<p>The <em>English</em> Fleet is about 140 sail <em>stately</em> and <em>brave</em>: we have this week taken 15 ships great and <reg orig="smal">small</reg> from the Enemy.</p>

<p>The Prince of <em>Conde</em> is in <em>Flanders</em> with the <reg orig="Arch duke">Archduke</reg>, his Brother <em>Conti</em> is to command the <em>French</em> Army. 150 Sail of <em>Eastland</em> Merchants are newly come into <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 16.</head>

<p>By divers Letters from <em>Scotland</em> we had this day a confirmation of the unhappy accident at <em>Lanker</em>, some fifteen miles from <em><reg orig="Dumfreize">Dumfries</reg></em>: Captain <em>Mason</em> understanding that the Enemy was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> advanced towards them with 80 Horse, which the Enemy understanding retired to their <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, <reg orig="wherupon">whereupon</reg> Capt: <em>Mason</em> having taken a Cornet and some other prisoners returned to <em>Lanker</em> to quarter there that night: Captain <em>Palmer</em> understanding also that the Enemy was at <em>Lanker</em>, he advanced with his Troop to encounter them; and being mistaken by the voice of the Scout who was a <em>Scotchman</em>, he fell upon Captain <em><reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg></em> men; whereupon Captain <em>Palmer</em> drew out a party of 30 men to fire the <reg orig="Guard house">Guardhouse</reg>; At which Captain <em>Mason</em> not <reg orig="induring">enduring</reg> the Indignity, did <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> him with a choice party of 40 Horse: in this skirmish by a most unhappy mistake divers were slain, and more wounded. The fight was very fierce in the long Lane at the Townsend, in which Capt: <em>Mason</em> himself was wounded.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, March 17.</head>

<p>It was this day confirmed by Letters from <em>Scotland</em>, that Gen: <em>Middleton</em> having landed in <em>Scotland</em> his men and Arms, he did write to the Sheriff of <em>Southerland</em>, requiring him to act no more in the names of the Keepers of the Liberties of <em>England</em>; or in the Name of <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> Lord Protector:<pb n="6" /> he did write to the high Sheriff that he would give him a Commission whereby to act.</p>

<p>It is advertised, that upon the <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> landing, the Lord <em>Seafort</em> hath gained together 600 men, and is gone to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him. <em>Glencarn, Kenmore, Glencarry, Huntly, Athol</em> and <em>Forbes</em> do intend to have their Rendezvous in <em>Murrayland</em>, some 24 miles westward from <em>Aberdeen</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised that another vessel with Arms is come unto <em>Middleton</em>, and hath put in at <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, whither he hath wrote to <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg>, if he can, to draw the Gentlemen of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to an <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg>. He speaks of divers vessels with Arms to come to him, and that he shall have as much assistance as can be desired: but the <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> finding that neither the number of men, or Arms now landed, do any ways answer their expectation, and the great things that were promised, do make but thin appearances at the <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg>, and altogether <reg orig="disrellish">disrelish</reg> the proceedings.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Sweden</em>, that the Lord Chancellor doth make excuses and delays, to see what the issue will be of our Treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>. Howsoever there is a fair correspondence betwixt him and our Lord Ambassador. It is said, that Discourses <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for the present do pass betwixt them, and nothing is drawn up to a Head.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, March 18.</head>

<p>Captain <em>Beach</em> that famous <reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg> is brought into <em>Plymouth</em>, where he and about 200 of his Men are close Prisoners, when he came aboard the <em>Warwick</em>, he demanded of Captain <em>Potter</em> the manner of performing his Articles, and said it was his promise to see him <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg> in <em>France</em>, at which Captain <em>Potter</em> being startled told him he never heard of any such Demand, and to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> him, he commanded Captain <em>Beach</em> to go aboard his own Vessel again, and fight it on, but <em>Beach</em> refused the same.</p>

<p>It is advertised that the <em>Dutch Freebooters</em> have taken some of our <reg orig="Colliers">Collier's</reg> ships as they were coming from <em>Newcastle</em> to this City; but a private Man of War of ours hath taken a Dutch ship of 400 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with <em>Eastland</em> commodities, she is brought into <em>Harwich</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 20.</head>

<p>Upon the approach of <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> and some other additional Forces, Gen: <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> fled away with his hundred Reformadoes; and so did <em>Glencarn, <reg orig="Huntly">Huntley</reg>, Athol, Glencarrus, Kenmore, Forbes</em>, and the rest, they are said to be in all 5000 <em>effective</em>, they retreated to their next Fastnesses. Our Forces are gone up to them, and have taken <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="straglers">stragglers</reg>. It is likely you will hear of action by the next. <em>Middleton</em> brought over in all about ten thousand Arms.</p>

<p>The Act for <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> the Excise <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be extant <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, I should here tell how long it is to continue, and what are the Names of the Commissioners; but till the Act be extant by Authority I am <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> commanded to be silent. There is a <em>Fast</em> on <em>Friday</em> next at the Church in <em>Lumbardstreet</em> to weep for our sins, that the Clouds may weep in abundance on us, and drop down fatness.</p>

<p>The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is yet in <em>France</em>, and so are his two Brothers, but all of them are upon their Departure. Their Mother hath declared that she cannot endure to stay in <em>France</em>, nor yet go to <em>Subaudia</em>, but is resolved to <reg orig="pertake">partake</reg> with her Children in all her travails wheresoever their sullen stars shall lead them. There are more taken who had a hand in the great Robbery at <em>Shooters Hill</em>.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable is:</p>

<p><i>The Act for continuing the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>. The great success in <em>Scotland</em>, <reg orig="severall">several</reg> prisoners taken. Gen: <em>Middleton</em> flying away with his hundred Reformadoes, and with the chief Commanders of the Army. <em>Glencarn, Glencarras, Athol, <reg orig="Huntly">Huntley</reg>, Kenmore, Forbes</em>, and the rest. The Debate of the Council concerning Farthing Tokens. The great Pirate <em>Beach</em> close prisoner in <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> with two hundred of his men. <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> ships taken by the <em>Dutch</em>, and some considerable <em>Dutch</em> ships taken by the <em>English</em>. And the Declaration of the late Queen of <em>England</em> to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with her Children.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>