<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell327">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 327</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, April 11. to <em>Tuesday</em>, April 18. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 11.</head>

<p>By Letters from the furthest part of <em>Germany</em> it is advertised, that on a part of the great <reg orig="Forrest">Forest</reg>, not far from the River of <em>Danubius</em>, there have been a Troop of Horsemen all in black coming out of the <reg orig="Forrest">Forest</reg>, and not far from them there was seen another Troop of Horsemen all in white, coming out of the said <reg orig="Forrest">Forest</reg> who <reg orig="encountred">encountered</reg> with the black Troop, and after half an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> fight, the black Troop prevailed, and forced the white Troop to retreat into the Wood. <reg orig="Immediatly">Immediately</reg> afterwards there appeared a tall man in black who was remarkable by many white streaks in his apparel, who with another strong party of the white, did fall upon the black Troop, and had the better of them; the fight being ended, the tall man in black who did lead the white Troop, and seemed like a <reg orig="Gyant">Giant</reg>, at did the first grow less and less, and being at the last no bigger <reg orig="then">than</reg> a Pygmy, he <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> vanished into <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, of which the Philosophers in <em>Germany</em> (who have had many disputations on this Subject in their Schools this last<pb n="1" /> Lent) doth say he was begotten; but that which doth seem to contradict them is, that the sound of the Drums, and Trumpets were heard, so likewise was the noise of the Guns, the clashing of their swords, and the neighing of their Horses, the <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> of the guns was seen, so likewise was the blood of the dead, and the wounded, and which strongly conduceth to prove it was no Apparition, the impression on the ground which the feet of the Horses made, was many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> afterwards to be seen; This hath been examined before some of the Judges in <em>Germany</em>, to give satisfaction to divers great Princes in the Empire, who have desired to be thoroughly informed of the Truth thereof, which hath been testified by some thousands who have seen it, not only once, but several times since.</p>

<p>The News which came this Day from <em>Scotland</em>, is fully represented in this ensuing Letter. I shall only desire you to remember that those Parties over which the English so happily were Masters, were those who were newly <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> in the Southern, and Western parts in <em>Scotland</em>, and were going to the <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in the North. It begins thus.</p>

<p>According to your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> Command I drew out 100 men out of my Col: Regiment, and we met at <em>Hambleton</em> on Tuesday last, from whence I sent 40 to <em><reg orig="Duglass">Douglass</reg></em>, and <em>Zanckers</em> appointing them to meet me within two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, at a place appointed; and with the rest of the Party I marched to <em>Newmils</em>, where I lay one night, making it my business to get what Intelligence I could of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> motion. The next morning by break of day, a Lieutenant and 9 Mossers came to the Towns-end, upon whom our sentinel fired, and they presently betook themselves to the Mosses; and notwithstanding they were closely pursued by the Guard, they could get but two Prisoners, and six horses, being but that night taken from some Country people, which I caused to be restored again, upon some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> consideration to the Soldiers that took them. The same day Lieut: <em>Evans</em> marching with his party from me to <em><reg orig="Duglass">Douglass</reg></em>, through the Mores took 8 Mossers more, notable Villains, and sturdy. I sent to the Governor of <em><reg orig="Air">Ayr</reg></em> to<pb n="2" /> desire him to acquaint me with the condition of Lieut: <em>Hickman</em>, who marched out with 70 horse from <em>Glasgow</em>, by reason it was reported he forced the Enemy in <em>Carick</em>, who was said to be double his number, but his Return to me was, that he was considerable enough, and that he had met, and fought some of the Enemy, routed and pursued them to <em>Chapell</em>, and so did <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> that my party might be most useful about <em>Zanker</em>, and those Passes, to that purpose I divided, and sent Lieut: <em>Evans</em> with 50 horse that way.</p>

<p>But two miles from <em>Comlock</em> I <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> to hear the Enemy by a Countryman, who reported them to be about 12, I sent a party to the place where they were, but they had the <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg>, and rid for it, their party <reg orig="stil">still</reg> increased, <reg orig="til">till</reg> they came to the number of 60. which were <reg orig="stil">still</reg> pursued by a Corporal, and ten men; at last they faced about, seeing no more, and our party made a halt, but so soon as ever they discovered my party coming, they presently began to flinch, and turn tails, I sent the Corporal therefore presently to charge their Rear, but they soon fled, and betook themselves to the Mosses, whither we pursued them at least 10 miles, in the most doleful place that ever I beheld; He followed them so long as our horses could step forward, and till they had not above 12 or 14 together in a body, the rest dispersed, many leaving their horses, which we picked up to the number of 25, but could that day take no more prisoners but 8. and 2 or 3 slain in the pursuit. This party was commanded by Major <em>Hamilton</em>, Capt. <em>Leglau</em>, and <em><reg orig="Campbel">Campbell</reg></em>, the last of which was not there. There was besides <em>Cragdorough</em>, with 50 horse that came up from about <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with these, and was quartered within a mile or two, where I fell upon these Youths; but by reason of our interposing could not come to them, but marched off <reg orig="intirely">entirely</reg> in a body to the left of us; I <reg orig="endevoured">endeavoured</reg> to get what Intelligence I could of their motion that night. The next morning I understood where they were; and what they intended which was to go by the way of <em>Douglas</em>, and so into the North over <em>Cluyd</em>. I presently mounted and marched another way, as fast as I could, thinking to have been before<pb n="3" /> them, but it so <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> that they were gotten past <em>Douglas</em> a full hour before me; I found out their Tract, and pursued after them as fast as I could, sending 16 of our best horse, if it were possible to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them, but all was to little purpose: we pursued them until we came within 4 miles of <em>Hamilton</em> long within night, but then lost them. I came to <em>Hamilton</em> this morning about one a clock, and presently sent out all the horse that were here, to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> upon the Passes of <em>Cluyd</em>, and to range the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> between <em>Evandale</em> and <em>Senerick</em>, where about I judge they will attempt to get over <em>Cluyd</em> I have also dispatched an express to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Cooper</em> desiring him to send to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, to draw forth their <reg orig="hors">horse</reg> on the Passes, that so if we miss of them here, they may perhaps light on them; they cannot but be much <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg>. I have also sent to <em><reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg></em> to Cap: <em>Robson</em>, to desire him to advise Lieut. <em>Hickman</em> with his party, which I understand is come out of <em>Carick</em>, to lye about the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Passes over <em><reg orig="Dumbarton shire">Dumbartonshire</reg></em>, where those dispersed people of <em><reg orig="Hamiltons">Hamilton's</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Leglans">Leglan's</reg></em> will certainly privately <reg orig="endevor">endeavour</reg> to get over. The 8 prisoners first taken, I sent to <reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg>, the rest I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> send this day to <em>Glasgow</em>: One is said to be a Capt: another a Lieutenant, and one a notorious murdering Moss Trooper, known to be so by the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> about from his childhood. Truly Sir, must now of necessity take some rest, both men and horses being utterly spent, and having not only <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg> out our own horses, but also those we took from the Enemy. I shall not further trouble your <reg orig="Honor">Honour</reg>.</p>

<p>It is further advertised, that some parties of Horse who were lately of Major Gen: <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Regiment have done remarkable service in gleaning of the new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> who were marching into the North. Four or five hundred have lately been dispersed of these <em>Scots</em>: General <em>Monk</em> is gone to take the command of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, he carrieth with him an Ordinance from the State <reg orig="tendring">tendering</reg> pardon to those who shall submit, some few of the Ringleaders being excepted.</p><pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>Wednesday, April 12.</i></head>

<p>It was advertised, that on last Friday the Messenger from <em>England</em> certifying the sealing of the Articles by the Commissioners on both sides, arrived at <em>Rotterdam</em>, where he stayed not an hour, but made his Dispatch towards the <em>Hague</em>, where no doubt there will be a sudden meeting of the States General for the Ratification of them; the substance of the Articles is to this effect.</p>

<p>That there shall be a closer <reg orig="Aliance">Alliance</reg> and confederacy between the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> was ever heretofore. That the Peace be published by both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> upon one and the same day; after which, all acts of hostility to cease after ten <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Seas; from thence to the Cape of St: <em>Vincent</em> after six weeks, and to the <reg orig="Medeterranean">Mediterranean</reg> Sea after six weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>; after all Prizes to be restored. That all acts <reg orig="past">passed</reg> be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither to act <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against the other. That all hostility cease between <em>England</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, none to assist the Rebels of either Nation with any supply, but assist each other against them; and the one not to receive those the other declares to be enemies, but cause them upon notice to depart within 28. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death. That no private persons be suffered to assist the enemies of either, not to pay to either great Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> others. The States ships to strike their <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg> to the English in the <reg orig="Brittish">British</reg> Seas; no retreat to be given to <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of the Ports of either; each to comprehend the other in any treaty with any Nation, if desired. That if any particular Persons break the Peace, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not break the National Confederacy: but those that do it to be punished. The Subjects of each to travel freely through all quarters of each, by Water or Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and submitting to the Laws where they are. That in storms each may have Harbour under other, if they break not bulk without paying of Customs. The Merchants or Mariners of either Commonwealth<pb n="5" /> not to be pressed to serve under the other, but upon inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction. That in each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Country, they pass between their ships, and Inns with lawful Weapons, both Offensive, and Offensive. That all ships of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> defend each other against all whomsoever, sailing their course together. That if any other take any ships out of either their Dominions, both parties to engage against them, until restitution be made. The Searchers of both, to take no more of any of either, <reg orig="then">than</reg> their Instructions. Letters of Reprisal not to be given for damage caused, if in 3 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> satisfaction may be had. That such as have private Commissions put in good security not to damage the subjects of either <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. That not above 8 ships of War remain in any Port of the <reg orig="others">other's</reg> <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> without consent. That Justice be done by the States on those that are alive that murdered the <em>English</em> in <em>Amboyna</em>. That there be Commissioners on both sides to examine the differences of the Inhabitants of both Nations in the <em>East Indies, Greenland, Muscovy, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg>,</em> and other places, and if they cannot agree within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to refer it to be determined by the Protestant <em>Switzers</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 13.</head>

<p>There is a report that the late Queen of <em>England</em> with her Children, and the Children of the Queen of <em>Bohemia</em> are all warned to depart from <em>France</em>, and places are assigned them to which they shall retire, but I can find no Letters of any certainty to confirm it.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last of the Commissioners to be chosen to conclude the business in relation to our <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> losses sustained by the stopping of their ships by the King of <em>Denmark</em>, &amp;c. I am this morning informed, that the same is agreed upon, and Security already given for the payment of the Money.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, April 14.</head>

<p>By Letters this day from <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> is advertised, that the parties of horse and Foot sent out by the chief Commander towards the borders of <em>England</em> have quite spoiled<pb n="6" /> all their <reg orig="leavies">levies</reg>, and having secured the borders of <em>England</em>, are returned with many prisoners.</p>

<p>We are once more desired to mention Mr. <em>Isaac Playford</em> Student and Practitioner in <reg orig="Physick">Physics</reg> and Chirurgery, Resident in Kings street in Covent-garden <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <reg orig="Signe">Sign</reg> of the Golden Fox at Mr. <em><reg orig="Wels">Wells</reg></em> his house, to let the Nation understand that he can make the Antidote called <em>Orivetan</em>, so much renowned over all Europe, which is a Remedy incident to most Diseases incident to Mankind; he having it always ready by him, you may constantly find him in his Study from five in the morning, <reg orig="til">till</reg> three in the afternoon.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 15.</head>

<p>It is further advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the <em>Scots</em> had lately a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in <em>Southerland</em>, where appeared two thousand Horse and Foot, five hundred of the Horse were very poor, they were a great part of them ordered to march to <em>Argyles</em> County, and the rest to continue in the North. <em>Middleton</em> added to their number at the <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> two hundred good horse, who had all good Riders, and two thousand five hundred men are daily expected, by which it appears that all the Forces they make, when amassed into one Body, will not make five thousand horse and foot. To encourage his men Gen: <em>Middleton</em> gave them some <em>Spanish</em> Gold, and <reg orig="tels">tells</reg> them what vast sums are promised by the Emperor, and how many men his Brother in Law is from thence to bring over with him. I made mention in my last of the advance of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em>, and <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Daniel</em> towards the North to encounter with this Body of the Enemy, before that any new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> can be raised, or Forces from <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> parts be arrived. Lieut: Col: <em><reg orig="Metchil">Mitchell</reg></em> is since marched to him with nine Companies of Foot, 6 Troops of horse, 2 gallant Troops of Horse more, and 5 Troops of Dragoons, to which are to be added four Troops of Horse, and three Companies of Foot, who will either force the Enemy to a <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, or to stay where they are, where it is impossible for them any long time to subsist, or else they must hazard the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of all their Horse by the length of the Mountainous <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, and scarcity of provisions.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 17.</head>

<p>The Ordinance for Uniting <em>Scotland</em> with the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, was this Day Passed, with some new Instructions.</p>

<p>The Enemy being quite dispersed, and chased from the Southern parts of <em>Scotland</em>, it was this Day advertised that the War is carried altogether in the North, where we are now very considerable in our Forces, and due care is taken for Provisions to be brought by Sea to <em>Aberdeen</em>, and <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em>, for all things necessary. We have fallen upon some Van <reg orig="Currers">Curriers</reg> of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Army, who we sent forth to observe the motion, and the numbers of our Army, which may be of great advantage to us, and will undoubtedly be made use of: Some of <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> Horse have been also taken upon the Pass over the <em>Tay</em>, and the Cornet of his own Troop killed, who was also of his own Name, their boasts are great in <em>Scotland</em>, not only of relief from <em>Germany</em>, which they say are to be shipped at <em><reg orig="Hambrough">Hamburg</reg></em>, and <em>Lubeck</em>, which is unlikely enough, but that <em>Count William</em> who is of the <em>Orange</em> Party in <em>Holland</em> will also come over to them with all the Power he can make, but how vain is this Rant, I leave to every knowing man to <reg orig="judg">judge</reg>. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is yet in <em>France</em>, where of late the inclination of the People do seem more propense unto him.</p>

<p>For our Fleet which from the <em>Spits head</em> did <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> almost all along the Channel like a moving Wood, did so <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg> them in <em>France</em> from <em>Deep</em> unto the River of <em>Garoon</em>, that the Commanders of all the Western Ports do stand upon their Guards, and have sent Letters to the Court to acquaint them with the danger that doth threaten them.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is,</p>

<p><i>The great success obtained against several parties of the <em>Scots</em>; the Van Curriers of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> own Army taken in the North; and a Defeat given to that Party Commanded by the Lord <em>Lorn</em>: the near <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> of both Armies. And the great Alarum over all the West of <em>France</em>, by reason of the <em>English</em> Fleet. The wonderful Apparitions in <em>Germany</em>, and the miraculous Conflict betwixt two several parties, attested by a thousand Witnesses. And the last certain News from the titular King of the <em>Scots</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>