<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell147#3">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 147#3</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 20. to <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 27. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 20.</head>

<p>I made mention in my last save one, that the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> was at <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, from whence (it is since advertised) that he is come to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em>, where he arrived in the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em>, and his followers in the <em>Elizabeth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>. His arrival is said to be so sudden, that the Magistrates of that City had not the opportunity to entertain him as they intended, but they have ever since deported themselves very civilly to him, which is acknowledged by his Lordship, who being not very well, made <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to land whenever he came to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, he made a stay there for the space of a week, and sent Letters to the Court at <em>Stockholm</em>, concerning the occasion of his coming. It is certified in several Letters that he stayed at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> till he had received an answer to those Letters which he had sent to the Queen.</p>

<p>I made also mention also in my last, of a large writing in Parchment, or Instrument, the Title whereof was, <i>The Government of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland and Ireland</i>. The substance whereof was.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>First that the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg>, Legislative Power of the three Nations shall be, and reside in one single Person, assisted with a Council of State, consisting of thirteen at the least, and twenty one at the most, and the Commons Assembled in Parliament.</p>

<p>That there shall be a Parliament every three years, and the next to begin on the third of <em>September</em> following.</p>

<p>The Parliaments for the time to come shall be chosen by the People, according to certain qualifications contained in the said Instrument.</p>

<p>That the time of their sitting shall be for five <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>.</p>

<p>That all Bills to be passed in Parliament shall be offered to the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em>, for his consent, which if he doth not afford assent unto within the <reg orig="compasse">compass</reg> of twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, the said Bill shall notwithstanding <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> unto, and become a Law, provided that it contains nothing contrary to the matters contained in the said Instrument.</p>

<p>That strict provision be made for the succession of Parliaments, the management of Elections, and that Returns be made by the respective Sheriffs of the persons that are Elected.</p>

<p>That the Parliament shall have power of making all Laws, saving in some cases, relating to the Guards of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and in matters of Religion, for which there is particular provision made in the Instrument, containing the Government.</p>

<p>That the LORD PROTECTOR be elective, and not hereditary, and to be chosen by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the death of the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em></p>

<p>That the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative power residing in one single Person, shall be called the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em> of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>. Decemb: 21.</head>

<p>This Day his Highness the <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em> sat with his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in the <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>-Chamber at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, it being the place where the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State used to sit, the number of them this Day that are already <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, are thirteen whose Names are as followeth.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<!-- Following 14 paras represents a list of names laid out in two columns: columns separated by a black line, transcribed going across the line and then down through the lines-->
<p>Major General <em>Lambert</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Charles Worsley</em></p>
<p>The Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em></p>
<p>Major General <em><reg orig="Desborow">Desborough</reg></em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Walter Strickland</em></p>
<p>Major General <em>Spippen</em></p>
<p>Mr: <em>Major</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Jones</em></p>
<p>Mr: <em>Laurence</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Sydenham</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Montague</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em></p>
<p>Mr.<em>Fr. Rous</em> the late Speaker.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last that the Highlanders, and some discontented Lords of <em>Scotland</em>, were <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in raising new <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, amongst whom was the Lord <em>Kinnoule</em>, whose locality, or Country confined him to raise men, being in <em>Angus</em>, and in <em>Mearns</em>; Captain <em>Lile</em> of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> Regiment had no notice of it, and marching in the night ten miles from his Quarters, with one hundred Horse, and Dragoons, he unexpectedly fell upon the Enemy by the break of Day, and took forty Horse, nineteen private Soldiers, two Captains, one Cornet and one <reg orig="Quarter-master">Quartermaster</reg>, he killed nine or ten more, they were all of the Earl of <em><reg orig="Kinnowls">Kinnowle's</reg></em> Regiment, which (as I have said) he was raising in <em>Angus</em>.</p>

<p>The names of those who were taken, are</p>
<!-- Following 14 paras represents a list of names laid out in two columns: columns separated by a black line, transcribed going across the line and then down through the lines-->
<p>Captain <em>Belfore</em></p>
<p><em>John Gardner</em></p>
<p>Captain <em>Blare</em></p>
<p><em>Robert Swan</em></p>
<p>Captain <em>Ramsey</em></p>
<p><em>John Brand</em></p>
<p>Quartermaster <em>Friar</em></p>
<p><em>Arthur Neile</em></p>
<p><em>George Black</em></p>
<p><em>John Batterson</em></p>
<p><em>John Merlum</em></p>
<p><em>Henry <reg orig="Man">Mann</reg></em></p>
<p><em>Francis Sharp</em></p>
<p><em>Henry <reg orig="Goodlee">Goodley</reg></em></p>
<p><em>David Ramsey</em></p>
<p><em>William Eviston</em></p>
<p><em>James Brace</em></p>
<p><em>John <reg orig="Mac Donnel">MacDonnel</reg></em></p>
<p><em>John Malklayn</em></p>
<p><em>Daniel Calmanick</em></p>
<p><em>William Fife</em></p>
<p><em>Archibald Gordon</em></p>
<p><em>Daniel Lawson</em></p>

<p>It is certified from <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, that the Writs issued out against persons in Debt, do make many of the <em>Lowlanders</em> to run to the <em>Highlands</em>. It is said that there are about four thousand Writs issued out against <reg orig="severall">several</reg> persons who have neither money, nor Estates to pay their Debts. Proposals <pb n="3" />therefore have been <reg orig="tendred">tendered</reg> to the Commander in chief, for the relief of poor Debtors.</p>

<p>1. That the Debts of the Inhabitants of <em>Scotland</em>, may be judged according to <em>Law</em>; and that those who are not able to pay their debts presently, may give security to pay it in a reasonable time, at a day appointed, without any use.</p>

<p>2. That such as will have benefit of the <unclear>Inferment</unclear> upon Land, may have the Land made over to them at such a rate, as it would have <reg orig="yeelded">yielded</reg> at such times as the money was lent upon it.</p>

<p>3. That the Act of pardon and Confiscation may be passed with much mercy for time past.</p>

<p>4. That a <em>Proclamation</em> be issued out, that after the said Act of <reg orig="Favor">Favour</reg> those that are to receive benefit thereof, may be so <unclear>curbed</unclear>, That if any Person contemn, or shall hereafter rise in Arms against the <em>Power</em> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; that they may be banished the three Nations, and all their Estates to be confiscated.</p> 
 
<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Decemb. 22.</head>

<p>This Day a Declaration was extant from his Highness the LORD PROTECTOR, and his Council, concerning the management of civil Affairs, to move in the same course as heretofore. It followeth in these words.</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector.</head>

<p><i>A PROCLAMATION of his <reg orig="HIGHNES">HIGHNESS</reg>, with the consent of his Council, for continuing all Persons being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, until his <reg orig="HIGHNES">HIGHNESS'</reg> further direction.</i></p>

<p>Oliver, LORD PROTECTOR of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, considering, that whereas the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the Administration of Government within the said <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, is invested, and established in his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, assisted with a Council, And left thereupon the <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and ordinary course of Justice in the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (if remedy <pb n="4" />were not provided) might receive interruption, his Highness in his care of the State, and <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Justice thereof (reserving to future consideration the reformation and redress of any abuses of Misgovernment, upon better <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> taken thereof) is pleased, and doth hereby expressly <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, declare, and ordain, by and with the advice, and consent of his Council, who have power until the meeting of the next Parliament to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary, which shall be binding, and in force until Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, That all persons who in the tenth day of this instant <em>December</em> were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction, or Government, within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, shall be, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and places respectively as formerly they held and enjoyed the same, and not otherwise, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which respect or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice, and all proceedings of what nature soever, in Courts of common Law, or Equity, or in the Court of Admiralty, or by Commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said tenth day of this instant <em>December</em>, until further Order given by his Highness therein, And that in the mean time (for the preservation of <reg orig="Publike">Public</reg> Peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, and for the safety of the State, all the said Persons, of whatsoever Place, Degree or Condition, may not fail every one severally according to his respective Place, Office or Charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all Duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them, whilst the former Government was in being.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> this 21 of Decemb: in the year of our Lord 1653</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>I made mention before of a party of the Lord <em><reg orig="Kinnowls">Kinnowle's</reg></em> new <reg orig="Leavied">Levied</reg> Regiment, routed by Captain <em>Lisle</em>. You are to understand that on the next day <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> was advertised that another party of them were lodged, and intended to Garrison themselves on the North side of <em>Angus</em>, to prevent which, he marched towards them with some Horse and foot, but the Country being as <reg orig="unfaithfull">unfaithful</reg>, as it was populous the <em>Scots</em> had notice of it, and three hours before his approach retreated towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. Howsoever he pursued them, and his diligence made that happy dispatch, that he took fifteen Horse. One Letter <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that they were so <unclear><reg orig="hazzarded">hazarded</reg></unclear> with want and travel, that being foundered, they were not worth the finding. But the Riders escaped, amongst whom was the Lord <em>Kinnowle</em> himself, and his <em>Right hand</em>, <em>Archibald Ramsay</em> his Lieutenant <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>, who if they had stayed in the Castle but two hours longer, had undoubtedly been taken.</p> 

<p>And yet for all these checks, the <em>Highlanders</em> do still proceed in their <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> of Soldiers, and <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg> the Fields wheresoever they do come. The <em>Lowlands</em> do make great complaint of it, as they have reason so to do, seeing by a wild and sad <em>metathesis</em> their <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>, and all their <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> (the pulses of their hearts only excepted) to be translated into the <em>Highlands</em>.</p>

<p>And yet both their eyes, and their hearts do follow them thither, as may appear by their daily complaints to our Commander in chief, not so much (<reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> my Letter) for any love to the English cause, as to make provision for themselves, by having the Goods they have lost recovered, and those which they have left secured.</p>

<p>There is a report that three hundred and three and thirty Barrels of powder have been discovered about this City, in several Storehouses, whose they were, or from whence they came, cannot yet be learned, which gives to many (and those not the least) a great occasion of <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>.</p>

<p>The three lusty <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and the <em>Marigold</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> being gone from <em>Yernmuth</em> Road to the <em>Downs</em>, to increase the number of our Fleet, for <pb n="6" />the guarding of the Seas. The <em>Expedition</em> hath since followed them from <em>Harwich</em>, and so have also the <em>Convertine</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and the <em>Centurion</em>, and the <em>Middleborough</em> (a Man of War taken from the <em>Dutch</em>) The <em>Advice</em>, the <em>constant Warwick</em>, the <em>Recovery</em>, and the <em>Advantage</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are following after. The <em>George</em>, the <em>James</em>, the <unclear><em>Lyon</em></unclear>, and the <em><reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg></em> are setting forth from <em>Chattam</em>. And so is the <em>Resolution</em>, but this last not so quickly as was expected.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Decemb: 23.</head> 

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the <em>Highlanders</em> newly <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> and those who were in Arms before, are all marched Northwards, to receive monies, Arms, and Ammunition, which (it is told them) is sent from their King, and from the States of Holland. Those who stay behind are Quartered in those Parishes among the Lowlands, which are <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>. The Lord <em>Kenmore</em> doth resolve (as it is informed) to raise Men, Horses, and <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, on this side of <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, and to make some <reg orig="Inrodes">Inroads</reg> into the Borders of <em>England</em>. Twenty Horsemen well mounted, and armed with pistols, and swords did very lately ride through <em>Durham</em>, &amp; took up their Quarter at <em>Plebees</em>, where the dumb Prophet is <reg orig="stil">still</reg> alive. It seems by this that they hold a correspondence with some in <em>England</em>, and that the Design is greater <reg orig="then">than</reg> represented. There was with them a <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg>, who was heretofore a Commander in the <reg orig="Parliaments">Parliament's</reg> party. We have lately taken one Captain <em>Stewart</em> raising Forces for his King, and Major <em>Moreland</em>, who was heretofore a Prisoner of War. The <em>Highlanders</em> do boast that fifteen hundred Volunteers, most of them <em>Irish</em>, are landed with more Arms, and Ammunition, and that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Diamond</em> hath bought a Dispatch from their King.</p>

<p>The <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg></em> party begin to be very hold on this side <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>. The Post boy coming from thence to London, was <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by them, and his Horse, <reg orig="mony">money</reg>, and Letters taken from him, so that it will be uncertain sending Letters without a Convoy. The young Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> is dead of a consumption, his two Elder Brothers perished in the late <pb n="7" />War unmarried, so that if he hath no children by marriage himself, that <em>Family</em>, which is the greatest In <em>Scotland</em> is extinguished. The Estate doth come to the Marquis of <em>Argyle</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb: 24</head>

<p>It is advertised, that the General <em>Monk</em> was with a Fleet of about 35 Sail lately at <em>Stoaks Bay</em>, some Prizes were then brought in laden with Linen and other Commodities. The <em>Dutch</em> are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in the West, so that it is very hard to pass by the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end without a Convoy. There is a ship taken by them laden with Malts, Beaver skins, and other Commodities.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Decemb: 26</head>

<p>This day came forth the Ordinance for the continuation of the Excise, which is to be managed and carried on by such good ways and means as may be most for the ease of the people, and advantage of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p>

<p>It was this day advertised, that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> was coming down to <em>Cleave</em>, and that he was invited by the Duke of <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em> into his territories which are the furthest parts of <em>Germany</em>, whither he will move it is yet uncertain. Prince <em>Rupert</em> hath been often heard to lament, that he ever <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> himself in the late unnatural war in <em>England</em>, wherein so many misfortunes and such <reg orig="il-wil">ill will</reg> attended him.</p>

<p>There were some Ministers this last week under custody, and examined before the Council for preaching against the present Government, but promising more care for the future, they were discharged.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable, is:</head>

<p><i>The resolution of the <em>Highlanders</em> to invade the North of <em>England</em>, and divers Horse gone out of <em>England</em> to them. Their great boast of a Letter of Encouragement from their King, and great sums of money, Arms, and Ammunition landed: Two parties of them taken by our Forces, with a list of their Names. A great design against this City suspected, and the reasons of it. <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> Prizes taken, and the last News from <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em>, and our Fleet at Sea.</i></p> 
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>