<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell325">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 325</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, March 28. to <em>Tuesday</em>, April 4. 1653.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 28.</head>

<p>Although peradventure it be not much minded here, and there is no need for it, yet in my opinion the endeavours of <em><reg orig="Monseur">Monsieur</reg> De Servient</em>, a great Minister of the State in the Kingdom of <em>France</em> are very remarkable, he declares that he will <reg orig="inrich">enrich</reg> and reform the whole State, and that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Crown Land shall be bought again; and that, after that, the people shall not be undone by so many Taxes.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>France</em>, that the Reformed Churches begin there to be much mistrusted that they neither are nor will be quiet; their Deputies have made their complaints at Court with great <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> and resolution; and the Baron of <em>Estissack</em> hath been heard to affirm, that the Reformed Churches have sent advertisements into <em>England</em>, and that for certain they have some design in hand contrary to the service of his Majesty.</p>

<p>It is certain that the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> begins to be favoured<pb n="1" /> again by the <em>Spaniard</em>, for the Archduke hath ordered, that the Earl of <em>Bussigny</em>, and the Abbot of <em>Mercy</em> shall be removed from the Castle of <em>Antwerp</em> to the Castle of <em>Gant</em>, on purpose to <reg orig="gratifie">gratify</reg> the Duke of <em>Lorrain</em>, who was very much offended that they should be imprisoned in the same prison with him. The Letters from <em>Brussels</em> do advertise, that many <em>Irish</em> do daily arrive there out of <em>Ireland</em>, who are all to secure the Pr: of <em>Conde</em>, and are marching to <em>Namur</em> where they are to be clothed, and armed. They are said to be men <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="poore">poor</reg>, and for the most part naked; many of them <reg orig="dye">die</reg> through want and poverty in the <reg orig="wayt">wait</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 29.</head>

<p>It was advertised from <em>Holland</em> that great preparations we have made to put forth to Sea doth much startle them there, but it is hoped that the Treaty will be Signed before the two Fleets do meet abroad.</p>

<p><i>I shall in this place give you a List of several Prizes taken by the <em>Ph&aelig;nix, Newcastle, Assurance</em>, and <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> since February, 1653.</i></p>

<p><em>March 2</em>. taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one Galliot hoy, whose mast being shot by the board, she was burnt.</p>

<p>Taken the same day by the <em>Assurance</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the <em>Hope</em> of <em>Housdown</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p>Taken then also by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> the <em>Claus</em> of <em>Housdown</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, only Ballast on board.</p>

<p><em>March 14</em>. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaids">Mermaid's</reg></em> Boat, the <em>Skell-fish</em> of <em>Mazelana Sluys</em> with Fish, Salt, and some empty Cask.</p>

<p>Taken the same day also by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat, the <em>Phampart</em> of <em>Muzeland Sluys</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> thirty <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise.</p>

<p><em>March 12.</em> Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> the <em>Providence</em> of <em>Mazeland Sluys</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading.</p>

<p><em>March 17</em>. Brought by the Lee by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em>, and her boat sent on board, and afterward run on board by the <em>Newcastle</em>, who broke her head, and Boltsprit, and forced the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> her Boat off, <em>viz</em>: the <em>Fortune</em> of <em>Delfs Haven</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with brandy Wine, French Wine, prunes, <em>&amp;c.</em></p><pb n="2" />

<p>Taken the same day by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> the <em><reg orig="Blew">Blue</reg> pigech</em> of <em>Pumurland</em>, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden also with Brandy Wine, French Wines, and Prunes.</p>

<p><em>March 18.</em> Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Galliot Hoy, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>.</p>

<p><em>March 19</em>. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Meremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> two <em>Scotch</em> Vessels; the one laden with Beef, Flower, Train <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Deer-skins, and Sugars, the other had only Ballast; both of them were going for <em>Holland</em>, having been first taken by a Private Man of War belonging to <em>Enchuisen</em>, but thus recovered.</p>

<p>March 20. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> the <em>Waking Bay</em> of <em>Enchuysen</em>, and with her eight guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable, twelve Pikes, ten Muskets, eight Pistols, and a Boat with four Oars.</p>

<p>It is advertised by Letters from <em>Scotland</em> that since <em>Middleton</em>, there is a Lord landed with some more men, and Arms.</p>

<head level="3"><i>From the Hague the 27 March</i></head>

<p>The last Thursday were brought here in a Pink sent for that purpose Letters of the 20. Instant from the Lord Ambassadors now in <em>England</em>, whereby we hear they give advice to the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> States, that the Treaty of Peace was not yet concluded, but that preparations for sea were made there in <reg orig="al">all</reg> <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, the occasion <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> was unknown to them, which caused some <reg orig="suspitions">suspicions</reg>, and jealousies amongst the said <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> States; Insomuch that the Vice Admiral <em>Ruyter</em>, and the Scout by night, <em>Tromp</em>, with other Captains received Orders to resort presently to <em>Amsterdam</em>, which they did accordingly on Wednesday morning, as also several Messengers were dispatched to the <reg orig="Counsels">Councils</reg> of the Admiralties. The Lieut: Admiral: the Lord <em>Van Opdam</em> was likewise commanded to come from <em>Brabans</em> where he was, hither.</p>

<p>And yet we cannot understand by the Letters come from <em>London</em> the night between the 20. and 21. that any difficulties should have risen wherefore the Treaty should not go on, so that it is <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg> that the same may have a good success, and that those preparations made there may be for some other<pb n="3" /> design. We have very little certainty of the Scottish Affairs. It is presumed that <em>Middleton</em> is arrived in <em>Scotland</em> to gather what forces he can to restore the titular King his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> Fortune. Last night a Pink hath been by the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> States dispatched from <em>Scheveling</em> into <em>England</em>, though he be but stirring up <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> to a boy, which without question will break this Spring.</p>

<p>What more thunderbolts yet? Is this all we can say of Peace during all this Treaty betwixt us and <em>Holland</em> would not any man think it sufficient, when that men are to treat upon <reg orig="indifferencie">indifference</reg> which concern themselves, that they should agree for themselves, and leave the rest to stand or fall upon their own <reg orig="leggs">legs</reg> ? is it not sufficient that we are like to <reg orig="loose">lose</reg> more by others; but me thinks this doth not <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the Reader, <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> more particularly thus: These Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> have protracted much time to little purpose, unless they suddenly conclude for themselves &amp; leave out <em>Denmark</em>, about which they pretend they must have new Instructions, or Orders from their Superiors, and have sent Letters accordingly, and the States have sent Letters unto them: In the mean time Action grows ripe both for Sea and Land, (and truly we have seldom sailed of good success over a Fast.)</p>

<p>At a late <reg orig="Randezouze">Rendezvous</reg> of <em>Holland</em> Fleet they talk of 300 sail, besides 50 Fireships, and at a Land <reg orig="randezvous">rendezvous</reg>, in <em>Scotland</em> they give forth of themselves, that they are 10000 Foot, and 7000 <reg orig="pitifull">pitiful</reg> Horses; and still they are forcing the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, and fed with such fond thoughts from beyond Sea, that the common <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> begin to vapour, and say that at their next <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> they will cry, <em>Vive Le Roy</em>.</p>

<p>Now to let you understand how this business is <reg orig="ballanced">balanced</reg>, take notice that the English fleet is floating upon the Narrow seas in a most stately <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg>, both for gallantry, and number. Also the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> having <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> <em>Ireland</em> in a gallant posture of Peace, and <reg orig="quietnes">quietness</reg>, is returned safe, and in <em>Scotland</em> (for all the proud boasts of the Enemy) our Army<pb n="4" /> desire nothing more, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to have a fair combat with them.</p>

<p>We have given fair satisfaction before of the Audience of the <em>French</em> Ambassador, and his Speech. I wish the difference (which brake forth into blows) between the French <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Gentlemen, and <em>Portugal</em> Ambassadors at <em>Tower-hill</em> after their landing, may not prove a bad <em>Omen</em>.</p>

<p>We have Intelligence of 5 ships more taken this week, and of a fight about an hour long betwixt 5 of the <em>Dutch</em>, and 3 English,, and 3 <em>English</em> took 2 of the <em>Dutch</em>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday, March 30.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> it is advertised, that the Ld: <em>Ray</em> hath sent to Gen: <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Magazine for Arms. <em>Seafort</em> with his 700 men was not long since to be at <em>Crabsdale</em>. Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, and Gen: <em>Monroe</em> <reg orig="then">than</reg> at <em>Strathsnager</em> in the <em>North</em>. The whole Body of the <em>Scotch</em> both Horse and Foot were some few days afterwards to rendezvous at <em>Jure</em>.</p>

<p>The Garrison of <em>Leuys</em> have made slaughter of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> people who at <em>Crabsdale</em> <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with <em>Seafort</em>. The old Inhabitants <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> with our men against the rest of the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, so that the divisions amongst themselves do cause great devastations in those parts. Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> is again come down from the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, and divers parties in several places steal Horses, which, it is said, that the wit of man cannot prevent. The Commander in chief of Scotland hath put forth a Proclamation, requiring all Burroughs to secure all suspicious persons, or to give intelligence of them to the next garrisons or quarters, under the penalty of being deemed Enemies to the present Government, and to be proceeded against accordingly. Several Towns hath been lately found guilty of the breach of this Proclamation, and have been fined by a Court Marshal for the same. The Fast week, a Town but 2 miles from <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> was fined 200 li. sterling for harbouring fifteen of the Enemy for the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving intelligence of them, at their going away they stole 15 horses. The person in whose house they were concealed is during pleasure to suffer Imprisonment<pb n="5" />, and the house where they were harboured is ordered to be razed to the ground, and a pair of Gallows to be raised in the same place. There are divers other Parishes who on the same account are summoned in to the Court Marshal, and will suffer with them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, March 31.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> it is again advertised, that <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Cooper</em> with a party of Horse and Dragoons being seconded with another party of ours did fall into the Isle of <em>Leven</em> where 300 of the Enemy were quartered, they took a Trumpeter and 35 other prisoners, and narrowly missed <em><reg orig="Mac Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em> who was Commander in chief, and <unclear>Peauzh</unclear> his Lieutenant <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, they killed 12 of the Enemy, one of them was a Lieutenant of Horse; they took 60 Horse and some Arms, and totally routed the whole party.</p>

<p>By Letters from the West it is advertised that the Commander of the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Merchant, and sent her into <em>Plymouth</em>, she was for the most part unladen. Another of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> called the <em>Paul</em> hath taken a <em>Flushing</em> Man of War of fifteen guns, she is also sent into <em>Plymouth</em>, the fight continued five hours, we lost not many men, but sustained some <reg orig="dammages">damages</reg> in the sails, and Rigging; the enemy lost thirteen men, and the ships much torn, there was silver, and Wine in her, enough to make merry the hearts of those that took her.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em> April: 1.</head>

<p>Yesterday an Ordinance was passed for suspending the proceedings of the Judges in the Act Intituled, <i>The Act for Relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</i>, it is to this effect.</p>

<p>Whereas upon perusal, and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, Intituled, An Act for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners, many Doubts, and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorized for sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such<pb n="6" /> Explanation, and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges authorized in, and by the said Act, several inconveniences, and mischiefs would grow, not only to the said Creditors, and Prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles, and suits in Law, and Equity; For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: And whereas many of the said Prisoners have offered really to <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the satisfaction of the said Creditors if some further time may be given for that purpose. Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale, or Disposition of any Estates Real or Personal, of any of the said Prisoners, or any other person or persons whatsoever, mentioned or intended in or by the said Act; or of any the powers or authorities given by the same, until the 20 day of <em>April</em> next. And be it further ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that all Acts or things to be done by the said several and respective Judges, or any of them, by virtue, colour, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said 20 day of <em>April</em>, shall be utterly void, null, and of none effect; saving only that it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg>, and may be lawful for the said several and respective Judges that have bailed, or let our Prisoners, <em>&amp;c</em></p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 3.</head>

<p>I was in good hope to be the first man that should inform you of the Signing and Sealing of the Articles of Peace betwixt the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, and of the glad sight of the Olive leaves under the happy Government of <em>Oliver</em> our Protector, I am the Trumpet that sounds before it, you will suddenly hear the Proclamation published.</p>

<p>It is advertised, that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is yet in <em>France</em>, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty will produce betwixt <em>England</em> and<pb n="7" /> <em>France</em>. He had a Present given him a little before <em>Easter</em> but some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom. In the <reg orig="Holydayes">Holidays</reg> his Mother came to see him in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal, and the King her Nephew in the <em>Lovure</em>, and on the next day returned to her devotions in the Nunnery. There is a Report of two <em>English</em> ships brought into <em>Tholoon</em>, which it is said, were taken by the <em>French</em> not far from <em>Messina</em>.</p>

<p>The Letters from <em>Scotland</em> speak of the <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlander's</reg></em> Army <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> all into one Body, which no doubt will be dispersed again into several parties for the Countries where they are, are so wasted, that they cannot maintain them, and it is probable they will not draw together with an intent to give <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg> until the middle of <em>May</em>, before which time the Peace with <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em> will so startle them, that they will have but little Resolution to fight.</p>

<p>The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War of fourteen Guns, and sent her into <em>Burlington Bay</em>; This was one of the four Capers that did much annoy us on the Northern Seas. The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> lay cruising three or four <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before he <reg orig="handsomly">handsomely</reg> could snap her.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p>&#x261e; The Articles of Peace betwixt <em>England, Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, absolutely concluded on. A great Victory obtained against the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>, with the true manner, and particulars of the Fight, and the number of the Enemy killed, and taken Prisoners. A great Fight at Sea, and some <em>Dutch</em> Men of War taken. The present condition of the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> in <em>France</em>, and a Present made unto him by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Nation. The Commissioners for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners not to proceed these twenty <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>.</p>
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>