<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell204">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 204</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, February 7. to <em>Tuesday</em>, February: 14. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, February 7.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised by Letters read in the Council, that the Merchants of <em>Bristol</em> had lost three ships by the <em>French</em> Men of War, the <em>Unicorn</em> of one hundred and twenty <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg>, carrying eight Guns, the <em>Swan</em> much about the same bulk, she was taken under the <em>Isle of Scilly</em> by two Men of War of <em>France</em>, one of which carried 38 guns, and was commanded by Captain <em>Beach</em> an English man, the <em>Mary Rose</em> was taken, was after a long fight which continued almost seven hours, taken by a Man of War belonging to <em>Ostend</em>, and was carried unto <em>Dunkirk</em>; the <em>French <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> have also taken three ships in the Westerns Seas belonging to <em>Barstable</em>, which they have carried into <em>Normandy</em>; one of the English ships was so torn in her bulk, and so unrigged in her sails with the long fight, that one of the Men of War were enforced to tow her along with him; one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> did what she could to rescue her, but the French ship being a good <reg orig="sayler">sailor</reg>, she could not overtake her, although she gave chase to the <em>Royal James</em> <pb n="1" /> (for so the ship was called) for the space of six and thirty hours, much about the same time the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> took a Dutch Man of War of 20 Guns, and 70 Men, she is sent also into <em>Plymouth</em>, five sail that came from <em>Maligo</em> which (as the times go) may prove Prizes.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Febr: 8.</head>

<p>Although the Merchants of <em>Bristol</em> complain of their late losses, yet their grief is mitigated by the arrival of some of the long Fleet from <em>Maligo</em>, and with the good news they brought that the remainder are safe at <em>Galloway</em> in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>They brought with them Intelligence that the French men had taken two ships belonging to <em>Milford Haven</em>, as they were sailing for <em>Ireland</em>, and standing off more to the South, they took three ships more, laden with Lead, and fish.</p>

<p>The <em>French</em> Men of War when the wind is Easterly, do <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> about the <em>Isle of Lundy</em>, and the Lands end, and if the Wind be Westring, they <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> about <em>Scilly</em>, taking all opportunities, that but give the least invitation for their profit. The Names of the Captain <em><reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> belonging to <em>Brest</em> in <em>Normandy</em> are these.</p>

<p>The <em>Royal James</em>, with 38 guns, <em>Richard Beach</em> Commander.</p>
<p>The <em>Michael</em>, 14 guns, <em>James Smith</em></p>
<p>The <em>Briget</em> with 8 guns, <em>William Smith</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> 10 guns, <em>Meldrum</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Mall</em> 10 guns, <em>Covel</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Loyal James</em> with 12 guns, <em>James Dillon</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Saint Mary</em> 4 guns, <em>Richard Dillon</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> with 10 guns, <em>William Durant</em>.</p>
<p>The &mdash; with 8 guns, <em>Jones</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Margaret</em> with 3 guns, <em>Heldish</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Francis</em> with 22 guns, <em>Martin</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Patrick</em> with 18 guns, <em>Swart</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Katherine</em> with 6 guns, <em>Estmond</em>.</p>
<p>The <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <em>Michael</em> with 6 guns, <em>Peters</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Snow</em> with 4 guns. <em>Nich: Murro</em>.</p>
<p>The <em>Adventure</em> with two guns, <em>George Lodde</em></p>
<p>Three <em>French men</em> with 15. 18. 20.</p>
<p>Three in the Stocks of 4 guns a <reg orig="peece">piece</reg></p><pb n="2" />

<p>In the mean time General <em>Blake</em>, and Gen: <em>Pen</em> have in several squadrons sent forth some part of our Fleet, who have sent in six considerable Prizes, one of which I have already mentioned in the passages.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that Major <em><reg orig="Knights">Knight's</reg></em> Cornet hath taken the Captain Lieutenant of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em> Regiment. A party of Scotchmen who formerly have done good service have been <reg orig="incouraged">encouraged</reg> to increase their numbers, and our Forces there have found an advantage by it; for having the Scottish tone, and broad <reg orig="pronuntiation">pronunciation</reg>, they have been taken by the <em>Highlanders</em> to be their friends, and by this mistake they have betrayed themselves unto them.</p>

<p>It is advertised, but not <reg orig="beleeved">believed</reg>, that the Lord <em>Seafort</em> hath stormed our Fort at Lewis Island with 1400 men, and taken it. The Governor which we had there was so confident of the strength of the place, that he said he could defend it against 10000 Assaulters, and he had intelligence before that <em>Seafort</em> had an intent to storm it.</p>

<p>There is a report that the Queen of <em>Swedeland</em> hath sent a Letter to the Titular King of the <em>Scots</em> by the importunity of Mr. <em>Crofts</em> who <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> himself his Ambassador, the substance of the said Letter is said to be, That her Majesty doth excuse <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, that the present condition of her affairs doth not permit her to give satisfaction to his Demands; and that she for the present can <reg orig="onely">only</reg> but contribute <reg orig="pitie">pity</reg> to his misfortunes.</p>

<p>The last news from <em>Holland</em>, is that although most of the Provinces have consented to the Articles of agreement, to the Peace betwixt <em>England</em> and themselves, yet <em>Freizland</em> stands off, and all the rest are under a cloud of <reg orig="jealousie">jealousy</reg>, for their <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are making ready with all the speed that may be, in which the Shipwrights by a strict command are so <reg orig="prophanely">profanely</reg> diligent that they do work <reg orig="Sundayes">Sundays</reg>, and all their whole Fleet will be ready to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth within these three weeks at furthest. The <em>French</em> Ambassador is most importunate to obstruct the proceedings of the Peace; and it is thought he will receive an Answer agreeable to his <reg orig="minde">mind</reg><pb n="3" /> in favour of those many and great testimonies of friendship which the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of the United Provinces hath enjoyed from the Crown of <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>The <em>Hollanders</em> have taken an English Man of War In the mouth of the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, and brought her into <em>Marseilles</em>, they have also brought into <em>Flushing</em> an English private Man of War, carrying six Guns. Three ships of <em>Denmark</em> are come to <em>Flushing</em>, laden with great Guns, and Ammunition of War. Those of <em>Ostend</em> (say the Letters from <em>Flushing</em>) have taken from our Fleet, though we be friends with them, five ships laden with cheese, and other commodities.</p>

<p>This being the Day appointed for entertaining his Highness the Lord Protector in the City of <em>London</em>, in the morning the streets from <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> hall in the Poultery to Temple Bar, were railed in on both sides the way, and the four and twenty Companies met at their several <reg orig="Hals">Halls</reg>, and about eleven of the clock they took their places within the said Rails, and all along the said Rails were set up a great many <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg>, and streams bearing the Arms of the respective Companies, and the Rails themselves were covered with <reg orig="blew">blue</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg>. Then the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen (on horseback) went to meet his Highness at Temple Bar, the sword-bearer carrying the Sword before him and when his Highness came the Lord Mayor took the Sword, and presented it to his Highness, and then his Highness delivered it back again unto him, and after some other Ceremonies performed, his Highness came through the City attended in this manner, <em>viz</em>.</p>

<p>First came a Marshal, and after him five Trumpets sounding, then came about sixty Gentlemen in gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg>, and well mounted, after them came six Trumpeters, and four heralds at Arms, next after them were carried nine white <reg orig="Flaggs">Flags</reg>, and after them <pb n="4" /> the Lord <reg orig="Mayors">Mayor's</reg> Officers, and the Clerks, <reg orig="Attornies">Attorneys</reg>, and other Officers belonging to the City, all on foot, then came the Sheriff, and Aldermen on horseback all in their scarlet Gowns, and next before his Highness the Lord Mayor bare-headed, carrying the Sword himself before him, his Highness having on a musk coloured Suit, richly <reg orig="imbroydered">embroidered</reg> with Gold, and the light Horse that was led by him, had a very rich <reg orig="imbroydered">embroidered</reg> Saddle, the Pistols <reg orig="fastned">fastened</reg> to the saddle had their locks, and barrels made of silver.</p>

<p>As his Highness passed by, the People were uncovered, and his Highness as he went, continually moved his hat to the People; there followed after his Highness about threescore <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg>, and other Superior Officers in very rich habits, and after them came two rich Coaches of his Highness with six stately Horses <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg>, the Postillions, and Coachmen riding bare, only with black velvet caps; after them followed thirteen other Coaches, <reg orig="al">all</reg> with six Horses <reg orig="apeece">apiece</reg>, in which were most of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Council, and seventeen other Coaches followed after them: The shops were shut up in Cheapside, and so to Temple-bar, and the <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> rung in every steeple. When his Highness came to Grocers-Hall (which was a little after two of the clock) he was most Royally entertained, with abundance of the <reg orig="choisest">choicest</reg> delicates this rich and plentiful City could afford. There was also a Song prepared, but it seems in great <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>. Do you <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> of it.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Come away, blest soul no more</line>
<line>Feed your eyes with what is poor;</line>
<line>It is enough that you have blest</line>
<line>What was rude, what was <reg orig="undrest">undressed</reg>.</line><pb n="5" />
<line>Come away, and cast your eyes</line>
<line>On this humble Sacrifice:</line>
<line>We no golden apples give,</line>
<line><reg orig="Heer's">Here's</reg> no Adam, <reg orig="heer's">here's</reg> no Eve,</line>
<line>Not a Serpent dares appear,</line>
<line>Whilst your Highness stayeth here.</line>
<line>Oh then sit, and take your due,</line>
<line>Those the first fruits are that grew.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>His Highness took his place in the middle of the upper Table in the great Hall, and his Son the Lord <em>Henry Cromwell</em> on the left hand, and the Lord Mayor on the right hand; and at the Table on each side of them sat the Council, with Gen: <em>Monk</em>, Commissary Gen: <em>Whaley</em>, Coll: <em>Pride</em>, Coll: <em>Hewson</em>, and other <reg orig="Collonels">Colonels</reg> and Officers of the Army, and <reg orig="Musick">Music</reg> and Singing continued all Dinner while. The Dinner being ended, the Lord Mayor conducted his Highness up stairs to a rich and stately Banquet; and about six of the clock at night his Highness and his Retinue repaired again towards <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em></p>

<p>Having received a present of forty dozen of silver Plates, to the value of two thousand pound, and Knighted the Lord Mayor, to whom he gave a very rich Sword in the remembrance of him, &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 9</head>

<p>This Day produced but little News, only that <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Mackworth</em> Governor of <em><reg orig="Shresbury">Shrewsbury</reg></em> was made one of his Highness Council: New Judges will suddenly be made to ride this next Circuit.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Febr: 10.</head>

<p><reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> parts afford but little News, the depth of the snow, and the <reg orig="extreamity">extremity</reg> of the cold Winter, of which they have been more sensible in other Countries, freezing the tame Sword in the sheath, and keeping the Soldier in his Quarters, but in <em>Scotland</em> they are so hot, their fury will admit of no cessation, the <em>Highlanders</em> in their bold <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> do force the <reg orig="plowmen">ploughmen</reg> to be soldiers, and turn their ploughshares<pb n="6" /> into swords, if they will not be obedient to their Drums, they plunder them, and where they find opposition, they do their utmost endeavour to lay all <reg orig="wast">waste</reg> behind them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Feb: 11</head>

<p>The Ratification of the Peace with <em>England</em> doth to all outward <reg orig="apparence">appearance</reg> very fairly advance <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> in <em>England</em>; It is reported that the States General of the United Provinces were sending the Lord <em>Brederode</em> to be their Ambassador, and with him the Lord <em>Opdam</em> Admiral of their Navy, but the Lord <em>Brederode</em> by reason of his great age, hath desired to be excused, what the event of the Treaty will be, will suddenly appear.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last, that our Fleet was put forth to Sea, but it hath since appeared otherwise, for by several Letters both on this day, and on <em>Tuesday</em> last it was advertised that our Fleet doth still ride <reg orig="neer">near</reg> unto Saint <em><reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg></em> point.</p>

<p>There lately passed by <em>Portsmouth</em> thirty sail of our <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships, which came all from the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>, <reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg>, Portugal</em>, and from the Bay of <em>Biscay</em>, who are all safely arrived on the River of <em>Thames</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised that a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War which carried 9 Guns, and did ride in <em>Calice</em> Road was beaten upon the shore and broken in pieces, and many of the men drowned.</p>

<p>The <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath been very active, and at Sea again, she hath brought into <em>Burlington bay</em>, a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <em>Dutch</em> Man Of War of four Guns, and about <reg orig="fourty">forty</reg> men in her; this was that ship which took some of our <reg orig="Colliars">Colliers</reg> as they were coming and going for Coals; the Captain and the men are sent to <reg orig="Jayl">Jail</reg> at <em>York</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>France</em>, that the Pr: of <em><reg orig="Condies">Condy's</reg></em> Brother is come to <em>Paris</em>, where he is gallantly received, and is to marry one of the fair <reg orig="Neeces">Nieces</reg> of the Cardinal. There hath been a long debate in the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of <em>France</em> concerning the sending of an Ambassador extraordinary to <em>England</em>, which some say is the Marshal of <em>Clarumbant</em>, others affirm it is the Marquis of <em>Arpason</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Febr: 13.</head>

<p>It was also certified from <em>France</em>, that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> hath been sorely shaken with so <reg orig="shrew'd">shrewd</reg> a spirit as an Ague, and is not yet rid of it; many young Lords of the Kingdom, both of the one religion, and the other, do daily come to visit him. The Protestant Nobility have of late been much respected, and preferred by the King of <em>France</em>, the Cardinal <em>Mazarini</em> no <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> repining at it.</p>

<p>Letters from <em>Holland</em> do make mention, that they even make themselves sure there of a Peace with <em>England</em>, to which the sending back of some Prisoners of which we had taken, and the continuance of our Fleet at St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point, which might have <reg orig="alarum'd">alarmed</reg> them, doth make them to presume the more of it. I am informed of a Letter which advertiseth of seven ships gone lately with Arms from <em>Holland</em> to the <em>Highlanders</em>, but I much doubt the truth of it, by reason of the present overtures, and the hazard they should run by so doing. I made mention before of some ships taken by the Dutch from us: We have taken this week seventeen ships from them, eleven whereof, some being Merchants, and some Men of War, are very considerable.</p>

<p>The Letters this Day make mention of some <reg orig="shipwracks">shipwrecks</reg> by reason of the high winds at Sea on the 4 and 5 of this present <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>. The Irish taking the advantage of the Winter season, play their pranks in some parts of the Nation, but they may be shortly met with.</p>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Daniel</em> hath done good service not far from St: <em><reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg></em>, and taken nine Troopers well mounted, their Cornet being killed upon the place. <em>Glencarn</em> hath sent a terrible Letter to the Scots Troop in our Army, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> them with the utmost <reg orig="extreamities">extremities</reg>, for the injuries received by them, and for the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of his Captain Lieutenant, who is his kinsman, so ruinous is his Resolution, that whosoever of their own Nation, will not deliver up their Men and Horses to serve him in the War, are to have their Families, and themselves imprisoned, and their Houses burnt with unquenchable fire.</p> 

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable is:</head>

<p><i>A Victory obtained against the Highlanders, and the number taken, and slain. Seventeen <em>Dutch</em> Merchants, and Men of War taken by the <em>English</em>, and the number of our <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships taken by the <em>Dutch</em>. The dangerous <reg orig="sicknes">sickness</reg> of the titular Duke of <em>York</em> at <em>Paris</em>. The substance of the <reg orig="Recorders">Recorder's</reg> Speech at the Lord <reg orig="Mayors">Mayor's</reg> magnificent <reg orig="extertainment">entertainment</reg> of his Highness a present of two thousand pound in silver Plates conferred on his Highness; the Lord Mayor Knighted, and a rich sword given him by the Lord Protector. New Judges to be chosen for the next Circuit. An Ambassador extraordinary expected from <em>France</em>. And the great outrages committed by <em>Glencarn</em>, and his terrible Letter to devour all with the fire, and sword.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>