<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell203">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 202#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />
<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 31. to <em>Tuesday</em>, February: 7. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January: 31.</head>

<p>Peace is now the main business which after so many Wars the Nations in <em>Europe</em> do pant after; It is that which we desire; it is that which the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>Holland</em> doth <reg orig="solicite">solicit</reg>; it is that which the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>Venice</em> do expect from the <em>Turks</em>, and would in some measure be accountable for it; it is that which the Pope, who is called the Father of the Church endeavours to procure, that in his <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> he may see (as he himself writes) an union betwixt his two great Sons, the most <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> King, and the most Christian King, but we look for our Peace at the latter end of the next <em>March</em>, and the others (for ought I can yet see) especially if some care help it, may look for theirs at latter <em>Lammas</em>.</p> 

<p>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> at <em>Amsterdam</em> have put forth this following Declaration.</p>

<p>The Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Admiralty residing at <em>Amsterdam</em>, To all those to whom these presents shall come, <em>Greeting</em>.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>Let it be known, that it being conceived, thought, and apparent, that upon the coming of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Deputies of this State from <em>England</em>, to make Report how far the Treaty is by <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> grace and favour effected: Some Merchants, and Masters of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships, upon presumption of a cessation of hostility, have been so forward as to have brought out their ships, and goods, and have beyond their hope suffered <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>.</p>

<p>We have therefore found good, and resolved to give warning unto all it concerneth; That the former hostility doth yet continue, and that it is not fit, nor convenient, that one should in regard of the Treaty think himself secure, before upon the continuation of the Negotiation, there shall be a cessation of the aforesaid hostility Proclaimed.</p>

<p><i>Acted in the Assembly of the said Council, the 16 alias 26 of Jan: 1653. 4</i></p>

<p><i>F: Herberts.</i></p>
<p><i>And by Order of the same.</i></p>
<p><i>David Wildt.</i></p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Febr: 1.</head>

<p>Whiles they are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in <em>Holland</em>, our Commanders, and Officers at Sea are as diligent for the <reg orig="Ingaging">Engaging</reg> of themselves to this present Government, under his Highness the Lord Protector: it follows thus.</p>

<p><i>The DECLARATION, with the humble Address of the Generals, and the several Commanders present in the Fleet, by them severally subscribed.</i></p>

<p>That these Nations of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, having been for some years like the bush which burned, but is not consumed: And though the Nations round about us stand gazing on to see us made a desolation, as well as a hissing unto them; yet we are hitherto by the mighty power of the Lord, and his wonderful outgoings amongst us, made rather an astonishment in our preservation, <reg orig="then">than</reg> a reproach, by our <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> and devastation.</p>

<p>In which great work of the Lord, we <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> with thankfulness Your Highness hath been a glorious Instrument<pb n="2" />; and hath undergone many hardships, and <reg orig="hazzard">hazard</reg> of all that was near and dear unto you, even to life itself, and understanding by providence Your Highness is <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> with, and hath accepted of the protection of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in the Government thereof.</p>

<p>We are in hopes that the Lord intends a settlement of Peace to these poor distracted Nations; and that our selves with all the People of the Lord <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="injoy">enjoy</reg>, and partake of the same under your protection, according to the Rule of the Lord Jesus. And <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> we have thought it necessary as a duty incumbent on us to declare, that we shall willingly be obedient, and <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> to your Highness, in performance of Your great Trust, and also in the utmost <reg orig="venter">venture</reg> our lives, (with what else is near and dear unto us) be serviceable unto you in the station the Lord hath placed You, against Yours, and the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Enemies in our <reg orig="severall">several</reg> places, and capacities, during our employments.</p>

<p>And having good testimony of Your great affection, and earning bowels after the <reg orig="Weale">Weal</reg> of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> People, we are <reg orig="imboldned">emboldened</reg> and encouraged to make this following Address.</p>

<p>That Your Highness will be pleased to have a more special eye of favour unto them above all others, in regard they are near and dear unto him, who is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, even our Lord Jesus. For which cause he is not ashamed to call them Brethren; And do humbly apprehend that their <reg orig="Priviledges">Privileges</reg> will be Your <reg orig="Priviledg">Privilege</reg>. And to account of them as of your greatest Jewels, which <reg orig="wil">will</reg> doubtless turn to you great advantage.</p>

<p>And hereby You will for time to come not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> engage their hearts unto You, who in times past have not stood at a distance from You, But Your Highness will also engage the great Jehovah, Your and their Father to be a refuge, Shield and defence unto You as well as an everlasting rest for You, when all the storms of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> shall cease, which <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be the <reg orig="unfaigned">unfeigned</reg> prayers of,</p> 

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> most humble, and faithful Servants,</i></p><pb n="3" />

<p>I made mention in my last of the Speech made by the Ld: Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, on the next day he had his Audience at <em>Upsall</em>, the University for the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, he was gallantly conducted, and his own Retinue made as gallant a <reg orig="shew">show</reg>, been all very richly <reg orig="apparel'd">apparelled</reg>, which seemed the more glittering, because it being in the evening, the Torches did more reverberate the lustre of the gold and silver upon their <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg>: My Lord Ambassador himself was <reg orig="apparel'd">apparelled</reg> in a black suit very plain, and found the Queen in as <reg orig="plaine">plain</reg> a habit as himself, for she was in a plain <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> stuff gown, and over that a coat of the same made close unto her body, <reg orig="fastned">fastened</reg> with great Buttons, it reached not lower <reg orig="then">than</reg> her knees, much like unto that garment which every day we see our Women ordinarily to wear, who follow their affairs abroad in the Markets; she had on her head a black hood, and on her neck a black <reg orig="scarfe">scarf</reg>, which was tied by a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> black <reg orig="Ribbond">Ribbon</reg>.</p>

<p>Having read this Letter, my <reg orig="Neighbours">Neighbour's</reg> Wives who carry Herbs, and flowers to the Market, did perk it up, and did look very high upon one another, gratulating their fortune, that without any contrivement of pride, they were all of the same fashion with the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. But when will they be like her in understanding, which indeed is above the capacity of her Sex, and though illustrious personages are for the most part attended with illustrious gifts, yet for the present our most deliberate reflections cannot find a Queen that is like unto her. A rare thing it was to see a young Lady of not above three and twenty years of age, in the simplicity of her habit, to overcome her sex, and in the excellence of <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg>, and discourse, to amaze the gravest understandings, and to conquer as well by language, and by her countenance, as her Father did by arms.</p>

<p>The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> finding that our Ambassador was not to be daunted either by countenance, or <reg orig="jestures">gestures</reg>, did by voice pronounce, that both himself, and his business was most acceptable to him, that her desire was to continue the old union, and enter into a <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg>. She thanked our Ambassador<pb n="4" /> for his acceptance of such entertainment in his tedious travels by Land, as that place would afford, she excused her habit by the indisposition of her body, and did commend it, that it inferred her love to our <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, for she chose rather <unclear><!--approximately 4 characters--></unclear> <reg orig="publiquely">publicly</reg> to be seen, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to disappoint the Ambassador of Audience.</p>

<p>On that day which in our English Calendar, is dedicated to the memory of the first Martyr Saint <em><reg orig="Stephens">Stephen's</reg></em>, our Ambassador had private audience for above two hours, and on the <em>Thursday</em> following he was admitted again to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> presence, with whom he was alone three <reg orig="houres">hours</reg> together. It is believed our Ambassador will have a dispatch very suddenly, to the high contentment of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. He hath been invited by the <em>Spanish</em>, and <em>French</em> Agents, and by the Ambassador of <em>Denmark</em>, as also by the Marshal of <em>Sweden</em>, and divers others of the Counsel of the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>. I might here <reg orig="tel">tell</reg> you what was the gallantry of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Guard, and how rich in their several degrees were the Retinue of our Ambassador, and how many Torches there were to conduct him the first night to the Court, but I leave it to those who to <reg orig="fil">fill</reg> up two sheets, do give you rather words, <reg orig="then">than</reg> Intelligence.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 2</head>

<p>The News from <em>Scotland</em> which this week is most remarkable is, that the Governor of Saint <em><reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg></em> understanding that the <em>Highlanders</em> were come down the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, commanded forth one hundred Horse, and one hundred Dragoons, who came to the Town where they Quartered, and unexpectedly falling on them, they <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> the Town, having killed the Scouts, and those who made resistance at the <reg orig="Baricodo">Barricade</reg>; seven of the <em>Highlanders</em> were killed, but the Town being <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg>, the Enemy fled out at the further end of it, which our Scouts suspecting were there ready with a party of Horse to receive them, but they made through them, as well as they could, being a great part of them beaten off from their Horse, and fled into the next Woods, and Fens for their protections. These were all <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> men, and did belong unto the<pb n="5" /> <em><reg orig="Blayr">Blair</reg></em>, our men took fifty Horses, and seven Prisoners, they took also many carbines, coats and cloaks (such as they were) and pistols; it is said that the Earl of <em>Athol</em> was there himself, in his own person, and as some Letters affirm, did <reg orig="harldly">hardly</reg> escape the danger; our Horse pursued them two miles beyond the Town, but the Woods, and Mountains being so <reg orig="neer">near</reg> they could not accomplish their victory so perfectly, as otherwise they would have done, if they had met their Enemies in the champion. Howsoever, it is a reasonable mercy, for the <em>Highlanders</em> began to vaunt much, concerning what they had done at <em>Drummond</em>, and <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> men which were defeated, were accounted the ablest men for courage, and the best armed of the <em>Highlanders</em>.</p>

<p>There is little News this week from <em>France</em>, the King is much taken with riding the great Horse, and the rather, because he is so much applauded by the Spectators, who say he rides as if the Horse and man were both of one piece, they compare him to <em>Chiron</em>, and <em>Erictheus</em>, or if there were any more famous <reg orig="then">than</reg> they. From the acclamations in the Court of the little <em>Burbon</em>, builded by his Grandfather, he hath removed himself to Saint <em><reg orig="Germans">Germain</reg></em>, to divert himself a little from the noise of the Court, with the recreation of hunting, and the chasing of the wild Boar; he shot one himself from a <em>Blanch</em> with a cross-bow; the Boar finding himself wounded, made towards the stand in a foaming fury, but he was <reg orig="encountred">encountered</reg> in the way by the young Lord of <em>Montmorency</em>, and some others, who with <reg orig="sphears">spears</reg> in their hands, gave a speedy and <reg orig="ful">full</reg> vent to the remainder of his discontented life, which in <reg orig="severall">several</reg> wounds came <reg orig="powring">pouring</reg> forth with his Blood.</p>

<p>Some of Major General <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Regiment in <em>Scotland</em>, amongst which are the Quartermaster, and the Chaplain of the Regiment, refusing to subscribe to the present Government, are returned from the service of the War, some of them to <em>Wales</em>, and some to <em>England</em>.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Feb: 3</head>

<p>The last Post from the North doth advertise us, that the Quakers not far from <em>Newcastle</em> attempting to interrupt the Minister in his Sunday Sermon, the Parishioners <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> upon them, and almost killed two of them, but the Quakers never owning their Name more seriously <reg orig="then">than</reg> at this present, trembling down upon their knees, some of the Parishioners were struck with such a Remorse, that they did begin to accuse one another for beating those who had done them no harm. Sermon being ended, the Minister being desired to discourse with the Quakers, some other of the Parish opposed, and said that they deserved rather a Beadle to correct them, hereupon the People being divided, they fell from words to blows, and did so soundly beat one another, that the scene being altered, those who did quake before, did now shake with laughter, there were but two of them hurt, but of the whole Parish, there was scarce anyone came home without his head, or his face broken.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Febr: 4.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised, that our Fleet is put forth to Sea, General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> set forth first with about fifty stout Men of War, he was seconded by General <em>Blake</em>, with twenty gallant ships, the whole Fleet met not far from <em>Portland</em>, where about this time twelve <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> was that dreadful Fight betwixt the <em>English</em>, and the <em>Dutch</em>. It was there ordered that our fleet should be divided into three Squadrons, the better to secure the Channel, and to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> the Seas; It is likely enough that they may meet with the <em>Dutch</em> Merchants, who bound for <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, and the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em> are numerous, and not adventuring through the Channel, have thought it their safer course to steer round about on the backside of <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Hume</em> with sixteen more well mounted, is gone out of <em>Berwickshire</em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the <em>Highlanders</em>. The Earl of <em><reg orig="Atholl">Athol</reg></em> since his Defeat at <em>Dunkel</em>, hath endeavoured to raise the Countries, but hath yet but a very slender appearance.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Febr. 6.</head>

<p>Those who were slain, and taken in the Defeat, given to the <em>Scots</em> were.</p>

<p>The Laird <em>Ballichan</em> Major <em>Mercer</em> wounded.</p>
<p>Captain <em>Hunter</em> Captain <em>Sibbel</em> taken.</p> 
<p>Captain <em>Robertson</em> Cornet <em>Graham</em> taken.</p>
<p>Captain <em>Mackland</em> Six more taken, and seven killed.</p>

<p>On our side there were two killed, and some wounded. Col: <em>Morgan</em> hath made a hard march into the <em>Highlands</em>, to find out the Enemy in this Winter season, but they fly back as he advanceth, the Winter will not yet permit to prosecute what was intended, and the Country <reg orig="yeelds">yields</reg> no provision but what we carry with us; several <reg orig="straglers">stragglers</reg> have been taken.</p>

<p>It is confirmed from <em>Holland</em> that the <em>Dutch</em> Merchants about 200 in number, young <em>Van Trump</em> with eight men of War, being their conduct, are sailed Southwards, it is possible that our fleet may meet with them.</p>

<p>The titular King of <em>Scots</em> had like to have been stabbed with a poynado by one (as it is said) of his own Court, but it pleased God that the Male content was amazed, and disappointed. We have no more News from <em>Sweden</em>, only that our affairs there do move very fairly. Great are the preparations to entertain his Highness in <em>London</em> on <em>Wednesday</em> next.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>Two hundred Dutch Merchants gone off to <em>Spain</em>, <em>Lisbon</em>, and the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, under the Conduct of young Van Trump. And the <em>English</em> Fleet consisting of about 80 gallant Men of War, set forth to Sea, and divided into three Squadrons, under the command of Gen: <em>Blake</em>, Gen: <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> and Gen: <em>Lawson</em>. A great Defeat given to the <em>Scots</em>, and a List of the Officers, and others taken, and killed. The titular King of the <em>Scots</em> in great danger to have been stabbed with a poynado. The acts and achievements of his Highness greatly extolled by the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. The <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight on Sunday was sevennight in the Church-yard of <em>Hasington</em>, where hardly one of the whole Parish escaped without a broken pate, or a bleeding Nose, occasioned by the Quakers. And the great preparations in the City of <em>London</em> to entertain his Highness on Wednesday next.</i></p>


<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>