<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell331">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 331</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, May 9. to <em>Tuesday</em>, May 16. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 9.</head>

<p>The Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> having made an Alliance with the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, did impute much therein, to the brave deportment of the Lord Ambassador, who, <i>she said, did deal roundly, and freely with her, and not like a Merchant</i>; she also gave many demonstrations of honour to the Lord Protector, to whose courage and <reg orig="wisedom">wisdom</reg> he is said to manifest her affection.</p>

<p>Much about the same time the Emperor of <em>Muscovia</em>, who, if you will believe the Letters, hath been pleased to make Wars against the <em>Polander</em> for the oversight of a Poet, the Letter thus. 2 reasons he mentioned; one because a certain <em>Poland</em> Poet writing a Narration of former Wars, when the <em>Pole</em> had the better, said, they had beaten the <em>Muscovite</em>, without adding his Title, <em>plain Muscovite</em>. The other, because in quoting something touching the Genealogy of the <em><reg orig="Muscovites">Muscovite's</reg></em> Ancestors, he named one as Father, which was the Son; and for these two grand offences, he demanded of the <em>Pole</em> the <reg orig="offenders">offender's</reg> head, which being denied, he makes War upon<pb n="1" /> them, and hath taken one City, and besieged one of the most considerable in <em>Poland</em>. These were the contents of his Letters. In his long title he hath of late called himself <em>Dominus parentum &amp; avorum fuorum</em>. The Queen being forced to answer <reg orig="somthing">something</reg>, because he asked her advice, returned, that she neither approved, nor disapproved his reasons, but thanking him for his civil communication, wished that he might receive good satisfaction from the <em>Pole</em>, being troubled that Christian Princes should disagree.</p>

<p>I shall in this place give you the advertisement concerning Farthing Tokens, there being some stamped of several sorts, and every one presuming that their own will be allowed to pass.</p>

<p>Therefore whereas several Persons have presented unto his Council divers patterns for the making of a common Farthing for the use of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; and have attended several times about the same, and at this Day the <reg orig="busines">business</reg> is depending before his Honourable Council. And yet notwithstanding in the mean time several persons have presumed without any Authority, or Declaration of the State, to set the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> Arms on pewter of the weight of about a quarter of an ounce, and have procured intimation in print to be made, that these pewter Farthings are allowed to pass <reg orig="currant">current</reg> through the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, &amp;c.</em> and in pursuance thereof, have, and do daily vent these unauthorized pewter Farthings in <em>London</em>, and other parts of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, to the great deceit and <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> of this Nation.</p>

<p>These are to give notice to all men, that if there be not a sudden stop of the making, and venting of those pewter Farthings, the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> will be greatly deceived, both by mixing the pewter with Lead, and also every Tinker, and other lewd persons will get <reg orig="molds">moulds</reg>, and make the said pewter Farthings in every corner. Therefore all people ought to take notice that no Farthings are to pass but such only as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be Authorized by his Highness, and his Council to pass through the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>.</p><pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 10.</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector did this Day sit with his Council upon some business of weighty importance. The Deputy from the King of <em>Denmark</em> had Audience this week, who with accustomed joy did congratulate the Peace established by his Highness.</p>

<p>The Commissioners have treated also with the Ambassador of <em>France</em>, and all things move fairly for the present for an accommodation with that Nation. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is at this present at <em>Chantilly</em>, which is a house heretofore belonging to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, but it is conceived he will not stay long there, nor in the Kingdom of <em>France</em>, as you will find by the <reg orig="Sequell">Sequel</reg>. He was invited by the young King of <em>France</em> to act a part in the great Mask, but by reason of the many difficulties that oppressed him, he was pleased to excuse himself.</p>

<p>This Day a Declaration is set forth by his Highness the Lord <em>Protector</em> for a Day of Thanksgiving for the Peace with <em>Holland</em>, and for the late seasonable Rain, it here follows.</p>

<p>That this hath been a Nation of blessings, in the midst whereof so many wonders have been brought forth by the <reg orig="out-stretched">outstretched</reg> arm of the Almighty, even to astonishment and wonder, Who can deny? Ask we the Nations of this matter, and they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="testifie">testify</reg>, and indeed the dispensations of the Lord have been as if he had said, <em>England</em> thou art my <reg orig="first-born">firstborn</reg>, my delight amongst the Nations, under the whole Heavens the Lord hath not dealt so with any of the people round about us.</p>

<p>The Lord having added another link to this golden Chain of his loving <reg orig="kindnes">kindness</reg>, by giving us a Peace with our Neighbours the <em>United Provinces</em>, (whereby he hath not only stopped a great issue of blood, but We trust also given us hearts to unite Our blood and strength for the mutual defence of each other) <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> for great return of Thanks for the same.</p>

<p>It is therefore thought fit to set apart <em>Tuesday</em>, being the 23 of this present <em>May</em>, as a day for Praise, &amp; for the thankful Acknowledgment of this blessing of Peace, which we hope<pb n="3" /> hath in the womb of it many other blessings.</p>

<p>And let us not forget our other Mercies, was not the Earth lately so unusually <reg orig="parcht">parched</reg> up, that it <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> <reg orig="Famin">Famine</reg>, and did cause the Beast of the field to mourn for want of food, and water to sustain it? And hath not the Lord so watered the Earth that he hath turned those fears into the expectation of the greatest plenty that ever was seen by any now living in this Nation? Consider we also the way whereby the Lord impaired this mercy to us, did any amongst us foreknow it was coming, was it not stirring up our hearts to seek the same by prayer, and that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> before the Lord vouchsafed us this mercy, <em>&amp;c</em>?</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 11.</head>

<p>It was confirmed, that General <em>Monk</em> was marching to <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, and from thence to the <em>Highlands</em> Gen: <em>Middleton</em> hearing of it, hath sent a Messenger to those that keep the Passes to double their Guards. The same Messenger he hath also sent to the Islands in the West, and doth use all his endeavours to reconcile the discontented Grandees in his Army. He hath so <reg orig="wel">well</reg> ordered his Camp, that though amongst the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> and those inhospitable places, it is a wonder to see which way their provision should come in such measure to him.</p>

<p>It is certified from <em>Venice</em>, that the <em>Turks</em> have received a great loss in the <em>Isle of <unclear>Crest</unclear></em>, five hundred of them have been destroyed at one time, and three hundred at another, when the great loss was received by the <em>Turks</em>, they lost themselves in that <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> eighteen hundred of their best men. In the mean time the Emperor to help the <em>Venetians</em> what he can, hath given order to all those who are in power under him, not only for Volunteers, but to stand upon the Guards, and be ready upon all attempts in <em>Hungary</em>.</p>

<p>There have been lately a great Tumult in Saint <em>Mallows</em>, the <em>French</em> having some ships taken by the <em>English</em>, did barbarously assault them there, &amp; at <em>Morleaix</em>, they seized upon their <reg orig="Ware-houses">Warehouses</reg>, <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> their Goods, and wounded<pb n="4" /> some of their men, the <em>French</em> King hearing of it, sent Orders that the <em>English</em> should be protected.</p>

<p>Major <em>Skut</em>, and some other of the Town of <em>Pool</em> presented a paper to the Council, which should have been inserted in this place, but room is wanting.</p>

<p>They write from <em><reg orig="Duncaster">Doncaster</reg></em>, that a Regiment of about 12 hundred stout men are marched that way towards <em>Scotland</em>, they say they belong to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Okey</em>.</p>

<p>This Post brought Letters of great stirrings, and preparations in <em>Scotland</em> on both sides <em>Middleton</em>, and the rest of that Crew do all they can to increase their numbers, and the Gen: <em>Monk</em> is as active in drawing together his Forces towards the Mountains, and by keeping them there (<reg orig="til">till</reg> they have spent their provisions) they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> afterwards be forced to fight, or lay down their Arms; In the mean while they keep their old trade of stealing down by parties, and doing what mischief they can, and some Country People run away with them to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and some Towns are so base unto us, that they have made stay of English Passengers that were but travelling through them. A party of ours met with about 30 Countrymen in a knot, going to the Enemy; After that they met with a party of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> horse, with whom they had a great fight, killed six, and took fifteen Prisoners; the like was also done by another party; The Enemy stands not long to it, except he be in a place of great advantage.</p>

<p>The <em>English</em> Fleet are now at a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Downs</em>, both <em>France</em> and <em>Spain</em> are very jealous what will be the ensuing design, and strong Guards are kept upon the Frontiers of both Kingdoms.</p>

<p>Whereas the Report is frequent that Count <em>William</em> of <em>Nassau</em> having called the Army together, they all declared to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with him, and they have since seized upon <em>Horn</em>, and <em>Enchuysen</em>, and some other considerable Towns in <em>Holland</em>, and are now sat down before <em>Amsterdam</em>, I do find after much inquiry, that there are no Letters to confirm it, and therefore do leave it a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> report as I found it, raised by some <reg orig="Malecontents">Malcontents</reg>, to set their tongues on working.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>I made mention before of the great complaints of the Merchants of Saint <em>Mallows</em>, by reason of some ships taken by the English, they have Petitioned to the King that Letters of Mart may be granted them to set out Men of War to have thereby what satisfaction they can find for their great losses.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, May 12.</head>

<p>The Post from <em>Scotland</em> brought this Day advertisement in several Letters that General <em>Middleton</em> hath sent Major Gen: <em>Drummond</em> amongst the <em>Loughabers</em>, to raise all the Forces they can, and that <em>Glencarn</em> with about one hundred Horse is gone into <em>Athol</em> to expedite the <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> there. Their design is, (as they give forth) to surround <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Morgan, but that it is very improbable, for Gen: <em>Monk</em> with considerable Forces is advanced to his Relief. The young Lord of <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em>, who is said much to resemble the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> in complexion, stature, and image, is raising <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> at <em>Branar</em>, and to strengthen him in his design, some parties are come to him from <em>Middleton</em>. It is said that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is suddenly expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> <reg orig="withe">with he</reg> <em>Highlanders</em>.</p>

<p>It is certain that the <em>Highlanders</em> have received provision from <em>Dunkirk</em>; two ships are arrived laden with Arms, Men, and Ammunition; this will further be examined.</p>

<p>Great was the Joy at <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> at the arrival of General <em>Monk</em>, where his Highness was Proclaimed <em>Lord Protector</em> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>. The next day the Ministers in the same City prayed openly in their Pulpits for the titular King of the <em>Scots</em>.</p><pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 13.</head>

<p>By Letters from the West of <em>England</em> it is advertised, that the <em>Indians</em> in <em>Virginia</em> had assembled themselves into a great number, and had an intent to fall upon the <em>English</em>, who being forewarned of it by one of their Enemies, whose humanity made him forget that he was a salvage, care will be taken to prevent their <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> design.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg> of <em>Brest</em> are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, not only on the Southern, and Western Seas, but some of them have adventured as far as the <em>Isle of Man</em>, and so upwards towards the <em>Scottish</em> Seas, they took not far from <em>Liverpool</em> three Vessels that were coming from the North. The <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg> also of <em>Ostend</em> do much infest our Coasts, amongst the rest, a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> hath done our Fishermen more mischief <reg orig="then">than</reg> all the others. A <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessel <reg orig="wel">well</reg> laden with <em>English</em>, and <em>French</em> Passengers, who were resolute men, were <reg orig="incountred">encountered</reg> by her, fought so gallantly, that in a short Dispute the <em>Ostend</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> lost seven men, and some wounded, but at last an unfortunate shot took place of the <em>English</em> Vessel, so that <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> she sunk, but the men were preserved.</p>

<p>A <em>Brest</em> Man of War commanded by Captain <em>Mildrom</em> took lately a Vessel belonging to <em>Tinmouth</em>, there were some English in this ship, who not long before being taken by our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, and released, did go to <em>Brest</em> again, these men having taken (as I have said) the Vessel belonging to <em>Tinmouth</em>, dismissed her again, and advised her to shift into <em>Scilly</em> with all the speed they could, for there were four or five <em>Brest</em> Men of War more coming down the North Channel, who would not deal so friendly with them, as they had done.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 15.</head>

<p>This morning we received the welcome News of 300. sail of Coals which are come into the River from <em>Newcastle</em>, but the wind which hath blown this fortnight from the East, and Northeast, hath not been altogether so favourable to some ships of ours bound for the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>It is certain that the last week a Woman in this City coming casually into a room where she found her Husband kissing another Woman, she <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> departed to her own house, and for all the declarations, and protestations of her Husband, she refused to be comforted, having her heart so much contracted with the <reg orig="suddennes">suddenness</reg> of that most ungrateful sight, that the next day she <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> for grief.</p>

<p>The Letters from <em>Scotland</em> do advertise, that Gen: <em>Monk</em> was lately in <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, and is now on his advance towards the <em>Highlanders</em>, to whom divers <reg orig="Renegadoes">Renegades</reg> do <reg orig="stil">still</reg> resort. Their access of new provision for the War doth much <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> them, so that their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> of late do much increase. <em>Middleton</em> knowing what an Enemy he hath to deal with, doth manage the War with great dexterity. Some Letters do represent, that he will fight with <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> before the access of more Forces are added to him. There was lately a great dispute at the maintaining of a Pass, in which Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> was Routed, and divers killed, and taken. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> hath sent a Letter to <em>Middleton</em>, in which he exhorteth and conjureth the Commanders to an union in this time of their greatest necessity.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>The great Fight at a Pass in <em>Scotland</em>, Sir <em>Arthur Forbes'</em> party <reg orig="wholy">wholly</reg> routed, and divers taken, and slain. The barbarous, and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Plot of the <em>Indians</em> to Massacre the <em>English</em> in <em>Virgina</em>. The Report of Count <em>William</em> of <em>Nassau</em> taking Arms in <em>Holland</em>, the Declaration of the Soldiers to live, and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with him, and their seizing on <em>Enchuysen</em>, <em>Horn</em>, and other places. The Letter of the titular King of <em>Scots</em> to Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, encouraging the Commanders to Union: Three hundred sail of Coals arrived. And the true Relation of a Woman, who the last week <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> for <reg orig="greef">grief</reg>, seeing her Husband to kiss another Woman.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>