<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell149#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 149#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 10. to <em>Tuesday</em>, January 17. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January: 10.</head>

<p>I made mention in my last of the Great Fire at <em>Amsterdam</em>, wherein I gave you as full an account as possibly could then be learned. It is since reported, that within the City of <em>Amsterdam</em> <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, the Iron Cross that stood upon the Western Church, which being twenty foot long, did weigh above fourteen hundred pound, was blown down by the violent storms, and the weather-cock above it, and the great copper <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> <reg orig="Boal">Bowl</reg> under it, which was said to hold <reg orig="neer">near</reg> a Hogshead of Beer. There was nothing left standing but the Imperial Crown on top of the Steeple. All the said weight fell down through the body of the Church, and breaking down some Monuments, <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters--></unclear> the <unclear>house</unclear>, and the bodies of the Dead, and <reg orig="dissiapted">dissipated</reg> their Dusts, that nothing but the Resurrection can put them in order again.</p>

<p>I shall in this place give you the Declaration by the Commander in chief of the Forces in <em>Scotland</em>, it followeth in these words.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>Forasmuch as it is apparent. That (notwithstanding my Proclamation of <em>Septemb</em>: last) many serviceable Horses daily go to the Enemy, to the great disservice of the Peace of this Nation, which could not be without too much connivance of the Owners or Possessors: These are therefore strictly to require all manner of persons who now are, or hereafter shall be possessed of any serviceable Horses, or Mares, exceeding the value of <em>5 l. sterling</em>, to bring in the same within 48 hours, next after publication hereof, unto the next adjacent Garrison, or Quarters of our Army, under the penalty not only of forfeiting treble the value of such Horses and Mares as shall not be brought in; the one <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> thereof to the use of the State, and the other <reg orig="moyety">moiety</reg> to the party informing, but also deemed as an open Enemy, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> accordingly: Which Horses and Mares so brought in, shall <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> be at the <reg orig="Owners">Owner's</reg> choice either to have meet satisfaction for them, as they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be reasonably worth, or keep them within the said Garrisons, or Quarters of our Army; And the respective Sheriffs and their Deputies, within their Sheriffdoms, and hereby required, to cause these presents solemnly to be proclaimed and published according to accustomed manner of publishing Proclamations. And afterwards (that none may pretend ignorance) to cause to be distributed to the several Presbyteries within their said Sheriffdoms a competent number hereof.</p>

<p><i>Given under my hand and Seal at</i></p>
<p><i>Dalkeith 14 Decemb: 1653. <em>R. LILBURNE.</em></i></p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, June 11</head>

<p>The gallant service performed by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, not long after that he had landed the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> at <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, being well worthy the observation, I shall give it you in this place, and almost in his own words.</p>

<p>On the 20 of <em>December</em> he came out with his ship, when the wind blew hard, with much snow, endeavouring the <em>Yutish</em> coast, anchored in ten fathom water, &amp; discovered a Fleet of ships, and 21 <em>Decemb</em>: in the morning, got the weather-gage of them, endeavoured to discover what Men of War were amongst <pb n="2" />them, and saw only one ship of countenance, and a private Man of War of eight Guns. The Fleet being <em>Hollanders</em> ran from the <em>Sound</em>, and 72 sail, some with six, some four, others two guns, upon our guns firing amongst them, cut their Cables, and run towards the <em>Sound</em>, but before they got clear, we boarded and manned three of them, which Prizes were kept to the Windward of us, about eight a clock engaged them.</p>

<p>After the passing of two broad sides, the private Man of War ran after their Fleet, we continued the dispute <reg orig="untill">until</reg> 4 a clock at night, (at which time we past broad sides close board and board, as fast as we could tack our ships) The Enemy then ran towards his Fleet, we pursued him, and after several broad sides intended to board him; and though our <unclear>Bolesprit</unclear> shot by the board, our Main and Fore-mast shot through, scarce a Shroud whole, our Hull much shot, four of our men slain, and eleven wounded; he firing as he retreated, yet we made him in such a sinking condition that whilst he fired his Guns, he called to his Fleet to save his Men, about four leagues off at anchor under an Island.</p>

<p>Above 400. horse and foot were looking on us from the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, we received shot from Enemy of <em>36 l.</em> weight. But night <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> our pursuit.</p>

<p>About three in the afternoon next day three <em>Holland</em> Men of War, (two of them very great ships) being come from <em>Holland</em> to convoy their Fleet, came right before the wind upon us, we then bore to our Prizes, took all our men out of them, and would have fired them had we had time. The Enemy came up close, and fired at us, and we at them (unanimously resolving to sink or burn, rather that to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> or call for Quarter) the two first shot they made (that raked us) the one shot the chain of our Fore-yard in <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, and the other, two thirds of our main Top mast-head above the bearing; they then would have boarded us, but we got without shot of them, who seeing we <reg orig="outstript">outstripped</reg> them, after an hours time bore to the Prizes, who were by this time <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>, our men having cut away all their Anchors, leaving them in the bottom of the Bay.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>The 22 a <em>Holland</em> Man of War stood <reg orig="crosse">cross</reg> our forefoot close to the windward of us, standing over to the coast of <em>Norway</em>, and the wind being fair for <em>England</em>, we bore away to Sea.</p>

<p>The 25 we came up with our own ships from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, having seen them two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before, but knew them not to be our ships, stood not with them till our ship was refitted the best we could, and then they sent to us. But on the 27 about eight in the night, by reason of a violent storm, we lost sight of them.</p>

<p>The <em>Swedes</em> of <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> report that the King of <em>Denmark</em> is much troubled that they affronted our Nation by their ships being staid and blames evil counsel for it. <em>De Wit</em> (when last in the <em>Sound</em>) endeavoured to comfort him with a cordial of their great Victories obtained against us at Sea, giving him a List of 22 sail of our ships sunk, and 8 taken, boasting much of their putting us <reg orig="stil">still</reg> to flight. But that <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> own Subjects are now able to inform him that the <em>Hollanders</em>, and not we, are <reg orig="stil">still</reg> the flying party, and that one day, one small <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, fought with, and routed their Fleet, and Men of War, and the next day made her way (the Lord helping us) through three of their ships coming to avenge their quarrel, the least of which (as to countenance) exceeded the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Jan: 12.</head>

<p>The Letters I have seen from <em>Scotland</em> differ something from those in print, for they make mention that the <em>Highlanders</em> are not altogether so barbarously <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> towards those they have taken. The greatest part of them had rather take ransoms, <reg orig="then">than</reg> take away lives, and yet this is not so much out of mercy, as necessity, their miserable condition <reg orig="perswading">persuading</reg> them to use all arts to preserve themselves.</p>

<p>It is certain that in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> they do miserably oppress their own Countrymen, that they now extol and commend the protection of the English, which before they murmured at, and his Intelligence being more quick <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary did not a little conduce to <unclear><!-- 3 characters approx --></unclear> captivity of the Lord <em>Kinnowle</em>, and the routing of his seventy Horse. On Friday December the 30, the Earl of <em>Kinnowle</em> about eight of the clock appeared <pb n="4" />with a party of Horse consisting of threescore and ten, the design was to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the English Horse as they came from watering, to this purpose he betook himself to a place of coverture, and took three of our Men, and did assure himself of the rest, but notice being given of it, the <reg orig="Bridg">Bridge</reg> was made good with two files of <reg orig="Musketeirs">Musketeers</reg>, which <em><reg orig="Kinnowles">Kinnowle's</reg></em> horse observing, they cursed the treachery of their own Countrymen, and riding up unto them, they resolved to fight with the English, before they should grow stronger by the access of new Forces, but the foot gave them so warm a charge that they routed and dispersed this Body of their Horse. Much at the same time a party of our Horse appeared, who did increase the disorderly retreat of the Enemy; The Lord <em>Kinnowle</em> was taken himself, who <reg orig="cryed">cried</reg> out much against those who trusting more to their speed <reg orig="then">than</reg> strength, did <reg orig="dishonorably">dishonourably</reg> (as he said) desert him: Amongst these was Major <em>Ramsey</em>, and some others of Quality, there were three killed of the <em>Scots</em>, and some 18 taken Prisoners.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Germany</em>, that three hundred thousand Crowns ordered for the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> by the <em>German</em> Princes, are by the <em><reg orig="Ellectoral">Electoral</reg> <reg orig="Colledg">College</reg></em> concluded to be given unto him. It is also Enacted that no Libels, or <reg orig="Pamplets">Pamphlets</reg> whatsoever, written in the <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> of the said King, shall be suffered to be sold in any part of <em>Germany</em>, upon pain of Death.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Sweden</em>, that the English People have the more trouble there, and find the <reg orig="lesse">less</reg> favour, because the Admiral of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> is a <em>Hollander</em> by his Nation.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em><reg orig="Cambridg">Cambridge</reg></em>, that two Petticoat Preachers came lately to <em>Sidney <reg orig="Colledg">College</reg></em>, and would needs enter into dispute with divers of the Collegians, who civilly, and Scholastically answered all the Positions, but those weak Vessels being not able to resist such able oppositors, used very uncivil language, telling the <reg orig="Schollars">Scholars</reg> they were Antichrists, and their <reg orig="Colledg">College</reg> a cage of unclean Birds, with divers other invective speeches, &amp;c. Hereupon the Students made a complaint to the Mayor, who sent for them to appear before him, <pb n="5" />and demanded whence they came, and where they lay the last night, they said they were strangers, and knew not the name of the place, but they <reg orig="payed">paid</reg> for what they called. Afterwards he asked them their names, but they made answer that they were written in the <em>Book of Life</em>: The Mayor desiring by what Names their Husbands were called, they answered, they had no Husband but <em>Jesus Christ</em>. The Mayor seeing them so obstinate, that they not only slighted the Clergy, but likewise all Civil Government, did cause them to be smartly lashed for their obstinacy, and afterwards to be turned forth of the Town.</p>

<p>Letters are received from <em>Portugal</em>, informing, that the <em>Spaniards</em> have driven from the <reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg> 1200. head of <reg orig="Cattel">Cattle</reg>, the <reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg> who were in gallant body of about one thousand Horse, fell upon the <em>Spaniards</em> who were 1500, and maintained the charge with so much resolution, that they utterly routed the <em>Spaniards</em>, and followed the pursuit so close, that many gallant Commanders <reg orig="fel">fell</reg> of the <em>Spanish</em> party, 300 <em>Spaniards</em> were killed on the place, and 400 taken Prisoners, and about 300 Horse: It is said that on the <reg orig="Portugals">Portuguese</reg> side, there was no Officer slain but one Major only.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Jan: 13.</head> 

<p>It is mentioned in some extraordinaries from beyond the Seas, that the great Tomb of <em>Mahomet</em> is fallen down at <em><reg orig="Mecha">Mecca</reg></em>, from the roof of his Temple; the Iron chest which <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> his Body, and hung in the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, was so <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> covered in rust that the loadstones could no longer exercise their <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>, and uphold the miracle betwixt Heaven, and Earth; the earth immediately opened up to receive it, but not without a dismal fire and <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg>, which continued for the space of <pb n="6" />half an hour, as horrid to the eye, as it was odious to the <reg orig="smel">smell</reg>.</p>

<p>One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> in the West met with a <em>Dutch <reg orig="Pickaroon">Picaroon</reg></em>, and pursued her so close, that she forced him to run on ground. The <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> did still shoot hard at him, insomuch that the Country coming down, being <reg orig="alarum'd">alarmed</reg> with the noise of the great Guns, to behold the fight, there were four of them killed, and wounded in the <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg>.</p>

<p>There is nothing this week of any action from <em>Scotland</em>. Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> Regiment of Foot, Major Gen: <em>Lamberts</em> Regiment of Horse, Commissary General <em><reg orig="Whaleys">Whaley's</reg></em> Regiment of Horse are gone towards <em>Scotland</em>, to suppress the motions of the <em>Highlanders</em>, and add new strength to our Forces there already, who (wheresoever they meet with the <em>Highlanders</em>, are <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> too hard for them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Jan: 14.</head>

<p>General <em>Blake</em> and Gen: <em>Monk</em> are now at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>. Gen: <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> in his <em>Swiftsure</em>, doth ride as Admiral of the Fleet. The Fleet is at the <em>Spice head</em> not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>. Some part of them are sent out to ply between <em>Portland</em>, and the <reg orig="Lands">Land's</reg> end, and over upon the coast of <em>France</em>, to suppress the <em>French</em> <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, and those of <em>Holland</em> who are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to them.</p>

<p>Three thousand <em>Irish</em>, under the command of the <em>Spaniard</em>, are brought up towards <em>Galizia</em>, who being <reg orig="al">all</reg> old Soldiers, do <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> trouble the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em>, fearing they may put a stop to the progress of their successes. The <em>Irish</em> in <em>France</em> boast that these in <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> will take an opportunity to come unto them, they do boast also, but no man <reg orig="beleeves">believes</reg> them, of a great Victory which lately they have got in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>The Diet is not yet concluded in <em>Germany</em>, there being new differences between the Prince Elector, and his Uncle, about the enjoying of some Lands, which each other pretend to be theirs.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Jan: 16.</head>

<p>The <em>Dutch</em> to their late grief, have wisely added one day of solemn sorrow, and this (on the beginning of the last week) was observed in a <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Humiliation to <reg orig="pacifie">pacify</reg>, or divert the anger of the Almighty. Their preparations at Sea are great; nothing is yet done as to the Answer which their Deputies brought from <em>England</em>, and nothing can be done <reg orig="til">till</reg> there be a general meeting of all their States, but it appears that their inclinations are for War.</p>

<p>But nothing doth more startle them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the celerity, industry and the resolution of the <em>English</em>. We have fifty lusty ships which have already met in one Rendezvous, the <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> will speedily be ready at <em>Portsmouth</em>. The <em>Rainbow</em> is going from <em>Chattam</em>. The <em><reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg></em> is already set forth from thence, she was seen yesterday morning beyond the <em>Castle</em>. Four lusty ships more are going from <em>Chattam</em>. And there are ten ships more at the <em>Hope</em> <!--??--><reg orig="complest">complex</reg> under sail, amongst which are the <em><reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg></em>, and the <em>George</em>. The <em>Resolution</em> which hath carried herself so stoutly during the all these Wars with <em>Holland</em>, is now to be equipped at <em>Chattam</em>. We shall have speedily abroad one hundred gallant ships, not only enough to daunt the <em>Hollander</em>, but peradventure the World.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable is:</head>

<p><i>The meeting of the States General of the United Provinces, in order to the Answer brought by their Deputies from England. The great and furious fight on the <reg orig="Baltick">Baltic</reg> Seas betwixt the <em>English</em> and the <em>Dutch</em>; several of their ships taken and the <unclear>rest</unclear> of their Fleet flying back to the <em>Sound</em>. The <reg orig="abbomination">abomination</reg> at <unclear><!-- approx. 8 characters --></unclear> discovered, <em><reg orig="Mahomets">Mahomet's</reg></em> Iron Tomb that hung is the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg> fallen: the Earth opening to receive it, and the dismal fire, and <reg orig="smoak">smoke</reg> and stench that did attend it. The Edict in <em>Germany</em>, that in <unclear>Books</unclear> shall be suffered to be extant there, in derogation of the titular King of the <em>Scots</em>. The false boasting of the <em>Irish</em> in <em>France</em> of a defeat given to the <em>English</em> in Ireland; and some Prizes taken for certain from the <em>French</em> and from the <em>Dutch</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>