<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell149">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 149</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, January 3. to <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 10. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 6.</head>

<p>It is in vain to <reg orig="conttive">contrive</reg>, or act against the decrees of Heaven. The <em>Dutch</em> in <em>November</em> resolving to be masters of our Channel in the Winter, as we were of their Seas in the Summer, had sixteen of their <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> devoured by the Tempest. If they continue in the like resolutions, for ought we know, may be punished with fire. Nothing being concluded on in the Treaty, this night (having sent away their <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> beforehand) they departed from their Lodgings in <em>Covent Garden</em>, and took Boat for <em>Gravesend</em>, in order to their return to their own Country. If any of them on better consideration, shall come back again, I shall inform you before I have ended this <em>Intelligence</em>.</p> 

<p>The <em>Dutch</em> Deputies had passes to return home.</p>

<p><i>Hague (2 Jan: <unclear>alias</unclear>) - <unclear>23</unclear> Decemb: 1653.</i>. The <em>Dutch</em> <reg orig="Deputies">Deputies'</reg> Letters say, the <em>English</em> press for satisfaction, security, the Dominion of the Seas, the contribution for Fishing, <em>&amp;c</em>. In which they desire further Instructions, which are <unclear>sent</unclear>, and<pb n="1" />30 new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> to be built. Admiral <em>Van Galen</em> was buried in the New Church, from the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> Court. First went the Lord Major in <reg orig="Armor">Armour</reg>, on horse back, his Guards on foot, then divers Officers trailed Pikes, then four Trumpeters with his Arms in Taffety, then his <reg orig="Flagg">Flag</reg> with his Arms, then his Secretary with his Scutcheon, one with his Gantlet, and one with his Helmet, with red and yellow Feathers, then his Spurs, and Sword, and <reg orig="Ponnyard">Poniard</reg>, Coat of Arms of Taffety, and Arms before and behind, then his mourning Horse led by his Lieutenant, and then his <reg orig="Corps">Corpse</reg>, and the <reg orig="Hears">Hearse</reg>-<reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg> carried by 16 Captains, Admiral <em><reg orig="Tromps">Tromp's</reg></em> Son one, after followed others with the Curiants, carrying the Commander Staff, then his Kindred, and after the Lords of the Admiralty, the Burgo-masters, and the 36 of the Council, East-India's Company, Directors of the East, and <reg orig="Medeterranian">Mediterranean</reg> Seas, and after all the <reg orig="Colledg">College</reg>, and the Officers of the Burgers, Mr: <em>Chanut</em> the French Ambassador here is daily treated with. Our Ambassador Mr: <em>Borrell</em> in <em>France</em> hath offered something there. The Lord States General do not sit until after <em>Christmas</em> <reg orig="Holidayes">Holidays</reg>. <em>Witte Wittense</em> is here.</p>

<p>The 23 instant, two <em>English</em> Prizes were brought in, laden with 160 lasts of Salt, the other with Coals. The dead body of the Deputy <em>Vander Par</em> from <em>England</em>, it is arrived at <em>Flushing</em>, to be buried there. The ship of the late Admiral <em>Tromp</em> is gone down the River almost clear, and is to carry 72 Guns, 4 more new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> of 40 and 42 Guns are ready to set sail.</p>

<p>We daily expect 150 ships from the <em>Sound</em>, several Men of War are gone for their Convoy. The Ordinance brought from Sweden have been <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> at Amsterdam, there are 500 hundred pieces, most part half <em>Cartows</em>, Captain Nicholas Pater hath taken an English Ketch before <em>Hull</em>, another at <em>Flamborough</em> Head, a Flute of 12 Guns, and 4 of Wood, of about 130 lasts, with Hemp, Flax, Coal and some <reg orig="Saltpeter">Saltpetre</reg>. Also near <em>Whitebay</em> a Pinnace of six Guns with refined Salt, and one by <em>Hover</em>, laden with Salmon, <reg orig="Sheep skins">Sheepskins</reg>, and Herrings; but the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of Cap: <em>Hans Margaren</em> ship, a Man of War with 18 guns which we hear the English have taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Newcastle</em>, is worth <pb n="2" />almost all these; and we hear of 8 ships taken from the Caribes, with Sugar, Tobacco, and other <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>, with their convoy of thirty Guns. Eight of the <em><reg orig="Newfound-land">Newfoundland</reg></em> Fleet we took, are made Men of War. We have taken a Turkish ship, and another in <em>Smirna</em>. One <em>Goldsbalk</em> hath rowed an English prize of 12 Guns into <em>Brest</em>. An English <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> met with 5 <em>French</em> ships of St. <em>Mallo</em>, took one called the <em>Year of Grace</em>, the <em>three Kings</em> hardly escaped, not yet heard of, the other three are at <em>Calice, Cornelius Joast</em>, with <em>Thymen Theaneste</em>, with the Ammunition are safely arrived from hence in <em>Muscovy</em>. There is likely to be hot War by <em>Russia</em>, and <em>Muscoviah</em> against <em>Poland</em>, and is already proclaimed in <em>Muscovia</em>, and the Deputies are sending to <reg orig="al">all</reg> the Princes in Christendom about it. One Army (and the biggest) is marched from <em>Muscovia</em> towards <em>Smolonsko</em>, and so on in the County; The Emperor will be there in person. A second commanded by Field Marshal <em>Bows, Petrooits, Sermotosts</em>, and <em>Semon, Cock, Janovies, <unclear>Streesnop</unclear></em> go from <em>Blascow</em> in <em>Rusland</em> with 40000 men, among which, 20000 well trained <em>Russians</em>. The third of 30000 from <em>Potien</em>, to the help of the <em>Zaponasse Cossacks</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordnance for continuing the Powers of Commissioners for compounding &amp;c. the Committee for advance of money, and Commissioners of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg>.</i></head> 

<p>Be it ordained by the his Highness the Lord Protector by and with the consent of his Council, That an Act of Parliament <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act <reg orig="impouring">empowering</reg> several Commissioners to put in all execution and every the Powers and Authorities heretofore give to the Commissioners for compounding with Delinquents, and for managing all Estates under Sequestration; And to the Committee for advance of money formerly sitting at <reg orig="Haberdashers">Haberdasher's</reg> Hall</i> be, and <em>is</em>, hereby continued, and shall stand, be, and continue in force until the first day of Feb: 1653. And that <em>Samuel Moyer, Josias Berns, Richard Moor, John Upton, Edward Cary, and Rice Williams</em> Esqs; or any four of them be hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> and <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to put in execution the said Act, and all and every <pb n="3" />the Powers and Authorities in and by the said Act given, and every Clause, Article, and thing therein contained. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, that an Act of Parliament <reg orig="entutuled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for transferring the Powers of the Commissioners of <reg orig="Indempnity">Indemnity</reg></i>, be, and is hereby continued, and shall stand, be, and continue in <reg orig="ful">full</reg> force, until the said first day of <em>February</em>, 1653. And that the Commissioners herein named, or any four or more of them, be hereby <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg>, and <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to put in execution the said last mentioned Act, and all, and every the Powers and Authorities in, and by the same Act given, and every Clause and Thing therein contained.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The declaration of <em>John Manley</em>, entrusted with the management of the Posts, for the better establishing of the same.</i></head>

<p>Whereas I am <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> by his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>, and the Council, with the management of the Posts of this Nation, these are to declare to all Gentlemen, Merchants, and others whom it may concern, that I have established the places under-named to be for the <reg orig="receits">receipts</reg> of Letters, as well those that go to <em>Oxford, <reg orig="Cambridg">Cambridge</reg>, Southampton, Winchester, Lye, Yarmouth, Norwich</em>, and the places upon those Roads, as to any of the other Roads of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. And to that end have contracted with such as are to receive them; as also with all Letter-carriers in, and about the City of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> by me for the purposes aforesaid, so that no man within the City, or Suburbs will be necessitated to give them more, <reg orig="then">than</reg> what his Letters shall be justly taxed at, according to the rates established by the State here under-written.</p>

<p>And because I have determined upon no pretence whatsoever, to countenance any of my Agents in their miscarriages, I do hereby promise upon reasonable notice of any abuse, or exaction in that particular, to do all persons that equal right which the nature of their complaints may justly challenge from me, who shall make it my endeavour to be in all things as serviceable to the Interest of those Persons whose concernments pass through my hands.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<head level="3"><i>The Rates of Letters.</i></head>
<p>To any place within 80 miles distance, 2 <em>d.</em> a single Letter, 4 d. a double Letter.</p>
<p>To a further distance 3 <em>d</em> a single Letter, 6 <em>d.</em> a double Letter.</p>
<p>To <em>Scotland</em> 4 <em>d.</em> a single Letter, 8 <em>d.</em> a double Letter.</p>
<p>To <em>Ireland</em> 6 <em>d.</em> a single Letter, 12 <em>d.</em> a double Letter.</p>
<p>And so <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> for treble or greater Packets of Letters, to any of the former places.</p>
<head level="3"><i>The places where Letters may be left.</i></head>
<p>Mr: <em>Jenn</em> at <em>Westminster-gate</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Adams</em> at the <em>Savoy gate</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Tysen</em> at the <em>three Daggers</em> in <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet street</reg>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Humphrey</em> at the <em>3 Sugar loafs</em> in <em>Fanchurch street</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Hall</em> at the <reg orig="Booksellers">Bookseller's</reg> shop at <em>Russelstreet</em> end, in <em>Covent Garden</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Wetherwood</em> Pewterer, at the <em>3 Foxes</em> in <em>Longlane</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Gregson</em> next door to the <em>white Lyon</em> in <em>Wapping</em>.</p> 
<p>Mr: <em>Hutchins</em> at the <em>white Hart</em> in <em>Charing Cross</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Best</em> at <em>Gayes-Inn-gate</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Taylor Temple lane</em>.</p>
<p>Mr: <em>Smith</em> next door to the <em>Cock</em> in <em>Ratcliff &amp;c.</em></p>

<p>It is desired that for the better <reg orig="conteinance">continence</reg>, all Persons will be pleased to give their Letters <reg orig="ful">full</reg> directions to the places, and Counties as shall be needful to prevent mistakes.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Jan: 5.</head>

<p>I made mention about a fortnight since of the Counties assigned at a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War to divers of the commanders of the <em>Highlanders</em>, where to <reg orig="Leavy">Levy</reg> new Forces of Horse, and Foot, for the carrying of the present War; I shall now give it to you again, but with many alterations: <em>Glengary</em> himself is to be for the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> about <em><unclear>Innernes</unclear></em>, he himself is marched Northwards to receive the monies, and Arms from <em>France</em>, and <em>Holland</em>, are there said to attend him. <em>Kenmore</em> <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> up to the <em>Bray</em> of <em>Mare</em>, and in the Glens that way <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> with Woods, and Rivers <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, his Quarters are the largest of any, for his Forces <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> all along in several fast places, from <em>Lough Tay</em>, towards the <em><reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg></em> of <em>Stermont</em>, and <em>Angus</em>, <em>Ramsey</em> is Quartered<pb n="5" /> on the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> of <em>Angus</em>: The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is making <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> in the Blair of <em>Athol</em>, and in <em><reg orig="Pertshire">Perthshire</reg></em>, where <em>Mack-nagh</em>, and others are raising for him one Regiment of Horse, and another Foot, but their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> are likely to be frustrated. The Garrison of <em>Weem</em> hath very large Quarters, and are laying in Provision against the return of <em>Kenmore</em> from the North. <em><reg orig="Mac-naughton">MacNaughton</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Mac riggs">MacRiggs</reg></em> are for the West <em>Highlands</em>, where the Eldest Son of the Marquis of <em>Argyle</em> is very much discontented.</p>

<p>It is again advertised that the <em>Highlanders</em> are grown numerous, and do go on with their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, do what we can to prevent them.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Jan: 6.</head>

<p>The taking of the strong Castle of <em><reg orig="Philipsburgh">Philipsburg</reg></em> by the Forces of the <em>French</em> King, was this Day confirmed. Notice being given to one of his Commanders, that the Deputy Governor with the chiefest of the Officers was gone on hunting, he <reg orig="imbraced">embraced</reg> the present opportunity and bringing up some considerable Forces before the Castle, he so amazed them, expecting no such thing, that he presently became Master of the place. The Deputy Governor returning in the Evening, found the <reg orig="Bridg">Bridge</reg> drawn up, and entrance denied him, whereupon he was forced to retire with all the <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> he could make. Some impute the taking of this strong place, not only to the <reg orig="remisness">remissness</reg>, but to the treachery of the Deputy.</p>

<p>The Commissioners appointed to draw out the Charge of High Treason against the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, has had several meetings and is now said to be finished.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>Letters came from the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> Ambassador to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, advertising that the next day after his coming to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>. The three Presidents of that City, with the Magistrates thereof did come to salute him, and one of them who spake for all, informed his Lordship, that they had received positive commands from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> to give all due respects to the English Ambassador who she understood by <em>Lagensfeld</em> would in a short time be there. He desired also his <reg orig="Lordships">Lordship's</reg> pardon, that they were not prepared to give him a more pompous entertainment.</p>

<p>The Presidents of the City, after consultations amongst themselves, did advise his Lordship not to trust at season the uncertainty of the Seas, but to carry all his <reg orig="moveables">movables</reg> by Land, which will be a very vast charge to his Lordship, who hath already found by experience what are the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> which belong to so numerous a <reg orig="Trayn">Train</reg>, and so tedious a Journey.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Jan: 7</head>

<p>It was this Day certified, that our Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em> is safely arrived, they are in number forty sail and are laden with very rich Goods. There are also five ships from the East-lands and one from <em>Zant</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised that a Vessel going from <em>Weymouth</em> towards <em><reg orig="Iersey">Jersey</reg></em>, was <reg orig="droven">driven</reg> back by so violent a Tempest, that she was cast away, and all the men in her, but the ship master, and two passengers.</p>

<p>Our Fleet are sailed Westwards, part of them are about <em>Plymouth</em>, and some at <em>Falmouth</em>, some of them <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> out towards the Coast of <em>France</em>, to try if they can meet with the Brest Men of War, who are grown numerous and have good ships, and a considerable strength at Sea.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>The Dutch Commissioners who on Tuesday last went to <em><reg orig="Graves-end">Gravesend</reg></em> to take shipping for <em>Holland</em>, have not yet set sail, but remain there, and have made some further applications to his Highness, and his Council, which whether or no, it <reg orig="wil">will</reg> call them back again, or late calamity in their own Country, will <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to make a penal, and absolute agreement with us, a short time will discover.</p> 

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Jan: 9</head>

<p>This Day the great calamity in <em>Holland</em> was again confirmed; it is affirmed that the Lightning leaping from the clouds, when the Thunder chid, the Houses began to take fire, and that 500 hundred of them suddenly were devoured by it. At the same time the wind arising, the Billows in vast tumults began to move towards the Town, as if they made <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to put out the fire. By the high workings of the Sea, the <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> did presage the danger to come, and therefore used all their art and care to keep their ships at a distance, least in the <reg orig="foulnes">foulness</reg> of the weather they should fall foul on one another, but their diligence could not make that quick dispatch, before a most violent gust <reg orig="clapp'd">clapped</reg> them together, and being involved in one danger, about forty of them did suffer in one <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>.</p>

<p>But others (to whom rather I incline) do affirm, that the fire was four miles from <em>Amsterdam</em> at their rope-<reg orig="mils">mills</reg>, where were their stores both of Hemp, and <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, which served to increase the flame. 400 Houses are said to be there burned, and about 30 ships sunk by the Tempest.</p> 

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable is:</head>

<p><i>The new Addresses of the <em>Dutch</em> Deputies to his Highness, and his Council for a Peace. The late lamentable fire at <em>Amsterdam</em> where 500 Horses were consumed by fire and Lightning, and above forty gallant ships sunk by the Tempests. The Letters from the Ld: <em>Whitlock</em> Ambassador to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. The <em>Speech</em> made unto him by one of the Presidents. The new incursions and <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> of the <em>Highlanders</em>, and some <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> received. And several Prizes taken by our Fleet in the West of <em>England</em>.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>