<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell332">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 332</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, May 16. to <em>Tuesday</em>, May 23. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 16.</head>

<p>Great was the joy this Day amongst our Commanders, some unexpectedly that <reg orig="cam">came</reg> from <em>Ireland</em>, did meet with some of our Commanders from Sea, so that both sea and Land did partake in the Joy, they were all Feasted by his Highness, the Lord Mayor of the City being one of the Guests.</p>

<p>I shall in this place insert a word or two, which for want of room was omitted in my last; the Sessions being the week before the Old <reg orig="Bayly">Bailey</reg>, there were two found guilty for <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> false half Crowns, and other monies, the Rings were silver, but the rest brass <reg orig="mettal">metal</reg>. Such monies have been lately <reg orig="Coyned">Coined</reg> by the Enemy in <em>Scotland</em>, and is passable amongst them.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Whitlock</em> having dispatched happily his <reg orig="Ambassy">Embassy</reg> with the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> is coming over the <em><reg orig="Baltick">Baltic</reg></em> Sea to <em>Lubeck</em>, where some ships of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> will be ready to attend him.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>I shall in this place give you the Declaration published in <em>Scotland</em> by Gen: <em>Monk</em>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness, and affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a chargeable and bloody War) into Union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much blood and treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge (of which this Nation undergoeth no more <reg orig="then">than</reg> their equal proportion with <em>England</em>) against their Enemies both abroad and at home, whereby all of them might enjoy the fruits and benefits of Peace; Yet divers lewd persons broken in their fortunes, and dissolute Levies are run into Rebellion, and being assisted and connived at by their Parents, Tutors, Masters, and People among whom they live, who secretly conceal them in their houses in the day time, and in the night suffer them to rob and plunder the Country, whereby the peaceable people of this Nation are many of them ruined, and the rest disturbed, so that they cannot live in peace. And to the end that no peaceable means might be left unattempted, for the prevention thereof.</p>

<p>I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority to me given by his Highness, and his Council, do Declare, That all such persons that are now in Rebellion, (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him or themselves, to the Governor of the next English Garrison, and give good security for his, or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons freely pardoned, for any Offence, Spoil, or Plunders committed by him or them in this present rebellion, (the killing of any person in cold blood only excepted.)</p>

<p>And in regard divers persons who are now in Rebellion, and who have lived remote from their friends, but could not probably break out into <reg orig="Rellion">Rebellion</reg>, without the <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> or consent of some of the Inhabitants of that Parish of Presbytery<pb n="2" /> where he or they last lived, before their breaking forth; I do therefore hereby Declare, That if the said Parish or Presbytery where he or they last lived, procure the said person or persons so broken forth hereof, and give security, as aforesaid, That then the Parish or Presbytery so offending, is hereby pardoned; But if otherwise, I do hereby impose upon the said parish, or Presbytery two shillings six pence a day for each horseman, and ten pence a day for each Footman, so broken into Rebellion, over and above their ordinary Sess, out of the said Presbytery, which the Governor of the next English Garrison is hereby authorized to <reg orig="levie">levy</reg> and receive <reg orig="monethly">monthly</reg>, during the time the said persons shall so continue in Rebellion.</p>

<p>And I do likewise hereby <reg orig="impower">empower</reg> all the good people of this Nation, to apprehend all such person and persons as are, or hereafter shall break out into Rebellion, or attempt so to do, and safely to deliver him or them to the Governor of the next English Garrison; and in case of resistance, to take such weapons as they can get, and to fight the said person, or persons, and if they shall <reg orig="killany">kill any</reg> of the said persons so resisting, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be questioned for the same, but (on the contrary) shall receive as a reward of their good service, all such Monies, Goods, Horse, and <reg orig="Cloaths">Clothes</reg>, as the said Rebellious persons are then possessed of, besides <reg orig="ful">full</reg> satisfaction for their pains and travel therein. And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, the Earl of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, <em>Donald, <reg orig="Mac Donald">McDonald</reg></em> Laird of <em><reg orig="Glengary">Glengarry</reg></em>, and Major Gen: <em>Dayel</em>; I do hereby <reg orig="therfore">therefore</reg> Declare, That what person excepted} shall kill any of the said principal Contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner to any Governor of any <em>English</em> Garrison, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner, as aforesaid, shall not only be pardoned, but also receive a Reward of his good service, the sum of 200 <em>l. sterling</em>, for every person so <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>, or brought prisoner, as aforesaid, <em>&amp;c</em>.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>It is further advertised from <em>France</em>, that the Duke of <em>Guise</em> is to command the <em>French</em> Fleet as General and the Marquis <em>Du Plessis</em> is to to be Lieutenant General. The Marshal of <em>Thuren</em> although a Protestant, is of great power in the Court, and doth command a powerful Army which are on their march for <em>Flanders</em>. The Forces in <em>Picardy</em>, <em>Campain</em> and <em>Burgundy</em> have had a <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg>, where being well <reg orig="cloathed">clothed</reg>, and contented for the present with some monies, they are by this time in the borders of <em>France</em>, and ready to pour themselves into <em>Italy</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 17.</head>

<p>Writs are preparing against the time they are to issue forth for the calling of a new Parliament, according to the Instrument of the Government of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, which was then extant when the General being made Protector, did exchange his <em>Excellence</em> into his <em>Highness</em>.</p>

<p><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg>, 10 <em>May</em>: Sir, I sent you by the last Post a <reg orig="Copie">Copy</reg> of General <em><reg orig="Monks">Monk's</reg></em> Declaration, since the publishing <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg> he is gone towards <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>, and thereabouts will be a Rendezvous of our Forces, and then shall we steer our course with all expedition to find out the Enemy, which keeps Col: <em>Morgan</em> waking, and yet flies from him.</p>

<p>The late supplies the Enemy hath had of men, money, and Ammunition by the way of <em>Dunkirk</em> adds some further life to those desperadoes that were engaged before; and to exasperate them the more, <em>Middleton</em> appeared in the head of some of his ragged Regiments with a bag of money in his hand, encouraging them to fight, and money would not be wanting. They prosecute their Levies with all the <reg orig="vigor">vigour</reg> that can be; yet if we can but climb well, we shall scatter them quickly. They are confident that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em> or the Duke of <em>York</em> will be with them if they stand but two months longer, and the Ministers <reg orig="wil">will</reg> hardly be kept from praying for them in <reg orig="publick">public</reg>, even in our own quarters. Divers Merchant men are gone forth to Sea from <em>Leith</em>.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>Gen: <em>Blake</em> sat in Council at <em><reg orig="White hal">Whitehall</reg></em> and Gen: <em>Pen</em> is with the Fleet upon the <em>Downs</em>, we hear a Squadron is designed further off.</p>

<p>There have been a long time some discontents between the <em>English</em>, and the Inhabitants of Saint <em>Mallows</em>; not long since the <em>Hector</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> attending to Convoy some <em>English</em> from thence, a Shallop was sent out of town to acquaint the Captain that the <em>English</em> should have all freedom, and liberty into that Port, but this was conceived to be but a plot to <reg orig="cojoal">cajole</reg> the <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> into the Haven.</p>

<p>The Letters from <em>Scotland</em> say, that we beat the Enemy in all parts we <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> with them, we have lately taken General <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Brother, and five or six Officers more, and routed the whole party, General <em>Monk</em> hath hanged two of them as Spies.</p>

<p>There was a man barbarously killed this last week, and being cut to <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg>, was put into a <reg orig="Bagg">Bag</reg>, and thrown into a <reg orig="hedg">hedge</reg> not much out of the way as you go to <em>Paddington</em>; the Murderer and his Female Companion falling out last <em>Saturday</em> might, she discovered him, and he being asked by the Justice how he could find in his heart to commit so <reg orig="unmerciles">unmerciless</reg> and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> an act, he made answer he could serve him so, if he had him in a place where.</p>

<p>There is a Report of a new Treason discovered, of which more in my next.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>France</em>, that the great Master of Eloquence <em>Monsieur de Balrack</em> being dead, hath left 2000 Livers for the University Orator <em>Angoulesme</em>, for 20 years, and the like sum to buy Books for the Dean, and Chapter of <em>Angoulesme</em>, not far from which is the Signiory, or <reg orig="Mannor">Manor</reg> of <em>Balzack</em>; This is that Gentleman who (although the too perpetulant, and censorious <reg orig="Critick">Critic</reg> <em>Nicholas de Moulinet</em>, in his Comical History of <em>Francion</em>, doth endeavour to detract from him) hath undoubtedly brought as much glory to <em>France</em>, by his pen, as their most <reg orig="laureaut">laureate</reg> Kings by their greatest Victories, most happy he is in rich, and clean expressions, in which so cutely he did excel.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorraign</em> a prisoner in <em>Antwerp</em> hath now the liberty of the walks of the Castle, and his Daughter hath her Diamonds and Jewels of great value restored to her. Those who are chief in attendance on him are now at liberty, and did go forth with those, who in a most gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg> did ride out of the City to congratulate the arrival of his Brother Prince <em>Francis</em>, who hath the reputation to be a virtuous, and <reg orig="couragious">courageous</reg> Gentleman.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>France</em> it is further advertised, that the <em>Palsgrave</em> and his Brother Prince <em>Edward</em> are in great favour with the Emperor, who according to the custom of Kings in such great meetings, doth look for a <reg orig="subsidie">subsidy</reg> or two, at the dissolution of the Diet, his propositions to the States of <em>Bohemia</em> are; That they use their utmost endeavour for the propagating the Romish <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion; That they celebrate the Feast of Saint <em>Joseph</em> as the rest of the Patrons of that Kingdom use to do; That they pay a considerable sum to the Emperor for the maintenance of his <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> Officers, Ambassadors, and Resendentiaries. That they pay their due proportions for the maintenance of the <reg orig="Frontire">Frontier</reg> places of <em>Hungary</em>. That they continue their maintenance of the Imperial Forces quartered in that Kingdom, and pay those which his Majesty shall disband. That they suffer not the importation, nor Manufacturers of the Turkish Wool. That they cause the River of <em>Elve</em> to be made Navigable as far as <em>Reignburgh</em>. That they suffer not the importation of <reg orig="Forraign">Foreign</reg> Salt without paying the usual Customs.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, May 19.</head>

<p>The <em>Italian Comedy</em> hath been often acted with much Ceremony in <em>Paris</em>, the next great solemnity will be the consecration of the King at <em>Rheims</em>, for which great preparations are made. At the last acting of the Comedy at <em>Paris</em>, the properties whereof are to be Translated to Rimes, and to be acted there also, there were present at the late Queen of <em>England</em>, the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, and the titular Dukes of <em>York</em>, and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>. The next day the Queen Regent came to give a Visit to the late Queen of <em>England</em>, the Civility<pb n="6" /> was the next day returned by her, the next day saving one, who with her Son did give a Visit to their Majesties at the <em>Louure</em>, and after supper, being entertained with a pleasure of a Mask, they returned to the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> Royal.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is arrived at <em>Lubeck</em>. The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> will certainly resign the Crown to her Kinsman <em>Carolus Adolphus</em>; his Brother Prince <em>John Adolphus</em> having laid down his Patent of the Lord High <reg orig="Marshall">Marshal</reg> of <em>Sweden</em>, is gone to <em>Stockholm</em> to confer with his elder Brother, who will shortly be invested with the Royal Dignity. The Lady Fleetwood being lately Deceased in <em>Swethland</em>, the Funeral will be in great pomp, the Queen <reg orig="her self">herself</reg>, and many of the Nobility being present at it.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 20.</head>

<p>The <em>Hollanders</em> do begin already to find the benefit of the Peace with <em>England</em>, they have brought in hither great store of Cheese, and <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>. The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> in the Western Seas are as bold, and <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> as ever, but they dare not adventure Easterly, where our Fleet lies on the <em>Downs</em> in a gallant <reg orig="Equippage">Equipage</reg>.</p>

<p>The Report is, that two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are seized upon at Saint <em>Mallows</em>, that some of our Men of War lying <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to <em>Saint Mallows</em>, threescore of our men being too bold to adventure for fresh Victuals, did go <reg orig="ashoar">ashore</reg>, and endeavoured to drive away some Cattle, but the Country receiving the <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg>, they rescued the Cattle, being assisted by some horse, and divers of our <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> were killed, and the rest pursued to the ships, two of which the Tide going forth, were stranded, whereupon great Guns were brought from <em>Saint Mallows</em> to batter the ships, which they did begin to do, but the Tide coming in, the ships got off without any great hurt. The Governor of Saint <em>Mallows</em> apprehending this to be a design against the Town, did take an occasion to turn out all the English Merchants, and to seize upon all their Goods in the Warehouses, and hath got all for the present into his own custody. Complaints have been made hereof, and the business as yet under examination.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>General <em>Blake</em> having been lately with his Highness, and received further Instructions, is gone down again to the Fleet, which on the latter end of this week will set sail from the <em>Downs</em>, and <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the expectation of Christendom, who begin to examine themselves, and know not certainly against what place the design is laid, which doth carry so much terror in it.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Whitlock</em> is at <em>Lubeck</em>, it is uncertain whither he will take shipping there for <em>England</em>, or rather at <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>. All the Nobility of <em>France</em> are gone to <em>Rheims</em> to the consecration of the young King, to which the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> was solemnly invited.</p>

<p>Some parties of our Horse have fallen upon the <em>Scots</em> in <em>Athol</em>, and <em>Murray</em>, and routed them, and taken several persons prisoners. There is a Report that there have been a great fight in <em>Scotland</em>, in which twelve hundred <em>Scots</em> were slain, and Gen: <em>Monk</em> wounded, but there is no such thing. General <em>Monk</em> is yet at <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg>. It appears that <em>Middleton</em> hath no desire to fight, he hath excellent Intelligence, and if he were in such a capacity to fight, as his partisans do report, he would undoubtedly have fallen upon <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> before the access of new Forces to him. <em>Scotland</em> is now a sad place, fire and sword <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> domineering</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>&#x261e; The <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> of our Men at Saint <em>Mallows</em>, and the battering there of two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>. The <em>English</em> Fleet setting sail from the <em>Downs</em>. The Report of the great fight in <em>Scotland</em>, and twelve hundred of <em>Scots</em> slain. The certainty of a great defeat given to a party of the <em><reg orig="Scots">Scot's</reg></em> Horse, and <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Brother taken with several eminent Commanders. Two other Defeats given to the Scots in <em>Athol</em>, and <em><reg orig="Murryland">Murrayland</reg></em>. The Murderer discovered by the Murderess and both of them apprehended, who the last week did cut the man in <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> in the way to Paddington, and did put his <reg orig="dismember'd">dismembered</reg> body into a <reg orig="bagg">bag</reg>. The Report of a new Treason discovered.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>