<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell207">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 207</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, February 28. to <em>Tuesday</em>, March 7. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, February 28.</head>

<p>I made mention heretofore of the fight at <em>Dunkill</em> by <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: Daniel, and since of the taking of the Castle of <em>Kildrummie</em> by <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em>, I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> in this place give you a more particular relation of it, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> coming to the Castle of <em>Kildrummie</em> sent in a summons by his Trumpet, strictly summoning them to deliver up unto the said Castle, with all the arms and Ammunition therein for the use of his Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, to which if they did <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg> obedience, they should have liberty to go to their own homes, and live at peace, <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> they will act nothing prejudicial to the English Army, but if by their means there shall happen the least effusion of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>, they are to expect no mercy at all. This Summons was directed to Major <em>William Drummond</em>, Governor of the said Castle for the said Earl of <em>Athol</em>, who returned unto it this following Answer.</p><pb n="1" />

<p><em>SIR</em>,</p> 
<p>I received yours, and find your propositions very hard without order from my Lord General, <reg orig="alwaies">always</reg> Sir, if you will be pleased to suffer me to send one to my Lord General, and upon his return we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> render the house if they come not again Monday at night for our relief, we shall march with our horse and arms to any part of the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Army in Scotland, and withal the place be made <reg orig="useles">useless</reg> for any garrison, and for the effusion of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> we take God to witness, yours shall be the fault: no further but</p>

<p><i>Yours as time shall produce, Wil. Drummond</i></p>
<p>Kildrummie 23 <em>Febr</em>: 1654.</p>
<p><i>For C L <em>Morgan</em>, Commander of the English Forces.</i></p>

<p>SIR, I have considered your Answer, and cannot grant your desires, yet so tender am I of shedding of <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> in case you be not satisfied with the terms I offered, if you please to send 1 or 2 Officers fully authorized to treat in order to your sudden surrender, I shall rather deal <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> use cruelty, <em>I</em> expect your answer by this Bearer, and am</p>
<p><i>Yours as occasion shall serve, Tho: Morgan</i></p>
<p><i>For Major <em>Drummond</em> Officer in Chief in the House of Kildrummie</i></p>

<p>SIR, I have received yours, and am as <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to shed blood at this time as any <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be, Sir, I thought you would have suffered me to have sent to my L. Gen: because I being put here by him, and on such a sudden to surrender, I <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> no man of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg> but might esteem me the basest of men, but however for the matter of Treaty, if you please to send down to the gate one or two, I shall wait on them there to hear your will; no more but that I am <i>Yours to meeting, W: Drummond</i></p>
<p><i>For <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: Morgan commander in chief of the English Forces in the North of Scotland.</i></p>

<p>Sir, according to your intimation I have sent Lieut. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Simmons</em>, and Major <em>Knight</em> to treat, in order to your sudden<pb n="2" /> surrender of the House of <em>Kildrummie</em>, and <reg orig="what ever">whatever</reg> they conclude, shall be made good by me <em>Tho: Morgan</em></p>

<p><i>For Major <em>William Drummond</em> Officer in chief within the House of <em>Kildrummy</em></i></p>

<p>The Commissioners could not agree, so that the Treaty <reg orig="broak">broke</reg>, but the next morning <em>Drummond</em> sent his Drum with this following Letter.</p>

<p>SIR. I thought good to show you that it is but a short time betwixt Monday, and Thursday, and because we have bedding, and some other things which we brought from the Country people and did not <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> to give them back at our leaving the place, before which time we can hardly get done, if you Sir, think this fit, let us meet, and condescend on Articles, and to such time I rest. <i>Yours as occasion offers, Wil. Drummond.</i></p>
<p>Kildrummie 12 <em>Febr</em>: 1653/4.</p>
<p><i>For Col: <em>Morgan</em> Commander in <reg orig="cheif">chief</reg> of the English Forces in the North. These.</i></p>

<p>SIR, I perceive that you <reg orig="stil">still</reg> persist in your <reg orig="delaies">delays</reg>, but this may suffice you that I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not afford you any longer time to march <reg orig="then">than</reg> <reg orig="too morrow">tomorrow</reg> at 10 a clock, and because your redelivery of the <reg orig="Countries">Country's</reg> Goods shall not cause you to Dispute: in case those whom I send to treat, and conclude and you agree, I shall give you liberty to leave one behind, to see the Goods disposed on according to your <reg orig="ingagement">engagement</reg>, who shall have free liberty to act accordingly; I expect your <reg orig="immediat">immediate</reg> answer, and remain <i>Yours if you be your own, Tho: Morgan.</i></p>
<p><i>For Major <em>Drummond</em> Commander in chief within the House of <em>Kildrummie</em>.</i></p>

<p>Sir, I received yours, and if we agree on Articles I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> march <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> by 10 a clock, so expecting those whom you send to treat at the place where we met last night, where I shall attend them. I rest Sir, <i>Yours as before.</i></p>
<p>Kildrummie 12 Febr. 1653/4</p>
<p><i>For Coll. <em>Morgan</em> Commander in chief of the English forces in the North. These.</i></p>

<p>Upon which these ensuing Articles were agreed upon, and Cornet <em>Barhom</em> was sent into the house as Hostage on our<pb n="3" /> part, and Cornet <em>Garden</em>, <em><reg orig="Kenmores">Kenmore's</reg></em> Cornet was delivered as Hostage for the House.</p>

<p>Articles agreed upon for the surrender of the House of <em>Kildrummie</em> this 26 Feb: 1653/4 betwixt Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Simmons</em>, and Major <em>Knight</em> on the behalf of the English Forces.</p>

<p>And Major W. <em>Drummond</em> Governor of the foresaid House, and Cap: <em><reg orig="Mathew">Matthew</reg> Hambleton</em>, on the behalf of the <em>Scotch</em> forces.</p>

<p><i>1.That the said Governor is to march with all the forces in the said House, Arms, Ammunition <reg orig="Bagg">Bag</reg> and Baggage <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> morning by ten a clock to the nearest place where any of the Scotch Forces, are, without molestation, and to have a <unclear>Pass</unclear> to that purpose from <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em>, unto whom he is to surrender the said House without any demolition for the use of his Highness the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>2.That the said Governor shall have liberty to leave an Officer to dispose of the Country goods which are in the said House, either belonging to the Earl of Marr, or any other.</i></p>

<p><i>3.That the said Governor shall march ten miles a day, with the party under his command, except the first day, till they come at the forces, and are not to molest or trouble any of the Forces belonging to his Highness the Lord Protector upon their march, upon any account whatsoever; for the performance whereof, each subscribed.</i></p>

<head level="3">POSTSCRIPT</head>

<p>Now I shall take the <reg orig="boldnes">boldness</reg> to acquaint you, that in case the Castle had not been delivered that day, neither our horse nor foot had been able to have continued there one night longer, the season of the year not permitting it; Neither were we able to do any good upon the House without bartering guns which could not have come to us in a <reg orig="weeks">week's</reg> time, so that <unclear>after</unclear> serious Debate at a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War, it was concluded better to allow <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg> to them, <reg orig="then">than</reg> with <reg orig="dishonor">dishonour</reg> to leave it, having been before it three nights.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, March 1.</head>

<p>It was advertised by Letters from <em>Scotland</em> that in the last Defeat given to the <em>Highlanders</em>, one of their Commanders made such <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> to provide for himself by flight, that he left behind him several Instructions sent unto him from Holland heretofore by Major General <em>Middleton</em>, and also several Letters of great concernment from the titular <em>Scots</em> King to the Earl of <em>Glencarn</em>, as also their papers for raising of more Forces and the way therein designed, for the maintaining of them; as also for the <unclear><!--approx. 2 characters --></unclear> comes of more Arms, and monies from other parts, all which being now fallen into the hands<pb n="4" /> of the English Commanders will be no little moment for the dispatching of the <reg orig="busines">business</reg> of the War in the North.</p>

<p>It was this Day advertised that the Lord <em>Newport</em>, and the Lord <em>Yongstall</em> who touched at <em>Harwich</em> the last week a little to refresh themselves, are come to <em>Gravesend</em>, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the Lord <em>Beverling</em>, whereupon Sir <em>Oliver <reg orig="Flemming">Fleming</reg></em> Master of the Ceremonies had Orders to meet them on the Friday following at the Tower-hill, and from thence Coaches were come to bring them, and their Attendants through the City of <em>London</em> to Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams's</reg></em> House in <em>Westminster</em>, which some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> hath been prepared for them.</p>

<p>An Ambassador from the <reg orig="Arch.duke">Archduke</reg> had this day Audience, who did congratulate his Highness, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> his Letters of Credence to confirm the sincerity, as <reg orig="wel">well</reg> as the authority of his gratulation.</p>

<p>Upon addresses made to his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, by the Magistrates of the City of <em>Westminster</em>, in relation to the Government thereof; there have been several Debates, and because the City of <em>London</em> is some way <reg orig="concern'd">concerned</reg> therein, the said City of <em>London</em> hath had notice of it, that so a Dispatch may be made of the whole, to the union, and content of both Cities. It was therefore ordered by his Highness Council that the chief Magistrates of the City of <em>London</em>, and the City of <em>Westminster</em> should be both sent for, and heard together. The <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> of the City of <em>Westminster</em> desire a Corporation, and have long sued for it.</p>

<p>Addresses have been made to the Lord Protector by <em>William Lenthal</em> Esquire, <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> Speaker of Parliament, <em>Thomas Pury</em> Esquire, <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> a Member of Parliament, and divers other Gentlemen from the City of <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, who in the name, and under the Seal of the said City signed by the <reg orig="Magistrats">Magistrates</reg> thereof have presented to his Highness a Declaration, congratulatory blessing the Lord for this established Government, and protesting much affection thereunto.</p>

<p>Instructions have passed the Council for suppressing Actors and Players, &amp;c.</p>

<p>It is certified by Letters from <em>Ireland</em> (whatsoever have <reg orig="bin">been</reg><pb n="5" /> buzzed abroad to the contrary) that the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em>, and other Commanders and Commissioners are all well, and that there is no fear of an Enemy to appear in any body; some <reg orig="theeves">thieves</reg> there are (as indeed where are not?) who make it their business to break open houses, and exercise their <reg orig="larceries">larcenies</reg>, but they are commonly taken, and suffer according to the demerit of their offence.</p>

<p>It is certified, that at the first hearing of the change of Government in <em>England</em>, some things were <reg orig="scrupuled">scrupled</reg> in <em>Ireland</em>; but upon better consideration the result gave better satisfaction, and they are now all unanimous.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, March 2.</head>

<p><reg orig="Somthing">Something</reg> was heard from the Magistrates of the Cities of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, and debated on this day touching a Corporation to be granted to the City of <em>Westminster</em>, which will be effected.</p>

<p>Mr <em>Feake</em> and Mr. <em>Vavasor Powel</em> have made their addresses for their liberty: some Ministers and others have been with them, and friendly advised them to be sensible of their mistakes.</p>

<p>It is further certified from <em>Windsor</em>, that one in the Castle belonging to the Ammunition had <reg orig="imbizelle'd">embezzled</reg> away some of the Powder, and being taken in the manner, he was brought before the Governor, and was sentenced to ride upon a Brass Saker when it is shot off with a half charge.</p>

<p>It is certified further from <em>Holland</em>, that great is their joy there that the Peace with <em>England</em> doth go so happily on. It was almost beyond their expectations, their joys therefore no doubt are doubled. It was feared that those of the House of <em>Orange</em>, and the Soldiery would have made some obstructions, but all was every way quiet, and no expressions of discontent were heard.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, March 3.</head>

<p>This day great was the confluence of the people to behold <em>Peace</em> and the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors enter into the City of <em>London</em>, they were met by six Coaches belonging to his Highness the Protector, and about 28 more drawn all<pb n="6" /> with six Horses; after them followed 40 Coaches drawn with 4 Horses, and about 60 Coaches drawn with two Horses. Many even of the last were of the Nobility of <em>England</em>, according as the violence of the late War had disposed of their Fortunes. In one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coaches was the Master of the Ceremonies, who with accustomed Complements received the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, and brought them to their Lodgings in the New <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> at <em>Westminster</em>, where at the charge of the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> they are to be entertained with their Retinue for certain days.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, March 4.</head>

<p>This afternoon the Lord Protector gave Audience to the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassador in the <reg orig="Banquetting">Banqueting</reg> House at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>; the subject whereof was partly congratulatory to his Highness, but the greatest part Declaratory to renew the old League which was between the two Nations before the late Wars did unhappily discontinue it, to which purpose the seven United Provinces did all consent to the agreement of a Peace, which they have received <reg orig="ful">full</reg> power to confirm, they therefore desire a speedy cessation of Arms, assuring that on their side all acts of Hostility <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> to the uttermost of their power be suspended, so that safely we may conclude, that the Peace will fully, and speedily be established.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, March 6.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised that our Fleet rideth still not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>, some squadrons are at the <em>Spits head</em>, and others at Saint <em>Ellens point</em>, they are ready to put forth to Sea in the most gallant <reg orig="equippage">equipage</reg> that may be, and the contented Seamen from several parts are making their dispatches thither to their <reg orig="imployment">employment</reg>. We have now in one body the bravest Fleet that <em>England</em> hath put forth since the Wars began.</p>

<p>It is confirmed that Mr: <em>Williamson</em> who was Ambassador here before from <em>Denmark</em>, is <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> again by that Crown into <em>England</em>, to make application to his Highness upon the success of the Treaty with the United Provinces.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>It is confirmed by Letters this day from <em>Scotland</em>, that whilst our Horse are in the more Northern parts of that Nation, Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> who is again recovered of his wounds, is marched Southwards to see what parties he can find <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg>, or what booty he can get <reg orig="aboat">about</reg> <em>Lenox</em>, or <em>Tivesdale</em>.</p>

<p>In the mean time the Earl of <em>Glencarn</em> is in the North, and not daring to hazard all his strength on the uncertainty of one <reg orig="Battel">Battle</reg>, doth divide his Forces into several parties, that he might thereby be better enabled to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> the importunity of their bellies, and <reg orig="incourage">encourage</reg> or <reg orig="inforce">enforce</reg> the Countries to increase their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>; the fiery crosses have had their run, and whirled from place to place in several Countries, but to no effect; it is wonderful indeed to consider what an impression <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> supernatural hath in all ages left in the minds of the common soldiers; to <reg orig="demurr">demur</reg> therefore from the <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> of new forces in the <reg orig="unsetled">unsettled</reg> Counties, it hath being reported wheresoever the Recruits are to be raised, that a Gentleman in the County of <em>Fife</em> had a Vision, in which he was <reg orig="admonish'd">admonished</reg> by a young man with all speed to address himself to <em>Glencarn</em> his Kinsman, and to acquaint him with the anger of God to fall on him, and all his Forces, if they pursued such destructive courses. The Gentleman disobedient to the Angel on the first night, was struck dumb the second, because he <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> not his voice as he was commanded; this Report hath been of more efficacy to trouble the <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and discourage the old Soldiers of <em>Glencarn</em>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> the certain arrival of our Regiments, and of 3 ships laden with Tents, <reg orig="cloaths">cloths</reg> and all manner of provision both for life and death.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>The Addresses of the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors and the speech of the Ld. <em>Yunngital</em> to his Highness for a peace betwixt both Nations, and the Results thereof. The <em>English</em> fleet in a most gallant equipage ready to put forth to sea. The congratulations of several Potentates to his Highness. The great deliverance of the titular Duke of <em>York</em> in <em>France</em>. And the wonderful vision that appeared to a friend of <em><reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg></em>, to dissuade him from the further prosecution of the War in <em>Scotland</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>