<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell208#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 208#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, March 7. to <em>Tuesday</em>, March 14. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, March 7.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised by Letters from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, that the Lord <em>Wilmot</em> who <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> himself Ambassador for the titular King of the <em>Scots</em>, being necessitated for the want of monies, did with much importunity press upon the Treasurer of the English Company, who fearing his power, and loath to part with those monies which belonged to all the English Merchants who <reg orig="traffick">traffic</reg> in those parts, did acquaint the <reg orig="Presidennt">President</reg> of the English companies with it, and withal, <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> the inconveniences that would arise, if he should deliver such monies to him, which against the Laws of Merchandise were not in his power to disburse, whereupon the President weighing the truth of the Reasons, made his complaint to the Senate, who <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> not to exact any sums of money of the Treasurer, unless he were able to put in good security for the re-disbursing of them. Some differences have been betwixt the Agent of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Brandenburgh">Brandenburg</reg></em>, and the Ambassador of the States General of<pb n="1" /> the United Provinces, in the emulation for the <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg>, which upon better consideration are reconciled.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Sweden</em>, that there have been a consultation betwixt the grand Chancellor, and the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> there was a <reg orig="Demurr">Demur</reg> about the Article of an Offensive, and defensive War, the English being at the present engaged in Wars, and the Crown of Sweden being at Peace with all Nations, but satisfaction was given by our Ambassador, that the Chancellor remained <reg orig="throughly">thoroughly</reg> satisfied. The Queen looks on <em>England</em> as much more <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> under the Lord Protector, <reg orig="then">than</reg> before. She hath been five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in the Country to visit her Mother, who is not in the Court of <em>Denmark</em>, as some too boldly have represented, the weather being <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> cold, according to the season of the year in that Country, she was <reg orig="slidd">slid</reg> home on a carriage without wheels, which dispatched a long way with incredible speed, in that icy Country.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em> March 8.</head>

<p>Several Petitions were this Day read by his Highness, and Orders passed therein. Something is referred to a Committee of the Council to consider of touching Religion, in order to what hath been offered by the Ministers, for the suppressing of those who are scandalous, and <reg orig="prophane">profane</reg>, and providing for those who are able, and painful Preachers.</p>

<p>A Minister in <em>London</em> lately summoned in part of his Parish before the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord Mayor for non payment of their Tithes, when the Case came to be heard, the Minister was opposed by one of the Parishioners, who (after the matter was <reg orig="wav'd">waved</reg> in point of Law) began to dispute it out in Divinity, saying that a Bishop ought to be no striker, <em>&amp;c.</em> that he ought to govern his own <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg>, but the <reg orig="Mans">Man's</reg> Wife governed him, &amp;c. yet this would not serve turn, but according to the Act, he was Ordered to pay Tithes to the Minister.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>Letters from <em>Newcastle</em> say, that the <em>French <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg></em>, and <em>Freebooters</em> do very much infest that Coast, and lately took two <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels of ours within sight of <em>Tinmouth Castle</em>, which makes the Colliers fearful to come, especially hearing there is such great probability of Peace, to be concluded on shortly.</p>

<p>The <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors had a private conference with his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council at <reg orig="White_hall">Whitehall</reg>, they press hard for a present cessation of Arms.</p>

<p>Last Sabbath day Major Gen: <em>Harrison</em> taught at <em>London house</em>, after the exercise was ended, a Letter was read which was directed to that Congregation from Mr: <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em>, <reg orig="wherin">wherein</reg> he expressed a hearty desire, that the spirit of meekness, love and unity might increase amongst them, but he <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that he findeth not the sprinkling of Infants in the New-Testament, (which is a thing that M. <em>Feak</em>, and he have often argued upon since their confinement at <em><reg orig="Winsor">Windsor</reg></em>) Mr. <em>Cradock</em>, and divers other Friends have been to visit them lately.</p>

<p>The Letters this Post from <em>Scotland</em> make mention, that be reason of the coldness of the season, and the great store of snow lately fallen in the Northern parts, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> returned back (from pursuing the Enemy to <em>Aberdeen</em>, but another party of ours have had another <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> with a party of about 60 of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> Horse, they fought at the first very stoutly; but soon turned their backs, and fled to save themselves in this fight we took one Lieutenant, and about 20 more prisoners, their main design at the present is to Rob and spoil what they can, &amp; therefore divide themselves into divers <reg orig="smal">small</reg> parties.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>From <em>Park</em> thus. There have been some motions made of late by friends in behalf of Cardinal <em>de Retz</em>, yet hath he not his enlargement.</p>

<p><i>This ensuing Letter is said to be written by the Cardinal to the Duke of <em>Orleans</em>.</i></p>

<p>SIR:</p>

<p>I can no longer live without writing, for I understand the Court hath done some kind of Justice wherewith you are reasonably well pleased, but if this content be not absolute, I am resolved not to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>; and truly it is a shame to see the bounties of Princes in the hands of such persons, who can neither be useful, nor pleasing unto them, and that honest men must <reg orig="stil">still</reg> <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves with the only testimony of a good conscience, and in the content they receive in well doing, for my part I <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not complain of fortune, if others must have the use of her. Now if the Ministers of State understood my secret, and that for satisfying of two, it were only necessary to oblige one, by acquitting themselves of what they owe another, they might easily spare what they have done unto me.</p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em> they write, that our Fleet are to have a Rendezvous upon the <em>Downs</em> this week; The <em>Hollanders</em> have also a <reg orig="verie">very</reg> great fleet in readiness; and if these two <reg orig="Armadoes">Armadas</reg> have the happiness to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> as one in League and <reg orig="Amitie">Amity</reg>, all the Enemies of these Nations may say as the Devil did when he was <unclear>sheering</unclear> of a <unclear>Hog</unclear>, <i>There is a great cry for a little <reg orig="wooll">wool</reg>.</i></p>

<p>The next Passage <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> to give no discontent unto any here, except Officers belonging to the Prize Office, the Admiralty, and Captains of Private Men of War; and the thing is this. The Articles of Peace are ordered to be engrossed with all haste, and the Ratification is speedily to be Signed: and that morning <unclear>may be wanting</unclear> on our part His Highness the Lord Protector hath appointed Commissioners to expedite<pb n="4" /> the whole matter with the Ambassadors of the seven united Provinces of <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p>By this the Lady <em>Elizabeth</em> and some others depart <em>Holland</em>, she goes to her eldest Son the <em>Palsgrave</em>.</p>

<p>The Treaty goes on also very effectually with the <em>French</em> Resident: The late Queen of <em>England</em> is to depart <em>France</em>, and go to the Duke of <em>Savoy</em>. Her Son <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and the Dukes of <em>York</em> and <em><reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg></em>, are to go into <em>Germany</em>, they not finding the affairs in <em>Scotland</em> to suit with their desires.</p>

<p>It is thought that Monsieur <em><reg orig="Berdeux">Bordeaux</reg></em> the French Ambassador, being a Person of a very large Revenue of his own, <reg orig="wil">will</reg> come in State through the City <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg> or next day; why may we not then expect shortly to drink a quart of Claret for <reg orig="eightpence">eight pence</reg> ?</p>

<p>Monsieur <em>Williamson</em> Ambassador for <em>Denmark</em> is also expected to make his Application to His Highness the Lord Protector very suddenly.</p>

<p>General <em>Desbrowe</em>, and Gen: <em>Monk</em>, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty are at <em>Chattam</em>; The prest-men are put on board, and many <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of the Army: the <em>Dutch</em> having added sixty new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> to their Fleet, so you see what readiness the Fleets are in on both sides; and if a Peace should not be concluded, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> likely that the greatest <reg orig="blowe">blow</reg> would be struck that hath been yet, but it is thought there is not any question now of a <reg orig="ful">full</reg> agreement.</p>

<p>Four <em>Dutch</em> ships were lately sunk by storm <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Enchusen</em>. An <em>English</em> Prize called, The <em>Bee-hive</em> is lately carried into the <em>Texel</em>, she is valued to be worth 3000 li. sterling. The Cantons of <em>Switzerland</em> have renewed their League with <em>France</em>.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday. <em>March 9.</em></head> 

<p>On <em>Tuesday</em> last one <em>John Fearn</em> stood in the Pillory <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to the Exchange for Perjury, as he confessed himself at the Sessions House in the <em>Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em>; for which he had five pound brought him by one <em>John Bishop</em> who told him that he brought him the said money from <em>William Allot</em>, who in the name of <em>John Evans</em> had commenced a Suit against one <em>Francis Turner</em>, and the said <em>Fearn</em> being produced as a Witness<pb n="5" /> against him in the behalf of the Plaintiff, for the lucre of the money, did most wretchedly forswear himself: which he having confessed as above said, he was sentenced on <em>Tuesday</em> last to stand in the Pillory from nine of the clock in the morning till one in the afternoon, which accordingly was done.</p>

<p>Several Complaints were this day made of the like forgeries, and Instructions passed to make <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg> in this Nature more exemplar for the time to come. Letters this day make mention of several Robberies committed, and 5 <reg orig="Highway-men">Highwaymen</reg> taken in one <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg> on the borders of <em>Northamptonshire</em>.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> doth still continue a prisoner in <em>Antwerp</em>, where he is used very magnificently; it being the nobleness of the <em>Spaniard</em> to use their prisoners with more humanity than other Nations are accustomed to do.</p>

<p>It is said that since the Imprisonment of the said Duke, several sums of his money have been discovered. The Jewels that were found about his daughter, which the young Lady did wear about her, though many of them were not laid open to <reg orig="publick">public</reg> view are valued at one hundred thousand pound.</p>

<p>Several complaints have been made, that some differing in judgement in points of Religion from others, have affronted them in their Pulpits to the scandal of Religion, whereupon there is something under consideration for a severe punishment to be inflicted impartially on all whatsoever who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> disturb the Congregation in their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> worship of God.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, March 10.</head>

<p>Another part of S: <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg> Church falling down this week, and increasing the ruins of the former, his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> was informed of it, and by order from him the Council took it into consideration to take the Isles of the Church down, but nothing was concluded therein.</p>

<p>It was this day advertised by Letters from the North, that the <em>Dutch</em> Freebooters have taken six or seven <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels which came from <em>Sunderland</em>, and caused another to run<pb n="6" /> ashore <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Hartlepool</em>. A <em>Freebooter</em> of <em>Enchuisen</em> hath lately retaken the <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ship called The <em>Chestnut tree of Amsterdam</em>, which had been taken by our ships not far from the <em>Ulie</em>. There is arrived at the <em>Ulie</em> a fleet of 140 sail, which came from the <em>Eastlands</em>, a great part whereof are come to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and the rest to several other Ports in that Country, their lading is chiefly Corn, and materials for setting forth of ships.</p>

<p>By Letters from <em>Deal</em> it was advertised, that on Thursday last another Fleet of Merchants belonging to the <em>Dutch</em>, consisting of about one hundred and fifty sail did steer Westwards, they sailed close by the Coast of <em>France</em>, and had a fair wind, which was the reason that our Fleet lying at <em>Saint Ellens point</em>, could not so suddenly discover them, nor easily overtake them. This <em>Dutch</em> fleet had a fear they should be <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> in their passage, they had therefore a strong Convoy with them consisting of 60 Men of War, but having brought them beyond the danger which they feared, a great part of them returned the same way they came, the others did go along with the fleet, being bound to several Ports lying on the Western Seas. In the mean time we make great preparations for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> our <reg orig="summers">summer's</reg> Fleet, 1000 private soldiers, besides seamen, were on <em>Monday</em> last drawn out of the 4 Regiments about <em>London</em>, and sent on ship <reg orig="bord">board</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday, March 12.</em></head>

<p>It was yesterday also by Letters advertised, that Gen <em>Middleton</em> is come again to <em>Scotland</em> with two Men of War, the greatest part of their lading was Arms, and Ammunition, some Corn, and some say some <reg orig="quantety">quantity</reg> of money, he landed at <em>Uny</em> in <em>Southerland</em>, there came with him,</p>

<p>Sir <em>George Monro</em> the <reg orig="yonger">younger</reg>. Major Gen: <em>Dyel</em>.</p>
<p><em>Thomas Dyell</em>. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> Gordon.</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Nappeir</em>. <em>Lodowick Drumland</em>.</p>

<p>The rest are said to be Soldiers of Fortune, and not any one man of Fortune amongst them, the Letters from <em>Holland</em> do <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> them to be three hundred in number, but the Letters from <em>Scotland</em> do not <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> them to be so many, they were no sooner landed, but as if they were peradvertised<pb n="7" /> of the necessities of their Countrymen, they <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> dispatched fifty <reg orig="pick'd">picked</reg> men under the command of Major Gen: <em>Dyel</em>, with ten Horse load of Arms, the rest they carried along with them, intending to meet with <em>Glencarn</em> in the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Murray</em>, where they are to have their Rendezvous.</p>

<p>The Lord Protector hath issued forth Orders that all Officers concerned <reg orig="therin">therein</reg>, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> repair to their charges in <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg></em>, March 13</head>

<p>The Commissioners chosen out of the Council of the Ld: Protector, did this Day meet again on the Articles of Agreement with the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors, which it is hoped will suddenly come to a good conclusion.</p>

<p>The Names of our Commissioners are,</p>

<p><em>Philip</em> Lord <em>Lile</em>. <em>John Laurence</em> Esquire.</p>
<p>Major General <em>Lambert</em>. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>. <em>George Montague</em>.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>. <em>Walter Strickland</em> Esquire.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that since the arrival of Gen: <em>Middleton</em> the <em>Highlanders</em> do grow numerous; at the Rendezvous in <em><reg orig="Murry-land">Murrayland</reg></em> the Arms were distributed, some monies received, &amp; Letters read from their titular King, promising his assistance to the uttermost of his power, at which some signs of great joy were made, which were suddenly cooled by the tidings of the approach of our Army, of which more in the next.</p>

<p>The titular King of <em>Scots</em> of his own accord did choose to go into <em>Germany</em>, it being a Journey long time in his intention The Qu: of <em>Bohemia</em> is going to <em>Frankendale</em> which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place and of great frequentation, it being the middle way between <em>Worms</em>, and <em>Spiers</em>, where she will do the best she can to entertain him; I have heard of Letters which affirm that the titular King of <em>Scots</em> is no way discouraged at his removal out of <em>France</em>, so familiar are his misfortunes with him.</p>

<p>Great was the joy the other day at <em>Wollidg</em>, at the <reg orig="lanching">launching</reg> forth of the new <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> which carrieth 60 guns, and was then <reg orig="christned">christened</reg> <em>Merston moor</em>. There is building another great ship for War, which is as broad, and longer <reg orig="then">than</reg> the <em><reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg></em>. That which this week is most remarkable is:</p>

<p><i>&#x261e; The landing of Gen: <em>Middleton</em> in <em>Scotland</em> with two ships laden with Arms, some monies, 300 Soldiers and the Names of the Commanders, their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> increasing, and their <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Letters read at the general Rendezvous. The approach of the English Army to <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> them. The Results of the Treaty with the <em>Dutch</em>, and the Names of our Commissioners chosen to conclude the Union. Some prizes taken by the <em>Dutch</em>. 140 of their Merchants come home from the East and 140 gone to the West with a Convoy of 60 Men of War. The <em>English</em> <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth, and the Debates of the Council of State for the taking <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em>.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>