<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="Wintell200">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 200</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 17. to <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 24. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January 17.</head> 

<p>The expectations of the discontented Party in this Nation are much disappointed, for they hoped there would be new troubles, and alterations in the Army, and elsewhere, but it hath pleased God that all things do appear more <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>, and like a fair morning do promise a clear, and an unclouded day.</p>

<p>The Officers of several Regiments, and in several Garrisons are very unanimous in signing the <reg orig="Addresse">Address</reg> to the Lord Protector, which is in these words.</p>

<p>Having for many years past been led under your Conduct, through many difficult Services, <reg orig="wherin">wherein</reg> through the blessing of God upon the <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg>, and endeavours of your Highness, we have in some measure been Instrumental in our places to free the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> from enemies. So we cannot but above <reg orig="al">all</reg> worldly things, most earnestly desire to see these Nations, after all the shakings which hath been in the <reg orig="midsts">midst</reg> of us, set up upon <reg orig="its">its'</reg> true, and proper Basis and <pb n="1" />Foundation, and thereby brought into a <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of rest and safety. The <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards Your Highness, and the whole Nation at this time, when it pleased God to give us hopes of establishment, by inclining you to accept of the Government, and Protection of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the People, both as men and Christians (the true end whereupon the great <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> hath been stated) will through the mercy of God be assured: We <reg orig="judg">judge</reg> it highly incumbent upon us to make our humble address unto you, and to declare that we shall not only be obedient unto you, in the performance of your great Trust; but in other places most faithfully, and diligently to the hazard of our lives, and whatsoever is near and dear unto us, be serviceable to you in the station God hath placed you against all opposition: Not doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; So you will to the utmost of your power and endeavours lay forth your self for the glory of God, and the good of this People, amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of Faith; over whom, we shall therefore further take his boldness most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> Your Highness more especially to spread the wing of your protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, which you continuing to do. We are confident their Father which is in Heaven, will be unto you a Buckler, and a Shield, and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>

<p><i>Your Highness most humble, and faithful Servants.</i></p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Jan: 18.</head>

<p>I made mention in my last that General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> was in the <em>Swiftsure</em> which ship, though long in repairing, is now one of the bravest Vessels that ploughs the Seas. A <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of War was there lately called, concerning the Prize-money due unto Seamen, and Soldiers who have served at Sea in this last <reg orig="years">year's</reg> expedition, and it was ordered and Declared.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>First that all Seamen and Soldiers that have served in the Fleet in the three last Engagements against the <em>Dutch</em>, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> list themselves aboard any of the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> ships, at or before the last of <em>March</em> next, shall have for their respective shares of Prizes, twenty shillings.</p>

<p>2. That such as have been in two of the said Engagements <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have thirteen shillings four pence.</p>

<p>3 That those who served only in one of the said Engagements, shall have six shillings eight pence.</p>

<p>4 That all such Seamen and Soldiers as have been disabled by sickness, or wounds received in the Service: As also the Widows of any such Seamen or <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, slain in any of the said Engagements, shall have paid unto them their full shares of Prize money, <em>viz</em>: twenty shillings.</p>

<p>5 That such of the Soldiers that are now again entertained in the Army (having Tickets for their Prize money) do produce unto the said Commissioners a Certificate under the hand of the Captain, under which they now serve: As also a copy of the late Muster-<reg orig="Rol">Roll</reg> of the Companies to which they respectively belong, or in default thereof, a Certificate under the hand of the Mustermaster, testifying their being in the service; whereupon Order <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be given for payment of the shares of Prizes due unto them.</p>

<p><em>John Dinbrow, George <reg orig="Monck">Monk</reg>, Robert Bake, Vin: Gookin, John Stone, John Clerk, Robert Blackborne</em> Secret:</p>

<p>It was further advertised from General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em>, that he hath examined some <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> ships which came into the River of <em>Thames</em> to find market for Deals, Pitch, Tar, Iron, Steel and other Commodities, these ships are three in number.</p>

<p>1. The <em>Golden Mawken</em> of <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, a ship <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with large Deals, Mats, Iron, Pith and Tar, of which <em>Hans Renson</em> is Master, which said ship is gone into <em>Portsmouth</em> to find market, she came in voluntarily into the Road.</p>

<p>2. The <em>Katherine</em> of <em>Gottenburgh</em>, having 18 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of Tar, 1200 great Deals, 11 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> of Iron, 100 great <reg orig="Sparrs">Spars</reg>, going into <em>Portsmouth</em> to find market, she came into the Road voluntarily<pb n="3" />, commanded by <em>John Jorgorson</em> the Master.</p>

<p>3. The ship called the <em>St: John</em> of <em>Lubeck</em>, having 7500 deals, and some Pipe staves, of which <em>Joachim Nickmeger</em> is Master, she is sent into <em>Portsmouth</em> to find Market, she came into the Road voluntarily.</p>

<p>The St: <em>John</em> of <em>Dantzig</em>, a ship having in her 800 Pipe staves, about 10000 li. weight of Hemp, 12 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of Pitch, and 2 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> of Tar, 600l. weight of Lead, 6000l. weight of Iron, 5000l. weight of Steel, which ship was bound for <em>Nantz</em> in <em>France</em>, (as was pretended, <em>George Vosse</em> is Master of her) which ship is at present in the Road of <em>Portsmouth</em>, desirous of demission rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> sale, she was met with at Sea, and there taken and sent in by the <em>Adventure</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Jan: 19</head>

<p>The sad accident which <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> lately at <em>Charenton</em>, some four miles from <em>Paris</em> down the River, was again this Day confirmed by several Letters from <em>France</em>, which was that divers Protestants, and some of great and eminent quality, having been at Church at <em>Charington</em>, the exercise of the Protestant religion being not permitted in the City of <em>Paris</em>, and not <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> that place, on their return to <em>Paris</em> by water, they were no sooner in the Boat, but the Mill going, the violence of the stream did force them under the Mill, and the boat breaking, threescore of them were drowned, amongst whom were the Sons of the <em>Miramnaut</em>, and many others of Quality.</p>

<p>There is great talk in <em>France</em>, that the Son of the Emperor of <em>Germany</em> who is called King of the <em>Romans</em>, shall marry the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is for certain leaving <em>France</em>, and it is thought that he will go to <em>Germany</em>, to give thanks for, and to receive the annual contribution which the Princes do allow him. It is spoken in <em>France</em>, that the Peace between the two <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> is concluded, and <em>Monsieur Borsel</em> the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassador in <em>France</em>, hath lately received Letters from <em>Holland</em> which do assure him of it.</p>

<p>It is certified by Letters from <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, that they have<pb n="4" /> been advertised from <em>Aberdeen</em>, that seventeen <em>Dutch</em> ships are arrived in the North, and hath bought with them two hundred Horse, great store of Arms, and fifteen hundred <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>.</p>

<p>I must retract from an Error heretofore committed, when I gave unto you, that <em>Lodowick</em> the late Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> had left no Brother behind him. It is since informed that the Lord Marquis his Father had four Sons, and the youngest of them, <em>Charles</em> is yet alive, and Inherits the titles, and Possessions of his Father. It is also advertised, that he, and the young Earl of <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em> are gone unto the Enemy, who make their spoils, and devastations wheresoever they do come.</p>

<p>I am desired to give notice, that if any persons concerned in the Probate of <reg orig="Wils">Wills</reg>, and Administration, do send for Commissions, they must return the same with speed, from time to time, to the Office at Star-chamber in <em>Westminster</em>, because the power of the Court doth expire the first of April next.</p>

<p>Some ships have been brought into the West of <em>England</em>; the <em>Hector</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> took one which had in her three thousand cheeses, the ship belongeth to <em>Amsterdam</em>.</p>

<p>A private Man of War hath also brought in a ship of <em>Rotterdam</em>, laden with Fish and Cheeses. A squadron of our fleet plying up and down at Lands end, the <em><reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg></em> are very quiet.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, January 20.</head>

<p>This day was the <reg orig="Joal">Gaol</reg> delivery at <em>Newgate</em>, 8 were hanged, 6 men, and 2 women, two of them for ravishing young <reg orig="Girles">Girls</reg>, the rest for Robbery One of the Women was hanged for bewitching two children, and the Mother of them. The Woman was bewitched to an <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> <reg orig="costivenes">costiveness</reg> in her body and repairing to a Doctor, he told her that she was bewitched, but if his <reg orig="physick">physique</reg> wrought with her, it might peradventure cure her, he directed her to make a cake, and to knead it with her own water, and to eat it, using a form of words, which he gave her in writing. This <reg orig="councel">counsel</reg> being followed, she became as it were distracted and in a strange manner, <reg orig="entring">entering</reg> into the <reg orig="Witches">Witch's</reg> House, she demanded her Picture, and the pictures of her <pb n="5" />children, which she carried home, and burned, but she did thrust a hot iron into the <reg orig="brest">breast</reg> of her own picture, and presently afterwards she felt herself went orderly to stool, when she was bewitched, she had also a grievous pain in her side, and back, and she found that in those places of her Body where she was pained, the pictures also had holes <reg orig="peirced">pierced</reg> in it. The Woman that was bewitched brought this picture, and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> it to the Justices on the Bench.</p>

<p>She would have received the Sacrament with a gathered Church, but it being <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg>, because she was reputed to have bewitched such a Woman, and her children, she <reg orig="denyed">denied</reg> the fact, and appealed to her God for her <reg orig="innocense">innocence</reg>; being asked who was her God, she said the God of the World, and wished she might never speak if it were not false, and desired that her God would show some eminent judgment on her if it were true, whereupon she presently was struck lame, and dumb, and so continued <reg orig="til">till</reg> the Rope deprived her of all possibility of speaking again.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, January 21.</head>

<p>The <reg orig="tryall">trial</reg> of the Brother of the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador is put off <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the next Sessions.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em> that the <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg> there are generally in a great distraction concerning the <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> to be raised by the <em>Highlanders</em>. Those in Commission for the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> requiring them (as great reason there is for it) not to be assisting to the <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> directly or indirectly, as they would not be deemed <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Enemies, and proceeded against as such to the utmost extremity. <em>Glencarn</em> on the other side who <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> himself Commander in Chief of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>, requires them to give obedience to his Orders, or else they shall suffer as disloyal Subjects, and professed Enemies to the advancement of his affairs. In these commands full of danger, and contrariety, the amazed People know not what to do, but receiving counsel from the danger, they comply with the English, who are the stronger part,<pb n="6" /> though their hearts are with the weaker.</p>

<p>However it is affirmed that the <em>Highlanders</em> do carry such an influence on them, that they do increase in their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, their musters being made more numerous by the <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of the Marquis of <em>Huntley</em>, and the Marquis of <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em>. The <em>Highlanders</em> fall often down in the <em>Lowlands</em>, after their accustomed manner, and having <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> the Countries, return with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary speed, for fear of being circumvented.</p>

<p>It is certified by Letters from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, that ten of our Merchants, laden with commodities from the <em>East-Indies</em>, are come safely to <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em>, five of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> are there, as a Convoy to them. The eight <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> commanded to ply about the Lands end, and to guard the Channel, are come in again, another part are sent out to be upon Duty in their places, General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> is still riding at <em><reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg> point</em>, not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>.</p>

<p>There hath been a conflict betwixt the Inhabitants of the <reg orig="Bishoprick">Bishopric</reg> of <em>Leige</em>, and the Forces of <em>Conde</em>, and <em>Lorraign</em>, who have possessed themselves of two <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Towns, and have Quartered themselves therein.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Jan: 23.</head>

<p>This morning it was advertised again, that the King of <em>France</em> hath for the present made a stop of all <em>English</em> ships in the <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg> of <em>France</em>. The titular King of <em>England</em> is for certain as yet in <em>France</em>, whatsoever is whispered to the contrary. Prince <em>Rupert</em> hath been so fortunate this Christmas at play, that he hath won twelve thousand Crowns of some of the Lords of that Kingdom.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>It is most certain that some Gentlemen who belong to the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> have wrote to their Wives in <em>England</em>, to make their peace for them with his Highness, having now lost all hopes of preferment by their young Master, and yet (they say) they felt there no want, but of the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg> only of their Native Country, and of their Companies.</p>

<p>Every street in this City, and the Exchange it self is full of the News of Peace with <em>Holland</em>, nay some are so bold, they will tell you what are the very Articles, but there is nothing certain of it. But on the contrary, General <em>Blake</em> who hath the <reg orig="Seamens">Seamen's</reg> hearts, and lost his blood with them is gone down to <em>Portsmouth</em>, and will be in a <reg orig="readines">readiness</reg> to put forth to Sea.</p>

<p>It is said that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> did ride in great magnificence about a mile from her Court, to give a meeting to our English Ambassador but this I have received from the tradition only of report.</p>

<p>It is most certain that some Tories amongst the Irish have broken forth again, and do much mischief. Being demanded some <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> a go, to deliver up their fire-arms, they murmured themselves into a conspiracy, being resolved to lay down their arms, and their lives together.</p>

<p>An unhappy accident lately fell out in the <em>Isle of Ely</em>; Some Gentlemen distasting the Drink, of the Inn, sent to <em>Wisbitch</em> for Wine. Another company of Gentlemen in the said Inn understanding it, desired to <reg orig="pertake">partake</reg> of their Wine, whereupon a Bottle was sent, but some sinister interpretation being given to it, a curious desire possessed one of the Gentlemen that sent for the Wine, to see who were those that desired it at the Inn, whereupon he took one of his Friends with him. Being come together, they fell from words to blows, the candle being struck out, one Mr: <em>Mallory</em> was killed, which was presumed to be done by one Mr: <em>Dymonds</em> who is fled, which adds to the <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>, and the Gentlemen upon his Death did charge the said Mr: <em>Dymonds</em> with it. The other is in durance for the Fact.</p>

<p>A Declaration came forth to Day, that it shall be treason for any man to speak, or write against the Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable is:</head>

<p><i>The stopping of all <em>English</em> ships in the Ports of <em>France</em>. The Peace with <em>Holland</em> uncertain; and General <em>Blake</em> for certain putting forth to Sea. The report of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> in her own person meeting the <em>English</em> Ambassador in great magnificence. The Declaration of General <em><reg orig="Pen">Penn</reg></em> to the Seamen and Soldiers. The <em><reg orig="Highlanders">Highlander's</reg></em> new <reg orig="plundring">plundering</reg>, and increasing their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> by the <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of the Marquis of <em>Huntley</em>, and the Earl of <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em>. And much mischief done in <em>Ireland</em> by the <reg orig="stragling">straggling</reg> <em>Tories</em>. Treason for any to speak or write against the Lord Protector.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>