<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell147#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 147#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 13. to <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 20. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 13.</head>

<p>I will begin where I last left off, which was at the Dissolution of the late Parliament. You are to understand that a great part of them having at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> resigned that power which they received of him. The <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> had a meeting with his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, where having expressed himself with that zeal, and fluency which are natural in him, some things were transacted both here, and afterwards at the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State, for the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of the Government of this Nation, of which more in the passages of the <em>Friday</em> following.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State.</i></head>

<p>The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State taking notice of the tumultuous, and barbarous <unclear>acting</unclear> at the <em>New Exchange</em> in the Strand in the County of <em>Middlesex</em> upon the 21 and 22 of November last past. The same being accompanied with the drawing of Swords, discharging of Pistols, and such other High Misdemeanours as are scarce to be <reg orig="parallel'd">paralleled</reg> by the actings of any <pb n="1" />persons living under the protection of a <reg orig="civill">civil</reg> Government; and which, in the effects thereof, produced not only a very great and notorious violation of the <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Peace, but also the murdering of one, and the assaulting, wounding, and affrighting of many other of the People of this Nation, pursuing their ordinary callings, and occasion: And for as much as the said <em>Exchange</em> is a place of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Resort, and Trade, The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> have therefore thought it necessary hereby to declare their resentment of those proceedings, and their just displeasure against the same. And as they intend vigorously to prosecute the offenders, so to the intent the like evils may be better prevented in time to come, they do hereby strictly require and charge; That no person or persons of what quality soever, do presume at the said <em>Exchange</em>, or any other like <reg orig="publick">public</reg> place, to occasion, encourage, or abet, any tumultuous meetings, or hazard a breach of the Civil Peace, by drawing there, or in any such place, any sword, or other weapon, discharging, presenting, or bearing any Gun, or Pistol, or firing of powder in <reg orig="Granadoes">Grenades</reg>, or in any otherwise whatsoever. Of which command, it will be expected, That all Persons whatsoever, take notice, and demean themselves accordingly upon peril of being reputed, and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> as disturbers of <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> peace; whereof a strict account shall be taken. And all Justices of the Peace, and other <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers, are required carefully to perform their duties in this behalf; as also to use their utmost endeavours, to prevent and refrain all immodest, and <reg orig="unhandsom">unhandsome</reg> <reg orig="demeanors">demeanours</reg> of such as shall resort to the said <em>Exchange</em>, that so no just cause of offence may be given to sober minds, nor any thing there acted <reg orig="dishonorable">dishonourable</reg> to Religion, or the Nation. <em>John Thurloe</em>, Sec.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Names of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State</i></head>

<!-- Following 31 paras represents a list of names laid out in two columns: columns separated by a black line, transcribed going across the line and then down through the lines-->
<p>The Lord <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>.</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>William Sydenham</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Philip Jones</em></p>
<p>Major Gen: <em><reg orig="Desborow">Desborough</reg></em></p>
<p>Sir <em>Charles Woolseley</em> </p>
<p><em>Walter Strickland</em> Esq;</p>
<p>Alderman <em>Tichborn</em></p>
<p><em>Henry Laurence</em> Esq;</p>
<p>Sir <em>Anthony Ashley Cooper</em> <pb n="2" />Baronet.</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> </p>
<p><em>John Carew</em> Esq;</p>
<p>Doctor <em>Jonathan Goddard</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Edward Montague</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>William Brownlow</em></p>
<p>Major General <em>Harrison</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Nathaniel Barton</em></p>
<p>Lord Viscount <em>Lisle</em></p>
<p><em>George</em> <em>Lord Eure</em></p>
<p><em>Richard Major</em> Esq;</p>
<p><em>John Stone</em> Esq.</p>
<p><em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Howard</em> Esq.</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>George Fleetwood</em></p>
<p>Col: <em>Anthony Rous</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>John James</em></p>
<p>Sir <em>William Roberts</em></p>
<p><em>John Anlab</em>, Esq</p>
<p><em>John Sadler</em> Esq;</p>
<p><em>Jervas Bennet</em>, Esq.</p>
<p>Sir <em>Robert King</em> Knight</p>
<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Bingham</em>.</p>

<p><em>Glencarn</em> hath sent out his Warrants as followeth.</p>

<p><em>Gentlemen</em>:</p>
																
<p>You are hereby required to deliver unto me as much good <em>Scottish</em> <reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg> as will <reg orig="cloath">clothe</reg> 200 Foot Soldiers, together with as much <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> and <reg orig="Shooes">Shoes</reg>, as will furnish the same number, each of them two shirts, and a pair of <reg orig="Shooes">Shoes</reg>, or two thousand pound of <em>Scottish</em> money, between this and the 2 Day of <em>December</em> next. If this you do perform accordingly, in regard to the season of the year, I do hereby promise you protection from any further trouble; but if ye delay to give obedience to this, you may expect I will exact this by force; Wherein if you suffer more prejudice, I am not to be blamed. So expecting your obedience to this, as you will answer it at your peril.</p> 

<p><i>Given under my hand at <em>Balloch</em> 7 Novemb: 1653</i></p>

<p>GLENCARNE.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wedenesday</em>; Decemb: 14</head>

<p>It was certified by Letters from <em>Dunkirk</em>, that several ships that were conceived to be Prizes, and were upon that account detained in <em>England</em>, are arrived at <em>Dunkirk</em>, others are expected to come into that Haven every day from <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, but it is feared by the Merchants at <em>Dunkirk</em> that they will meet with the same fortune which most of the rest do, who come through the Channel.</p>

<p>The Soldiers who in their stations do keep by order the <pb n="3" />night Guards at <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em>, do constantly affirm, that lately they have seen by night a great flame in the <reg orig="ayr">air</reg>, as if the Suburbs of that City had been all in a flame. They perceived at the last that the fire removed Southwards, and took its course towards <em>England</em>. Of this several men have declared their several opinions, every one as their fancy do suggest unto them.</p>

<p>But to cry upon their own inclinations, the discontented in <em>Scotland</em> do give forth, that not only <em>Middleton</em> is come with a vast number of Arms, but that the titular Duke of <em>York</em> is designed for that place from <em>France</em> and that he brings with him a choice number of Commanders who heretofore followed his <reg orig="Brothers">Brother's</reg> Fortunes, and that the <em>Irish</em> who fell off from the <em>Spaniards</em>, and came to the King of <em>France</em>, are all <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> in this expedition. Some are so inconsiderate to affirm that the <em>Lorraigners</em> having no certain <unclear>seat</unclear>, will take up their habitations among the <em>Highlanders</em>, and if they can amongst the <em>Lowlanders</em>. Others have designed Quarters for the Prince of <unclear><em><reg orig="Condies">Condie's</reg></em></unclear> Army in <em>Ireland</em>, thinking the <em>Irish</em> to be an apt Nation to mingle with so unruly a People. The titular King of <em>Scotland</em> (according to their device) is to plant himself in <em>England</em>, when <em>France</em> shall shake hands with <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em>, and the Emperor, and the German Princes shall all combine to his assistance, but to this, (whatsoever discourse may be to the contrary) there is not any probability.</p>

<p>It was advertised this morning by Letters from <em>Plymouth</em>, that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> had taken a <em>Dutch</em> Merchant of three hundred <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Sack, and Sugar, and that some other of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> who came lately from <em>Portsmouth</em>, have seized on two other gallant Ships who pretend to be <em>Hamburgers</em>.</p>

<p>The last news from the Sound of <em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg></em> is sad, which is that the <em>Sussex</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a gallant ship, was blown up by her own Gunpowder, which accidentally did take fire. A lamentable sight it was to see our men leaping from one <reg orig="merciles">merciless</reg> Element into another, and a <unclear><!--could be "wall"--><reg orig="wast">waste</reg></unclear> of fire in the midst of water.</p>

<p>It was advertised from <em>Flushing</em>, that Captain <em>Bunk</em> is come <pb n="4" />thither with the <em>Dutch</em> that were prisoners in <em>England</em>, most of them are sick. A private Man of War hath brought into that <reg orig="Harbor">Harbour</reg> two prizes, the one laden with Coals from <em>Newcastle</em>, and the other laden with Salt.</p>

<p>The Treaty with the three <em>Dutch</em> Deputies is doubtfully delivered, some saying that there are great probabilities for a Peace, others affirming that there are no great hopes. What will be done betwixt these two Nations, whose eyes no hands but their own could scratch forth, <reg orig="wil">will</reg> now suddenly appear.</p>

<p>The Agent for the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> hath had his last Audience at <em>Denmark</em>, and though he hath made great Importunities, yet the King of <em>Denmark</em> having sent a small present to him as a token of Acknowledgement, hath declared a great inability to relieve him according to his expectation during these troubles that threaten him from <em>England</em> on the one side, and from <em>Sweden</em> on the other.</p>

<p>I do find by the best Intelligence that I have, that the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> is going from <em>France</em> into <em>Germany</em>. Some say that his expedition will be with all speed, others that it will be deferred until the middle of <em>March</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised that one deputed from the King of <em>France</em> came to <em>Dantzick</em>, where he had audience before the Senate, to whom he <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> his Commission to arrest all <em>English</em> Merchants and their Goods in the <reg orig="reprizal">reprisal</reg> of fourteen Nuns, who intending from <em>France</em> to <em>Poland</em> were taken by the English at Sea. The Senate of <em>Dantzick</em> hath taken this into consideration.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Decemb: 15.</head>

<p>By letters from <em>Scotland</em> it is advertised that the <em>Highlanders</em> being grown more numerous, do continue still their <reg orig="plundrings">plunderings</reg> in the <em>Lowlands</em>. The Earl <em>Atholl</em> is returned into his own Country, with 80 Horse to the Castle of <em><reg orig="Blayr">Blair</reg></em>, that he might raise his <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> with greater liberty. His to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horse in <em>Perthshire</em>, and the whole Foot thereof, The Lord <em>Kinoube</em> is to raise a Regiment in <pb n="5" /><unclear><em>Barchlausts</em></unclear>, and <em>Merns</em>, and <em>Couper</em> in <em>Angus</em>, <em>Glengary</em> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> a Regiment of Horse out of <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, <em>Southerland</em>, <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> and <em>Murray</em>, and to be Commander in chief of the Foot <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> there. <em>Kenmore</em> is designed to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> the Horses in the <reg orig="Shiere">Shire</reg> of <em>Aberdeen</em>, and <em>Blakader</em> of <em><unclear><!--nearly illegible: best guess-->Tulliallen</unclear></em> is to <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg> in a part of the Shire of <em>Fife</em>. Sir <em>Mungo Murray</em> is to make his <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> in the Country next to <em>Stirling</em>. This is the design, which being discovered, is in a fair way to be prevented.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Decemb: 16.</head>

<p>I made mention that the Parliament having resigned their power to his Excellency from whom they received it, his Excellence called a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of Officers, where advice was taken with some other persons of Eminence, how the great <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> of Governing the three nations should be born. And after three <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> <reg orig="Counsell">Counsel</reg> and prayers unto God to direct the <reg orig="counsel">council</reg>, it was resolved that a <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of able persons should be named, consisting of one and twenty, and that the Lord General should be chosen <em>PROTECTOR</em> of the three Nations. And this afternoon about one of the clock his Excellence came from <em><reg orig="white-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> to <em>Westminster</em>, to the Court of <em>Chancery</em>. There were present the Ld. Commissioners for the great Seal, the Barons of the Exchequer, and Judges in their Robes. After them followed the <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, after them the Lord Mayor, the Aldermen, and Recorder of the City of <em>London</em> in their scarlet Gowns. Then came his Excellence <reg orig="apparel'd">apparelled</reg> in black, without any formality of Robes at all, he was attended with many chief Officers of the Army, and the Chair of state <pb n="6" />being set in the Court of <em>Chancery</em>, he stood on the left hand thereof uncovered, till a large writing in parchment, in the nature of an Oath was read, which also expressed the power with which his Excellence was invested. His Excellence having subscribed to it in the face of the Court, he immediately sat down covered in the said Chair, the Lord Commissioners, and every one standing bare. The Lord Commissioners delivered him up the Great Seal, and the Lord Mayor his Sword, and Cap of Maintenance, which were returned to them again. The Court then rose, and his Excellence returned to <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the Lord Mayor uncovered carrying the Sword before the PROTECTOR all the way. Being come to <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, a Sermon was made by Mr. <em><unclear>Lockyer</unclear></em> one of the Chaplains of the PROTECTOR. As the PROTECTOR came from <em>Westminster</em>, the Soldiers in <em>Westminster</em> Hall, and the <reg orig="Pallace-yard">Palace yard</reg> made acclamations of joy; and the great Guns afterwards did go off at the Tower, and some great ships that lay not far from thence.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb: 17</head>

<p>This week were the sessions in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayly">Bailey</reg></em>, and this day and yesterday the trial of the Brother to the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador was expected, but by reason of this, the further prosecution of the Court of Justice were referred <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the <em>Monday</em> following.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Decemb 19.</head>

<p>This morning came forth from this Proclamation from the Council of State.</p>

<p>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their Powers and Authorities, The Government of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, by a <em>LORD PROTECTOR</em>, and successive <pb n="7" />Triennial Parliaments, is now established; And Whereas <em>OLIVER <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg></em>, Captain General of all the Forces of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, is declared <em>Lord Protector</em> of the Nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make publication of the <reg orig="Premisses">Premises</reg>, and strictly to Charge and Command all, and every person and persons, of what Quality and Condition soever, in any of the said three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established, and all Sheriffs, Majors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="Publick">Public</reg> Ministers, and Officers, whom this may concern, are required to cause this <em>PROCLAMATION</em> to be forthwith published in their respective Counties, Cities, Corporations and Market Towns, To the end none may have Cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</p>

<p><i>Given at <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> this 16 day of December, 1653.</i></p>

<p>This day with sound of Trumpets, and great solemnity, His Excellence was Proclaimed <em>PROTECTOR</em> of the three Nations in the words above-mentioned by a <reg orig="Serjeant">Sergeant</reg> of Arms at the <em>Exchange</em> in <em>London</em>, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and common <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> being present, and in several other places of the City of <em>London</em>, and in <em>Westminster</em>.</p>

<p>The Quarter Sessions in the <em>Old <reg orig="Bayly">Bailey</reg></em> are adjourned till after <em>Christmas</em>. The Letters this Day make mention of <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Prizes taken. Our fleet is yet on the <em>Downs</em>.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable, is:</head>

<p><i>The solemn form, and manner of making his Excellence <em>PROTECTOR</em> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, in the Court of <em>Chancery</em> in <em>Westminster Hall</em>, the Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal, the Barons of the <em>Exchequer</em>, and the Judges, the Lord Mayor, the Aldermen, and common <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> of the City of <em>London</em> being present. The Lord Mayor carrying the Sword bareheaded before the <em>PROTECTOR</em> from <em>Westminster</em> to <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>. The solemn form of Proclaiming his Excellence <em>PROTECTOR</em> in the Cities of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>. The last news from <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> at Sea, <reg orig="Severall">Several</reg> more Prizes taken; and the Quarter Sessions in the <em>Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg></em> adjourned till after <em>Christmas</em>. The <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> of a new <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State.</i></p>
 
<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>