<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell328">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 328</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, April 18. to <em>Tuesday</em>, April 25. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 18.</head>

<p>Whiles some are striving for honour, and <reg orig="preheminence">pre-eminence</reg>, and others to confirm their kingdoms to them, the young Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath given an excellent Example of a most invincible virtue; She doth overcome her Sex in the Constancy of her Temper, and in the election of a single life. She doth overcome most Kings in <reg orig="Knowledg">Knowledge</reg>, Power, and magnificence, but in Resigning her <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Authority at so young a Age, she doth overcome the condition of Mortality, and <reg orig="shews">shows</reg> <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> most worthy of that incomprehensible Crown, to which only she aspires. The excellence of her Spirit may be easily discovered in her Letter to <em>Monsieur Chanute</em>, in which, though ill enough translated, you may read many admirable marks of the innocence, and height of her confidence; And this Letter no doubt was penned by her own hand, as by the stile, and flourish of it all along, may easily appear to any knowing Spirit.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>It is said that <em>Carolus Ludovieus Aldolphus</em>, to whom the Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> doth resign the Crown, is to marry with the Princess Royal, <reg orig="Widdow">Widow</reg> of the late Prince of <em>Orange</em>, but you may look upon this as a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> Report, as also that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath a resolution to go <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> to the <em>Hague</em>, to advance the Marriage, which is another story of the same Complexion, with the former.</p>

<p>For the last Letters from thence do advertise, that she intends to reside in the Castle of <em>Stetin</em>, which is making ready for her, and that the Lands which her Father did win by the Sword in <em>Pomerania</em> shall be some part of her maintenance, and that she hath made choice of <em>Upsal, Stetin</em>, and <em>Stockholm</em>, for the chief places of her Residence, as the seasons of the year shall invite her to them. Some are of opinion that she will Marry <em>Ludovicus Adolphus</em> when that is done, but there appears no great probability for it, in regard she so often hath refused that marriage, by reason of the proximity of their <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>.</p>

<p>The Intelligence from <em>Holland</em>, as well as the Letters from <em>Sweden</em> do confirm this; That the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> hath done this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> most remarkable service, and hath been of greater influence for making the <em>Dutch</em> to understand their own <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> by a well grounded Peace, <reg orig="then">than</reg> if we had landed an Army of twelve thousand men in <em>Holland</em>. The Qu: of <em>Sweden</em> doth seem <reg orig="every day">everyday</reg> to be more retired <reg orig="then">than</reg> other, and the old Chancellor of <em>Sweden</em> being much indisposed in his health, Orders are given to Count <em>Henry</em>, his second Son, to treat with our Ambassador.</p>

<p>Two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and the <em>Middleborough</em> being abroad to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg> the Seas, and seeing all things <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg>, they wished for an Enemy on whom to <reg orig="execise">exercise</reg> their valour, when behold towards the South, they <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> discovered a Fleet of about 36 sail, and making up unto them, they found by their Lilies that they were <em>French</em> Merchants; The Fleet perceiving the resolution of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, did begin to stand of to Sea with all the sail they could make, but their diligence could not make that quick dispatch, but our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg><pb n="2" /> overtook them, and assaulted them, and in less <reg orig="then">than</reg> an <reg orig="hours">hour's</reg> fight their Admiral sinking, we took five of their ships, and might have given a far better account of the service, but that a sudden storm arose, and severed our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>, which having received some prejudice in their tackling, it gave some advantage to the remainder of the <em>French</em> Fleet to shift for themselves as well as they could.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 19.</head>

<p>The Articles of the Peace betwixt the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> being sent over <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> in a large Silver Box, were this day perused by the Council, and approved; and his Highness the Lord Protector for a <reg orig="ful">full</reg> confirmation of all things will sign to the said Articles; which Counterpane so signed is suddenly to be sent over to <em>Holland</em>, to which purpose a silver Box is making answerable to the former, and the Arms of his Highness and the Commonwealth of <em>England</em> to be engraven, so that now you will suddenly hear when the Peace will be proclaimed.</p>

<p>In the mean time it is reported, that some of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken on the Coast of <em>Holland</em> a <em>Dutch</em> Merchants ship of 800 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> newly builded, she was going to the <em>East Indies</em>, and had in her some Moneys, and such Merchandise as usually is transported into those places. I have seen Letters which make mention of some ships of ours which the Freebooters have met with, and sent them for the present into <em>Ulie</em>.</p>

<p>It is observable that for all the Peace doth so hopefully advance <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, that now there wanteth nothing to it but the last Complement which is the Proclamation of it; yet both the <em>Dutch</em> and <em>English</em> Fleets are making as great preparations as in the time of their most violent Wars. The <em>English</em> fleet was never in a better equipage <reg orig="then">than</reg> at this present, and are dancing attendance not far from <em>Portsmouth</em>, being in an <reg orig="hourely">hourly</reg> expectation when order shall be given to put forth to Sea. In the like manner it is certified from the <em>Hague</em>, that orders have been issued to all the Admiralties to hasten forth their Fleet to Sea, which the Letters say is more strong and numerous than ever any Fleet which yet they had. It is very remarkable<pb n="3" />, that the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> have written to all the Provinces and considerable Cities of their <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> to feel their pulses, and understand what their opinions are concerning the Family of the Prince of <em>Orange</em>, and the Children of the late King of <em>England</em>. In the mean time the young Princess Dowager doth keep at <em>Breda</em>, and both Families being in a great declension, the Ladies when they meet have not such animosities as heretofore they exercised.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 20.</head>

<p>The Letters yesterday from <em>Scotland</em> do advertise, that there is a general alienation in <em>Scotland</em> from the <em>English</em>, and the Design to rise is every day more universal. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Pride</em> is ordered with his Regiment to go into <em>Scotland</em>; some of the Clerks belonging to the Courts of Justice at <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> are <reg orig="stoln">stolen</reg> away to their old <reg orig="Associats">Associates</reg> on the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, and it is said that divers <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> out of <em>Leith</em> are gone the same way, and some also out of <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>. Any little discontent affords subject enough to fly unto the Enemy.</p>

<p>And certainly whatsoever the business is, there is <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> extraordinary in it, that the <reg orig="Rhetorick">Rhetoric</reg> is so prevalent to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> men to abandon their own Nation, and those Swords to which their hearts did cleave as fast as their hands, to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with an Enemy, who the Peace being Proclaimed, cannot (in the broadest eye of probability) find the least advantage at what Ports, or from what places relief may come unto them, and whose Native Country is so <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="harrassed">harassed</reg> with the ruinous War that they are not able to maintain themselves; they must either be <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> with a strong Despair of themselves, or a violent hatred against the Flourish of our present Government, or transported with extraordinary, and incredible hopes of an impossible relief to arrive unto them.</p>

<p>In the mean time our Commissioners are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in making choice of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers.</p>

<p>In all the Transactions there is no respect had to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> so much as grace in <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> hearts, some University men, for defect thereof, have been laid by, and some who never were<pb n="4" /> University men, yet furnished with Gifts and Graces, have been received and welcomed.</p>

<p>No difference at all among the Commissioners themselves, thought they be of divers judgments about Church matters, all minding the advancement of the Gospel.</p>

<p>They being 38 in number are severed into three divisions, each division sitting their <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, so that the work will go constantly on.</p>

<p>Nor partiality used in their <reg orig="tryals">trials</reg>. Testimonies, and Certificates are narrowly looked into, because much depends upon them.</p>

<p>If Patrons would present good men, it would much help on this work.</p>

<p>Some of the men who have been already tried, have preached at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Jameses">James's</reg></em> <reg orig="Chappel">Chapel</reg>, and its probable others will hereafter be put upon this way of exercising their Gifts.</p>

<p>If the carriage of this business were in the view of the Nation, the Censures of men would be <reg orig="forborn">forborne</reg>; and whereas some are of opinion, that these Triers ought to have been sent from Churches, men are to know, that the Magistrate only looks to the sending forth Preachers, and takes not upon him to set down Church Officers; but out of the number of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Preachers, Church Officers may afterwards be chosen, if Congregations see cause.</p>

<p>An extraordinary number of Preachers are continually attending upon these Commissioners to receive their <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg>; and yet there will be want of thousands. They usually sit upon the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before mentioned, from 8 <reg orig="til">till</reg> 12 in the morning; and <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> every day, because of the abundance of business pressing upon them.</p>

<p>No Certificates are approved but such as come subscribed under the hands of such persons as are known to the Commissioners or some of them.</p>

<p>Mrs. <em>Hannah Trapnel</em>, she that lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, hath for some time been in these parts. There seem to be two convincing Reasons against her Spirit; the one is, that it withdraws from Ordinances<pb n="5" />, and the other is, that it is <reg orig="non-sensical">nonsensical</reg>. There are in her Company one Mr: <em>Langdon</em>, and Mr: <em>Bauden</em>, two members of the late short-lived Parliament. The Justices of this County have taken notice of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg>, and practises; and Mr: <em>Lobb</em> giving the charge here this last Sessions, willed the Jury to enquire, 1. concerning Vagrants, 2 such as occasioned unlawful meetings. 3 Such as speak against the present Government. There were two Indictments drawn against her, <em>Langdon</em> and <em>Baudon</em> her Compeers, and abettors, endeavoured to make a learned Defence for her, but it was not suffered, only they <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into Bonds of three hundred pounds for her good behaviour, and appearance at the next Assizes. If you had inquired better into her business, when she tranced it at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, it might have prevented the staggering of many a spirit in <em>Cornwall</em>. The design intended to be made use of by means of this Woman, is (it seems) to compass <em>England</em>, and pass from one good Town to another to vent her Prophesies, and thereby disaffect the People to the present Authority. It <reg orig="cals">calls</reg> to mind the old story of <em>Elizabeth Barton</em>, the holy maid of <em>Kent</em> (as she was called) in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of <em>Henry</em> the 8. who was made use of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests, by <reg orig="fained">feigned</reg> Miracles, and Trances, to raise admiration in the multitude, and foment seditious <reg orig="humors">humours</reg> against the Government; for which she had in the end her reward.</p>

<p>The Ordinance was this Day extant for suspending the proceeding of the Judges for the Relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners until the 15 day of <em>May</em> next ensuing.</p>

<p>The Resident in <em>England</em> for the Duke of <em>Guelders</em>, who is also Count of <em>Egmant</em>, was yesterday in gallant Equipage attended to <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, where he had Audience with great respect from his Highness.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, April 21.</head>

<p>By Letters by the Post from <em>Scotland</em>, it was this Day advertised, that Major Gen: <em>Dyal</em> who lately came over with Gen: <em>Middleton</em> hath besieged <em>Senclair</em> Castle, with a party of 400 Foot, and 800 horse, but the place being made strong both by Art, and Nature, and well victualled, they do not much fear the assaults of their Enemies.</p><pb n="6" />

<p>It was certified that one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> who Convoyed some Ammunition, and divers Merchants ships to <em>Leith</em>, was set upon by the <em>Dutch</em>, and after a furious Fight boarded, and carried away. There is a Report also, that they took some other ships that were with her. In the mean time <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> with about 2000 Foot, and 1200 Horse, and Dragoons, doth press close upon <em>Middleton</em>, who is said not to exceed 4000, <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> hath some advantage of him in respect of the ground, and will undoubtedly either force him to fight, or to fly through such a Purgatory of Rocks, and Boggs, and Mountains, that the Pilgrimage of Death is a pleasure to them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 22.</head>

<p>It was this Day certified that the <em>Constant Warwick</em> had no sooner put off from <em>Plymouth</em> where she was new tallowed, but she met with a <em>Picaroon</em> belonging to <em>Brest</em>, and <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg>, she carried but four guns, but was an excellent <reg orig="saylor">sailor</reg>.</p>

<p>The Ratification of the Peace Signed by his Highness the Lord Protector, was yesterday sent into <em>Holland</em>. The Mother of the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> is removed from <em>Paris</em>, and some say she was sent by the King her Nephew, to see what she could prevail upon her Brother the Duke of <em>Orleans</em> to bring him to the Court. Other Letters affirm that the Duke hath solemnly invited her to his House <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Blois</em>, she was attended by Prince <em>Rupert</em>, and her three Sons, and about sixteen Coaches; the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> having brought her one <reg orig="dayes">day's</reg> Journey, did return with his Brother the titular Duke of <em>York</em> to <em>Paris</em>, where the King of <em>France</em> made one <em>Darcy</em> an <em>Irish</em> Man Lieutenant of his Regiment, and to second the favour conferred upon him, the next day the titular King of <em>Scots</em> made him a Knight.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 24.</head>

<p>The publication of the Peace is to be both in <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> on <em>Wednesday</em> next, as may appear by this ensuing Order of the Council.</p>

<p>Whereas a Peace is made, concluded, and ratified, between his <em>Highness</em> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, &amp; the States<pb n="7" /> General of the United Provinces of the Low <reg orig="Countreys">Countries</reg>. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof shall be made on both parts on <em>Wednesday</em> next, being the six and twentieth day of this instant <em>April</em>; From which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after 12 days, within these Seas; And all in all other places on this side of the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>, after six weeks; And from thence, within the <em><reg orig="Mediterranian">Mediterranean</reg></em> Sea, and to the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em> Line, after ten weeks; And beyond the <em>&AElig;quinoctial</em>, after the space of eight Months: Which several spaces were so limited, to the intent, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said Peace, in all places where it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be necessary. The Council have therefore thought fit hereby to give notice thereof to the several Ports of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to all others, whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof; To the end, they may have warning, to provide for their own safety, and not expose their Ships to danger within the several, and respective times aforesaid.</p>

<p>The good service this Day was advertised by our Parties in the North of <em>Scotland</em>, against the Forces of Gen: <em>Middleton</em>, where some parties of ours have met with several parties of theirs, and routed them, killed some, and took some eminent Persons prisoners, by whom it is confessed that <em>Middleton</em> hath called several <reg orig="Counsels">Councils</reg> of War, and was not at that time resolved whether to Fight, or to retire to the protection of the inhospitable Mountains; one of the two by this time he hath done.</p>

<p>One of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> called the <em>Paul</em> hath taken two <em>French</em> ships, and sent them to <em>Falmouth</em>. A Poet belonging to the Court of <em>France</em> hath been taken, and soundly punished for making some Verses against the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, and his Brother the Duke of <em>York</em>, of which more in my next. It is reported in <em>France</em>, that on the Peace with <em>England</em>, the Emperor <reg orig="wil">will</reg> have a Design on some part of <em>Holland</em>, but what need they fear.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable is:</p>

<p><i>&#x261e; The Peace to be <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> Proclaimed on <em>Wednesday</em> next both in <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, and what ships taken to be restored. The brave service performed by the <em>English</em> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> against the <em>French</em>, and the number of the ships that were fired, taken, and drowned. The late Queen of <em>England</em> gone from <em>Paris</em>, with her Sons, and Prince <em>Rupert</em>; and the punishment inflicted on a Poet for abusing the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, and his Brother the Duke of <em>York</em>. The Emperor <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <em>Holland</em> with War. The <em>Raven</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and some other ships taken by the <em>Dutch</em>, going to <em>Scotland</em>. Some good success in <em>Scotland</em> and the <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> of the Armies in the North. And a great overthrow given to the <em>Christians</em> by the <em>Turks</em>.</i></p> 


<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>