<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell326">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 326</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, April 4. to <em>Tuesday</em>, April 11. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 4.</head>

<p>There hath been a Disputation in <em>France</em> whether these be the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> in which the Devil, The Prince of the Ayris let loose; much as I hear hath been argued by the Protestant Churches, both in relation to that Nation, and to others, but I leave that to them, and the Catsuits to <reg orig="deside">decide</reg>, my <reg orig="busines">business</reg> is Intelligence.</p>

<p>The Letters this Day from <em>Bristol</em> do speak of some <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> they are building there, and of one ready to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth to <reg orig="scoure">scour</reg>, and to secure the Seas in those parts, and never more need, for <em>Bristol</em> hath suffered more <reg orig="then">than</reg> any City that I know of in this Nation. It is advertised that most of the best ships belonging to <em>Bristol</em> are lately taken by the<em> French</em> <reg orig="Picaroes">Picaroons</reg>, and some by the <em>Dutch</em>, so that the City is <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of <reg orig="sadnes">sadness</reg>; the <em>Wild Boar</em> a stout ships of two hundred and fifty <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> taking in some lading at the <em>Island of Madera</em>, was forced by a storm to cut her Cable, and to put forth to Sea, where when ever fair weather appeared, she had the foul fortuned to meet<pb n="1" /> with a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War of 22 Guns, with whom she fought like a true <em>Bristol</em> ship, <em>that is</em>, <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> most resolutely, and stoutly, but after 5 hours fight, being <reg orig="shrowdly">shrewdly</reg> torn, she was <reg orig="overpowred">overpowered</reg> by numbers, and <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to submit to the <em>Dutch</em> Man of War, who did tow her into <em>Flushing</em>, this Ship was thought to be worth 9000 pound, but this ship may be restored at the Proclamation of Peace with <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p>The Charity of <em>Bristol</em> a ship of one hundred <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, was lately taken by two <em>Brest</em> Men of War, the Master of which ship is detained in <em>Brest</em>, to have him exchanged if they can for Capt: <em>Beach</em> who is Prisoner in <em>Plymouth</em>, and having Commission from the titular King of <em>Scots</em>, was taken by the <em>Constant Warwick</em> about 3 weeks since.</p>

<p>Three <em>Brest</em> Men of War have much infested the Western Seas, as if they would be revenged for the loss of their Admiral, they have lately taken a ship belonging to <em>Westchester</em>, and four Vessels belonging to <em>Weymouth</em>, and to <em>Dartmouth</em>.</p>

<p>The Letters from <em>Plymouth</em> do make mention of a desperate fight betwixt the <em>Expedition</em> of <em>Plymouth</em>, and a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War; the fight began not far from the Burlings, and continued eight hours, at the last night parted them, the <em>Dutch</em> Man of War being <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> torn, made up towards the Coast of <em>France</em>, but was so broken in her Hull, that it is said she sunk before she could get thither; the <em>Expedition</em> also having received many shot, did sink the next morning in sight of the Town, but the men were all saved by the care of the Inhabitants, who did send forth Boats to receive them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, April 5.</head>

<p>This Day the Lords of the Council, and M: Secretary of State attended his Highness the Lord Protector at the Cock-pit, after which they sat in Council in <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, and several businesses of great consequence were transacted.</p>

<p>The <em>French</em> Ambassador is removed from Sir <em>Abraham Williams</em> to his own Lodgings in Covent Garden.</p>

<p>This day the Agent from the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had Audience by his Highness, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his Highness divers Lords<pb n="2" /> of the Council, and Mr: Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Sir <em>Shomas Wethrington</em>, and the Lord Commissioner <em>Lisle</em> were this day sworn Commissioners of the Great Seal of <em>England</em>, for the Court of Chancery, by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, in the Council-Chamber at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> who is now in <em>Sweden</em>, is also to be one with them.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Dalkeith</em>, March 28.</head>

<p>Our Forces from <em><reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg></em> have taken sixty horse, and 36. prisoners beyond <em>Dunbarton</em> Castle; since which, one of <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Captains was taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Haddington</em>, with six more. About fifty Gentlemen are gone from the West to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, with good Horses Arms <em>&amp;c.</em> of which, some Knights, and two of the Lord <em>de la <reg orig="Banks">Bank's</reg></em> Brothers. <em>Glencarn, Kenmore, Athol, Forbs</em>, and <em>Glengary</em>, <em>&amp;c.</em> are gone Northward to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with <em>Middleton, Seafort</em>, and the Lord <em>Ray</em>, and so to force <em>Southerland</em>, and <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, to rise with them; their return it is thought will be about a fortnight hence, <em>Seafort, Middleton</em>, and <em>Raget</em> men, surprised a Vessel of ours going to the <em>Lewis</em>, by some Boats they sent out; we had in her fourteen men, Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for that Garrison. <em>Middleton</em> hath besieged <em>Cinkeler</em> Castle in <em><reg orig="Cathness">Caithness</reg></em>, but they bad him defiance. <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em> returned from <em><reg orig="Innernes">Inverness</reg></em> the 21 instant, over the Hill for <em>Aberdeen</em>. The enemy have been cruel in burning, and destroying the Country that do not freely <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them; yet Sir <em>James <reg orig="Mac Donnald">McDonald</reg></em>, and the Captain of the <em>Clans <reg orig="Renolds">Reynolds</reg></em>, are in Arms against <em>Middleton</em> in the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, for preservation of their Country.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> March 28.</em> An <em>Ostend</em> Man of War is brought in by the <em>Falmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and three <em>Dutch</em> Prizes are also brought into this Port, one with <reg orig="Figgs">Figs</reg>, and Raisins from St: <em>Lucas</em>, the other two with French Wines.</p>

<p><em>Ellins 1 April.</em> Yesternight the <em>Reserve</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, one of our Scouts brought into the Fleet a Prize called the <em>John Baptist</em>, <reg orig="loaden">laden</reg> with some Pepper, and Indico, her burthen is about 300 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> from St: <em>Mallows</em>, bound for <em>Amsterdam</em>, the Captain<pb n="3" /> of her a <em>French</em> man, made short dispute, and then <reg orig="surrendred">surrendered</reg>.</p>

<p><reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Rous</em> is added to the Committee of the Admiralty, and Navy. The Committee for approbation of Ministers sit on <em><reg orig="Mondayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdaies">Wednesdays</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Fridaies">Fridays</reg></em> at <em><reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg></em>.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> they write, that at the Request of the English Resident Monsieur <em>Bradshaw</em>, the Senate hath imprisoned an English revolted Merchant, whose name is <em>Waites</em>, who will now be made to answer dearly for his former Treachery.</p>

<p>A <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Pink from <em>Holland</em> came with some few Passengers, and Letters from the States to their Ambassadors here in <em>England</em>, and they that came with them say, that the contents of those Letters are, that their Ambassadors should hasten the Ratification of the Peace with <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorrain</em> hath given his consent that his Brother <em>Francis</em> shall be Commander in chief of his Army.</p>

<p>The last night about nine of the clock the Lords Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> signed the ratification of the Articles of Peace, so did likewise the Commissioners in behalf of his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>The great work this day was the dispatching away of a Pink with the said Articles and Ratification to be signed by the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg>, and upon the return again of the said Ratification, his Highness the Lord Protector <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> also, and the major part of his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>.</p>

<p>In this accord and agreement <em>Denmark</em> is also fully included, so that Peace is likewise made with that Nation.</p>

<p>The <em>French</em> puts in very strongly for Peace too, whereupon our Merchants are required to bring in an Account what damages they have sustained by the <em>French</em>. In this <reg orig="Ambassey">Embassy</reg> the Knights of <em>Malta</em> claim some old Arrears from <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Within a few days the Guard. <reg orig="Pentioners">Pensioners</reg>, and other Officers and Attendants for his Highness (chosen with the approbation of the Lords of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> ) will be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> in their respective places. His Highness was lately at Hampton Court, and Orders are given for repairing that House.</p><pb n="4" />

<p>It is said that a Squadron of our Fleet is designed for the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Mr: <em>Feak</em> and Mr: <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em> are yet as highly resolved in their former ways as ever, say some of their Letters to their friends in <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>Yesterday a man for a wager undertook to drive a Wheelbarrow with 14. pound weight in it, from <em>London</em> to Saint <em>Albans</em>, and back again from 5 of the clock in the morning, <reg orig="til">till</reg> 7 of the clock at night, but he was tired by that time he came back to <em>Highgate</em>.</p>

<p>When Articles of Peace, and Ratification are returned back Signed by the States, and so again here as aforesaid, you may expect to have it Proclaimed with great solemnity both in <em>England</em>, and <em>Holland</em>, all which may be done in few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; We are likely also to have a <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Alliance with <em>Sweden</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, April 6.</head>

<p>Yesterday the Sessions began in the Old <reg orig="Baily">Bailey</reg>, 3 of those men are there to be tried who committed the late great Robbery on <em>Blackheath</em>.</p>

<p>It is confirmed by Letters from <em>Scotland</em>, that in the Southern parts of <em>Scotland</em> not far from <em><reg orig="Carlile">Carlisle</reg></em> the <em>Scots</em> are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in raising and <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> men to increase their strength; and to suppress these <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg> our Horses are so <reg orig="harrassed">harassed</reg> with perpetual travel, that they are even <reg orig="tyred">tired</reg> out: the Letters say that these who <reg orig="leavie">levy</reg> are so cunning that we cannot meet with them in any considerable Body, though many are suspected for <reg orig="complyance">compliance</reg>, and divers apprehended.</p>

<p>The <em>Highlanders</em> do still continue in <em>Skelbo</em> Castle, and the better to secure themselves have cast up some work about it. They have also a garrison in the Town <reg orig="neer">near</reg> unto the Ferry of the River <em>Tay</em>. It is said that Gen: <em>Middleton</em> hath brought a very large Commission from the titular King of the <em>Scots</em>, in which he seems to make him his Vicegerent, and hath given him the free disposal of all affairs both <reg orig="Ecclesiasticall">Ecclesiastical</reg> and Civil.</p>

<p>I made mention in my last, that those <em>French</em> Regiments<pb n="5" /> who made their Intrado into the <reg orig="Bishoprick">Bishopric</reg> of <em>Leige</em> were in great danger to be cut off upon their return being <reg orig="invironed">environed</reg> by the <em>Spanish</em> Army, and some of the Pr: of <em><reg orig="Condies">Condi's</reg></em> Horse; but <em><reg orig="Monseiur">Monsieur</reg> Faber</em> who commanded them did retreat with such generous dexterity, that matching six days together in sight of the Enemy, he on the seventh did bring his Forces in safety over the River of <em>Mace</em>, where they rested with much honour on the frontiers of <em>Picardy</em>.</p>

<p>But the Regiment of Horse commanded by <em>Vienuille</em> had not that success, for some of the Pr: of <em><reg orig="Condies">Condi's</reg></em> Troops did meet them about <em>Dinam</em>, and in a fierce <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> overthrew them; <em><reg orig="Monseir">Monsieur</reg> Londe</em> the Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: was taken prisoner with many others, there being but few who escaped to bring news of the overthrow into <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>The King of <em>Denmark</em> had notice lately sent him from the <em>Hague</em>, that seventy English men of War had steered their course Northwards, which Fleet they feared was designed against the <em>Sound</em>, which by the assistance of the <em>Swedes</em> might be surprised if not timely prevented; so that for all the hopes of Peace until the Articles were Signed on last night, they were <reg orig="fearfull">fearful</reg> of the event, &amp; both <em>Holland</em> and <em>Denmark</em> made preparations to defend themselves.</p>

<p>The Letters from <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em> do advertise, that the Friends of the Court, and of the King of <em>France</em>, do much suspect the design of the English Fleet, and the preparation for war.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, April 7.</head>

<p>The Ordinance was this day proclaimed for the adjourning of part of <em>Easter Term</em> unto the first Return of the Term following.</p>

<p>I made mention before of the Articles that were Signed and Sealed by the Lord Ambassadors of <em>Holland</em> with full power from the States, and our Commissioners with full power from the Lord Protector, which are very speedily to be Signed by the Lord Protector himself, and by the States of <em>Holland</em>. It is so concluded, that the Peace shall be proclaimed in <em>England</em> and in <em>Holland</em> in one day. The loss sustained by the <em>English</em> Merchants which is <reg orig="alledged">alleged</reg> to amount to fifteen<pb n="6" /> hundred thousand pound is referred to 2 <em>English</em> Merchants and to two <em>Dutch</em> Merchants to determine, who are to sit upon it at <em>Guild Hall</em>.</p>

<p>The business of <em>Amboyna</em>, and the loss sustained there as well of lives as of goods is referred to eight Commissioners, who have the space of six months allowed them to determine of; and in case they cannot agree, there are Arbitrators to be chosen to conclude the difference.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, April 8.</head>

<p>It was advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the Earl of <em>Athol</em> is come to <em>Glencarn</em> with 700 Horse and Foot; the Ld: <em>Seaford</em> is expected to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him with his Forces who are about 7 or 800. The Forces of <em>Glencarn</em> are about 2000 Horse and Foot. It is likely the whole Body of the Enemy will <reg orig="randezvous">rendezvous</reg> there. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> is advanced towards them with his Forces, he takes with him five troops of <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: Rich his Regiment, and four of Dragoons; he intends to take along with him also Col: <em><reg orig="Thomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> Regiment, and 5 Companies of Foot out of <reg orig="Innernes">Inverness</reg>, Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em><reg orig="Michil">Mitchell</reg></em> is marched with him nine Companies of Foot.</p>

<p>Two of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken a <em>Dutch</em> Merchant bound for the <em>West Indies</em>, she sailed round about, thinking it to be the nearer way, but she was met with; howsoever she was laden with <em>Spanish</em> Wines, and <reg orig="linnen">linen</reg> <reg orig="Cloath">Cloth</reg>, and other good commodities.</p>

<p>Major General <em>Middleton</em> is <reg orig="stil">still</reg> about <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, and <em>Southerland</em>, he expects the access of more Forces, and carrying himself very plausibly, many steal from the <em>Lowlands</em> to him, and divers have been intercepted in the way, amongst whom were some young Lairds, and others, who having a Design to be Masters of a party of Horse of <em><reg orig="Louthian">Lothian</reg></em>, were all of them taken, and carried Prisoners to <em>Dalkeith</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, April 10.</head>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the Army of the <em>Highlanders</em> are drawing together all into one Body, some say <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to receive Instructions at the <reg orig="generall">general</reg> Master; others, that they are resolved to fight the English Army which doth not seem so probable; what the event will be will now suddenly be known: many <reg orig="poore">poor</reg> fellows that are <reg orig="leavied">levied</reg> are daily taken, and some persons that are considerable who were volunteers.</p>

<p>Lieut: <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Lilburn</em> being said to have attempted again <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> against the State, is carried from the <em>Tower</em> to be a prisoner in some remoter place.</p>

<p>The titular King of the <em>Scots</em> is still at <em>Paris</em>, and of late <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> more merry than ordinary. The Deputies for <em>Languedoc</em> telling him, that if there were a Peace with <em>England</em>, it would be well for all the Protestants in <em>France</em>; He made answer that he was glad of it, for then it would be the better for himself.</p>

<p>This day was the <reg orig="Jayl">Jail</reg> delivery, three were hanged, one whereof <reg orig="dyed">died</reg> most desperately, and going up the Cart drank a health to the <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> majesty: one was pressed last Saturday, and being afterwards heard to groan was carried down to the Presyard again to have the execution <reg orig="dispatcht">dispatched</reg>.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable is,</p>

<p><i>The Signing of the Articles of Peace, the demand of the <em>English</em> Merchants requiring fifteen hundred thousand pound referred to some Commissioners: and the business of <em>Amboyna</em>, referred to others. The great and terrible fight at Sea betwixt an <em>English</em> ship and a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War, and their sinking one another. The words of the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> concerning the Peace with <em>France</em>. Some losses received in the Western Seas by the <reg orig="Picaroes">Picaroons</reg> of <em>Brest</em>, and the drawing together of the <em>English</em> and <em>Scots</em> Armies to give <reg orig="battel">battle</reg> to one another: and the desperate death of one hanged yesterday at Tiburn, who going up the Cart drank a health to the <reg orig="Devils">Devil's</reg> Majesty.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>The Art of Cookery <reg orig="refin'd">refined</reg>, containing an Abstract of some rare unpublished Conceits, collected from the practise of that incomparable Master of these Arts, Mr. <em>Joseph Cooper</em>, Cook to the late King. And are to be sold by <em>R. Lowns</em> at the <reg orig="White-lyon">White Lion</reg> in <em>Paul's</em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>