<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell147#4">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 147#4</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 27. to <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 3. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, Decemb: 27.</head>

<p><em>Sero sed serio</em>. The Treaty hath held long betwixt the Committee of the Council of <em>England</em>, and the Deputies of <em>Holland</em>. The Lord <em>Lisle</em>, Sir <em>Anthony Ashley</em>, Sir <em>Gilbert Pickering</em>, Mr: <em>Walter Strickland</em>, Master Secretary <em>Thurloe</em>, have lately Treated with them, sometimes one, sometimes two hours together, and the peace betwixt the two Nations, (in which Denmark is also included) hath not so far advanced itself, but that two of the Deputies are gone into <em>Holland</em>. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> the new Great Seal will be made ready for the confirmation, and establishment of all things. For you are to understand that there is to be an alteration to several Names, and Forms. The Ordinance runs thus.</p>

<p><em>OLIVER</em>, LORD PROTECTOR of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereunto belonging, having the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said <pb n="1" /><reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> invested, and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council, who have Power until the meeting of the next Parliament, (which is to be on the third of September next following) to make Laws and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of the Nations, where it shall be necessary, and which shall be binding, and in force, until the Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same, <em>&amp;c.</em></p>

<p>There was a paper delivered to his Highness from one Mr: <em>Rogers</em>, the Persons and Titles of Orthodox Divines do seem to be much displeasing to him: I shall here give it to the discreet Reader for novelties sake.</p>

<p>Take heed of <em>protecting</em> the carnal, national, antichristian <em>Clergy</em> (though they come in the name of Orthodox, or learned, for so did the <em>Scribes</em> and the <em>Pharisees</em>.) <em><reg orig="Zedekiahs">Zedekiah's</reg></em> indulgence to the Priests, and false Prophets of the Nation, <reg orig="imboldned">emboldened</reg> <em>Hananiah</em> in his lies, <em>Jer</em>:28. 1. <em>&amp;c.</em> Which (<em>Zedekiah</em> <reg orig="beleeving">believing</reg>) persecuted the true Prophets, and brought dreadful destruction upon his own head. So <em>Ahab</em> (a notable politician) did protect his national Clergy, or prophets (who were his, not the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg>, 2 <em>Chro</em>: 18. 5. and by their suggestion hated and persecuted the true Prophet <em>Maaziah</em>, which proved his <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>. Thus the Rulers that were led by the Priests, proved Tyrants to the true Ministers of the New Testament, <em>Act</em>: 4.16.17. And whiles they would defend them, they destroyed themselves. Thus the worldly Clergy do ever fly to worldly Powers for protection (having none from God) and for this end it is, they flatter great men, to engage them to their <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>; so do <em>Antichrists</em>, now they are <reg orig="neer">near</reg> falling, and (without the <em>Lord</em> hear prayers for you, and deliver you from this fearful danger,) they will ensnare you, and cast you asleep with their <reg orig="Inchantments">Enchantments</reg>, and render you unfit to follow Christ any further, but (under the name of the Ministry) most miserably <reg orig="intangle">entangle</reg>, and <reg orig="subtilly">subtly</reg> seduce you into <em><reg orig="Antichrists">Antichrist's</reg></em> cause: Which if they do, will be your utter <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg>, at <em>Revel</em>: 4.9, 10. If any worship the Beast, or his Image, and receive his mark in their forehead, or in his head, or in his <pb n="2" />hand, the same shall drink of the Wine of the wrath of God; <em>&amp;c. Rev</em>: 19.2. And the Beast was taken, and with him the false Prophets, with whom he deceived them that received the mark of the Beast, and them that worshipped the Beast, these were cast alive into the lake burning with brimstone. Therefore (my LORD) if a word from Jehovah on high, may (as yet) be received, look about you! and before you! with an <em>ocule irretorto</em>! Make <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> (my LORD) for <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg> protection against the plagues that are (as sure as God is righteous) coming upon <em>Babylon</em>, and all that will cleave to his <em>Interest</em>. <em>Luther</em> was not too bold (in the name of the LORD) to tell his Lord <em>Protector</em>, the Elector of <em>Saxony</em>; <i>That by his Prayers he had gained him more safety and protection, <reg orig="then">than</reg> he received from him; and that the cause of Christ needed not his protection, but he needed <reg orig="thats">that's</reg> protection. The power of Man (<em>indeed</em>) protects <reg orig="Antichrists">Antichrist's</reg> cause, but it is the power of God (<em>set awork by Faith and Prayer</em>) that protects <reg orig="Christs">Christ's</reg>.</i> And <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, <i>Whether you will <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> it or no, yet this way I will undertake to secure, and protect your <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> Soul, Body, Estate, and all, (viz: <em>by Faith, and Prayer</em>) if you <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> freely in this cause of Christ against Antichrist.</i> So say I (my LORD) in that Name which sent me, (which <reg orig="fils">fills</reg> me with courage and confidence) that if you will freely oblige for <em>Christ</em> and his <em>Interest </em>, the loud-crying faith, and <reg orig="incessent">incessant</reg> high-spirited prayers of the Saints, will all <reg orig="Ingage">Engage</reg> for you, and never give Jehovah <unclear>Niffs</unclear>, the Lord our Protector rest, till the excellency of <em>Jacob</em> have prevailed, 2 <em>Chron</em>: 19. 6. <i>Take heed what you do</i>.</p>

<p>Thus the Lord hath stirred me up by an irresistible, and restless <em>Power</em>, (once more) to lay his work before you; for that he hath used You as a most glorious Instrument in the three Nations, (by the Faith and Prayers of his People) to make way for this Work; which if you reject, will reject you, and be the infallible <reg orig="fore-runner">forerunner</reg> of your fall: Which that God may prevent, is the fervent prayers of your <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> People night and day, whose souls mourn in secret for you, whose hearts <reg orig="ake">ache</reg> and bleed abundantly on your behalf; as on a man (most dear in their souls, but) under most desperate <pb n="3" />temptations, and dangers.</p>

<p>In these <em>Proposals</em> I am sure I have kept my sphere, and followed the strong impulse of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> own spirit in me, and many others, however it be taken. Wherefore the great God awake you to his work! else the time will come when God will say: <i>Let him alone, he is <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> to Idols.</i> Hos: 4. 17.</p>

<p>Now that the hand of the Lord may be with you, see what these five fingers point at, to you; which if you practise, will be able to protect you, as well as direct you in this dreadful day of the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> <reg orig="controversie">controversy</reg> for <em><reg orig="Sion">Zion</reg></em>: They concern you (my Lord) more <reg orig="then">than</reg> <em><reg orig="C&aelig;sars">C&aelig;sar's</reg></em> paper did him. Mow that they may prove a hand-writing against you (and a cup of Trembling put into your hands) they are <reg orig="strengthned">strengthened</reg> with a Divine generosity, and shall struggle with you in the Faith, Tears and Prayers of many, who pray and mourn for you, and amongst others,</p>

<p><i>Your (afflicted) <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> Servant, for the interest of the Lord Jesus,</i> John Rogers.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Decemb: 28.</head>

<p>Divers Officers of the Army did this Day come to his Highness at the Cockpit, and signified their full union in the present Government. The Lord Ambassador of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> had Audience yesterday by his Highness the LORD PROTECTOR, who did gratulate him in his new Authority.</p>

<p>By letters from <em>Leith</em>, and <em><reg orig="Edinborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> it was advertised, that the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> hath sent a Letter to the Earl of <em>Kilmore</em>, assuring him that what men can be spared in Germany, and will willingly upon the Beat of the Drum <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> in his service, shall be transported with all <reg orig="conveniency">convenience</reg> into <em>Scotland</em>, and that he will assist them with a large proportion of Arms, Ammunition and Monies. He also (as it is said, but much doubted) hath assured him that he will be in person shortly with them, as soon as he hath received monies to carry on that great Design he hath in hand.</p>

<pb n="4" />

<p><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> is still at <em>Stoaks</em> Bay where I left him in my last. He hath had lately a Court Martial, in that stout ship now rigged, called, The <em>Swiftsure</em>; where <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="offendors">offenders</reg> were sentenced to be punished for their <reg orig="misdemeanors">misdemeanours</reg>, which accordingly was put in execution.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> making a heady In-road into the <em>Lowlands</em>, was <reg orig="encountred">encountered</reg> by Captain <em>Hart</em>, who at the first drawing of the Sword baffled him, and made ready the spur to pursue him; he took sixty five Horses, such as they were, for they were extremely harassed with <reg orig="travell">travel</reg>: there were taken also sixteen prisoners, and divers killed Sir <em>Arthur Forbes</em> himself, and his Major one <em><reg orig="Erwyn">Erwin</reg></em> fighting most bravely were both wounded, and had undoubtedly been taken, but the Dangers themselves took compassion of them.</p>

<p>I have been sent a Letter from Captain <em><reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg></em> (a brave Man no doubt) to the <em>Scots</em> at the foot of the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> not far from St. <em>Johnstons</em>, <reg orig="disswading">dissuading</reg> them not to partake in these new tumults, lest they partake in the calamities that attend them. I had an intent to insert it in this place, being of great consequence, and relishing of those spirits which you shall find in History when Reason and Resolution commanded Fortune, and laid the world open to the Empire of their swords. But room is wanting, but you shall find it howsoever in the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> proceedings extant upon <em>Thursday</em> last.</p>

<p>The Brother to the <em><reg orig="Portugall">Portugal</reg></em> Ambassador who was a Prisoner in <em>Newgate</em>, is translated from his close Imprisonment there, to the <em>Tower</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Decemb. 29.</head>

<p>I must retract from something mentioned in the beginning of this <em>Intelligence</em>, which was, that the Peace was in a good way concluded betwixt this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the <em>Dutch</em>, we were this Day more fully informed, that it is not as yet brought to that happy period.</p> 

<p>It is informed from <em>Scotland</em>, that the <em>Highlanders</em> <pb n="5" />are gone towards the North, to receive Arms (as it is said) some report them five thousand Horse and Foot, but the best <em>Intelligence</em> affirms that they are not above three thousand Horse and Foot, The Marquis of <em>Huntley</em> being dead, divers of his followers took part with the <em>Highlanders</em>, and meeting with eight of our Troopers, they fell from words to blows, in which one of them, and two of ours were slain, the conflict increasing, by the <reg orig="accesse">access</reg> of new numbers to the <em>Highland</em> party, four more of our men were taken, the other two hardly escaping.</p>

<p>The Highlanders have imprisoned some for denying their <reg orig="Leavies">Levies</reg>, and give out that they will proceed in like manners with others.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Decemb: 30.</head>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Holland</em>, that if the Treaty takes no effect, the <em>Dutch</em> will send sudden assistance to the <em>Highlanders</em>; some say that the Duke of <em>York</em> is there already in person, but that is not so, for the last Letters from <em>France</em>, do affirm that he is there. Some say that the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> is going thither; Others, that Prince <em>Rupert</em> is to be <em>Generalissimo</em> of the <em>Highlanders</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Decemb: 31.</head>

<p>The good service performed by the <em>Assistance</em>, and the <em>Nonesuch</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, was confirmed, who missing of the Design to destroy the ships at <em>Conquet</em>, because the Enemies had filled their Houses with <reg orig="Musketiers">Musketeers</reg>, did make two hundred and thirty great shot into the Town, which did great <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> to it.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, January 2.</head>

<p>This day was extant the Government of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> by his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> especial commandment. Many <pb n="6" />of the Heads I have already exhibited; I shall only <reg orig="adde">add</reg>, that the Parliament sitting his Highness shall dispose the Militia by Sea and Land by their consent, and shall order it in the Intervals of Parliament by the consent of the greater part of his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>. That the raising of Moneys for the <reg orig="Warrs">Wars</reg> shall be by consent of Parliament, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that the Lord Protector shall have power <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the meeting of the next Parliament to raise Money for the present service, and to make Laws, and Ordinances for the welfare of the Nations with the Consent of the greater part of his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg>. That a Parliament being chosen of four hundred persons, sixty of them shall be deemed the Parliament of <em>England</em>, &amp;c. and the <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Legislative Power is to reside in the Lord Protector and such a Parliament. The Parliaments are not to be adjourned, or dissolved without their own consent during the first three Months of their sitting, and in case of future War with any <reg orig="forraign">foreign</reg> Nation, a Parliament shall forthwith be summoned for their advice concerning the same. That a constant <reg orig="yeerly">yearly</reg> Revenue shall be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> for the remaining ten thousand Horse and Dragoons, and twenty thousand Foot in the three Nations for the security of them, and a convenient number of Ships for guarding the Seas, and two hundred thousand pound <reg orig="yeerly">yearly</reg> to defray the necessary charges for the <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg> of the Government, which Revenue is to be raised by the Customs, and such other ways as the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="Councell">Council</reg> shall think fit. That in case there needs not so great a Defence either at Land or Sea, that an abatement be made, and the Money saved to be kept in bank for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> service. That the Lands, Rents, and Royalties yet unsold or be indisposed by Parliament belonging to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> (except the <reg orig="Forrests">Forests</reg>, <reg orig="Honors">Honours</reg> and <reg orig="Mannors">Manors</reg> belonging to the same, and some Lands forfeited in <em>Ireland</em> and <em>Scotland</em>, and the Lands of some Papists and Delinquents in <em>England</em>) be vested in the Lord Protector to hold to him and to his Successors. That the Christian Religion contained in the Scriptures be held forth, and that a provision less subject to scruple, and more certain than the <pb n="7" />present be made for the <reg orig="incouragement">encouragement</reg> of painful Teachers, and confusion of Errors, and that to the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Profession held forth none shall be compelled by penalties, and that all such as profess Faith in GOD by Jesus Christ, though differing in <reg orig="judgment">judgement</reg> from the Doctrine <reg orig="publickly">publicly</reg> held forth, shall be protected in the profession of the said Faith and exercise of their Religion, so as they abuse not this Liberty; provided it extend not to Popery, or Prelacy.</p>

<p>The Oath taken by his Highness <em>OLIVER <reg orig="CROMWEL">CROMWELL</reg></em>, LORD PROTECTOR was some prelibations being before made in these words. I do accept, and take upon me the protection, and Government of these Nations in the manner at large expressed in the Form of Government, and I do promise in the presence of God, that I will not violate, or infringe the matters, and things contained therein, but to my power will observe the same, and cause them to be observed, and shall in all other things to the best of my understanding Govern these Nations, according to the Laws, Statutes and Customs, seeking their peace, and causing Justice, and <em>Law</em> to be equally <reg orig="admininstred">administered</reg>.</p>

<p><em>O. Cromwell</em></p>

<p>The News this Day from <em>Scotland</em> is, that the <em>Highlanders</em> who are come into the South of <em>Scotland</em>, would be glad with all their hearts if they were on the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> again, many of them are taken, and the drifts of snow being great, some of their heads are set so right, that they draw bows, and branches of Trees behind them, that the errors of their feet may not be discovered.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable, is:</head>

<p><i>The Oath taken by his Highness the LORD PROTECTOR for the Government of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, <em>Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>. The heads of the Articles for the present Government, The Treaty betwixt <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> of no effect for the present. The titular King of <em>Scots</em>, his Brother, and Prince <em>Rupert</em>, all designed for <em>Scotland</em>. Some <reg orig="smal">small</reg> success of the <em>Scots</em> in the late <reg orig="Ingagement">Engagement</reg> with <em><reg orig="Huntleys">Huntley's</reg></em> Men. Several parties taken, and remarkable service performed by Sea.</i></p> 

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>