<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell$242">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 224</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, May 23. to <em>Tuesday</em>, May 30. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, April 4.</head>

<p>I concluded in my last with the Treason, of which I told you you should hear more hereafter, and I must this week conclude in the same words again, because the Examinations are not yet fully persecuted. Before I shall give you a more particular account of it, let it suffice you to understand, that the Design was to take away the life of the Lord Protector, which God prevented, and in the amazement and hurry of the tumult, to have Proclaimed the titular King of the <i>Scots <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> the Second King of England</i>. It was high time to look about, when in the sharpest discretion of the eye. it was probably conjectured that he was not far off himself.</p>

<p>It is impossible in such a divided Nation to find an absolute concurrence of an exact obedience, but the Proclamation of his Highness was to a great effect, which followeth in these words.</p><pb n="1" />

<p>O.P.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the LORD PROTECTOR.</i></head>

<p>Whereas the Enemies of the Peace of this Nation (notwithstanding the many signal providences of God in frustrating of their former Counsels, and malicious Designs) do appear <reg orig="stil">still</reg> restless in their Attempts, to involve this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> in blood and confusion. In Order whereunto divers of them have lately repaired to <em>London</em>, as well from beyond the Seas, as from several parts of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. His Highness with the advice of his Council, hath therefore thought fit, and hereby expressly Charge and Command, That for the better discovery of Persons ill affected to the Peace of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> by Constables of the respective Parishes within the Cities, of <em>London</em> and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and the Lines of Communication, do forthwith after the Publication hereof, repair to the several houses within their respective Parishes, &amp; require from the <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> a List of the names of all such persons as now do, or did <reg orig="lodg">lodge</reg> in their respective Houses on <em>Friday</em> night last being the 19 of this instant <em>May</em>, or at any time since, with their several qualities and conditions, and how long they have been lodged there. And all and every the said <reg orig="Housholders">Householders</reg> are accordingly to deliver to the said Constables, or one of them, a true List of all such names upon peril of being reputed and dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, as <reg orig="Complices">Accomplices</reg> and Partakers in the said Designs, which Lists so delivered, the respective Constables of the Parishes within the Cities of <em>London</em>, and <em>Westminster</em>, <reg orig="Burrough">Borough</reg> of <em>Southwark</em>, and Lines of Communication, are within 48. hours to deliver the Lord Mayor of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Southwark</em>, respectively, whereof the said Constables are not to sail at their utmost peril. And the Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> are to return the Lists so to be by them received, to his <reg orig=" Highness "> Highness's </reg> Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after the <reg orig="receits">receipts</reg> thereof. And his Highness doth likewise strictly require, all Person or Persons <reg orig="whatoever">whatsoever</reg>, so living within the said Lines<pb n="2" /> of Communication, do change his or their several and respective lodgings, or depart out of the said Lines for the space of 10 days after the date hereof, without a special Licence and Pass in that behalf obtained from the Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliff">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, or <em>Southwark</em> respectively, under their respective hands and seals; which Pass the said Lord Mayor, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are hereby Authorized to give all such persons, concerning whom they shall be satisfied, that they have no <reg orig="il">ill</reg> intentions or designs against the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and to none else, And if any such <reg orig="perperson">person</reg> shall presume to depart out of the said Lines, within the said time, without licence obtained as aforesaid, it shall be reputed a Contempt of this his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Command, and be punished according to <reg orig="it's">its</reg> demerit. And the Lord Mayor of the City of <em>London</em>, and <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg> of <em>Westminster</em>, and <em>Southwark</em> respectively, are to cause this Proclamation forthwith, after Publication thereof, to be sent to the several Constables aforesaid, and to require and demand from them an account of their proceedings thereupon.</p>

<p><i>Given at Whitehall the 23 of May, 1654.</i></p>

<p>This day was the day of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Thanksgiving, Mr. <em>Lockyer</em> and M: <em><reg orig="Goodwyn">Goodwin</reg></em> Preached at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>, his Highness, and his Council being present. After the Sermon a Woman made a disturbance by inveighing against the present Government. The Day of Thanksgiving was observed in several Parishes of this City, yet some men there were (as I am informed) who instead of a day of Thanksgiving, did make it a day of Humiliation. These are those Non-Conformists, who by a new and dangerous <reg orig="Logick">Logic</reg>, would have a wild distinction; they would disobey the Protector, and yet serve God too.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, May 24.</head>

<p>Letters from <em>France</em> did this day make mention, that the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> (who civilly refused to be an Actor in the Comedy of <em>Beleus</em>, and <em>Thetis</em>, which hath lost much of <reg orig="it's">its</reg> lustre, being (I know not by what, too confident a pen) translated into English) is yet in <em>Paris</em>, but is suddenly on his removal, and of this we have informed you long<pb n="3" /> ago, but this hath relation to a higher <reg orig="Sphear">Sphere</reg>, as the <reg orig="Counsels">Councils</reg> of the Nations shall espouse one another: A <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> well established, is a Mistress that is courted by <reg orig="al">all</reg> the World, and <reg orig="Salick">Salic</reg> Law of <em>France</em> is lusty on the <unclear>Malel</unclear> and they will be there as wise as they are caprchlous to, Court a Mistress for their own advantage.</p>

<p>Peace being made with <em>Holland</em>, the <em>Muscovite</em> had no sooner notice of it, but he sends his Agents to congratulate the Peace, and to buy the preparations of the future War, which have been made trust <unclear>are</unclear> by this happy Union.</p>

<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Pride</em> is now in Town, but some part of his Regiment (as I am informed) are landed at <em>Aberdeen</em>, and some part at old <em><reg orig="Montross">Montrose</reg></em>. If there hath been any distemper of melancholy amongst them, it hath been purged by the visitation of the Sea: A Letter from an eminent hand represents, that <em>Glencarn</em> keeps a distance from <em>Middleton</em> both in his mind, and his Brigade. <em>Middleton</em> it is said is a running posture, and much incensed against <em>Glencarn</em>, and his <reg orig="Associats">Associates</reg>, which had appeared more, had not the titular King of <em>Scotland</em> opportunely arrived, who like another Nature did <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> the unruly Elements of their constitution into a Geographical Peace.</p>

<p>I dare not be so bold as to give you the Names of those who are said to be Actors in the great Conspiracy. This <reg orig="Busines">Business</reg> by the Respite of an Indulgence of Time, would <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> even the <em><reg orig="Scipticks">Sceptics</reg></em> themselves, but there is no man so untutored, who by better demonstrations might not be corrected to nobler proncopley. I cannot give you a Name of those Men who are said to be <reg orig="accessary">accessory</reg> in this great Plot, my business hath been <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> to inform you with the truth. And although you will confess with me it is truth enough, that such a Plot hath been continued, yet I am not able in this relation to Truth to give you a particular of the Names until the next; for the persons examined do make a diversity of Relations, you must therefore <reg orig="like wise">likewise</reg> <em>Logicians</em> suspend for a while the premises until the infallible conclusion <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> determine<pb n="4" />, and pronounce the truth.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May 25.</head>

<p>It was this Day by several Letters advertised to his Highness, that the Peace to be proclaimed in <em>Holland</em>, and the solemnity of the day to be observed, the young Prince <em>Dowager</em> with her Mother in Law is removed from the <em>Hague</em> into <em>Breda</em>. The States General are upon consultation to give satisfaction for the losses received at <em>Denmark</em>. Their Fleet for <em>Greenland</em> is gone to Sea, and another Fleet of Merchants is for <em>Spain</em>, and <em>Portugal</em>, and another for <em>France</em>, that Nation working <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> both by Sea and Land (but of late in some places inprosperously) for their own advantage. There is nothing in the world that hath more honoured the Provinces, but their love to Learning, and they have had some <reg orig="Schollars">Scholars</reg> to <reg orig="adstipulate">estipulate</reg> that love, they had otherwise been a Sea, or a heap of Ashes.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, May 26.</head>

<p>I have been so long on the business of Action, I shall now give you <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> determined upon in Council, which is this.</p>

<head level="3"><i>At the Council at <reg orig="White hall">Whitehall</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Whereas Information hath been given to his Highness the Lord Protector, by the Committee sitting at <em>Sadlers Hall London</em>, appointed to take care of carrying on the business of Collections in <em>England</em>, and <em>Wales</em>, for and towards the relief of the Inhabitants of the Town of <em><reg orig="Marleborough">Marlborough</reg></em> in the County of <em>Wilts</em>, and <reg orig="redifying">re-edifying</reg> of the said Town (a great part thereof being lately consumed by a sad, and lamentable fire,) That there are divers sums of money collected in divers Parishes, Cities, and Towns Corporate in England, and Wales, for the uses aforesaid, which are through <reg orig="remisness">remissness</reg>, or some other sinister ends, detained in the hands of such as have Collected the same, and have not paid them over to such persons as have been appointed by the said Committee to receive them, whereby the Charity of good People is abused, and these poor Inhabitants frustrated or delayed of the relief intended them thereby. It is<pb n="5" /> therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, That all Churchwardens, Collector, <reg orig="Receivors">Receivers</reg>, Mayors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, Constables, and other Persons, who have in their hands any of the monies collected for the uses aforesaid, do forthwith, upon sight hereof, pay over the same to such person or persons, as Alderman <em>Andrews</em>, Alderman <em>Tichborn</em>, Alderman <em>Ireton</em>, Col: <em>Owen Roe</em> Mr <em>Edward Bushel</em>, Mr: <em>Maximilian Beard</em>, Mr: <em>Greensmith</em>, Mr: <em>Herring</em> Major <em>Packer</em>, Mr: <em>Thomas Lamb</em>, Mr: <em>Wollaston</em> Mr: <em>Tempest Milnor</em>, Mr <em>Theophilus Ryley</em> Major <em>Wareing</em>, Mr: <em>Ashurst</em>, Mr: <em>Strong</em>, Mr: <em>Samuel Wilson</em>, Mr: <em>Robert <reg orig="Barret">Barrett</reg></em>, Mr: <em>Anthony Dowse</em>, Mr: <em>John Price</em>, Mr: <em>William Kiffin</em>, Mr: <em>Babington</em>, Major <em><reg orig="Bancks">Banks</reg></em>, Captain <em>Manton</em>, Mr: <em>Etandrith</em>, Mr. <em>Isler</em>, Mr: <em>Lawrence Steel</em>, Mr: <em>William Malyn</em>, Captain <em>Aldron</em>, Cornet <em>Comely</em>, being the said Committee at <em>Sadlers</em> Hall, or any five of them, shall appoint and authorize to receive the same; and all the said Collectors, and other Officers and persons before mentioned, are hereby required to perform the same accordingly, as they <reg orig="wil">will</reg> answer their neglect and contempt at their peril.</p>

<p><i>Ex: <em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>By <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Letters from <em>Scotland</em> as followeth. <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg>, May 14</em>. <em>Middleton</em> and the rest of his party that remains of those that are run to their own houses, are still in <em>Southerland</em> and <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em>, Col. <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> brigade lies in the Shires of <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> and <em><reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg></em>, blocking them up as formerly; <em>Drummond</em> is about <em>Loughtay</em>, and the <reg orig="Bailiffe">Bailiff</reg> of <em>Athol</em> is gone to him, to advise concerning the speedy raising of all Gentlemen in that Country (for the <em>Highlanders</em> are no other) <em><reg orig="Montrosse">Montrose</reg></em> with about 450 Horse and Foot were lately in the <reg orig="Braies">Brays</reg> of <em>Anguish</em>, forcing men to rise with him: <em>Glencairn</em> we hear is gone South through the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg> of <em>Renogh</em>, and from the Hills we understand, the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> foot runs away over the <reg orig="Mountaines">Mountains</reg>, by thirty and forty in a Company, and are necessitated to eat Horseflesh where they <reg orig="goe">go</reg>, provisions being so exceeding scarce in those parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> May 16.</em> Thursday last the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> came hither with part of Col. <em><reg orig="Okeys">Okey's</reg></em> his <reg orig="owne">own</reg> Regiment, and four<pb n="6" /> Companies of Sir <em>William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg></em> of Foot, we hear nothing of any considerable part of the Enemy being in these parts: only we have Intelligence, that Captain <em>Kympton Hilliard</em> being marched down toward <em>Douglas</em>, having Intelligence, That <em>Cardinesse Forgison</em> and <em>Mallace</em> with about 40 of the Rebels were about <em>New Mills</em> resolved to engage them with 20 of his Troop, and a Sergeant that were with him, but upon a nearer approach found them above 60 ready mounted, and drawn up to receive him, notwithstanding which, he continued his Resolution, and upon his approach the Rebels <reg orig="seem'd">seemed</reg> much to scorn the <reg orig="smallnesse">smallness</reg> of his number; but it pleased God so to order it. That after he had received their charge, he fell <unclear>o</unclear> upon them, and broke them, <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg> <em>Cardinesse's</em> Cornet, and <em>Porgiffin's</em> Cornet, and mortally wounded <unclear><reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg></unclear> <em>Wallis</em>, <reg orig="kil'd">killed</reg> two Horses of theirs, and took <reg orig="foure">four</reg>. The rest, although <reg orig="disperst">dispersed</reg>, got away well Mounted. He took 6 or 8 suits of Arms, being good Backs, and <reg orig="Brests">Breasts</reg>. Most of the Enemy had the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> Mark. We had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> two wounded and after two <reg orig="houres">hours</reg> keeping the field, he returned to <em><reg orig="Aire">Ayr</reg></em>. The Rebels were marching towards the Hills, but by this means it is supposed they will have no great mind to engage.</p>

<p>This day the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> and Forces march from hence to <em>Cardrosse</em>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Hills, where he will <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in the Fields for some time; <em>Glencairne</em> is come with some Forces into those parts.</p>

<p><em><reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg> May 20</em>. Wednesday at night last some Prisoners broke from their place of Durance; But were most of them retaken within two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after. <em>Middleton, Monroe, Athol</em> and <em>Forbes</em> are in <em><reg orig="Caithnesse">Caithness</reg></em> with their broken Regiments; <em>Kenmore</em> <reg orig="remaines">remains</reg> sick in <em>Southerland</em>, and hath been so for this <reg orig="moneth">month</reg> past. <em>Glencairne</em> and Col: <em>Drummond</em>, with some foot and Horse <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at <em>Abersoyle</em>, the most considerable pass to &amp; from the Hills, about 12 miles from <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em>; <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <em>Monk</em> is Marched that way to observe the <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Passes upon the <reg orig="Brayes">Brays</reg>, and to take some course with them.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 29.</head>

<p>The proceedings of the Commissioners at <em>Salters Hall</em>, which will give a great check to the abuses in the Common Law, will suddenly be confirmed by Authority, and be extant by the <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> of his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Hewson</em> and some other Commanders of the Army in <em>Ireland</em> having received further Instructions from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, are on their way towards <em>Ireland</em>. The Deputed Lord <em>Fleetwood</em> is every day expected, not to lay down, but to be confirmed in his Authority.</p>

<p>Something I have from <em>Rheims</em>, and the Coronation of the French King. The Fortune-teller, and his story is too long for this page, but I am sure of it, it is witty enough, I shall refer it to my next. There have been some Gentlemen lately apprehended in the pursuit of the Conspiracy against his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, of which more hereafter.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable: is,</p>

<p><i>The Law settled to <reg orig="rectifie">rectify</reg> the Common Law. The Report of the <reg orig="arrivall">arrival</reg> of the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>, in <em>Scotland</em> and the events thereupon. The landing of the Regiment of Col <em>Pride</em> in the North of <em>Scotland</em>, and the present posture of the <em><reg orig="Scots">Scot's</reg></em> Army, and Division betwixt <em>Glencairn</em> and Gen: <em>Middleton</em>. <em><reg orig="Glencairns">Glencairn's</reg></em> submitting <reg orig="himselfe">himself</reg>, and desiring a Capitulation. The remarkable Service performed by Gen <em>Monk</em> in the West of <em>Scotland</em>, and the Isle of <em>Mala</em>, and the contemplative condition of Prince <em>Rupert's</em> Melancholy in <em>France</em>.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>The most <reg orig="easie">easy</reg>, cheap, certain, and <reg orig="speedie">speedy</reg> way of curing the <em>French Pox</em>, and <em>running of the Reins</em>, without confining the Patient, either to keeping of house, or <reg orig="extremitie">extremity</reg> of <unclear>Flaming</unclear> <reg orig="Physick">Physic</reg>; and without having the least <reg orig="symptome">symptoms</reg> of the Disease behind either inward by pains, or outward by pustules, is carefully performed.</p>

<p>By the <reg orig="Physitian">Physician</reg> at the porch <unclear>guild</unclear> House in <reg orig="Maiden-head">Maidenhead</reg> Court in Aldersgate-street over against Peter-house.</p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>