<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell206">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 206</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, February: 21. to <em>Tuesday</em>, February: 28. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, February 21.</head>

<p>Let others think what they please, but unto me the superirrogating Star which was seen all <em>Wednesday</em> last in the afternoon (as if it would contend with the Sun for the supremacy of its glory) doth appear to be truly wonderful, the lustre, and the magnitude of it (when the Sun was down, and gone) did <reg orig="confesse">confess</reg> the efficacy of its influence by his <reg orig="scintulation">scintillation</reg>, at what time there was never beheld in the Firmament a more numerous appearance of the Stars, with admiration rather to look on his, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to manifest their own <reg orig="splendors">splendours</reg>.</p>

<p>And <reg orig="siace">since</reg> other men deliver their own judgments on it, why may not I assume the like freedom to <reg orig="expresse">express</reg> my own, and (without the vanity of Astrology) tell you, that it presageth Peace and <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> to the Nations, as did the Star called <em>Julium Sydus</em>, when <em>Augustus</em> by the hand of Peace did shut up the iron gates of War, and <em>Januus</em>; the Nations were then amazed at the change of the present Government, and so was<pb n="1" /> <em>Pliny</em> himself, the most excellent man amongst them, yet writing of this Star, and the consequences of it, he was convinced to conclude, <em>Et st verum fatemur, salutare id terris fuit</em>.</p>

<p>By Letters from beyond the Seas it was this day confirmed, that the Pope endeavouring to bring his <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> hairs with peace unto the grave, doth use all his power to work a reconciliation betwixt his two Sons the most <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> and the most Christian Kings; and this Mediation by Agents of undoubted knowledge and Authority hath already in a fair way advanced <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>.</p>

<p>The King of <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg></em> hath already gratulated our <em>Protector</em> by his Ambassador; and the King of <em>France</em> (as I am informed) is sending over an Ambassador to him, to salute his Highness in those words of complement by which Kings are accustomed to salute and gratulate one another. It is also advertised, that the King of <em>Denmark</em> is sending over that Ambassador who was here before, to congratulate his Highness, the Kings of <em>France</em> and <em>Denmark</em> hoping that their Interests are also included in the Peace with <em>Holland</em>.</p>

<p>The titular King of the <em>Scots</em> hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg> lately sick of a cold, but is now pretty well recovered. His Mother is altogether in her Devotions at <em>Chaloons</em>; on <em><reg orig="Ashwednesday">Ash Wednesday</reg></em> last she took her ashes from the hands of Mr. <em>Philips</em>, who was sometimes her Confessor in <em>England</em>.</p>

<p>Concerning the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, some Letters affirm that our Ambassador and the Grand Chancellor have had two meetings concerning the more <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> of our <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> with that Crown, and the Debates have not produced any such differences, but a <reg orig="successfull">successful</reg> issue may (it is hoped) be speedily obtained. The Chancellor being satisfied with our <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Commission, that he had a plenipotentiary power, did go over all the Articles in <reg orig="generall">general</reg>, and there appeared nothing so difficult which did not find an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> and a <reg orig="pleasie">pleasy</reg> interpretation. It is supposed they will not break, but after that Time hath ripened the Debates, we <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> receive an Answer to our full contentment. The change of the Government in <em>England</em> hath arrived to the knowledge of<pb n="2" /> the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, who (the Letters say) hath received the Credentials with all willingness; she bearing so great a respect to his Highness the Lord Protector, that (if we hear the truth) she hath desired to see his Picture.</p>

<p>But the Letters sent to <em>Holland</em> from <em>Swedeland</em> do affirm, that our Ambassador hath had <reg orig="severall">several</reg> Audiences since he came, and doth all he can to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> the Queen to an Amity, to which (they say) she hath <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> it but little inclination, and hath commanded her Subjects to give her a List of all their losses sustained by the <em>English</em>. The loss of divers Merchants of <em>Holland</em> hath caused the Admiralty there to prohibit all Masters of ships to set forth to Sea upon the penalty of one hundred pound <em>English</em> money, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> such time as the Peace with <em>England</em> be proclaimed.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Febr: 22</head>

<p>I shall in this place give you the Proclamation of <em>Glencarn</em>, and advertise you what is the <reg orig="successe">success</reg> that hath attended his <reg orig="threatnings">threatenings</reg>, and how low thereby the hearts of the <em>Highlanders</em> hath fallen.</p>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased his Majesty to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>, for opposing the common Enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, whom God in his justice hath permitted to overcome, and to be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we could turn to him by <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> repentance. And to the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies may be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires, and Parishes, and head Burghs by open Proclamation, that every one may make his several proportions ready to be delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under out of hand wheresoever the foresaid Officers shall come <unclear>or</unclear> send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and<pb n="3" /> without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of <reg orig="honor">honour</reg>, will move to their duty, may be proceeded against with fire and sword, unworthy to be looked upon as <em>Scotchmen</em>, to the terror of all false-hearted <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>, who by their treacheries and rebellions against their lawful King, and his just power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</p>

<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses has been brought forth from any <reg orig="wel">well</reg> affected person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said Horses has been taken, that they shall meet, and stent themselves equally, for having <reg orig="equall">equal</reg> burden, &amp; resound the persons from whom any Horses has been taken beyond their Proportions; and the just proportion of Horse now to be put forth, is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries forth of every thousand pound of Rent: and the proportion of foot, every third man; and what Dragoons are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one Dragoon. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes; where no Burghs are, the Provost and <reg orig="Baylies">Bailies</reg> of Burghs to Proclaim this at the Market Cross of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as you will answer the contrary at their highest peril. Given under our hand the first day of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p>

<p><i>Sic subsciribitur Glencarns.</i></p>
<p><i>God save King <em><reg orig="CHARLS">CHARLES</reg></em> the second.</i></p>

<head level="3"><em>From Daiketh</em> 14 <em>Febr</em>: 1653.</head>

<p>On Wednesday last Coll: <em>Morgan</em> with eight companies of Foot, 6 Troops of Horse, and three Troops of Dragoons, with a party of commanded horse out of the <em>Mearns</em> of <em>Angus</em>, marched from <em>Aberdeen</em>, and upon Thursday about two a clock we came to the <em>Lough</em> at the head of <em>Cromar</em>, where <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at a Rendezvous, and (after a little Dispute) he totally routed their Army, but being so near to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, he could do no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> to take and kill about<pb n="4" /> 140, having pursued them seven miles in the field; their General hardly escaping with about 40 Horse. After this engagement, Col: <em>Morgan</em> marched towards <em>Kildrummy</em>.</p>

<p>Nor was Cap: <em>Mutloe</em> in the Western <em>Highlands</em> idle, for hearing that the Laird of <em>Archaton</em> (being one of the chief Malignants in <em>Lorn</em>) had Garrisoned his house for the Enemy, he drew forth a party out of <em>Dunstaffenage</em>, and <em>Dunnelly</em>, fell upon the house, and took a Lieutenant with other Prisoners, and store of Ammunition, and arms. The Gent. And Heritors of the Shire of <em>Argyle</em> had lately a meeting with the Marquis thereof at <em>Innerara</em>, where they resolved not to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those people now in Arms; but to be ready at 24 hours warning to oppose them. The business of the <em>Lewis</em> was thus, <em>Normand macCloud</em> with 4 or 500 hundred men landed in <em>Lewis Island</em>, and after 3 or 4 days staying in some <reg orig="in-accessible">inaccessible</reg> places of the Isle, fell upon our <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, who lay at Sternway out of the Fort, and killed 12 of them; but a party out of the Fort beat them thence, relieved the remainder of the men, removed the Goods into the Fort, and burnt the houses. The last week Lieu: Coll: <em>Cottrel</em> <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> out of Glasgow, to reduce the Garrison of Rodsew <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Loughlomand, and before he came <reg orig="neer">near</reg> it, the Enemy ran away, and left word they had no order to fight. We hear also that <em>Brockie</em> Capt: Lieut: to the late Col: <em>Wogan</em>, is dead of his wounds; and the Earl of <em>Athol</em> that fires and burns <reg orig="folks">folk's</reg> corn, and horses, <reg orig="threatned">threatened</reg> to shoot <em>Holland</em> the <reg orig="Chyrurgeon">Chirurgeon</reg> unto death, for not curing <em>Wogan</em> and <em>Brockie</em>. Some of those blades begins to cry <em>Peccavi</em>, and sends to desire liberty to live peaceably; and no doubt <unclear>here</unclear> long they will betray one another into our hands. This day the Lord <em>Salender</em> is apprehended upon an information against him of <reg orig="correspondencie">correspondence</reg>.</p>

<p>By Letters from the North it is advertised, that Captain <em>Pack</em> hath taken a <em>Dutch</em> Man of War, who for seven years together fought very stoutly, but was at the last <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to submit; we slew seven of his men, and wounded 15. At the first beginning of the fight her Topmast was shot by the <reg orig="bord">board</reg>, and in her fall, her tackling being unable to hold her up, she<pb n="5" /> bruised many of her own men; the ship was so torn betwixt wind and water that she was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> sinking, whereupon we were <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to rough her at our stern to the Port of <em>Grimsby</em>.</p>

<p>Captain <em>Fester</em> hath also advertised, that according to his Instructions he repaired to the River of <em>Humber</em>, but being <reg orig="hindred">hindered</reg> by <reg orig="Northernly">Northerly</reg> winds, and thick weather, he gave notice thereof to the rest of the Commanders appointed to go along with him in the Expedition, the <em>Amity</em> came up to him, and the wind standing to the North and North west, our two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> standing along the Dagger did fall in amongst the Busses of the <em>Hollanders</em>, who had two Men of War to be their Convoy, the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> made up with a high wind towards one of them, and the <em>Amity</em> towards the other, but the lusty ship which the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> took to be a Man of War proved to be a ship belonging to <em>Swedeland</em>, which was laden with Coals from <em>Newcastle</em> But some other Goods which were prohibited being found on <reg orig="bord">board</reg> of her, and she having twice the number of men to sail such a ship, she was brought by the <em>Ph&oelig;nix</em> into the River of <em>Humber</em>. I am informed this is the same ship which was brought into the Port of <em>Grimsby</em>.</p> 

<p>But that ship which to which the <em>Amity</em> did advance, did indeed prove to be at enmity with <em>England</em>, she was a ship of 20 Guns, and about 80 men; although she was not of the same bulk as the <em>Amity</em>, yet she fought most bravely for the space of 2 hours, but her Top-mast being shot by the <reg orig="bord">board</reg> also, and most of the men being slain, or wounded, she was forced to submit.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Febr: 23.</head>

<p>It was this Day confirmed that the Duke of <em>Lorraign</em> being arrested by the Authority of the Arch Duke, was brought to <em>Antwerp</em>, where he is kept close Prisoner in the Castle, many of his menial servants are also arrested, and distributed into several Prisons; it is said that he endeavoured to betray the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and his Army to the King of <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>It is certified from <em>Germany</em>, that in some parts thereof the ground hath been almost covered with innumerable forts of Mice of several complexions, which have devoured the grass in the fields, and the grain in the barns, so that they conceive<pb n="6" /> this plague to be not only a Fore runner of Famine, but of a new War, to the apprehension of which they have been terrified with a blazing Star, not much unlike to that which was beheld all <em>Europe</em> over, a little before the <em>German</em> Wars began.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Febr: 24.</head>

<p>It was this Day advertised that the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>, and the <em>Constant Warwick</em> had rescued the <em>Samaritan</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, and a Pink belonging unto <em>Plymouth</em>, which were both taken by Captain <em>Beach</em>, who was <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to leave them, and had much to do to escape himself, but a companion of his, an old <em>Picaro</em> was taken in the <em>Samaritan</em>, and is now in hold in the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Febr: 25.</head>

<p>I made mention before of a great Victory obtained against <em>Glencarn</em> by <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em>, where in the fight, and the pursuit one hundred and twenty of the enemy were killed and seven and twenty taken prisoners, with all their Arms, and Ammunition, and about fourscore Horse; The Letters this Day make mention of another Victory obtained by <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Daniel</em> not far from <em>Dunkel</em>, where the Enemy had a considerable Garrison, this party of the <em>Highlanders</em> were commanded by the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, and Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg></em>, who misdoubting their strength, in a disordered march retreated to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, leaving the Garrison well manned, which our men immediately attempted with pickaxes, and other Instruments, being come under the <reg orig="wals">walls</reg> without any great <reg orig="losse">loss</reg>; in a short time they became Masters of one part of the House, and three of the Enemy being slain, the rest cried out for Quarter, which was granted to them. The Castle because it should be no more a receptacle for such dangerous persons, was consumed with fire.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, Febr: 27.</head>

<p>By Letters from <em>Scotland</em> it was this Day advertised, that the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, Sir <em>Arthur <reg orig="Forbs">Forbes</reg>, Glencarn</em>, and <em>Kenmore</em>, are <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> together in one Body, but their Forces are so broken, and discouraged, that they are unable to make any present opposition, there were taken in the Earl of <em><reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg></em> House,</p><pb n="7" />

<p>Two Lieutenants. One hundred Pikes.</p>
<p>One Ensign which blew. Fifteen case of Pistols.</p>
<p>One Quartermaster. Store of swords, and other Arms.</p>
<p>Two <reg orig="Serjeants">Sergeants</reg> Sixteen barrels of Powder.</p>
<p>Two Cornets. Five and twenty Troop horses.</p>
<p>120 <reg orig="Bouldiers">Boulders</reg> Great store of Meal, Malt and Oats</p>
<p>Fourscore Muskets.</p>

<p>I have this morning seen a Letter which informs that the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors are landed at <em>Harwich</em>; it is believed that this Day they will come to <em>London</em>; Sir <em>Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg></em> House in the <reg orig="Pallace">Palace</reg> yard is prepared for them.</p>

<p>On <em>Saturday</em> night last the Countess <em>Dewager</em> of <em>Excester</em> <reg orig="dyed">dyed</reg> <reg orig="snddenly">suddenly</reg> at her House in Saint<em> Johns</em>. This Day being the <reg orig="Joal">Gaol</reg> Delivery at <em>Newgate</em>, three Men, and one Woman was hanged in <em><reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg></em>, and five at <em>Tyburn</em>, those who suffered in <em><reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg></em> had broken there into the <em>Greyhound</em> Tavern, robbed the House, and <reg orig="desperatly">desperately</reg> wounded the Vintner himself; The Robbery was attended with such circumstances of aggravation, that it was thought fit they should be made exemplar by losing their lives in the same place where the Robbery was committed. The Letters make mention of other great Robberies at <em><reg orig="Maydenhead">Maidenhead</reg></em>, and other places at <em>Salisbury</em>. Fifteen <reg orig="Highway-men">Highwaymen</reg> have been lately taken, and brought to <em>Bedford </em> <reg orig="Joal">Gaol</reg>. There was a Bill exhibited this last Sessions against a <reg orig="Counsellor">Councillor</reg> for corruption, which was nine yards in length, and a foot in <reg orig="bredth">breadth</reg>.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>The landing of the <em>Dutch</em> Ambassadors at <em>Harwich</em>. A great fight at Sea. And another Victory obtained against the <em>Highlanders</em> in <em>Scotland</em>; a List of the Commanders. Officers, and others that were slain, and taken Prisoners. The last News of the titular King of <em>Scotland</em>. The wonderful apparitions in the Heavens, and the fruits of the Earth in some places covered, and devoured with mice. The inclinations of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> in reference to the Treaty with the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>. The Duke of <em>Lorraign</em> close Prisoner at <em>Antwerp</em>. And the Prince of <em>Conde</em> hanged in his effigies at <em>Paris</em>.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>