<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell330">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 330</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, May 2. to <em>Tuesday</em>, May 9. 1654.</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, May 2.</head>

<p>Although the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> is said to resign her Crown to her Kinsman <em>Carolus Gustavus Adolphus</em>, yet those who pretend to know much of the State affairs, do much doubt of it, in regard that if she should resign the <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Authority, her Demands are so great for the maintenance of her own Port, that but little would be left during her life, for the maintenance of the Royal Authority in her Successor, and this the Prince Palatine hath complained of, and seems to decline the present Government upon that account, what they will conclude upon, Time will shortly manifest, for the News of the Peace of <em>England</em>, with <em>Holland</em>, is no doubt brought to their ears before this time, which will cause new <reg orig="Counsels">Councils</reg> in almost all the Courts of Christendom.</p>

<p>In the next place we will give you the <reg orig="ful">full</reg> substance of the Articles concluded betwixt his Highness the Lord Protector,<pb n="1" /> and the States <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the <em>United Provinces</em>.</p>

<p>It is agreed that there shall be an inviolable Peace, and a <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> Alliance betwixt the two <reg orig="Common.wealths">Commonwealths</reg>. 2. That all Hostility shall cease both by Sea, and Land. 3. That all Offences, and <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg> sustained since the beginning of the War <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be forgotten, and perfect abolition to be of all things. 4. That all Prisoners of what condition soever shall be discharged. 5. That the two Commonwealths shall remain confederate friends against all whomsoever, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="disturbe">disturb</reg> either State by sea, or Land, or being declared Enemies to the freedoms, and liberties of the people <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> shelter themselves under either of the said Governments. 6. That neither of the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> may make, do, act, deal, or undertake against the other, but shall actually oppose all whomsoever, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> act, or deal, or undertake <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> against either <reg orig="Common_wealths">Commonwealths</reg>. 7. That neither <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, nor the people dwelling or residing therein, shall give, or lend any help, counsel, or favour to the Enemies, or Rebels of either, upon pain of Treason. 8. That the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> assist each other as need shall require by sea and Land, with men and ships, at the charge of the parties who desire the same. 9. That neither of the <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, or the people thereof shall receive any person or persons, which by their <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall be declared Enemies, Rebels, or Fugitives. 10. That in case either <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> by their <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Letters shall declare unto the other, that any persons are their Enemies, &amp;c: then upon such notice the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> where such person or persons resideth, shall warn them to depart within 28. <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death, and loss of Lands. 11. That no Rebel of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> shall be received, or suffered to remain in any of<pb n="2" /> the Castles, Cities, Havens, and Cricks, or other places <reg orig="priviledged">privileged</reg> within the Jurisdiction of the <em>United Provinces</em>. 12. That the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the people thereof, and the <em>United Provinces</em>, and the Inhabitants of the same, shall be bound to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> each other with all love, and friendship. 13. That the ships of the United Provinces meeting in the Narrow Seas any of the English Men of War, shall strike the <reg orig="Flagg">Flag</reg> as in former times. 14. That neither of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> shall receive in any of their <reg orig="Harbors">Harbours</reg>, or assist, or refresh any <em><reg orig="Pyrat">Pirate</reg></em>, or Sea Rovers. 15. That either of the <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> do make a Treaty of Amity with any <reg orig="Republicks">Republics</reg>, Princes or States, they shall comprehend each other, in case they desire it. 16. That if <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> shall be done, or committed by any of the People of either party against this Treaty, by Land or Sea, the confederation <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not be broken, but the particular party shall be punished, <em>&amp;c.</em> 17. That the People of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> may freely, and with all safety travel through all quarters of the <em>United Provinces</em> to drive their Trade, armed, or unarmed, and the people of the <em>United Provinces</em> shall have the like <reg orig="priviledg">privilege</reg> here.</p>

<p>18. That in case any <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships of either State by any accidents be driven into any Havens, <em>&amp;c</em>. they may depart at their pleasure without paying Customs, if they break not Bulk. 19. That the Merchants, Skippers, <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg>, <em>&amp;c.</em> of either <reg orig="Common.wealths">Commonwealths</reg>, their ships, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall not be Arrested, nor seized to serve at War, unless upon inevitable necessity. 20. That the Merchants, and Skippers on both sides, when they go on Land, may carry any weapons of defence, and offence. 21. That the Men of War of both <reg orig="Common.wealths">Commonwealths</reg> meeting, and holding one course, shall defend, and protect each other. 22. That if any ships be taken by a third party, they shall do their endeavour to recover the same, and restore it at the charges of the owners. 23. That the Searchers, and other Officers shall regulate themselves according to the Laws of either <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg>. 24. That in case any injury be done by any people of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> contrary to this Treaty, no Letters of Mart shall be granted until<pb n="3" /> Justice have been sought in an ordinary way. 25. That all persons on both sides going to Sea with particular Commissions, shall give security that they shall do no <reg orig="dammage">damage</reg> to either side. 26. That it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be lawful for the People on either side to repair to any Port, <em>&amp;c.</em> with <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, and Men of War to victual, <em>&amp;c.</em> 27. That Justice be done against such as are living which had a hand in the business of <em>Amboyna</em>. 28. That the King of <em>Denmark</em> pay 14000 <em>l</em>. for seizing some <em>English</em> ships, and Goods, and other injuries, are referred to arbitration. 29. This Obligation being performed, all acts of Hostility between the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the King of <em>Denmark</em> are to cease, and Ambassadors from <em>Denmark</em> are to be admitted with the like honour, as the Ambassadors of other States who are friends with <em>England</em>. 30. That Commissioners to meet of injuries, <em>&amp;c.</em> shall meet in <em>London</em> the 18 of this instant <em>May</em>. 31. That both parties shall firmly keep this Treaty. 32. That such as the States at any time shall make Captain General, <em>&amp;c:</em> shall be bound by Oath to confirm this Treaty. 33. That all this Treaty shall be confirmed by the Lord Protector, and the States General.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, May, 4.</head>

<p>By the Post from <em>Leith</em> in <em>Scotland</em> thus. We conceive the enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagued with their inroads upon the Lowlands, where they burnt and destroyed all that stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfrieze">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reason of these mischiefs, and our loss is want of Intelligence from amongst them, for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce squeeze ten true words out of them, we hear that <em>Middleton</em> is gotten out of <em>Southerland</em>, <reg orig="wherin">wherein</reg> <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="intrapt">entrapped</reg> his Horse, or force him to fight until some greater numbers be added to <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em>Morgan</em>, and then it's likely the Enemy <reg orig="wil">will</reg> play fast and loose, in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em>Yorks</em> coming to them, and then all the Country voluntarily to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him, but 'tis thought the Peace with <em>Holland</em> <reg orig="wil">will</reg><pb n="4" /> cross their expectations; and indeed the Letters from <em>Holland</em> say, that there is News, that <em><reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em> are going to the <em>Spaw</em> in expectation to meet the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> <reg orig="wil">will</reg> shortly return thence.</p>

<p>In <em>Holland</em> there is also News that <em>France</em>, and <em>Spain</em> have had a Treaty for making a League for ten years, but some say it will not take effect.</p>

<p>Gen: <em>Pen</em> is gone to Gen: <em>Blake</em> with the Fleet, and hath carried down Instructions from the Lord Protector, and his Council, which are not yet fit to be published.</p>

<p>The <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador had late Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>His Highness hath a foot Guard to his Person, and to carry up meat of 60, they have not Coats with Cullissances after the old fashion, but have grey Cloaks with black velvet <reg orig="Collers">Collars</reg>, and black velvet, and silver lace, they have 50 <em>l. per annum</em> <reg orig="a peece">apiece</reg> <reg orig="sallary">salary</reg>.</p>

<p>Lieut <reg orig="Coll">Col</reg>: <em><reg orig="Lilburns">Lilburn's</reg></em> Friends have sent to him about a <em>Habeas Corpus</em>, they have yet no Answer returned.</p>

<head level="3"><i>By the Lord Protector: a Proclamation.</i></head>

<p><em>OLIVER</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Dominions thereto belonging. Whereas the Commissioners appointed by Us to treat with the Ambassadors Extraordinary of the United Provinces; and the said Ambassadors, by way of Explanation of the third of those Articles of Peace, lately concluded between this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and that of the United <em>Netherlands</em>, and for removing of all questions and differences that may arise thence from Have agreed, and concluded the following Article, <em>viz</em>: <i>That whereas in the third of those Articles of Peace, Union, and Confederation made established and <reg orig="promulged">promulgated</reg> between the Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, and the Lords the States General of the United<pb n="5" /> Provinces, it is agreed, That all Injuries, Charges, and <reg orig="Dammages">Damages</reg>, either party hath sustained by the other since the 18 of May in the year one thousand six hundred fifty two shall be taken away, and forgotten in such manner as that hereafter neither party shall pretend any matter against the other. &amp;c.</i></p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, May 5.</head>

<p>This Day afforded memorable Intelligence from several places, as that the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> fallen out with Prince <em>Rupert</em>, for selling the Guns belonging to the great ship called the <em>Swallow</em>, there was in her fifty brass <reg orig="peeces">pieces</reg> of Ordnance; the titular King of the <em>Scots</em> was seldom seen so much out of his own temper, which it is thought would have declared <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> by some effects, had not the certain News of Peace betwixt <em>England</em>, and <em>Holland</em> made them shake hands. Two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> who had a long time exercised their <reg orig="Pyracy">Piracy</reg> about the Bay of <em>Biscay</em>, having sent their men on <reg orig="shoar">shore</reg> for fresh meat, had their men <reg orig="intrapped">entrapped</reg>, and two <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> were taken by the Men of War of <em><reg orig="Burdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>. The Commissioners for the Protestants (the setting forth of the <em>English</em> Fleet having <reg orig="alarumed">alarmed</reg> the King of <em>France</em>) have at last received a <reg orig="gratious">gracious</reg> answer, according to their desires. Letters from <em>France</em> advertise, that there was seen over the City of <em>Paris</em>, a blazing Comet, which shot her <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> Train towards the North; some interpret that it pretends great miseries, and to speak the truth, four hundred of the <reg orig="Malecontents">Malcontents</reg> murmuring themselves into a conspiracy, and crying out in the streets. No <em>Mazarin</em>, no <em>Tillier</em>, no <em>Servient</em>, the Provost with a strong Guard came to suppress them, and falling <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> to blows, divers slain, and divers wounded on both sides. The great overthrow given to the <em>Christians</em> by the <em>Turks</em>, is confirmed.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, May 6.</head>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Sweden</em>, that the Queen is resigning her Crown, it is said that her Debts grew so high, that she was forced to it. A strange thing it is, her Father having conquered<pb n="6" /> almost all the most famous Cities of the Empire, and got into his hands almost all the wealth of the Empire, that his Daughter should be said to resign her Crown for want of money, I cannot <reg orig="beleeve">believe</reg> it, but do so sling it by as some Malignant aspersion, for <reg orig="wot">what</reg> you what? the Letters do affirm, that the Peace with <em>Swedeland</em> is concluded and by this time signed, and that my Lord Ambassador is in his way towards <em>England</em>, with great satisfaction, that he shall bring along with him the Alliance of a Nation so powerful, and considerable as the <em>Swedes</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that the differences amongst the Grand <reg orig="Commadders">Commanders</reg> of the <em>Highlanders</em> do still continue, and yet for all that, many daily are flocking to them. Those of <em>Loughaber</em> who were about 1200. in number, were all marching homewards again, but some say by the <reg orig="sollicitations">solicitations</reg> of the Lord <em>Lorn</em> they returned. As strong as <em>Middleton</em> is, he dares not <reg orig="incounter">encounter</reg> us, for he no sooner saw Col: <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Forces on the other side the River, but thinking the <em>English</em> Army had wings (as <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> it was said) that <em><reg orig="Alexanders">Alexander's</reg></em> had, he <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> retreated towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, &amp; those places that were supposed to be impossible, some say that he had so <reg orig="harrassed">harassed</reg> <em>Southerland</em>, and <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, that he was <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to look for new Quarters, the Countries being so <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> exhausted, that he could continue there no longer. The Letters affirm that Gen: <em>Middleton</em> was very angry with <em>Glencarn</em>, and the other Commanders for marching into <em>Southerland</em> without his Orders for his directions were, that they should stay in <em><reg orig="Rosse">Ross</reg></em> to have secured that great Passado, but our Horse and Foot from the Garrison of <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> were so terrible unto them, that they durst not obey his Commands. The <em>Hollanders</em> having almost lost all the footing they had in <em>Brazil</em> it is high time to send relief to their friends there; five Men of War are designed for that service, some Galliots are ordered to call in the <em>Freebooters</em>. A Fleet of about 100 sail having with them a considerable Convoy, are gone forth of the <em>Texel</em>, being bound for <em>Spain, Portugal</em>, and the West of <em>France</em>.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, May 8.</head>

<p>There is a great ship come from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> laden with all sorts of <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg> <reg orig="cloath">cloth</reg>, and will make amends for that lately taken by the <em>French</em>. Our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken seven <em>French</em> <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships, three whereof are sent into <em>Plymouth</em>.</p>

<p>It is advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that Gen: <em>Monk</em> is at <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> and on his march towards <em>Aberdeen</em>, where if the wind be favourable, there <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be more Forces ready to attend him. <em>Middleton</em> being dislodged from <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, is now tugging with the Rocks, &amp; <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, where the miserable <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> of the place defends <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> from the necessity of the Soldiers, for the Country is so barren, they can make no <reg orig="wast">waste</reg> in it. <em>Glengarry</em> was lately in the <em>Island of Mula</em>. Our Garrison of <em>Ayr</em> have lately snapped some that were going to him.</p>

<p>Our Fleet are to be in the <em>Downs</em> on the middle of this week, the formidable strength whereof doth not only <reg orig="Alarum">Alarm</reg> <em>France</em> but the common Enemy of Christendom, the <em>Turks</em>, who finding Peace made with <em>Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>, and that we have no visible Enemies abroad, but a few inconsiderable <em>Scots</em> do begin to fear that in holy Wars our courage will be <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, and draw no swords but what are sanctified.</p>

<p>That which this week is most remarkable, is:</p>

<p><i>&#x261e; The Peace made, and Signed betwixt the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>, and the Crown of <em>Sweden</em>, and the Return of the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>. The advance of Gen: <em>Monk</em> from <em><reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg></em> to <em>Aberdeen</em>, and the flight of Gen: <em>Middleton</em> from <em><reg orig="Caithnes">Caithness</reg></em>, to the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg> and Mountains. Several <em>Scots</em> taken Prisoners by the Garrison of <em>Ayr</em>, and the taking of several Prizes from the <em>French</em>. The dreadful Comet seen over the City of <em>Paris</em>. The <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Insurrection that followed, and divers slain and wounded on both sides. The great disagreement betwixt the titular K: of <em>Scots</em>, and Prince <em>Rupert</em>. And the formidable <em>English</em> Fleet gone out to Sea and <reg orig="Randezvous">Rendezvous</reg> on the <em>Downs</em>, in order to the great Design in hand.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>A dark <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> <reg orig="Nagg">Nag</reg>, with a <reg orig="bal'd">bald</reg> face, one wall eye, three white <reg orig="leggs">legs</reg>, and about thirteen handfuls and a half high; <reg orig="stol'n">stolen</reg> the 18th day of <em>April</em> 1654. out of a stable at <em>Ogbourne</em> Saint <em>George</em>, <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Marlburrough">Marlborough</reg></em> in <em>Wiltshire</em>: if any can give notice <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg> unto <em>Francis Eglesfield</em> Stationer, at the <em><reg orig="Marygold">Marigold</reg></em> in St: <em>Paul's</em> <reg orig="Church-yard">Churchyard</reg>, or unto <em>John Hammond</em> Bookseller in <em><reg orig="Marlburrough">Marlborough</reg></em>, they shall receive full content.</p>


<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>