<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WIntell202">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Intelligencer, Issue 202</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">THE</head>
<head level="1">Weekly Intelligencer</head>
<head level="2">OF THE</head>
<head level="2"><reg orig="COMMON-WEALTH">COMMONWEALTH</reg></head>
<head level="2">Faithfully communicating all Af-</head>
<head level="3">fairs both Martial and Civil.</head>

<hr />
<p>From <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 24. to <em>Tuesday</em>, January: 31. 1653</p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>F. Neile</em> in Aldersgate-street.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em>, January: 24.</head>

<p>I made mention in my last of the report that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> in her own person did meet the English Ambassador a mile from her own Court; and this we had from those who came lately from <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em>, but this Day Letters came from <em>Sweden</em>, giving a full account thereof, and expressing that it was not the Queen in her own person that met the Ambassador, but two of her own <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. The Letter maketh mention at large of my Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> tedious Journey by Land in the depth of Winter, from <em><reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg></em> to <em>Upsall</em>, where the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> had then her Court, which was not without many inconveniences, and great <reg orig="expences">expenses</reg>, some of the Retinue being <reg orig="inforced">enforced</reg> to <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in straw, for want of other Lodging. The Queen sent our Ambassador word that she was astonished at his being advanced so far in his Journey, it being much beyond her expectation, and that she was resolved to receive him with more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary respect, for the which preparation could not be made in so short a time <pb n="1" />as we might come from <em>Encopin</em> to <em>Upsall</em>. It was therefore her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> desire that his Excellency should repose himself until Monday at <em>Encopin</em>, and then to come two Leagues to a <reg orig="Gentlemans">Gentleman's</reg> House, which the <em>Grand Master</em> had commanded to be provided for him. And from thence upon Thursday to come to <em>Upsall</em> where the Queen was My Lord knew no other answer to this desire, and in this place, but to submit to it, the rather because our Baggage was not come up to us, for want of Horses with which Mr. <em><reg orig="Stapilton">Stapleton</reg></em> continued, and took extraordinary pains and care, and endured many hardships in his attendance upon that charge.</p>

<p>Tuesday morning my Lord went from thence towards <em>Upsall</em>, the weather continuing <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hard, half a League before we came to Town, the Master of Ceremonies met him, and told him that the Queen had sent him to congratulate his safe arrival, and to conduct him to <em>Upsall</em>: about a quarter of a League from the Town, two Senators met him, that is, two of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of State met him, they spake to him in the <em>Swedish</em> tongue, to the same effect the Master of Ceremonies had done, as I understood by their Interpreter; My Lord answered them in English, that the respect which her Majesty did bear to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, appeared in her honourable reception of him their Servant, which he desired to <reg orig="acknowledg">acknowledge</reg> with thanks to her Majesty, they then brought him into a rich Coach of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>; where the two Senators, and Master of Ceremonies sate with him. There were divers other Coaches of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg>, in all eighteen: every one with six horses, and a great many of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> servants on Horse back, they brought my Lord to my Lodging, and then left him: The rooms of Entertainment, and four or five Bed-chambers were furnished with the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Hangings, and Beds: The Bed in his own chamber was richly Embroidered with Gold; about half an hour after, came in a Gentleman of the Bed-chamber to my Lord, and told him that the Queen had sent to see how he did after his Journey, to bid him <reg orig="welcom">welcome</reg>, and my Lord returned his thanks to her Majesty: a little after him, Mr: <em>Lagerfeildt</em> <pb n="2" />came to see my Lord, and told him the Queen commanded him to come unto him, and to take care that if he wanted any <reg orig="accomodation">accommodation</reg> we might be <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg>.</p>

<p>Then the Master of the Ceremonies desired of him copy of his Credentials, which he had ready, and gave to him, who <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> them presently to the Queen, and left them with her and returned back to accompany his Lordship to Supper. In a Lobby next to the withdrawing Room, is a constant guard of the Qu: <reg orig="Partizans">Partisans</reg>, beyond that a very fair Room, which was very <reg orig="wel">well</reg> furnished, with a great deal of plate, and many wax candles in it; two Tables were plentifully <reg orig="furnish't">furnished</reg>, the one for my Lord, the other for his Steward; over the <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> seat was a canopy of State. About the middle of Supper the Master of Ceremonies rose from his seat, and came to him, and with a great glass of Wine begun to him a health to the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em>; my Lord told him, That it was neither agreeable to his Judgment, nor to the practice of those whom he served in <em>England</em>, to drink, or <reg orig="pledg">pledge</reg> any health. He pressed it earnestly upon my Lord, and his Lordship as earnestly refused it; and some words of a little heat passed betwixt them, but being in French, every body did not take notice of it; he then began a health to Capt: <em>James Whitlock</em> who likewise refused it. Then he began a health to Dr: <em>Whittler</em>, who refusing it, the Master of Ceremonies in a slighting way desired him to give it some other name; the Dr: answered, That if he pleased he might call it a eating &amp; health; When the Master of Ceremonies saw himself thus resisted, he was quiet, and seemed much displeased, and my Lord no <reg orig="lesse">less</reg>. After Supper, Mr: <em>Lagerfieldt</em>: came to us again, to whom the Ambassador related this passage at Supper, and desired that our liberty, and the manner of our Country might be reserved to himself, and company, which he said was most fitting, and he would take care that the like should not be done hereafter. Then the Lord <em>Whitlock</em> desired my Lord <em>Lagerfieldt</em> to move the Queen that if she pleased he might have his Audience before the Holidays which he very willingly undertook to do, and it sped well, for the next day <pb n="3" />my Lord <em>Lagerfieldt</em> brought my Lord word, that the Queen was very ready to <reg orig="gratifie">gratify</reg> his Request, and had appointed him Audience upon Friday, till which time our Entertainment will be her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> charge: We are put to great inconvenience at this place for want of Beds, most of our company lying upon straw, but the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> Officers <unclear>have</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> to the Country, and we are in <unclear>hope to have</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters--></unclear> <unclear>brought to</unclear> here shortly. The <unclear>Plague continues</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 3 characters --></unclear> at <em>Stockholm</em> and there is no speech of the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> removing <unclear>thither</unclear>. My Lord is <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> weary of our long, and great <unclear>Feasting</unclear>.</p>

<p>Yesterday the Queen was not well, but kept her bed, but this day she was abroad again. We shall prove <unclear>Frenchmen</unclear>; that Language is more spoken at the Court, <reg orig="then">than</reg> any other. By this time I presume you are weary of my long Letter; I <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> reserve my self until after my <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Audience, when you may look to be troubled again. The Audience is to be tomorrow afternoon.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Wednesday</em>, Jan: 25.</head>

<p>I made mention in my last, that the Lord <em>Lorn</em> Eldest Son to the Marquis of <em>Argyle</em>, was upon some disagreement gone from the Lord <em>Glencairn</em>. The reason (as since we are informed) is, that the Army of the Enemy being in <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> <reg orig="Fathers">Father's</reg> Country, he intended to have the chief command of them himself, especially of those who were there <reg orig="Leavied">Levied</reg>, which he finding that he could not obtain, and that he was resolutely opposed by <em>Glencairn</em>, he fled away by night, with all the <reg orig="hast">haste</reg> that his Horse could take, and was only attended but with six followers, <em>Glencairn</em> sent <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> after him, and to bring him back alive or dead, but could not overtake him. <em>Glencairn</em> was advertised by <em><reg orig="Lorns">Lorn's</reg></em> own Messenger, that <em>Lorn</em> had sent a Letter to one of our Officers who commanded a Castle not far off, to advise him where to fall on <em>Glencairn</em> with the best advantage, <em>Glencairn</em> having read the Letter, and told the bearer that he was truer to his Country, <reg orig="then">than</reg> his Master, drew up a Party to strengthen his Quarters, and having apprehended seven or eight of those who were most familiar with <em>Lorn</em>, he put them all into custody, and intends <pb n="4" />if the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> find through numerous, are so unserviceable for want of Arms, both for Horse and Foot, that six hundred of our Soldiers in all probability overcome them.</p>

<p>It is further advertised from <em>Scotland</em>, that Captain <em>Crosse</em>, Captain <unclear>Lieutenant</unclear> <unclear><!-- approx. 3 characters --></unclear> Captain <em><unclear>Ozey</unclear></em> with a party from <em>Saint <reg orig="Johnstons">Johnstone</reg></em> is <unclear>into</unclear> the Quarters of about forty of the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> Horse, and took ten Prisoners, and sixteen Horses, and killed two on the place. <unclear><!-- approx. 9 characters --></unclear> Body of the Enemy is now fallen into <em><unclear>Murrayland</unclear></em> where they are <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> their Assessments, and indeed to <unclear>debate</unclear> all correspondence betwixt <em>Aberdeen</em> and <em>Innernes</em>. Colonel <em><unclear>Morgan</unclear></em> is drawing all the Forces of the North, to driveth them out from thence.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Thursday</em>, Jan: 26.</head>

<p>The English Regiments of Horse and Foot in <em>Scotland</em>, are these.</p>

<p>General <em>Monk</em>. <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Daniel's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Rodes">Rode's</reg></em> <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Fitch's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Oklyes">Oakley's</reg></em> <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Ashfield's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Fenwicks">Fenwick's</reg></em>.<reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Sebbett's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Riches">Rich's</reg></em> <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg><em>Salmon's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Fairfaxes">Fairfax's</reg></em> <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Tomlinson's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Twistletons">Twistleton's</reg></em> Part of <reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em>Sanderson's</em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> The company at <em><reg orig="Dunbarton">Dumbarton</reg></em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Overtons">Overton's</reg></em> <unclear><!--8 characters--></unclear> going to <em>Scotland</em></p>
<p>That which was M.G. <em><reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg></em> Major General <em><reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg></em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Alweds">Alwed's</reg></em> Commis: Gen: <em><reg orig="Whaleyes">Whaley's</reg></em></p>
<p><reg orig="Collonel">Colonel</reg> <em><reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg></em> Sir <em>William<reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg>.</em></p>

<p>It is again confirmed from <em>Scotland</em>, that the Commander of our Garrison at <em>Drummond</em> having sent forth a party of thirty Horse, to rescue a flock of Sheep, which the <em>Highlanders</em> had drove away in the face of the Castle, they were <reg orig="overpowred">overpowered</reg> by the Enemy, who killed the Lieutenant, the Cornet, the Corporal, and some Troopers, and took others, but they did not fall unrevenged, for those who fought stoutest, were many of them wounded, and some slain, in which number was he who commanded them in chief he was the first himself that fell, and by his Death taught the rest to <reg orig="dye">die</reg> honourably.</p><pb n="5" />

<p>Letters this Day read upon the Exchanged, make mention of several Prizes brought in <em>Holland</em>, where the conclusion of a Treaty with <em>England</em> makes a great noise, but finds no certainty at all: It is confirmed that they are there making ready twenty new ships, of thirty eight foot broad, and some one hundred and thirty, some one hundred and forty, and some one hundred and fifty foot in length. There are divers Ambassadors from several Princes come to the <em>Hague</em>, what there business is, time will suddenly make known. The <em>Dutch</em> Merchants that were in <em>France</em> understanding that our Fleet were at Sea, sailed towards their own Country on the back side of <em>Ireland</em>, truly conceiving, that the furthest way about is the <reg orig="neerest">nearest</reg> way home. It is said that two hundred sail from <em>Holland</em> designed to <em><reg orig="Spaine">Spain</reg>, Portugal</em>, and the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, are to sail round about also that way.</p> 

<p>Our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> have taken this week from the <em>Hollanders</em> five ships belonging to <em>Holland</em>, and sunk two of their ships on the Coasts of <em>France</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Friday</em>, Januar: 27.</head>

<p>Part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church at the South side thereof did fall down this afternoon, some of the Rubbish did fall on the head of a child and sorely hurt it, and bruised the left side of his body; no other harm was done by it as I can learn.</p>

<p>I shall in this place give you the substance of the Speech of the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>. He declared, that although the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> are not <reg orig="incouraged">encouraged</reg> to send abroad when they reflect upon the barbarous usage of their Messengers in some places, yea in her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Government they have not the least <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>, but gracefully acknowledged their experience to the contrary; From thence he proceeded to the deliverances of the Armies of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, which have been <reg orig="wonderfull">wonderful</reg>, and touched upon the excellencies of her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Person and Government, making a comparison betwixt her and Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>. He then made mention of the Wars of her Father for the orthodox Religion, and just liberties, which were also the occasions of the Wars of this <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> both in <pb n="6" /><em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, in which GOD was <reg orig="alwayes">always</reg> pleased to determine for the Parliament, and after 8 tenders of a Treaty for Peace to change the Government of <em>England</em> which was occasioned through the extremity of the ill government of the Successors of Queen <em>Elizabeth</em>, who although <reg orig="forreiners">foreigners</reg> had otherwise received all obedience and subjection from her people. He then made a <reg orig="similltude">similitude</reg> betwixt the Nations of <em>England</em> and <em>Swedeland</em> in language, manners, and dispositions; and that in no Age there hath been a declared War against them, which being considered, to lay a stronger obligation upon both Nations by which their tranquillity may be preserved, her Majesty having to that purpose sent her late <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Ministers into <em>England</em>, the <reg orig="Common.wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England</em> to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> how acceptable those overtures were, do not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> renew the former amity between both Nations, but have <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> her to enter into a more strict <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath yet been for the good of both.</p>

<head level="3"><em>Saturday</em>, Januar: 28</head>

<p><reg orig="Somthing">Something</reg> came yesterday by the Post from <em>Scotland</em>, <reg orig="wherin">wherein</reg> it is said that <em>Glencarn</em> in his Proclamations doth imply, that he hath a design to extirpate all the English, as the old, and <reg orig="antient">ancient</reg> Enemies to <em>Scotland</em>, he therefore threatens to sequester, and confiscate the estates of all, who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> presume to send either Horse, or arms to the common Enemy.</p>

<p>One of the <em>Dutch</em> Commissioners is again returned from <em>Holland</em>, and declares the consent of that Province to the Articles lately agreed upon with his Highness, and that the like is promised, and expected from the rest of the Provinces. <em>Zealand</em> only for the present doth seem <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> averse; The general adstipulation being made, there will come Ambassadors from the Provinces to see the confirmation of the Peace.</p>

<p>Master <em>Feak</em>, and Mr: <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em>, who were taken into custody, have been examined before the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, and do both stand committed.</p><pb n="7" />

<head level="3"><em>Monday</em>, January 30.</head>

<p>We have nothing further as yet from <em>Sweden</em> but only that the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> doth much admire the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> for her discourse, and <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> in the Affairs of all States.</p>

<p>It is again advertised from <em>Holland</em>, that the agreement with <em>England</em> is concluded, and the rather, because of the great Entertainment of our Ambassador in <em>Sweden</em>. The ships that were forced from the <em>Texel</em>, in the late great Tempest, and thought to be devoured by the Sea, are returned, though much shaken. The rich ships are also arrived from <em>Norway</em>, and from the <em>Eastland</em> Countries; the <em>Texel</em> hath been seldom seen so <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of shipping, as at this present.</p>

<p>There was lately a combustion in <em>Wales</em>, occasioned by some who refused to subscribe to this present Government, but upon better consideration they submitted, and have conformed themselves, so that all things are there quiet.</p>

<p>There is no News from Sea of any Victory at all, the Letters make mention of a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Prize taken <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Scarborough, and a Bark laden with <em>French</em> Goods, not far from the <em>Isle of Guernsey</em>. The Robbers at Sea are numerous, Letters from <em>Pendennie</em> do number them to be five and twenty sail, but many of them are such <reg orig="smal">small</reg> Vessels, that they will <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> in Creeks, and wait for their prey, where our ships of burden cannot come at them. The Robbers by Land, who robbed the Lady <em>Spencer</em> at <em>Hatton</em> <em>house</em>, are two of them taken, and carried to <em>Newgate</em>.</p>

<head level="3">That which this week is most remarkable, is:</head>

<p><i>An Ambassador from <em>Holland</em>, declaring there the full agreement to the Peace with <em>England</em>, and Ambassadors from <em>England</em> expected in <em>Holland</em> for ratification of it. The Speech made by the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> to the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>; the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> amazement at his great care and Industry; and his admiration of the Queen for her <reg orig="knowledg">knowledge</reg> and great understanding. Mr: <em>Feake</em> and Mr: <em><reg orig="Sympson">Simpson</reg></em> again examined and committed. The disagreement in <em>Wales</em> reconciled, and all there subscribing to the Government. A Defeat received in <em>Scotland</em> from the <em>Highlanders</em>. And some Prizes taken at Sea.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>FINIS.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>