<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost151">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 151</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">Great <reg orig="Brittain's">Britain's</reg></head>

<head level="1">POST</head>

<head level="3">Impartially communicating</head>

<p><i>The Remonstrance of the Members of the late Parliament, concerning their sudden Dissolution on the 12 of Decemb. 1653. with the Cause and manner thereof. And the Speech of Mr. <unclear>Rous</unclear> the Speaker, to his Highness the Lord Protector <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg>, upon the resigning of the Commission, Powers, and Authorities; with the proceedings of the great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Nation thereupon; and divers Parliament men refusing to subscribe unto the <reg orig="Generals">General's</reg> Commission. With variety of choice Intelligence, from Denmark, France, Sweden, Holland, and Germany, of, and in relation to the Government of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and the King of Scots.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From Wednesday Decem. 14. to Wednesday Decemb. 21. 1653</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for G. HORTON.</p>

<p>In the <reg orig="middest">midst</reg> of this great <em>Change</em> and <em>Revolution</em>, give me leave (I beseech you) <em>once more</em> to usher in, and act the Tragicomedy of this unexpected <em>Catastrophe</em>. <reg orig="O">Oh</reg> admirable constitutions! from whose rare Architecture, proceeds so excellent a <unclear><em>Basis</em></unclear>, essentially necessary to the very Being of these Nations; unto whose <pb n="1" /><unclear>protecting</unclear> Sanctions, we owe the Beauty, and Order of our present Enjoyments. I shall not be <unclear>copious</unclear> in my first <reg orig="Center">Centre</reg>; but descend to the Effects of this <em>Revolution</em>, to wit; The Parl. having upon their Dissolution delivered up the power which they received from his Excellency at their first sitting, by a Writing under their hands and seal, his Excellency thereupon called a Councel of Officers, &amp; advised how this great Burden of governing <em>England, Scotland,</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, with the Armies therein, and Navy at sea should be born, and by whom; who after <reg orig="severall">several</reg> <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> seeking of God and advising <reg orig="therin">therein</reg>, It was resolved that a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of godly able and discreet persons should be named, consisting of 21. And that his Excellency <reg orig="shold">should</reg> be chosen Lord Protector of the three Nations, which was accordingly <reg orig="solemnized">solemnised</reg> on Friday last, in manner and form as followeth:</p>

<p>His Excellency about one of the clock in the afternoon went from Whitehall to Westminster, to the Chancery court, attended by the Lords commissioners of the great Seal of England, Barons of the Exchequer, and Judges in their Robes; after them, the <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of the commonwealth, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Recorder of the city of <em>London</em> in their scarlet Gowns: then came his Excellency attended with many of the chief Officers of the Army, and a <reg orig="chalr">chair</reg> of State being set in the said court of chancery, his Excellency stood on the left hand thereof uncovered, till a large Writing in parchment, in the nature of an Oath, was read; there being the power with which his Excellency was invested, and how his Excellency id to govern the three Nations; which his Excellency <unclear>accepted of</unclear>, and subscribed in the face of the court; and <unclear>immediately</unclear> hereupon sat down covered in the said <unclear>chair</unclear> the Lord commissioners and every one standing <unclear>b<!--3 characters--></unclear>. After which they <pb n="2" />presented Him with the great Seal, the city Sword, and cap of Maintenance, which were returned to them again. The court then rose, and his Excellency returned to <em><reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, the Lord Mayor uncovered, carrying the Sword before the Protector all the way. Being come to <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> a Sermon was made by one of M. <em>Lockier</em> (Chaplain to the protector. Thus, after a stately <reg orig="solemnization">solemnisation</reg>, the same thereof soon <reg orig="eccho'd">echoed</reg> forth with great acclamations of joy both from the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg>, and others; the Bells ringing, the Muskets <reg orig="ratling">rattling</reg>, and the Cannons roaring.</p>

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen being returned from this great <reg orig="solemnization">solemnisation</reg>, in pursuance thereof, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>; went in their scarlet Gowns, to meet the <reg orig="Herauld">Herald</reg> of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and to proclaim the Lord Protector, which was accordingly done by 12 Trumpets both in Cheapside, and at the Royal Exchange, where the ensuing Proclamation was <reg orig="publickely">publicly</reg> read, to the end, that all men may conform and submit themselves to this present Government.</p>

<head level="3">&para;  By the Council</head>

<p>Whereas the late Parliament dissolving themselves, and resigning their powers and Authorities, The Government of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, Scotland, Ireland, by a Lord Protector, and successive Triennial Parliaments, is now established; And whereas O. <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg> Captain General of all the forces of this Commonwealth is declared Lord Protector of the said Nations, and hath accepted thereof: We have therefore thought it necessary (as we hereby do) to make publication of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>, and strictly to charge and command all, and every person or persons, of what quality and condition soever, in any of the said three Nations, to take notice hereof, and to conform and submit themselves to the Government so established. And all Sheriffs, Majors, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, and other <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <pb n="3" />Ministers and Officers, whom this may <unclear>concern</unclear>, are required to cause this Proclamation to be forthwith published in their respective counties, cities, corporations, and Market towns; to the end none may have cause to pretend ignorance in this behalf.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Given at <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg> this 16 day of December, 1653.</i></head>

<p>As touching the cause and manner of the dissolution of the late Parliament, I hold it needful, by reason of various Reports, to give you a brief account of the business; the sum whereof take as followeth:</p>

<p>The House being sundry times divided; the prevalent party at last began to oppose the Anabaptists, and to interwove their speeches with some bitter Invectives, saying, That they endeavoured to destroy the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, as appeared by their Vote upon Saturday. In consideration whereof the Presbyterian party declared, That they <i>could</i> not <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves to sit any longer, and so be guilty of bringing confusion and desolation upon the Nation.</p>

<p>2 The Church party urged, that the Dissenters had dealt disingenuously with the Army, in moving that the Officers should be treated with to lay down their pay, &amp; likewise to <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the casting out the Bill of <reg orig="Assessement">Assessment</reg>. To which, they answer, That as to what was urged as disingenuity to them, in <reg orig="endeavoring">endeavouring</reg> to retrench some of the <reg orig="Officers">Officer's</reg> pay. It was moved indeed to order to the abatement of the Tax; That in respect of their great <em>estates</em> already gotten, and the little pains and hazard they were now at in this time of peace, and the sore and heavy burden that was upon the people, That the chief Officers would for one year in this time of <reg orig="streight">strait</reg>, serve the commonwealth freely, as they had called the <em>Parl.</em> to do. And concerning the motion of casting out the Bill of <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> <pb n="4" />was upon this ground, That it was an unequal and oppressive way of Levy, which yet, least <reg orig="then">than</reg> the emergent affairs of the Nation should suffer it was <reg orig="waved">waived</reg>, hoping ere another <reg orig="Assesment">Assessment</reg> should be laid, it might be done by a pound rate, or some other more equal way of <reg orig="Assesse">Assess</reg>, instance being given of some Towns and Counties in the Commonwealth, paying 12 and 13 s. in the pound, and others but two and three. So that the Debate growing high, divers members <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> their <em>Protest</em> in dissatisfaction to the thing moved, and without putting it to the Question, or adjourning to any other place, the Speaker left the chair, and with divers members went hastily out of the House with them: some 30 and odd <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> within, who mutually declaring, that they had <reg orig="profest">professed</reg> in the presence of the Lord, that they were called of God to that place, which was the principal motive that drew them thither; <reg orig="aod">and</reg> that they apprehended their said call was chiefly for promoting the interest of Jesus Christ. Beginning therefore to consider what to do, col. <em>Goff</em>, and Lieu. Col. <em>White</em> came in and entreated them earnestly to go out, <unclear>pressing</unclear> it often. It was earnestly <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> to them, that at their personal Request they could not; but desired them to withdraw, unless they had command to put them forth; which when they perceived, they commanded in some <reg orig="Musqueteers">Musketeers</reg>; upon which they withdrew: soon after, several <i>were</i> sent for to come to Whitehall, where an Instrument was drawn up for resigning the power to the General, which was subscribed by many, but refused by others. This the late Speaker M. <em>Rous</em>, with a short preamble delivered to the General, saying, That whereas they did <reg orig="fore-see">foresee</reg> clearly that their waitings and expectations of ever coming on to things of <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good, were more and more disappointed in <unclear>obedience</unclear> unto the call given them by his Excellency, they freely resigned up the powers and authorities invested on them. &amp;c.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From Scotland thus. The Highlanders give out that the Duke of York is to come from France to be their Commander in chief for his brother the Scots King. They have lifted 6 or 7000 horse and foot; they have by plunder gotten horse, and most of the horse and foot have Arms, but not armour, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the chief Officers. They break open houses in the night, where contribution is refused to them, and are resolved to force it with much violence. And last week were so bold, in the night, as to come within half a mile if this place, with a Troop of horse, and <reg orig="plendered">plundered</reg> some houses, and then rid away again. They have had 150 horse from Holland transported to them; which are to be charging horses for their Leaders. They <reg orig="presse">press</reg> the Scot to rise, but divers run away. They had thoughts to storm Aberdeen and <reg orig="Innernesse">Inverness</reg>, but they go not on upon that design.</p>

<p>They seduce many to run away with their <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> horses to them, upon promises of share of their plunder, which is their great design: So that they are the most <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg>, Runnagado Rabble that hath gathered all these wars; and those few Gentry that are with them, are such as are so greatly in debt, that they cannot subsist without some such desperate way any longer.</p>

<p>The enemy doth still increase, so that the Southern parts of Scotland are fearful of being <reg orig="plundred">plundered</reg> by them. They will <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="inlarge">enlarge</reg> quarters upon the Lowlands. Their first attempts will be to regain the Northern <reg orig="garisons">garrisons</reg> from us; but those that so plunder upon our borders will hardly join with Highlanders yet, for fear they carry their plunder away from them into the Highlands, for that trade is the chief design they drive. The Ring-leaders are eminent with them.</p>

<p>Another Express from Scotland assure us, That the insolence of the Highlanders, forced our Commander in chief (though the <pb n="6" />weather was unseasonable) to march from <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> against them; but as soon as he appeared, they quitted their station, and ran afrightedly towards the <reg orig="Hils">Hills</reg>, not daring to stand a shot, or strike one <reg orig="stroak">stroke</reg>, They increase their numbers <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> in the Highlands, all men of desperate fortunes flocking to them. They continue their excursions still, and expect the rising of a Party with them in the Lowlands. They have attempted to <reg orig="fortifie">fortify</reg> a <reg orig="Passe">Pass</reg> betwixt <reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg> and St. Johnstons, but they will be forced to give over the work. Middleton is not yet amongst them, but they expect him, and great matters to be done by him. The Guards here saw a great <unclear>fire</unclear>: after a while it took <reg orig="its">it's</reg> course toward the South, and so vanished, which gives occasion to several <reg orig="Prognosticks">Prognostics</reg>.</p>

<p>General Monk is gone for the Downs, where the residue of the ships appointed for the Winter Guard, are to meet him.</p>

<p>The Portugal <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassador's</reg> brother (some Ladies coming to visit it him on Tuesday night last was a seven-night) made an escape out of Newgate in <reg orig="womens">women's</reg> apparel, by the assistance of the Lady <unclear>Moon</unclear>, but by the industry of the Keepers was re-taken on Wednesday night, and ordered to be put into the Dungeon of the aforesaid prison, for future security till his <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg>. But the Quarter <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> in the Old <reg orig="bayly">Bailey</reg> are adjourned till after Christmas.</p>

<p>A general Redemption is suddenly expected for all prisoners, by a <reg orig="Goal">Gaol</reg>-delivery from his Highness the Lord Protector, both in City and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, except for Murder.</p>

<p>Amsterdam, Decem. 13. Our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> in the late storm is confirmed to have been 23 ships, and 1000 men, under which, two of the best in the country not heard of, apparently sunk in the sea. The States have drawn in their whole Fleet, not intending to set forth another <reg orig="his">this</reg> Winter; so much is their confidence of having peace with England.</p>

<p>From Scotland further thus: The Highlanders play <em>Rex</em> upon the Lowlanders, and descend down in several place, like so many billows into the Ocean sea, where they swallow justice, as an Ox doth water, taking no remorse nor pity upon poor souls; but committing sundry and <reg orig="unparalel'd">unparalleled</reg> outrages.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>The last <em>Post</em> from <em>Dover</em> bringeth Intelligence, <i>That the Royal party in the Netherlands are very high in their <unclear>consultations</unclear>, and with <unclear><!--15 characters, three words--></unclear> <unclear>resolutions</unclear> upon our Commonwealth; and forsooth, in a bird witted way, would fain usher over a flight into these three Nations, saying, that the Du. Of Lorain <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> exchange his <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> for Ireland; the Prince of Conde to be made King of Scotland; and young Charles to be content with England alone. In the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg>, Middleton is making all the haste he can to transport from hence great store of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg> and Ammunition to the assistance of the Highlanders, who have <unclear>declared</unclear> for Charles Stuart; and (as they say) want nothing but <reg orig="armes">arms</reg> to beat the English out of Scotland. The Earl of Athol &amp; Glencarn are raising divers Regiments of horse and foot, and great assistance is expected from the German Princes; but to this there is little probability; nor need we in the least fear them, since the Queen of Sweden has declared for the interest of this Commonwealth; and withal has sent propositions to the States of Holland adjuring them once more upon pain of her Royal Revenge not to infringe her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Liberties, by violating her trade and <reg orig="traffique">traffic</reg>. the King of Denmark has likewise declared a great inability to a war with England; but looks with a notable <reg orig="sheeps">sheep's</reg> eye upon the North of Scotland.</i></p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> Decemb. 20.</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord protector has spent some time with the great <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of the Nation, about the settling of the Government, both in Church and State, the satisfying of the people, and taking off Oppressions. In Him therefore let Us confide, and render that honour, worship, and fear, which is due unto his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> under God.</p>

<hr />

<head level="2">Licensed according to Order.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>