<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost$126">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 126</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2"><i>The Politique</i></head>
<head level="1">POST</head>
<head level="3">Truly Representing,</head>

<p><i>The concluding of a Treaty between his Highness the Lord Protector and the Lord Ambassadors from the States of Holland; with the Declaration, and Letter, sent from the Independent and Anabaptist part to all the private Churches throughout the Nation; And a Remonstrance concerning the <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, and the Church of England, in order to the present Power and Government: Likewise, the Narrative for removing all Oppressions, the administering of true justice, the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of Religion and the restoring of all men to liberty. Together with variety of choice Intelligence from the Nation, and all parts of Europe.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From Wednesday Jan. 4. to Wednesday Jan. 11. 1653</head>
<hr />

<p>LONDON, Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</p>

<hr />

<p>There is no sight so lovely, and taking to the eyes of all ingenious and since <i><unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear></i> as naked Truth; it being a jewel of such singular worth, that the excellency thereof has <reg orig="induc'd">induced</reg> we (in these great juncture of Affairs) to present you with such Occurrences, as shall <reg orig="center">centre</reg> upon the Basis of Enquiry, Common Right, and Reason: And first, we shall take an exact View of An Answer to a paper <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> A true Narrative of the cause and manner of the <pb n="1" />dissolution of the late Parliament, &amp;c. Wherein, saith the Author, three things were evidently in the principles of divers of those men in the house (whom I, amongst others, thought it safe to sit longer with) which though I will not determine but that they might be the issues of a deluded mind, yet looked very like the worst designs.</p>

<p>First, a general owning themselves to rule the Nation <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as Saints, to whom the right of civil Government did belong, as having an extraordinary call from Christ thereto, being the beginning of a <unclear>fife</unclear> Monarchy, which was never to cease, but to break in pieces all powers, by making war with them. In which, besides the dishonour cast upon the good ways of God and his people, and the abuse of many Truths, and in particular that of the Kingdom of Christ on earth, a thing to be expected and longed for, as the Scriptures hold it forth to us; 'Tis no way hard to discern what a foundation was laid of exalting men (who should take to themselves the name of Saints, though never so unduly) in Government, and excluding all others who had ever so great Interest in the Nation, and other fitness thereto, and have a civil Right to rule, when Providence <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give them a lawful Call thereto.</p>

<p>Secondly, how great a ground was this to put the stamp of infallibility upon all they should do, and conclude the Nation in whatsoever Impositions they should lay upon them, by pretending themselves</p>

<head level="2">Ruling Saints</head>

<p>And that unquestionably by a Divine and extraordinary Right <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> thing never before heard of as thus held forth; and which certainly if pursued to the utmost, would give them under that notion, a right to posses all <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> properties and estates, <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> as dispose and go with them, and introduce such Axioms, as would soon have <unclear>turned the</unclear> three Nations into blood and confusion. I intend not hereby and reflection upon the Name of Saints, which my soul honours, nor upon the advantage of having godly men to rule; but upon the ill and dangerous use by <reg orig="Satans">Satan's</reg> Temptations may be made of such pretences, <pb n="2" />especially in these Times, wherein his Temptations lie mostly that way. The second was their manifestly rigid Principles of Imposition, contended against with the blood of so many precious Saints, &amp; laying such foundations as would shortly have introduced the bitterest and sorest persecution: To this none are so conscious, or can be, as those that <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> with them in the House, where they heard men unsainted and <reg orig="condemn'd">condemned</reg> into the fourth Monarchy, and looked upon as <reg orig="obstructors">obstructers</reg> of Reformation, and no longer fit for the Work, if not through-paced to all the Principles of <em>Reformation</em>, held forth Mr. <em>Peak</em> and others at <em>Black fryers</em>, and other places, and stickled for by some in the House. To this purpose, Letters are written to the Churches all the Nation over, to blast that part of the House that agreed not with them; and at a set-meeting at a <reg orig="Members">Member's</reg> house, of divers Members, consultation had to leave the House, and remonstrate against them as hinderers of <em>Reformation</em>, and not fit to govern the Nation any longer. And things indeed amongst them was grown to that height that it was evident (in a short time) scarce any should have been judged meet to publish the Gospel, or receive the <reg orig="Magistrates">Magistrate's</reg> countenance, that had not been <reg orig="baptized">baptised</reg> into their spirit and principle. And this I cannot but mention, that when the last great Debate was about ejecting scandalous Ministers, it was confidently averred, None should be countenanced by the Magistrate but such as disclaimed their Ordination: Which though though<!--repeated in text--> I would not seem to <reg orig="justifie">justify</reg> it in the least, how hard an Imposition it was to put men upon this Dilemma, either to leave their present subsistence, or disclaim the Ordination they had (it may be <reg orig="conscienciosly">conscientiously</reg>) received either from Bishops or Presbyterians is no hard thing to judge.</p>

<p>Thirdly, there appeared an evident Design to alter the Government of the Army, and have put it into such hands as would have perfectly corresponded with their principles, and given them a safe opportunity to have imposed whatsoever they had pleased upon the Nation; and as there was just cause to fear would have brought out what did not yet appear, <em>viz.</em></p>

<p><i>Blood upon the Nation</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>This was certainly given in direction to divers Members met together, to pull down some in the Army, and set up others, either with of before them, as is most notoriously known: And what other signification, but to alter the Government of the Army, the endeavours of many in the House who came purposely prepared to take away the <reg orig="Officers">Officer's</reg> pay, could have, I know not, unless it were to make a dangerous breach between the Parliament, and the Army who called them thither, or else to breed animosities in the Army, and set them at variance among themselves. This could not but be judged a most destructive thing, considering the strength of the Nation, and the Interest of all the good people, was not a little bound up in the <reg orig="Armies">Army's</reg> safe and well consisting together. And this I cannot but remember, that some of the chief of those who declaimed so much against the Officers taking their pay, and not going a warfare at their own charge, did at the same time while they were gazing at the mote in their <reg orig="brethrens">brethren's</reg> eye, never reflect upon the beam in their own, they holding several places under the Commonwealth more beneficial <reg orig="then">than</reg> most individual Officers pay in the Army, so much declaimed against.</p>

<p>Now for the particulars expressed in the printed Narrative, I shall consider them apart, and give the true and genuine signification to divers things there picked up, and put together with the greatest disadvantage and prejudice that is possible.</p>

<p>On the twelfth instant divers Members came to the House with an intention to inform them of our insufficiency to do that good we were called for, as so constituted, and to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> them to resign their Power (as being a thing most safe and <reg orig="adviseable">advisable</reg>) whence they received it; and if their concurrence could not be had, judged it their duty to do it in their particulars, and did it accordingly, by withdrawing themselves accompanied with the Speaker, to the Horse-Chamber in <em><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg></em> where near eighty Members voluntarily subscribed a Resignation of their Power to the Lord General, to which place none were compelled to come, and in which resignation none were desired to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> but such as had a freedom thereto, as was there often <reg orig="exprest">expressed</reg> by some Members present; which resignation by the Speaker <pb n="4" />accompanied likewise with the said Members, was delivered to the Lord General. What happened to those few Members that remained in the House I know <reg orig="nat">not</reg>; but I am conscious of no force (as is intimated) either intended or offered to the Parliament <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> a House was sitting.</p>

<p>All which particulars are asserted for truth, by a cordial lover of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> Liberties; who with his Lines, presents himself to <reg orig="publick">public</reg> view.</p>

<img src="" alt="bearded man holding 2 keys" />

<pb n="5" />

<p>The last <em>Post</em> from <em>Holland</em> advertiseth, That there has been an exceeding mighty Thunder and Lightning <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Amsterdam</em>, which burnt and destroyed above five hundred houses, and done wonderful Damage upon the country; as may be represented by the ensuing Figure, the <em>Rivers</em> having brake forth beyond their Bounds, and made great Devastation.</p>

<img src="" alt="2 maps, one a magnification of part of the other" />

<p>There has likewise been above forty <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships sunk in the <em>Texel</em>, by a Tempest, and many others exposed to great hazards and <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg>.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>The like dreadful Thunder has been at <em>Pembroke</em> in Wales, where not long before the great Lightning, appeared a Blazing Star, to the great admiration of all that beheld it.</p>

<img src="" alt="shooting star" />

<p>What these dreadful <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> from Heaven portend, I am not able to make out; but certainly they are <reg orig="Fore-runners">Forerunners</reg> of some wonderful events-</p>

<p>There is arrived the Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em>, consisting of about forty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg> &amp;c. There is likewise come five ships from the East-Land; as also one from <em>Zant</em> with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet not come up the <em>River</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Gravesend Jan. 9.</i></head>

<p><i>The Ambassador from the States of Holland have made some further application to his Highness, and his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>; and 'tis hoped there will be a firm and lasting Peace.</i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>By our last <em>Post</em> and intelligence from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, we have received very certain and credible <reg orig="intelugence">intelligence</reg>, That Colonel <em>Charles James</em> having received a Commission from the King of Scots, is <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth into the Deep with the Brest Men of War who has now struck sail upon the Coast of <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>, and there set up his Flag on the Poop of the Patrick called the Vice-Ambral, as here represented is the causing Figure.</p>

<img src="" alt="Flag with 3 feathers in a crown on a ship" />

<p>From Her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, our Post further advertiseth, that the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, with his Retinue was received in a most high and pompous manner, by the Magistrates of <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, who made a speech to hid Lordship, by way of congratulation, in reference to his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> from the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England.</p>

<p>From Amsterdam it is further certified that there hath <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> a very sad and lamentable fire not at <em>Amsterdam</em>, as is said by some, but at a town some 3 miles of the said City: occasioned by tempestuous and stormy weather, a Rase Mill being driven with that force and violence that, that they took fire with such fury and violence, that the Flames issued forth in such Flakes, that no possible <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> could prevent this sad and dreadful devastation.</p>

<hr />

<p><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>