<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost174">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 174</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Weekly</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Articles of Agreement fully concluded upon by the States of Holland, &amp; the proclaiming of Peace on Thursday next within the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England. The hanging forth of the white Colours aboard the English &amp; Dutch fleets; and the <reg orig="comming">coming</reg> in of the Brest men of war into the very mouth of Severn, seizing of the English Vessels, and beating us with our our<!--repeated over a line break in the original--> own weapons. The great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> of Gen. Middleton in Scotland, the dividing of his Army into several Brigades, the number of forces is each County to be <reg orig="levyed">levied</reg>, and a Narrative of the particular proceedings on both sides.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> the 11. Of <em>April</em>, to <em>Tuesday</em> the 18 of <em>April</em> 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>R. Wood</em>, for <em>G, Horton</em>, <i>for information of the</i>.</p>
<head level="3">PEOPLE.</head>
<hr />

<p>The first thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view this Week, is, the motion of the grand Wheels in <em>Sweden</em>, between her Royal Majesty Queen <em>Christiana</em>, and his Excellency the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em>; whose industrious Negotiation has received a candid acceptation; for indeed the Queen has so great an affection for <em>England</em>, and in particular to His Highness the Lord Protector, that she is very inclinable to make up this <reg orig="allyance">alliance</reg> before she acquits the Government, which will be a very fair and specious conclusion of her Reign, that she has gained to <em>Sweden</em> so considerable an <reg orig="Allie">Ally</reg> as the State of <em>England</em>.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg> April 11.</i></head>

<p>This day came to my hand, The substance of the Peace agreed upon between England and Holland, which according to the best Intelligence that I can gather, is to this effect; but somewhat larger in particulars, That there shall be a closer Alliance and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of England, and the States of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> was heretofore. That the Peace be published by both Commonwealths, upon one and the same day; after which, all Acts of Hostility to cease after 10 days, in the British Seas; from thence to the Cape of St. Vincent after six weeks, and to the Mediterranean sea after ten weeks, and the furthest parts before eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>; after which, all prizes to be restored. That all acts past be forgotten, and all prisoners on both sides released; both to defend each other against all enemies, neither to act <reg orig="ang thing">anything</reg> against the other. That all hostility cease between England and Denmark; none to assist the Rebels of either Nation with any supply, but assist each other against them; &amp; neither to receive those that are declared enemies, but cause them upon notice to depart within 28 days, on pain of death. That no private persons be suffered to assist the enemies of either, nor to pay to either greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> others. The <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships to strike their Flags to the English in the British Seas; no retreat to be given to <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of the Ports of either; each to comprehend the other in any Treaty with any Nation, if desired. That if any particular persons break the peace, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not break the National Confederacy, but those that do it to be punished. The Subjects of each to travel freely through all quarters of each, by Water or Land, not exceeding forty in a company, and submitting to the Laws where they are. That in storms each may have harbour under other, if they break <unclear>not bulk</unclear>, without paying of <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, The Merchants or <reg orig="Marriners">Mariners</reg> of either Commonwealth not to be pressed to serve under the other, but upon inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction. That in each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Country, they pass between their Ships and Inns with <reg orig="lawfull">lawful</reg> weapons, offensive and defensive. That all ships of both Commonwealths defend each other, against all whomsoever, sailing their course together. That if any other take any ships <unclear>out</unclear> of either of their Dominions, both parties to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> against them <reg orig="untill">until</reg> restitution be made. The Searchers of both, to take no more of any of either, <reg orig="then">than</reg> their instructions. Letters of Reprisal not to be given for damage caused, if in three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> satisfaction may be had. That such as have private Commissions, put in good security not to damage the Subjects of either Commonwealth, That not above 8 ships of War remain in any Port of the <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Commonwealth, without consent. That Justice be done by the States on those that are alive, that <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in <em>Amboyna</em>. That there may be Commissioners on both sides to examine the differences of the inhabitants of both Nations in the East Indies, Greenland, <unclear>Muscovy</unclear>, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg>, or other places, and if they cannot agree within three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to refer it to be determined by the Protestant Switzers. Security is already given for payment of <pb n="2" />the monies to the Eastland Company, upon the business of Denmark, and the <reg orig="summe">sum</reg> agreed upon.</p>

<p>Take here the Copy of a Letter from Scotland. SIR, The <reg orig="inclosed">enclosed</reg> will inform you what kind of task the Horse are put upon in these parts, to <reg orig="suppresse">suppress</reg> the Rebels and Mossers, who daily gather and are as often scattered. Besides what was done by Major General <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> late Regiment, commanded by Cornet Kennet, coming from <reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg>, with some Seffe which they had collected, were set upon by 40 of the Enemy, received their charge, and then charged through the Rebels, routed them, killed 4 on the place, took 6 whereof 3 mortally wounded, and had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> 4 of his party wounded. Lieut. Hickman with another party fell upon 60 of the Enemy under the command of Captain Campbel, took 6 above 20 horse: Captain Campbel was shot in the back, his horse taken, but he himself escaped amongst the <reg orig="Whins">Whins</reg> and Bogs. <reg orig="Glencarns">Glencarn's</reg> and <reg orig="Glencarry">Glengarry</reg> &amp;c. are gone over Taine into Southerland to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with Middleton, and then they will be near 4000. yet I doubt not but Col. Morgan <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> to <reg orig="ingage">engage</reg> them with his party. Montross and the Lord Dodhoppe are raising men in the Brays of Angus, and report already speaks them 300 horse. Thus do they <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> strive to make themselves and the Country miserable, having yet appeared the most cowardly enemy that ever we dealt <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>. Upon <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> night last they had a party returning from the South towards Aberfoy pass, to which joined another party of the enemy, of about 60 Horse and 60 Foot, commanded by Col. Mac-Naughton; at which time Cornet Keys with about 20 horse from Dumbarton, and <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Francis Young of Captain <reg orig="Callants">Callant's</reg> company of Col. <reg orig="Reads">Read's</reg> Regiment, with 18 Horse, and 30 Foot from Bohannan made after them; the Enemy got the Pass first, nevertheless they were totally routed by ours, who killed one <reg orig="Coptain">Captain</reg>, and 12 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, took <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Col. George <unclear>Herriot</unclear>, William Bohannan Captain, Robert Camphel Cornet, Hugh Wells Quartermaster, above 40 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and above 20 horse, Mac-Naughton fled with 16 Horse, and all of them being killed and taken save himself and 3 others. We had <reg orig="onely">only</reg> one killed, one wounded, and two horses killed. This is all the intelligence that affords <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> at present, having had nothing from our parties that are abroad in these parts since the last. The Scots rise in several parties in the Lowlands, and 4 or 500 have been lately dispersed in several parties, and divers of them killed and taken. And Gen. Monk is gone to take command of the Forces in Scotland.</p>

<p><i>Dalkeith April 6, 1654.</i></p>

<p>From Colchester it is certified, That the Right Honourable Col. <em>Barkstead</em>, High Steward of the aforesaid Town, was received with great solemnity, by the Mayor, Aldermen, Common-<reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>-men, <reg orig="Burghesses">Burgesses</reg>, and other eminent Townsmen; who conducted him to the Town-Hall, where he was at the Sessions sworn free <reg orig="Burghess">Burgess</reg>, and a Justice of Peace. After, a Declaration was agreed on, and signed by them all, which he this day presented to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>The last Post from <em>Rochel</em> in <em>France</em> <reg orig="advertizeth">advertiseth</reg>, That the Report of the conclusion of the Treaty between <em>England</em>, and the <em>United Provinces</em>, and that nevertheless there was a mighty Fleet ready to go to Sea, riding <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Portsmouth</em>, the same hath given a strong <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> along the Coast of <em>Brittany</em>, in these parts, as far as the River of <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>, each Governor and Commander of Castles standing much upon their guards, and not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> so, but they have likewise sent letters to the Court, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to demand assistance, but also to know His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure therein.</p> 

<p>The Governor of the castle of <em>Falkenstein</em> having a most <reg orig="cruell">cruel</reg> manner plundered a <reg orig="Ministers">Minister's</reg> house, turned him and his Family out of doors; but it so incensed the <reg orig="Countreyes">Countries</reg> adjacent, that watching their opportunity when one half of the Garrison was absent, resolved to make a retaliation thereof, and most unanimously (as one man) marched up to the Walls, assaulted the Defendants, and at last entered the Turn-pikes, took possession of the Gates, and as many as were found in opposition were all put to the sword, and the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> (for his cruelty) let blood in the Neck <reg orig="vain">vein</reg>, and so he departed this life,</p>

<head level="2">A just Reward for so cruel a Sword-man.</head>

<p>From <em>Minhead</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the <em>Brest</em> men of war do much harm in that channel, having of late taken several Vessels, whereof some of a considerable value which belonged to <em>Bristol</em>: others of no great esteem, yet too good to be lost. Nay, they are grown to such a height, that they dare presume to come even into the very mouth of <em>Severn</em>, where they beat us with our own Weapons, by employing our own Vessels against Us.</p>

<p>From <em>Ireland</em> we have intelligence, that there is scarce <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> wanting in that <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> but people to manure the <em>ground</em>, and a good conscience to hold forth their infallible practices, which indeed has been too much eclipsed in these our <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. The plague is well <reg orig="appeas'd">appeased</reg> in many parts; yet notwithstanding the pestilence rageth too too much amongst many: from which,</p>

<head level="2">Good Lord deliver Us.</head>

<pb n="4" />

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have intelligence, that on the first instant General <em>Middleton</em> had a general <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Skilbo</em> in <em>Southerland</em>; and after the receipt of Orders from this experienced Generalissimo, part of the Army marched for the South Highlands, the rest were to continue in the North, and both to prosecute their Levies, and then to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> in the South. Commissions are gone forth in the Name of their Master <em>Charles</em>, to <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> the Army, <em>viz.</em></p>

<head level="2">The County of Ross 250.</head>

<head level="2">The County of Southerland 300.</head>

<head level="2">The County of Caithness 600.</head>

<head level="2">The County of Stranarvar 300.</head>

<p>And do <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> in every county where they have command. The Lord <em>Seaford</em>, and <em>Mackoldwie</em> are suddenly expected with their Levies also, which are not a few; and this Son of <em>Mars</em> Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> gives out, that he hath brought a great store of Spanish Gold, lent by his Master the Emperor, from whom is expected a great Loan, and many men,</p>

<head level="2">(in a Hop-sack.)</head>

<p>which is negotiated by the Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and to be brought by his Brother in law, which he had <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for, but for the appeasing of the discontent he heard was amongst his friends, for his often failing in his promised coming amongst them. Sometimes they make desperate incursions, out pay often for their bold attempts. Nay, this is not all, but 'tis said they have more Arms and Ammunition landed. Of which, more in due time.</p>

<p>In the interim, true it is, that many horse and foot are expediting down, and Lieu. col. <em>Mitchil</em> is <reg orig="marcht">marched</reg> with 9 Companies of Foot, six Troops of Horse, and a gallant party of resolute Dragoons, which are to march tomorrow to <em>Brahan</em>; to which are added 4 Troops of horse, and 3 companies of foot, all which, are to keep a pass at <unclear>Dinghil</unclear>, and to engage the enemy, if possible.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The French Letters <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Majesty hath sent to the little Queen, the K. of <em><reg orig="Scotts">Scots</reg></em>, and the rest of her children, to desire them to remove out of his Territories, for that the English were resolved to send an <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> reciprocally into <em>France</em>, and that their pensions should be paid to them where they should please to point to have it paid; whereupon they are making preparations for their departure out of <em>Paris</em>, the Queen goes to dwell at <em>Angers</em>, and <em>Charles Stuart</em> with his brothers and Prince <em>Rupert</em>, are bound for <em>Chantilly</em>, and they have had serious consultations whether they should bend their course from thence to <em>Scotland</em>, or rather to <em>Germany</em>; the latter being supposed to be the safest way to keep their heads on their shoulders.</p>

<p>There are some Merchants have received Letters from Holland, that the States of the United Provinces have signed and ratified the Instrument of Peace, and the Messengers are upon their return with it, for his Highness the Lord Protector to do the like. And it is supposed that on Thursday next being the 20 of this instant, <em>Peace</em> will be generally proclaimed throughout <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em>, a copy of the Instrument I have briefly in the precedent pages presented you with.</p>

<p>Three English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships returning very richly laden from <em>Smyrna</em>, were set upon by three French men of War near <em>Cape </em><unclear><em>Spartavento</em></unclear>, and after a cruel and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> fight between them, they took one of the English, stranded another, and the third being nimble in sailing, escaped away by <em>Messina</em>. Also on the 25 of the last Month, a Mountain called <em><reg orig="Vesuve">Vesuvius</reg></em> in <em>Naples</em>, began to cast forth fire and ashes, to the great astonishment of thousands of people, who ran into the Churches, and caused the <reg orig="Bels">Bells</reg> to be rung, to give warning thereof to all the Country about.</p>

<p>The States of <em>Holland</em> have sent an express to the King of <em>Denmark</em> to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> him what agreement they have made with <em>England</em> concerning that Kingdom, and begin to cease their warlike preparations all generally being very willing to embrace <em>Peace</em>.</p>

<p>The last Letters from <em>Germany</em> <reg orig="advertize">advertise</reg>, That the new Levies are almost finished, and that great is the expectation of the <reg orig="Emperours">Emperor's</reg> playing a new Game with certain Christian Princes. They have reinforced the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Casal</em>, and the Dukes of <em>Florence, Parma</em> and <unclear><!--approx. 6 characters--></unclear> are also raising</p>

<pb n="6" />

<!--table in two columns separated by a vertical line, seems to be intended to be read as a single column-->

<head level="2">15000 Foot.</head>
<head level="2">3000 Horse.</head>
<head level="2">700 <reg orig="Curiazers">Cuirassiers</reg></head>
<head level="2">500 Battle Axes</head>
<head level="2">48 Pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>, and abundance of Powder Match, and Bullet; besides, Hand <reg orig="Granadoes">Grenades</reg></head>

<p>But what their Design is, we cannot as yet give you an Account of; <reg orig="onely">only</reg> thus much, that there is a bloody war to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> on vigorously this Summer. Indeed, all <em>Europe</em> seems to be in a Chaos of confusion; and nothing but war and <reg orig="Rumors">Rumours</reg> of war throughout most of the <em>Christian Territories</em>: The Vice King of <em>Naples</em> threatens destruction of <em>Catalonia</em>, and the King of <em>Spain</em> is determined to take field suddenly. The Prince of <em>Conde</em> begins to move, and his received new Instructions from the Council of <em>Spain</em>, which has given so great an <reg orig="allarum">alarm</reg> to the King of <em>France</em>, that no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> fifty thousand horse and foot are designed to impede their march, and Gen. <em>Thurene</em> is to advance forthwith into <em>Picardy</em>, and take a view of the Army, and to set it in a posture fit for a march: he has received Commission from his Master King <em>Lewis</em> as chief Generalissimo, and his Majesty and the great Court-Favourite Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, are both resolved to honour him with their own persons in the field, and to take a view of all the <reg orig="frontire">frontier</reg> Towns and Castles.</p>

<p>Since the Prince of <em>Conti's</em> coming in to the King, and taking the <em>Oath of <reg orig="Allegeance">Allegiance</reg></em>, his Majesty hath created him Vice King of <em>Naples</em>; and a very sumptuous and admirable Equipage is making ready for <reg orig="solemnizing">solemnising</reg> the Journey.</p>

<p>The 14 instant, was acted at the <em>Lovure</em> the stately Italian <em>Comedy</em>, called, the Nuptials of <em>Peleus</em> and <em>Thetis</em>, being a thing of incomparable invention, and no less costly. There was a mighty affluence of people, amongst the rest, came the disconsolate Queen, her three Sons, <em>Charles, James</em>, and <em>Henry</em>, and the Princess her Daughter.</p>

<p>The Duke of <em>Lorain</em> doth still remain at <em>Antwerp</em> close prisoner, and there is a strong Report that he is to be <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> prisoner into <em>Spain</em>, which is <em>malum omen</em>, for the obtaining that liberty which he <pb n="7" />was promised, when he was apprehended. <i>Ha! Ha! This is as like to prove as bad to him, as is already the disposing of all his estate that hath already been found in that estate.</i></p>

<p>By Letters further from <em>Holland</em> it is certified, That the States have fully ratified the Agreement for Peace with great <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> and alacrity of Spirit, and that they have sent a Return of the Instrument to his Highness the Lord Protector; insomuch, that 'tis given out, that the Articles are to be proclaimed on Wednesday next.</p>

<p>All which particulars, appears to be evident; for that the English Fleet hath weighed anchor from S. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em> Point, and now rides with their white Flags and Streamers in Stokes Bay. A great part of the <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> for the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg>, and other places.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>Peace, <em><reg orig="ethnick">ethnic</reg></em> heart, I tell thee there is <em>Peace,</em></line>
<line>Why art an Infidel? I prithee <reg orig="ceace">cease</reg></line>
<line>Thy doubts; both our Religions are <reg orig="reform'd">reformed</reg>,</line>
<line>Our Languages in many words are <reg orig="form'd">formed</reg></line>
<line>Alike, our <reg orig="Neighbor hood">Neighbourhood</reg> might move us much;</line>
<line>Then <em><reg orig="Eccho">Echo</reg></em> tell our <reg orig="Canons">Cannons</reg> to the <em>Dutch</em>:</line>
<line>But thou, not like to some, dost far short speak,</line>
<line>(<reg orig="Then">Than</reg> those that call thee <reg orig="Babler">Babbler</reg> are but weak)</line>
<line>Of what thou dost <em>receive</em>, thereby <em>deceive</em></line>
<line>The <reg orig="Neighbor">Neighbour</reg>-Nations with a <em>Narrative</em></line>
<line>Of our exaltings. Let our <reg orig="Bone fires">Bonfires</reg> say</line>
<line>The darker Night is <reg orig="turn'd">turned</reg> the brighter day.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>The 14 instant, his Highness came to <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, where He dined with many of the Lords of his Council; their Reception was performed magnificently; and a great affluence of People; but many returned unsatisfied, by reason that a guard of <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> were put upon duty, upon the <reg orig="solemnizing">solemnising</reg> of the Feast.</p>

<p>It is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em> is to have the <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> of a <em>Habeas Corpus</em> at the Return of the next Term; and 'tis hoped his <reg orig="inlargment">enlargement</reg> will suddenly follow. The same measure I could wish might be meted to <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> under restraint.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>