<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost169">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 169</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of the English Nobility touching his Highness the Lord Protector, and the present Government of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Dominions thereunto belonging. The <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> of Gen. Middleton <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Aberdeen in Scotland, and the number of Ordnance, Arms, and Ammunition, brought into the field, with the taking of Skelbe Castle, and the fortifying of it by Major Gen. Dyler. The Demands of his Highness the Lord Protector to the King of France, and the Ordinance for continuing of the <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, with the Names of the Commissioners and Governors constituted and appointed for the great <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg> and new Impost.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 14. to <em>Wednesday</em> March <unclear>22</unclear>. 1654</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies</i>.</p>
<hr />

<p>The first thing that our <em>Post</em> presents you with this Week, is the summons of Ge. Middleton to the Gentry in the North, inciting then to come in, and engage as one man for their King and <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>, &amp; to yield obedience no longer to the English, but to speak truth, this is very <reg orig="disourable">dishonourable</reg>, and many are averse to their <unclear>present</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 3 characters--></unclear>factions; yet notwithstanding, they have <reg orig="randevouzed">rendezvoused</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Aberdeen, <unclear>having</unclear> two pieces of <reg orig="canon">cannon</reg>, ten thousand Arms and <unclear><!--approx. 4 characters-->hundred barrels</unclear> of Gun powder, col. Morgan is preparing to impede their further march.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><em>Tuesday</em> the 14 of <em>March.</em></head>

<p>This day Major <em>Bourn</em> and others were robbed at <reg orig="Shooters">Shooter's</reg> Hill, <i>an injury not to be born with:</i> many that had been before robbed were bound, and laid by in a Wood <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <reg orig="adjoyning">adjoining</reg>: the same Thieves assaulted a Coach coming from <em>Canterbury</em> wherein was one Gentleman, and two Ladies, with a Gentleman on horseback appertaining to the Coach, who with <reg orig="undanted">undaunted</reg> valour charging them, which were 5 in number, was in the Conflict slain, though assisted by him in the Coach, who received a shot, and fought with such gallantry, that he wounded one of the Thieves. Notwithstanding whose valour, the Coach at last was robbed of 30 l. but the Thieves, through haste and fear, did over-see 50 l. which was in a <reg orig="Portmantle">Portmanteau</reg>. The <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> was raised, and Col. <em>Bloant</em> made <reg orig="Hu">Hue</reg>-and Cry after them but to no effect. The Gentleman slain in the Combat was buried at <em>Greenwich</em>, and, as it is credibly reported, the Thief that was wounded coming to Mr. <em><reg orig="Moloines">Moloine's</reg></em>, a <reg orig="Chyrugeon">Surgeon</reg> in <reg orig="Shooe">Shoe</reg>-lane, to be <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>; and having laid down his Cloak, being desired to stay till a Gentleman wounded at <reg orig="Shooters">Shooter's</reg> hill was <reg orig="drest">dressed</reg>, <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to tempt his Destiny, made use of his heels, but not his Cloak; and being pursued with full cry, was (as 'tis <reg orig="rumour'd">rumoured</reg>) taken in Cheapside, and is like to make his Will at Tyburn.</p>

<p>The treaty between the Dutch Ambassadors, and our Commissioners, had some furtherance this day.</p>

<p>From on board the <em>Taunton</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> the 17 of <em>March</em> then <unclear>at <em>Portsmouth</em></unclear>; and by a Letter of a later date, thus: This day we came from Sea; but know not how soon we shall out again to meet with the <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg> of <em>Holland</em>: their number, as we have received intelligence, consists of one hundred and forty men of War.</p>

<p>From Upsal in Sweden Jan. 20. thus: The treaty goes on between the Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> and her Majesty by her grand Chancellor, who treats <reg orig="onely">only</reg> in the <reg orig="Latine">Latin</reg> Tongue. <i><unclear>Then</unclear> who but blind men would put out <em>England's</em> Eyes, the <em>Universities</em> like the Fox in the Fable, condemning the Grapes they cannot reach.</i></p>

<p>It was a saying of <em>Scipio</em>, that excellent Commanders, Statesmen, and Philosophers, that he loved not a City, <i>stantibus <unclear>manibus, ruentibus</unclear> moribus</i>. Let those Sons of Ignorance interpret the former by <pb n="2" />this saying of <unclear><em>Seneto</em></unclear>. <!--the following Latin is rather unclear I have made a guess at the words that are more clear--><i>O! <unclear>Vtinam vertulis adversarii, non alia ratione punerant ut, quod <!--approx. 10 characters--> virtulem videant, <!--approx 26 characters more than one word, possibly some punctuation--></unclear></i>. The two Ordinances touching Ministers, and touching the law is before a Committee, whereof Justice Hales in the Chair.</p>

<p>This day the Commissioners from the Lord Protector went from his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> in two Coaches, with the Secretary of State, and the Clerk of the Council, and their attendants to the Dutch Ambassadors, at Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg>; from whence they are not yet removed to Sir John <reg orig="Trevers">Trever's</reg>: they were met at the gate by the Lords Ambassadors, where the Lord Beverling made a speech to them and they received them with great respect and love on both sides. Being come into the House and into a chamber appointed for their Conference; they spent much time in order to the finishing of the peace. The business this day, was to confer their Papers of the agreement, for though they have agreed, yet it is <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> by each side, and on Wednesday last they compared their papers; which when both compared together, do in all particulars agree; then they are to sign on both sides. And what they sign, the Dutch Ambassadors do in the name of the States General. But to confirm it the more, it is to be sent to the States, who are also to give their assent after the Ratification, and then they deliver the Articles on both sides, which its conceived will be done within the space of three weeks.</p>

<p>This Certificate I have here inserted at the desire of Mr. <em>Edmund Felton</em>, and ancient, experienced, and approved Engineer.</p>

<p>Whereas <em>Edmund Felton</em> Gent. hath of late discovered unto the Committee of Fortification of the City of <em>London</em>, how an Engine of his Invention will secure the foot from the horse, and the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> from musket shot; one Engine to supply the room of 24 Pike men, or more, which said Engine two men may manage at pleasure: for the seeing of which we appointed some of the said <reg orig="Comittee">Committee</reg> to see and try the said Engine, which hath hanging Brest-works, and was shot at about 40 paces distant, the <reg orig="musquetiers">musketeers</reg> <reg orig="raming">ramming</reg> in powder and bullet, yet could not the shot pierce <reg orig="thorow">through</reg> the said Breast-work, which we who were appointed did see, and so reported to the rest of the Committee; And being requested by the said <em>Ed.Felton</em> so to <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg> under our hands of the truth of what we saw and reported of, we have done accordingly. Witness our Hands the 14 of March, 1653.</p>

<p><i>Vera Copia Ex.</i></p>
<p><i>Rich. Bateman, Tho. Nowel, Christopher Pack, <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Story, P. Miles</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>The Lord Protector and his Council have set forth an Ordinance for the continuing of <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>; and the Rates for every Barrel of Beer of Ale above 6 s. the barrel brewed by the common Brewer, or by any other person or persons who shall sell or tap out Beer or Ale <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> or privately, to be paid by the said Brewer or such other person or persons respectively is 2 s. For every Barrel of six shilling Beer or Ale, or above 4 shilling the Barrel 6d. And so <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> for a greater of lesser quantity of Beer or Ale above 4s. the Barrel And no allowance to be made from henceforth for any Beer or Ale to be used in Fishing Vessels at sea, which is bought of the <reg orig="comon">common</reg> Brewer or <reg orig="Retaler">Retailer</reg> of Beer or Ale. <reg orig="Allum">Alum</reg> English the hundred weight, containing 112 pounds, to be paid by the maker 6d. Coperas English, the hundred weight 6d. English Hops, the hundred weight, to be paid by the Planter 2s. English Saffron, for every 20 s. value, to be paid by the Planter 1 s. Tin, for every 20 s. value, to be paid by the buyer 1 s. Iron English, for every hundred weight, to be paid by the maker 1 sh. 6 d. For all Aquavitae or strong water made or distilled within the Commonwealth whether of <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> or <reg orig="domestick">domestic</reg> Spirits or materials to be sold upon every gallon, to be paid by the first maker or Seller thereof respectively two pence. For every barrel of <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within this Commonwealth of what sort soever, to be paid by the maker, and so <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg> for hard <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> or soft <reg orig="Sope">Soap</reg> made within the Land 4 s. For every Ounce Troy of silver or gold prepared, melted down, or disgrossed for <reg orig="Wyer">Wire</reg>, to be paid at the bar where the same shall be disgrossed 2 d. For every pound weight <reg orig="conteining">containing</reg> sixteen Ounces Averdupois, of any copper or other metal, that <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> prepared, and made fit or disgrossed, to be paid at the bar where the same <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> <reg orig="disgros'd">disgrossed</reg> one shilling. For all Linseed <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Blubber <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>, Rape <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, Pilchard <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, and all other <reg orig="oyls">oils</reg> made within this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, upon every Tun to be paid by the maker six s. <em>per</em> Tun, &amp;c.</p>

<p>For every Fother of Lead, <reg orig="conteining">containing</reg> 2000 weight, at 112 pounds to the hundred, to be paid by the maker or smelter 6s. 8d. For all Salt, made, or to be made within England, Wales, or the Town of Berwick, which is or <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> shipped or conveyed by water, to be paid by the first buyer of such Salt at the place of landing or unlading <reg orig="therof">thereof</reg>, <pb n="4" />upon every Gallon a half <reg orig="peny">penny</reg>. For all other salt, not shipped, or conveyed, to be paid by the first buyer upon delivering, every Gallon a half <reg orig="peny">penny</reg>. For all <reg orig="Syder">Cider</reg> and Perry, each Hogshead 2s. 6d. and so for a greater and less measure <reg orig="proportionably">proportionally</reg>. For all Metheglin or Mead, and such like Drinks sold out by <reg orig="retayl">retail</reg>, to be paid by the <reg orig="Retayler">Retailer</reg> on every Gallon, and so <em>pro rata</em>, one <reg orig="peny">penny</reg>. For all Starch, upon every 20 s. value, to be paid by the first maker one s. For all sorts of <reg orig="Glasse">Glass</reg> or glasses, upon every 20 s. value, to be paid by the maker one shilling.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Rates of Excise of <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> goods imported.</i></head>

<p>For every pound of Tobacco not of the English Plantation <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> already imported and remaining in the hands of the Merchant or Importer, as to be imported to be paid by the first buyer one s. For every pound of Tobacco of the English Plantation, <reg orig="aswel">as well</reg> imported and remaining in the hands of the Importer as to be imported, to be paid by the first buyer 3 d. For every tun of Wine already imported or to be imported, to be paid by the first buyer 6l. For every tun of Wine Vinegar 2l. For all kind of Spirits, each Gallon 4d. For all strong Waters, each Gallon 1s. For all Beer or Ale imported by sea, or brought in by land into England, Wales, or town of Berwick, for every Barrel to be paid by the Importer 5s. For all <reg orig="Peppars">Peppers</reg>, Sugars, white and brown Muscavadoes, Candy white and brown, and all other grocer and mercery wares, wrought silks, <reg orig="stiks">sticks</reg> in gum, <reg orig="Linnens">Linens</reg> fine and course, Upholstery, Haberdashery, Paper, skins, and Leather, upon every 20 s. value to be paid by the first buyer one s. For all manner of drugs, according as they are distinguished by the book of Rates for the custom, upon every 20 s. value, to be paid by first buyer 20s. For every hundred weight of <reg orig="forein">foreign</reg> <reg orig="sope">soap</reg> 5s. For all <reg orig="forein">foreign</reg> Hops, the hundred weight 5s. For all hemp, flax, tow, tar, Rozen, pitch, wax, tallow, cable yarn, and all manner of cordage, upon every 20s. to be paid 6d. For all sorts of glasses and earthen ware, upon every 20s. to be paid 2s. For all raw silk, upon every 20s. to be paid 6p. For all <reg orig="forrein">foreign</reg> salt, each gallon three half pence. For all bonelace imported for every 20s. in value, 3s. For all <reg orig="died">dyed</reg> silk imported for every 20s. value 5s. For all silk Lace, every 20s. value 3. And all other goods and <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg> imported, or to be imported, upon which no values are set, either in the said book of Rates for <reg orig="Customes">Customs</reg>, not in these present Rates for <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, upon every 20s. value, to be paid by the first buyer one shilling. </p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>This day his Highness the Lord Protector took up his Lodgings at Whitehall, and thereby hath made it a Court, for <reg orig="Princes">Princes'</reg> presences make Courts, and not the Princes. See! What a <reg orig="Prophetick">Prophetic</reg> Spirit <em>Auluem</em> had, that he began to write on this very week, wherein his Highness vouchsafed to honour <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>As welcome as is the green-mantled Spring</line>
<line><reg orig="Vnto">Unto</reg> the plumed Quire, the who joyfully sing</line>
<line>And Carol welcomes, as the Plants we see</line>
<line>Now revelling in Summer <reg orig="Liverie">Livery</reg>:</line>
<line>Indeed, my Lord, <reg orig="you'r">you're</reg> mightier <reg orig="then">than</reg> a King,</line>
<line>He brings in glittering <unclear>Trains</unclear>, but you the Spring.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> March 17.</head>

<p>The Highlanders increase in Scotland, and Gen. Middleton begins to play <em>Rex</em> again: they has a <reg orig="Rendevous">Rendezvous</reg> upon the 11 instant, and are now marching towards the Lord <reg orig="Reaffs">Reaff's</reg> Bounds. There hath lately happened a great disaster between Cap. <reg orig="Palmers">Palmer's</reg> troop and Cap. <reg orig="Masons">Mason's</reg>, the manner thus: Cap. Palmer having pursued the enemy, at last met with a party of horse, which he took to be the enemy, whereupon he charged them desperately, but were as gallantly repulsed by Cap. Mason, who charged them through and through, and for the space of half an hour the business was very disputable, in which unhappy engagement 6 were slain on both sides and 8 wounded, whereof Cap. Palmer is one.</p>

<p>From Plymouth <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have certain intelligence, that the <reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath sent in 9 ships, which was taken upon the French Coast, and the Non-such <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> hath taken three delicate Vessels laden with Wine, Beans and Salt. Nine more taken on the Coast of Scotland and Cap. Wilkins hath taken another, bravely fraught with rich <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg>. The Royal <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> is now put forth to sea, and rides in Stoke bay. Two <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships that were coming from Ipswich toward London, were taken by a Dutch man of war, they <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the English of both under the Decks of one of them, on the 4 of March, and then left them, sending them homeward; but the next day the English at a seasonable time lifted up the decks relieved themselves, took the Dutch and <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> them under the deck where they were, and brought away both their ships to the Downs which are now safe in the River, with the prisoners.</p>

<p>The Queen of <em>Bohemia</em> <unclear>(</unclear>sister to the late King of Great Britain) is going to <em>Frankendale</em>, which is her Dowry, a most wealthy place, and great frequentation, it being the mid-way betwixt <em>Wormes</em> and <em>Spiers</em>, where she will do the best she can to entertain young <em>Charles</em>, and to accommodate him in the present juncture of <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg>. His brother JAMES (second Son to his late Majesty) is as valiant as Hector <pb n="6" />in the King of France's Army; but the little Queen (his Mother) is of a sudden struck very solentary The Lord <em>Wilmot</em>, and the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> so with much importunity press upon the loyal breasts of the English in several places to support the weak distressed Estate of their Prince; especially at the city of <reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg>, where the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> did <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> <reg orig="solicite">solicit</reg> and importune the Treasurer of the English company, who fearing his power, and loath to part with those monies which belonged to all the English Merchants who <reg orig="traffick">traffic</reg> in those parts, acquainted the President of the English Companies with it, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> the inconveniences that would arise if he <reg orig="shold">should</reg> deliver <reg orig="moneyes">monies</reg> to him. Whereupon the President weighing the truth of the Reasons, made his complaint to the Senate, who <reg orig="enjoyned">enjoined</reg> the Lord <em>Wentworth</em> not to exact any sums of money of the Treasurer, unless he was able to put in good security for the re-disbursing of them.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> we have received intelligence that the Constant Warwick, and the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> being together, met with the great <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> Cap. <em>Beach</em>, who had newly taken two prizes; but perceiving that out <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> intended to pursue him, he left the Prizes, and was afterward secured by the night coming on. The same night the Portsmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> and the constant Warwick chanced to part company, and it so fell out about midnight that <em>Beach</em> raving about, lighted on the <em>Constant Warwick</em> all alone, which before he came near, he took to be a Merchant man, and went on with an intent to board him; but the <em>Warwick</em> demanding who he was, he <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> he was the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> and for <em><reg orig="Whit-Hall">Whithall</reg></em>. But the <em>Warwick</em> suspecting him, bade him round off. Then <em>Beach</em> perceiving his mistake, and seeing the <em>Warwick</em> to be a man of <reg orig="Warre">War</reg>, he presently made away; but the <em>Warwick</em> being a good <reg orig="Sailer">Sailor</reg>, made after him, and kept company with him all night. About 6 in the morning, <em>Beach</em> began the fight, firing 3. Guns, which were answered by the <em>Warwick</em>. The encounter lasted till two in the afternoon, at which time <em>Beach</em> and his men called for Quarter, and had it. He had five foot water in the hold when he yielded; he had 200 men, 20 whereof were killed; his <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> is a gallant new Vessel, of 42 Guns, whereof but 38 thirty eight were mounted. There are taken aboard with him <pb n="7" />nine Captain, and 200 <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, who are all close prisoners, and ready to resign themselves up to the merits of Justice. There are several Articles of High-Treason exhibited against this famous <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> capt. <em>Beach</em>; who disputed the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the Seas in the Royal James with great Resolution: insomuch, that coming aboard the Warwick, he demanded of valiant cap. <em>Potter</em> the manner of performing his Articles, and said it was his promise to see him ashore in <em>France</em>; whereupon cap. <em>Potter</em> answered, That he never heard of such Demand; but to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> him, proffered cap, <em>Beach</em> to go aboard his own ship again, and fight it out; but the captain refused it, retorting, <i>No Sir, 'tis good sleeping in a whole skin.</i></p>

<p>The Ordinance before mentioned is to commence from the 25 day of March, 1654. and to continue to the 25 day of March 1655. And all Courts of Justice of this <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and all Judges and Justices of the same and all Sheriffs, <reg orig="Councellors">Councillors</reg>, Attorneys, Solicitors, and all other persons, are hereby required to conform themselves accordingly, without any opposition or dispute whatsoever. The Names of the Commissioners constituted and appointed for putting in execution this new Impost and <reg orig="Excize">Excise</reg>, are</p>

<!--table in 2 columns-->

<!--column 1-->
<p><em>Thomas Allen</em>, Alderman of the city of <em>London.</em></p>
<p><em>Thomas Wood</em>,</p>
<p><em>George Bury</em></p>

<!--column 2-->
<p><em>George Langham</em> Esquires.</p>
<p>AND</p>
<p><em>Gearge Foxcroft</em> Merchant.</p>

<p>There is newly given in an account of the vast sum of moneys due upon <reg orig="publike">public</reg> faith, and the <reg orig="Souldier">Soldier</reg> Arrears, which amounts to nine millions of money; but care is taken to <reg orig="audite">audit</reg> their Accounts.</p>

<p>We hear that his Highness hath demanded of Monsieur <em>Bourdeaux</em>, Ambassador for the King of France, restitution from that crown, for the injuries <reg orig="sustainded">sustained</reg> by the English; which if granted, there will then <reg orig="necessay">necessary</reg> follow, a firm and lasting peace.</p>

<p>The Peers of this Nation and the Gentry have cordially embraced the silver thread of Amity, and have declared to live peaceably under the present Government. But from Scotland our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, that the Royal party there is too prone to Ruptures, having taken a Castle, and some other Passes. Middleton has furnished them with Arms and Ammunition, and has brought them some <reg orig="canons">cannons</reg>.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">READER, BY reason of several Post-letters being intercepted, I was constrained to impede and adjourn a day; but hereafter expect us on the Tuesday.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>