<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost$127#2">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 127#2</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2"><i>The Grand Politique</i></head>
<head level="1">POST</head>
<head level="3">Truly Representing</head>

<!--the following paragraph has very erratic use of italics, I have not attempted to tag for emphasis-->

<p><i>The Declaration of his</i> Highness the Lord Protector, and his Honourable Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, <i>concerning the</i> Dukes, Earls, Lords, Knights, and Gentry, <i>throughout</i> England, Scotland, and Ireland; <i>with the</i> Orders of his Highness <i>to all the</i> Free-Born People, <i>and a</i> Narrative <i><reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> what shall be adjudged</i> High-Treason <i>within this</i> <reg orig="Common-Wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, and all the Dominions thereunto belonging: <i>The sending of</i> Letters into all Counties throughout England and Wales; <i>the advancing of</i> Gen Blake with the English Fleet; <i>the conveying of the Merchants over the Narrow seas; and the number of Dutch ships taken on the Western channel. The</i> Proclamation concerning Brass Farthings, and the Order for the tolerating of them to pass free and current, without any let or molestation.</p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> Jan. 17. to <em>Tuesday</em> Jan 24. 1653</head>
<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON, Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<p>These are to give notice unto all whom it may concern, that it is thought meet and requisite (out of a tender respect and care to the Weal-<reg orig="publique">public</reg>) that Brass Farthings be tolerated to pass free and current, and that none presume to refuse them, until such time that his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> shall be pleased to prohibit them, which I hope will never be. As touching the Blazing Star seen lately Westward, I cannot say much; but give me leave to think the more; and to praise some body with <reg orig="teares">tears</reg> in my eyes, as great men do mustard.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>Having in my last represented you with the <reg orig="Virgins">Virgin's</reg> <reg orig="Prophesie">Prophecy</reg>, I shall in this communicate the Sonnet after <em>Democritus</em>, contained in the <em><reg orig="Hu">Hue</reg></em>-and-<em>cry</em>, VIZ.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The <reg orig="Cryers">Crier's</reg> <unclear>Inquest</unclear> after Mercurius Democritus.</i></head>

<head level="3">A SONNET</head>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line><reg orig="Ore">O'er</reg> Hills, Dales, Crags, Rocks, Mountains,</line>
<line>in <em>Cynthia's</em> gloomy Walks;</line>
<line><reg orig="Ore">O'er</reg> Caves, Lakes, Rivers, <reg orig="Fountaines">Fountains</reg>,</line>
<line>where <reg orig="Eccho">Echo</reg> mocks my talks.</line>
<line>Through Clouds, Fogs, pitchy Darkness</line>
<line>in dull <em>Cymmentian</em> Night,</line>
<line>When <reg orig="Dayes">Days</reg> cry out of <reg orig="shortnesse">shortness</reg>,</line>
<line>and <em>Sol</em> denies his light.</line>
<line>With <reg orig="Voyce">Voice</reg> more loud <reg orig="then">than</reg> Thunder</line>
<line><em>Democritus</em> I cry,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Windes">Winds</reg> so meet with wonder,</line>
<line>the Seas do backward fly.</line>
<line>With <em>Mercury</em> I <reg orig="chanc'd">chanced</reg> to meet,</line>
<line>and thus to him did say,</line>
<line>Lend me thy Wand and <em>winged feet</em></line>
<line>that I may fly away,</line>
<line>The <reg orig="Suns">Sun's</reg> bright <unclear>horse I</unclear> mounted,</line>
<line>and overthrew his <unclear>Car</unclear>,</line>
<line>Each Region short I counted</line>
<line>though it were <reg orig="nere">ne'er</reg> so far.</line>
<line>And crying still <em>Democritus</em>,</line>
<line>one answered me in <reg orig="spight">spite</reg>,</line>
<line>Go seek him in <em>Noctunicus</em>,</line>
<line>th'<em>Antipodes</em> to light.</line>
<line>To <unclear>Wood street</unclear> Counter then I came</line>
<line>where in a danksome Cell</line>
<line>I <reg orig="call'd">called</reg> <em>Democritus</em> by Name,</line>
<line>who <reg orig="cry'd">cried</reg> out <em>I'm in Hell</em>,</line>
<line>On <em><unclear>Cerberus</unclear></em> I then did fly,</line>
<line>for to <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> my friend;</line>
<line>And then I <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> my <em>Hue-and-Cry</em>,</line>
<line>and so <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters more than one word--></unclear> end.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3">Jan 17.</head>

<p>Presents us with two notable Letters from <em>Hereford</em>; the exact copies take as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>The first Letter.</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>The wise and zealous Commissioners of the city of <em>Hereford</em> have appointed one reverend and worthy Doctor in Divinity, and another learned Master of Arts, to be Collectors for the first <reg orig="sixe">six</reg> <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> contribution in the said city <reg orig="joyning">joining</reg> them with Barbers, <reg orig="Shoo">Shoe</reg> makers, and <unclear><!--8 characters--></unclear>, for their co-partners; all which actions are contrary to an Act of Parliament made in the 17 year of the late king <em>Charles</em>, which <reg orig="dis-inabled">disenabled</reg> all persons in holy Orders to exercise <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters, 2 words--></unclear> jurisdictions: And the reason in the said Act being given <i><unclear><!--approx 14 characters--></unclear>ought not to be <reg orig="intangled">entangled</reg> with secular jurisdiction or <unclear>affair</unclear></i> which is presumed, that it never was intended by the said Act; to <unclear><reg orig="dis-enable">disenable</reg></unclear> process in holy Orders, to exercise any temporal Authority to eminent places of jurisdiction; and to permit inferior Officers to make them <reg orig="lyable">liable</reg> to be put in such Office, as Collectors, or Constables; all which is presumed to be contrary to the Lord Protector, and the Act which gave the said commissioners power to nominate Assessors and Collectors: Which disgraceful affronts to the sacred <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, hath forced such learned Divines to leave their habitations and to sojourn in other countries, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> to violate their Calling, or to submit to such reproach, and prostrate their sacred Function to such an apparent disgrace.</p>

<p><i>Hereford <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. 9. 1659<!--1659 is in the original presumably a mistake--></i></p>

<head level="3"><i>The second Letter.</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>I am to inform you, that those in authority in this city, on <em>Christmas</em> Eve last, sent to all the Bakers in and about the city, to charge and prohibit them that they should bake no Pies on <em>Christmas</em> day; but whether for fear of burning, or baking them too hard, I know not. For other News at present we have none, save a general <reg orig="rejoycing">rejoicing</reg> at the change of Government, as it is now established by a Lord Protector.</p>

<p><i>Hereford 10. 1653</i></p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>By intelligence from Scotland we are advertised, that some hundreds of horse and foot are landed in the North, with great store of arms and ammunition; and <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg> Fame gives out, that their Standard is drawn forth in white Sarcenet, according to the ensuing figure; which if true, confident I am that their Crowns and Coronets <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be cast off from their stately Pillars, and their Rampant Powers cast down like so many <reg orig="Mole-hills">Molehills</reg>.</p>

<img src="" alt="shield with 3 lions/checked field between 2 crown topped pillars" />

<head level="2"><reg orig="Vnder">Under</reg> the Crowns be it spoken</head>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector and his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council have set forth and Ordinance, declaring, that if any person or persons shall compass or imagine the death of the Lord Protector, it <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be</p>

<head level="2">Treason</head>

<pb n="4" />

<p>Secondly <unclear>that if any person or persons shall maliciously</unclear> or advisedly either by <unclear>writing, printing,</unclear> openly declaring, preaching, teaching or otherwise publish, that the Lord Protector and the people in Parliament assembled are not the <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Authority of this Commonwealth; or that the Exercise of the chief Magistracy, and administration of the Government over the said Countries and Dominions, and the people thereof, is not in the Lord Protector, assisted with a Council, it shall be</p>

<head level="2">Treason</head>

<p>Thirdly that if any person or persons <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> say that the present Government is tyrannical, usurped, or unlawful; or that there is any Parliament now in being, or that hath any continuance, or any Law in force for continuing the Parliament, which is declared to have been absolutely dissolved and determined upon the 20 day of April 1653. and shall be adjudged and taken so to be; or shall plot, contrive, or <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to stir up or raise force against the Protector or the present Government, or for the subversion or alteration of the same, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> declare any such <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> or <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> by any open Deed, then every such offence shall be taken and adjudged to be</p>

<head level="2">High Treason</head>

<p>But for your further satisfaction, I shall refer you to the Ordinance <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, printed by <em>Henry Hills</em>; Printer to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>Our last Post from the West certifieth, that Gen. Blake is gone aboard the Navy, and that the fleet are all preparing to put out to sea; which sudden motion is conceived to be upon the great preparations of the Hollander, and the abundant of <reg orig="Punctillioes">Punctilios</reg> insisted upon by the States, in reference to their Answers for an Agreement for peace. Gen. Pen has <reg orig="convoyen">convoyed</reg> a fleet of English Merchants over the narrow Seas, and upon his return towards the Isle of Wight, took two prizes.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>After much diligence and inquiry into the truth of the Declaration of Hannah the Prophetess, one of M. <reg orig="Simpsons">Simpson's</reg> church, who hath lain above 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at Whitehall sometimes in a trance, and sometimes singing and praying; but having finished her time, she left the ensuing Declaration for his Highness, and is now returned to <reg orig="Hacney">Hackney</reg>.</p>

<p>That the eternal Lord God, and great Jehovah-Nissi, would be pleased to protect his Highness, and keep him close to himself, as he hath hitherto, so still to have his heart set upon the things of the Lord; not to be vain, nor regard earthly pomp and pleasures, and things below, but the things of God and his people, that he may be delivered from carnal <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg>, and being seduced to please the men of the world, and those that seek unrighteousness, that he may not leave the counsel of the godly, to hearken to those who are worldly wise and earthly politicians, but wise in the wisdom of God; that the <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> whom God hath made instrumental to overcome the enemy without, and in the world, may not be overcome of their inward spiritual enemies, to provoke God to lay them aside, and make use of others the perfecting of that Work in which God hath so far employed them. That the Merchants of this Nation would not so far seek and mind their great profit by sea, as thereby to provoke and ungodly and wicked peace with the Dutch. That the Lord would cause the people of this Nation to leale their sins and profaneness as Gentlewomen black spots and patches, powderings of hair, gold and silver lace and all other wickedness whatsoever. Lo which, let all the Saints and people of God say <go>Amen, Amen.</go></p>

<p>At the Sessions in the Old-<reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg> was arraigned one Eliz. Wenman, who lived in White-<reg orig="chappel">chapel</reg>, but having her <reg orig="pres'd">pressed</reg> for a <reg orig="sea-man">seaman</reg> <reg orig="bewitcht">bewitched</reg> the <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> wife that <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg> him, and 3 children, some lame and blind; others so bound in their bodies, that they had no vent downwards: insomuch that the Mother went to the Doctors who administered <reg orig="physick">physic</reg>, and wrought it: then she came again, and he appointed her to make a Cake and knead it with her own water, &amp; eat it, using these words, which he gave her in writing. Lord <reg orig="sanctifie">sanctify</reg> this unto me, and grant that by its full and perfect operation, the evil Spirit may be cast out from amongst us; but when she had eaten it, she was almost distracted, and running and raging to M. Lilly, he presently cast a figure, and bid her go to the <reg orig="Witches">Witch's</reg> house, and demand her picture, which she did, and making search in her house, she found the said picture, and some of her <reg orig="childrens">children's</reg>, which she did carry home and burnt; and they <reg orig="stunck">stunk</reg> extremely for 3 or 4 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; but thrusting an hot iron into the breech of her own picture, she went orderly to stool, since which time her children are likewise recovered. And in those places of her body where she was pained the picture had holes pierced in it, which she brought and <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> to the Bench.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>The Witch before mentioned having a desire to receive the Sacrament with a Gathered Church, she was told, that she was not to be admitted, because she was reputed to be a Witch, and had bewitched such a woman and her children: she denied it, appealing to her God: she was asked who was her God? she said the god of the world, and wished that she might never speak if it was true; and that GOD would <reg orig="shew">show</reg> some eminent judgement upon her if it was true. Whereupon she was presently struck lame and dumb, and ever since <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> nothing but <reg orig="I">Aye</reg> and No. For which she hath received Sentence of Death.</p>

<p>The Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg> of Hull, and the rest of the Garrisons throughout the Nation,, have sent up a Declaration to his Highness; a Copy whereof followeth:</p>

<p>Having for many years past been led under your conduct, through many difficult services, wherein through the blessing of God upon the vigilancy and <reg orig="endeavors">endeavours</reg> of your Highness, we have in some measure <reg orig="bin">been</reg> instrumental in our places to free the Commonwealth from <reg orig="its">it's</reg> enemies: so <reg orig="wee">we</reg> now cannot but above all worldly things most earnestly desire to set these Nations after all the shakings that have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> in the midst of us, set up upon its true and proper Basis and Foundation, &amp; thereby brought into a <reg orig="harbor">harbour</reg> of rest and safety. The <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> whereof having led us to the consideration of what further might be our duties towards your Highness, <unclear>so</unclear> the whole Nation, at this time when it pleased God to give us hope of establishment by inclining you to accept of the Government and protection of this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>; whereby we are <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that the liberties of the people, both as men and Christians, will through the mercy of God be assured: We judge it highly cumbent upon us to make our humble address unto you, and to declare that We shall not only be obedient unto you in the performance of your great Trust: but in our places most faithfully and diligently to the hazard of our lives and whatsoever is near and dear unto us be serviceable unto you in the Station God hath placed you in against all opposition: Not doubting but as God and Man hath so highly <reg orig="intrusted">entrusted</reg> you; so you will to the uttermost of your power and endeavours lay forth your Self for the glory of God, and the good of this people; amongst whom we have reason to think there are very many of the <reg orig="Houshold">Household</reg> of Faith; over whom we shall take this boldness most humbly to <reg orig="intreat">entreat</reg> your Highness more especially to spread the wing of your protection, and to account of them as the apple of your eye, the which you continuing to do, We are confident their Father which is in Heaven, will be unto you a Buckler and a Shield, and an exceeding great reward, which is and shall be the prayer of</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> most humble and faithful Servants,</i></p>

<p>From France our last <em>Post</em> advertised, That there is a great <reg orig="Imbargo">Embargo</reg> laid upon the English ships by King Lewis and his great council; but the Protestants look very big upon the Crown, so that the <reg orig="splendor">splendour</reg> of its glorious Diadem begin now to be eclipsed.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>William Earl of Glencairn, Lord Killmaris, Commander in chief of His <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Forces within the Kingdom of Scotland.</p>

<p><go>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission directed to us by his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> for <reg orig="leavying">levying</reg> if forces, horse and foot, for suppressing the Common Enemy within this kingdom. We do hereby require you, and every of you, within this of <em>Ayre</em> and <em>Renfrew</em>, upon sight hereof, to sound forth for his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service (forth of every thousand pounds rent within your said shires respectively, one sufficient well-mounted man, with Pistols, and other furniture and weapons belonging thereto, and to deliver the same at <em>Rosdew</em>, to Lieuten. Col. George Maxwell, Lieut. Col. <em>George Herriot</em> and Captain <em>James Cunningham</em>, or any having their Orders to that effect; certifying that all Persons of whatsoever quality, within the said Shires respectively, that doth either refuse or delay to give Obedience: is this our Order and Command, they shall be taken notice of, and proceeded against as <reg orig="disloyall">disloyal</reg> <unclear>Subjects</unclear>, and <reg orig="profess'd">professed</reg> Enemies to the present Expedition; Whereas by the contrary <reg orig="Wee">We</reg> do hereby Oblige <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> to <unclear>protect</unclear> and defend against all Enemies whatsoever, all such as <unclear><!--4 characters--></unclear> willingly put forth their <reg orig="severall">several</reg> propositions of the foresaid Horse <reg orig="leavy">levy</reg>, and whatsoever Horses, or any other Goods, shall be taken from any one of them, so <unclear><!--9 characters--></unclear> in any disorderly manner, shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be restored again but the Person or Persons <reg orig="offendors">offenders</reg>, shall according to the quality of the offence at the sight of the Party offended, be <reg orig="seveerly">severely</reg> punished, to the terror of others, And ordains this to be published at every Headbrough, or Parish Church, within the said shires respectively, That every heritor, and others therein contained, pretend no ignorance of the <reg orig="premisses">premises</reg>.</go></p>

<p>Given at Garth, the 23 of December, 1653.</p>

<p>Sic subscribitur, GLENCARN.</p>

<p>For the whole Noblemen, gent. Heritors, and others. Inhabitants within the <reg orig="Sherif">Sheriff</reg>-doms of Ayre, and <reg orig="Ranfrew">Renfrew</reg>.</p> 

<p>We expect your answer at Rosdew the 6 of January, 1654.</p>

<p><go>There happened an unhappy Accident in the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> if Ely, Viz. 3 or 4 Gent, having been sporting at <em><reg orig="Feasants">Pheasants</reg></em>, came towards the Evening to repose and refresh themselves to a petty Inn in <em>Macch</em>, a small <reg orig="Towne">Town</reg> in the <reg orig="Ile">Isle</reg> of Ely, where finding no good accommodation, they sent for three of four Bottles of Wine to <em>Wichbich</em>, some other company being in the house, sent to them, to desire a Bottle of their Wine, which caused a Dispute amongst them, in which fray, one <em>Mr. Mallory</em> was killed by one <unclear>Dyman</unclear>, who is since fled, and some others of their Company committed to Prison.</go></p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>