<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost177">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 177</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Weekly</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Articles of Agreement between her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, and his Excellency the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, for the concluding of a firm and everlasting Peace between the Crown and Subjects of that Kingdom, and the Commonwealth of England. The intercepting of a Letter from Mr. John Lilburn, and carrying it to his Highness the Lord Protector, The landing of 7000 men in the North of Scotland; their marching up towards Gen. Middleton, the <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> of the English Fleet upon the Downs; the new Instructions and Design of Gen. Pen, the advancing of the English fleet Northwards, and the going of the gallant Fairfax Admiral.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> the 2. Of <em>May</em>, to <em>Tuesday</em> the 8 of <em>May</em> 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G, Horton</em>, <i>for information of the People.</i>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Game's not yet at an end, <em>Gentlemen</em>, we have more Cards still to play: and there seems to be a notable <reg orig="Confederacie">Confederacy</reg> amongst the <em>German Princes</em>; whom we hear, are endeavouring to bring to their Alliance his <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Majesty of <em>Spain</em>, and the Duke of <em>Florence</em>, and to attempt something (if possible) in behalf of the distressed Family: But <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable, we may have an Errand to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the great Duke, and demand satisfaction for the loss of our good <em>Bonadventure</em>, and other delicate ships, at <em>Leghorn</em>: The seamen are very unanimous, and desire nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> action.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The Articles of the perpetual peace, concluded between his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c. <reg orig="one">on</reg> the one part; and the high and mighty Lords, the States-General of the United Provinces of the Netherlands on the other part.</p>

<p><i>1 <unclear>That from henceforward</unclear> there shall be a firm <reg orig="unchangable">unchangeable</reg> Peace, sincere friendship and a closer Alliance, and Confederacy between the Commonwealth of England, and the States of the United Provinces <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been ever heretofore, and of their respective Lands, Cities, and Countries, and of all under their obedience wheresoever, and of what <unclear>condition</unclear> soever.</i></p>

<p><i>2. That from henceforth all hostility shall cease.</i></p>

<p><i>3. That all <unclear>wrongs</unclear> and offences suffered by the one, or the other party shall be forgotten and <unclear>neither</unclear> party shall pretend anything thereupon. All actions shall be nulled, except those that shall be done in the British seas after the time of 12 days, and from that <unclear>Sea to the</unclear> Cape of St. Vincent in the time of six weeks, and from thence in the <unclear>Mediterranean sea</unclear>, as far as the line after the time of ten weeks, and at the other side of the line <unclear>in the time</unclear> of eight <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, to be <unclear>resigned</unclear> from the time of the publication of the Peace, and all prizes taken after that time shall be restored.</i></p>

<p><i>4. That all the prisoners on both sides be released without ransom.</i></p>

<p><i>5. That both Commonwealths shall be considerate friends to defend one the other against whosoever.</i></p>

<p><i>6. That neither of both shall act against the other either by Land or by Sea.</i></p>

<p><i>7. That the States shall cause restitution to be made of all the ships and goods seized upon the English by the King of Denmark, that are yet in being, as also a full compensation of the worth of the goods that may be sold already, and likewise that all damages and spoil of goods shall be made good to the Owners, by estimation, and when such satisfaction shall to be done the said King, then all hostility shall cease between England and Denmark.</i></p>

<p><i>8. That no Inhabitants of either Commonwealth shall assist any Rebel of either with money, <unclear>ships</unclear> victuals.</i></p>

<p><i>9. That both Commonwealths shall assist one the other at their proper charges against their Rebels.</i></p>

<p><i>10. That neither shall receive those that are, or shall be declared enemies of either Commonwealth.</i></p>

<p><i>11. That either Commonwealth having notice by the other that some of their enemies are in <reg orig="its">it's</reg> Dominions, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give them warning to depart in 28 days upon pain of death.</i></p>

<p><i>12. That the English shall not pass greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> other Nations.</i></p>

<p><i>13. That the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships shall strike their Flag before the English in the British seas.</i></p>

<p><i>14. That neither of the Commonwealths shall give retreat to any <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> in any of their Ports.</i></p>

<p><i>15. That in case the English of the Dutch make any Treaty with any Prince, they shall therein comprehend each other reciprocally; if they desire it.</i></p>

<p><i>16. That in case some hostility should happen between the inhabitants of both Commonwealths, by one against the other; that the Alliance shall <reg orig="neverthelesse">nevertheless</reg> hold and remain in full force; and the parties that shall be found guilty shall be punished.</i></p>

<pb n="2" />

<p><i>17.That the Subjects of the Commonwealth of England shall freely travel through all quarters of the United Provinces by water or by land, or into any Cities or <reg orig="Garisons">Garrisons</reg> thereof, armed or unarmed, provided they go not above 40 in a company, either with or without their <reg orig="Merchandize">Merchandise</reg>; and the Subjects of the Netherlands are to have the like <reg orig="priviledge">privilege</reg> in England, and every, and all places under their subjection, carrying themselves submissively to the Laws of each Commonwealth.</i></p>

<p><i>18. That if it so fall out, that any ships of either State shall by storm or <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> be driven into any of the Heavens of the one or the other State, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> have liberty to go to sea again at their pleasure with their ships and goods, without paying any Custom or Impost; provided, that they break not the <reg orig="bulke">bulk</reg>, behaving themselves according to the <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and <reg orig="customes">customs</reg> of the place where they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take harbour.</i></p>

<p><i>29.<!--29 in text, presumably an error--> That no Merchants or Mariners of one or the other Commonwealth shall have their goods, ships, or <reg orig="merchandizes">merchandises</reg> arrested in any of the havens or rivers or either Commonwealth to serve at War, or otherwise, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of any general or particular command, except it be upon some inevitable necessity, and then to have satisfaction, not including herein, the Arrests by ordinary Courts of Justice.</i></p>

<p><i>20. That the Merchants, and their Factors, and servants, and the Mariners may travel and turn back again to their ships from the seas, waters, and havens of the one and the other Commonwealth and at their landing may use for defence of themselves, and their goods, all sorts Arms, offensive and defensive, save <reg orig="onely">only</reg>, that being come to their <reg orig="Inne">Inn</reg>, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> lay their Arms aside until they return into their ships again.</i></p>

<p><i>21. That men of War of both Commonwealths, or Merchants ships meeting together at sea, they shall defend each other against all whomsoever that shall offer to make any attempt upon either of them, so long as they sail on course.</i></p>

<p><i>22. That if any ship or ships of either <reg orig="Republicke">Republic</reg>, or of a Neutrality shall by a third party be taken out of the havens or Dominions of either Commonwealth, both parties shall be engaged to follow the business for the restitution of the ships and goods to the owners.</i></p>

<p><i>23. That Searchers and other such Officers in the execution of their Office, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> regulate themselves according to the Laws of each Country, and take no more of any <reg orig="then">than</reg> is permitted by their Instructions.</i></p>

<p><i>24. That if one party shall cause some damages to the other, there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be no Letters of Reprisal given: But if in three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> time, no satisfaction is done, then the said Letters may be granted.</i></p>

<p><i>25. That all persons of either Commonwealth going to sea with particular Commissions, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be obliged by sufficient sureties, before the Judges of the Court where they receive their Commissions, That they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> do no damage to any subject of either Commonwealth.</i></p>

<p><i>26. That no more but eight ships of War <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be suffered to come or remain in the Ports of each <reg orig="others">other's</reg> Commonwealth at one time: And when there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be occasion for a greater number, then the consent trust be first asked.</i></p>

<p><i>27. That the States <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> so Justice upon those that be found alive, that have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the English in Amboyna.</i></p>

<p><i>28. That there <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be Commissioners established to examine the wrongs or injuries <!--ries repeated over line break-->done, or <reg orig="pretendedd">pretended</reg> to be done or suffered by the Inhabitants of either Commonwealth <pb n="3" />in the East-Indies, Greenland, Muscovey, <reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg>, or other places. And if the Commissioners cannot agree thereupon within the time of three <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>, then the aforesaid differences to be referred to the Judgement of the Protestant <em>Switzers</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>29. And whereas formerly, some question and misunderstanding hath arisen between the Commonwealth of England, and the King of Denmark, by reason of the detaining of some ships and goods, it is agreed, and concluded on both sides, that satisfaction being given, all differences whatsoever shall be forgotten and buried in eternal Oblivion, so as the said King, Kingdoms and Dominions, shall be received in this Treaty as a friend, in such manner, that he shall be re-established in the amity of the Commonwealth, as he was formerly before the said detention, and his Deputies and Ambassadors shall be admitted with the like Honour, as the Deputies and other Ambassadors of other States being in amity.</i></p>

<p><i>30. It is further agreed, that at the time when the ratification shall be delivered, four Commissioners shall be nominated on both sides, who on the 18 of May next ensuing, English stile, shall meet here in London, to consider and moderate all injuries and damages, on either side, from the year 1611. to the 18 of May, 1652. and in case of non-agreement, to refer it to the judgement and <!--umpirage??-->umpieridge of the Switzer Protestant Cantons.</i></p>

<p><i>31 Furthermore, it is agreed and concluded, That both parties shall truly and firmly keep and maintain this present Treaty, and all the matters therein contained, and strictly take care, that the same be observed and performed by either of their people.</i></p>

<p>32 <unclear>Then</unclear><i> For further certainty an assurance that this peace an amity shall be uprightly, and in good faith observed, the States General do oblige an bind themselves, that all and every Officer both by sea and land shall be bound to confirm this Treaty, and all the Articles thereof, and promise sacredly upon Oath, that they shall, as far as is possible, religiously observe the same, and as far as to them belongeth, shall perform the same, and take care that it be observed and performed by others.</i></p>

<p><i>33 Furthermore it is agreed, concluded, and accorded, that this present Treaty, and all that is therein comprised and expressed, shall be confirmed by the said Lord Protector, and the States General aforesaid, by open Letters on both sides, confirmed with the great Seal; in due and <reg orig="authentick">authentic</reg> form, within 15 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> next ensuing, or sooner if it can be done, and that within the said time, the Ratification on both sides <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> exchanged, and that presently after the delivery and exchange of the Ratification, this Peace and <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg> shall be published in such manner, and in such places as is usual, and from thence forwards all hostility on both sides shall cease.</i></p>

<head level="3">The Contents of the Commission.</head>

<p>For the assurance and witness of all this, we the Commissioners of his Highness the Lord Protector, and the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> of the States General of the United Provinces, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> and force of the respective procurations of Our Commissions, have subscribed this present Treaty with our own Hands, and have confirmed it with our Seals. <i>Done in Westminster the 5 day of April, 1654.</i></p>

<!--table in 3 columns each name with a centred capital O beneath it-->

<!--column 1-->
<p><i>H. Laurence, <unclear>Pr&aelig;f.</unclear></i></p>
<p><i>J. Lambert</i></p>
<p><i>F. <unclear>Montague</unclear>,</i></p>

<!--column 2-->
<p><i>P. Lisle,</i></p>
<p><i>Gilb. Pickering,</i></p>
<p><i>W. Stricklandt,</i></p>

<!--column 3-->
<p><i>H. Beverningh,</i></p>
<p><i>Wil. Nieuport,</i></p>
<p><i>Alb. P. Yongestal.</i></p>

<pb n="4" />

<p>From <em>Ireland</em> they write, That the Lord Deputy <em>Fleetwood</em>, and his <reg orig="councel">council</reg> of Officers, have ordered that 5000 horse and foot be sent to the North of <em>Scotland</em>, and col. <em>Venables</em> is taking care to transport 'em, <i>good shipping attend them</i>. The General <reg orig="councel">council</reg> hath cast Lots for the Provinces, for satisfying the Arrears of the <reg orig="Souldiery">Soldiery</reg>, and the Lot of the General Officers is fallen in <em>Munster</em>. The standing Army from <em>June</em> 1649. are content to take two Thirds at present. The Officers of the Army have <reg orig="joyntly">jointly</reg> subscribed a Letter to his Highness, owning the Government which is invested in Him.</p>

<head level="2">Charles Fleetwood,</head>
<p><i>Anagram</i></p>
<head level="2"><reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> he calls Food:</head>
<p><i>Epigram,</i></p>
<p><reg orig="Vertue">Virtue</reg> He calls his Food; and justly may</p>
<p>For 'tis his chief delight, both night and day.</p>

<hr />

<head level="2">Bridget Fleetwood,</head>
<p><i>Anagram,</i></p>
<head level="2">Be ere dutiful to God:</head>
<p>Be ever dutiful to GOD: for He.</p>
<p>A Crown of Glory hath prepared for thee.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and her Highness Protectress, are gone to <em>Hampton Court</em>. The Yeomen of his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> Guard wait by turns Monthly, and Mr. <em>Ingoldsby</em> (brother to col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>) is made captain of the Guard. Their coats are grey cloth with black Velvet <reg orig="collers">collars</reg>, and black Velvet and silver lace and trimming, col. <em>Nathaniel Fiennes</em> is added a member to the council.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador makes many applications to his Highness, by way of negotiating a peace between <em>England</em> and his Majesty (who is now of years to be crowned very suddenly) if he propound <reg orig="tearms">terms</reg> safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>, he need not doubt of his Errand, <i>For it is a sign of godliness to be at peace with all men; yet peace cannot <reg orig="tryumph">triumph</reg>, except Reason ruleth.</i></p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has spent much time with his Council, about regulating the Law, the easing of the people, the redressing of Grievances, and the abating of Taxes, and it is hoped, we shall now have the enjoyment or our long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for Liberties.</p>

<p>The next Term is like to be kept without any interruption, and a new Oath was lately administered to the Judges, whereby impartial Justice may be equally executed.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> it is certified, That there has been a great dispute between the K. of <em>Scots</em>, and P. <em>Rupert</em>, about the <em>Swallow</em> Guns; but <reg orig="wisdome">wisdom</reg> over-swaying passion, Amity at last <reg orig="interveen'd">intervened</reg>, and the Gentlemen were both reconciled. It is said that the Queen of <em>Sweden</em> hath resigned her Crown, and is expected this Summer at the <unclear><em>Sparo</em></unclear>, where young <em>Charles</em>, and his brother <em>James</em>, to intend to meet her Majesty, and divert themselves at the Season.</p>

<p><em>Dover</em> the 24 of <em>April</em>, 1654. This evening came into this Road a private man of War being a <em>Marget</em> Hoy of 6 Guns, and about 50 men, who having found in the channel a Dutch ship coming from the West-Indies that had been long at Sea, and both ship and men much spent by the tediousness of the Voyage, did of a sudden clap Them aboard, and after a short (but sharp) dispute, became Masters of her, and brought her along with them: The ship is said to be of great value, for besides plate, whereof several Letters say there is a good quantity, the ship will be found full of other rich commodities, which will prove very beneficial to the Takers, when it comes to be judged a prize.</p>

<p>From <em><reg orig="Hamborough">Hamburg</reg></em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That the King of Denmark has been to visit the new Church of <em>Altenaw</em>, &amp; the next day went back to <unclear><em>Gluckstadt</em></unclear>; upon whose <reg orig="arival">arrival</reg> came intelligence of Gen. <unclear><em>Koningsmarks</em></unclear> <reg orig="surprizing">surprising</reg> of the Town of <em>Bremerburgh</em>. Upon the Queen of <em><reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg></em> Demands to the Emperor of <em>Germany</em> for 1350000 Rix-dollars being so much left unpaid by the upper Rhine, it was granted.</p>

<p>Gen. <em>Pen</em> is going from <em>London</em> to the Fleet; the design <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg>; but the Instructions private. Of which more in our next.</p>

<p>In the interim, some of the English <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> have <reg orig="allarm'd">alarmed</reg> the French, and rides <reg orig="tryumphantly">triumphantly</reg> upon that coast; but two Reg. are sent to Rochel to reinforce that <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>: from whence they write, <i>That the English have taken 42 of their ships laden with Wines, which doth very much trouble the King and Council; unto whom, a <em>Message</em> is come from his <pb n="6" />Holiness, for celebrating a <em>Marriage</em> between his <reg orig="Neece">Niece</reg>, and K. Lewis: If you will have any more news at present, you must go to Pope <em>Innocent</em> the Tenth, who is now going to his grave; his death will make the <em>Janseninas</em> high in France, and will occasion some Tumults, it may be.</i></p>

<p>The K. of <em>France</em> is preparing large Offers to the <em>English</em> for peace; and among other things, <i>that the Protestants in that Kingdom shall enjoy their Liberties and freedom in <em>Religion</em>.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, That Gen. Middleton having drawn most of his forces Northwards, some engagement happened, and a party of 40 horse commanded by an English Captain, advanced as far as Provost <em><reg orig="Marburnies">Marburnie's</reg></em> house near <reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg>, which they <reg orig="fir'd">fired</reg>; but the Provost and his party maintained the Tower against them, and after a desperate storm, and sharp dispute, two of the English were slain, divers wounded, and the castle being not feasible, the enemy made good their retreat, with little loss. col. <em>Morgan</em> <reg orig="remaines">remains</reg> still about <em>Dingwel</em>, unto whose assistance col. <em>Pride</em>, col. <em>Allnred</em>, and divers other Regiments are designed from <em>England</em> and <em>Ireland</em>. Upon Gen. <em>Monk's</em> arrival, he sent for all his Officers at <em>London</em> to make all possible speed to their Charge, being resolved to proceed with all expedition, and to engage suddenly. And the enemy are preparing to receive him, who have determinated in Council, to dispute the field either to Death or Victory. In the late Engagement capt. <em>Rogers</em> (Agent for the K. of <em>Scots</em>) was taken, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to <em>Dalkieth</em>, where he was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg>, condemned, and executed, and received his Sentence of Death with great humility and meekness of Spirit, making a copious Speech upon the Ladder, interwoven with sundry <reg orig="methodicall">methodical</reg> expressions, touching his life and conversation, and his integrity to the Trust reposed in him, saying, <i>That he deemed it a singular mercy from the great Tribunal of <reg orig="Haven">Heaven</reg>, that Providence had decreed him worthy of laying down his life.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Southampton</em> thus: Sir,<i> Mr. John Lilburn (we hear) is committed to the old Castle in Jersey, where he deports himself with abundance of patience and humility, and has also declared, That he <reg orig="aymes">aims</reg> at nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> the glory of God; the advancement of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the restoring of every free born man of England, to its ancient Rights and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg>, and the perfect purging of the Law from all abuses and corruptions</i></p>

<p>He sent a Letter to his very much afflicted wife; bur it was intercepted, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to his Highness.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>The Ambassador from the King of <em>Denmark</em> has presented his Letters credential from the King his Master, and on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> last he has audience before his Highness, where he congratulated him in his place of Government, and seemed to acknowledge it a <reg orig="happines">happiness</reg> that so much of the differences were taken up by the Treaty with the Dutch, and hoped all would conduce to a happy peace, to the advancement of the Protestant Religion, and stopping the effusion of innocent <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg>. This appears very fair; but he had something more of State Affairs, which he imparted in writing unto his Highness, and will afterwards be taken into consideration.</p>

<p>There is to be a general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Downs by the <em>English</em> fleet very suddenly; and Rear-Admiral <em>Lawson</em> is already gone towards the Northern parts with 20 men of war; the <em>Fairfax</em> is Admiral; and 'tis said he hath landed 6 or 7000 men near the Isles of <em>Orkney</em>, who intend to make up suddenly towards Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, who has sent the Lord <em>Glengary</em> into the West with 500 resolute men of fortune to raise the people <reg orig="ingeneral">in general</reg>.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> is marched to <em>Tain</em>, where he saw the enemy, but could not come at them for want of Boats, the water being broad and very impetuous, which <reg orig="constrain'd">constrained</reg> him to return back to <em>Dingwel</em>.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A <em>Letter</em> from <em>Sweden</em></i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p><i>I sent unto you about a fortnight since; but having very little news in that letter, I was <reg orig="resolv'd">resolved</reg> to make you amends in this, (though in a few words) by acquainting you that our Treat with the Queen is concluded, and the Articles of Agreement are signed, which are, 1 That from henceforward there shall be a firm and perpetual peace. 2 That they shall assist each other against any enemy whatsoever. 3 That there shall be free Trade and Commerce. The rest are very honourable on both sides. And my Lord intends for England suddenly.</i></p>

<p>Upsal, April 8. 1654.</p>

<p><i>The last letters from Holland say, That the Royal party give out, that there hath been a great fight in Scotland, and that Gen. Middleton hath obtained a great Victory, and killed col. Morgan; yes, <em>in skies</em>: but I conceive this to be <reg orig="coyn'd">coined</reg> with a false stamp; so that probably we may <!--chance????-->chouce them in time for their fictitious and <reg orig="vain-glorious">vainglorious</reg> Reports.</i></p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers Printed by Authority, and <reg orig="Entred">Entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>