<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost170">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 170</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The advancing of the King of <em><reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg></em> Forces towards the Borders, under the conduct and command of <em><reg orig="Generall">General</reg> Middleton, Gen. Glengarn, Lieu. Gen. Kenmore, Major General</em> Monroe, and a List of the Lords, Knights, and Colonels, together with the number both of Horse and Foot, Blunderbusses and Bow-men; and the raising of all from 16 to 60 in <em>Southerland, Caithness, Ross</em>, and other places. The seizing and taking of the Dutch Papers going to Dover, and a Transcript of the Contents thereof. The <reg orig="randevouzing">rendezvousing</reg> of one hundred men of war upon the Western Channel, and some English ships taken. The <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Reception of the Lord <em>Ambassador</em> from the King of France yesterday, and hid receiving <em>Audience</em> this present <em>Tuesday</em>.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 21. to <em>Tuesday</em> March 28. 1654</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i>.</p>
<hr />

<p>The Dutch Letters going from <em>Southwark</em> towards <em>Dover</em>, on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> morning last about 3 of the clock, was seized and broke open by 5 Hectorian Knights of Fortune within a mile of St. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> Church; but finging no <reg orig="moneyes">moneys</reg> in the <reg orig="Male">Mail</reg>, broke open the Letters, cast them upon the ground, and turned the Messenger back again. Some of these Letters made mention of a final Agreement between the two Republics of England and Holland. And Monsieur <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg> Neusuille</em>, Ambassador from the King of France was brought in state through the City on the 27 instant, to Sir Abraham Williams in the Palace-yard: He is to receive audience on the 28 instant. We have lately taken two prizes laden <pb n="1" />with Wines and Sugars, and another of the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> men of war is taken. The English fleet, consisting of 100 men of war, are still upon the Western Channel, col. <em>Ingoldsby's</em> Reg. and divers others are <reg orig="shipt">shipped</reg>, and we hear that several Squadrons seem to promise a Relief for Christians from Turkish slavery. From <reg orig="Edenborough">Edinburgh</reg> it is advertised, that since the landing of Gen. <em>Middleton</em> the Royal party are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in all parts, and give out that the L. <em>Vilmot</em> is to come with a great supply from the Emperor: No less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 160000 Dollars prepared by his Imperial Majesty, as they say, for the raising 30 Reg. of horse and foot, to be commanded by the D. of <em>York</em> Col: <em>Hinderson</em> is very active for his <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, and the E. of <em>Athol</em>, and Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> have placed a Garrison in the Isle of <em>Tay</em>, where they intend to have a stock of provisions, and also to keep such Commissioners and Heritors as refuse to bring in their Levies at 40 marks Scots for an horse, and 100 l. Scots for a <reg orig="foot-man">footman</reg>: they threaten fire and sword to all that <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> oppose, and have lately seized some of the English by their Ambuscadoes; but, as a retaliation to part of our loss, we have taken a Cornet, 4 Redshanks, and 11 horse; <i>A great purchase, they are scarce worth their skins</i>. From <em>France</em> they write that his Royal Majesty hath sent a Commission and Instructions to the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg></em>, to conclude a Peace with the Lord Protector <em><reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>; which is effected, there must be permission in <em>France</em> for preaching of the Protestant Religion. From whence we likewise hear that there is a Marriage concluded between the K. of Scots and the D. of <em><reg orig="Lorains">Lorain's</reg></em> daughter, and that he is to have more millions of money. <i>Alas <unclear>alas</unclear>! the truth I question</i>: Yet thus much we are <unclear><reg orig="ascertain'd">ascertained</reg> that monies</unclear> is preparing amongst the Princes of <i>Germany, <unclear>I wish that chancery may</unclear> extend <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> to all Objects of misery</i>. King <em>Lewis</em> has <reg orig="past">passed</reg> Sentence of death against the Pr. of <em>Conde</em>, <i>A most excellent Engine, to cut off a <reg orig="Gentlemans">Gentleman's</reg> head with words</i>. The Count of <unclear><em>Aubijova</em></unclear>, and the Baron of <em>Brisac</em> are both hanged at the Palace Royal in picture. Prince <unclear><em>Rupert</em></unclear> escaped narrowly, for pistolling of one of his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Monsieurs.</p>

<p>The great Fleet of Colliers from Newcastle are now come safe into the River of Thames; and the price is already ordered by many, to sell them for eight pence a bushel: in pursuance whereof Proclamation hath been made at Westminster, and the said price is stated &amp; <pb n="2" />put in execution. Twelve of this fleet were stranded by the Hollander, who have taken a Vessel belonging to Yarmouth laden with Wine, coming from <reg orig="Bourdeaux">Bordeaux</reg>; but they purchased her at a <reg orig="deer">dear</reg> rate; for having taken excess of the <reg orig="juyce">juice</reg> of Grapes, they steered <reg orig="head-long">headlong</reg> among the Rocks at Hartlepool, where they all received <reg orig="ship-wrack">shipwreck</reg>, and the Vessel was torn in pieces.</p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuation of an Act, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, An Act for Laying an imposition upon <reg orig="Coles">Coals</reg>, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas.</i></head>

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament, <reg orig="intituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for laying an imposition upon <reg orig="Coles">Coals</reg>, towards the building and maintaining ships for guarding the Seas</i>; And all power and clauses therein contained be and are hereby continued, and shall and do stand in full force, until the 26 day of <em>March</em>, 1655.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for continuing an Act for impressing of Sea men.</i></head>

<p>Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That one Act of Parliament <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg> <i>An Act for impressing of <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg></i>, And all powers and clauses therein <reg orig="conteined">contained</reg>, be, and are hereby revived, and <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> continue and stand in full force, until the first day of <em>Novemb.</em> 1654.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>An Ordinance for passing Custodies of <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg> and Idiots.</i></head>

<p>Whereas by an Act of late Parl. on the behalf of Idiots and <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg>, it was, among other things, enacted, That the <reg orig="Bils">Bills</reg> for passing of the Custodies of the said Idiots &amp; <reg orig="Lunaticks">Lunatics</reg> should be signed by the Council of State before the Commissioners of the great Seal of <em>England</em>, should pass the same under <pb n="3" />the said Seals; And whereas that <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> is since dissolved, Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That the Chancellor, Keeper, or Commissioners of the great Seal for the time being, do not pass the said Subsider under the Great Seal, before the same be signed by his Highness the Lord Protector, and that the same, so signed by his Highness, shall be a sufficient Warrant for passing the same under the said Great Seal, any Law, Statute, Act, Ordinance, or <reg orig="Custome">Custom</reg> to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>

<p>HEN. SCOBEL, <i>Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>By a Letter from <em>Harwich</em> it is <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, that there is a Dutch ship of 400 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with Pitch, Tar, Masts, and Iron, to a great value brought in thither, taken by a private man of War.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March the 21.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Protector set forth a Declaration, inviting the People of <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, to a solemn day of fasting and humiliation, and ordered that <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> the 24 instant be set apart for the cities of London and Westminster; and the same day fortnight for all the Counties in general in England and Wales. The Causes are first the common notorious sins impenitently practised amongst us. Secondly, the present long drought, threatening famine and mortality. The sins taken notice of by his Highness are, Notwithstanding the just Liberty Spiritual and Civil, God hath procured by his own people, yet want of humble walking in the <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg> of Christ, or to communicate that liberty one to another. Or thankfully to acknowledge our liberty of worshipping God in holiness, want of brotherly love. Not owning one another for the grace of God more <reg orig="then">than</reg> form: Not seeking the Kingdom of Christ within us, before one without us. <reg orig="Listning">Listening</reg> to false Christs: Temporal for Saints. A crying up of the Spirit; with a neglect of Love, and the other fruits of the Spirit: And an evil carriage towards them without: crying down Ministers that have a large seal of their Ministry, want of old Puritan self <reg orig="deniall">denial</reg>; Mercy to the poor, uprightness, justice, and contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints, as it ought to be <reg orig="apostatizings">apostatisings</reg> of many running after notions and fancies against Magistracy, <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>, Scriptures and Ordinances, contempt of the Gospels, and sincere Professors <pb n="4" />of it, even for the Image of Christ in them. Oaths, Drunkenness, Revellings, and all manner of licentiousness. And the impunity of these things, through neglect of the Magistracy in several parts of the Nation.</p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> we have received intelligence, That there are Articles of High-Treason exhibited against the famous <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> capt. <em>Beach</em>; who disputed the <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> of the Seas in the Royal James with great Resolution: insomuch, that coming aboard the Warwick, he demanded of valiant cap. <em>Potter</em> the manner of performing his Articles, and said it was his promise to see him ashore in <em>France</em>; whereupon cap. <em>Potter</em> answered, That he never heard of any such Demand; but to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> him, proffered cap, <em>Beach</em> to go aboard his own ship again, and fight it out; but the captain refused it.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Shall <em>Potter</em> in a fight not fear to <reg orig="dy">die</reg>,</line>
<line>And I not offer to his Victory</line>
<line>One Distick? sure my duty to it leads,</line>
<line>Poets are Trumpets of <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Deeds,</line>
<line>Then found a Charge, my <em>Muse</em>, and change some shot,</line>
<line>Frighten the Ocean, make the Welkin hot,</line>
<line><reg orig="Parboyl">Parboil</reg> the Fish, pickle in blood and dust</line>
<line>The braver <reg orig="soules">soul1s</reg>, who <reg orig="ne'r">ne'er</reg> with <reg orig="slothfull">slothful</reg> Rust</line>
<line>Would be <reg orig="consum'd">consumed</reg>. Hark! how Sea-Welkin roars</line>
<line>As if they had the Hichop <reg orig="o're">o'er</reg> and <reg orig="o're">o'er</reg>,</line>
<line>Ordinance and Flames Thunder, Lightning seem,</line>
<line>The Sea a Kettle <reg orig="boyling">boiling</reg>, by its <reg orig="steem">steam</reg></line>
<line>Appears, and <em>Thetis</em> hath the <reg orig="Chollick">Colic</reg> got,</line>
<line>Reverberated by incessant shot.</line>
<line>Death rides <reg orig="tryumphant">triumphant</reg> on a furious Wave,</line>
<line>Which seems to threaten to each ship a Grave.</line>
<line>Now <em>Beach</em> hath Flood-gates ope into his <reg orig="Hould">Hold</reg>,</line>
<line>'Tis madness now, not valour to be bold;</line>
<line>He craveth quarter, comes on board and then</line>
<line>Demandeth freedom for himself and men.</line>
<line>I gave them such Articles <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he,</line>
<line>That proffered to fight it instantly,</line>
<line>And repossess him of his ship: alas!</line>
<line>He would no tempt destruction by the Brass</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Thy worth let <reg orig="Canons">Cannons</reg> with their wide mouth <reg orig="rore">roar</reg>,</line>
<line>While Earth has water, or the Main hath shore.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From <em><reg orig="Vpsal">Upsal</reg></em> in <em>Sweden</em> thus: The Treaty goes on but slowly; yet doubtless, if the Transactions between <em>England</em> and <em>Holland</em> take effect, they will soon be <reg orig="quickned">quickened</reg> in new Councils; for her Maj. promiseth fair to the L. <em>Whitlock</em>; and hath revived her former Overtures of resigning up the Government to her Successor, and desires the liberty of retiring into privacy. The great Taxes upon the people is conceived <reg orig="wil">will</reg> push them forward to some notable design, which causeth the Senators to sit very close in <reg orig="councel">council</reg>. They are consulting, what Answer to return to her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Proposals, for resigning up the Crown and <reg orig="Scepter">Sceptre</reg>, to her Successor, or Lord Protector.</p>

<head level="3"><i>March the 20.</i></head>

<p>Sith this day, or yester-night (and the evening and the morning were the first day) one <em>Foulcher</em> was <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> to the <reg orig="Gate-house">Gatehouse</reg> in Westminster, upon suspicion of <reg orig="coyning">coining</reg> half crowns of no true allay; and of a truth, <em>Aulicus</em> in this is a <em>Politicus</em>; for he would have such persons (who usually use Oaths, as bracelets to their Speech) to be stringed like Beads, if found guilty of such and <reg orig="inormous">enormous</reg> Crime.</p>

<poem basefont="roman">
<stanza>
<line>Wl y tempt thus the Fates, ye Sons of wrong?</line>
<line>Ye have but half-crowns sure, that use this long,</line>
<line>Or once at all, why <reg orig="deifie">deify</reg> ye Dross?</line>
<line>The <em>Harp</em> ye find doth play you to the <em>Cross</em>.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<p>One thing I cannot omit, that Tuesday last the English Commissioners, and the Dutch Ambassadors, after another audience before his Highness, had a large conference, and sundry papers were read by Mr. <em><reg orig="Iesop">Jesop</reg></em> Clerk to the Council and the Transactions of the Treaty debated by Mr. <em>Thurloe</em> Sec of State; upon the Result whereof, the Articles were even made ready to finish, and the <reg orig="Accompts">Accounts</reg> of <em>Denmark</em> took up much time.</p>

<head level="3"><em>March</em> the 24.</head>

<p>No news but that upon a <reg orig="meer">mere</reg> invitation the City should so solemnly observe a Day of fasting and humiliation, and it is wished that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> this day fortnight may keep it no worse: for we have great cause to bury our <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> in the dust for our notorious sins so boldly and impertinently practised among us, and to consider the Rod of God upon us, in an universal Drought for some years, and still continued, <reg orig="threatning">threatening</reg> <reg orig="famin">famine</reg>, and mortality: for, true it is, that in the North of England, and several other parts of this Nation, the Springs River, and <reg orig="Brookes">Brooks</reg>, are almost dry for 20 miles distant. O then consider!</p>

<poem basefont="italic">
<stanza>
<line>To Fasting why should sensual flesh be <reg orig="loth">loath</reg>?</line>
<line>Fasting is good for soul and body both.</line>
</stanza>
</poem>

<pb n="6" />

<p>From Dublin thus: The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, when he comes back to you <reg orig="wil">will</reg> confute those false Reports that were raised of us here, he having had a reception as a Prince, with 300 horse out of the City (most of them Citizens) with <reg orig="bone-fires">bonfires</reg> at night throughout the City.</p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, have passed an Ordinance appointing Commissioners for approbation of <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Preachers; and for prevention of all scandalous and popish intruders, it is ordained, That every person who <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from and after the 25 of March instant be presented, nominated, chosen, or appointed to any Benefice (formerly called Benefice with Care of Souls) or to preach any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> Lecture in England or Wales, shall, before he be admitted into any such Benefice or Lecture, be adjudged and approved by the persons hereafter named to be a person for the grace of God in him, his holy and <reg orig="unblamable">unblameable</reg> Conversation as also for his knowledge and utterance, able and fit to preach the Gospel and that after the said 25 of <em>March</em> no person but such as <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> upon such approbation be admitted, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> take any <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Lecture or Benefice as aforesaid &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Names of the Commissioners.</i></head>

<!--table in 3 columns, separated by vertical lines-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Francis Rous Esq;</p>
<p>Dr. Tho. Goodwin,</p>
<p>Dr. John Owen</p>
<p>M. Thankful Owen,</p>
<p>Dr. Arrowsmith,</p>
<p>Dr. Tuckney,</p>
<p>Dr. Horton,</p>
<p>M. <reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg> Caryl</p>
<p>M. Philip Ny,</p>
<p>M. William Carter,</p>
<p>M. Sidrach Simpson</p>
<p>M. William Greenhill</p>
<p>M. William Strong</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>M. Thomas Manton,</p>
<p>M. Samuel Slater,</p>
<p>M. Cooper</p>
<p>M. Marshal,</p>
<p>M. Tombes</p>
<p>M. Cradock,</p>
<p>M. Faircloth,</p>
<p>M. Hugh Peters,</p>
<p>M. <unclear>Sherrey</unclear></p>
<p>M. <unclear>Bamford</unclear></p>
<p>M. Valentine</p>
<p>M. <unclear>Jaffee</unclear></p>
<p>M. Obidiah Sedgwick,</p>

<!--column 3-->
<p>M. Nic. Lockier</p>
<p>M. Dyke, M. Russel</p>
<p>M. Campfield</p>
<p>Rob. <unclear>Tichborn</unclear> Alderman of London</p>
<p>Mark Hildesley,</p>
<p>Thomas Wood</p>
<p>John Sadler</p>
<p>Wil. Goff</p>
<p>Tho. St. Nicholas</p>
<p>Wil. Packer</p>
<p>And Edw. Cresset Esquires.</p>

<p>These, or any five of them, are appointed commissioners for such approbation and admission as is above said, and upon death or removal of any of them, others <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> from time to time be nominated in their places by the Lord Protector and his Successors, by advice of his Council in the service of Parliaments; and sitting the Parliament, by the Protector and Parliament. And the said Commissioners, or any five or more of them, met together in some certain place of the city of <em>London</em> or <em>Westminster</em>, as his Highness shall appoint, are hereby <reg orig="authorized">authorised</reg> to judge take knowledge of the ability and fitness of any person so presented, chosen, or appointed, according to the <unclear>qualification</unclear> <pb n="7" />above mentioned; and upon their approbation of such his ability and fitness, to grant unto such person admission to such Benefice or Lecture by an Instrument in Writing, under a common Seal to be appointed by his Highness, and under the hand of the Register or Registers for the time being, and to be also nominated by the Lord Protector and his Successors; which Instrument the said Register or Registers <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> cause to be entered in a book for that purpose, and kept upon Record.</p>

<p>On <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, being the 27 of this instant <em>March</em>, there came a <em>Post</em> from Scotland, intimating, That the Royal party increaseth, and that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise <em>Southerland, Caithness</em>, and the county of <em>Ross</em>, and so to drain the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, even as a <reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> sucketh in Water, of all the able, stout, and resolute hearts, that are able to bear Arms from sixteen to sixty; with a Resolution to descend down into the Lowlands: for, indeed, they grow numerous, and swell up as a Snow-Ball doth in its rolling; but may as soon dissolve again in the like Element. The Lord <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to seven hundred, the Earl of <em>Athol</em> five hundred, Col. <em>Forbs</em> five hundred, and the last general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> seven thousand horse and foot they spake themselves to be <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> armed, but have not obtained as yet the silver Instrument, which is the life of the Cause, and the very sinew of War: but their expectation is great from <em>Germany</em>, and for ought I know, long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for mat come at last: in the interim they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march. And the Names of the chief Commanders are as followeth, <em>viz.</em></p>

<!--table in 2 columns divided by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, commander in</p>
<p>chief.</p>
<p><em>Saundy Glencarn</em>, General of the</p>
<p>Horse.</p>
<p>The Earl of <em>Athol</em> General of</p>
<p>the Foot</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Kenmore</em> Lieutenant</p>
<p>General</p>
<p>Sir <em>George Monroe</em>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg></p>
<p>Major</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em>, <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> of the</p>
<p>Ordinance</p>
<p>Col. <em>Hinderson</em>, commander in chief</p>
<p>of the Bow-men.</p>
<p>Col. Dyler, commander in chief of</p>
<p>the Bow-men</p>
<p>Col <em>Sinclare</em>, Engineer.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Cranford</em>.</p>
<p>Col. <em>Hume</em>,</p>
<p>And divers other eminent Officers.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i><unclear>Extracted out of the Original Papers published</unclear> by Authority</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>