<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost$127">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 127</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST</head>
<head level="3">Truly Representing</head>

<p><i>The <em>Bloody Vision</em>, presented to his Highness the Lord Protector by prophet <em>Evans</em>; and his Proclamation at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> Gate, concerning the King of Scots, and the present Government with the Declaration and <reg orig="Prophesie">Prophecy</reg> of a Virgin, touching his Highness, and the <reg orig="fift">fifth</reg> Monarchy; with her Message to the Council; and the manner how she was struck in a trance at Mr. <em><reg orig="Roberts">Robert's</reg></em> house, <unclear>near</unclear> the late <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <reg orig="Kitchin">Kitchen</reg>, and her speech to the people at her awaking. The Proclamation of the States of Holland, and the publishing of another in Scotland. A Message from the King of France, and a List of the Names of the Lords, Colonel, and Gentlemen, that are to lead and conduct the Netherland, forces with sundry other Intelligence from the States of the United Provinces, and the proceedings of the Navy at Sea.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> Jan. 10. to <em>Tuesday</em> Jan. 17. 1653</head>
<hr />

<head level="3">LONDON, Printed for GEO. HORTON, 1653.</head>

<p>The States if Holland sit very close upon the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> and weighty Affairs and very much are they importuned to condescend to a <reg orig="peice">peace</reg> with England; for the wants of the Poor are abundant, and the <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> that their Merchants have <unclear>sustained</unclear> great. Besides, all sorts of Provisions are excessive <unclear>dear</unclear>, and most of their Banks &amp; <reg orig="Store-houses">Storehouses</reg> very empty and naked: yet notwithstanding, they go on with their preparations for War; but few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> <reg orig="wil">will</reg> make a discovery of the event of this great Transaction.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3">Tuesday Jan. 10.</head>

<p>Produced Letters from Amsterdam, intimating, that their Fast-India fleet, consisting of 150 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, is much feared to be cast away; such almighty <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> hath not happened these hundred years; besides, many houses are burnt, &amp; the great iron cross, with the Weathercock, and <reg orig="guilded">gilded</reg> Bowl under it, which was said to hold a Hogshead of Beer, was all blown down, and falling upon the Graves, tore the dead bodies. At which time, began the great fire, at the Hemp Mill, which consumed all St. <reg orig="Jacobs">Jacob's</reg> Street, the <reg orig="Anabaptists">Anabaptist's</reg> Congregation house, with the Church house, &amp; Townhouse. So that the fire running with over-<reg orig="violency">violence</reg>, flew over to the Bremster-Dike, and burnt the Bridge.</p>

<p>But the greatest loss I hear of was at <em>Rype</em> in North Holland, where an <reg orig="Oyl">Oil</reg>-Mill by the storm, in a violent motion by <reg orig="its">it's</reg> own heat, took fire, and burning furiously, destroyed above five hundred houses, and many men, women, and children, were burnt alive, and <reg orig="mony">money</reg> goods, valued to be worth forty hundred thousand pounds. Great was the lamentation and <reg orig="cryes">cries</reg> of children to their Parents, and husbands to their wives, but could not be helped: many a <reg orig="mothers">mother's</reg> bowels pressing her into the smoke and flame to save her child, lost her life, and her <reg orig="childs">child's</reg> also. So the destruction of the Town was in a moment, but the Lord divert and stay his heavy hand of judgement.</p>

<p>By an Express from the Navy, thus: The fleet is still in the channel, and General Pen with them; but Gen: Blake, Gen: Monk, and Gen: Desborough are returned to Whitehall.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors are now gone over to Holland <unclear>and 'tis</unclear> said, there is a Peace concluded: into the truth whereof <unclear>I shall</unclear> make a diligent inquiry by my next.</p>

<p>The French Ambassador, newly come <unclear>over</unclear> from <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> <unclear>after the</unclear> King, had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, <unclear>whom he</unclear> congratulated in his new Government.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador Whitlock is said to arrive at Upal, four miles from Stockholm the 24 Decemb. Where he is to have audience from the Queen.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>By an Express from Scotland, thus: The Highlanders have had a great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> upon the Hough, from whence they marched North with a Body of horse and loot, intending to meet the Lord Seafort who has made lamentable <reg orig="spoyl">spoil</reg> upon the English horse which they stole out of <reg orig="Gentlemens">Gentlemen's</reg> stables. And the Earl of Kinoul lately appearing <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Glans with a party of horse, had a Design to <reg orig="surprize">surprise</reg> the horse belonging to the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, as they came from watering, lying in ambuscado for that purpose, thinking thereby to increase hid number, and to procure exchange for his men taken at Eghil; and coming at first with a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> party riding into Glans, took three of our men, which Major Ducket, who commanded Col: <reg orig="Riches">Riche's</reg> Troop there, having notice of it, sent out his Quartermaster with twenty horse to discover his party, who advancing with two files of <reg orig="musquetiers">musketeers</reg> that were to make good a bridge, gave them a charge, and routed and dispersed their whole Body, took the Lord Kinoul, and fourteen men, all wounded, and divers horse; pursued the rest even to the very Bogs: but Major Ramsey escaped. We had one man killed, and three wounded; but the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> loss were far greater.</p>

<p>This day sevennight the Ministers and six of the Elders of the French Church, and a Marquis of France, were with hid Highness the Lord Protector, to congratulate, declaring their <reg orig="sence">sense</reg> of engagement to bless God for Him, and their hope of protection to themselves, and the rest of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> people from him; to which; his Highness returned them a very satisfying Answer: So that there is like to be that <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> with the Protestant Churches of <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> parts, which yet hath not been, which will be a great blow to Antichrist, and the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> means to exalt the Throne of the Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Amsterdam</em> it is certified, That the Dutch Deputies are arrived, and have made their <em>Reports</em> concerning the <em>Treaty</em>, which the people generally desire, and comment upon, to be for <em>Peace</em>.</p>

<p>The last intelligence from the King of Scots <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, that at the Palace Royal in Paris He hath feasted the French King; with some Lords &amp; Ladies, and was accompanied by his two brothers the Dukes of York and Gloucester. Prince Rupert was likewise there; but his brother Prince Maurice is said to be drowned. We have advice from Pomerania that by the town of Prit over against Holdin there hath been a sight in the <reg orig="Skie">Sky</reg>, of a Coffin with a black Cross, and there hath also appeared a Dutch Lord overcomed by another Nation: after which was seen a fair Rainbow, and afterward the last <reg orig="Dooms-day">Doomsday</reg>, at which sight many have been much astonished, and exceedingly affrighted.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>By Letters from Lime it is certified, That one of our <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> having met with a Dutch Man of War, gave him chase, and followed so close, that he forced him to run on ground on the hither side of the Bay of Camaret, and by reason of his shooting hard at him made the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> to come down to the water side; but it so happened, that some shot made execution on the shore, and killed and wounded five or six; yet by reason of the night approaching, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> being all <reg orig="allarumed">alarmed</reg> thereby, could not fetch her off; but ours put to sea again, to clear from the Rocks before it was dark.</p>

<head level="2">A Proclamation:</head>

<p>By <em>William</em> Earl of <em>Glencairn</em>, Lord <em>Kilmore</em>, Commander in chief of all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> forces within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em>.</p>

<p>By <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of a Commission from his Majesty granted to me for levying of forces within the Kingdom of Scotland, for opposing the common enemy, I do by these Presents ordain Col: <em>Alexander Blacader</em> to levy out of the Presbytery of <em><reg orig="Dumfermling">Dumfermlin</reg></em> a sufficient Troop of Horse, with one well armed man out of every thousand <em>li.</em> of Rent, with Fortifications. If they fail after the sight of this my <em>Order</em>, the said Col. <em>Alexander Blacader</em>, or any having his power, is to <reg orig="seiz">seize</reg> on the Person of the Deficients, and carry them prisoners to the Army, drive the goods away <reg orig="untill">until</reg> they do duty; and likewise they shall be esteemed enemies to their</p>

<head level="2">KING</head>

<head level="3">AND</head>

<head level="2"><reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> </head>

<pb n="4" />

<p>By an Express from the Hague it is certified, that there is a Design to new model the Dutch Army; and the Commanders in chief are said to be these, <em>viz.</em></p>

<p>The Lord <em>Brederode</em>, Col. <em>Van Galen</em>,</p>

<p>Count <em>Will</em> of <em>Nassaw</em>, Col. <em>Forbus</em>,</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Craven</em>, Col. <em>Brown</em>,</p>

<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Massey</em>, Col. <em>James</em>,</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Van de Par</em>, Col. <em>Ogleby</em>,</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Piercy</em>, Col. <em>Priestman</em>,</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Fielding</em>, Col. <em>Long</em>,</p>

<p>Col. <em>Vere</em>, Col. <em>Twisden</em>,</p>

<p>Col. <em>Frogmorton</em>, Col. <em>Andrews</em>,</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em>, Col. <em>Major</em>,</p>

<p>Col. <em>de la Roche</em>, Col. <em>Godfrey</em>,</p>

<p>Col. <em>Middleton</em>, Col. <em>Sinclare</em>.</p>

<!--the above is presented as a table in two columns-->

<p>Which Army is to be sent against the Lorainers, who have made a great incursion upon the Netherlanders; and to that end, Proclamation is made throughout all the United Provinces, for all men to put themselves in a posture of defence against the common enemy. We hear, that the States are very much inclining to a peace with England, which if once ratified, will prove the greatest Blow to the <reg orig="Iesuiticall">Jesuitical</reg> party that ever <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> in Europe.</p>

<p>There is a Virgin Prophetess come to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, who has declared great and wonderful touching this present Government, and <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> that she comes from God, to declare a message to the Council; she has been sundry times in a Trance at M. <em>Roberts</em> his house, where many eminent persons frequented, and upon her awakening, she declared, That the eternal God was her refuge, and that he was leading her through the green Pastures, to his sacred Pavilion. Therefore, be encouraged in the Lord, ye children of the most High, and remember, that the <reg orig="Saints">Saint's</reg> <reg orig="tryals">trials</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> end in <reg orig="tryumph">triumph</reg>, and the Night of Misery will have a most glorious Morning of Victory, for the exiled and banished <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be restored in the fifth Monarchy.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>By an Express from Jersey it is certified, that there hath been a ship cast away upon that Coast, and most of the passengers and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> drowned.</p>

<p>The King of Scots Men of War are still plying about the Isle of Lundy, and often come into the Severn mouth, where some time they sit very unhandsomely upon Our Jackets, and unworthily <reg orig="seiz">seize</reg> our small Vessels.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have likewise received intelligence, that the Highlanders <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> REX upon the Lowlanders, and commits abundant of Outrages; they are very high in their Levies; but not altogether so successful in their Enterprises, though notwithstanding Fame reports them to be above seven thousand horse and foot (in skits) and that they expect additional supplies from beyond the seas. They have drawn forth their whole Army in a Regimental way, which consists of these ensuing Regiments, to wit;</p>

<!--table in 2 columns with a vertical line between them-->

<p>Gen. Glencarn, Col: Forbis,</p>

<p>Lieut. Gen. Lorn, Col: Brown,</p>

<p>Gen. Major Homes, Col: Middleton,</p>

<p>Colonel Macwait, Col: Melvin,</p>

<p>Col: Mac Donel, Col: James,</p>

<p>Col: Hume, Col: Stuart,</p>

<p>Col: Ennis, Col: Straughan,</p>

<p>Col: Lilburn is very active, and useth all <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> possible to prevent and deter them from making inroads upon the English; but by reason of the Winter Season, great is their advantage upon Us; so that additional forces from <pb n="6" />England are preparing; and Sir William <reg orig="Constables">Constable's</reg> Regiment are designed for the North: The Oath and Engagement is to be tendered to every Regiment before they march; and the Names of those that have already subscribed, are Col: Ingoldsby, Col: Goff, Col: Whaley, &amp;c. whose Regiment, with Major General <reg orig="Lamberts">Lambert's</reg>, are designed for Scotland.</p>

<p>There is arrived the Fleet from <em>Dunkirk</em>, consisting of about forty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, whereof a good part are laden with rich goods, as Silks wrought and unwrought, <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>, <reg orig="Thred">Thread</reg>, &amp;c. There id likewise come five ships from the East-Land; as also one from <em>Zant</em>, with <reg orig="Currents">Currants</reg>, but as yet not come up the <em>River</em>.</p>

<p>By our last <em>Post</em> and intelligence from the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, we have received very certain and credible intelligence, That Colonel <em>Charles James</em> having received a Commission from the King of Scots, is <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth into the Deep with the Brest Men of War, who has now struck sail upon the Coast of <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg>, and there set up his flag on the Poop of the Patrick called the Vice-Ambral.</p>

<p>From Her Royal Majesty the Queen of Sweden, our Post further asvertisseth, that the Lord Ambassador Whitlock, with his Retinue was received in a most high and pompous manner by the Magistrates of <reg orig="Gottenburgh">Gothenburg</reg>, who made a speech to his Lordship, by way of congratulation, in reference to his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg> from the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England.</p>

<p>From Amsterdam it is further certified, that there hath <reg orig="hapned">happened</reg> a very sad and lamentable fire, not at <em>Amsterdam</em>, as is said by some, but at a town some 3 miles off the said City: occasioned by tempestuous and stormy weather, a Rase Mill being driven with that force and violence, that they took fire such fury and violence, that the Flames issued forth in such Flakes, that no possible <reg orig="meanes">means</reg> could prevent this sad and dreadful devastation.</p>

<p>The like dreadful Thunder has been at <em>Pembroke</em> in Wales, where not long before the great Lightning, appeared a Blazing Star, to the great admiration of all that beheld it.</p>

<p>What these dreadful <reg orig="Signes">Signs</reg> from Heaven portend, I am not able to make out; but certainly they are <reg orig="Fore-runners">Forerunners</reg> of some wonderful Events-</p>

<p>By an Express from <em>Portsmouth</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Pen</em> rides as Admiral of the English Fleet without St. <reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg> point 3 Leagues from thence, with forty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of gallant ships, ready upon any advice of</p> 

<pb n="7" />

<p>The next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view is, a brief transcript of the Declaration and Confession, which was made at the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> meeting house at Hexham, by <em><reg orig="Ioseph">Joseph</reg> Ben <unclear>Israel</unclear></em>, a <reg orig="Iew">Jew</reg>, to wit; I do here avow thee Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg> my true Saviour, and I rejoice in thy Church and People, thy precious Saints, who do here walk through thy grace, according to thy Rule and holy Commands. I so here solemnly vow thee my Lord and King, thy Saints and Ordinances; and now I heartily desire all the people of God to pray for me, that the residue of my <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> may be spent according to this beginning. O Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, who hath appointed Ordinances, and sufferings for thee who shall reign with thee in glory, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> the desire of my soul is to thee; I do thou therefore convey the grace of Ordinances into my heart that I may live to the honour of thy name, as <reg orig="becommeth">becometh</reg> thy professed servant, waiting for thy second coming. So come Lord <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>, and tarry not. <i>Baruch Adonay <unclear>lengolain</unclear> vanged,</i> Amen ve Amen.</p>

<p>The <em>Bloody Vision</em> interpreted by <em>Arise Evans</em>, was presented to his Highness the Lord Protector by the said Author, who notwithstanding the high invectives therein contained, proving that the late Parliament was the mark of the Beast, mentioned in the Revelations, and that the <reg orig="fift">fifth</reg> Monarchy should suddenly be established under the power of <em>Charles Stuart</em>, &amp;c. yet did the favourable clemency of his Highness extend so far, that he graciously remitted this imperious Representation, and permitted him his liberty. Nevertheless, when he departed, he went to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, and there made Proclamation of what was published by him</p>

<head level="2">Arise Evans:</head>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>