<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost172">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 172</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Message sent from the Dutch Ambassadors to their superior Masters the States of the United Provinces, and one hundred and fifty thousand pounds demanded of the King of Denmark by the English; the Commissioners appointed to sit at Guild Hall within the City of London, and the particulars of the business touching the Demands of his Highness the Lord Protector to the Hollander, concerning the burning of the English with lighted Torches in Amboyna. The new Addresses of the Christian Princes, the seizing of the English ships upon the coast of Naples, a Declaration from Wales, and the proceedings of the Royal party in Scotland.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> April 4. to <em>Tuesday</em> April 11. 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i></p>

<p>The Royal Party in Scotland are very much exasperated, and increase <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg>: they Commanders have <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into an Oath of <reg orig="Secresie">Secrecy</reg>, and say that they expect suddenly that Son of Valour <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> Stuart; they have had several <reg orig="Rendevouzes">Rendezvous</reg>, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> many diversions, insomuch that the English have retaliated their former losses, and taken sundry eminent prisoners; Col. <em>Morgan</em> and Lieu. Col. <em>Michil</em> are upon action.</p>

<p>The Earl of <em>Athol</em> is come to <em>Glencarne</em> with about 500. horse and foot, <em>Seafort</em> and some new raised forces by him, are to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with them. <em>Glencarn</em> being 2000. horse and foot, is at <em>Dingwel</em>, and it is thought we may engage them there.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>His highness the Lord Protector, and his <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> Council, upon mature Debate of redressing the grievances of poor prisoners, resolved, that an Ordinance for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, <reg orig="entituled">entitled</reg>, <i>An Act for the relief for Creditors and poor Prisoners</i>, should be forthwith printed and published. An Ordinance also passed for relief of persons that have acted in the service of the Parliament. There was another Ordinance likewise passed for prohibiting Cock-Matches, the exact Copy take as followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> Meetings and Assemblies of people together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cock-fighting, are by experience found to tend many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publique">public</reg> peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practices, to the dishonour of God, and do often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of persons and their families. For prevention thereof, Be it ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, That from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publike">public</reg> or set meetings or Assemblies of any persons within England or Wales, upon matches made for Cock-fighting; And that every such meeting and assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an unlawful Assembly and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be, and punished; And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, <reg orig="Majors">Mayors</reg>, <reg orig="Bayliffs">Bailiffs</reg>, Constables, and Headboroughs, within their several Counties, Cities, Limits, and Jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such meetings and assemblies.</p>

<p><i>Hen. Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</i></p>

<p>No news from Sea, save that a Dutch man of war, called the <em>John Baptist</em>, bound from St. <em>Malos</em> to <em>Amsterdam</em>, and laden with <reg orig="Indico">Indigo</reg> and Pepper, was taken by the Reserve <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>: the Capt. was a Frenchman, but the service being so <reg orig="extream">extreme</reg> hot, he was at last soundly <reg orig="pepper'd">peppered</reg>, and forced to surrender to cool himself. An Ostend man of war is brought into Plymouth by the Falmouth <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and 3 Dutch prizes <pb n="2" />laden with French Wines, Figs, and Raisins from St. Lucas. Alas! but to these sweet Fruits, we hear of very sharp and <reg orig="sowr">sour</reg> <reg orig="sawce">sauce</reg>: for true it is, that the Brest men of War have taken the <em>Charity</em> of <em>Bristol</em>, and detain the Master for cap. <em>Beach</em>, whom they threaten to mete the same measure unto, as shall be inflicted upon the said <em>Beach</em>. They have also taken two Weymouth Vessels, another of Westchester, and most of the best ships belonging to Bristol. Nay, this is not all; but the Wild-Boar is <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> by a Fleming, a delicate Vessel, and bravely fraught, and valued worth 5000 <em>li.</em> To this sad and <reg orig="dismall">dismal</reg> scene ensues another fatal Act, that is, the <em>Expedition</em> of <em>Plymouth</em> coming from <em>Zant</em>, laden with <em>Currants</em>, was set upon by a <reg orig="Dutch-man">Dutchman</reg> of war, and after a long and sharp dispute both ships were sunk.</p>

<p>This day was presented to his Highness the Lord Protector a <unclear>Declaration</unclear> and Recognition by M. <em>Dickeson</em> Alderman, and Sir <em>Thomas <unclear><!--10 characters--></unclear></em> Recorder of the City of <em>York</em>: the true copy whereof is as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>To his Highness <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <em>England, Scotland</em>, and <em>Ireland</em>, &amp;c.</i></head>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased the Lord, whose eyes run to and fro through the earth, to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself strong on the behalf of them whose hearts are perfect to him, to make bare his Arm and bring salvation to a Nation not worthy to be beloved, &amp; to break many yokes from off our necks, in accomplishment <reg orig="wherof">whereof</reg>, though humane Might and Power have been made use of, yet things have been so ordered and <reg orig="over-ruled">overruled</reg> by the Spirit in the midst of the wheels, that we may justly say, We are not saved by Bow, or by sword, but by the Lord our God; and therefore, in the first place we look upon it as our duty to acknowledge Salvation and blessing to him that sits upon the Throne of Heaven judging the right, who hath done whatsoever it pleased him, both in Heaven, and in Earth, and in all deep places. Yet when we also consider how it hath seemed good in the eyes of God to single out your Highness as the man of his right hand, whom he hath made strong for himself, and through your <reg orig="vigilancy">vigilance</reg>, courage, and constancy, to do great and wonderful things in the <pb n="3" />midst of us, in delivering us from eminent and pressing dangers on the right hand and on the left. While, we bless the Lord, our heart is also to the Governors of <em>Israel</em>, who have <reg orig="jeoparded">jeopardised</reg> their lives in the high places of the field, and are <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> going on to second their valiant Acts by prudent Councils, that we may enjoy the end of every just War, which is, a safe and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> peace. Unto your highness therefore (as all the people of Israel to their Ruler) we humbly and heartily say, <i>Peace be to thee, and peace be to thine helpers.</i></p>

<p>For which congratulation, his Highness returned thanks to the City of <em>York</em>, and the Gentlemen that presented it.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday April 4.</i></head>

<p>The Lord Ambassador of the King of Portugal had this hay audience by his Highness at the Cockpit, and the Queen of <reg orig="Swedens">Sweden's</reg> <em>Agent</em> had likewise audience, being attended by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, and divers Gentlemen, there being with his Highness divers Lords of the Council, and Mr. Secretary of State.</p>

<p>The Committee for approbation of Ministers have met in <reg orig="White Hall">Whitehall</reg>, chose their Register, and other Officers, and began to proceed in the business according to the Ordinance of his Highness. The place which they sit in, is at the end of the stone Gallery, at the corner of the Court, and their proceedings are such as promiseth much good to this Nation by the <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of a able, godly, and powerful Gospel <reg orig="Ministery">Ministry</reg>. They sit <reg orig="Mundayes">Mondays</reg>, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg>, and <reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg>.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Welch-men">Welshmen</reg> have sent a Declaration to his Highness, wherein they bless God for the late Change and present Government. And the like is come from <em>Norfolk</em>, and other places. <i>To God be all the glory.</i></p>

<p>The Commission of the great Seal being <reg orig="alter'd">altered</reg>, the Lord <em>Lisle</em>, and sir <em>Tho: Withrington</em> were this day sworn Commissioners for the custody of the great Seal of <em>England</em> for the Court of Chancery by the Clerk of the <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>, before his Highness, and his Council, in the Council chamber at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>. The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is added to them.</p>

<p>From <em>Naples</em> we have received intelligence, That the French men <pb n="4" />of war upon the Coast of <em>Apulia</em> have done much harm, and taken many prizes, among whom is an English ship worth fifty thousand pounds taken at <em>Cape Spativento</em>.</p>

<p>The Dutch Ambassadors have sent an Express to their Masters the States of the United Provinces, giving them an Account of the Ratification for Peace, which is to be signed and sealed by the Lord Protector within 14 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and then to be <reg orig="publikely">publicly</reg> proclaimed both in England and Holland in one day. The Agreement with Denmark is also taken in upon the Articles; and for the loss sustained by the English Merchants, whose Demands to about one hundred and fifty thousand pounds, it is referred to two English and two Dutch Merchants absolutely to determine those Demands within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and their place of sitting appointed at Guild <reg orig="Hal">Hall</reg>. Also the business of <em>Amboyna</em> is referred to eight Commissioners, who have six <reg orig="moneths">months</reg> time to determine thereof, and in case they agree not, Umpires are nominated.</p>

<p>Upon the arrival of the <reg orig="Newes">News</reg> at the Hague, touching the signing and sealing of the Articles of Peace between England and Holland, the Royal party were much startled thereat, and Major Gen. Massey was pleased to make this construction upon the Ratification, That sith Providence had pleased to make up the Breach between the two <reg orig="Republiques">Republics</reg>, it was impossible that his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> Game should go forward, and that he conceived it would redound most to the honour of the English Chevaliers to engage mutually in the Christian service; against the Turks and Pagans. A most noble and <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Design, and I desire that it may prove effectual.</p>

<p>But on the contrary, the major part are exceedingly revived in spirit, and the Merchants on both sides have great cause to <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg>; for the <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> begin already to seek out for shelter, and to striffe off from the Narrow Seas. <i>A fair riddance.</i> And the Navigable <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> appear somewhat <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg>, the Clouds of <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> being gallantly expelled. The Ordinance for better amending and keeping in Repair the common <reg orig="High-wayes">Highways</reg> within this Nation, was presented to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view. From Scotland, we have received further intelligence, that the <pb n="5" />mickle Lairds, are also upon their march for a general conjunction with a Resolution to force all they can to rise with them. Hey toss now the Game goes forwards: but confident I am, and with a candid Resolution I desire, that the success may <reg orig="center">centre</reg>, where the justness of the Cause most depends, and no otherwise. <em>Middleton</em> has a very large commission, and ordered by his Master <em>Charles</em> to dispose of all Affairs both Ecclesiastical and civil. He proceeds with fire and sword against all those that will not <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him and hath besieged <em>Cinkeler</em> castle; besides, they have taken a Vessel of ours going to Lewis Island laden with Ammunition, Provision, and <reg orig="cloaths">clothes</reg> for that Garrison. In the Southern parts towards <em>Carlisle</em> they are very active in rising daily, which puts the English horse to extraordinary duty, even to <reg orig="tyring">tiring</reg> out.</p>

<head level="3"><reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg> April 7.</head>

<p>Since our last, We have received intelligence, that the <reg orig="Highlanders">Highlanders'</reg> Army are all <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> into one body; <unclear>but</unclear> <unclear>approx. 20 characters</unclear> they may be <reg orig="disprerced">dispersed</reg> again for the English <unclear>are endeavouring to give them</unclear> battle and desire nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> sudden action. They speak high; but as yet dare not descend low: neither dare they interpose, unless with great advantage. The Broad Seal, we hear, is taken by order from his Highness, and disposed of, and the Commissioners for the Relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners are not to proceed these 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. Sundry other excellent things are under Debate.</p>

<p>It is advertised that the King of Scots is yet in France, where (say the Letters) he will stay a little, and see what effects the Treaty will produce betwixt England and France. He had a Present given him a little before Easter by some of the Protestant Nobility of that Kingdom. In the <reg orig="Holydayes">Holidays</reg> the little Queen his mother came to see him in the Palace Royal, and King <em>Lewis</em> vouchsafed him a visit in the <em>Lovare</em>; After which, she returned to her Devotions in the Nunnery. But if there be a peace concluded between the Commonwealth of England, and the Crown of France, then they are to be excluded from the Court. Well! Patience is a Virtue: And I question not but <reg orig="e're">ere</reg> long to represent you with the glad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg> of the Olive leaves under the happy Government of <em>Oliver</em> our Protector.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<p>There hath been a very sharp Dispute between the Paul <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and a Flushing man of War, the last Week; but after 5 hours Conflict, the Hollanders were forced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, and now <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the mercy of our States in Plymouth.</p>

<head level="3">Saturday April 8.</head>

<p>Presents us with an Ordinance for adjourning part of <em>Easter</em> Term, which take as followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas may abuses and corruptions are crept into the ordinary course and administration of Justice, both in Law and Equity, the Reformation whereof hath not yet been attained: Out of a tender care and desire that so necessary and good a work may at length be brought to effect, It is held convenient and necessary to Adjourn part of the next Term of <em>Easter</em>: Be it therefore Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the consent of His <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>. That <unclear>part of the</unclear> said Term of <em>Easter</em> now next coming to be Adjourned, <unclear><!--one third of a line--></unclear> Return called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, unto the first <unclear><!--one third of a line--></unclear> <em>Crastino Trinstatis</em>: And all and every person or <unclear>persons which have cause or</unclear> commandment to appear in any of the Courts at <unclear><em>Westminster</em>, in or at one <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> time</unclear> from and after the said Return, called <unclear><em>Quindena Pasche</em></unclear>, and <unclear>during the said Term,</unclear> called <em>Easter</em> Term, may tarry at <unclear>the</unclear> dwellings, or <unclear><!--16 characters--></unclear> <unclear>shall</unclear> <reg orig="lye">lie</reg>, without resorting to any of the said Courts for that Cause, and <unclear><!--approx. 14 characters--></unclear> or forfeiture, penalty or contempt to be in that behalf. And be it also Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That Writs of Adjournment shall be <unclear>directed to the</unclear> Justices of the said Courts, giving them authourity to adjourn the said Term of <em>Easter</em>, as aforesaid, that is to say, from and after the first Return called <em>Quindena Pasche</em>, until the first Return of <em>Trinity</em> Term, called <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em> as before is said, and the said Adjournment shall be made, as aforesaid. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all Matters, Causes and <reg orig="Sutes">Suits</reg>, Depending in any of the said Courts, shall have continuance, and the parties shall have day, from the day of the said Adjournment, until the said Return of <em>Crastino Trinitatis</em>, as is aforesaid: And the Lords Commissioners of the Great Seal are required to issue forth Writs accordingly. And be it further Ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That the Sheriffs of <em>London</em> and <em>Middlesex</em>, and all other Sheriffs both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>, do <unclear>forthwith</unclear> proclaim and publish this Ordinance in the Chief Market Towns within their several and respective Counties.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<head level="3">Mr. <em>Tho. Lewis</em>, Mr. <em>Tho. Powel</em> and Mr. <em>Griffith Hatley</em>, <i>their Letter to Master <em>Jenk. Jones</em>.</i></head>

<p>Mr. Jones, We desire to be resolved by you, whether the elected Ministers of this Country, who have been silenced and suspended, now this long time, <em>ab officio, &amp; beneficio</em> may at last have the door of utterance opened, and be permitted to preach the Gospel freely among those that do much want it, and do as earnestly call for it, as the parched Earth after the dew and Rain of Heaven. The reason why we put this business to the question is: because about the last spring, some of our fellow Ministers, taking the boldness to preach the word of God, were some of them, sent prisoners to <em><reg orig="Chepsto">Chepstow</reg></em> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, others pulled out of the Pulpit, and all the rest were threatened to have the same measure meted unto them, if they should make the same attempts: and therefore we desire to know whether we are under the same restraint still, or are at liberty: we doubt not but that you can resolve us herein, as well as any other in this County, and we hope you will be pleased to <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> our civil request herein and vouchsafe a line of answer, which you may direct to either of the subscribers who are Sir</p>

<p>Your friends, as far as you are a friend to Christ and his ways</p>

<p>Feb. 6. 1643. <i>Tho. Lewis, Tho. Powell, Griffith Hatley.</i></p>

<head level="3">Mr. Jenk. <reg orig="Jones">Jones's</reg> letter in Answer to the former.</head>

<p><i>Gentlemen,</i></p>

<p>Your Letter dated <em>Feb. 6. 1653.</em> I received the 1. of <em>March</em>. <unclear>And the</unclear> answer to what you propose therein I shall only put you in <reg orig="minde">mind</reg> that you are still, and more than like to be in the same condition, with those in the last Spring: and tell you that you are to expect the same measure from the present <unclear>Power</unclear> whose connivance you seem, at least, to <reg orig="fancie">fancy</reg> to <reg orig="your selves">yourselves</reg>, as your brethren had the last Spring from the then powers: And also that you need not pretend your being pressed as from <reg orig="pitty">pity</reg> to water the parched earth, there being more Sermons preached now in one <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, <reg orig="then">than</reg> were formerly in twelve, and with very much, though I dare not say greater blessing: confide the restraint-fearing Spirit <reg orig="thats">that's</reg> in you, Your friend and servant,</p>

<p><i>March 2. 1653. Jen. Jones.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Deal</em> the 7. instant: The Ships which were in this Road are now gone Southward. The English Fleet are an 100. sail, lie at St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg> point</em>, and the rest at the <em><reg orig="Spit's">Spits</reg> head.</em></p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>