<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost171">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 171</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Articles of Agreement between his Highness the Lord Protector and the States of the United Provinces: With the sole and absolute concluding of a firm Peace and Union betwixt the two <reg orig="Common wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of England and Holland, and the King of Denmark. And the Proclamation to be published throughout the Territories of Scotland. The Declaration of the Queen of <em>Sweden</em>, and the bloody <em>Sentence</em> and Charge of High-Treason exhibited &amp; pronounced against the Prince of <em>Conde</em> for his Rebellion. A Remonstrance for the allowance of Brass Farthings, and a Declaration touching the City and <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Butchers.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 28. to <em>Tuesday</em> April 4. 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i></p>
<hr />

<p>There will suddenly be extant a Remonstrance concerning the allowance of brass Farthings, wherein is comprised sundry excellent Reasons <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> the lawfulness thereof, and the great profit that will <unclear>redound</unclear> to the State and Commonwealth thereby.</p>

<p>From Scotland it is advertised, That Cap. <unclear>Lilburn</unclear> and Cap. Ortan have landed three Companies of Col. <reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg> Regiment at Leith, and that Col. Lilburn is preparing to interpose with the Enemy. They are nothing <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <unclear>so</unclear> formidable, as reported. Neither will they fight us but upon great advantages.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, being the 27 of this instant <reg orig="moneth">month</reg>, there came a <em>Post</em> from Scotland, intimating, That the Royal party increaseth, and that Gen. <em>Middleton</em> <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to raise <em>Southerland, Caithness</em>, and the county of <em>Ross</em>, and so to drain the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>, even as a <reg orig="Spunge">Sponge</reg> sucketh in Water, of all the able, stout, and resolute hearts, that are able to bear Arms from sixteen to sixty; with a Resolution to descend down into the Lowlands: for, indeed, they grow numerous, and swell up as a <reg orig="Snow-Ball">Snowball</reg> doth in its rolling; but may as soon dissolve again in the like Element. The <reg orig="Lor">Lord</reg> <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised his number to seven hundred, the Earl of <em>Athol</em> five hundred, Col. <em>Forbs</em> five hundred, and the last general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> seven thousand horse and foot they spake themselves to be <reg orig="compleatly">completely</reg> armed, but have not obtained as yet the silver Instrument, which is the life of the Cause, and the very sinew of War: but their expectation is great from <em>Germany</em>, and for ought I know, long <reg orig="lookt">looked</reg> for may come at last: in the interim, they march towards our Borders, forcing their Levies throughout their march.</p>

<p>From Scotland it is further <reg orig="advertized">advertised</reg>, That Col. <em>Morgan</em> hath sent a Letter to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, declaring, That it was not unknown what amicable <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> they has <reg orig="us'd">used</reg>, to avoid the effusion of Christian blood, since they came into those parts, which though hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they should <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> the same; <i><reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> further</i>, That their Arms were still <reg orig="strecht">stretched</reg> out ready to embrace them, <reg orig="when ever">whenever</reg> God should incline them to come in, and that they sought not domination over them, to enslave them, nor to depress them in any lawful way, but to carry on the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Work: And that if they would still be blinded, and persist in the <reg orig="gain-saying">gainsaying</reg> and opposing, then what further misery befell their Nation by famine or sword, would <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> heavy upon them. This Letter (though favouring so much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adversaries; for <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> thereupon, an Answer was returned; which being briefly contracted, the genuine sense take as followeth; That in case they were not in a capacity against the unjust proceedings of the English, yet were they in a capacity to suffer, and should submit to <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Will, either by doing or suffering, until the time of their deliverance come; and that if it were their happiness to perish in their <pb n="2" />Duty and Loyalty, it would be a sufficient mercy to them: and when the persecution had arrived to its height, their captivity should be returned. But doubtless, but that in time we shall be able to put a Hook into the Nostrils, and a Bridle into the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of these high and mighty Youngsters, who threaten nothing but fire and sword to all that shall oppose them. There has been a Summons sent to the castle of Lough by col. <em>Morgan</em>, in the name of the Lord Protector, demanding a rendition. But the Governor returned Answer, That as for the castle it stood upon a Rock, and as for the Lord Protector he knew no such man: in consideration whereof, he was resolved to dispute the Walls by Inches, and to fight it out to the last man.</p>

<p>The 27 instant, the French Ambassador had Audience before his Highness the Lord Protector, at which time, upon the presenting of his Letters Credential from his Master the King, he made a very learned and excellent Oration, touching his <reg orig="Embassie">Embassy</reg>, and the renewing of a more stricter League and Union between both Nations. Of which, more in our next.</p>

<p>The 29. the Lord Ambassador <em><reg orig="Burdeux">Bordeaux</reg></em> from the King of <em>France</em>, had <reg orig="publick">public</reg> Audience in the Banqueting house in <em>Whitehall</em>, which was richly hung with stately Hangings, and thousands of people present. Being carried in the L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and with him some of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg>, &amp; Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> Master of the Ceremonies, attended by divers Noble persons, being in all above forty Coaches, more with six horses <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>. Where he was received by his Highness the Lord Protector, his <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> being with his Highness at the upper end of the Banqueting house, where after several <unclear>Congies</unclear> each to other, the L. Ambassador made a speech to his Highness, and after his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> answer and salutings, he returned back again. The sum of the L. <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Speech was to declare that he came from the K. of <em>France</em> his Master to treat in order to a firm peace to be <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> with <em>England</em>. Touching which he had a <reg orig="kinde">kind</reg> answer.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of 18. Prizes taken by the Phoenix, Newcastle, Assurance, and <reg orig="Mairmayd">Mermaid</reg> <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</i></head>

<p>Taken by the <em>Newcastle</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, a Galliot Hoy, whose Mast being shot by the Board she was burnt. 2. Taken by the Assurance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, the Hope of Hous-down, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50. <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 3. Taken by the <em>Phoenix</em>, the Claus of Housdown <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 50 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 4. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaids">Mermaid's</reg></em> Boat, the Fortune of Mazeland Sluys, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 32 Tons; wherein were many barrels of Fish, and 6. of Salt, with about 40 <pb n="3" />empty Cask. 5. Taken by the same day by the <em><reg orig="Newcastles">Newcastle's</reg></em> Boat, the Skell-fish of Mazeland Sluys, with Fish, Salt, &amp; empty Cask. 6. Taken by the <em>Phoenix</em> her Boat, the Plumpart of Mazeland Sluys, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 30 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with Fish, Salt, and empty Cask likewise. 7. Taken by the <em>Mairmaid</em>, the Providence of Mazeland Sluys, 28 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, with the like lading. 8. Taken likewise the Fortune of Delfs-haven, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 200 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>, laden with Branywine, French wine, Prunes &amp;c. 9. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em> one Gallio Hoy, <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg> 25 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg>. 10. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, two Scotch vessels, laden with Beef, Flower, Train-<reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, Deer-skins and Sugars. 11. Taken by the <em><reg orig="Maremaid">Mermaid</reg></em>, the Waking Boy of Enchuysen a private man of War, of 8. Guns, 150 pounds of powder, shot proportionable. 12 Pikes, 10. Muskets, eight Pistols, and a Boat with four Oars. 12. A Merchant ship brought in prize into <em>Rye</em>. 13. A Denmark ship brought into <em>Scarborough</em>. 14. A rich prize laden with Sugar, and other <reg orig="Merchandizes">Merchandises</reg>, taken by a private man of War worth 150000 l. A private man of War belonging to <em>Zealand</em>, taken by the <em>Paul</em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> with 15. piece of Ordinance and 60 men, after six hours dispute, she is brought into <em>Plymouth</em>.</p>

<p>The Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is returned from <em>Ireland</em>, and is (blessed be God) safely arrived at the Cock-pit. All is quiet and in a good condition in <em>Ireland</em>.</p>

<p>From Leghorn our Post hath brought intelligence, that the French <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> have taken two English Merchant ships bound for London, but purchased them with the lost of much blood.</p>

<p>From Upsal in Sweden thus: All the actions of our great Queen are so many wonders, and continual effects of her <reg orig="vertues">virtues</reg>, and of the greatness of her incomparable courage; but some few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> since in special she did give such proof thereof, that the same may be called the Crown of all her other actions, seeing it doth manifest to the World how this admirable Princess hath set <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> above the Crowns, under which man commonly do seek their satisfaction and glory. The 23 of Feb she having summoned all the Senators of the Land, they all made their appearance except 9 who were out of the Land upon <reg orig="publike">public</reg> employment: her Majesty declared unto them the design she had to leave the charge of the Kingdom, and to that end she was resolved to go to Nicoping to confer with the Prince Palatine of Sweden her Cousin, having sent him Letters to invite him thither, and <reg orig="withall">withal</reg> to <reg orig="perswade">persuade</reg> him to accept the charge of the Kingdom, and the managing of the State Affairs: This Prince is the same who was heretofore Generalissimo of the Swedish Armies in Germany, concluded first a peace with the Duke Picolomini and <pb n="4" />the year 1650 at the Coronation of the Queen, was then declared apparent Heir to the Crown of Sweden, and by the States and Commonalty acknowledged so, having made their Oath of Allegiance to him, as unto their future King, after the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> death; we are expecting with great impatience the event of that generous and unthought of Resolution. The 26 of Feb. her Majesty had a mask danced in the behalf of the Earl <em>de Montecuculli</em>, Gen. of the horse to the Emperor, where were present the English and Spanish Ambassadors, with many of our Senators: the beginning of this Mask was of an exquisite harmony of voices and instruments, to sing some <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg> Poems, composed first by an Italian called: <em>Albertus Vemino</em>, in honour of the Emperor: in the midst of it was made a splendid and Royal Collation of <reg orig="Sweet-meats">Sweetmeats</reg>, and other Rarities, and at the end of the Mask was brought by the Earl of <em>Todta</em> a rich Collar, and being laid <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Queen, <unclear>there was a</unclear> Cushion laid at her feet: then having called to her the Earl of <em>Montecuculli</em>, and with her own hands invested him of that <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters--></unclear> Knighthood called of <em>Amarantha</em>, and first instituted <unclear><!--approx. 15 characters--></unclear> who holding both his hands, did make him promise <unclear>that he would</unclear> truly and faithfully keep and observe all the <unclear><!--approx. 6 characters--></unclear> <unclear>of that Order</unclear>. During all this Ceremony the <reg orig="musick">music</reg> both <unclear><!--approx. 18 characters--></unclear>, and among other rare pieces the sung, was one <unclear><!--approx. 14 characters--></unclear>, whereof all the verses ended thus, <i>Long may live <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear></i>.</p>

<p>The English Fleet are divided into four Squadrons, the better to scour and secure the Narrow Seas, they are excellently well equipped and as bravely <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>: Nothing wanting, but a resolute Enemy to fight them; which <unclear>neither</unclear> curled Waves, nor Weltick Ocean can bear, in case the Belgick <reg orig="Canons">Cannons</reg> be silenced. They have already forced some of the <reg orig="Pyrats">Pirates</reg>, Rovers, and Irish <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg>, from Brest to Toulon in <unclear>France where</unclear> they have now time enough to sing the second part to the same tune, <em>O lione, O lione</em>. We have taken another of their men of War, and a Dutch Merchant laden with extraordinary good commodities.</p>

<p>The Dutch fleet are also in a pretty formidable, and new Orders issued fort to Vice-Admiral <em>Ruiter</em>. The King of Spain looks with a notable <reg orig="sheeps">sheep's</reg> eye upon the Belgick <reg orig="Lyons">Lions</reg>, and 'tis conceived <reg orig="somthing">something</reg> may probably be attempted.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>Came to my hands the Copy of an Act for Reformation of sundry abuses practised by divers persons in the common markets and streets of the City of London: the genuine sense whereof runs thus:</p>

<p><go>Whereas several good Laws and Ordinances have <reg orig="bin">been</reg> heretofore made as well by the Court of Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> and Aldermen, as by others for the <reg orig="wel">well</reg> ordering of the Markets of the City of <em>London</em>, for <reg orig="redresse">redress</reg> of several abuses of Butchers, Victuallers, and others thereunto reporting, for sale of their flesh victuals, and other commodities in the several Markets of this City, and assigning places and times for the said Markets to be kept and held, Which said Laws and Ordinances by daily experience are found not effectual to prevent some present and growing inconveniences no; have wrought that good effect as was intended thereby. For redress whereof, be it enacted by the Right <reg orig="Honorable">Honourable</reg> the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg>, Alderman and Commons in Common <reg orig="councel">council</reg> assembled, that no Butcher or <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>-Farmer, Victualler, or other person or persons whatsoever, either free of the City of London or not free of the said City, from and after the first day of <em>Decemb.</em> Next, after the publication of this Act, shall sell, offer, or put to open <reg orig="shew">show</reg> or sale in the streets or white-markets in within this City; that is to say, <em>Leaden hall street</em> without the Hall, <em>Cheapside</em> and <em>Newgate market</em>, any Beef, upon pain that every person or persons that from and after the time aforesaid, shall sell, utter, put to sale, or <reg orig="shew">show</reg> in any of the said Markets any Beef, <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> forfeit and lose 20s. for every time so offending, and further be it enacted. That all and every Butcher, free or not free of the <reg orig="Citie">City</reg> of <em>London</em> who keepeth no Butcher shop or shops within the said City and Liberties thereof or within two miles distance of the liberties thereof shall, and may sell, utter, <reg orig="shew">show</reg>, and put to sale, his, or their Beef, Mutton, Veal, Lamb, Pork &amp; other Butchery ware at certain stalls and places in that behalf appointed in <em>Leaden-hall</em> &amp; the <em>Green-yard</em> there, that <reg orig="onely">only</reg> upon <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg> and <reg orig="Saturdayes">Saturdays</reg> weekly and not in any other place or places within the said City of <em>London</em> and Liberties thereof, upon pain of 20s. forfeit. And <reg orig="wheras">whereas</reg> of late times many of the standings and stalls within <em>Leaden-hall</em> and the <em>Greenyard</em> there have, and yet are in the occupations of several persons who are not Butchers by trade, who let them out at dear rates to others; and likewise many of the said stalls are are <!--repeated in text over a line break--> in the possession of Butchers who live within the City of London and Liberties thereof who keep the said stalls add likewise their shops: By means whereof the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Butchers, and other Butchers who keep no shops within the said City, or within two miles of the Liberties of the City of London, &amp; would furnish the said Markets with Butchery ware, can get no convenient room there, and so are necessitated to sell and utter <pb n="6" />their Commodities in the White-markets, and other places, or to forbear the Markets whereby prices are <reg orig="inhaunsed">enhanced</reg>; and the said Market disfurnished. For remedy whereof, be it enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all the ground where the standings and places for sale &amp; uttering of flesh &amp; Butchery ware within Leaden hall and the Greenyard there, be resumed and taken into the <reg orig="Cities">City's</reg> hands, and actual possession, before the said first day of Decemb. Next ensuing. And further, that no stall, standing, or place within Leadenhall or the Greenyard there, shall from henceforth be letted or farmed out unto any Butcher or Butchers, who doth or shall keep any Butcher shop or shops within the City of London or Liberties thereof, or within two miles of the Liberties of the said City for so long time as be, or they, shall keep any <reg orig="Butchers">Butcher's</reg> shop within the Limits aforesaid.</go></p>

<p><go>And that from thenceforth the Stalls, standings, and places in Leadenhal and the Greenyard there be let unto <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Butchers, or such freemen who are Butchers, and keep not any Butcher shop or shops within the City of London and Liberties thereof, or within two miles distance of the Liberties of the said City, and for so long time <reg orig="onely">only</reg> as he or they shall furnish the said stalls, standings and places with <reg orig="wholsom">wholesome</reg> Beef, Mutton, Veal, Lamb, <reg orig="Porke">Pork</reg>, or other Butchery ware upon Wednesdays and Saturdays, being the usual Market days and not as Servant or servants to others.</go></p>

<p><go>And further, that no Butcher whatsoever shall have and enjoy more <reg orig="then">than</reg> one stall standing, or place within Leadenhal or the Greenyard there at one time. Provided always, That the Butchers freemen of the City of London, shall and may at all times convenient sell, utter, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> and put to sale their flesh and Butchery wares in their Shops within the said City of London, and Liberties thereof as formerly; <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> in this Act to the contrary notwithstanding. Provided that the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> Farmer, Lader, or Bidder as to all <reg orig="wholsom">wholesome</reg> flesh victuals and other Commodities except Beef may have liberty to sell, <reg orig="shew">show</reg> and utter the same in the Common and <reg orig="publique">public</reg> White markets within the City of London and Liberties thereof in Market times: this Act or <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> contained therein to the contrary. And forasmuch as of late the <reg orig="forain">foreign</reg> Butchers Victuallers and other people resorting to the Markets of the City of London to dell their flesh victuals &amp; other Commodities, do continue and keep their Markets all the day, &amp; until night not observing the hours appointed for their departure by former Acts and Ordinances, To the end the streets may in due time be cleansed for the health of the Inhabitants of those places; which doing of theirs tendeth much to the disorder of the said Markets, <reg orig="inhaunsing">enhancing</reg> the prices of <reg orig="Comodities">Commodities</reg>, disturbance and <reg orig="hinderance">hindrance</reg> of Passengers and Tradesmen dwelling near the said places and reason thereof the streets cannot be cleansed as they ought to be, to the scandal of the Government of the City of London, and is very necessary to be reformed.</go></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>The great expectation of Peace and Union between the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> of England and Holland is now arrived our Ears, insomuch, that we can certainly assure you, that the Articles both in relation to them and Denmark, are absolutely concluded on, and the Commissioners are even now ready to sign and seal on both sides.</p>

<p>Paris April the first. All the discourse at present is concerning that which was acted in the Parliament on Saturday last, when all the Chambers being assembled, and every member in their scarlet <reg orig="gownes">gowns</reg>, the King then came, and being sat in his bed of Justice, they proceeded in the business of the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, and <reg orig="immadiatly">immediately</reg> read the sentence, which is, That for being found guilty of high Treason and Rebellion against the King his Lord and liege <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, he was to be put to death, and that so soon as he should be apprehended, his Sentence to be executed, his lands and goods all <unclear>forfeited</unclear> to the Crown; in regard of his quality he is not to be executed in <reg orig="Effigie">Effigy</reg>, &amp; as touching the manner of his death the Parliament would not determine but <unclear>left unto</unclear> his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> pleasure. The <unclear>Prince of <em>Conti</em> is</unclear> much troubled <unclear><!--1 line--></unclear> Court.</p>

<p>From <unclear><!--two thirds of a line--></unclear> That the Commander in chief <unclear><!--two thirds of a line--></unclear> <reg orig="Buroughs">Boroughs</reg> <unclear>and Parishes to</unclear> <unclear><!--half a line--></unclear> to this <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg>: Several Towns have been <unclear><!--approx. 9 characters--></unclear> of the breach hereof, the persons confined, and their <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters--></unclear> with the ground, and a pair of Gallows erected in the same place. The 21 instant Col. Cooper with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg> and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of <em>Leven</em>, where about 300 of the enemy quartered [about 4 in the morning) took Mac-<reg orig="Naughtons">Naughton's</reg> Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, but Col. Newark escaped. In this Conflict many a stout Spirit saluted the ground and, the whole party was totally routed, with very little.</p>

<p>There hath been a very sharp Dispute between the Paul <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg>, and a Flushing man of War, the last Week; but after 5 hours Conflict, the Hollanders were forced to <reg orig="yeeld">yield</reg>, and now <reg orig="lye">lie</reg> at the mercy of out States in Plymouth.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, licensed and <reg orig="entred">entered</reg> into the Register Book of the Company of Stationers.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>