<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost167">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 167</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2"><i>The Grand Politique</i></head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating</head>

<p><i>The Declaration and Proposals of the Lord Ambassadors from the States of Holland, to his Highness the Lord Protector, upon their receiving Audience in the Banqueting house at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, on Saturday last in the Afternoon. With the Articles of Agreement, for the ratifying, and <reg orig="setling">settling</reg> of a firm and lasting Peace, and the taking of the Chairs of State this present Tuesday by his Highness and the said Ambassadors with the coming up of the Lord Williamson from the K. of Denmark, and his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Message to the Lord Protector. The going of the King of Scots into Germany. The setting forth of the fiery Crosses in the North, the revolting of some of the English <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and the number taken and executed.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 28. to <em>Tuesday</em> March 7. 1654</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>The King of Scots (we hear) is going for <em>Germany</em>, being invited thither by the Princes, and his brother <em><reg orig="Iames">James</reg></em> is designed for <em>Flanders</em>, where the Arch Duke <em>Leopold William</em> (General for the King of S<em>pain</em>) is very potent. The Lord <em>Digh</em> is said to go along with him as Lieut. Gen. and Sir Lewis Dives as Maj. Gen. Marshal Thurene is preparing likewise to take the field. The Lord Inchiquin has received great command from the King, and is to command under Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>. The Lord Jermin is Excluded from the Court, but the Lord <unclear><em>Taass</em></unclear> is taken in.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>Whereas the great point of <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> and concernment to the safety and benefit of a Commonwealth, is the Electing and disposing of its own Magistrates, or the great Officers of State. And as for the <em>present Council</em>, and the election of them in the way it hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg>: It must be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg>, that we were in the beginning of a new Government, necessitated to create a little World out of a Chaos, and bring Form out of Confusion; so that there was an absolute necessity, that some who are known to be persons of integrity, and firm for the present Settlement, should at the same instant be taken in, to carry on the work: which can be no ground of just exception, especially seeing for the future, Elections shall run in the appointed channel, where their <reg orig="streames">streams</reg> are to flow from the People, and their original-Fountain. Yea, the high Office of Protectorship <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> is to be derived also from hence; and as in time it will appear, that the People in Parliament have the main choice of the Council, so they will likewise be <reg orig="Chusers">Choosers</reg> of the Lord Protector: For, it being left to the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> Him, and they hereafter coming to be chosen and trusted by the Parliament, it cannot otherwise be conceived, but that the Choice of Him takes its rise mediately from the People in Parliament: because as whatsoever a <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> doth, is said and taken in a political sense to be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> act, because they are chosen and trusted by the people; so in like manner, and upon the same political account, when the Council comes to be chosen by Parliament, as is before expressed, then the Act of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, must by a parity of Reason be reputed the Act of the people in Parliament: And so you see, in effect, mediately or immediately, the election of all Magistrates (both high and low) are, or will at length, by this Constitution of Government, be in the hands of the People. Lastly, as to what concerns the Office of <em>Lord Protector</em>, it is to be observed, that he is not to be admitted to that dignity upon the Interest of Himself or Family, but <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> upon the account of his fitness for Government: it <unclear>must pass</unclear> not by Inheritance, but Election. And certainly it is a great advantage to Nation that the coming in and continuance of their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> depends only upon his own goodness, and the good will of the People; as <unclear>it</unclear> is in an <em>Elective Prince</em>, who standing upon terms of good <unclear>behaviour</unclear> will be continually employed for the benefit and defence of the Community. And therefore if it shall please the Lord <unclear>to bless this</unclear> Commonwealth (as we trust he will) successively with a choice of <unclear>godly</unclear> persons into that high Office, it is easily <unclear>foreseen what an advantage</unclear> it will be to these 3. Nations, to have their whole <unclear>strength and force</unclear> <unclear><!--approx. 12 characters--></unclear> under one head, for the safety of all: this Form being (without question) the <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear> and most convenient for the Magistrate to put things on, and in quick execution (as his proper work) <unclear>for the</unclear> <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good: <unclear>as and what a condition it will</unclear> be to all the godly in the <em>Protestant Churches</em> abroad, who may have some more <pb n="2" />sure and certain from <em>England</em> than <unclear><!--approx. 15 characters--></unclear>; which as it is the greatest Body, being united with <em>Scotland</em>, so it will prove (we hope) the grand Bulwark of the <em>Reformed Religion</em>. Moreover, as touching the Person, whom the Lord hath now advanced and set over <unclear>us to be our</unclear> <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Magistrate, We shall not say much, because he seeks not the <unclear><!--approx. 6 characters--></unclear> of <unclear><!--approx. 5 characters--></unclear> only we believe even the enemies will confess; that he is every way worthy to Rule, whom God hath been pleased to use as his Instrument in that glorious Work of Redeeming the Liberties of his people: For we are bold to say (weighing all circumstances together) that this Nation was never really Free, nor in a Way of enjoying its Freedom so fully as now: so that there wants nothing but a cordial Close with the Government, to destroy all hopes of the common Enemy, and <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> our happiness. But if men shall yet proceed to lengthen their own <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg>, by hankering after that Family which God hath cast out before us, or by an unnatural seeking to <reg orig="imbroil">embroil</reg> their Country again in blood and misery, for the sake of that <reg orig="infortunate">unfortunate</reg> Interest, as we are <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to suspect such a thing, and can hardly imagine that any should be so forlorn and desperate after so fair a Composure.</p>

<p>The Ambassadors from the States of Holland are landed with full power to conclude a peace. They are expected this day at <reg orig="Whitehal">Whitehall</reg>, with all their gallant Retinue, consisting of one hundred in number, most excellently equipped; and divers eminent Gentlemen and Officers are appointed to congratulate them from Gravesend to Westminster with the States Barges and others, there being high and <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> preparations at Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg> house in the Palace yard.</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> Feb. 27.</i></head>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> from Scotland advertiseth, that the English forces have fallen upon the Highlanders, and after an <reg orig="irresistable">irresistible</reg> and furious Onset, took above 120 Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, great store of Arms, Ammunition, Horses with plenty of provision and afterwards blew up the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Dunkel. Col. Morgan hath also removed the <reg orig="Enemies">Enemy's</reg> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> at Kildrumny, and at Cromar put 120 to the sword, took 127 prisoners, 80 horse &amp; all their Bag and Baggage.</p>

<p>The two Ambassadors from Holland, the L. Newport, and the L. Yongstal that are to come to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with the L. Beverling, are now at Gravesend, and <unclear>Rir</unclear> Oliver Fleming, Master of the Ceremonies hath orders to receive them on <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, March 3. at which time they are to come from Gravesend to Tower-hill; and from thence, Coaches will be appointed to bring them and their attendants through the Cities <pb n="3" />of London and Westminster, to Sir Abraham <reg orig="Williams">Williams'</reg> house in the Palace-yard which is trimmed up for their reception.</p>

<p>Mr. Wil. Lenthal, formerly Speaker of the Parl. and divers other Gentlemen, have sent a congratulatory Declaration from the City of <reg orig="Glocester">Gloucester</reg>, to his Highness the Lord Protector, blessing the Lord for this established Government and protesting much affection thereto.</p>

<head level="3">The Articles for Peace</head>

<p>1. That from hence forward there shall be a more sure and inviolable Peace, sincere Friendship, and a closer <reg orig="Allyance">Alliance</reg>, &amp; Confederacy between the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>, and the States of the United Provinces, <reg orig="then">than</reg> hath been ever heretofore, and the of their respective Lands, Cities, and Countries, and of all under their obedience whatsoever, and of what condition soever. 2. That from henceforth all hostility shall cease. 3. That all wrongs and offences suffered either by the one or the other party shall be forgotten; and neither party shall pretend <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> thereupon. All actions past shall be nulled, except those that shall be done in the British seas after the time of twelve <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, and from that sea to the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em> in the time of 6 weeks; and from thence in the <em>Mediterranean</em> Sea, as far as the line, after the time of ten weeks; and at the other side of the line in the time of eight months, to be reckoned from the time of the publication of the Peace, and all Prizes taken after at that time <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be restored. 4 That all the prisoners of both sides be released without Ransom. 5 That both Commonwealths <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be confederate friends, to defend on the other against whomsoever. 6 That neither of both <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> act against the other, either by Sea or Land. 7 That the States shall cause restitution to be made of all the ships and goods seized upon the English by the King of <em>Denmark</em>, that are yet in being; and also a full compensation of the worth of those goods that may be sold already; and likewise that all the <reg orig="dammages">damages</reg> or spoil of goods <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> made good to the Owners by estimation, and when such satisfaction <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> done by the said King, then all hostility <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> cease between <em>England</em> and <em>Denmark</em>. 8 That no Inhabitants of either <reg orig="Common-wealth">Commonwealth</reg> <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> assist any Rebel of either with monies, ships, or victuals. 9 That both Commonwealths <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> assist one the other at their proper charges against their Rebels. 10 That neither shall receive <pb n="4" />those that are, or <reg orig="shalbe">shall be</reg> declared enemies of either Commonwealth. 11 That either Commonwealth having notice by the other that some of their Enemies are in its Dominions, they <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> give them warning to depart in 28 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> upon pain of death. 12 That the States <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not suffer any of the inhabitants of their Dominions to assist the enemies of <em>England</em>. 13 That the English <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> not pay greater Impositions <reg orig="then">than</reg> other Nations. 14 That the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> ships <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> strike their Flag before the English in the British seas.</p>

<p>The Ambassadors landed with their <reg orig="Attendents">Attendants</reg> at Tower Wharf, where were Coaches provided for them, their Lordships were in one of the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Coaches, and the Master of the Ceremonies with them, drawn by <reg orig="sixe">six</reg> horses: Next followed the French and the Portugal <reg orig="Ambassadors">Ambassador's</reg> Coaches, with above <unclear>20</unclear> more all with 6 horses, besides above 40 Coaches most with 4 horses <reg orig="a piece">apiece</reg>; they rode in a stately equipage through the City from Aldgate by the Royal Exchange, and so to the Palace yard Westminster to Sir Abraham Williams's, where they are to be <reg orig="entertaioed">entertained</reg>, with their Retinue, at the <reg orig="States">States'</reg> charge for some <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. And on Saturday in the afternoon they had audience given by his Highness the Lord Protector in the Banqueting house at <reg orig="White-hal">Whitehall</reg>, the room was richly hung with hangings, and a rich chain of State set for the Lord Protector, and Chairs on the one side for the Ambassadors, the entertainment was stately, and gallant, and the subject of this Audience was partly congratulatory to his Highness, and to declare the business of their coming to make and settle a firm peace, and to renew their old friendship which hath been for many years between the two Nations.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The Lord Mayor of the city of <em>London</em>, and the Recorder of the said city, on the party of the city of London; and divers Magistrates to attend his Highness and the Council, at the Council chamber in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>; and yesterday they were heard touching the business for a Corporation to be granted to the city of Westminster, and something therein, it is probable will shortly be done. Several new Orders are drawing up by sundry eminent persons within the city, for the regulating of abuses in Trades, <em>viz.</em> <reg orig="Shoo">Shoe</reg> makers, Silk-weavers, Tailors, Butchers, Carpenters, and <reg orig="Joyners">Joiners</reg>, and for the suppressing of <reg orig="foreiners">foreigners</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>France</em> we have received advertisements, that Card. <em>Mazarine</em> has reduced both King, Princes, and that Gen. <em>Turene</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>, are preparing to take the field against the Spanish forces.</p>

<head level="3">Thursday March 2.</head>

<p>From Windsor we have received Intelligence, that there is a notable Plot or Conspiracy discovered, against some that should have betrayed their Trust in the castle; and one of them being taken <reg orig="imbezelling">embezzling</reg> and carrying away the powder, was apprehended and <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> before the Governor, who received sentence to ride upon a Saker when it is shot off with an half charge. Mr. <em>Peak</em>, and Mr. <em>Simpson</em>, are both there still, and in good health, blessed be God. But poor Judge Jenkins declines exceedingly.</p>

<p>Yesterday an Ambassador Extraordinary from the <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> <em>Leopold</em> in Flanders, had Audience by his Highness the Lord Protector, where he did congratulate his Highness, <reg orig="shewing">showing</reg> him his Credentials, and presented him with a message from his master <em>Leopold William</em>, by the grace of God <reg orig="Arch-duke">Archduke</reg> of <em>Austria</em>, Duke of <em>Burgonie</em>, and Lieu. Gen. and Cap. Gen. of the Low countries. After which, he was conducted from thence by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em>, master of the Ceremonies. The said <reg orig="Arch-Duke">Archduke</reg> hath set forth two Declarations against that famous old Thief <unclear><em>Charles</em></unclear> Duke of <em>Lorain</em> who hath filled a great part of Christendom with his rapines and cruelties, and now lies close prisoner at Atwerp; for the K. of Spain is resolved to set up <em>Francis</em> the younger brother in the elder <reg orig="brothers">brother's</reg> place, and that the said L. Duke <em>Francis</em> shall undertake the sole command of the Army, with all the Engines and Banners thereunto belonging.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>Tuesday Feb. 28.</i></head>

<p>Presents us with an Abstract of Scotland, intimating, That the E. of Athol hath drawn most of his forces together from Weems, and other places, and he with the L. Bruce were the 14 at Glenshier, marching Northwards to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with Glencarn, Glengary, Kenmore, and the rest of the Royal party: Upon their conjunction they will be at the least 4000. and then they intend to be revenged upon the English, if they can: but <reg orig="Athols">Athol's</reg> foot are much discontented at the <reg orig="cowardize">cowardice</reg> of their horse; and the English that come with Col. Wogan out of Francs, are much dejected at the death of their valiant Colonel. Col. Lilburn is sending Recruits to Col. Morgan; but somewhat inconsiderable, until such time that the new supplies are gone from England. The Scots are very high at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, and breath forth Victories instead of Defeats, giving out that the late blow given by Col. Morgan was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to some few <reg orig="Countreo">Country</reg> men, when that it is evident, that G. Glencarn was there in person, and the valiant young Laird of Loughaber, who was one of the first that ran out of the field, and left his Commission from their King, signed C.R. behind him, together with the last Instructions of Lieu. Gen. Middleton, 5 Letters from Others to the Commander in chief of the Highlanders: All which Papers are to be sent up to his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>There hath been lately some meetings of godly Ministers about London, to consider of a way of union and reconciliation of the differences that unhappily have crept in among the godly, and other excellent things in order to the progress of the Gospel. And this day Mr. Owen, Mr. Tho. Goodwin, M. Sydrack Simson, Mr. Nie, and divers other revered pious Ministers were with his Highness.</p>

<p>From Ireland our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, that the L. Deputy Fleetwood, and the Officers of the Army, have caused to be printed at Dublin their Declaration to live and <reg orig="dye">die</reg> with his Highness in the present change of Government: but indeed at first many there were that scrupled it; yet upon consideration they unanimously assented thereunto.</p>

<p>From Newcastle they write, that cap. <em>Wetang</em> hath scoured those coasts of the Pickeroons, and that he hat sunk and taken some. But alas! this doth not <reg orig="equalize">equalise</reg> our loss in the West; for true it is, that the Brest men of war have taken the George of Bristol, being richly laden with Indigo, Sugar, and Tobacco.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>From Yarmouth our <em>Post</em> bringeth intelligence, that the Lord <em>Williamson</em> is landed, as Ambassador Extraordinary from the King of <em>Denmark</em>, whose Majesty hath sent a Message to his Highness, making application upon the success of the Dutch Treaty. And the Lord Ambassadors from <em>Holland</em> have presented their Credentials wherein they desire to include his Majesty. In order whereunto, the States of the 7 United Provinces do all of them agree and consent to the Agreement of Peace, and the said Ambassadors are <reg orig="impowred">empowered</reg> fully to confirm and <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the same, desiring a speedy cessation of Arms, and that all Acts of Hostility may cease on both sides. Their Lordships are to have Audience again on Tuesday, being the 7 of this instant <em>March</em>, so that undoubtedly some few circumstances being considered on, all will be concluded, and a Peace fully <reg orig="setled">settled</reg>.</p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> we have received intelligence, that the enemy are divided into divers parties to raise their assigned Levies, and the Earl of <em>Athol</em>, having a considerable party of Horse and Foot, hath sent forth the fiery <reg orig="Cresses">Crosses</reg>, threatening fire and sword to all that <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> comply with the English. Sir <em>Arthur Forbs</em> is marched toward <em>Lenox</em> with several Troops, and its conceived in design for the South. Divers of Col. <em><reg orig="Daniels">Daniels'</reg></em> are revolted to the enemy, but some of them were taken, and rewarded with a Rope. Others were <reg orig="tyed">tied</reg> up to the Gallows at <em>Dunkel</em>, and Marshal Law is <reg orig="dayly">daily</reg> executed upon all those who incur the penalty thereof. The Tories are somewhat high in <em>Ireland</em>, and some distempers are brake forth; but the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em> is safely arrived to put a period to those Distractions.</p>

<p>The English Fleet remains still about St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg></em> point by the Isle of Wight, and the Merchant men are all gone from <em>Dover</em> Road toward <em>France</em>, and other parts. Our men of War <reg orig="playes">plays</reg> the Rex upon the Narrow seas; but the Hectors in <em>Kent</em> proceed on most inhumanely killing, robbing, and destroying all that comes <reg orig="neer">near</reg> them.</p>

<p>O Yes, O yes, O yes, These are to give notice unto all whom it may concern, That in Glamorgan-shire there is a young man in love with a Widow that hath had two bastards by her last <reg orig="husbands">husband's</reg> son before he <reg orig="marryed">married</reg> her, and two more in the time that she was his wife.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>