<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost152">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 152</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">Great <reg orig="Brittain's">Britain's</reg></head>
<head level="1">POST</head>
<head level="3">Impartially communicating</head>

<p><i>A Declaration of his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em> of England and his honourable Council, concerning the establishing the Government of this Commonwealth; Together with the Articles signed by his Highness when he was invested <em>Lord Protector</em>, on Friday the 16 of December. Also the Proceedings of the States of <em>Holland</em>, and their great preparations against <em>England</em>. The landing of Money, <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and Ammunition in <em>Scotland</em>, and the <em>Scots</em> resolution to fall into the Borders of <em>England</em>. Together with the taking of divers ships from the Dutch, laden with Pitch, <reg orig="Tarre">Tar</reg>, and other <unclear>last</unclear> land Commodities.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From Wednesday Decem. 21. to Wednesday Decemb. 28. 1653</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for G. HORTON.</p>

<p>The Western Letters <reg orig="specifie">specify</reg>, That the Dutch are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> in those parts, insomuch, that it is very hard for any Vessel to pass by the Lands-End without a good Convoy; and they have lately taken a Ship of London coming from New England, Laden with Masts, <reg orig="Bever">Beaver</reg> skins, and the like commodities. But in retaliation thereof, a private Man of War hath brought <pb n="1" />Dutch Vessels into the Holy Island, both being about 150 <reg orig="Tuns">Tons</reg> <reg orig="burthen">burden</reg>, which were taken coming from the East-country, laden with <em>Pitch, <reg orig="Tarre">Tar</reg></em>, and other useful commodities.</p>

<p>Having in my last communicated the manner of the <reg orig="solemnization">solemnisation</reg> at the Investment of His Highness the Lord Protector, the next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view, is, the same and constitution of the Government established; a Copy whereof is here briefly inserted.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Articles Signed by His Highness <em>Oliver <reg orig="Cromwel">Cromwell</reg></em>, Lord Protector of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, on Friday the 16 of December, 1653.</i></head>

<p>1 That the <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Legislative power of <em>England, Scotland</em> and <em>Ireland</em>, shall be and reside, in one single person, assisted with a <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> of 13 at least, and 21 at most, and the Commons assembled in Parliament.</p>

<p>2 That this single person shall be called, <em>The Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland and Ireland.</em></p>

<p>3 That there be constant Triennial Parliaments, and the first to begin on the 3. of <em>September</em> next, 1654. and so from 3 years to 3 years.</p>

<p>4 That Parliaments shall be chosen by the people, and that the time of their sitting be for five months.</p>

<p>5 That the <em>Parliament</em> shall have power of making all Laws, saving some cases relating to the Guards of the <reg orig="common-wealth">commonwealth</reg>, and Matters of Religion (for which there is particular provision made in the Instrument) containing the Government.</p>

<p>6 That such Laws as shall be agreed on in <em>Parliament</em>, shall be pretended to the Lord protector for his assent, which if he do not consent unto within 20 days, shall notwithstanding <pb n="2" />become a Law, and stand in full force and <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg>; provided, they contain nothing contrary to the Matters expressed in the said Instrument.</p>

<p>7 That all Writs, <reg orig="processe">process</reg>, &amp;c. shall issue forth in the name of the Lord protector.</p>

<p>8 That the Ministry of the Gospel <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> be maintained and the present way of their maintenance continued, till some other way more convenient shall be found out and provided.</p>

<p>9 That Articles of War shall be made good.</p>

<p>10 That the Lord protector is to be Elective, and not Hereditary, and to be chosen by the Council, <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> upon the death of the Lord protector, &amp;c.</p>

<head level="3">An Advertisement</head>

<p><i>ALL persons who are Adventurers for lands in <em>Ireland</em>, are desired to take notice, That the committee for claims for lands on Thursday the 12 of Jan. next coming to be a day of lottery at <em><reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall London</em>, for provinces and counties; and Thursday the 19 of Jan. to be a lottery for counties, for all such Adventurers who have made their choice in provinces; and after the said 19 of <em>Jan.</em> the said committee intend to fit three mornings in a week, <em>viz.</em> Tuesdays, Thursdays, and Saturdays, for preparing certificates for such Adventurers as have, or <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> by this time draw their lots.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>The Copy a Letter from Scotland.</i></head>

<p>SIR <i>On the 10 instant Cap. <em>Lisle</em> of col. <em>Riches</em> Regiment hearing of a party of the enemy about 10 miles from his quarters, marched in the night from <em>Monros</em> with <unclear>100</unclear> Horse and Dragoons, and fell upon them by break of day near <unclear><em><reg orig="Glams">Glamis</reg></em></unclear>, took 40 horse, 19 private <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, two captains of horse, one Cornet, one Quartermaster, and killed 9 or 10 of them. The next day col. <em>Morgan</em> having notice of a party <pb n="3" />of them in Eghil, a strong house in <em>Angus</em> near the <reg orig="hils">hills</reg>, marched towards it; but the enemy having notice, fled away upon his approach; he turned and took 15 horses; but the Lord <em>Kinoul</em>; and col. <em>Ramsey</em> escaped. They increase daily, and are gone Northwards to receive arms lately landed from Holland. But at their return, we took some of their Bobtails <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Aberdeen</em>.</i></p>

<p><i>A party of Maj. Gen. <reg orig="Harrisons">Harrison's</reg> Regiment were at the heels of col. <em>Wogan</em> and those that came with him at <em>Kelsith</em>; but they gave them the run, and got safe to the Mountains. It is supposed, that he and some others landed in <em>Lancashire</em>; and have commissions and Instructions from their Master <em>Charles Stuart</em>.</i></p>

<p>Dalkeith Decemb. 17. 1653.</p>

<head level="3">By the Lord Protector</head>

<p>&para; <i>A PROCLAMATION of his Highness, with the consent of his Council, for the continuing of all Persons, being in Office for the Execution of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice at the time of the late change of Government, until his <reg orig="Highness">Highness'</reg> further Direction.</i></p>

<p>OLIVER, Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, considering that whereas the exercise of the chief Magistracy, and the administration of Government within the said Commonwealth, is invested and established in his Highness, assisted with a Council, and left thereupon the <reg orig="setled">settled</reg> and ordinary course of Justice in the Commonwealth (if remedy were not provided) might receive interruption, hid Highness in his care of the State, and <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice thereof (reserving to future consideration the reformation and redress of any abuses of <reg orig="Mis-government">Misgovernment</reg>, upon better knowledge taken thereof is pleased, and doth hereby <reg orig="expresly">expressly</reg> <reg orig="signifie">signify</reg>, declare and ordain, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, who have power until <pb n="4" />the meeting of the next Parliament, to make <reg orig="Lawes">Laws</reg> and Ordinances for the peace and welfare of these Nations, where it shall be necessary; which shall be binding and in force until Order shall be taken in Parliament concerning the same: That all persons who on the tenth day of this instant December were duly and lawfully possessed of any place of Judicature, or Office of Authority, Jurisdiction or Government, within this Commonwealth, shall be, and shall so hold themselves continued in the said Offices and places respectively as formerly they held and enjoyed the same, and not otherwise, until his Highness pleasure be further known; And all Commissions, Patents, and other Grants, which respect or relate unto the doing and executing of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Justice, and all proceedings of what Nature soever, in Courts of common Law, or Equity, or in the court of Admiralty, or by commissioners of Sewers, shall stand and be in the same and like force to all intents and purposes as the same were on the said tenth day of this instant December, until further order given by his Highness therein. And that in the <reg orig="mean time">meantime</reg> (for preservation of the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> peace, and necessary proceedings in matters of Justice, and for safety of the State) all the said persons, of whatsoever place, Degree, or condition, may not fail every one severally according to his respective place, Office or charge, to proceed in the performance and execution of all duties thereunto belonging, as formerly appertained to them and every of them <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> the former Government was in being.</p>

<p><i>Given at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> this 21 of December, in the Year of Our <em>Lord</em>, 1653.</i></p>

<p><em>Kenmore</em> endeavours to raise men and monies in the South, with whom he resolves to make inroads into the borders of <em>England</em>, and the new Levies are gone into the North, to receive monies, arms and ammunition, which <unclear>they</unclear> say was sent from their King.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<head level="3">A List of the Names of his Highness the Lord <i><reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Council</i>.</head>

<p>Major Gen. <em>Lambert,</em></p>

<p>Lord Viscount <em>Lisle,</em></p>

<p>General <em>Disborow</em></p>

<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Skippon,</em></p>

<p>Sir <em>Anthony-Ashley Cooper,</em></p>

<p>Mr. <em>Strickland</em></p>

<p>Sir <em>Gilb. Pickering,</em></p>

<p>Sir <em>Charles Woolsley</em>,</p>

<p>col. <em>Sydenham</em>,</p>

<p>col. <em>Jones</em>,</p>

<p>col. <em>Montogue</em>,</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Rous</em>,</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Major</em>,</p>

<p>Mr. <em>Lawrence</em> President.</p>

<p>On the 22 instant, His Highness the Lord Protector <reg orig="sate">sat</reg> with the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> above named, in the Council chamber at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, and several things were transacted in order to a quiet and peaceable settlement of the three Nations: After which, his Highness, in a sweet speech, pressed them to act for God, and the peace and good of the Nations; and particularly recommended to them, to consider and relieve the distresses of the poor and oppressed. So that we have great cause abundantly to bless for this new <em>Change of Government</em>.</p>

<p>By an Express from the fleet it is certified, That Gen. <em>Monk</em> is at S. <em><reg orig="Ellins">Ellin's</reg></em> Road with 30 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, &amp; has sent out his <em>Scouts</em>, who have brought in several prizes: the <em>Dutch</em> have also taken some English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> Ships; and are very <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the West of England.</p>

<pb n="6" />

<head level="3"><i>A true <reg orig="Narratime">Narrative</reg> of the Cause and Manner of the dissolution of the late Parliament, Decemb. 12. 1653.</i></head>

<p>On Friday the 12 of December, 1653. Very many persons came an hour and more sooner to the House <reg orig="then">than</reg> was usual, which was the first apprehension that was taken of <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> to be done; but by that, something more <reg orig="then">than</reg> ordinary was conceived would be attempted: The Speaker taking the Chair, a Member made his address to him to this effect, <i>That he must <reg orig="disburthen">disburden</reg> himself of some things that had a long time lain upon his heart; That he was now to speak to the (Esse) or <reg orig="beeing">being</reg>, rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> the (bene esse, or) wellbeing of the Commonwealth, which was ready to sink under us, through the ill management of the power betrusted with us and that for his own part he must resign his power from whence he had it, <reg orig="fore">for</reg> seeing clearly that their waitings and expectations or ever coming on to things of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> good, were more and more disappointed;</i> and so came to these particular instances:</p>

<p>1 <i>That we had dealt disingenuously with the Army, in moving that the Officers should be treated with to lay down their pay; and when we could not effect that, the Bill of Assessments was endeavoured to be cast out.</i></p>

<p>2 <i>That we had not a spirit to do justice, which appeared in our Act for confirming the sale of Sir <em>John <reg orig="Stowels">Stowel's</reg></em> estate, though he were relieved by the Court of Articles. And that however he was as <reg orig="vild">wild</reg> as could be imagined (<em>so was his expression)</em> yet he knew not but that man was left to be as a <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> upon us whether we could do justice <unclear>or</unclear> not.</i></p>

<p>3 <i>That we had a principle of destroying and pulling down amongst us, though nothing were set up in the stead; and this was especially manifested in our Vote for removing the Chancery, and total alteration of the Laws.</i></p>

<p>4 <i>That though we called <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> a Parliament, yet we acted most unlike to it: and that appeared in our endeavours to destroy Propriety, in attempting to take off the power of <unclear>Patrons</unclear> to preserve Church-livings.</i></p>

<p>5 <i>That we would destroy the Ministry <reg orig="it self">itself</reg>, which appeared by our Vote upon Saturday last. For these considerations they could no <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> themselves to sit any longer, and so be guilty of bringing confusion and desolation upon the Nation. But if any would yet be so hardy as to continue there, he would say unto them in the words of the Prophet; <em>Ephraim</em> hath <reg orig="joyned">joined</reg> himself to Idols, let him alone.</i></p>

<p>This was seconded by two others, who interwove their speeches with some <unclear>bitter</unclear> invectives, which was heard with patience (and <pb n="7" />shall not be here inserted.) After that, another member stood up and declaring himself to speak with much disadvantage, in that he had not as the other, any premeditated thing to say; but he told the Speaker he had in his hand an Expedient in reference to the things comprehended in the Vote on Saturday last, that he hoped would <reg orig="satisfie">satisfy</reg> all; and that the Committee for regulating the Law had ready to be offered the House Bills of very great concernment, to the good and ease of the people, and protested before God, Angels, and men, his dissatisfaction to the thing moved, as being destructive to the Commonwealth. Others standing up to second him, could not be suffered to speak: But some others pressing the former motion, saying <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, it was not now a time to debate. The Speaker being of their judgement (the whole business being before contrived) without putting it to the Question, or adjourning to any other place, left the Chair, and went hastily out of the House with them: some 30 and odd <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> within, who mutually declaring that they had protest in the presence of the Lord, that they were called of God to that place, which was the principal motive that drew them thither; and <unclear>that</unclear> they apprehended their said Call was chiefly for promoting the interest of Jesus Christ. Beginning therefore to <unclear>consider</unclear> what to do Col. <em>Goff</em>, and Lieu.col. <em>White</em> came in and entreated them earnestly to go out, pressing it often. It was as earnestly <reg orig="replyed">replied</reg> to them, that at their personal Request they could not; but desired them to withdraw, unless they had command to put them forth: which when they perceived, they commanded in some <reg orig="Musqueteers">Musketeers</reg>; upon which they withdrew. <i>Thus much in brief.</i></p>

<p>From Holland 'tis certified that the people murmur very much that the Treaty holds so long with England, and fear nothing will come of it. Others there are (though but few) who are good Patriots, and desire an Union with England, as the greatest Interest of <unclear>their</unclear> Country, but can do nothing, because over-<reg orig="powred">powered</reg> in all their <reg orig="Councels">Councils</reg>. They are making great preparations against Spring, and 30 new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> are now upon the stocks, to be added to the former 30 already built; they say their fleet will consist of above 100 sail, and <unclear><em>Tromp</em></unclear> is ordered to go into the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em> with 12 Men of War to <unclear>secure</unclear> their Traders in those parts.</p>

<p>The Lord <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> <em>Whitlock</em> arrived at <reg orig="Gottenbergh">Gothenburg</reg> the 15 of Nov. and was nobly <reg orig="entertain'd">entertained</reg> by the Citizens; from whence he sent <unclear>Letters</unclear> to Court, and waits there for an answer.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>