<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost179">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 179</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Weekly</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The great and bloody Plot discovered against his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, and his Council; the taking of divers of the Conspirators and chief Actors, their Examination and Confession before the Lords of the Council on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last; the passing of an Order for committing them to the Tower of London; and the manner how they should have killed the Lord Protector, <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the Council, and put all to the sword that should have stood in opposition against them, The rising of the Royal party in Holland, the <reg orig="rendevouzing">rendezvousing</reg> of the Dutch Army, against the States, by Count William of Nassaw, and Gen Oxenstern to land in England. A great Victory obtained in Scotland; the particulars of that lamentable Engagement, the number killed, Col. Middleton taken, and divers executed.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> the 16. of <em>May</em>, to <em>Tuesday</em> the 24 of <em>May</em>, 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G, Horton</em>, <i>for information of the <em>People</em></i>.</p>
<hr />

<p>The Messenger which was <reg orig="imployed">employed</reg> to carry the <em>Habeas Corpus</em> to Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em> (prisoner in the Isle of <em>Jersey</em>) is returned, and <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, <i>That he is well, and in health, <em>blessed be God</em>; but the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> (Col. <em>Haynes</em>) refused (as by Law he might) to return him back to the Upper Bench, upon sight of the first <em>Habeas Corpus</em>; but <reg orig="its">it's</reg> probable, that upon the second or third, it will be granted, by reason that it is the undeniable right of every <reg orig="English-man">Englishman</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Mr. <em>Feak</em> and Mr. <em>Simpson</em> are also well and in health: <i>The Lord work a deliverance for all poor Captives.</i></p>

<pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>The Declaration of General <em>Monk</em>.</i></head>

<p><i>The Commonwealth of <em>England</em> having used all means of tenderness &amp; affection towards the people of this Nation, by receiving them (after a <reg orig="chargable">chargeable</reg> and bloody war) into union with <em>England</em>, and investing them with all the liberties and <reg orig="priviledges">privileges</reg> thereof (purchased at the <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of so much blood and treasure) and by daily protecting them with their Army and Navy, at a great charge against their enemies both abroad and at home, that so they might enjoy the fruits and benefits of peace; yet divers <reg orig="leud">lewd</reg> persons broken in their fortunes, and dissolute in their lives, are run into Rebellion; for prevention whereof, I, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the Authority given unto me by his Highness and his Council, do declare, That all such persons that are now in rebellion (except such as are excepted in the Acts of Grace) who shall within 20 <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> after the publication hereof, come in, and submit him, or themselves, to the Governor of the next English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, and give good security for his or their future peaceable living, shall be, and is hereby in his and their persons, freely pardoned for any offence, spoil, or plunders, committed by him or them in this present Rebellion (the killing of any person in cold blood <reg orig="onely">only</reg> excepted.) And in regard this present Rebellion hath been principally contrived, fomented, and is now obstinately maintained by Maj. Gen. <em>Middleton</em>, the E. of <em>Seaforth</em>, Viscount <em>Kenmore</em>, Maj. Gen. <em>Dayel</em>, Laird <em>Glengary</em>, Laird <em>MacDonald</em>; I do hereby therefore declare, that what person or persons soever of this Nation (except such as are before excepted) shall kill any of the said principal contrivers, or shall deliver any of them prisoner to any Governor of any English <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>, the said person or persons so killing, or bringing prisoner shall not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> be pardoned for <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> he or they have acted in this late rebellion, but also <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> receive as a reward of his good service, the sum of 200 li. sterling, for every person so <reg orig="kild">killed</reg> or brought prisoner, as aforesaid.</i> Given under my hand at Dalkieth this 4 day of May, 1654.</p>

<p>GEORGE MONK</p>

<head level="3"><i>Westminster the 16.</i></head>

<p>Came lamentable news from the West; signifying, That the <em>Brest</em> men of war have taken three ships coming from <em>Dublin</em> to <em>Liverpool</em> and <em>Chester</em>, as also a <em>Bristol</em> ship; And a Bark coming from <em>Diep</em> to <em>Rye</em>, in which was many passengers, was set upon by an <em>Ostend</em> man of war and after a <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> conflict, she was sunk, only most of the passengers were saved, but 7 of the <em>Ostend</em> men were slain. They have taken two more in the Western channel; and we have taken 7 <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the Lands-end; <pb n="2" /><i>Ha, ha, let them laugh that wins</i>; For I can assure you, there is nothing yet concluded in the Treaty with the <em>French</em> Ambassador; so tender is his Excellency of the honour and preservation of <em><reg orig="Englands">England's</reg></em> Interest, that we may expect Tribute, and satisfaction for the horrid massacre of the Protestants, and the Isle of <em>Ree</em> business. On the last <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day there preached before the Protector in <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> learned Dr <em>Horton</em>, where his Highness writ down the Sermon, and desires it may be a general practice throughout the Nations. <i>Excellent graces, in so pious a Prince, and not to be <reg orig="paralleld">paralleled</reg> throughout all Europe.</i></p>

<p>Gen. <em>Blake</em> being come from the fleet to <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, dined this day with his Highness, and the lord Mayor, and divers members of the Council, were present. At which time, col. <em>Venables</em>, and col. <em>Ingoldsby</em>, presented their Addresses from the Council in <em>Ireland</em>, by way of <em>congratulation</em>, and owning the present Government.</p>

<p>The Committee met about the Law, but find it a hard work to alter the old channel; but it is believed something will be dispatched about a fortnight hence for the Committee at Salters Hall to act by. In the interim, an Ordinance is passed for relief of the poor creditors in <em>Scotland</em>. Mr. <em>John Lilburn</em> has received his <em>Habeas Corpus</em> from the Upper Bench, and desires to be brought thither; which we hope <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be granted.</p>

<p>The Writs of his Highness the Lord Protector are preparing against the time they are to issue forth, for the calling of a Parliament, according to the Instrument of the Government of the Commonwealth of <em>England</em>; <i>so that 'tis hoped we shall then receive the full fruition of our long promised liberty.</i></p>

<p>His Highness hath <reg orig="past">passed</reg> an Ordinance for the Courts that use to be kept in <em>Chester</em> city, to be kept at <em><reg orig="North-wich">Northwich</reg></em>, during the time of the Sickness being in <em>Chester</em> city.</p>

<p>The Emperor of <em>Germany</em> has sent Propositions to the States of <em><reg orig="Bohemiah">Bohemia</reg></em>, conjuring them, 1 That they use their utmost <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> for propagating of the Romish <reg orig="Catholick">Catholic</reg> Religion. 2 That they celebrate the Feast of St. <em>Joseph</em> as the rest of the Patrons of the Kingdom use to do. 3 That they pay a considerable sum to the Emperor.</p>

<p>It is confirmed from, <em>Brazil</em>, that the <em>Hollanders</em> are almost totally banished from those parts; and are <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> threatened in other places. The last news from <em>Scotland</em> <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg>, That the Royal party grow numerous, and that they spake themselves to be above 11000 <pb n="3" />at the last <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, being resolved to fight us; which is <reg orig="extreamly">extremely</reg> desired by the merry Redcoats: so that by our next, no doubt but you will hear of action.</p>

<p>From <em>Guernsey</em> they write, That the <em>Hector</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> attending without St. <em>Mallows</em> divers <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> for conveying the English from thence who are still detained under the arrest, a Shallop was sent out of the Town to tell the Captain that the English should have all freedom; but this was found to be <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> a Decoy, to draw him in, and so not trusted.</p>

<p>For, we hear, that two of our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg> are seized upon, and that upon the going of 60 of our men ashore for fresh victuals, endeavoured to drive away some cattle; but the country receiving the <reg orig="allarm">alarm</reg>, rescued the cattle, fell upon our men, and <reg orig="kill'd">killed</reg>, wounded, and took above 30, pursuing the rest to the ships, two of which were stranded upon going forth of the Tide: whereupon the great Guns were brought from St. <em>Mallows</em>, to batter the ships, which they did begin to do; but the Tide coming in, the ships got off without any great hurt. The <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> apprehending this to be a design against the Town, took an occasion to turn out all the English Merchants, and to seize upon all their Goods in the Warehouses, and hath got all for the present in his own custody. Complaints hath been made hereof, and the French Ambassador hath had audience, so that the business is under examination.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassador <em>Whitlock</em> is arrived at <em>Lubeck</em>: The Queen of <em>Sweden</em> will certainly resign the Crown to her kinsman <em>Carolus Adolphus</em>; his brother Prince <em>John Adolphus</em> having laid down his Patent of the Lord High Marshal of <em>Sweden</em>, is gone to Stockholm, to confer with his elder brother, who will be shortly invested with the Royal Dignity.</p>

<p>Gen. <em>Oxenstern</em> is appointed to go as an Ambassador into <em>England</em> with a great Retinue, and a gallant Train both by Sea and Land are expediting forth.</p>

<p>The Hollanders do already begin to find the benefit of the peace with England; and about 20 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> are come into the River of <em>Thames</em> with great store of cheese and <reg orig="Linnen">Linen</reg>.</p>

<p>Divers Colliers are likewise safely arrived, and the great fleet is suddenly expected.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Pickeroons">Picaroons</reg> in the Western seas are as bold, and as <reg orig="busie">busy</reg>, as ever <pb n="4" />but dare not adventure Easterly, where Gen. <em>Pen</em> <reg orig="lyes">lies</reg> with the Fleet in the Downs, in a gallant <reg orig="Equippage">Equipage</reg>. And the next main design 'tis though will be to help the Venetians against the great Turk, for that he is the common enemy of all Christendom; and as he is making of himself stronger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, so doth he <reg orig="shew">show</reg> himself more insolent <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever, and hath <reg orig="clapt">clapped</reg> the Venetian Ambassador in close prison, not so much as <reg orig="rendring">rendering</reg> a reason for it, or intending to have any further Treaty or capitulation with the Duke of <em>Venice</em>.</p>

<p>This week the Packet Boat coming for England from beyond sea, was taken by the <reg orig="out lying">outlying</reg> <reg orig="Pyrates">Pirates</reg> abroad: some of the English passengers were drowned, and those that were saved were <reg orig="stript">stripped</reg> to the skin; but the next morning the Master, one woman, and two more, had pieces of broken <reg orig="sayls">sails</reg> given them to cover their nakedness, and put in an old Cock-Boat to shift for themselves.</p>

<p>&#x261e; There was a man most barbarously murdered in the last week, and being cut to pieces, was put into a bag, and thrown into a Ditch not far from <i>Paddingtom, (the ready Road to Tyburn)</i> he was so <reg orig="mortifi'd">mortified</reg> and dismembered, that none can make a discovery what he is; for not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> his head and nose were separated from his body, but his hands arms, legs, and thighs, were also cut off: This was done by one man and a woman, who falling out in Turnball street on Saturday night last, she discovered him, and <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> he was apprehended and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> before a Justice, who asked him, how he could find in his heart to commit so unmerciless and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> an act, he made answer, <i>Pish, Justice Ass, that's a thing of nothing, I could serve you so, if I had you in place where.</i></p>

<p>&#x261e; On Saturday last there was a great Plot discovered against his Highness the Lord protector and his Council, and many of the Conspirators being examined on the <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> following, before the council, and Order passed for their restraint, &amp; accordingly they were committed to the Tower, as intending to be Actors, the <em>Plot</em> being <reg orig="contriv'd">contrived</reg> in <em>France</em>, and so to have taken away the life of his Highness the Lord Protector, and to have <reg orig="murthered">murdered</reg> the council, and to have massacred all those that should have stood in opposition against them: Nay, this was not all; but their Design was wholly to subdue, extirpate, and break asunder, those Chains of Mercies, and <reg orig="Linkes">Links</reg> of Liberties, so long contended for, and at last happily effected, though with the loss and <reg orig="expence">expense</reg> of the <reg orig="bloud">blood</reg> of many thousand Saints.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That since the concluding of a peace there hath been great discontents; and that the Princess Dowager, the Princess Royal, and the rest of the family of Nassaw, have presented a Declaration to the States General, bemoaning and applying their condition as sad by the late Articles of peace with England; and the very women have <reg orig="address'd">addressed</reg> themselves in the <reg orig="Princes">Prince's</reg> behalf, wringing their hands, and crying out, <i>Ah! poor Prince, what hast thou done that thou shouldst be thus used? Ah poor Child! What a sad condition art thou in?</i> and the like penetrate expressions; whereupon, <reg orig="its">it's</reg> conceived, the States will have compassion on them, and permit them to live peaceably, if they please. The great Duke of <em>Muscovy</em> has sent as <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg> to the Hague, demanding Officers and warlike Ammunition: from thence he goes to <em>France</em>, where the whole <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> have received special commandment from their <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg> Lord the King to be all in arms.</p>

<head level="3"><i>Dover the 18. instant.</i></head>

<p>There are sundry <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> making ready at Rochel, and at several other places in <em>France</em>, where abundance of provisions are making for War, and most of the Garrisons are <reg orig="re-inforced">reinforced</reg> and filled with <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, and their Castles and Magazines <reg orig="supplyed">supplied</reg> with plenty of Ammunition. Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em> hath issued forth <em>Orders</em> for drawing sown the Army towards the sea coast, where they have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="intrench'd">entrenched</reg> themselves, and raised great <em>Batteries</em>, but also planted above one hundred pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>; and expect nothing more <reg orig="then">than</reg> a sudden war.</p>

<p>His Majesty hath sent new Propositions to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, &amp; desires an Agreement. Notwithstanding great Levies are raising in all his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Dominions, and Marshal <em>Thurene</em>, and the Duke of <em>York</em>, are to command a potent Army in <em>Flanders</em>. The D. of <em>Joycuse</em> is to be Lieu. Gen. of the Horse, and Duke <em>Bellieure</em> Lieu. Gen. of the Foot. The Duke of <em>Guise</em> goes General of the fleet, and the L. <em>Pimontelly</em> Vice Admiral, they are to <reg orig="rendevouz">rendezvous</reg> <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em>Rochel</em>, and so to strike sail (as one <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> body) for <reg orig="cleering">clearing</reg> of the coast of <em>Campaigne, Brittany</em> and other places, <i>if they can.</i></p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> further thus: Here is arrived a Messenger from Scotland, which <reg orig="sweaks">speaks</reg> of a great Victory obtained against the English, and glorying very much at G. <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> <reg orig="successe">success</reg> since his going thither. <pb n="6" />Whereupon <reg orig="tis">'tis</reg> said, that the K. of Scots, and his brother <em>James</em>, intends suddenly to leave <em>France</em>.</p>

<p>By the last Express from <em>Scotland</em>, thus: We conceive the Enemy is drawing to their great <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg> in the <em>Highlands</em>, we have lately been grievously plagued with their inroads upon the Lowlands, where they burnt and destroyed all that stood before them <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Dumfriez">Dumfries</reg></em>, and other places; the reason of their mischiefs and our <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> is want of intelligence from amongst them; for if we should hang up a hundred of them that we take, we should scarce <reg orig="squeez">squeeze</reg> ten true words out of them. Gen. <em>Middleton</em> we hear hath made his way out of <em>Southerland</em>, where col. <em>Morgan</em> thought to have <reg orig="ingaged">engaged</reg> his horse, but it proved not feasible; for indeed we have an enemy as subtle as resolute, and they play fast and loose with us in places of advantage; they expect the Duke of <em><reg orig="Yorks">York's</reg></em> coming to them, and their thoughts extend so far, that there will then be a general Rising of the people.</p>

<p>From <em>Paris</em> it is certified, That the <em>Portugal</em> Ambassador has received audience of his Majesty, to whom he imparted the joyful <reg orig="Tydings">Tidings</reg> of a Victory obtained by the <em>Portugal</em> fleet against the <em>Hollanders</em> in <em><reg orig="Brasil">Brazil</reg></em>; and of the taking of <em>Reclif</em>, and about 40 other Towns and Castles from them. Which doth not a little <reg orig="rejoyce">rejoice</reg> the Royal Family: <i>Win gold, and wear it; 'tis fit <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> should have their own.</i> Upon a delicate Banquet between the King and Queen, on the 3 of May, the K of <em>Scots</em>, and his afflicted Mother were both invited, in whose presence, his Maj. danced the great <em>Ballet</em>; but young <em>Charles</em> exceeds him far in the Italian Comedy. Propositions are preparing to be sent to the K of <em>Spain</em> for a ten years Truce.</p>

<p>There hath been a great plot discovered against the English in <em>Virginia</em>, by an <em>Indian</em>, who being privy to the design of the Natives, repaired to the Governor, unfolded the business, and told him that upon the 4 of this instant May, there was a conspiracy to fall upon the English, and stab and cut the throats of all in general, both men, women, and children. Whereupon the Governor <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> called a council; and forthwith secured the chief Actors, hanging up divers in several places. <i>A just Reward for so detestable Miscreants; and nothing but a halter can <unclear>reclaim</unclear> them.</i></p>

<p>Gen. <em>Monk</em> hath sent a Letter to his Highness the Lord Protector, whereby he signified, That he was advanced beyond <em><reg orig="Sterling">Stirling</reg></em> toward the Highlanders, from whence he intends, after securing of some few <pb n="7" />passes, to take the field. In the interim, col. <em>Lilburn</em> hath performed a singular piece of service, by <reg orig="ingaging">engaging</reg> col. <em>Middleton</em> (brother to Gen. <em>Middleton</em>) and after a sharp Dispute, took prisoner this valiant <em><reg orig="Heroe">Hero</reg></em> and divers other Commanders, routed the whole party (<i>but they were not many</i>) and pursued them towards <em>Caithness</em>, making good their Retreat, with little loss.</p>

<p>Col. <em>Morgan</em> is about <em>Tane</em>, watching opportunities to engage them, and the Highlanders are preparing to receive them; having fortified several passes, and made them inaccessible. Gen. <em>Monk</em> hath caused two Gentlemen to be <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> as <reg orig="Spyes">Spies</reg>, burnt the Inn at <em>Muscleborough</em> that harboured them, and erected a <reg orig="Gibbit">Gibbet</reg> in the same place.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Copy of a Letter from Amsterdam.</i></head>

<p>SIR,</p>

<p><i>Great are the discontents in these parts by the house of <em>William</em> of <em>Nassaw</em>, and all that are that way <reg orig="allyed">allied</reg> or affected, declare, that they knew not but of one or two of the Articles of peace till they were concluded and published; and therefore determinate, to set the Royal Bellows at work, to blew new Embers, and kindle a consummating fire within the bowels of both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>; in order whereunto, Count <em>William</em> is calling his Army to a general <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>, and declares very high for the Royal Interest: so that we are constrained to keep very strong Guards, both here and at other places, and do expect new Commotions to be had very suddenly; very high words they give forth, in behalf of the young Prince of <em>Orange</em>, yet they seem rather to proceed from abundance of affection, <reg orig="then">than</reg> judgement, valour, or anything that may add life, nerves, and sinews to a new war. Upon the beating up of Drums both here, and in France, the discontented persons come in, and list themselves voluntarily, and, if Report speaks truth, many are sent from thence into Scotland. We hear that the foreign Ambassadors have had audience with Cardinal <em>Mazarine</em>, in order to the carrying on of a general peace. The Prince of Conde hath had new Propositions sent to him for an agreement since his effigies were hanged up in Paris; and his brother Conti, who is now in great favour, <reg orig="indeavors">endeavours</reg> to be an effectual Mediator between his brother and the Court, who have a sum of money for the King of Scots, but the pittance was so small, that he is like to have occasion (poor Gentlemen) to make new addresses for more before he can get of that <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>.</i></p>

<p>Amsterdam, May 19, 1654.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>