<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost164">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 164</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2"><i>The Grand Politique</i></head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Agreement of the high and mighty States of the United Provinces, with his Highness the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland; and their ratifying, confirming, signing, and sealing of the Articles for Peace. With their electing of the Lord High Admiral Opdam to be sent to his Highness. The k. of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> letter to the Highlanders, &amp; their proceedings with fire &amp; sword against the Lowlanders. The rising of the Tories in Ireland, and the sending of an Ambassador from the King of France to the Lord Protector in England. The advancing of the Royal <reg orig="Iames">James</reg> from Brest, and a List of the Names of the new ships <reg orig="commission'd">commissioned</reg> by the King of Scots, with sundry other remarkable Occurrences, from Denmark, Sweden, and the Netherlands.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 7. to <em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 15. 1654</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>The Highlanders are very much exasperated near the Land of <reg orig="Gyants">Giants</reg>, and have proceeded with fire and Sword against the Lowlanders, in Murray-land. They have assaulted Sir Peter <reg orig="Hayes">Hayes's</reg> house called Meginch, but were forced to retire after a <reg orig="smal">small</reg> dispute. Since which time, a strong Party of horse have been in Gowry, and have burnt abundance of Corn, making great devastation upon the Earl of Lithgow.</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>The Lord Mayor and Aldermen of London having invited His Highness the Lord Protector to dinner at <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall, the several Companies of the City had (this day) Order from the Lord <reg orig="Major">Mayor</reg> to meet at <reg orig="Guild-hall">Guildhall</reg> in their Gowns, and from thence to place themselves according to their superiority in the streets, from the lower end of Cheapside even to Temple-Bar, to attend the coming in of so great and honourable a Personage; as appeared by the high &amp; mighty preparations, fit for the greatest Prince of Potentate; for the streets were <reg orig="rais'd">raised</reg>, as in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of the Kings; and the Rails were all hung with blew Cloth: The City Banners, and the Golden Streamers and Standards were all placed along the said <reg orig="Railes">Rails</reg> in a most delicate and stately manner. The which being erected and set up, the Lord Mayor, with the Mace, Sword, and Cap of Maintenance, and the <reg orig="dermen">Aldermen</reg> in their Scarlet Gowns, rode as far as Temple-Bar, where they met his Highness and all his magnificent Train: And his Highness had the Sword delivered to him by the Lord Mayor, which was returned again; and after a short Oration, in congratulation of his Highness, so soon as He came out of His Coach, the manner of this great <reg orig="Solemnization">Solemnisation</reg> was as followeth: First came the City Marshal and some other Officers; then six Trumpeters, with his <reg orig="Highnesses">Highness's</reg> <reg orig="Life-guard">Lifeguard</reg>; then eight Trumpets more, with the City Streamers, red and white; then the Aldermen in their Scarlet Gowns: Next after them the two Sheriffs, and their Officers; then the Heralds of Arms with rich Coats, adorned with the <reg orig="Commonwealths">Commonwealth's</reg> Arms, <em>viz.</em> the Cross and Harp; then the Golden Mace and Cap of Maintenance: After which, came the Lord Mayor bare headed, carrying the Sword; next after, rode two Gentlemen bare before his Highness; with whom went twelve of his foot-men, in <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> coats, and silver and black silk Lace: His Highness had a very rich coat <reg orig="embroyder'd">embroidered</reg> with gold and a gold <reg orig="Hatbond">Hatband</reg>, who in the height of this <reg orig="Magnificiency">Magnificence</reg> <reg orig="shewed">showed</reg> abundance of humility to the people, moving his hat continually unto them all along the streets. After his Highness, came Major General <em>Skippon</em>, and the rest of his <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> Council: then the Officers of the Army, with renowned col. <em>Pride</em>, who was as plain as a <reg orig="Pike-staff">Pikestaff</reg> in a <reg orig="gray">grey</reg> short coat: Then after them, divers Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, in a most excellent equipage, both on horseback and in <pb n="2" />Coaches. And coming to <reg orig="Grocers">Grocer's</reg> Hall, the Recorder made a Speech to his Highness, letting him understand, how happy the city were in the enjoyment of his Person. After he had done, his Highness having retired himself a while above <reg orig="staires">stairs</reg>, came down to dine in the great Hall, where he sat in the middle of a long Table, his Son the Lord <em>Henry</em> on the left hand, and the Lord Mayor on the right; &amp; on each side of them the Council, with Gen. <em>Monk</em>, Commis. Gen. <em>Whaley</em>, &amp; Mr. <em>Claypool</em>, master of the horse to his Highness, being entertained (besides rare <reg orig="Chear">Cheer</reg>, and delicate Dainties) with <reg orig="musick">music</reg>, <reg orig="Voyces">Voices</reg>, Drums, and Trumpets. After this, his Highness was conducted upstairs again, by the Lord Mayor, to a noble Banquet. This being done, his <reg orig="Highnes">Highness</reg> departed being <reg orig="plaid">played</reg> out by <reg orig="Hoboys">Oboes</reg>, and other loud <reg orig="musick">music</reg>. In all which, this famous city hath by these solemn expressions of affection given a <em>good</em> example to the rest of the Nation. I wish we may enjoy benefit under his protection. For, to speak truth, many are unsatisfied, and during the time of this magnificent Feasting, divers of the discontented (though not long since a precious) party betook <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> to praying. <i>The Lord unite the hearts of all his saints.</i></p>

<p>By an Express from abroad the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>, thus: On the 26 of <reg orig="Ian">Jan</reg>. we took the <em>Doggord</em> of <em>Flushing</em>, and on the 27 we recovered the <em>Patrick</em> of <em><reg orig="Leverpool">Liverpool</reg></em> from the Brest men of War, who act by commission from the K. of Scots. We chased cap. <em><reg orig="Dillons">Dillon's</reg></em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>, but she ran to <reg orig="neer">near</reg> <em><reg orig="Pensance">Penzance</reg></em> key, that we durst not follow her. The I intended to make up to the Lands-end; but by cross winds we were soon brought within sight of 4 ships of S. <em>Maloes</em> coming from <em>Marseilles</em>, bound for <em><reg orig="New-haven">Newhaven</reg></em>, viz the St. <em>Martin</em> with 18 guns &amp; 44 men, the St. <em>Helena</em> with 14 guns, and 32 men, the <em>Protection</em> with 12 guns, and 32 men, and the <em>Francis</em> with ten guns, and 38 men laden with soap, <reg orig="oyl">oil</reg>, cotton, &amp;c. with whom we came up about one of the clock, and fought them 5 hours. The <em>Martin</em> and <em>Helena</em> had both yielded but we had none of our men aboard; it beginning to be dark, and We being ready to board the <em>Protection</em>, whom we had well paid with shot, bethought <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> that we should lose the other two in taking her &amp; so <reg orig="cleered">cleared</reg> <reg orig="our selves">ourselves</reg> with much ado, &amp; stood to the other who being secured we were bearing for the other yet untaken; but these two ships we had taken were so much disabled, as we were forced to keep <pb n="3" />by them to save them from sinking, &amp; sent our Carpenter aboard to stop leaks, &amp; men to fit the Rigging, the Admiral not being able to bear <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>, which occasioned the losing of the other two. Our ships suffered in hull, masts, rigging, &amp; sails, <em>viz.</em> in the main mast three shot, the top mast two, our fore-yard &amp; mizen-yard made unserviceable; we had several shot between wind &amp; water, 5 men killed, and 19 wounded: some having lost their legs &amp; others their arms: <i>A <unclear>dismal</unclear> sight to see.</i></p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Prizes taken the last week</i></head>
<!--a table in 2 columns-->

<!--column 1-->

<p>One Prize laden with Wine, taken by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>One sweet Prize laden with Raisins &amp; Figs, taken by the old <em>Warwick</em>.</p>

<!--column 2-->

<p>One man of war, with 20 guns, taken by the <em><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></em>.</p>

<p>Two private men of war taken to the <em>Nortward</em>.</p>

<p>Two ships laden with Almonds, taken by the <em>Portsmouth</em> <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg>.</p>

<p>From Scotland they report, that the L. Seafort hath stormed the Fort at Lewis Island, with 1400 men, and taken it from the English; Of this more in my next.</p>

<p>From Windsor it is certified, That Mr. Feak and Mr. Simpson have sent a letter to the Lord Protector, and another to their Churches, to desire them to keep close together, and wait upon God, for that the Lord had spoke peace to their <reg orig="soules">souls</reg>, &amp; confident they were that deliverance was <reg orig="neer">near</reg> at hand. Some things are under consideration touching the restoring of Maj. Gen, Brown to liberty: 'tis time! But poor Judge Jenkins lies still captivated in Windsor Castle. The business of Sir Jo. Lenthal and the Upper-Bench is likewise taken into consideration: of which an account will be suddenly given. The Queen of Sweden has sent a Letter to the K. of Scots, wherein her Majesty doth excuse <reg orig="her self">herself</reg> that the present condition of her affairs doth not suffer her to give him satisfaction upon his Demands, protesting that she pities his misfortune. Of this, more hereafter. The peace is concluded between the K. of Poland, and the Cossacks; but the great Duke of Muscovy has sent a letter to the <reg orig="Queens">Queen's</reg> <unclear>Maj.</unclear> at Upsal, signifying that he hath mustered a hundred and sixty thousand men, and desires her Maj. to declare and <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him against the said King. The great Duke of <reg orig="Tuskany">Tuscany</reg> has sent an Ambassador to congratulate the Lord Protector and the Lo. Of Amiland in Holland has sent an Agent to his Highness, with Credentials desiring that they may be esteemed as Neutrals, and be accounted as a free State, having not been hitherto subject (as is pretended to any <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg>. The United Provinces have not yet brought in their Resolves for ratification of the Articles; but go on pell-mell with their Navigable proceedings, and every man is constrained to work upon the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> day. The K. of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> Pickeroons increase, as appears by the ensuing list and daily infest the Western channel.</p>

<head level="3">A List of the Brest men of War, &amp;c.</head>

<!--a list in two columns-->

<!--column 1-->

<p>The Royal James with 38 guns, Richard Beach Captain.</p>

<p>The Michael 14 guns, Cap. James Smith.</p>

<p>The Bridget 8 guns, Cap. <reg orig="Wil">Will</reg> Smith.</p>

<p>The Francis 10 guns, Cap. Covel,</p>

<p>The loyal James 12 guns, Cap. Ia. Dillon</p>

<p>The Mary 4 guns, Cap. Rich. Dillon,</p>

<p>The St. Francis 20 guns, Cap. Durant,</p>

<p>The Charles 8 guns, Cap. Jones,</p>

<!--column 2-->

<p>The Blossome 22 guns, Cap. Martin,</p>

<p>Margaret 3 guns, Cap. Heldish,</p>

<p>Patrick 18 guns, cap. Swart,</p>

<p>Katherine 6 guns, Cap. Estmund.</p>

<p>Swiftsure 6 guns, Cap. Peters,</p>

<p>Frost 7 guns Cap. Rivers,</p>

<p>Snow 4 guns, Cap. Murro,</p>

<p>Adventure 12 guns, Cap. George,</p>

<p>Three French-men with 18 &amp; 20 Gun.</p>

<p>Three in the Stocks of 4 guns apiece.</p>

<head level="3"><i>The Declaration and bloody <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg>.</i></head>

<p><em>Gentlemen</em>, I hope I shall be <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> from the blood of this Generation, being sent of God to declare the things hereafter mentioned: For it is evident, I <reg orig="fore-told">foretold</reg> the manner of the death of King Charles, and do herein <reg orig="fore see">foresee</reg> a great and mighty change. So that if the people now refuse to hear me, (who have had so many witnesses to <reg orig="shew">show</reg> that God is pleased to declare his determinate Will by me) they of all others will be the least excusable for despising me, and so the least capable of mercy. For, have they not known how God by me declared the most remarkable things that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> these kingdoms since the wars began: How that 20 years ago I declared the things that <reg orig="befel">befell</reg> my late <reg orig="Soveraign">Sovereign</reg>, and that I suffered three <reg orig="yeares">years</reg> imprisonment for the same? How that I declared to the Earl of Essex 7 years before he was a General, that he should be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> General against the King? Have they not known how that in the year <unclear>1646</unclear> I declared the <reg orig="downfal">downfall</reg> of the Presbyterians. How I declared, that the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Son would come to England long before he came to Worcester, and his success likewise? How I declared to the <unclear>Parl.</unclear> that they should be destroyed long before their dissolution? And now, as concerning you, ye discontented people of Black-fryers, that use to meet every <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg>, ye pray, ye preach, ye fast, and complain that God doth not hear your prayers; and ye cry to God that he would lend the Spirit of <reg orig="Prophecie">Prophecy</reg> by some one or other, to let you understand the things to come, and yet you cannot see them now <pb n="5" />when God <reg orig="sheweth">showeth</reg> you all these things by me his poor messenger: Therefore, I say unto you, bend your prayers for the present Power; submit unto OLIVER your <reg orig="supream">supreme</reg> Governor and Lord Protector and then doubtless ye <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> prevail with God in prayers for him, and, have all your desires accomplished; that is, to have the late members of Parliament called to an account for all their vast sums of money, and to have the people eased of their heavy Taxations, and <reg orig="wearisom">wearisome</reg> Burdens, which for many years (poor <reg orig="soules">souls</reg>) they have undergones For indeed what is become of the <reg orig="Bishops">Bishop's</reg>, <reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg>, and <reg orig="Chapters">Chapter's</reg> <reg orig="lande">land</reg> and <reg orig="Delinquents">Delinquent's</reg> estates, forsooth? and many other things that are gone I know not where: no, nor he that has as big a head as a Horse I believe: But sure I am, that there are many worth a thousand li. now, that were not worth one hundred pence before the wars began: So that you may <reg orig="cleerly">clearly</reg> see, we have had more <reg orig="Juglers">Jugglers</reg> than Gypsies of late <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>. And therefore, if ye would have God to hear you, why do you not hear him by doing justly to his Highness, and submitting to the present Government, <em>that righteousness may run down as a River</em>, or else all your seeking the Lord <reg orig="wil">will</reg> be in vain; for if ye will still have your prayers granted according to your own sense and will, that is, for you to prevail, <reg orig="kil">kill</reg>, and slay all that <reg orig="wil">will</reg> not submit unto you, then the Lord <reg orig="wil">will</reg> <reg orig="shew">show</reg> your folly to all the world. And do not you boast, as some of you do, that ye have had the Spirit of <reg orig="Prophesie">Prophecy</reg> these 7 years, that the Armies <reg orig="over-coming">overcoming</reg> your enemies is the fruit of your prayers. Alas! it is but your pride, for it was <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Decree to deliver hid people into your hands for a time, to punish them for their sins, and he revealed in unto me 20 years ago, that your party should prevail as they have done, and then come to a miserable end.</p>

<p>But I shall take occasion by the way to speak a Word also to M. Feak, Mr. Simpson, and others of their party, meeting at the aforesaid place at <reg orig="Black-Fryars">Blackfriars</reg>, not doubting but when God <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> Arrest them saying, King: 21.19. Hast thou killed and taken possession in that place where the King &amp; his people lost their blood, in that very place <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> thy blood be spilt, even thine; and set their Bloody <pb n="6" />Deeds to cry unto their Consciences, saying, We are thine, and we will not leave thee until thy <reg orig="judgment">judgement</reg> come; and when <reg orig="Nathans">Nathan's</reg> Riddle is opened unto others, saying, thou art the man, for thou hast given great occasion to the Papist to blaspheme, saying, These are the works of such as would be altogether ruled by the Bible: they will break their <reg orig="Vowes">Vows</reg>, and kill and steal by authority; when like <reg orig="Davids">David's</reg> their sin as a bloody sheet is set before them, It <reg orig="wil">will</reg> make them roar like David, saying, I acknowledge mine iniquity, and my sin is ever before me; against thee, thee <reg orig="onely">only</reg> have I sinned, by causing the enemies to blaspheme thy Word, the holy Bible. Oh now I will repent, and <reg orig="endeavor">endeavour</reg> to make restitution to the families we have spoiled, and I will pay my own Vows, and stop the <reg orig="mouthes">mouths</reg> of the Blasphemers of thy Word thereby, so far as I am able, help me Lord, that I may prevail and appease thy hot indignation against me: and my desire is, that those of Mr. <reg orig="Simpsons">Simpson's</reg> party would repent and be of the same Resolution: But I know of a certain, there is a Party in this Land that shall fall by their wilful impenitency. But consider, I beseech you, that the Elect must endure and <reg orig="flye">fly</reg>, until the Lord come as Lightening to lighten the Earth, to give them hope and assured knowledge that Judgement is coming upon their Persecutors; for ye know, that we are exhorted by Christ Jesus, to compare what we see in his Word with the things done in our times; for he gives us true <reg orig="signes">signs</reg>: And then <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> he, When ye see these things begin to come to pass, know that your redemption draweth nigh.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>Truly I have no cause to doubt these people; for though they have not yielded to the truth: yet they have been <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> that my Declaration was so much in the way of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Spirit, that they did not molest me at all, when I delivered my Petition to the Council of the Army, and spoke in defence of King Charles at that time when I disputed it before them all four hours together. And now I am as the <em>Paul</em> of these Times: he was a Tent-maker, I am a Taylor: I plant and <reg orig="shew">show</reg> these things, <em>Apollo</em>, that i, the eloquent Ministers of Christ are to water them; but God giveth the increase. So I recommend all to God and his Ministers, and remain your faithful Servant in Christ <reg orig="Iesus">Jesus</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Arise Evans.</i></p>

<p>His Highness the Lord Protector has appointed certain <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> every week to receive Reports from the Masters of Requests of Petitions presented to them, and to give Answers.</p>

<p>The Highlanders grow numerous in Scotland; and the Tories are too potent in Ireland. They have had several <reg orig="Randevouzes">Rendezvous</reg>; and sundry times made incursions upon the Lowlanders. But care is taken to prevent the like for the future, if we can. The King of Scots has sent Letters to them, promising aid and assistance. But alas! fair words butter no Parsnips.</p>

<p>The English fleet rides still about St. <reg orig="Hellens">Hellen's</reg> Point; but the Dutch are not yet forth. There has been a great <reg orig="shipwrack">shipwreck</reg> upon the Coast of France, and divers men drowned. The English fleet from the Straits, Spain, Portugal, and Biscain, are come false into the River of Thames, and several Dutch Prizes also. Ten more are expected every Tide. The last Post from France advertiseth, that King Lewis and his Council have agreed to send an Ambassador Extraordinary unto his Highness the Lord Protector.</p>

<p>From Holland it is further certified, that the United Provinces have brought in their Ratification to the Articles for Peace, and that they have both signed and sealed in general; and are preparing of an Ambassador to be sent unto his Highness the Lord Protector, for the confirming thereof: It is said the Lord Updam is the man elected: But of this, more in my next.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>