<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost175">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 175</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Weekly</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Proclamation for Peace; or, the Declaration of his Highness the Lord <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>, to be published by the Heralds of Arms, and sound of Trumpets <reg orig="to morrow">tomorrow</reg>, being the 26 of this instant <em>April</em>, throughout all Cities, Towns, Sea-Forts, and Harbours, within the <reg orig="Common wealth">Commonwealth</reg> of England, and the Dominions thereunto belonging; and the United Provinces in the Low countries. The number of English and Dutch men of war, designed for the <reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg> and Levant seas, under the command of Gen. <em>Pen</em>, and young <em>Tromp</em>; A Narrative touching the surrender of <em>Dunkirk</em> to his Highness by the K. of Spain, for the landing an Army of Redcoats in France. The advancing of the K. of Scots, and the D. of York from Paris, the true proceedings of their forces in Scotland, and the several Onsets &amp; Engagements with the particular loss on both sides.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> the 18. of <em>April</em>, to <em>Tuesday</em> the 25 of <em>April</em> 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed by <em>R. Wood</em>, for <em>G, Horton</em>, <i>for information of the</i>.</p>
<head level="3">PEOPLE.</head>
<hr />

<p>The delivery of <em>Opinions</em>, and the sundry <em>Mutations</em> and <em>Changes</em>, which hath of late years sprung up within the <em>Confines</em> of <em>Great <reg orig="Brittain">Britain</reg></em>, causeth as much wonder as admiration: and the redeeming of Us from a perpetual and short-lived <em>Parliament</em>, was no small joy to the people of <em>England</em>; But to be restored to their Original <em>Constitution</em> and to embrace <em>Liberty</em> and <em>Freedom</em>, O what a sweet and pleasant Harmony would found in the Ears of all men: The which, as it is with great fervency desired, so is it with as great integrity and fidelity assured, by <reg orig="vertue">virtue</reg> of the late <em>Constitution of Government.</em></p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>So serious and deliberate is his Excellency in all his actions, that not one is omitted without diligent perusal; neither doth He <reg orig="passe">pass</reg> by Matters of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> concernment, without due examining; As King <em>James</em> did, when He was under his Tutor the learned Divine Doctor <em>Buchanan</em>, passed under his Hand several Instruments, as Grants and Pardons, exceeding pernicious to his people, without any examination. Well! <em>Buchanan</em>, that he might the more substantially reprehend him for his so doing, first desireth of his Majesty to grant him a Boon, &amp; the same morning that he was to go a hunting, bringeth an Instrument to be signed, which was an absolute Resignation the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> to <em>Buchanan</em>: the King signeth it, and at night after supper, withdraweth himself with his Tutor, to <reg orig="reade">read</reg> some Author, as was his custom, <em>Buchanan</em> <!--orig or typo?-->siteth down in the <reg orig="Kings">King's</reg> Chair, and said, He was King. Upon that, gave the King the Papers that he had signed in the morning Upon reading thereof, his Majesty wept, committed the conveyance of the kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> into the fire, and afterwards resolved, according to the advice of his <reg orig="faithfull">faithful</reg> and good Tutor, never to pass <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> without perusal and deliberation. &mdash; But to Intelligence:</p>

<head level="3"><i><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg>, April 18.</i></head>

<p>Monsieur <em>Lodowick de Gand</em>, Lord of <em>Brachey</em>, and Resident here in <em>England</em> in behalf of the high and mighty Prince <em>Lewis</em>, Duke of <em>Guelders</em> and <em>Juliers</em>, Conte of <em>Egmont</em> and <unclear><em>Zutphen</em></unclear>, &amp; was this day, with many Gentlemen of quality accompanying him in coaches, attended by Sir <em>Oliver Flemming</em>, Master of the Ceremonies, unto his Highness the Lord Protector; The Lord President <em>Laurence</em>, and some other Lords of the Council, with the Secretary of State, being present in his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> chamber, where the said Lord Resident had audience and made a congratulatory Speech, which was answered with abundance of respect from his Highness.</p>

<p>By an Express from <em>Naples</em> it is certified, That Gen. <em>Delfino</em> having besieged the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Clim</em>, found so cold a welcome, by the hot and desperate sallying out of the Turks, that after a lamentable and <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> conflict, he was totally routed, and left behind him above a thousand gallant men, and all his Bag and Baggage, besides some pieces of <reg orig="Canon">Cannon</reg>.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<p>The next thing that we shall present you <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, is an Express from abroad the <em>Pearl</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> in <em>Dover</em> Road, signifying, That a Squadron of English ships are commanded to <em>Deep</em> un <em>France</em>, to conduct over the two <em>French</em> Lords, who have received further <em>Credentials</em> from their Master the King, for the concluding of a firm League and Union with his most Excellent Highness, <em>Oliver</em> Lord Protector, &amp;c. So runs the Title of the Commission: from whence we may infer that the <em>Harp</em> makes the sweetest Harmony: Form, true it is, that many <em>Christian Princes</em> have resolved to congratulate his Highness and to that end, sundry Ambassadors are preparing: <i>so that they begin to work out their deliverance with fear and <unclear>trembling</unclear>.</i></p>

<p>The <em>Commissioners</em> for <i>approbation of <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Preachers</i> sit <em>on Mondays, <reg orig="Wednesdayes">Wednesdays</reg></em>, and <em><reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg></em>; of which <em><reg orig="Frydayes">Fridays</reg></em> for <em>Augmentations</em>. In all the Transactions, there is no respect had to <reg orig="any thing">anything</reg> so much as grace in <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> hearts; some University men, for defect thereof, have been laid by; and some who were never were University men, yet furnished with gifts and graces, have been received and welcomed. No Difference at all among the <em>Commissioners</em> themselves, though they be of divers judgements about <em>Church matters</em>, all minding the <i>advancement of the Gospel</i>. They being 38 in number are severed into three Divisions, each sitting their month. No partiality used in their <reg orig="Tryals">Trials</reg>; nor do certificates approved of, but such as come subscribed under the hands of such persons as are known to the <em>Commissioners</em>.</p>

<p>From sea, the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> news is, that a fleet of 40 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of <em>French Merchant-men</em> were met with off of <em>Ushant</em>, by the <em>Portsmouth</em> and <em>Middleburgh <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg></em>, who assailed them, and maintained a very hot Dispute, in which they sunk the <em>French</em> Admiral, and took 5. But the foulness of the weather separating our <reg orig="frigats">frigates</reg>, impeded their further pursuit of Victory and so the fleet escaped.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the ships taken and sunk in the aforesaid Engagement.</i></head>

<!--table in 2 columns separated by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>1 The Admiral sunk, called the <em>Foundore</em>, 22 guns.</p>
<p>2 The St. <em>Clement</em> sunk, a ship of 14 guns.</p>
<p>3 The Rear-Admiral taken, called the <unclear><em>Leveirge</em></unclear>, a ship of 18 guns</p>
<p>4 The <em>Lough Blanch</em> taken; a ship of 11 guns</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>5 The St. <em><reg orig="Jaques">Jacques</reg></em>, a delicate ship of 18 guns.</p>
<p>6 The <em>John Baptist</em> 12 guns</p>
<p>Those that escaped, were,</p>
<p>The <em>Concord</em>, the <em>Protect</em>, the <em>Joseph</em>, the <em>George</em>, the <em>Chevalier</em>, the <em>Souldier</em>, the <em>Peter</em>, the <em>Le Fume</em>, the <em>Palma</em>, the <em>Julia Lunia</em>, and some others.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>By an Express from <em>Scotland</em>, we have received very remarkable intelligence, intimating, That the Royal party increaseth, and have taken some few prisoners from the Borders of <em>Cumberland</em> to the Hills, the Lord <em>Forrester</em>, and the Lord <em>Dudhop</em> are in <em>Athol</em>, and very active in attending the motion of General <em>Middleton</em>. The rest of their forces in <em>Caithness</em> have left no means unassayed for raising of the whole <reg orig="countrey">country</reg>; but the people being <reg orig="timerous">timorous</reg> of rising, <reg orig="feariny">fearing</reg> least the <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Sinclair</em>, commanded by <em>Langrish</em> of col. <em><reg orig="Fitches">Fitch's</reg></em> Regiment should punish them for their Loyalty, after <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> march from thence: whereof for their encouragement, Maj. Gen. <em>Dyel</em> with a strong party of foot, and 100 stout horse, is ordered to sit down before it for the reducing of it, which is conceived to be a work of great difficulty, the place being situated on a very high <em>Rock</em>, yet if they prove successful in this Achievement, they intend then to attempt <unclear><em>Ruthin</em></unclear> <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg>; but cap. <em>Hill</em> (the Governor) has reinforced it with provisions, and is well provided for a siege.</p>

<p>The Armies of both sides are preparing to receive each other, and Col. <em>Morgan</em> has <reg orig="drain'd">drained</reg> <em><reg orig="Innerness">Inverness</reg></em> to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with those forces which he brought from <em>Aberdeen</em>, so that he lies with about 1700 Horse and Dragoons, and 2000 Foot, betwixt the enemy and <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> <unclear>they</unclear> must needs march through, if they intend to move out of the North corner; so that they will be compelled to fight, and <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> they are resolved; there being no way left them to <unclear><!--approx. 7 characters--></unclear>, but through such inaccessible bounds, as 'tis impossible for their horse to march that way, and very difficult for their foot, it being exceeding <reg orig="mountainovs">mountainous</reg>, and scarcely inhabited, and the <reg orig="countrey">country</reg> they are in will not long be able to sustain them, it being very poor. I doubt not but a <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> will give us an account of some action between him and <em>Middleton</em>; what the success will be, the Lord <reg orig="knowes">knows</reg>; for, to speak truth, we have a very stout and stubborn enemy to deal <reg orig="withall">withal</reg>, and as potent they speak themselves to be as valiant, saying they <unclear>scorn</unclear> to prove <unclear>perfidious</unclear> (in the least) to so great a Cause wherein the interest of their King so much depends; but will rather <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> to sacrifice their lives in the field, and dispute the mountainous passes by inches.</p>

<p>The two Armies continue now at an <reg orig="easie">easy</reg> distance from each other for some days past<!--possibly should reg to passed--> and 'tis conceived that the English have some advantage of them in respect of ground, and will endeavour by all <pb n="4" />means to engage them, though their number far exceeds ours. But alas! during the time of their declining engagement many of our <reg orig="souldiery">soldiery</reg> run from several parts to the enemy, which do much exasperate them, and annoy Us. We expect a sudden Engagement, and many desperate Onsets there hath already been; yet not much cause to laugh on either side as yet: Therefore, for the success, we must refer it unto Him in whose hands are all the Corners of the Earth.</p>

<head level="3"><i>A List of the Commanders in chief of the Scottish Army.</i></head>

<!--list in 2 columns divided by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<head level="2">Gen. Middleton,</head>
<head level="2">Lieu. gen. Glencairn,</head>
<head level="2">gen. major Kenmore,</head>
<head level="2">The E. of Athol,</head>
<head level="2">The L. Forrester,</head>
<head level="2">The L. Dudhop,</head>
<head level="2">Sir George Monro,</head>

<!--column 2-->
<head level="2">Sir Arthur Forbs,</head>
<head level="2">Sir Cha. Dyar,</head>
<head level="2">Col. Mac-donald,</head>
<head level="2">Co: stuart,</head>
<head level="2">Co: Welch,</head>
<head level="2">Co: Brown,</head>
<head level="2">Co: Fitz James.</head>

<p>By an Express from <em>Paris</em> it is certified, that one <em>James Darcy</em> an Irish Gentleman was made by the King Lieutenant of the D. of <em>York's</em> Regiment, and the next day was made Knight by the King of <em>Scots</em>: The Governor of <em>Jamets</em> having made a design with the <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Mouson</em> to beat up the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> quarters at <em>Wirton</em> in <reg orig="Luxembourgh">Luxembourg</reg>, carried the Work on with so much dexterity and gallantry that they reinforced their passage, put to the sword most of the Troops there quartered, and took the rest prisoners, with most of the Spanish <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> likewise.</p>

<p>By an Express of a later date, thus: In answer to yours concerning the little Queen, and her Son the King of <em>Scots</em>, thus much at present; On the 22 of <em>April</em> she went form hence, having two <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> before taken her leave of the King and Court, There went with her, her two sons, <em>Charles</em> and <em>James</em> Prince <em>Rupert</em>, the Lord <em>Digby</em>, sir Lewis <unclear><em>Divis</em></unclear>, and divers other Gentlemen, in all about <unclear>12 Coaches</unclear>; some say she intends for <em>Orleans</em>: others, to the Duke her brother, at his house near <em>Blois</em>. The King of <em>Scots</em> is to convoy her on her way, and to return, but not yet to leave <em>France</em> as reported.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>From <em>Truro</em> in <em><reg orig="Cornwal">Cornwall</reg></em>, our <em>Scout</em> bringeth intelligence, That Mrs <em>Hannah <unclear>Frapnel</unclear></em>, who lately acted her part in a Trance so many <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> at <em><reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg></em>, hath for some time <reg orig="bin">been</reg> in those parts, where she passed from Town to Town, to <unclear>vent</unclear> her <reg orig="Prophesies">Prophecies</reg>, and <unclear>alienate</unclear> the hearts of the people from the present Government. There are in her company one Mr. <unclear><em>Langdon</em></unclear>, and Mr. <unclear><em>Baudon</em></unclear>, two members of the late short-lived <em>Parliament</em>: But the Justices having taken notice of her <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> and practices, she was apprehended; and M. <em>Lobb</em> giving the Charge in the last Sessions, willed the Jury to inquire, 1 concerning <em>Vagrants</em>, 2 such as occasioned unlawful meeting, 3 such as speak against the present Government. There were two Indictments drawn against her; M. <em>Langdon</em>, and M. <em>Baudon</em>, endeavoured to make a learned Defence, and could no be <unclear><!--8 characters--></unclear>: <reg orig="onely">only</reg> they <unclear>entered into Bond</unclear> of 300l. for her good behaviour; and appearance at the next Assizes. This passage <unclear>reminded me</unclear> of the old story of <em>Eliz. Barton</em>, the Holy Maid of <em>Kent</em> as she was called in the days of H.8 who was <unclear>made</unclear> us of by certain <reg orig="fanatick">fanatic</reg> Popish Priests by <reg orig="feined">feigned</reg> Miracles &amp; Trances, to raise admiration in the <unclear>multitude</unclear>, and foment seditious Humours against the Government; for which she and her <unclear>accomplices</unclear> were all hanged <i>but the heads</i>.</p>

<p>From <em>Holland</em> they write, That the States <unclear>General have sent to all</unclear> Provinces, and considerable cities to bring in their opinions and consents concerning the House of <unclear><em>Orange</em></unclear>, and the <em><reg orig="Stuarts">Stuart's</reg></em> Family; <i>'tis hoped all things will prove for the best.</i> And 'tis conceived the Q of <em>Sweden</em> hath a good <unclear>intention for</unclear> the <em>Low-Countries</em>. Unto which confines, valiant Duke <em>Francis</em> of <em>Lorain</em> is said to prosecute his journey with a stately Train. Their great <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg>, far bigger <reg orig="then">than</reg> ever is designed to <reg orig="lanch">launch</reg> forth into the Deep about the merry month of <em>May</em>: at which time they intent, to play strange pranks, <i>over the left shoulder.</i></p>

<p>The States have had several meetings for preventing of the Designs which may be intended against the <em>Sound</em>, and to preserve the <reg orig="intire">entire</reg> right to the K. of <em>Denmark</em>; and upon the Result, sent Orders to the Admiralty of <em>Amsterdam</em>, to carry on the Naval <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> with expedition. </p>

<p>From <em>Plymouth</em> it is certified, That capt. <em>Potter</em> Commander of the <em>Constant Warwick</em>, (who not long since brought in that famous <reg orig="Pyrate">Pirate</reg> cap. <em>Beach</em>) hath again disputed the <reg orig="soveraignty">sovereignty</reg> of the seas with another Brest man of War, called the <em>Bridget</em>, and after a sharp and <pb n="6" />cruel conflict came to <reg orig="grapling">grappling</reg>, and at last boarded her, and brought her into the aforesaid Port; she is one of the neatest things and best <reg orig="saylor">sailor</reg> that ever spread her canvass upon the curled Waves.</p>

<p>From <em>Warsaw</em> they write, that the <em>Muscovites</em> before they would grant the <em>Cossacks</em> their protection, obliged them to renounce the Amity of the <em>Tartarians</em> that they should never acknowledge their old Polish Lords, nor wear any habit after the polish mode, or wear any red or yellow boots, but <reg orig="onely">only</reg> black ones; and that they shall <unclear>drink no</unclear> strong waters, play at cards, or take tobacco &amp;c.</p>

<p>The French <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> are in a <reg orig="pannick">panic</reg> fear that the K. of Spain will deliver into the hands of the Lord protector of England, the town of Dunkirk for security of forces, which they fear shall be sent over to the Prince of <em>Conde</em>, for the service of the K. of Spain, against the Crown of France.</p>

<p>The Q of Sweden hat written a letter to the French Ambassador, concerning her <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> Resolution of <reg orig="surrendring">surrendering</reg> Her Crown and Kingdom to Pr. <em>Charles</em>, which is conceived to be <reg orig="onely">only</reg> for promoting of the princess of <em>Orange</em> the King of <reg orig="Scots">Scots'</reg> sister.</p>

<p>The Articles of peace are delivered to his Highness the Lord protector in a silver box, signed and sealed by the States of the United provinces, all concurring; and his Highness hath appointed the like to be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> here, and to pass the Great Seal of England; and then he will sign it by his sign <em>Manual</em>, which then is to be put into a silver box, and be sent to the <em>Hague</em>, and after signification of the States General receiving thereof, it will be published in both <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg>.</p>

<p>From Scotland we have received intelligence, that the grand design of Rising doth appear every day more universal, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the Scots flying out, bur divers English; and amongst the rest three Clerks, belonging to the Court of Justice at <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, divers <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> out of Lieth, and about 50 from Sterling are gone to the Hills; from whence they descend down <reg orig="somtimes">sometimes</reg> into the Lowlands, and amongst the others, the E. of Salkirk, second son to the Marq of <em>Douglas</em>, started out the other day, and took from Boggehal 60 horse. Nay, this is not all, but divers other <reg orig="English-men">Englishmen</reg> are got to the Hills under the command of an <reg orig="Irish-man">Irishman</reg>: so that <em><reg orig="Middletons">Middleton's</reg></em> Army consists of at least 800 horse &amp; 3000 foot, and are resolved to engage us. Whereupon col. <em>Morgan</em> with 850 horse, &amp; 1600 foot is advanced against them, and a sudden engagement is expected.</p>

<p>Cap. Staner, and Cap. Smith, Commanders of the Tonnington &amp; Plymouth <reg orig="frigots">frigates</reg>, have taken an Holland East-India ship outward bound of 800 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg>, laden with 350 <reg orig="Tun">Ton</reg> of goods, and 4 Chests of silver. The Constant Warwick hath brought in Prize a Brest man of war with 8 guns, and 50 men into Plymouth.</p>

<p><reg orig="Ay">Aye</reg>! But to this welcome <reg orig="newes">news</reg>, we have received very sad <reg orig="tydings">tidings</reg>, that is, on Tuesday last Cap. Southwood, commander of the White-Raven, going from <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> Road towards Newcastle, was set upon by a 11 Dutch men of war, boarded and taken, and the 13 instant a private man of war ours, was <reg orig="accidently">accidentally</reg> blown up in Leith Road, and 6 men killed.</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>From <em>Deal, April</em> 21. thus: This Afternoon arrived here the Express, who doth return into <em>Holland</em> to carry to the Sates General the <reg orig="ratificatiod">ratification</reg> of the peace, signed and sealed by his Highness the L. Protector, which upon signification of their receiving, will suddenly be proclaimed both in <em>England</em> and <em>Wales</em>.</p>

<p>There are brought into this Road three Dutch prizes, whereof one was a ship bound for the East-Indies, and the other two of great value. There are also brought into <em>Harwich</em> two Dutch prizes which came from <em>Norway</em>; and some Busses are taken by a private man of war, and <reg orig="carryed">carried</reg> into <em>Tarmouth</em>, laden with fish.</p>

<p>By an Express from aboard the <em>Pearl</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg> it is certified, That about 50 <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> of English men of War, and as many Dutch, are designed for the <em><reg orig="Streights">Straits</reg></em>, the <em>Indies</em>, and <em>Levant</em> seas; and that Gen. <em>Pen</em> is to be commissionated for this famous Expedition. The Fleet rides as yet in <em>Stokes-Bay</em>; but expects daily command to weigh Anchor.</p>

<head level="3">SATURDAY, <em>April</em> 22. 1654.</head>
<head level="2">By the Council at <reg orig="White-Hall">Whitehall</reg>.</head>

<p><i>Whereas a place is made, concluded, and ratified, between his Highness the Lord Protector, and the States General of the United Provinces of the Low countries. And whereas it is agreed, That publication thereof shall be made of both parts on <em>Wednesday</em> next, being the 26 of this instant <em>April</em>; from which time, restitution is to be made of all ships that shall be taken on either side, after 12 days, within these seas; and in all other places on this side the Cape of St. <em>Vincent</em>; and from thence within the <em>Mediterranean</em> sea, and to the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg> Line, after ten weeks; and beyond the <reg orig="&AElig;quinoctial">Equinoctial</reg>, after the space of 8 <reg orig="moneths">months</reg>: which several spaces were so limited to the <unclear>intent</unclear>, convenient time might be allowed for notice to be given of the said peace, in all places where it shall be necessary. The Council have therefore <unclear><!--approx. 10 characters--></unclear> hereby to give notice thereof to the several Parts of this Commonwealth, and to all others whom it may concern, within the Dominions thereof; <unclear>to the</unclear> end, they may have warning to provide for their own safety, and not expose their ships to danger within the several and respective times aforesaid.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">Ordered by the Council, That this be forthwith printed and published. <em>W. Jessop</em>, Clerk of the Council.</head>
<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>