<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost166">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 166</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2"><i>The Grand Politique</i></head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>The Speech and Confession of Mr. <em>James Harrington</em> on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last, at the place of Execution, over against the <reg orig="Grayhound">Greyhound</reg>-Tavern, at the lower end of <reg orig="Fleetstreet">Fleet Street</reg>, with the Cause and manner of his Death, and his Declaration and Narrative to the People touching the Meal <reg orig="mans">man's</reg> wife of <em>Brainford</em>, and the whole <em>Particulars</em> of the Business. Likewise, a <em>Declaration</em> to the <em>Nation</em>, touching the present Government, and his Highness the <em>Lord Protector</em>. The releasing of Mr. <em>Roger Coter</em>, and divers others, out of the Tower of <em>London</em>; the coming up of the <em>Dutch Ambassadors</em> with full power to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> and confirm the Articles. And a mighty Victory obtained in the North of <em>Scotland</em>.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 21. to <em>Tuesday</em> Feb. 28. 1654</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i></p>

<hr />

<p>The last <em>Post</em> from Scotland advertiseth, that the English forces have fallen upon the Highlanders, and after an <reg orig="irresistable">irresistible</reg> and furious Onset, took above 120 Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>, great store of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, Ammunition, Horses with plenty of provision, and afterwards blew up the strong <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of Dunkel. Col. Morgan hath also removed the Enemies Garrison at Kildrumny, and at Cromar put 120 to the sword, took 27 prisoners, 80 horse, &amp; all their Ammunition. Mr. Roger Cotes, and some others, are discharged of their imprisonment in the Tower; but Mr. Dutton, and Capt. Smith remains there still,</p>

<pb n="1" />

<p>Since which time, we have received intelligence, that young <em>Charles</em> hath sent a message unto the States of Holland, desiring the transportation of some horse and foot raised for his service; but the States returned Answer, that in this juncture of time with England, they neither could nor durst expose their shipping to any other service, but what might redound to the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> good of the United Provinces: Whereupon a Dispatch was made to the King of Denmark, imploring <reg orig="Ayd">Aid</reg> and Assistance from thence: but alas! the emergent and weighty Affairs of that Kingdom being so great, his Majesty can no <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> possible answer his expectation. For <reg orig="wee">we</reg> have not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> taken certain Prizes from the Dane; but some likewise from France &amp; Holland, notwithstanding the present Overtures for peace from the Netherlands; which cannot be as yet) <reg orig="avoyded">avoided</reg>, <reg orig="untill">until</reg> the expected Ambassadors are come over, to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> their Articles, and to confirm and establish a perfect peace, and a firm League and Union; which Ambassadors are expected within few <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>, if they do not (as formerly they have done) derogate from anything that hath formerly agreed on. But if they prove so apostate, then let England judge things rightly and take heed how they make Leagues and Union with such a people: how they forbear to mind what the <reg orig="voyce">voice</reg> of Providence <reg orig="saith">sayeth</reg> to them, or neglect to take the opportunities that such a signal hand of God (as hath lately appeared) hath put before them, to secure themselves, do justice to their people, and maintain the Reputation of that Cause amongst them, which God hath written his name upon both at Sea and Land, in such <reg orig="unparallel'd">unparalleled</reg> and glorious Characters. And let every man take heed how he seeks to bind the Hand of God, when he is shaking his Rod over a <reg orig="peoole">people</reg>, especially when they have upon them the symptoms of Displeasure; and how they stand in the way of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> Design in the World, and how they express more tenderness to such a people, <reg orig="then">than</reg> to the security, Blood, and Right of their <reg orig="Countrey-men">Countrymen</reg>, and the Will of God, which We ought to pray to be done in earth as it is in Heaven. For when the Lord is moved from his Throne, to do his great work in the world, in routing Antichrist, making of his name glorious, in relieving the oppressed, delivering the Captive, and throwing down the unrighteous powers on Earth.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3">Thursday Feb. 23.</head>

<p>This day came a letter from Cap. Foller of a desperate fight with the Hollander, and taking the Convoy of the Dutch <reg orig="fisher-men">fishermen</reg>, a copy whereof followeth:</p>

<p><i>Right Honourable,</i></p>

<p>In pursuance of your <reg orig="Honours">Honour's</reg> Order dated 28 Jan. 1 prepared to the river Humber, the 11 instant (having till then been prevented by Northerly winds and thick weather) and gave notice thereof to the rest of the Commanders appointed to proceed with me in this Expedition, whose answer to me intimated their unfitness to sail at that present. The 12 the wind being Southerly, the <em>Phanix</em> and the <em>Amity</em> set <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg> toward the station, desiring the others speedy repair to Us; towards night the wind came to N.N.W. we standing alongst the Dogger, fell amongst the <reg orig="Hollanders">Hollander's</reg> Dogger Boats, and the 13 so soon as day appeared in the morning we discovered two sails which we concluded to be their Convoys, and bore the one of us to one of them, and the other to the other, being about two leagues distant. The <em>Phenix</em> sailing best, I chose the ship furthest off, fearing he might escape the other; coming up each with his chase, mine proved to be a Swede come from Newcastle, which having on board prohibited goods, exceeding his allowance for provisions as also being <reg orig="perswaded">persuaded</reg> he was the man of <reg orig="Wars">War's</reg> prize, he being in the body of their Vessels, and having twice the number of men on board accustomed to sail such a ship, I have thought it my duty to bring him into the Humber, not assuming the power to permit <reg orig="any one">anyone</reg> to pass of whom I have the least cause of <reg orig="suspition">suspicion</reg>. I have sent and referred him to the Commissioners for prize goods at <em>Hull</em>. The ship the <em>Amity</em> stood with, proved to be the <reg orig="fishers">fisher's</reg> Convoy, a man of war of Zealand, 20 Guns, &amp; 70 men, and lying in his two courses, seemed at a distance to be no such ship, but discovering the Amity <reg orig="staid">stayed</reg> for him, they engaged very smartly for 2 hours, and the Amity having shot his top-mast by the board, shattered the ship exceedingly, &amp; slew and wounded most of her men. The <em>Amity</em> is shattered; but we have totally routed them, with the loss of one man, and some few wounded.</p>

<p><i><!--??-->Phenix <reg orig="Frigat">Frigate</reg> 14 Feb. 1654.</i></p>

<p>There hath been another great fight between Cap. <em>Pack</em>, and a Dutch man of War, who for 7 hours disputed it with a great deal of gallantry, until such time that most of his men were killed and wounded, his ship so rent and torn between wind and water, that she was almost ready to sink, her upper decks ran down with blood and the sails and masts were all besmeared with dead <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> brains &amp; <reg orig="skuls">skulls</reg>, so that after a lamentable engagement, the Commander Cap. Blanker exposed himself to the mercy of the English. But this is not all, for Cap. Allin, Cap. Unpheries, and Cap. Sansum, with the Advice, Nightingale, and Adventure <reg orig="frigots">frigates</reg>, have taken the St. David, the Royal Bean, and the Arms of <unclear>Reign</unclear>, whose lading was 2000 Holland Cheeses. 8000 Pan Tiles. 21 Firkins of Butter, 2000 Pipe stoves, and great store of Wheat, Rye, <reg orig="Beanes">Beans</reg>, and <reg orig="Pease">Peas</reg>, besides another sweet prize laden with Sugar, which makes Mr. Hans look somewhat dejected and <reg orig="sowr">sour</reg>.</p>

<pb n="3" />

<p>Whereas the great point of <reg orig="Soveraignty">Sovereignty</reg> and concernment to the safety and benefit of a Commonwealth, is the Electing and disposing of its own Magistrates, or the great Officers of State. And as for the <em>present Council</em>, and the election of them in the way it hath <reg orig="bin">been</reg>: It must be <reg orig="remembred">remembered</reg>, that we were in the beginning of a new Government, necessitated to create a little World out of a Chaos, and bring Form out of Confusion; so that there was an absolute necessity, that some who are known to be persons of integrity, and firm for the present Settlement, should at the same instant be taken in, to carry on the work: which can be no ground of just exception, especially seeing for the future, Elections shall run in the appointed channel, where their <reg orig="streames">streams</reg> are to flow from the People, and their original-Fountain. Yea, the high Office of Protectorship <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> is to be derived also from hence; and as in time it will appear, that the People in Parliament have the main choice of the Council, so they will likewise be <reg orig="Chusers">Choosers</reg> of the Lord Protector: For, it being left to the <reg orig="Counsel">Council</reg> to <reg orig="chuse">choose</reg> Him, and they hereafter coming to be chosen and trusted by the Parliament, it cannot otherwise be conceived, but that the Choice of Him takes its rise mediately from the People in Parliament: because as whatsoever a <reg orig="Parlament">Parliament</reg> doth, is said and taken in a political sense to be the <reg orig="peoples">people's</reg> act, because they are chosen and trusted by the people: so in like manner, and upon the same political account, when the Council comes to be chosen by Parliament, as is before expressed, then the Act of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> in <reg orig="chusing">choosing</reg> the <em>Lord Protector</em>, must by a parity of Reason be reputed the Act of the people in Parliament: And so you see, in effect, mediately or immediately, the election of all Magistrates (both high and low) are, or will at length, by this Constitution of Government, be in the hands of the People. Lastly, as to what concerns the Office of <em>Lord Protector</em>, it is to be observed, that he is not to be admitted to that dignity upon the Interest of Himself or Family, but <reg orig="meerly">merely</reg> upon the account of his fitness for Government: it must pass, not by Inheritance, but Election. And certainly, it is a great advantage to a Nation that the coming in and continuance of their <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> depends only upon his own goodness, and the good will of the People, as it is in <em>Elective Prince</em>, who standing upon terms of good behaviour, will be continually employed for the benefit and defence of the Community. And therefore if it shall please the Lord to bless this Commonwealth (as we trust he will) successively, with a choice of godly persons into that High Office, it is easily foreseen what an advantage it will be to these 3. Nations, to have their whole strength and force combined thus under one head, for the safety of all: this Form being (without question) the fittest and most convenient for the Magistrate to put things on, and in quick execution (as his proper work) for the <reg orig="publick">public</reg> good: as also what a comfort it will be to all the godly in the <em>Protestant Churches</em> abroad, who may have some more <pb n="4" />sure and certain protection from <em>England</em> than heretofore; which as it is the greatest Body, being united with <em>Scotland</em>, so it will prove (we hope) the grand Bulwark of the <em>Reformed Religion</em>. Moreover, as touching the Person, whom the Lord hath now advanced and set over us to be our <reg orig="Supream">Supreme</reg> Magistrate, We shall not say much, because he seeks not the praise of men: only we believe even the enemies will confess, that he is every way worthy to Rule, whom God hath been pleased to use as his Instrument in that glorious Work of Redeeming the Liberties of his people: For, we are bold to say (weighing all circumstances together) that this Nation was never really Free, nor in a way of enjoying its Freedom so fully as now: so that there wants nothing but a cordial Close with the Government, to destroy all hopes of the common Enemy, and <reg orig="compleat">complete</reg> our happiness. But if men shall yet proceed to lengthen their own <reg orig="burthens">burdens</reg>, by hankering after that Family which God hath cast out before us, or by an unnatural seeking to <reg orig="imbroil">embroil</reg> their Country again in blood and misery, for the sake of that unfortunate Interest, as we are <reg orig="loth">loath</reg> to suspect such a thing, and can hardly imagine that any should be so forlorn and desperate after so fair a Composure.</p>

<p>At the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg> on Thursday, <reg orig="Fryday">Friday</reg>, and Saturday last was <reg orig="tryed">tried</reg> one <reg orig="Mistris">Mistress</reg> <em>Beard</em>, who upon Evidence, was cast for bewitching a child: the manner thus: About fifteen weeks ago, the child was struck lame on the left leg then in the right Arm, and afterwards struck in a most lamentable and fearful manner, sometimes lying raging and speechless, and at other times foaming at the mouth with her hand closed up: And having continued thus for many weeks together, at last the said <em>Beard</em> came by, which the child perceiving, immediately fell a raving, by making of <reg orig="signes">signs</reg>, and the like: Whereupon the Parents suspecting her to the Woman that had <reg orig="bewicht">bewitched</reg> their child, <reg orig="fetcht">fetched</reg> a Warrant, and had her before a Justice; and after examination, she was committed to Newgate, &amp; from thence, brought down to the Sessions in the Old <reg orig="bayley">Bailey</reg>, where she was arraigned for her life; and upon the Examining of Witnesses, and searching of her, it appeared that she had three long Teats <reg orig="neer">near</reg> to her <reg orig="privie">privy</reg> Parts, which she said was <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the <reg orig="Pyles">Piles</reg>: But upon the giving in of Evidence, she was cast, and divers others, who suffered death on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last.</p>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> from <em>Holland</em> intimates, that the Difference grows great between the Royal Party, and the Netherlanders, and that they have already disputed the Quarrel touching <em>England</em>. But sure it is, that their Ambassadors are now come with full power to <reg orig="ratifie">ratify</reg> the Articles of Peace Of which, more by the next.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>This day come Letters from <em>Scotland</em> touching the proceedings of the Highlanders, and the setting forth of a Proclamation by General <em>Glencarn</em>, a Copy whereof followeth:</p>

<p>Whereas it hath pleased his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg> to appoint Horse and Foot to be levied within the Kingdom of <em>Scotland</em> for opposing the common Enemy, for giving a check to the pride and oppression of these cruel Traitors, who God in his Justice hath permitted to overcome and to be the instrument of <em><reg orig="Scotlands">Scotland's</reg></em> punishment for its sin, and are no otherwise to be looked on but as <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> scourge upon us, which he will soon remove and consume in his wrath, if we could turn to him by <reg orig="unfained">unfeigned</reg> repentance. And to to <!--repeated over line break-->the end his <reg orig="Majesties">Majesty's</reg> service may be advanced, and that none of <reg orig="hir">his</reg> faithful Subjects may pretend ignorance, and that it may appear how willing we are that the Levies mat be done orderly and equally, we have thought fit to cause intimate to all Shires and Parishes, and Head Burghs by open <em>Proclamation</em>, that <reg orig="every one">everyone</reg> may make his several proportions ready to be delivered to the respective Officers appointed for the same, and Commissioners likewise under our hand wheresoever the foresaid Officers shall come or send to require them. Likewise that all who after intimation hereof do remain disobedient, and without fear of God, duty to their King and Country, <reg orig="tyes">ties</reg> of Covenant, love of Religion, sense of honour will not move to their duty, may be proceeded against with fire and sword, unworthy to be looked upon as Scotchmen, to the <reg orig="terrour">terror</reg> of all false-hearted <reg orig="Traytors">Traitors</reg>, who by their treacheries and rebellions against their lawful King and his just Power and Authority, has drawn on this great deluge of <reg orig="Gods">God's</reg> wrath upon all the three Kingdoms.</p>

<p>And likewise we do hereby require, that where heretofore any horses had been brought forth from any well-affected person or persons beyond their due proportion, that the respective Parish, or next adjacent Parishes where the said horses, has been taken, that they shall mete and stint themselves equally, for bearing equal burden, and resound the persons from whom any horses has been taken beyond their proportions; and the just proportion of horses now to be put forth is declared to be one man well mounted, with all necessaries, forth of <pb n="6" />every thousand pound of Rent: And the proportion of Foot, every third man; and what <em>Dragoons</em> are to be levied, two foot are to be accounted for one <em>Dragoon</em>. And for the further publication hereof, these are to ordain Commissioners of Parishes, where no Burghs are, the Provost and Bailies of Burghs to Proclaim this at the <reg orig="Merkat">Market</reg> <reg orig="Crosse">Cross</reg> of each Burgh, and to give Copies hereof to all Parishes within their Presbytery, as they will answer the contrary upon their highest peril. Given under our hand the first of <em>February</em>, 1654.</p>

<p><i>Sic subscribitur Glencarne.</i></p>

<p>God save King <em>Charles</em> the second.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3">Colonel <reg orig="Morgans">Morgan's</reg> <i>Letter of the routing of the Highlanders in Scotland.</i></head>

<p>SIR</p>

<p>I marched out of <em>Aberdeen</em> on Wednesday last with 5 Companies of Col. <em>Ashfields</em>, three of the late Maj. Gen. <em><reg orig="Deans">Dean's</reg></em> four Troops of Col. <em><reg orig="Tomlinsons">Tomlinson's</reg></em> horse, and two of Col. <em>Riches</em>, and the party that came from the <em>Merns</em> and <em>Angus</em>, with three Troops of my own <em>Dragoons</em>. And upon Thursday about two <reg orig="a clock">o'clock</reg> we come to the <em>Lough</em> at the head of <em>Cromar</em>, where <em>Glencarn</em> and <em>Kenmore</em> were at a <reg orig="Randezvouz">Rendezvous</reg> where after a little dispute we totally routed their Army, but being so near the Hills we could do no more execution <reg orig="then">than</reg> take and kill about 140, having pursued them seven miles into the Hills, their General hardly escaping with about <reg orig="fourty">forty</reg> horse. All the rest being quite dispersed, Maj. <em>Knight</em> came up even when we were going to engage; we are now upon our march towards their <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> of <em>Kildrumy</em>, which we hope to give you a good account of, I shall give you the particulars in my next: no more but that I am</p>

<p><i>Your <reg orig="Honors">Honour's</reg> humble Servant <em>Tho. Morgan</em></i></p>

<p><i>Lowrie, 10 Febru. 1653. at 6. in the morning.</i></p>

<pb n="7" />

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 27 instant, proved a fatal day to many; for, besides the Witch before-mentioned, eight more having received Sentence of death were executed; amongst the rest, four of them were <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> at the lower end of Fleet street, over against the Dog Tavern where they committed the Fact, having not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> <reg orig="rob'd">robbed</reg> M. <em>Hancock</em> (Master of the said house) of great store of Plate; but likewise cut and wounded him in several places; for which, Mr. James Harrington (a <reg orig="Bayley">Bailey</reg> of Middlesex) and the Meal-<reg orig="mans">man's</reg> wife of Brainford, who served the said Mr. Hancock with meal, and knew the Orders of the house, and where the Plate lay, suffered the bitter pangs of death; a just reward for the Woman, but a pitiful Object to behold the man: for she was not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> the grand <reg orig="Settor">Setter</reg>, and chief contriver of the Design, in drawing in of poor Mr. Harrington; but likewise the <reg orig="onely">only</reg> betrayer and Decoy of her Noble Hectors, whom she so termed; as appears by the Speech and Confession of the said James Harrington under the Gallows, who spake to the people as followeth:</p>

<p><i>Gentlemen, and Christian friends</i>, You are this day come hither to behold a sad and pitiful Object, and a man to be taken off in the midst of his years: Nevertheless, although Providence hath decreed me such an untimely end, yet I doubt not, but that this ignominious and reproachful death, will to me prove a glorious and perpetual change; and I bless God I have a Conscience within speaks peace to my poor soul, fully assuring me, that this day shall I be in Paradise with my blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; and that though my sins be as red as scarlet, yet <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> they be made as white as snow; for confident I am, I never was guilty of <reg orig="any ones">anyone's</reg> death, neither had I ever brought <reg orig="my self">myself</reg> to this untimely end, had it not <reg orig="bin">been</reg> for this woman (meaning the Meal-<reg orig="mans">man's</reg> wife) but forgive her; and so the Lord bless and protect both you and mine.</p>

<hr />

<p>Tuesday Feb. 21. Rich. Luckin of Dives Hall in the county of Essex Esq. was robbed of 700 li. money 4 or 5 slit silver spoons marked with R.E. one silver preserving ladle, punched with 4 <reg orig="rowes">rows</reg> of holes, and a Rapier with a russeted Hilt, and a black Horse haired handle; it had no scabbard. The <reg orig="theeves">thieves</reg>, one of them was a slender man, a this face, <reg orig="ful">full</reg> of pock-holes, a white close coat: another was a strong set man with a cast upon his eye: his <reg orig="cloathes">clothes</reg> were a liver <reg orig="colour'd">coloured</reg> coat and breeches. Another was a fair <reg orig="hair'd">haired</reg> man, in a loose white <reg orig="horsemans">horseman's</reg> coat girt to him. If any can give notice of the goods or persons, or any of their company, to Mr. Beachams a Goldsmith, at the Rose in Cheapside, they shall have 3 l. for their pains.</p>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>