<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPostWood171">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Grannd Politique Post (printed by R. Wood), Issue 171</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The <reg orig="Grannd">Grand</reg> <reg orig="Politique">Politic</reg> </head>
<head level="1">POST</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating,</head>

<p><i>A great Victory obtained in Scotland over the <em>Highlanders</em>, the taking of above 60 horse, many prisoners of quality, and the scattering and total routing of the Rebels. A <reg orig="bloudy">bloody</reg> Fight at Sea between the <em>English</em> and <em>Dutch</em> in St. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> channel, for the space of five <reg orig="houres">hours</reg>, with a List of the ships that were taken and brought into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>. A Declaration of his Highness for the relief of creditors and poor prisoners. Also an Ordinance prohibiting <em>Cock Matches</em>. Together with the Agreement made between the English and Dutch Commissioners, concerning the signing the Articles of Peace between <em>England, Holland</em>, and <em>Denmark</em>.</i></p>

<hr />
<p><i>From <em>Tuesday</em>, March <em>the 28</em>, to <em>Tuesday</em>, April <em>the 4th</em>. 1654.</i></p>
<hr />
<head level="3"><i>London, <em>Printed</em> by <em>R. Wood</em>; to prevent all false Copies.</i></head>

<p>The last Letters from <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg> <reg orig="certifie">certify</reg>, that the Commander of the <em><reg orig="Sophire">Sapphire</reg></em> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg> sent in thither a Dutch prize, laden <reg orig="onely">only</reg> with some few barrels of Pitch, Tar, &amp;c. And that the <em>Paul</em>, a ship in the <reg orig="States">State's</reg> service, met with a man of War belonging to <em>Flushing</em> in St. <em><reg orig="Georges">George's</reg></em> channel, which carried 15 Guns, with whom she fought continually for five hours together, yet thanks be to God, lost not a man, but sustained some <reg orig="losse">loss</reg> in her Masts, sails, and rigging; the Enemy lost 13 or 14 men, and his ship was much torn; Yet our men made shift to <reg orig="towe">tow</reg> her into <reg orig="Plimouth">Plymouth</reg>; she had aboard her some small quantity of Wines, and some silver, which our men easily <reg orig="pocketted">pocketed</reg> up, and well they <reg orig="deserv'd">deserved</reg> it, <i>Win Gold and Wear it.</i></p><pb n="1" />

<head level="3"><i>A List of 14 other Prizes, taken by the <reg orig="Phenix">Ph&oelig;nix</reg>, Newcastle, Assurance, and Mermaid <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg>.</i></head>

<p>1. The Claus of Housdown, 50 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Jacob Timison Skipper, taken by the <reg orig="Phenix">Ph&oelig;nix</reg> <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 2.</p>

<p>2. The Plumpart of Mazeland <reg orig="sluce">sluice</reg>, 30 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, William Pumisson Skipper taken by the <reg orig="Phenix">Ph&oelig;nix</reg> boat, March 14.</p>

<p>3. The <reg orig="Blew">Blue</reg> Pigeon of <em>Pumerland</em>, 200 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Peter Johnson Skipper, taken by the <reg orig="Phenix">Ph&oelig;nix</reg>, March 17.</p>

<p>4. The Fortune of Delphs, 200 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, James Jacobson Skipper, taken by the <reg orig="Phenix">Ph&oelig;nix</reg> and Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 17.</p>

<p>5. A Galliot Hoy, taken by the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, and burned, March 2.</p>

<p>6. The Hope of Housdown, 50 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Adrian Jacobson Skipper taken by the Assurance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 2.</p>

<p>7. The <reg orig="Shelfish">Shellfish</reg> of Mazeland <reg orig="sluce">sluice</reg>, 25 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Jacob Johnson Skipper, taken by the Newcastle <reg orig="Frigots">Frigate's</reg> boat, March 14.</p>

<p>8. The Providence of Mazeland <reg orig="sluce">sluice</reg>, 28 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Aryan Yorreson Skipper, taken by the Mermaid <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 12.</p>

<p>9. The Fortune of Mazeland <reg orig="sluce">sluice</reg>, 32 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, Aryis Yaris Skipper, taken by the <reg orig="Meremaids">Mermaid's</reg> boat, March 14.</p>

<p>10. A Galliot hoy, 25 <reg orig="tuns">tons</reg> burthen, taken by the Mermaid <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 18.</p>
 
<p>11. A Scotch Vessel, taken by the Mermaid, March 19.</p>

<p>12. Another Scotch Vessel, taken by the Mermaid at the same time.</p>

<p>13. The Waking Boy of Anchusen, a private man of War, commanded by Capt. Tho. Johnson, taken by the Mermaid, March 20.</p>

<p>14. A private man of War taken by the Assurance <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>.</p>

<p><i>Besides those fourteen, there are Four more are taken, by private men of War. viz.</i></p>

<p>1. A small Merchant ship brought prize into Rye.</p>

<p>2. A Denmark ship taken and brought prize into Scarborough.</p>

<p>3. A rich prize, being a private man of War, with Sugar and Merchandizes, taken by a private man of War, worth 150000 l.</p>

<p>4. A private man of War belonging to Camfear in Zealand, commanded by Capt. John Poll a Flushinger, taken by the Paul <reg orig="Frigot">Frigate</reg>, March 13.</p>

<p>The English Fleet is in a gallant equipage in the Narrow about St Ellens having sent forth several squadrons.</p>

<p>At the landing of the French <reg orig="Embassador">Ambassador</reg>, there was a difference between some of his Gentlemen, and the Portugal <reg orig="Emb">Amb</reg>. attendants about <reg orig="precedency">precedence</reg>, fell to drawing of swords, and some were hurt before the <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> came in; who immediately parted the fray, and disarmed the <reg orig="contestors">contesters</reg>.</p><pb n="2" />

<p>We have received Intelligence from <em>Upsalah</em> in <em>Sweden</em>, which certifies; That the Lord <em><reg orig="Whitlocks">Whitlock's</reg></em> Answer is delayed, till they hear how the Treaty with us proceeds, that being the Wheels with which they intend to move. The <em>Queen</em> is desirous to live a <reg orig="retir'd">retired</reg> life, and surrender up the Government to her successor, and to that purpose summoned a Grand Council or Parliament to meet on the 12 of March, 1653.</p>

<p>From the Texel we received intelligence, The Freebooter Captain <em>Oomke</em> with another went to sea the 12 instant, and two other Freebooters also went to sea the next day. The said Captain <em>Oomke</em>, with Captain Hogtenbeen came home the 15 with a good prize of Flute laden with French Wines going for <em>London</em>, and from thence for <em><reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg></em>. It is here reported that 20 English ships have appeared before the wall, near the Texel, and that about 8 more are passed towards the North. And that they have taken about five fisher-boats within the sight of this land, two belonging unto this place, and three to <em>Huysdayn</em>. The <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> are hasting the dispatch of an Ordinance for <reg orig="High-ways">Highways</reg> for mending them where need is, and for prevention of breaking the ways by such great Wanes and Carts as have been by six seven or eight horses in a Team, not for the future to exceed such a number as shall be proportioned; and the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> were also about some other Ordinances which will shortly be dispatched.</p>

<p>The <em>Dutch Freebooters</em> have lately taken some <reg orig="Barks">Barques</reg> near <em>Scarborough</em> coming from <em>Sunderland</em>, and caused another to run ashore near <em><reg orig="Hartlepoole">Hartlepool</reg></em>: and there are great store of <em>Coal-ships</em> ready laden at <em>Newcastle</em>, which had they but a good <reg orig="Winde">Wind</reg>, would quickly bring warm weather to <em>London</em>.</p>

<p>A Petition Congratulatory hath been presented from the Town of <em>Newcastle</em> to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, professing much affection to his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg>, and the late change of Government.</p>

<p>From <em>Scotland</em> our <em>Post</em> is <reg orig="inform'd">informed</reg>, that <em>Middleton</em> hath summoned in all the Gentlemen of <em>Sutherland</em> and <em>Ross</em>, and prohibited the sheriffs to act any more in the name of the Lord Protector, saying he will give them a new commission to act by. He brought over above 60 Officers, the least of them a Captain; there is since another Vessel landed in <em>Caithness</em> with more arms and ammunition, and <em>Seaforth</em> hath raised 600 men and is upon his march to <reg orig="joyn">join</reg> with him. He expects more provisions daily from <em>Holland</em>, and gives out, that <reg orig="assoon">as soon</reg> as the prepared parties are ready, and the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> sent the 160000 Rixdollars for the raising of 30. Regiments, that then their King, or the Duke of York will come to be their General. The Earl of <em>Athol</em> and Sir. <em>Arth. Forbs</em> have placed a <reg orig="Garison">Garrison</reg> in the Isle of <em>Lough Tay</em>, where they intend to have a stock of Provisions.</p><pb n="3" />

<p>His <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> hath passed an Ordinance for suspending the proceedings of the Judges named in the Act, intituled, <i>An Act for the Relief of Creditors and poor prisoners</i>, which being of so general concernment take as followeth.</p>

<p>Whereas upon perusal, and serious consideration had of one Act of Parliament, intituled, <i>An Act for the relief of Creditors, and poor Prisoners</i>, many doubts and difficulties do appear, which must necessarily occasion an Explanation of the said Act, for the better <reg orig="inabling">enabling</reg> the Judges in the said Act named and authorized for sale of such Estates as are to be sold by the said Act, for satisfaction of Creditors, which cannot in short time be effected; and without such Explanation, and further direction to be given to the several and respective Judges authorized in, and by the said Act, several inconveniences and mischiefs would grow, not <reg orig="onely">only</reg> to the said Creditors, and Prisoners, but to divers other persons, not meant or intended to be included within the said Act, and will occasion many troubles, and suits in Law, and Equity; For the prevention whereof, due care is likewise to be had: and whereas many of the said Prisoners have offered really to <reg orig="indeavour">endeavour</reg> the satisfaction of the said Creditors, if some further time may be given for that purpose; be it therefore Ordained by his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that the said several and respective Judges mentioned in the Act, or any of them, shall not proceed to the sale, or Disposition of any the Estates real or personal, of any of the said Prisoners, or any other person or persons whatsoever mentioned or intended by the said Act <unclear><!-- approx. 6 characters --></unclear> shall otherwise intermeddle in the execution of the said Act; or of any <unclear><!-- approx. 11 characters --></unclear> or authorities given by the same, until the 20 day of <em>April</em> next. And be it further ordained by the Authority aforesaid, That all <unclear>Acts or things</unclear> to be done by the said several and respective Judges, <unclear>or any of them, by virtue, colour</unclear>, or pretence of the said Act, from henceforth, and before the said 20 day of <em>April</em>, shall be utterly void, null, and of none effect; saving <unclear><!-- approx. 7 characters --></unclear> shall and may be lawfull for the said several and respective judges that have bailed or let out any prisoners upon Sureties <unclear><!-- approx. 18 characters --></unclear> or Prison (which prisoners are to appear again at a certain day before the said Judges, and are not absolutely discharged by any Order of the said Judges, <i>as see further by the Act.</i></p>

<p>From Scotland our Post received intelligence, That the Commander in chief having issued forth a Proclamation requiring all Burgesses and others to secure all suspicious persons, or otherwise to give intelligence of them to the next adjacent Garrison or Quarters under pain of being deemed Enemies to the present government, and proceeded against accordingly: Several towns have been lately found guilty of the breach of that Proclamation, and have been fined by a Court-Marshal for the same. The last week the Parish of <em>Liberton</em>, two miles from <reg orig="Edenburgh">Edinburgh</reg>, for harbouring 15 of the Enemy by the space of a night and a day, and neither securing them, nor giving intelligence of them, and the Tories at their going away stealing 15 horses, the Parish<pb n="4" /> was for that offence fined 200 <em>l</em>. sterling, the person in whose house they were concealed, sentenced to imprisonment during pleasure, and the house where they were harboured to be <reg orig="raced">razed</reg> to the ground, and a pair of <reg orig="Gallowes">Gallows</reg> to be built there. There are divers other Parishes who are summoned in to Court Marshals upon the very same account, who will suffer for it. It is hoped this course will in time <reg orig="compell">compel</reg> the Scots not to give any Entertainment unto the Tories, but give notice of them where ever they shall come, otherwise they will suffer for it.</p>

<p>The 21 instant Col. Cooper with a party of Horse and Dragoons from <reg orig="Glascow">Glasgow</reg>; and another party at the same time falling into the Isle of Leven, where about 300 of the enemy quartered (about 4 in the morning) took <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughtons">McNaughton's</reg></em> Trumpet, and 35 other prisoners, and narrowly missed <em><reg orig="Mac-Naughton">McNaughton</reg></em> and <em>Newark</em>, who were both there; they killed 12, whereof one of them (as the enemy confess) was a Lieutenant of Horse, and took about 60 Horse and some <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>, and totally scattered and routed the whole party, returning without any loss at.</p>

<p>Captain <em>Orton</em> Commander of the Sun, and Captain <em>Lilburn</em> of the Union, came into <reg orig="Lieth">Leith</reg> Road from <em>Lewis</em> and <em>Orkney</em>, and brought three Companies of Col. <em><reg orig="Coopers">Cooper's</reg></em> Regiment, and herewith a particular relation of the late infall of the Earl of Seafort into <em>Lewis</em> Island.</p>

<p>Take this in brief from <reg orig="forreign">foreign</reg> parts. They write from <em>Leghorn</em> that they heard by a ship which came from Barbary, that the Turkish Agent being come to Tunis, hath pressed or taken up all the <reg orig="Gallies">Galleys</reg> and ships fit for service, and intends to do the same at Algier and Tripoli; in her voyage thither, she met with two Turkish Pirates, who being come up to him on both sides, supposing <reg orig="themselvs">themselves</reg> not able to grapple with her, they tacked about and left her. There is likewise a flying report, that the French <reg orig="pyrates">pirates</reg> have met with two English <reg orig="Merchants">Merchants'</reg> ships homewards bound, and after a tedious fight had taken them; but by reason those that brought the <reg orig="newes">news</reg> vary very much, therefore little credit is yet to be given to it till further confirmation.</p>

<p>From <em>Poland</em> we hear, that the inhabitants are in great fear, hearing of the great preparations that are made in <em>Muscovia</em>, where they have levied above two hundred and fifty thousand men, with which they threaten to enter the Country three several <reg orig="wayes">ways</reg> at once.</p>

<p>The general Diet is not yet concluded at <reg orig="Regensburgh">Regensburg</reg>, although the <reg orig="Emperour">Emperor</reg> doth press very much that they should speedily put a period to it, his presence being required in <em>Hungaria</em>, to provide against the invasion of the Turks, who are now <reg orig="busie">busy</reg> about the borders.</p><pb n="5" />

<head level="3"><i>Here followeth the Copy of a Letter, dated at the Hague the 27 of March, new style. 1654.</i></head>

<p><i>SIR</i></p>

<p>The last Thursday was brought here, in a Pink sent for that purpose Letters of the 20 instant from the Lord <reg orig="Embassadours">Ambassadors</reg> now in England, whereby we hear they give advice to the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> States, that the Treaty of Peace was not yet concluded, but that preparations for Sea were made there in all <reg orig="hast">haste</reg>, the occasion whereof was unknown to them, which caused some suspicions and jealousies amongst the said <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> States; Insomuch that the Vice-Admiral Ruyter, and the Scout by night Trump, with other Captains received orders to resort presently to Amsterdam, which they did accordingly Wednesday morning, as also several Messengers were dispatched to the <reg orig="Counsels">Councils</reg> of the Admiralties. The <reg orig="Lievtenant">Lieutenant</reg> Admiral, the Lord Van-Opdam was likewise commanded to come from Brabant where he was hither.</p>

<p>And yet we cannot understand by the Letters come from London the night between the 20 and the 21 that any difficulties should have arisen wherefore the Treaty should not go on, so that it is believed the same may have a good <reg orig="successe">success</reg>, and that those preparations made there may be made for some other design. We have very little certainty of the Scottish Affairs. It is presumed that Middleton is arrived in Scotland to gather what forces he can to restore the titular King his <reg orig="Masters">Master's</reg> fortune. Last night a Pink hath been by the Lords States dispatched from Sheveling into England.</p>

<p>And Sir, After long expectation, we hear not yet of a conclusion of peace so much desired and expected by the Merchants of this City, who had great hope upon the going away of the <reg orig="Embassadors">Ambassadors</reg> for England that the <reg orig="businesse">business</reg> would have been fully and finally ended without any further delay, and it was given out over all these Lands, that they had full power and instruction for that purpose: so that men are much troubled here, that they cannot burn the triumphant Pitch barrels which stand ready for the sacrifice. Where the obstruction is, we know not; but <reg orig="doubtlesse">doubtless</reg> it is the true interest of these Provinces to maintain peace with England <unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> necessities call aloud for it.</p>

<p>Here is news which affrights us, of an extraordinary Fleet a setting forth in England; besides, divers of your men of War have been upon our coasts, and taken vessels, which hath been given the States occasion of issuing out immediate Orders to all the <reg orig="Colledges">Colleges</reg> of the Admiralty, to make all possible speed with the Fleet to sea; but it is hoped an Accommodation may be signed before the two Fleets do meet abroad, and that all these storms will at length end in a happy and honourable Calm, which would be a blessing to both Nations.</p>

<p><i>Take this from your Servant, <em>J. T.</em></i></p><pb n="6" />

<p>On Friday last, <reg orig="whilest">whilst</reg> we (according to order) were at our devotions, the Portugal <reg orig="Embassadour">Ambassador</reg> was a Revelling, and divers of our English Gentry were present, whose absence would have been more to their honour.</p>

<p>The last Tuesday there was very much hurt done on the River of Thames by violent storms and gusts of <reg orig="winde">wind</reg>, divers Lighters being sunk, and many boats split one against the other.</p>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> hath also received further intelligence from Scotland, that the devastations there are very great, and the <reg orig="Countrey">Country</reg> people being sensible that those in the Hills seek to <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> the whole Nation, assisted our men, and they have made a great slaughter amongst the Lord <reg orig="Seaforts">Seafort's</reg> Levies; and they have found hidden in a wall, divers <reg orig="musquets">muskets</reg>, <reg orig="fire-locks">firelocks</reg>, swords, <reg orig="bandaliers">bandoliers</reg>, match and powder: Sir Arthur Forbs descended lately from the Hills, and stole some horses out of the Lowlands, whose incursions the wit of man cannot prevent.</p>

<p>It is confidently ascertained from the French Court, that the Protestant German Princes and the King of Denmark have of late given <reg orig="Charls">Charles</reg> Stuart to understand, that the desolation of the late wars hinders them from being able to entertain him, if he forsakes France to come unto them.</p>

<p>The business of the Treaty with the Dutch <reg orig="Ambassadours">Ambassadors</reg>, lies thus. We are now in all things agreed with them, and they may sign that agreement when they please; they have power to do it, and may have peace for themselves, if they will leave Denmark to themselves; the <reg orig="Lords">Lord's</reg> Ambassadors have sent over to the States to know their pleasure herein.</p>

<p>General <em>Desborow</em>, General <em>Monk</em>, and the Commissioners of the Admiralty, have been at <em>Chattam</em>, and dispatched all things for the <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> of the <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg>, which are now near ready; <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> are already <reg orig="prest">pressed</reg>, and Land <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> drawn out of several Regiments, to be sent of <reg orig="Shippoard">Shipboard</reg> with all expedition, and a gallant Fleet will suddenly be equipped, to meet at a Rendezvous in the <em><reg orig="Downes">Downs</reg></em>, with those which ride near St. <em><reg orig="Hellens">Helens</reg></em> point. On the other side, the Dutch are likewise preparing to put forth to sea, and are fitting of sixty new <reg orig="Frigots">Frigates</reg> to <reg orig="adde">add</reg> to their fleet. Yet 'tis hoped there will be a fair <reg orig="correspondency">correspondence</reg> for all this, it being the <reg orig="sureest">surest</reg> way to treat with a drawn sword.</p>

<p>The <reg orig="Marquess">Marques</reg> of <em>Faber</em> that commands the <em>French</em> Army quartered in <em>Liege</em>, is environed on all sides; first, by the E. of <em>Fuenseldagne</em> Commander of the <em>Spanish</em> forces near <em><reg orig="Ardenne">Ardennes</reg></em>, <em>Don Parde</em> General of the Duke of <em><reg orig="Luxemberghs">Luxembourg's</reg></em> forces, and lastly by the Prince of <em>Conde's</em> Army; so that it's <reg orig="conceiv'd">conceived</reg> almost an impossibility for them to escape without fighting one of those parties, yet he being a subtle Monsieur, may perhaps lead the crafty <i>Foxe a French Curranto</i> rather <reg orig="then">than</reg> be made his prey.</p><pb n="7" />

<p>The Reformed Churches begin to be mistrusted, and are charged by the Baron of <em>Estissac</em> <reg orig="Governour">Governor</reg> of <em>Rochel</em>, for sending Ministers into England on some <reg orig="designes">designs</reg> prejudicial to his <reg orig="Majestie">Majesty</reg>, all which they formally deny; but more of that in my next.</p>

<p>Captain <em><unclear><!-- approx. 5 characters --></unclear> Pritchard</em> obtained an Ordinance the last Wednesday, upon the Petition <unclear>of</unclear> the Prisoners for suspending the Act for Prisoners, and proceedings of the Judges at Salters Hall thereupon till <em>July</em>; the Ordinance will be printed with all possible speed.</p>

<p>Since the Lord <em>Henry <reg orig="Cromwels">Cromwell's</reg></em> return from <em>Ireland</em>, we have received little of News from thence; save <reg orig="onely">only</reg> that about 1200 <em>Tories</em> were shipped from Limbrick, and 1700 more are ready for transportation, which will render that Nation more free from Robbers than in times of the greatest peace.</p>

<p>Our <em>Post</em> hath received farther intelligence from <em>Sweden</em>, that the <em>Queen</em> having visited her mother at <em>Nicoping</em>, is again returned to <em>Upsal</em> to be present at the great Assembly of the Senators.</p>

<p><reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> the 3 of April, was published an Ordinance, <reg orig="Entituled">Entitled</reg>; <i>An Ordinance prohibiting Cock-Matches.</i> A perfect Copy whereof take as followeth.</p>

<p><i>Whereas the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> Meetings and Assemblies of People together in divers parts of this Nation, under pretence of Matches for Cockfighting, are by experience found to tend many times to the disturbance of the <reg orig="publike">public</reg> peace, and are commonly accompanied with Gaming, Drinking, Swearing, Quarrelling, and other dissolute practises, to the dishonour of God, and do often produce the <reg orig="ruine">ruin</reg> of persons and their families. For prevention thereof, Be it Ordained by his Highness the Lord Protector, by and with the advice and consent of his Council, that from henceforth there shall be no <reg orig="publike">public</reg> or set Meetings or Assemblies of any persons within <em>England</em> or <em>Wales</em> upon Matches made for <reg orig="Cock-fighting">Cockfighting</reg>; And that every such meeting, and assembly of people for the end and purpose aforesaid, is hereby declared to be an Unlawful assembly, and shall be so adjudged, deemed, and taken to be, and punished; And all Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, <reg orig="Maiors">Mayors</reg>, <reg orig="Baylifs">Bailiffs</reg>, Constables and Headboroughs, within their several counties, cities, liberties and jurisdictions, are hereby required to suppress, hinder, and disperse all such meetings and Assemblies.</i></p>

<p>Ordered by His Highness the Lord Protector and His Council, That his Ordinance be forthwith printed and published.</p>

<p><em>Henry Scobel</em>, Clerk of the Council.</p>

<head level="3">FINIS.</head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>