<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE newsbookDoc SYSTEM "newsbookDoc.dtd" >

<newsbookDoc id="WPost168">
<newsbookHeader>
<title>The Weekly Post, Issue 168</title>
</newsbookHeader>
<newsbookText>
<pb n="0" />

<head level="2">The Grand Politique</head>
<head level="1">POST,</head>
<head level="3">Faithfully communicating</head>

<p><i>The landing of Lieu. Gen. Middleton in Scotland on the fourth of this instant March; and a List of the Names and Number of the Lords, Knights, Colonels, Gentlemen, and <reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg>, that have engaged with him for their King; with the Orders of his Highness the Lord Protector thereupon. The further proceedings of the Treaty between the English and Dutch; the putting forth of the Belgick Fleets, and a List of the English <reg orig="Navie">Navy</reg> that are ready to attend their motion. The proceedings of the Council at <reg orig="White-hall">Whitehall</reg> touching the ancient Cathedral of <reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg>, the last news from col. Serles in the Barbadoes, the Rebellion of the Negers against the English, the cutting off of <reg orig="mens">men's</reg> hands, and the Number of those burnt and executed.</i></p>

<hr />
<head level="3">From <em>Tuesday</em> March 7. to <em>Tuesday</em> March 14. 1654.</head>
<hr />

<p><em>London</em>, Printed for <em>G. Horton</em>, <i>to prevent all false Copies.</i>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The last <em>Intelligence</em> from Col. <em>Dan. Serl</em>, Governor of the <em>Barbadoes</em>, advertiseth, That on the 13 of <em>December</em> last, was held a General Sessions for Gaol-Delivery, and Common-pleas, which continued for the space of five <reg orig="dayes">days</reg>; amongst others, who received corporal punishments, one <em>John Barkley</em>; a Scots man was <reg orig="hang'd">hanged</reg> for buggering and <unclear><em>Afrego</em></unclear> Mare, which Mare was brought to the place of execution, there <reg orig="ty'd">tied</reg> to a stake and burnt to Ashes, in defence of the said <em>Barkley</em>, who was afterwards <reg orig="immediatly">immediately</reg> executed. After which, one Mr. <em>Robert Richards</em> was hanged for killing an <pb n="1" />Irish-man, that was a servant in this <em>Island</em>, and three Negro<reg orig="=men">-men</reg> at the same time hanged about a <reg orig="murther">murder</reg> some nine months since committed in the night time by several Negroes, who beset the house of one Mr. <em>Dobs</em> a Planter, killed him, his wife, and child: So just is the most <reg orig="heroick">heroic</reg>, honoured, and very much approved noble Colonel <em>Serles</em>, to administer equal justice upon all <reg orig="Offendors">Offenders</reg>, that the very <reg orig="ballance">balance</reg> of the <reg orig="Skales">Scales</reg> are rightly terminated upon all Facts, Crimes, <reg orig="Designes">Designs</reg>, and Actions: Which, indeed, will remain as a <reg orig="Trophicall">Tropical</reg> Palm to <reg orig="eternize">eternise</reg> his Name throughout all Ages. And so tender is the said Governor likewise in managing of the weighty <reg orig="Affaires">Affairs</reg> of that Island, that for the suppressing of runaway Negroes, and to prevent the increase of their great Numbers, He commanded some three hundred men to hunt and range the words, who the first day killed two of the Negroes, one whereof was conceived to be the chief of them, afterward seven other Negro-men were brought in, and upon <reg orig="Tryal">Trial</reg> found guilty of the said <reg orig="Murther">Murder</reg>, four of them had first their right hands cut off, and then hanged; the other three were also executed. About a fortnight since came in sight of the <em>Island</em> a small Dutch man of War, which stood <reg orig="neer">near</reg> the shore, and put forth the English Colours, and a Parliament Jack, and made as if he intended to come in: Upon which four Shallops going from the Bridge to the Leeward, part of this <em>Island</em>, with Commodities, thinking it had been an English ship, and standing towards her, were <reg orig="surprized">surprised</reg> and taken, which was a considerable loss.</p>

<p>The English Fleet rideth not far from the Isle of Wight: some Squadrons are at the <reg orig="Spits">Spit's</reg> head, and others at Saint <reg orig="Ellens">Ellen's</reg> point: they are ready to put forth to Sea in the most gallant equipage that may be. For we have now in one Body the bravest Fleet that ever was put forth since the Wars began, and the <reg orig="Sea-men">Seamen</reg> are very unanimous. Divers foot-<reg orig="souldiers">soldiers</reg> are gone down to their assistance, no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 30 out of a company were drawn forth on <reg orig="Munday">Monday</reg> last, and divers others are to follow: <i>A prosperous Gale attend them.</i></p>

<p>The <em>Royal <reg orig="Soverain">Sovereign</reg></em> is now ready to spread her <unclear><!--approx. 8 characters--></unclear> upon <reg orig="Neptunes">Neptune's</reg> curled Waves, and the <em>Resolution</em> (formerly called in the <reg orig="dayes">days</reg> of our late King <em>Charles</em>, the <em>Prince Royal</em>) is <reg orig="lanched">launched</reg> forth into the <i>Ocean seas</i>.</p>

<pb n="2" />

<head level="3"><i>A List of the English Summer Fleet.</i></head>

<table>
<tr>
<td><p>&nbsp;<!--empty cell--></p></td><td><p>Men</p></td><td><p>Guns</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>The Resolution</p></td><td><p>550</p></td><td><p>88</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Worcester frig.</p></td><td><p>220</p></td><td><p>50</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Advice <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>42</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Diamond</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>42</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>James</p></td><td><p>360</p></td><td><p>66</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Tryumph">Triumph</reg></p></td><td><p>350</p></td><td><p>62</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>George</p></td><td><p>350</p></td><td><p>58</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Lawrel">Laurel</reg></p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Saphire">Sapphire</reg></p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>38</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Pelican</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Mairmaid">Mermaid</reg></p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>34</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Loyalty</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Society</p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Adventure</p></td><td><p>160</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Providence</p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>33</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Bear</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>45</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Hearts-ease">Heart's-ease</reg></p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>36</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>London</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Speaker</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>56</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Sussex</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>46</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Tyger">Tiger</reg></p></td><td><p>150</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Violet</p></td><td><p>170</p></td><td><p>40</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Falmouth</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>38</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><!--??-->Phenix</p></td><td><p>130</p></td><td><p>34</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Lyon">Lion</reg></p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>50</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Ruby</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>41</p></td></tr>
</table>

<pb n="3" />

<table>
<tr>
<td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>Men</p></td><td><p>Guns</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>Men</p></td><td><p>Guns</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Assistance</p></td><td><p>280</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p>Essex <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>250</p></td><td><p>44</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Foresight</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>42</p></td><td><p>Hampshire <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>130</p></td><td><p>44</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Portsmouth</p></td><td><p>170</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>Fairfax</p></td><td><p>1204</p></td><td><p>44</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Exchange</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>Samuel</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>30</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Richard and Martha</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>46</p></td><td><p>Benjamin</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>30</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Sarah</p></td><td><p>90</p></td><td><p>34</p></td><td><p>King Ferdinando</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>36</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Lixa Merchant</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>Roebuck</p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>30</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Victory</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>60</p></td><td><p>Rainbow</p></td><td><p>300</p></td><td><p>58</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Centurion</p></td><td><p>200</p></td><td><p>41</p></td><td><p>Convertine</p></td><td><p>210</p></td><td><p>44</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Expedition</p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p><em>Amity</em> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>150</p></td><td><p>36</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Middleborow">Middleborough</reg></p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>Dolphin</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>30</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Raven</p></td><td><p>140</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>Arms of Holland</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>34</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Exchange</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>Tulip</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>32</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Globe</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>Jonathan</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>30</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Mary</p></td><td><p>200</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>Dragonere</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>32</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Thomas and Lucie</p></td><td><p>125</p></td><td><p>28</p></td><td><p>William and John</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>36</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Andrew</p></td><td><p>360</p></td><td><p>56</p></td><td><p>Nicodemus</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p>12</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Assurance</p></td><td><p>160</p></td><td><p>36</p></td><td><p>Grayhound</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Princes">Princess</reg> Maria</p></td><td><p>90</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p><reg orig="Duches">Duchess</reg></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Water-Hound</p></td><td><p>170</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>Crown</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Pearle</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>26</p></td><td><p><em>Ann Piercy</em></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Reformation</p></td><td><p>160</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p>Peter</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Industry</p></td><td><p>100</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>Merlin</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Kentish <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>50</p></td><td><p><reg orig="Faulkon">Falcon</reg></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Great president</p></td><td><p>180</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p>Hannibal</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Nonsuch">Nonesuch</reg> <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>170</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p><em>Ann</em> and <em>Joyce</em></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Success</p></td><td><p>150</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p><em>Mary</em></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Welcome</p></td><td><p>200</p></td><td><p>40</p></td><td><p><em>Hound</em></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Oak</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Brazil <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p><reg orig="Totall">Total</reg> of the whole fleet</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>130</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Eastland Merchant</p></td><td><p>110</p></td><td><p>32</p></td><td><p>Total of men</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>17246</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Adventure</p></td><td><p>160</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>Total of Guns</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>4824</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Samaritan</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td><td><p>&mdash;</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p><reg orig="Vant-guard">Vanguard</reg></p></td><td><p>390</p></td><td><p>56</p></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="3"><p>Besides the Naseby <reg orig="frigot">frigate</reg> is preparing for the Cerulian Waves, and divers other stately ships.</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Entrance</p></td><td><p>200</p></td><td><p>43</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Dragon</p></td><td><p>160</p></td><td><p>38</p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Convert</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p><unclear>33</unclear></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Paul</p></td><td><p>120</p></td><td><p>38</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>Guise</p></td><td><p>133</p></td><td><p>34</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
<tr>
<td><p>President <reg orig="frigat">frigate</reg></p></td><td><p>115</p></td><td><p>30</p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td><td><p>&nbsp;<!--blank cell--></p></td></tr>
</table>

<pb n="4" />

<p>The last Post from Holland advertiseth, that there is arrived at the Uly about 140 sail of <reg orig="Merchants">Merchant's</reg> ships that came from the Eastland, whereof divers are going up to Amsterdam, the rest to other Ports. The Commander Ruittier is chosen Vice-Admiral for that City, and great are their preparations in most places. There is come to the Hague an Agent from the great Duke of Maltha, who is called the Chevalier Palant; he hath had Audience of the States General, and after that delivered in certain papers, wherein are expressed at large the occasion of his <reg orig="comming">coming</reg>, and his Demands. The two great ships (so long expected) are now safely arrived at the Uly from the Charibde Islands, and some few ships taken by the English are again re-taken by the Dutch. Nay, further, they have taken some of our ships on the Northern Coast, towards Bridlington Bay, <reg orig="Scarbrough">Scarborough</reg>, and Newcastle, and stranded others <reg orig="neer">near</reg> Hartlepool: there is a great Fleet coming from Newcastle, <reg orig="soo">so</reg> soon as the Wind will permit, and a Convoy is ready to attend their motion. There is another great Fleet of Dutch Merchant men (consisting of no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> one hundred and fifty <reg orig="sayl">sail</reg>) gone to the Westward, sailing close by the Coast of France, and having a fair Wind, gave our Fleet the go-by: they have a Convoy of 60 men of war, and well <reg orig="man'd">manned</reg>, and are to return speedily to the <reg orig="Generall">General</reg> <reg orig="Rendevouz">Rendezvous</reg>. Our Fleet rides <reg orig="tryumphantly">triumphantly</reg> in the Western Channel, and mighty preparations there are for <reg orig="compleating">completing</reg> of it: no less <reg orig="then">than</reg> 1000 <reg orig="Red-coats">Redcoats</reg> were drawn out of four Regiments the last week, and sent on ship board.</p>

<pb n="5" />

<p>The next thing that presents <reg orig="it self">itself</reg> to <reg orig="publike">public</reg> view is, the high and magnificent entertainment of the Dutch Ambassadors, upon their receiving audience by his Highness the Lord Protector. They were attended from the Palace-yard to the Banqueting-house at Whitehall, by Sir <em>Oliver Fleming</em> (Master of the Ceremonies) the L. <em>Strickland</em>, and the L. <em>Jones</em>, (two of the Council) who were all brought in the L. <reg orig="Protectors">Protector's</reg> chief Coach, and his <reg orig="Highness">Highness's</reg> footmen, besides the Ambassadors, to run by the Coach; and after the said Coach followed divers others belonging to several Peers of the Nation, in which <reg orig="rid">rode</reg> several persons of honour, and the Gentlemen belonging to the Ambassadors. There were set at the upper-end of the Banqueting house a mighty rich Chair of State for his Highness, and by it on the right hand, three rich <reg orig="stooles">stools</reg> for the Ambassadors, and a place railed in covered with Carpets, and the ground spread with Carpets wherein the chair and stools were set. The L. Protector came into the Banqueting house with the Lords of the Council, M. <em>Thurloe</em>, Secretary of State, and M. <em>Claypool</em> Gent. of the Horse; at whose coming in, all the people put off their hats &amp; stood bare, &amp; his Highness put off his hat to the people, &amp; went up to the Chair, but did not sit down in it at all, neither before, at, nor after the Audience. His Highness stood on the left side of the Chair, with his hat on, and the Lords of the Council, M. <em>Thurlo</em>, &amp; M. <em>Claypool</em> were within the Rails, all bare during Audience. In this equipage his Highness waited a short time, for the reception of the Ambassadors, and a lane was made for them to come up to his Highness from the one end of the room to the other. So soon as the Ambassadors were come into the Room they put off their hats to salute his Highness; and his Highness did the like to them again; and so a second, and a third time, as they came <reg orig="neerer">nearer</reg> to the L. Protector; and when they came up to the place where the chair, stools, &amp; carpets were, where his Highness was, with the Lords of the Council; and after a low salute of his Highness &amp; the Ambassadors each to other; the L. Protector put on his hat, and the Ambassadors also: but the Lords of the Council, &amp; all others being bare, his Highness and the Ambassadors standing up, the L. <em>Youngstal</em> made a Speech to His Highness, declaring the desire of his Masters the States of the United Provinces, to renew Amity, and to settle a more firm Peace <reg orig="then">than</reg> <pb n="6" />heretofore. To which his Highness made an excellent Speech in answer thereunto, declaring, That he desired nothing more than a firm Peace and happy Union and to renew the ancient friendship between both Commonwealths, &amp;c. Afterwards his Highness &amp; the Ambassadors saluted each other; and the Ambassadors returned back three times to salute his Highness; and his Highness also staying for that purpose saluted them; but they being gone down, his Highness with the Lords of the Council, returned also by the Privy door.</p>

<p>The Lord Ambassadors from the States of Holland, have again addressed themselves to his Highness, intimating That if the Articles can be <reg orig="ingrossed">engrossed</reg> in a day, they were willing to sign the Ratification of the Peace: whereupon his <reg orig="Highnesse">Highness</reg> appointed the Lord Strickland, and five Commissioners more of the Lords of the Council, to meet with the Dutch Ambassadors, and to explain and <reg orig="cleer">clear</reg> some scruples in the Articles: so that its supposed Subscriptions will be made on either side, in order to a firm Peace and Amity. Upon the effecting whereof, divers <reg orig="honorable">honourable</reg> persons are to be excluded the two <reg orig="Common-wealths">Commonwealths</reg> <em>viz.</em></p>

<!--list in 2 columns divided by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>The Queen of Bohemia going from Holland, to her Son Prince Charles the Palsgrave.</p>
<p>The Prince of Orange</p>
<p>The Princess</p>
<p>The King of Scot, going for Germany, Likewise</p>
<p>The Duke of York</p>
<p>The Duke of Gloucester</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Prince Rupert</p>
<p>Prince Philip</p>
<p>The late Queen of England is to depart France: she goes to the Duke of Savoy, the <reg orig="Dutchess">Duchess</reg> being her sister</p>
<p>And all other Lords and Gentlemen that shall be found enemies against the two States.</p>

<p>There is like to be a sudden conclusion between the Kings of France, Denmark, and the Q. of Sweden; and then beware poor Germany. Her Majesty, and his Excellency the Lord Ambassador Whitlock have treated of every Article, and there is great probability of a very good issue: but the Queen demurs about the Article of an offensive and defensive war by reason that the English are at present in wars, and her subjects in peace. Her Resident hath had audience in Holland and likewise the French Ambassador: since which time, the States are preparing to send forth their great <reg orig="Armado">Armada</reg>, and have added 60 new <reg orig="Frigats">Frigates</reg> to the Navy, notwithstanding the present Treaty: whereupon Gen. Desborow, and Gen. Monk are gone down to Chattam, to hasten out the rest of the English Fleet. On the 10 instant, the Highlanders had a great <reg orig="Randevouz">Rendezvous</reg> about Badgenoth, and the truth is they are very strong, though many times we take some of them.</p>

<p>An Ordinance is preparing for the <reg orig="tryal">trial</reg> and approbation of Ministers, and thirty Commissioners (Ministers and others) will be appointed to put them in execution;</p>

<pb n="7" />

<p>The Articles of Agreement between the Dutch and Us (as before mentioned) are not yet <reg orig="engrosed">engrossed</reg>; but the English Commissioners of the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> to the Lord Protector, <em>viz.</em></p>

<!--a table in 2 columns separated by large curly brackets }{-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>The Lord <em>Lisle</em>,</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Lambert</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Strickland</em>,</p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Sir Gilbert <unclear><em>Pickering</em></unclear>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Montague</em>,</p>
<p>Mr. <em>Lawrence</em>.</p>

<p>Appointed to finish the business of the Dutch Ambassadors, have had several meetings, and the Results of all (as fairly conjectured) tends to a speedy Union.</p>

<p>Another part of <em><reg orig="Pauls">Paul's</reg></em> Church falling down the last week at the great South door, where a part fell before: it was under consideration by the <reg orig="Councel">Council</reg> for taking it down; but nothing yet done in it.</p>

<p>Our last <em>Post</em> from <em>Scotland</em> bringeth certain intelligence, That there are divers great Commanders, and eminent persons landed at the <reg orig="Ferrey">Ferry</reg> of Uney in Southerland a List of their Names We <reg orig="shal">shall</reg> here present you with as followeth:</p>

<head level="3"><i>A list of the Lords, Knights, and Colonels, landed in Scotland, and the number of Officers and <reg orig="Souldiers">Soldiers</reg>.</i></head>

<!--table in 2 columns separated by a vertical line-->

<!--column 1-->
<p>Lieut. Gen. <em>Middleton</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Douglas</em>,</p>
<p>The Lord <em>Murrey</em>,</p>
<p>Sir <em>George Munroe</em>,</p>
<p>Sir <em>Alexander Ennis</em>,</p>
<p>Maj. Gen. <em>Dyel</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Dyel</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Lodowick Drumland</em></p>

<!--column 2-->
<p>Col. <em>Stuart</em>,</p>
<p>Col. <em>Gibson</em>,</p>
<p>24 Captains,</p>
<p>27 Lieutenants,</p>

<p>And about 60 other Officers and Gentlemen</p>
<!--next para begins in column 2-->
<p>Great store of Arms, Ammunition, and other warlike Provisions; by way of Tradition 'tis said, that they have brought over three white Flags, <!--picture is set in the middle of the paragraph--> <img src="" alt="white shield with crossed daggers" />with the cross bloody Daggers, and that they are already marched up to Achness with divers Horse load of <reg orig="Armes">Arms</reg>: from whence, they intend to march up to Strath-Heer, terminating to have a conjunction with Gen. <em>Glencarn</em> in the Highlands, and then to proceed with fire and sword against all those that shall oppose them in the Lowlands. But let them beware, that <reg orig="Valors">Valour's</reg> great <em>Elixir</em>, who do's three Nations <reg orig="aw">awe</reg>, doth not once more with his brandish Sword give the Redshanks a Law; for which end, his Highness hath ordered all Officers to repair to their several charges.</p>

<hr />

<head level="3"><i>Extracted out of the Original Papers, published by Authority.</i></head>

</newsbookText>
</newsbookDoc>